<Summary id="CDR0000257994" LegacyPDQID="2659" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062809"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Prevention</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Breast cancer prevention strategies include avoiding known risks, having a healthy lifestyle, and medications or surgery for those at high risk. Learn more about breast cancer prevention, risks and protective factors, and how to estimate risk in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/patient/breast-prevention-pdq">Breast Cancer (PDQ®): Prevention</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/hp/breast-prevention-pdq">Breast Cancer (PDQ®): Prevention</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038832">breast cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041588">cancer prevention</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_302">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about breast cancer prevention. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_303">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>breast cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>cancer prevention</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Breast Cancer Prevention (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Breast Cancer Prevention</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Breast Cancer Prevention</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>What Is Prevention?</Title><Para id="_2">Cancer prevention is action taken to lower the chance of getting cancer. By preventing cancer, the number of new cases of cancer in a group or population is lowered. Hopefully, this will reduce the burden of cancer and lower the number of deaths caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_312">Cancer is not a single disease but a group of related diseases. Our <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef>, lifestyle, and the environment around us work together to increase or decrease our risk of getting cancer. Each person's cancer risk is made up of a combination of these factors.</Para><Para id="_139">To prevent new cancers from starting, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientists</GlossaryTermRef> look at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factors</GlossaryTermRef>. Anything that increases your chance of developing cancer is called a cancer risk factor; anything that decreases your chance of developing cancer is called a cancer protective factor.</Para><Para id="_56">Some risk factors for cancer can be avoided, but many cannot. For
		example, both smoking and inheriting certain genes  are risk factors for some
		types of cancer, but only smoking can be avoided. Regular exercise and a healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef>  may be protective factors for some types of cancer. Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may lower your risk, but it does
		not mean that you will not get cancer.</Para><Para id="_138">Different ways to prevent cancer are being studied, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_133" Style="bullet"><ListItem>changing lifestyle or eating habits</ListItem><ListItem>avoiding things known to cause cancer</ListItem><ListItem>taking medicines to treat a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">precancerous</GlossaryTermRef> conditions or to keep cancer from starting</ListItem><ListItem>having risk-reducing surgery.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>General Information About Breast Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_6">Breast cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells
		  form in the tissues of the breast.</KeyPoint><Para id="_7">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef> is made up of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046188" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lobes</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046441" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ducts</GlossaryTermRef>. Each breast has 15 to 20 sections called
		  lobes, which have many smaller sections called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046308" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lobules</GlossaryTermRef>. Lobules end in dozens of tiny bulbs that
		  can make milk. The lobes, lobules, and bulbs are linked by thin tubes called
		  ducts.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000415520" type="image/jpeg" alt="Illustration of the female breast anatomy. On the left, a front view shows lymph nodes inside the breast going from the breast to the armpit. On the right, a cross-section shows the chest wall, ribs, fatty tissue, lobes, ducts, and lobules. Also shown in both panels are the muscle, nipple, and areola." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_143"><Caption language="en">The female breast contains lobes, lobules, and ducts that produce and transport milk to the nipple. Fatty tissue gives the breast its shape, while muscles and the chest wall provide support. The lymphatic system, including lymph nodes, filter lymph and store white blood cells that help fight infection and disease. </Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_8">Each breast also has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood
		  vessels</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph
		  vessels</GlossaryTermRef>. The lymph vessels carry an almost colorless, watery fluid called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph</GlossaryTermRef>. Lymph
		  vessels carry lymph between <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph
		  nodes</GlossaryTermRef>. Lymph nodes are small, bean-shaped structures that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748828" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">filter</GlossaryTermRef>  lymph and store <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> that help fight
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef> and disease. Groups of lymph nodes are found near the breast in the
		  axilla (under the arm), above the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collarbone</GlossaryTermRef>, and in the chest.</Para><Para id="_177">Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summaries containing information related to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_178" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000257995" url="/types/breast/patient/breast-screening-pdq">Breast Cancer Screening</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062955" url="/types/breast/patient/breast-treatment-pdq">Breast Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062970" url="/types/breast/patient/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062969" url="/types/breast/patient/male-breast-treatment-pdq">Male Breast Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062855" url="/types/breast/hp/breast-ovarian-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Breast and Gynecologic Cancers</SummaryRef>  (written for health professionals)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_10">Breast cancer is the second leading cause of death from cancer
		  in American women.</KeyPoint><Para id="_11">Women in the United States get <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> more than any other
		  type of cancer except for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skin cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Breast cancer is second to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> as a cause of cancer death  in American women. Breast cancer
rates in women increased gradually for many years until the early 2000s and then decreased rapidly, coinciding with a drop in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmenopausal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef>  use. However, since 2005, there has been a small but steady increase in breast cancer rates in women. Deaths from breast cancer declined by 44% between 1989 and 2022. However, breast cancer deaths in Black women remain about 38% higher than in White women. Breast cancer also occurs in men, but the number of new
		  cases is small.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><Title>Breast Cancer Prevention</Title><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_14">Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may
		  help  prevent cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_13_md_53">Avoiding <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> may help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> certain cancers. Risk factors include smoking, having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overweight</GlossaryTermRef>, and not getting enough exercise.  Increasing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factors</GlossaryTermRef> such as quitting smoking and exercising may also help prevent some cancers. Talk to your doctor or other health care professional about how you might lower your risk of cancer.</Para><Para id="_179"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI's</GlossaryTermRef> <ExternalRef xref="https://bcrisktool.cancer.gov/">Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool</ExternalRef> uses a woman's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> to estimate her risk for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> during the next five years and up to age 90. This online tool is meant to be used by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care provider</GlossaryTermRef>. For more information on breast cancer risk,  call 1-800-4-CANCER.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_217"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_218">The following are <Emphasis>risk</Emphasis> factors for breast cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_289"><KeyPoint id="_290">Older age</KeyPoint><Para id="_291">Besides being a woman, older age is the main risk factor for breast cancer. The chance of getting breast cancer increases as a woman gets older. A 30-year-old woman has about a 1 in 175 chance of being <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> with breast cancer in the next 10 years, while a 70-year-old woman has a 1 in 9 chance of getting the disease during the same time period.</Para><Para id="_316">Women aged 50 to 69 years who have screening mammograms have a lower chance of dying from breast cancer than women who do not have screening mammograms. Screening by mammography decreases breast cancer deaths by identifying cases for treatment at an earlier stage.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_273"><KeyPoint id="_274">A personal history of breast cancer or benign (noncancer) breast disease</KeyPoint><Para id="_276">Women with any of the following have an increased risk of breast cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_275" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">invasive breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045674" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ductal carcinoma in situ</GlossaryTermRef> (DCIS), or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046315" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lobular carcinoma in situ</GlossaryTermRef> (LCIS).</ListItem><ListItem>a personal history of            <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign breast disease</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_285"><KeyPoint id="_286">Inherited risk of breast cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_287">Women with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of breast cancer in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460150" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">first-degree relative</GlossaryTermRef> (mother, sister, or daughter) have an increased risk of breast cancer.</Para><Para id="_194">Women who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> changes in the <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046047" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">BRCA1</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName> or <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">BRCA2</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> or in certain other genes have a higher risk of breast cancer. The risk of breast cancer caused by inherited gene changes depends on the type of gene <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutation</GlossaryTermRef>, family history of cancer, and other factors.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_195"><KeyPoint id="_196">Dense breast tissue</KeyPoint><Para id="_197">Having breast tissue that is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335487" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dense</GlossaryTermRef> on a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mammogram</GlossaryTermRef> is a factor in breast cancer risk. The level of risk  depends on how dense the breast tissue is. Women with very dense breasts have a higher risk of breast cancer than women with low breast density.</Para><Para id="_198">Increased breast density is often  an inherited trait, but it may also occur in women who have not had children, have a  first <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pregnancy</GlossaryTermRef> late in life,  take  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmenopausal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef>, or drink <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef>. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/breast-changes/dense-breasts">Dense Breasts: Answers to Commonly Asked Questions</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_199"><KeyPoint id="_200">Reproductive history resulting in greater exposure to estrogen</KeyPoint><Para id="_201"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046076" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Estrogen</GlossaryTermRef> is a hormone made by the body. It helps the body  develop and
			 maintain female sex characteristics. Being exposed to estrogen over a long time may increase the risk of breast cancer.  Estrogen levels are highest during the years a woman is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046297" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menstruating</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_268">The following factors in a woman's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reproductive history</GlossaryTermRef> increase the length of time her breast tissue is exposed to estrogen and may increase the risk of breast cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_202" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Early menstruation</Strong>: Beginning to have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000410605" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menstrual periods</GlossaryTermRef> before age 12 increases the number of years the breast tissue is exposed to
				estrogen.</ListItem> 
			 <ListItem><Strong>Starting <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopause</GlossaryTermRef> at a later age</Strong>: The more years a woman 
				menstruates, the longer her breast tissue is exposed to  estrogen.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Older age at birth of first child or never having given birth</Strong>: <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pregnancy</GlossaryTermRef> lowers a woman’s lifetime number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045784" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menstrual cycles</GlossaryTermRef>. Breast tissue is exposed to more estrogen for longer periods of time in women who become pregnant for the first time after age 35 or who never become pregnant.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_203"><KeyPoint id="_204">Taking hormone therapy for symptoms of menopause</KeyPoint><Para id="_205">Hormones, such as estrogen and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045158" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progesterone</GlossaryTermRef>, can be made into a pill form in a laboratory. Estrogen, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progestin</GlossaryTermRef>, or both may be given to replace the estrogen no longer made by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef> in postmenopausal women or women who have had their ovaries removed. This is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304725" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopausal hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (MHT) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046127" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone replacement therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (HRT).  Estrogen therapy that began close to the time of menopause is associated with an increased risk of developing breast cancer. Estrogen therapy that began at or after menopause is associated with an increased risk of developing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endometrial cancer</GlossaryTermRef>  and total cardiovascular disease, especially stroke.   The risk of breast cancer does not decrease after women stop taking estrogen.</Para><Para id="_317">Combination hormone therapy (HT) is estrogen combined with progestin. This type of  HT increases the risk of breast cancer.  Studies show that when women stop taking estrogen combined with progestin, the risk of breast cancer decreases.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_206"><KeyPoint id="_207">Radiation therapy to the breast or chest</KeyPoint><Para id="_208"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the chest for the treatment of cancer increases the risk of breast cancer, starting 10 years after treatment. The risk of  breast cancer depends on the        <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef>  and the age at which it was given. The risk is highest if radiation treatment was used during  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">puberty</GlossaryTermRef>, when breasts are forming.</Para><Para id="_209">Radiation therapy to treat cancer in one breast does not appear
			 to increase the risk of  cancer in the other breast.</Para><Para id="_210">For women who have inherited changes  in the <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> or <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>    gene,  exposure to radiation, such as that from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chest x-rays</GlossaryTermRef>, may further increase the risk of breast cancer, especially in women who had x-rays before age 20.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_211"><KeyPoint id="_212">Obesity</KeyPoint><Para id="_213"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Obesity</GlossaryTermRef> increases
				the risk of breast cancer, especially in postmenopausal women  who have not used HT.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_214"><KeyPoint id="_215">Drinking alcohol</KeyPoint><Para id="_216">Drinking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef>  increases the risk of breast cancer. The level of risk rises as the amount of alcohol consumed rises.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_77"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prevention methods</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_79">The following are <Emphasis>protective</Emphasis> factors  for breast cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_223"><KeyPoint id="_224">Reproductive history resulting in less exposure to estrogen</KeyPoint><Para id="_225">A woman’s reproductive history can affect the length of time her breast tissue is exposed to estrogen. Early onset of menstruation, late onset of menopause, later age at first pregnancy, and never having given birth have been linked to an increase in estrogen exposure and breast cancer risk. The following reproductive factors decrease the length of time a woman's breast tissue is exposed to estrogen and may help prevent breast cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_226" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>

Early pregnancy</Strong>: Estrogen levels are lower during pregnancy. In one study, women who had a full-term pregnancy before age 20 had a lower risk of breast cancer than women who did not have  children or who gave birth to their first child after age 35.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Breast-feeding</Strong>: Estrogen levels may remain lower while a woman is breast-feeding. Women who breastfed have a lower risk of breast cancer than women who have had children but did not breastfeed.</ListItem> </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_299"><KeyPoint id="_300">Taking selective estrogen receptor modulators or aromatase inhibitors and inactivators</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_83"><KeyPoint id="_84">Selective estrogen receptor modulators</KeyPoint><Para id="_186"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000509341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tamoxifen</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572250" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">raloxifene</GlossaryTermRef>   belong to the family of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">selective estrogen receptor modulators</GlossaryTermRef> (SERMs).   SERMs act like estrogen on some tissues in the body, but block the effect of estrogen on other tissues.</Para><Para id="_187">Treatment with tamoxifen lowers the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045270" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estrogen receptor-positive</GlossaryTermRef> (ER-positive) breast cancer and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DCIS</GlossaryTermRef> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045268" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">premenopausal</GlossaryTermRef> and postmenopausal women at high risk. Tamoxifen is also used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> breast cancer and to prevent cancer from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurring</GlossaryTermRef>  after surgery to remove breast <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>. Treatment with raloxifene also lowers the risk of breast cancer in postmenopausal women. With either drug, the reduced risk lasts for several years or longer after treatment is stopped. Lower rates of broken bones have been noted  in patients taking raloxifene.</Para><Para id="_86">

Taking tamoxifen increases the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256567" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hot flashes</GlossaryTermRef>, endometrial cancer, stroke, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440102" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cataracts</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clots</GlossaryTermRef> (especially in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef> and legs). The risk of having these problems increases markedly in women older than 50 years compared with younger women. Premenopausal women  who have a high risk of breast cancer may benefit the most from taking a low dose of tamoxifen, which may decrease breast cancer risk while also reducing some side effects of the drug. The risk of endometrial cancer  lasts for 5 years after tamoxifen is stopped,  but the risk of cataracts or blood clots does not last long. Talk with your doctor about the risks and benefits of taking this drug.</Para><Para id="_114">Taking raloxifene increases the risk of  blood clots in the lungs and legs but does not appear  to increase the risk of endometrial cancer. In postmenopausal women with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteoporosis</GlossaryTermRef> (decreased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone density</GlossaryTermRef>), raloxifene lowers the risk of breast cancer for women who have a high or low risk of breast cancer.   It is not known if raloxifene would have the same effect in women who do not have osteoporosis. Talk with your doctor about the risks and benefits of taking this drug.</Para><Para id="_136">Other SERMs are being studied in clinical trials.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_115"><KeyPoint id="_116">Aromatase inhibitors and inactivators</KeyPoint><Para id="_117"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044232" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Aromatase inhibitors</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045504" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anastrozole</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045421" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">letrozole</GlossaryTermRef>) and inactivators (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">exemestane</GlossaryTermRef>) lower the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrence</GlossaryTermRef> and of  new breast cancers in women who have    a history of breast cancer. Aromatase inhibitors also decrease the risk of breast cancer in women with the following conditions:</Para><ItemizedList id="_180" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>postmenopausal women with a personal history of breast cancer</ListItem><ListItem>	women with no personal history of breast cancer who are 60 years and older, have a history of DCIS with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045777" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mastectomy</GlossaryTermRef>, or have a high risk of breast cancer based on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256564" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gail model</GlossaryTermRef> tool (a tool used to estimate the risk of breast cancer)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_181">In  women with an increased risk of breast cancer, taking aromatase inhibitors decreases the amount of estrogen made by the body. Before menopause, estrogen is made by the ovaries and other tissues in a woman's body, including the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef>, fat tissue, and skin. After menopause, the ovaries stop making estrogen, but the other tissues do not. Aromatase inhibitors block the action of an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> called aromatase, which is used to make all of the body's estrogen. Aromatase inactivators stop the enzyme from working.</Para><Para id="_182">Possible harms from taking aromatase inhibitors include muscle and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">joint</GlossaryTermRef> pain, osteoporosis, hot flashes, and feeling very tired.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_91"><KeyPoint id="_92"> 
 

Risk-reducing or prophylactic mastectomy</KeyPoint><Para id="_93">Some women who have a high risk of breast cancer may choose to have a risk-reducing or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044227" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prophylactic mastectomy</GlossaryTermRef> (the removal of one or both breasts when there are no signs of cancer). After surgery, the risk of breast cancer becomes much lower in these women, and most feel less <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxious</GlossaryTermRef> about their risk of breast cancer.            Some women diagnosed with breast cancer may decide to have a healthy breast removed at the same time the breast with cancer is  removed. This is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803190" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">contralateral prophylactic mastectomy</GlossaryTermRef>. However,  it is very important to have a cancer risk assessment and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counseling</GlossaryTermRef> about the different ways to prevent breast cancer before making any decision about surgery.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><KeyPoint id="_141">Ovarian ablation</KeyPoint><Para id="_301">The ovaries make most of the estrogen that is made by the body. Treatments that stop or lower the amount of estrogen made by the ovaries include surgery to remove the ovaries, radiation therapy, or taking certain drugs. This is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045811" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovarian ablation</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_142">Premenopausal women who have a high risk of breast cancer due to certain  changes in the <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> or <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> gene may choose to have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000808594" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk-reducing oophorectomy</GlossaryTermRef>  (the removal of both ovaries when there are no signs of cancer). This decreases the amount of estrogen made by the body and lowers the risk of breast cancer. Risk-reducing oophorectomy also lowers the risk of breast cancer in average-risk premenopausal women and in women with an increased risk of breast cancer due to radiation to the chest. However, it is very important to have  a cancer risk assessment and counseling before making this decision. The sudden drop in estrogen levels may cause the      <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of menopause to begin. These include hot flashes, trouble sleeping, anxiety, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>. Long-term effects include decreased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sex drive</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044308" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaginal</GlossaryTermRef> dryness, and decreased bone density.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_227"><KeyPoint id="_228">Getting enough exercise</KeyPoint><Para id="_229">Women who take part in physical exercise have a  lower risk of breast cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_119"><KeyPoint id="_120">It is not clear whether the following  affect the risk of breast cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_307"><KeyPoint id="_308">Hormonal contraceptives</KeyPoint><Para id="_309"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormonal contraceptives</GlossaryTermRef> contain estrogen or estrogen and progestin. Some studies have shown that women who are current or recent users of hormonal contraceptives may have a slight increase in breast cancer risk. Other studies have not shown an increased risk of breast cancer in women using hormonal contraceptives.</Para><Para id="_310">In one study, the risk of breast cancer slightly increased the longer a woman used hormonal contraceptives. Another study showed that the slight increase in breast cancer risk decreased over time when women stopped using hormonal contraceptives.</Para><Para id="_311">More studies are needed to know whether hormonal contraceptives affect a woman's risk of breast cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_124"><KeyPoint id="_125">Chemicals in the environment</KeyPoint><Para id="_313"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> are studying whether exposure to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemicals</GlossaryTermRef> in the environment may increase a woman's risk of breast cancer.    Studies of this kind can be difficult to conduct and interpret for many reasons:</Para><ItemizedList id="_314" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>It is hard to determine the specific chemicals people have been exposed to in the past.  It can take decades after a potential exposure before cancer develops, and a person may not be aware of or remember the past exposure.</ListItem><ListItem>Even if a chemical is shown in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> to cause cancer, this does not necessarily mean it will cause cancer in people exposed to that chemical in the environment. A chemical may cause cancer when tested at high levels in laboratory studies but not at the lower levels seen in the environment.</ListItem><ListItem>Individual chemicals are likely to cause only a small increase in risk, and it can be difficult to detect that increase in the context of the other factors that may influence a woman's risk of breast cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_315">These reasons make it hard to know which chemicals, if any, may increase the risk of breast cancer.  More studies are needed to know whether chemicals in the environment affect a woman's risk of breast cancer.  To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/substances/carcinogens">Environmental Carcinogens and Cancer Risk</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_234"><KeyPoint id="_235">Studies have shown that some factors have little or no effect on the risk of breast cancer.</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_304"><Para id="_271">The following have little or no effect on the risk of breast cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_270" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having an abortion</ListItem><ListItem>making <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef> changes such as eating less fat or more fruits and vegetables</ListItem><ListItem>taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045233" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fenretinide</GlossaryTermRef> (a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin A</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cigarette</GlossaryTermRef> smoking, both active and passive (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhaling</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538647" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">secondhand smoke</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>	using underarm deodorant or antiperspirant</ListItem><ListItem>taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390255" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statins</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cholesterol</GlossaryTermRef>-lowering drugs)</ListItem><ListItem>taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044817" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bisphosphonates</GlossaryTermRef> (drugs used to treat osteoporosis and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypercalcemia</GlossaryTermRef>) by mouth or by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000520363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous infusion</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>changes in your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790629" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">circadian rhythm</GlossaryTermRef> (physical, mental, and behavioral changes that are mainly affected by darkness and light in 24 hour cycles), which may be affected by working night shifts or the amount of light in your bedroom at night</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_94"><KeyPoint id="_62">Cancer prevention clinical trials are used to study ways to prevent cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_94_md_14">Cancer prevention <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> are used to study ways to lower the risk of developing certain types of cancer. Some cancer prevention trials include healthy people who may or may not have an increased risk of cancer. Other prevention trials include people who have had cancer and are trying to prevent recurrence or a second cancer.</Para><Para id="_94_md_15">The purpose of some cancer prevention clinical trials is to find out whether actions people take can prevent cancer. These may include eating fruits and vegetables, exercising, quitting smoking, or taking certain medicines, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>, or food <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_63"><KeyPoint id="_64">New ways to prevent breast cancer  are being studied in clinical trials. </KeyPoint></SummarySection><Para id="_12_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about breast cancer prevention.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Breast Cancer Prevention. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/patient/breast-prevention-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/patient/breast-prevention-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389410]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062779"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-08</DateLastModified></Summary>
