<Summary id="CDR0000257990" LegacyPDQID="1094" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062686"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatment options for adult acute myeloid leukemia (AML) include chemotherapy, radiation therapy, stem cell transplant, and other medications. Get detailed information about the treatment of new and recurrent AML in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037885">adult acute myeloid leukemia</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_208">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult acute myeloid leukemia. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_209">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adult acute myeloid leukemia</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Acute Myeloid Leukemia</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Adult acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is a type of cancer in which the bone marrow makes a large number of abnormal blood cells.</KeyPoint><Para id="_91"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">AML</GlossaryTermRef> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> of the blood and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>.  It is the most common type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045145" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> in adults. This type of cancer usually gets worse quickly if it is not treated.  AML is also called acute myelogenous leukemia and acute nonlymphocytic leukemia.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000755927" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the bone; drawing shows spongy bone, red marrow, and yellow marrow. A cross section of the bone shows compact bone and blood vessels in the bone marrow. Also shown are red blood cells, white blood cells, platelets, and a blood stem cell." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_206"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the bone. The bone is made up of compact bone, spongy bone, and bone marrow. Compact bone makes up the outer layer of the bone. Spongy bone is found mostly at the ends of bones and contains red marrow. Bone marrow is found in the center of most bones and has many blood vessels. There are two types of bone marrow: red and yellow. Red marrow contains blood stem cells that can become red blood cells, white blood cells, or platelets. Yellow marrow is made mostly of fat.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_198"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_199">Leukemia may affect red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets.</KeyPoint><Para id="_200">The bone marrow makes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765906" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> (immature cells) that become mature blood cells over time. A blood stem cell may become a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046279" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myeloid</GlossaryTermRef> stem cell or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046298" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoid</GlossaryTermRef> stem cell.</Para><Para id="_201">Myeloid stem cells go through several stages of development in the bone marrow before fully maturing into:</Para><ItemizedList id="_202" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> that carry oxygen and other substances to all
			 tissues of the body</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">granulocytes</GlossaryTermRef> and other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> that help the body’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> respond to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>, allergens, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef> that  help stop bleeding by forming <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clots</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526219" type="image/jpeg" alt="Blood cell development; drawing shows the steps a blood stem cell goes through to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell. Drawing shows a myeloid stem cell becoming a red blood cell, platelet, or myeloblast, which then becomes a white blood cell. Drawing also shows a lymphoid stem cell becoming a lymphoblast and then one of several different types of white blood cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_156"><Caption language="en">Blood cell development. A blood stem cell goes through several steps to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_203">In AML, there is an increase in the number of immature white blood cells called myeloblasts (or myeloid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046503" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blasts</GlossaryTermRef>). The myeloblasts in AML are abnormal and do not become healthy white blood cells. As the number of these cells, also called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000804071" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia cells</GlossaryTermRef>, increases in the blood and bone marrow, there is less room for healthy platelets, red blood cells, and other white blood cells. This may lead to easy bleeding, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef>, and infection.</Para><Para id="_599">The leukemia cells can spread outside the blood to other parts of the body, including the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> (CNS; brain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>), skin, and gums. Sometimes leukemia cells form a solid tumor called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000806037" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myeloid sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>. Myeloid sarcoma is also called extramedullary myeloid tumor, granulocytic sarcoma, or chloroma.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by cell type</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_10">There are different subtypes of AML.</KeyPoint><Para id="_101">Most AML <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000733642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subtypes</GlossaryTermRef> are based on how mature (developed) the cancer cells are at the time of diagnosis, and how different they are from normal cells.</Para><Para id="_163"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Acute  promyelocytic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (APL) is a subtype of AML. This leukemia occurs when <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 15 switch places with some genes on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000737156" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosome 17</GlossaryTermRef>, and an abnormal gene called <GeneName>PML</GeneName>::<GeneName>RARA</GeneName> is made. The <GeneName>PML</GeneName>::<GeneName>RARA</GeneName> gene sends a message that stops promyelocytes (a type of white blood cell) from maturing. Problems with severe bleeding and blood clots may occur. This is a serious health problem that needs treatment as soon as possible. APL usually occurs in middle-aged adults.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_116">Smoking, previous chemotherapy treatment, and exposure to radiation may increase the risk of AML.</KeyPoint><Para id="_647">AML is caused by certain changes to the way blood stem cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Some risk factors for AML, like smoking, can be changed. However, risk factors also include things people cannot change, like their genetics, getting older, and their health history.</Para><Para id="_648">There are many risk factors for AML, but many do not directly cause cancer. Instead, they increase the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> damage in cells that may lead to AML. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_649">Having one or more of these risk factors does not mean that you will get AML. Many people with risk factors never develop AML, while others with no known risk factors do.</Para><Para id="_117">Possible risk factors for AML include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_118" Style="bullet"><ListItem>being male</ListItem><ListItem>older age</ListItem><ListItem>smoking</ListItem><ListItem>having had treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> in the past</ListItem><ListItem>being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> in the environment (such as nuclear radiation) or to the chemical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270734" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benzene</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of a blood disorder such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelodysplastic syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">syndromes</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> disorders</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_650">Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_14">Signs and symptoms of AML include fever, feeling tired, and easy bruising or bleeding.</KeyPoint><Para id="_15">The early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of AML may be like those caused by the flu or other common diseases. Check with your doctor if you have:</Para><ItemizedList id="_230" Style="bullet"><ListItem>weakness or feeling tired</ListItem><ListItem>fever</ListItem><ListItem>infection</ListItem><ListItem> paleness or loss of  normal skin color</ListItem><ListItem>bleeding</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_231">Less common signs or symptoms may be caused by clusters of leukemia cells in the CNS or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046611" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testicles</GlossaryTermRef>, or a tumor of myeloid cells called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chloroma</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_239">Symptoms of acute leukemia often develop between 4 and 6 weeks before diagnosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_17"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_18">Tests that examine the blood and bone marrow are used to diagnose AML.</KeyPoint><Para id="_19">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_20" Style="bullet"> 
		  
		  <ListItem><Strong>Complete blood
			 count (CBC)</Strong> checks a sample of blood for: 
			 <ItemizedList id="_21" Style="dash"> 
				<ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> and
				  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
				<ListItem>the number and type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the amount of hemoglobin (the protein that carries oxygen) in
				  the red blood cells</ListItem> 
				<ListItem>the amount of hematocrit (whole blood that is made up of red blood
				  cells)</ListItem> 
			 </ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526546" type="image/jpeg" alt="Complete blood count (CBC); left panel shows blood being drawn from a vein on the inside of the elbow using a tube attached to a syringe; right panel shows a laboratory test tube with blood cells separated into layers: plasma, white blood cells, platelets, and red blood cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_145"><Caption language="en">Complete blood count (CBC). Blood is collected by inserting a needle into a vein and allowing the blood to flow into a tube. The blood sample is sent to the laboratory and the red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets are counted.  The CBC is used to test for, diagnose, and monitor many different conditions.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong>Peripheral blood smear</Strong> checks a sample of blood for   blast cells, the number and kinds of white blood cells, the number of platelets, and changes in the shape of blood cells.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Flow cytometry</Strong> measures the number of cells in a sample, the percentage of live cells in a sample, and certain characteristics of the cells, such as size, shape, and the presence of tumor (or other) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> on the cell surface. The cells from a sample of a patient's blood, bone marrow, or other tissue are stained with a fluorescent dye, placed in a fluid, and then passed one at a time through a beam of light. The test results are based on how the cells that were stained with the fluorescent dye react to the beam of light. This test is used to help diagnose and manage certain types of cancers, such as leukemia and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy</Strong> is the removal of bone marrow, blood, and a small piece of bone by inserting a hollow needle into the hipbone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000549425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breastbone</GlossaryTermRef>. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the bone marrow, blood, and bone under a microscope to look for signs of cancer.  <MediaLink ref="CDR0000554337" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy; drawing shows a patient lying face down on a table and a bone marrow needle being inserted into the hip bone. An inset shows a close up of the needle being inserted through the skin and hip bone into the bone marrow." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_157"><Caption language="en">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy. After a small area of skin is numbed, a long, hollow needle is inserted through the patient's skin and hip bone into the bone marrow. A sample of bone marrow and a small piece of bone are removed for examination under a microscope.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem> 
		  
		  <ListItem><Strong>Tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of cells or tissues from a lump using a needle. This may be done if the doctor suspects the leukemia cells may have formed a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solid tumor</GlossaryTermRef> called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000806037" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myeloid sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> (also called a chloroma).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Cytogenetic analysis</Strong> checks the chromosomes of cells in a blood or bone marrow sample for changes, such as broken, missing, rearranged, or extra chromosomes. Changes in certain chromosomes may be a sign of cancer. Cytogenetic analysis is used to help diagnose cancer, plan treatment, or find out how well treatment is working. Other tests, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460151" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluorescence in situ hybridization</GlossaryTermRef> (FISH), may also be done to look for certain changes in the chromosomes.</ListItem> 
		<ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766166" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Molecular testing</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> checks for certain genes, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef>, or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef> in a sample of blood or bone marrow. Molecular tests also check for certain changes in a gene or chromosome that may cause or affect the chance of developing AML. A molecular test may be used to help plan treatment, find out how well treatment is working, or make a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Immunophenotyping</Strong> uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to identify cancer cells based on the types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> on the surface of the cells. This test is used to help diagnose specific types of leukemia. For example, a cytochemistry study may test the cells in a sample of tissue using chemicals (dyes) to look for certain changes in the sample. A chemical may cause a color change in one type of leukemia cell but not in another type of leukemia cell.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction test (RT-PCR)</Strong> measures the amount of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> substance called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000662001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mRNA</GlossaryTermRef> made by a specific gene. An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> called reverse transcriptase is used to convert a specific piece of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046568" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RNA</GlossaryTermRef> into a matching piece of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef>, which can be amplified (made in large numbers) by another enzyme called DNA polymerase. The amplified DNA copies help tell whether a specific mRNA is being made by a gene. RT-PCR can be used to check the activation of certain genes that may indicate the presence of cancer cells. This test may be used to look for certain changes in a gene or chromosome, which may help diagnose cancer. This test is used to diagnose certain types of AML including acute  promyelocytic leukemia (APL).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_165"><KeyPoint id="_166">After AML has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if the cancer has spread to other parts of the body. </KeyPoint><Para id="_167">  </Para><Para id="_229">The following tests and procedures may be used to determine if the leukemia has spread outside the blood and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_168" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Lumbar puncture</Strong> is a procedure used to collect a sample of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> (CSF) from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000396787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal column</GlossaryTermRef>.   This is done by placing a needle  between two bones in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef> and into the lining around the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> to remove a sample of CSF. The sample of CSF is checked under a microscope for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000804071" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia cells</GlossaryTermRef> have spread to the brain and spinal cord.   This procedure is also called an LP or spinal tap.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000503953" type="image/jpeg" alt="Lumbar puncture; drawing shows a patient lying in a curled position on a table and a spinal needle (a long, thin needle) being inserted into the lower back. Inset shows a close-up of the spinal needle inserted into the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in the lower part of the spinal column." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_169"><Caption language="en">Lumbar puncture. A patient lies in a curled position on a table. After a small area on the lower back is numbed, a spinal needle (a long, thin needle) is inserted into the lower part of the spinal column to remove cerebrospinal fluid (CSF, shown in blue). The fluid may be sent to a laboratory for testing.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs.  A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_640"><KeyPoint id="_641">Some people decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_642">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your AML diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_643">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI’s Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_23">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance
		  of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_94">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options for AML depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_99" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the person's age</ListItem><ListItem>whether the leukemia has spread to the CNS</ListItem><ListItem>whether the patient has a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044177" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef> at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>whether the patient has a very high white blood cell count at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>the subtype of AML</ListItem><ListItem>whether the patient received chemotherapy or radiation therapy in the past to treat a different cancer</ListItem><ListItem>whether there is a history of a blood disorder such as myelodysplastic syndrome</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has been treated before or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_98"> It is important to treat  AML right away. Older age at diagnosis may be linked to lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef> rates and more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complications</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_164"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stages of Acute Myeloid Leukemia</Title><SummarySection id="_170"><KeyPoint id="_171">There is no standard staging system for acute myeloid leukemia (AML).</KeyPoint><Para id="_645">The extent or spread of cancer is usually described as stages. Instead of stages, AML treatment is based on one or more of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_646" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257990#_9" url="/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">subtype</SummaryRef> of AML</ListItem><ListItem>whether the leukemia has spread outside the blood and bone marrow</ListItem><ListItem>whether the leukemia is newly diagnosed, in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045863" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_173"><Strong>Newly diagnosed (untreated) AML</Strong></Para><Para id="_174">In untreated AML, the disease is newly diagnosed.  It  has not been treated except to relieve signs and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> such as fever, bleeding, or pain, and the following are true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_175" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045107" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complete blood count</GlossaryTermRef> (CBC) is abnormal.</ListItem><ListItem>At least 20% of the cells  in the bone marrow are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046503" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blasts</GlossaryTermRef> (leukemia cells) or there are certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> changes.</ListItem><ListItem>There are signs or symptoms of leukemia.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_176"><Strong>AML in remission</Strong></Para><Para id="_177">In AML in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef>, the disease has been treated and the following are true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_178" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The CBC is normal.</ListItem><ListItem>Less than 5% of the cells in the bone marrow are blasts (leukemia cells).</ListItem><ListItem>There are no signs or symptoms of leukemia in the brain and spinal cord  or elsewhere in the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_179"><Strong>Refractory or recurrent AML</Strong></Para><Para id="_180">After treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, some people with newly diagnosed AML will not go into remission. This is called  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045863" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. In contrast, recurrent AML is cancer that has recurred
		(come back) after remission. The AML may come back in the
		blood or bone marrow.</Para><Para id="_644">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_37"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_38">There are different types of treatment for people with acute myeloid leukemia (AML). </KeyPoint><Para id="_638">Different types of treatments are available for people with AML. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the phase of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment.</Para><Para id="_639">Talking with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You'll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you'll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_46"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_126">The treatment of AML usually has two phases.</KeyPoint><Para id="_127">There are two treatment phases of AML:</Para><ItemizedList id="_128" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Remission induction therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is the first phase of treatment.  The goal is to kill the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000804071" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia cells</GlossaryTermRef> in the blood and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>.  This puts the leukemia into <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Consolidation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is the second phase of treatment.  It begins after the leukemia is in remission.  The goal of consolidation therapy  is to kill any remaining leukemia cells that may not be active but could begin to regrow and cause a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapse</GlossaryTermRef>.  This phase is also called remission continuation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_240"><KeyPoint id="_241">Patients receive supportive care for side effects of  treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_242">Patients must be closely monitored during
treatment of AML. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Myelosuppression</GlossaryTermRef>, a condition which results in fewer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef>, is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effect</GlossaryTermRef> of both AML and treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Supportive care</GlossaryTermRef> during remission induction therapy may  include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_243" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>red blood cell and platelet <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transfusions</GlossaryTermRef> to replace blood cells destroyed by the cancer or its treatment</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibiotics</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antifungals</GlossaryTermRef> to prevent or treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infections</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_135"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_47">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_48"><KeyPoint id="_49">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_610">Chemotherapy (also called chemo)  uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000733642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subtype</GlossaryTermRef> of AML being treated and whether the leukemia cells have spread to the central nervous system (CNS; brain and spinal cord). </Para><Para id="_611">Systemic chemotherapy is when chemotherapy drugs are taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body.</Para><Para id="_612">Systemic chemotherapy drugs used to treat AML include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_613" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496239" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/azacitidine">azacitidine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000540242" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cytarabine">cytarabine</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000649927" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/daunorubicinhydrochloride">daunorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000790948" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/daunorubicinhydrochlorideandcytarabineliposome">daunorubicin and cytarabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem> <DrugRef href="CDR0000495366" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/decitabine">decitabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000762190" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/idarubicinhydrochloride">idarubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000788890" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/midostaurin">midostaurin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000764240" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/mitoxantronehydrochloride">mitoxantrone</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_614">Combinations of these drugs may be used. Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_615">Intrathecal chemotherapy may be used to treat AML that has spread to the CNS (brain and spinal cord). Intrathecal chemotherapy is a method of placing chemotherapy directly into the cerebrospinal fluid, which is the fluid that surrounds the brain and spinal cord. This approach is used because the blood-brain barrier, a protective layer around the brain, can prevent chemotherapy drugs given by mouth or into a vein from reaching the CNS.</Para><Para id="_616">Cytarabine and <DrugRef href="CDR0000586940" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/methotrexate-sodium">methotrexate</DrugRef> are two chemotherapy drugs given as intrathecal chemotherapy to treat AML. These drugs can also be given systemically.</Para><Para id="_617"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000539773" type="image/jpeg" alt="Intrathecal chemotherapy; drawing shows the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in the brain and spinal cord, and an Ommaya reservoir (a dome-shaped container that is placed under the scalp during surgery; it holds the drugs as they flow through a small tube into the brain). Top section shows a syringe and needle injecting anticancer drugs into the Ommaya reservoir. Bottom section shows a syringe and needle injecting anticancer drugs directly into the cerebrospinal fluid in the lower part of the spinal column." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_159"><Caption language="en">Intrathecal chemotherapy. Anticancer drugs are injected into the intrathecal space, which is the space that holds the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF, shown in blue). There are two different ways to do this. One way, shown in the top part of the figure, is to inject the drugs into an Ommaya reservoir (a dome-shaped container that is placed under the scalp during surgery; it holds the drugs as they flow through a small tube into the brain). The other way, shown in the bottom part of the figure, is to inject the drugs directly into the CSF in the lower part of the spinal column, after a small area on the lower back is numbed.  </Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_619">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_51"><KeyPoint id="_52">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_53">Radiation therapy uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. AML is sometimes treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">external radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. This type of radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> sends radiation toward the whole body. It is a type of external radiation that may be used to prepare the body for a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> when the leukemia has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_620">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_131"><KeyPoint id="_132">Chemotherapy with stem cell transplant</KeyPoint><Para id="_133">High doses of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells. Healthy cells, including blood-forming cells, are also destroyed by the cancer treatment. Stem cell transplant is a treatment to replace the blood-forming cells. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> of the patient or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef> and are frozen and stored. After the patient completes chemotherapy and/or total-body irradiation, the stored stem cells are thawed and given back to the patient through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These reinfused stem cells grow into (and restore) the body's blood cells.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000765030" type="image/jpeg" alt="Donor stem cell transplant; (Panel 1): Drawing of stem cells being collected from a donor's bloodstream using an apheresis machine. Blood is removed from a vein in the donor's arm and flows through the machine where the stem cells are removed. The rest of the blood is then returned to the donor through a vein in their other arm. (Panel 2): Drawing of a health care provider giving a patient an infusion of chemotherapy through a catheter in the patient's chest. The chemotherapy is given to kill cancer cells and prepare the patient's body for the donor stem cells. (Panel 3): Drawing of a patient receiving an infusion of the donor stem cells through a catheter in the chest." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_207"><Caption language="en">Donor stem cell transplant. (Step 1): Four to five days before donor stem cell collection, the donor receives a medicine to increase the number of stem cells circulating through their bloodstream (not shown). The blood-forming stem cells are then collected from the donor through a large vein in their arm. The blood flows through an apheresis machine that removes the stem cells. The rest of the blood is returned to the donor through a vein in their other arm. (Step 2): The patient receives chemotherapy to kill cancer cells and prepare their body for the donor stem cells. The patient may also receive radiation therapy (not shown). (Step 3): The patient receives an infusion of the donor stem cells.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_625">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/stem-cell-transplant">Stem Cell Transplants in Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_244"><KeyPoint id="_245">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_246">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. Your doctor may suggest <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000805418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biomarker tests</GlossaryTermRef> to help predict your response to certain targeted therapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_621">Targeted therapies used to treat AML include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_622" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000505269" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemtuzumabozogamicin">gemtuzumab ozogamicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem>
     <DrugRef href="CDR0000788890" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/midostaurin">midostaurin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000813149" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/quizartinib-dihydrochloride">quizartinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000817185" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/revumenib-citrate">revumenib</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_605">Less-intensive targeted therapies in people who are unable or unwilling to receive other treatments  include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_623" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000790240" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/enasidenibmesylate">enasidenib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000796043" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gilteritinibfumarate">gilteritinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000796042" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/glasdegibmaleate">glasdegib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000794061" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ivosidenib">ivosidenib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000780272" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/venetoclax">venetoclax</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_624">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_137"><KeyPoint id="_138">Other drug therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_139"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046018" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Arsenic trioxide</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367465" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">all-trans retinoic acid</GlossaryTermRef> (ATRA) are anticancer drugs that kill leukemia cells, stop the leukemia cells from dividing, or help the leukemia cells mature into white blood cells.  These drugs are used in the treatment of a subtype of AML called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute promyelocytic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_58">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.
		  </KeyPoint><Para id="_57_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_57_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_57_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_213"><KeyPoint id="_214">Treatment for acute myeloid leukemia may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_213_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_154"><KeyPoint id="_155">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_154_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_154_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_217"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037885">adult acute myeloid leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Untreated Acute Myeloid Leukemia</Title><Para id="_219"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Standard  treatment</GlossaryTermRef> of untreated acute myeloid leukemia (AML) during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef> phase depends on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000733642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subtype</GlossaryTermRef> of AML and may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_220" Style="bullet"><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> that includes <DrugRef href="CDR0000540242" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cytarabine">cytarabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem>combination chemotherapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000788890" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/midostaurin">midostaurin</DrugRef> or <DrugRef href="CDR0000813149" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/quizartinib-dihydrochloride">quizartinib</DrugRef>), for people whose AML has a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutation</GlossaryTermRef> in the  <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000789010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FLT3 gene</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName></ListItem><ListItem>combination chemotherapy with the targeted therapy drug <DrugRef href="CDR0000505269" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemtuzumabozogamicin">gemtuzumab ozogamicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (cytarabine or <DrugRef href="CDR0000586940" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/methotrexate-sodium">methotrexate</DrugRef>), for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> (CNS) leukemia</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supportive care</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_252">For older adults or people who are unable or unwilling to receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000796903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intensive chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, the following may be continued as long as the person benefits or  until <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxic</GlossaryTermRef> effects occur:</Para><ItemizedList id="_598" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>targeted therapy (<DrugRef href="CDR0000790240" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/enasidenibmesylate">enasidenib</DrugRef>,
<DrugRef href="CDR0000796043" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gilteritinibfumarate">gilteritinib</DrugRef>,
<DrugRef href="CDR0000796042" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/glasdegibmaleate">glasdegib</DrugRef>,
<DrugRef href="CDR0000794061" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ivosidenib">ivosidenib</DrugRef>, or
<DrugRef href="CDR0000780272" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/venetoclax">venetoclax)</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">low-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000496239" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/azacitidine">azacitidine</DrugRef>, low-dose <DrugRef href="CDR0000540242" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cytarabine">cytarabine</DrugRef>, or <DrugRef href="CDR0000495366" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/decitabine">decitabine</DrugRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>targeted therapy with low-dose chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>intrathecal chemotherapy, for CNS leukemia</ListItem><ListItem>supportive care</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_629">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257990#_135" url="/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_217_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_221"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039083">adult acute myeloid leukemia in remission</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Acute Myeloid Leukemia in Remission</Title><Para id="_223">Treatment of acute myeloid leukemia (AML)  during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef> phase depends on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000733642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subtype</GlossaryTermRef> of AML and may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_224" Style="bullet"><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> that includes <DrugRef href="CDR0000540242" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cytarabine">cytarabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <DrugRef href="CDR0000788890" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/midostaurin">midostaurin</DrugRef>, for people whose AML has a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutation</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000789010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FLT3 gene</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName></ListItem><ListItem>maintenance therapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> using the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cells</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>high-dose chemotherapy, with or without radiation therapy, or reduced-intensity therapy, followed by a stem cell transplant using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef> stem cells</ListItem> 
		  
		  
		   
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_630">Learn more about these treatments in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257990#_135" url="/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_221_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_225"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038678">recurrent adult acute myeloid leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Refractory or Recurrent Acute Myeloid Leukemia</Title><Para id="_227">There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045863" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> acute myeloid leukemia (AML). Treatment depends on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000733642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subtype</GlossaryTermRef> of AML and may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_228" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <DrugRef href="CDR0000790240" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/enasidenibmesylate">enasidenib</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000505269" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemtuzumabozogamicin">gemtuzumab ozogamicin</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000796043" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gilteritinibfumarate">gilteritinib</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000794061" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ivosidenib">ivosidenib</DrugRef>, or <DrugRef href="CDR0000817185" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/revumenib-citrate">revumenib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cells</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_631">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257990#_135" url="/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_225_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_232"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039910">adult acute promyelocytic leukemia (M3)</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by cell type</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia</Title><Para id="_233">Treatment of newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute promyelocytic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (APL) may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_234" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367465" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">all-trans retinoic acid</GlossaryTermRef> (ATRA) plus  <DrugRef href="CDR0000500188" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/arsenictrioxide">arsenic trioxide</DrugRef> (ATO), for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">low-risk</GlossaryTermRef> to intermediate-risk disease</ListItem><ListItem>ATRA plus <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, followed by ATO, for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-risk</GlossaryTermRef> disease</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_632">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257990#_135" url="/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_232_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_235"><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia</Title><Para id="_600">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute promyelocytic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (APL) may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_236" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000500188" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/arsenictrioxide">arsenic trioxide</DrugRef> (ATO) with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> using the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef> stem cells</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_633">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257990#_135" url="/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_142"><Title>To Learn More About Leukemia</Title><Para id="_143">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  leukemia, visit the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia">Leukemia Home Page</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_142_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_142_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult acute myeloid leukemia.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389377]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062869"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
