<Summary id="CDR0000257999" LegacyPDQID="1491" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062727"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood Hodgkin lymphoma (classical or nodular lymphocyte-predominant HL) treatment usually involves chemotherapy and/or radiation therapy. Learn more about the symptoms, diagnosis, staging, and treatment of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/hp/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040228">childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000566058">childhood nodular lymphocyte predominant Hodgkin lymphoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_260">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_261">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly, and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              </Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Childhood nodular lymphocyte-predominant Hodgkin lymphoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Childhood Hodgkin lymphoma is a cancer that develops in the lymph system.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef> is part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>. It helps protect the body from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef> and disease.</Para><Para id="_279">The lymph system is made up of:</Para><ItemizedList id="_280" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph</GlossaryTermRef>: Colorless, watery fluid that travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> and transports <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">T</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044953" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">B lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef> are a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cell</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph vessels: A network of thin tubes that collect lymph from different parts of the body and return it to the bloodstream.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>: Small, bean-shaped structures that filter  lymph and store white blood cells that help fight infection and disease. Lymph nodes are found along a network of lymph vessels throughout the body. Groups of lymph nodes are found in the neck, underarm, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046288" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mediastinum</GlossaryTermRef> (the area between the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef>. Hodgkin lymphoma most commonly forms in the lymph nodes above the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diaphragm</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Spleen</GlossaryTermRef>: An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> that makes lymphocytes, stores <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> and lymphocytes, filters the blood, and destroys old blood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>. The spleen is  on the left side of the abdomen near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046616" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thymus</GlossaryTermRef>: An organ in which T lymphocytes mature and multiply. The thymus is in the chest behind the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000549425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breastbone</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>: The soft, spongy tissue in the center of certain bones, such as the hip bone and breastbone. White blood cells, red blood cells, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef> are made in the bone marrow.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tonsils</GlossaryTermRef>: Two small masses of lymph tissue at the back of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef>. There is one tonsil on each side of the throat.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000653807" type="image/jpeg" alt="Lymph system; drawing shows the tonsils, thymus, spleen, bone marrow, lymph vessels, and lymph nodes. One inset shows the inside structure of a lymph node and the attached lymph vessels with arrows showing how the lymph (clear, watery fluid) moves into and out of the lymph node. Another inset shows a close up of bone marrow with blood cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_237"><Caption language="en">The lymph system is part of the body's immune system and is made up of tissues and organs that help protect the body from infection and disease. These include the tonsils, thymus, spleen, bone marrow, lymph vessels, and lymph nodes. Lymph (clear, watery fluid) and lymphocytes (white blood cells) travel through the lymph vessels and into the lymph nodes where the lymphocytes destroy harmful substances. The lymph enters the bloodstream through a large vein near the heart.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_5">Bits of lymph tissue are also found in other parts of the body such as the lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal tract</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045629" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bronchus</GlossaryTermRef>, and skin.</Para><Para id="_125">There are two general types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>: Hodgkin lymphoma and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-Hodgkin
		  lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>. This summary is about the treatment of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma.</Para><Para id="_7"> Hodgkin lymphoma occurs most often in adolescents 15 to 19 years of age. The
		  treatment for children and adolescents is different than treatment for adults.</Para><Para id="_293">Other PDQ summaries with information related to lymphoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_294" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258002" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-nhl-treatment-pdq">Childhood Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000257991" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/adult-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_135">The  two main types of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma are classic and nodular lymphocyte-predominant.</KeyPoint><ItemizedList id="_157" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000574284" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Classic Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the most common type of Hodgkin lymphoma. It occurs most often in adolescents. When a sample of lymph node tissue is looked at under a microscope, Hodgkin lymphoma <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cells, called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046557" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Reed-Sternberg cells</GlossaryTermRef>, may be seen.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000576466" type="image/jpeg" alt="Reed-Sternberg cell; photograph shows normal lymphocytes compared with a Reed-Sternberg cell." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_185"><Caption language="en">Reed-Sternberg cell. Reed-Sternberg cells are large, abnormal lymphocytes (a type of white blood cell) that may contain more than one nucleus. These cells are found in people with Hodgkin lymphoma. Reed-Sternberg cells are also called Hodgkin and Reed-Sternberg cells.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_295">Classic Hodgkin lymphoma is divided into four subtypes, based on how the cancer cells look under a microscope:</Para><ItemizedList id="_296" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Nodular-sclerosing Hodgkin lymphoma occurs most often in older children and adolescents. It is common to have a chest <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638197" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mass</GlossaryTermRef> at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Mixed cellularity Hodgkin lymphoma most often occurs in children younger than 10 years of age. It is linked to a history of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef> (EBV) infection and often occurs in the lymph nodes of the neck.</ListItem><ListItem>Lymphocyte-rich Hodgkin lymphoma is rare in children. When a sample of lymph node tissue is looked at under a microscope, there are Reed-Sternberg cells and many normal lymphocytes and other blood cells.</ListItem><ListItem>Lymphocyte-depleted Hodgkin lymphoma is rare in children and occurs most often in older adults and adults with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HIV</GlossaryTermRef>. When a sample of lymph node tissue is looked at under a microscope, there are many large, oddly shaped cancer cells and few normal lymphocytes and other blood cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000574286" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nodular lymphocyte-predominant Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is less common than classic Hodgkin lymphoma. It most often occurs in children younger than 10 years of age. Nodular lymphocyte-predominant Hodgkin lymphoma often occurs as a swollen lymph node in the neck, underarm, or groin. Most children do not have any other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer at diagnosis. When a sample of lymph node tissue is looked at under a microscope, the cancer cells are shaped like popcorn.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_9">Epstein-Barr virus infection and a family history of Hodgkin lymphoma can increase
		  the risk of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_10">Anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop childhood Hodgkin lymphoma, and it can develop in some children who don't have any known risk factors. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_252">Risk factors for childhood Hodgkin lymphoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_121" Style="bullet"><ListItem>being infected with the Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)</ListItem><ListItem>being infected with HIV</ListItem><ListItem>having certain diseases of the immune system, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">autoimmune</GlossaryTermRef> lymphoproliferative syndrome</ListItem><ListItem>having a weakened immune system after an organ <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef> or from medicine given after a transplant to stop the organ from being rejected by the body</ListItem><ListItem>having a parent, brother, or sister with a personal history of Hodgkin lymphoma</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2721"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Inherited</GlossaryTermRef> changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> may increase the risk of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma.</Para><Para id="_220">Being exposed to common infections in early childhood may decrease the risk of Hodgkin lymphoma in children.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_13">Signs of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma include swollen
		  lymph nodes, fever, drenching night sweats, and weight loss.</KeyPoint><Para id="_14">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of Hodgkin lymphoma depend on where the cancer forms in the body and the size of the cancer. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>painless, swollen lymph nodes near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collarbone</GlossaryTermRef> or in the neck, chest, underarm, or groin</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>fever for no known reason</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>drenching night sweats</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anorexia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>itchy skin</ListItem> 
		<ListItem>coughing</ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing, especially when lying down</ListItem><ListItem>pain in the lymph nodes after drinking alcohol</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_221">Fever for no known reason, weight loss for no known reason, or drenching night sweats are called B symptoms. B symptoms are an important part of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef> Hodgkin lymphoma and understanding the patient's chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_2707">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than childhood Hodgkin lymphoma. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor. The doctor will ask you when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them as a first step in making a diagnosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">Tests that examine the lymph system and other parts of the body are used to diagnose
		   and stage childhood Hodgkin lymphoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_297">If your child has symptoms that suggest Hodgkin lymphoma, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or to another problem. They will ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. The doctor may recommend diagnostic tests to find out if your child has Hodgkin lymphoma. The results of these tests will also help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_2708">The tests used to diagnose Hodgkin lymphoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong>Complete blood count (CBC)</Strong>: A procedure in which a sample of blood is drawn and checked for:<ItemizedList id="_298" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The number of red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets.</ListItem><ListItem>The amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemoglobin</GlossaryTermRef> (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> that carries <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef>) in the red blood cells.</ListItem><ListItem>The portion of the blood sample made up of red blood cells.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000526546" type="image/jpeg" alt="Complete blood count (CBC); left panel shows blood being drawn from a vein on the inside of the elbow using a tube attached to a syringe; right panel shows a laboratory test tube with blood cells separated into layers: plasma, white blood cells, platelets, and red blood cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_304"><Caption language="en">Complete blood count (CBC). Blood is collected by inserting a needle into a vein and allowing the blood to flow into a tube. The blood sample is sent to the laboratory and the red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets are counted.  The CBC is used to test for, diagnose, and monitor many different conditions.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Blood chemistry studies</Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000616062" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">albumin</GlossaryTermRef>, by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>C-reactive protein test</Strong>: A test in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amount of c-reactive protein in the blood. C-reactive protein is made by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> and sent to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bloodstream</GlossaryTermRef> in response to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammation</GlossaryTermRef>. A higher-than-normal amount of c-reactive protein in the blood may be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Sedimentation rate</Strong>: A procedure in which a sample of blood is drawn and checked for the rate at which the red blood cells settle to the bottom of the test tube. The sedimentation rate is a measure of how much inflammation is in the body.  A higher-than-normal sedimentation rate may be a sign of lymphoma.  Also called erythrocyte sedimentation rate, sed rate, or ESR.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CT scan (CAT scan)</Strong>:  A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the neck, chest, abdomen, or pelvis, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.  Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_262"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>PET scan (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> tumor cells in the body.  A small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive glucose</GlossaryTermRef> (sugar) is injected into a vein.  The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body.  Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000775456" type="image/jpeg" alt="Positron emission tomography (PET) scan; drawing shows a child lying on table that slides through the PET scanner." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_263"><Caption language="en">Positron emission tomography (PET) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the PET scanner. The head rest and white strap help the child lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the child's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>MRI (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the lymph nodes. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_292"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>PET-CT scan</Strong>: A procedure that combines the pictures from a positron emission tomography (PET) scan and a computed tomography (CT) scan. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time with the same machine. The combined scans give more detailed pictures of areas inside the body than either scan gives by itself.</ListItem><ListItem> <Strong>PET-MRI scan</Strong>: A procedure that combines the pictures from a positron emission tomography (PET) scan and a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. A PET scan uses a radioactive tracer to highlight abnormal areas in the body. An MRI uses radio waves and a powerful magnet to take detailed pictures of tissues in the body. For a PET-MRI, the scans are done at the same time with the same machine. The combined scans give more detailed pictures of areas inside the body than either scan gives by itself. The overall amount of radiation a person is exposed to is also reduced. A PET-MRI may be used to help diagnose disease, such as cancer, plan treatment, or find out how well treatment is working.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Chest x-ray</Strong>: An x-ray of the organs and bones inside the chest.  An x-ray is a type of energy beam that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the body.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy</Strong>:  The removal of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> and a small piece of bone by inserting a hollow needle into the hipbone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000549425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breastbone</GlossaryTermRef>. A pathologist views the bone marrow and bone under a microscope to look for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> cells. Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy is done for patients with advanced disease and/or B symptoms.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775458" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy; drawing shows a child lying face down on a table and a bone marrow needle being inserted into the right hip bone. An inset shows the bone marrow needle being inserted through the skin into the bone marrow of the hip bone." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_305"><Caption language="en">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy. After a small area of skin is numbed, a bone marrow needle  is inserted into the child’s hip bone.  Samples of blood, bone, and bone marrow are removed for examination under a microscope.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Lymph node biopsy</Strong>:
			 The removal of all or part of one or more lymph nodes. The lymph node may be removed during an image-guided CT scan or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046119" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thoracoscopy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046287" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mediastinoscopy</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laparoscopy</GlossaryTermRef>. One of the following types of
			 biopsies may be done: 
			 <ItemizedList id="_126" Style="dash"><ListItem><Strong>Excisional biopsy</Strong>: The removal of an entire lymph node. </ListItem> 
				<ListItem><Strong>Incisional biopsy</Strong>: The removal of part of a lymph node.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Core biopsy</Strong>: The removal of tissue from a lymph node using a wide needle.</ListItem> 
				</ItemizedList><Para id="_183">A pathologist views the lymph node tissue under a microscope to check for cancer cells called Reed-Sternberg cells. Reed-Sternberg cells are common in classic Hodgkin lymphoma.</Para><Para id="_222">The following test may be done on tissue that was removed:</Para><ItemizedList id="_223" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Immunophenotyping</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to identify cancer cells based on the types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> on the surface of the cells. This test is used to help diagnose specific types of lymphoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2714"><KeyPoint id="_2715">You may want to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_2716">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's diagnosis and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">treatment plan</GlossaryTermRef>. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get important medical test results from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>, slides, and scans before giving a recommendation. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another approach, or provide more information about your child's cancer.</Para><Para id="_2717">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_21">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance
		  of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_127">If your child has been diagnosed with Hodgkin lymphoma, you may have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef>. The prognosis depends
		  on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_128" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer (the size of the cancer, including whether the cancer is a larger tumor mass called bulky disease, and whether the cancer has spread below the diaphragm or to more than one group of lymph nodes)</ListItem><ListItem> whether there are B symptoms (fever for no known reason, weight loss for no known reason, or drenching night sweats) at diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>the type of Hodgkin lymphoma</ListItem><ListItem>having more than the usual  number of white blood cells or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef> at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>whether there is fluid around the heart or lungs at diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>the sedimentation rate or the albumin level in the blood</ListItem><ListItem>the child's sex</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_22">The treatment options also depend
		  on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_129" Style="bullet"><ListItem>whether there is a low, medium, or high risk the cancer will come back after treatment</ListItem><ListItem>the child's age</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">long-term side effects</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_147">Most children and adolescents with newly diagnosed
		  Hodgkin lymphoma can be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cured</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_2713">Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_24"><Title>Stages of Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</Title><SummarySection id="_25"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_26">After childhood Hodgkin lymphoma has been diagnosed,
		  tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the lymph
		  system or to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_27">The process used to find out if cancer has spread is called staging. The information gathered from the staging
		  process determines the stage of the
		  disease.  The results of the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_16" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">tests and procedures</SummaryRef> done to diagnose and stage <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> are used to help make decisions about treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_186"><KeyPoint id="_187">There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_186_md_69">Cancer can spread through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_186_md_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.
</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_34">The following stages are used for childhood Hodgkin lymphoma:
		  </KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_35"><KeyPoint id="_36">Stage I</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000648701" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage I childhood Hodgkin lymphoma; drawing shows cancer in one lymph node group above the diaphragm and in the spleen. Also shown are the Waldeyer’s ring and the thymus. An inset shows a lymph node with a lymph vessel, an artery, and a vein. Cancer cells are shown inside the lymph node." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_211"><Caption language="en">Stage I childhood Hodgkin lymphoma. Cancer is found in one or more lymph nodes in a group of lymph nodes or, in rare cases, cancer is found in the Waldeyer’s ring, thymus, or spleen. In stage IE (not shown), cancer has spread to one area outside the lymph system.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_198"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430896" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage I</GlossaryTermRef> is divided into stage I and stage IE.</Para><ItemizedList id="_199" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Stage I: Cancer is found in one of the following places in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>:<ItemizedList id="_224" Style="bullet"><ListItem>One or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in one lymph node group.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000777073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Waldeyer's ring</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046616" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thymus</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Spleen</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Stage IE: Cancer is found outside the lymph system in one  organ or area.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><KeyPoint id="_39">Stage II</KeyPoint><Para id="_40"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430897" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage II</GlossaryTermRef> is divided
			 into stage II and stage IIE.</Para><ItemizedList id="_200" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Stage II: Cancer is found in two or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> groups either above or below the diaphragm (the thin muscle below the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef> that helps breathing and separates the chest from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>).<MediaLink ref="CDR0000648702" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage II childhood Hodgkin lymphoma; drawing shows cancer in two lymph node groups above the diaphragm and below the diaphragm. An inset shows a lymph node with a lymph vessel, an artery, and a vein. Cancer cells are shown inside the lymph node." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_212"><Caption language="en">Stage II childhood Hodgkin lymphoma. Cancer is found in two or more lymph node groups that are either above the diaphragm or below the diaphragm.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIE: Cancer has spread from a group of lymph nodes to a nearby organ that is outside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer may have spread to other lymph node groups on the same side of the diaphragm.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000648703" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IIE childhood Hodgkin lymphoma; drawing shows cancer in a lymph node group above the diaphragm and cancer that has spread to a nearby area (the left lung). An inset shows a lymph node with a lymph vessel, an artery, and a vein. Cancer cells are shown inside the lymph node." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_213"><Caption language="en">Stage IIE childhood Hodgkin lymphoma. Cancer has spread from a group of lymph nodes to a nearby organ or area that is outside the lymph system.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_41"><KeyPoint id="_42">Stage III </KeyPoint><Para id="_43">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430898" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III</GlossaryTermRef>, the cancer is found:</Para><ItemizedList id="_201" Style="bullet"><ListItem>in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> groups above and below the diaphragm (the thin muscle below the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef> that helps breathing and separates the chest from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>); or </ListItem><ListItem>in lymph node groups above the diaphragm and in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000648704" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage III childhood Hodgkin lymphoma; drawing shows (a) cancer in lymph node groups above and below the diaphragm. Also shown is (b) cancer in a lymph node group above the diaphragm and cancer in the spleen. The lungs are also shown. An inset shows a close-up of a lymph node with a lymph vessel, an artery, and a vein. Cancer cells are shown inside the lymph node." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_2722"><Caption language="en">Stage III childhood Hodgkin lymphoma. Cancer is found (a) in lymph node groups above and below the diaphragm; or (b) in lymph node groups above the diaphragm and in the spleen.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_44"><KeyPoint id="_45">Stage IV</KeyPoint><Para id="_204">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430899" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IV</GlossaryTermRef>, the cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_205" Style="bullet"><ListItem>has spread throughout one or more organs outside the lymph system and may be in lymph nodes near those organs; or</ListItem><ListItem>is found in two or more groups of lymph nodes that are on the same side of the diaphragm (the thin muscle below the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef> that helps breathing and separates the chest from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>) and in an organ that is outside the lymph system and not near the affected lymph nodes; or</ListItem><ListItem>is found in groups of lymph nodes on both side of the diaphragm and in any organ that is outside the lymph system; or</ListItem><ListItem>has spread to the lungs, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> from areas far away. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000648705" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IV childhood Hodgkin lymphoma; drawing shows four panels: (a) the top left panel shows cancer in the liver; (b) the top right panel shows cancer in the left lung and in two groups of lymph nodes below the diaphragm; (c) the bottom left panel shows cancer in the left lung and in a group of lymph nodes above the diaphragm and below the diaphragm; and (d) the bottom right panel shows cancer in both lungs and the liver. There is also a pullout showing cancer in the bone marrow." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_2723"><Caption language="en">Stage IV childhood Hodgkin lymphoma. Cancer (a) has spread throughout one or more organs outside the lymph system, such as the liver; or (b) is found in two or more groups of lymph nodes that are on the same side of the diaphragm  and in an organ that is outside the lymph system, such as the lung, and not near the affected lymph nodes; or (c) is found in groups of lymph nodes on both sides of the diaphragm and in any organ that is outside the lymph system, such as the lung; or (d) has spread to the lungs, liver, or bone marrow from areas far away.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_299"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_300">In addition to the stage number, the letters A, B, E, or S may be noted.</KeyPoint><Para id="_301">The letters A, B, E, or S may be used to further describe the stage of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma.</Para><ItemizedList id="_302" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A: The patient does not have B symptoms (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef>, weight loss, or drenching night sweats).</ListItem><ListItem>B: The patient has B symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem>E: Cancer is found in an organ or tissue that is not part of  the lymph
			 system but which may be  next to an area of the lymph system affected by the cancer. </ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>S: Cancer is found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_162">Childhood Hodgkin lymphoma is treated according to risk groups.</KeyPoint><Para id="_163">Untreated childhood Hodgkin lymphoma is divided into <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000711109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk groups</GlossaryTermRef> based on the stage, size of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>,  and whether the patient has B symptoms (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef>, weight loss, or drenching night sweats). The risk group describes the likelihood that Hodgkin lymphoma will not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recur</GlossaryTermRef> (come back) after treatment. It is used to plan initial treatment.

</Para><ItemizedList id="_164" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_83" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Low-risk childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_89" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Intermediate-risk childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_102" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">High-risk          childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_303">Low-risk Hodgkin lymphoma requires fewer cycles of treatment, fewer anticancer drugs, and lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of anticancer drugs than high-risk lymphoma.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_306"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_307">Sometimes childhood Hodgkin lymphoma does not respond to treatment  or comes back after treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_308">Primary refractory Hodgkin lymphoma  is cancer that does not respond to initial treatment.</Para><Para id="_309">Recurrent Hodgkin lymphoma is cancer that  has recurred
		(come back) after it has been treated. The lymphoma may come back in the
		lymph system or in other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, bones, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_51"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_52"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_53">There are different types of treatment for children with
		  Hodgkin lymphoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_54">There are different types of treatment for children with
		  Hodgkin lymphoma. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health, and whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_56"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_57">Children with Hodgkin lymphoma should have their treatment
		  planned by a team of health care providers who are experts in treating childhood
		  cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_58">A
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric
		  oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>, a doctor who specializes
		  in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma. The pediatric oncologist works with
		  other pediatric health care providers who are experts in treating children
		  with Hodgkin lymphoma and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_59" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medical
			 oncologist</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046370" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hematologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation
			 oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		   
		   
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		<ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_233">The treatment of  Hodgkin lymphoma in adolescents and young adults may be different than the treatment for children. Some adolescents and young adults are treated with an adult treatment <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimen</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_66">The following types of treatment may be used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_67"><KeyPoint id="_68">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_119">Chemotherapy is a cancer treatment that uses one or more drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them  from dividing.   Cancer treatment using more than one chemotherapy drug is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.  When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para><Para id="_225">The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000711109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk group</GlossaryTermRef>. For example, children with low-risk Hodgkin lymphoma receive fewer cycles of treatment, fewer anticancer drugs, and lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of anticancer drugs than children with high-risk lymphoma.</Para><Para id="_219">For more information, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/hodgkin-lymphoma">Drugs Approved for Hodgkin Lymphoma</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><KeyPoint id="_71">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_120">Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para><Para id="_310">Certain ways of giving radiation therapy can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>. These types of external radiation therapy include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_267" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270731" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Conformal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a  type of external radiation therapy that uses a computer to make a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3-D) picture of the tumor and shapes the radiation beams to fit the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (IMRT) is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044487" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional (3-D) radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> that uses a computer to make pictures of the size and shape of the tumor. Thin beams of radiation of different intensities (strengths) are aimed at the tumor from many angles.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_269">Radiation therapy may be given, based on the child's risk group and chemotherapy regimen. The radiation is given only to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> or other areas with cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_207"><KeyPoint id="_208">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_209">Targeted therapy is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells.  Types of targeted therapy include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_283" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046066" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Monoclonal antibody</GlossaryTermRef> therapy: Monoclonal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef> made in the laboratory to treat many diseases, including cancer.  As a cancer treatment, these antibodies can attach to a specific target on cancer cells or other cells that may help cancer cells grow.  The antibodies are able to then kill the cancer cells, block their growth, or keep them from spreading.  Monoclonal antibodies are given by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>.  They may be used alone or to carry drugs, toxins, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> material directly to cancer cells.<Para id="_287"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Rituximab</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000710543" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brentuximab</GlossaryTermRef> may be used to treat high-risk, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> childhood Hodgkin lymphoma.</Para><EmbeddedVideo id="_332" ref="CDR0000801837" hosting="youtube" unique_id="dxnjAc-rqz8" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>monoclonal antibodies: how monoclonal antibodies treat cancer</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">How do  monoclonal antibodies work to treat cancer? This video shows how monoclonal antibodies, such as trastuzumab, pembrolizumab, and rituximab, block molecules cancer cells need to grow, flag cancer cells for destruction by the body’s immune system, or deliver harmful substances to cancer cells. </Caption></EmbeddedVideo></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_285" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000393541" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Proteasome inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> therapy blocks the action of proteasomes in cancer cells. Proteasomes remove proteins no longer needed by the cell. When the proteasomes are blocked, the proteins build up in the cell and may cause the cancer cell to die.<Para id="_289">    <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bortezomib</GlossaryTermRef> is a proteasome inhibitor used to treat refractory or recurrent childhood Hodgkin lymphoma.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2710">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_274"><KeyPoint id="_275">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_276">Immunotherapy uses the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to fight cancer.  Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the body's natural defenses against cancer.  Types of immunotherapy include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2706" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000772606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immune checkpoint inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> therapy: Some types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797381" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune cells</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">T cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and some cancer cells have certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef>, called checkpoint proteins, on their surface that keep <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune responses</GlossaryTermRef> in check. When cancer cells have large amounts of these proteins, they will not be attacked and killed by T cells. Immune checkpoint inhibitors block these proteins, and the ability of T cells to kill cancer cells is increased. The following is a type of immune checkpoint inhibitor therapy:<ItemizedList id="_286" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000777027" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PD-1</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797389" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PD-L1</GlossaryTermRef> inhibitor therapy: PD-1 is a protein on the surface of T cells that helps keep the body's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune responses</GlossaryTermRef> in check. PD-L1 is a protein found on some types of cancer cells. When PD-1 attaches to PD-L1, it stops the T cell from killing the cancer cell. PD-1 and PD-L1 inhibitors keep PD-1 and PD-L1 proteins from attaching to each other.  This allows the T cells to kill cancer cells.<Para id="_288"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000764538" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pembrolizumab</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000767747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nivolumab</GlossaryTermRef> are types of PD-1 inhibitors that may be used in the treatment of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma that has come back after treatment. </Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000774646" type="image/jpeg" alt="Immune checkpoint inhibitor; the panel on the left shows the binding of proteins PD-L1 (on the tumor cell) to PD-1 (on the T cell), which keeps T cells from killing tumor cells in the body. Also shown are a tumor cell antigen and T cell receptor. The panel on the right shows immune checkpoint inhibitors (anti-PD-L1 and anti-PD-1) blocking the binding of PD-L1 to PD-1, which allows the T cells to kill tumor cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_290"><Caption language="en">Immune checkpoint inhibitor. Checkpoint proteins, such as PD-L1 on tumor cells and PD-1 on T cells, help keep immune responses in check. The binding of PD-L1 to PD-1 keeps T cells from killing tumor cells in the body (left panel). Blocking the binding of PD-L1 to PD-1 with an immune checkpoint inhibitor (anti-PD-L1 or anti-PD-1) allows the T cells to kill tumor cells (right panel).</Caption></MediaLink><EmbeddedVideo id="_291" ref="CDR0000795515" hosting="youtube" unique_id="GIUu239FWMg" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>immune checkpoint inhibitors</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Immunotherapy uses the body’s immune system to fight cancer. This animation explains one type of immunotherapy that uses immune checkpoint inhibitors to treat cancer.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_227"><KeyPoint id="_228">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_229">Surgery may be done to remove as much of the tumor as possible for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">localized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000574286" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nodular lymphocyte-predominant Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> in children.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_169"><KeyPoint id="_170">High-dose chemotherapy with stem cell
			 transplant </KeyPoint><Para id="_281">High doses of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells. Healthy cells, including blood-forming cells, are also destroyed by the cancer treatment. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment to replace the blood-forming cells. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> of the patient or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef> and are frozen and stored. After the patient completes chemotherapy, the stored stem cells are thawed and given to the patient through an infusion. These reinfused stem cells grow into (and restore) the body's blood cells.</Para><Para id="_247">For more information, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/hodgkin-lymphoma">Drugs Approved for Hodgkin Lymphoma</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_74"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_75">Clinical trials</KeyPoint><Para id="_182">A treatment <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> is a research study meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. Because cancer in children is rare, taking part in a clinical trial should be considered.</Para><Para id="_2711">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_2712">Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_230"><KeyPoint id="_231">Proton beam radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_232">

<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Proton beam therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of high-energy, external radiation therapy that uses streams of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044715" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protons</GlossaryTermRef> (small, positively-charged particles of matter) to make radiation. This type of radiation therapy may help lessen the damage to healthy tissue near the tumor, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef>, heart, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_238"><KeyPoint id="_239">Treatment for childhood Hodgkin lymphoma causes side effects and late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_238_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_240">Side effects from cancer treatment that begin after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Because late effects affect health and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000637716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">development</GlossaryTermRef>, regular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> exams are important.</Para><Para id="_241">Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_242" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems that affect:<ItemizedList id="_243" Style="dash"><ListItem>development of sex and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046564" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reproductive organs</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility</GlossaryTermRef> (ability to have children)</ListItem><ListItem>bone and muscle growth and development</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046036" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef>, heart, or lung function</ListItem><ListItem>teeth, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000481753" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gums</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">salivary gland</GlossaryTermRef> function</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef> function (increased risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem></ItemizedList>
</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">second cancers</GlossaryTermRef> (new types of cancer), such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445087" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_244">

For female <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> of Hodgkin lymphoma, there is an increased risk of breast cancer. This risk depends on the amount of radiation the breast received during treatment and the chemotherapy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimen</GlossaryTermRef> used. The risk of breast cancer is decreased if radiation to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef> was also given.</Para><Para id="_255">Doctors may recommend that female survivors who received radiation therapy to the breast have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mammogram</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> once a year starting 8 years after treatment or at age 25 years, whichever is later. They may also suggest that female survivors do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast self-exam</GlossaryTermRef> every month beginning at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">puberty</GlossaryTermRef> and have a breast exam done by a health professional every year beginning at puberty until age 25 years. The breast exams done by a health professional will increase to every 6 months at age 25 years.</Para><Para id="_2705">For male survivors who received radiation therapy to the chest, there may be a higher risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748137" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cardiovascular disease</GlossaryTermRef>.  Limiting radiation therapy to the chest is suggested if possible.</Para><Para id="_2724"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572255" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Dexrazoxane</GlossaryTermRef> is a drug that can reduce the risk of long-term heart damage in Hodgkin lymphoma survivors. The drug is usually taken alongside chemotherapy and other treatments.</Para><Para id="_245">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_188"><KeyPoint id="_189">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_188_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_188_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_188_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_190"><KeyPoint id="_191">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_190_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_190_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_192"><KeyPoint id="_193">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_192_md_55">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_192_md_56">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_197">For patients who receive chemotherapy alone, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> may be done 3 weeks or more after treatment ends. For  patients who receive radiation therapy last, a PET scan should not be done  until 8 to 12 weeks after treatment ends.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_83"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040229">stage I childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040227">stage II childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Low-Risk Classic Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_270">For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_65" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_84">Treatment of newly diagnosed low-risk <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000574284" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">classic Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_257" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also be given to the areas with cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_83_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_89"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040229">stage I childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040227">stage II childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040230">stage III childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040231">stage IV childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Intermediate-Risk Classic Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_2700">For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_65" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_144">Treatment of newly diagnosed intermediate-risk  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000574284" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">classic Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_258" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also be given to the areas with cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_89_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_102"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040230">stage III childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040231">stage IV childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of High-Risk Classic Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_2701">For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_65" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_104">Treatment of newly diagnosed high-risk <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000574284" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">classic Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_250" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Higher-dose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Combination chemotherapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000710543" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brentuximab</GlossaryTermRef>) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000767747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nivolumab</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also be given to the areas with cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_102_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_234"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000566058">childhood nodular lymphocyte predominant Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Nodular Lymphocyte-Predominant Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_2702">For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_65" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_235">Treatment of newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000574286" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nodular lymphocyte-predominant Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_236" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery, if the tumor can be completely removed.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without low-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">external radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_234_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_115"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040232">recurrent/refractory childhood Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Primary Refractory or Recurrent Hodgkin Lymphoma in Children and Adolescents</Title><Para id="_271">For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257999#_65" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_116">In children and adolescents, treatment of primary refractory Hodgkin lymphoma (cancer that does not respond to initial treatment) or recurrent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> (cancer that came back after treatment) may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_117" Style="bullet"> 
		 
		 
		 
		<ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000613764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">steroids</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rituximab</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000710543" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brentuximab</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bortezomib</GlossaryTermRef>), or both of these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000764538" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pembrolizumab</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000767747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nivolumab</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">High-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> using the patient's own <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cells</GlossaryTermRef>.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046066" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Monoclonal antibody</GlossaryTermRef> therapy (brentuximab) may also be given. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may be given after stem cell transplant using the patient's own stem cells or if the cancer has not responded to other treatments and the area with cancer has not been treated before.</ListItem><ListItem>High-dose chemotherapy with stem cell transplant using a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor's</GlossaryTermRef> stem cells.</ListItem><ListItem>Targeted therapy (brentuximab) as maintenance and consolidation therapy for patients who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapsed</GlossaryTermRef> after a stem cell transplant that used the patient's own stem cells.</ListItem> 
		 
	 </ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_115_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2718"><Title>Coping With Your Child's Cancer</Title><Para id="_2720">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_175"><Title>To Learn More About Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_176">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_218" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/hodgkin-lymphoma">Drugs Approved for Hodgkin Lymphoma</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/stem-cell-transplant">Stem Cell Transplants in Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_175_md_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_175_md_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood Hodgkin lymphoma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/patient/child-hodgkin-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389224]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062933"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-08</DateLastModified></Summary>
