<Summary id="CDR0000258010" LegacyPDQID="3127" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062848"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Endometrial cancer screening is currently not recommended because no standard or routine screening test has been shown to be effective. Endometrial cancer is usually found early due to symptoms and survival rates are high. Learn more in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/patient/endometrial-screening-pdq">Endometrial Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-screening-pdq">Endometrial Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038737">endometrial cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_112">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about endometrial cancer screening. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_113">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>endometrial cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Endometrial Cancer Screening (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Endometrial Cancer Screening</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Endometrial Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>What Is Screening?</Title><Para id="_2"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Screening</GlossaryTermRef> is  looking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> before a person has any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. This can help find
		cancer at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef>                                            <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> or cancer is found early, it may
		be easier to treat. By the time symptoms  appear, cancer may have begun
		to  spread.</Para><Para id="_3"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef>  are trying to better understand which
		people are more likely to get certain types of cancer. They also study the things
		we do and the things around us to see if they cause  cancer. This
		information helps doctors recommend who should be screened for cancer, which
		screening tests should be used, and how often the tests should be done.</Para><Para id="_4">It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily
		think you have cancer if he or she suggests a  screening test. Screening
		tests are given when you  have no cancer symptoms.</Para><Para id="_92">If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045959" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>General Information About Endometrial Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_6"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_7">Endometrial cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer)
		  cells form in the tissues of the endometrium.</KeyPoint><Para id="_8">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endometrium</GlossaryTermRef> is the
		  innermost lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>. The uterus is
		  a hollow, muscular organ in a
		  woman's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>. The uterus is where a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046400" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fetus</GlossaryTermRef> grows.  In most nonpregnant
		  women, the uterus is about 3 inches long.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000609921" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the female reproductive system; drawing shows the uterus, myometrium (muscular outer layer of the uterus), endometrium (inner lining of the uterus), ovaries, fallopian tubes, cervix, and vagina." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_109"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the female reproductive system. The organs in the female reproductive system include the uterus, ovaries, fallopian tubes, cervix, and vagina. The uterus has a muscular outer layer called the myometrium and an inner lining called the endometrium. </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_9"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> of the endometrium
		  is different from cancer of the muscle of the uterus, which is called
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterine sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>.    For more information, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257805" url="/types/uterine/patient/uterine-sarcoma-treatment-pdq">Uterine Sarcoma
		  Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_106">Other PDQ summaries containing information related to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endometrial  cancer</GlossaryTermRef> include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_107" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062964" url="/types/uterine/patient/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Endometrial Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258009" url="/types/uterine/patient/endometrial-prevention-pdq">Endometrial Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_11">Endometrial cancer is most common in postmenopausal women.</KeyPoint><Para id="_111">Endometrial cancer  occurs most often in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmenopausal</GlossaryTermRef> women, with 60 being the average age at diagnosis.</Para><Para id="_143">From 2012 to 2021, the number of new cases of endometrial cancer increased slightly in White women and by  2% to 3%  each year in women of all other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">racial</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ethnic groups</GlossaryTermRef>. From 2013 to 2022, the number of deaths from endometrial cancer increased by  just under 2% each year.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_15"> Different factors increase or decrease the risk of getting endometrial cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_16">Anything that increases your chance of getting a disease
		  is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Anything that decreases your chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factor</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_144">Learn more about risk factors and protective factors for endometrial cancer in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258009" url="/types/uterine/patient/endometrial-prevention-pdq">Endometrial Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><Title>Endometrial Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_52"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Screening methods</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_53"> Tests are used to screen for different types of cancer when a person does not have symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_55"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests to find those with the fewest harms and most benefits. Cancer screening trials also are meant to show whether early detection (finding cancer before it causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>)  helps a person live longer or decreases a person's chance of dying from the disease. For some types of cancer, the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef> is better if the disease is found and treated at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_100"><KeyPoint id="_101">Endometrial cancer is usually found early.</KeyPoint><Para id="_102"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endometrial cancer</GlossaryTermRef>  usually causes symptoms (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044308" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaginal</GlossaryTermRef> bleeding) and is found at an early stage, when there is a good chance of recovery. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_69"><KeyPoint id="_70">There is no standard or routine screening test for endometrial cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_71">Screening for endometrial cancer is under study and there are screening clinical trials taking place in many parts of the country.
			 Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><KeyPoint id="_19"> Tests that may  detect (find) endometrial cancer are being studied:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_20"><KeyPoint id="_21">Pap test</KeyPoint><Para id="_48">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045978" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pap test</GlossaryTermRef> is a procedure to collect cells from the surface of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>.  A piece of cotton, a brush, or a small wooden stick is used to gently scrape cells from the cervix and vagina.  The cells are viewed under a microscope to find out if they are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef>.  This procedure is also called a Pap smear.</Para><Para id="_22"> Pap tests are not used to screen for endometrial cancer; however,  Pap test results sometimes show signs of an abnormal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endometrium</GlossaryTermRef> (lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>). <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> tests may
			 detect  endometrial cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><KeyPoint id="_27">Transvaginal ultrasound</KeyPoint><Para id="_103">No studies have shown  that screening by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046633" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transvaginal ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> (TVU) lowers the number of deaths caused by   endometrial cancer.</Para><Para id="_49">Transvaginal ultrasound (TVU) is a procedure used to examine the vagina, uterus, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef>. It is also called endovaginal ultrasound. An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367430" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound transducer</GlossaryTermRef> (probe)  is inserted into the vagina and used to bounce high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>. The
			 doctor can identify tumors by looking at the sonogram.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000618018" type="image/jpeg" alt="Transvaginal ultrasound; drawing shows a side view of the female reproductive anatomy during a transvaginal ultrasound procedure. An ultrasound probe (a device that makes sound waves that bounce off tissues inside the body) is shown inserted into the vagina. The bladder, uterus, right fallopian tube, and right ovary are also shown. The inset shows the diagnostic sonographer (a person trained to perform ultrasound procedures) examining a woman on a table, and a computer screen shows an image of the patient’s internal tissues." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_110"><Caption language="en">Transvaginal ultrasound. An ultrasound probe connected to a computer is inserted into the vagina and is gently moved to show different organs. The probe bounces sound waves off internal organs and tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture).</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_105">TVU is commonly
			 used to examine women who have abnormal vaginal bleeding. For women who have or are at risk for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044884" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hereditary nonpolyposis colon cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, experts suggest yearly screening with transvaginal ultrasound, beginning as early as age 25.</Para><Para id="_108">The use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000509341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tamoxifen</GlossaryTermRef> to treat or prevent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> increases the  risk of  endometrial cancer. TVU is not useful in screening for endometrial cancer in  women who take tamoxifen but do not have any symptoms of endometrial cancer. In women taking tamoxifen, TVU should     be used in those who have vaginal bleeding.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_94"><KeyPoint id="_95">Endometrial sampling</KeyPoint><Para id="_104">It has not been proven that screening by endometrial sampling (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>) lowers the number of deaths caused by endometrial cancer.</Para><Para id="_96">Endometrial sampling is the removal of tissue from the endometrium 
			 by inserting a brush, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046460" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curette</GlossaryTermRef>, or thin, flexible tube through the cervix and into the uterus.  The tool is used to gently scrape a small amount of tissue from the endometrium and then remove the tissue samples.  A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells.</Para></SummarySection><Para id="_74">Endometrial sampling is commonly
			 used to examine women who have abnormal vaginal bleeding. If you have abnormal vaginal bleeding, check with your doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_114"><KeyPoint id="_115">Screening tests for endometrial cancer are being studied in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_114_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_34"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risks of screening</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Risks of Endometrial Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_35"><KeyPoint id="_36">Screening tests have risks.</KeyPoint><Para id="_37">Decisions about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests can be difficult. Not all screening tests are helpful and most have risks. Before having any screening test, you may
		  want to discuss  the test with your doctor.  It is important to know the risks of
		  the test and whether it has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from
		  cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><KeyPoint id="_39">The risks of endometrial cancer screening tests include:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_65"><KeyPoint id="_66">Finding endometrial cancer may not improve health or help a woman live
			 longer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_67"> Screening
			 may not improve your health or help  you live longer if  you have   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endometrial cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or if it has already spread to
			 other places in  your body.</Para><Para id="_91"> Some cancers  never  cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>
			 or become life-threatening, but if    found by a screening
			 test,  the cancer may be treated. It is  not known if treatment of these cancers  would help you live longer than if no treatment  were given, and treatments for cancer may have serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><KeyPoint id="_44">False-negative test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_45">Screening test results may appear to be normal even though endometrial cancer is
			 present. A woman who receives a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-negative test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that
			 shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical care  even if she has symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_40"><KeyPoint id="_41">False-positive test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_57">Screening test results may appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> even though no
			 cancer is present. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-positive test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and is usually followed by more  tests  (such as
			  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>), which also have risks. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_78"><KeyPoint id="_79">Side  effects  may be caused by  the test itself.</KeyPoint><Para id="_90">Side effects that may be caused by screening tests for endometrial cancer include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_85" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Discomfort.</ListItem><ListItem>Bleeding.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Infection</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Puncture of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef> (rare).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_87"><Para id="_89">If you have any questions about your risk for endometrial cancer or the need for screening tests, check with your doctor.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about endometrial cancer screening.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Endometrial Cancer Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/patient/endometrial-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/patient/endometrial-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389486]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062819"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-06</DateLastModified></Summary>
