<Summary id="CDR0000258019" LegacyPDQID="3436" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062874"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Lung cancer screening with low-dose   scans has been shown to decrease the risk of dying from lung cancer in heavy smokers. Learn more about tests to detect lung cancer and their potential benefits and harms in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/lung-screening-pdq">Lung Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/hp/lung-screening-pdq">Lung Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040209">lung cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_99">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about lung cancer screening. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_100">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>lung cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Lung Cancer Screening (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Lung Cancer Screening</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Lung Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>What Is Screening?</Title><Para id="_2">Screening is  looking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> before a person has any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. This can help find
		cancer at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> tissue or cancer is found early, it may
		be easier to treat. By the time symptoms  appear, cancer may have begun
		to  spread.</Para><Para id="_3">Scientists  are trying to better understand which
		people are more likely to get certain types of cancer. They also study the things
		we do and the things around us to see if they cause  cancer. This
		information helps doctors recommend who should be screened for cancer, which
		screening tests should be used, and how often the tests should be done. </Para><Para id="_4">It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily
		think you have cancer if he or she suggests a  screening test. Screening
		tests are given when you  have no cancer symptoms. </Para><Para id="_77">If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045959" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>General Information About Lung Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_6"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_7">Lung cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form
		  in the tissues of the lung.</KeyPoint><Para id="_8">The lungs are a pair of cone-shaped breathing organs in the chest.
		  The lungs bring <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> into the body as you breathe in. They release <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538147" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carbon dioxide</GlossaryTermRef>,  a
		  waste product of the body's cells, as you breathe out.
		  Each lung has sections called lobes. The
		  left lung has two lobes. The right
		  lung is slightly larger, and has three lobes. A thin membrane called the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045842" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pleura</GlossaryTermRef> surrounds the lungs.      Two
		  tubes called bronchi lead from the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> (windpipe) to the right and
		  left lungs. The bronchi are sometimes also involved in lung cancer. Tiny air sacs called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alveoli</GlossaryTermRef> and small tubes called
		  bronchioles make up the inside of
		  the lungs.  <MediaLink ref="CDR0000466533" type="image/jpeg" alt="Respiratory system anatomy; drawing shows the right lung with the upper, middle, and lower lobes, the left lung with the upper and lower lobes, and the trachea, bronchi, lymph nodes, and diaphragm. An inset shows the bronchioles, alveoli, artery, and vein." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_82"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the respiratory system showing the trachea, the right and left lungs and their lobes, and the bronchi. The lymph nodes and the diaphragm are also shown. Oxygen is inhaled into the lungs and passes through the alveoli (the tiny air sacs at the end of the bronchioles) and into the bloodstream (see inset), where it travels to the tissues throughout the body.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_9">There are two main types of lung cancer: <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045327" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small
		  cell lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-small cell
		  lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. <Strong/></Para><Para id="_80">Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summaries  containing information related to  lung cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_81" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062825" url="/types/lung/patient/lung-prevention-pdq"> Lung Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062956" url="/types/lung/patient/non-small-cell-lung-treatment-pdq">Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062947" url="/types/lung/patient/small-cell-lung-treatment-pdq">Small Cell Lung Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><KeyPoint id="_11">Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer death in the United States.</KeyPoint><Para id="_12">Lung cancer is the second most common type of non-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skin cancer</GlossaryTermRef> in the United States. Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer death in men and in women.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_94"><KeyPoint id="_95">Different factors increase or decrease the risk of lung cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_96">Anything that increases your chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Anything that decreases your chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factor</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_108"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439432" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tobacco</GlossaryTermRef> smoking is the most important risk factor for lung cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cigarette</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748146" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cigar</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748824" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pipe</GlossaryTermRef> smoking all increase the risk of lung cancer. Tobacco smoking causes about 9 out of 10 cases of lung cancer in men and about 8 out of 10 cases of lung cancer in women. The best way to prevent lung cancer is to not smoke.  </Para><Para id="_97">For information about risk factors and protective factors for lung cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062825" url="/types/lung/patient/lung-prevention-pdq">Lung Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><Title>Lung Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Screening methods</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_15">Tests are used to screen for different types of cancer when a person does not have symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_66">Scientists study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests to find those with the fewest harms and most benefits. Cancer screening trials also are meant to show whether early detection (finding cancer before it causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>)  helps a person live longer or decreases a person's chance of dying from the disease. For some types of cancer, the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef> is better if the disease is found and treated at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><KeyPoint id="_19"> Three screening tests have been studied to see if they decrease the risk of dying from lung cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_74">The following screening tests have been studied to see if they decrease the risk of dying from lung cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_89" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803200" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Low-dose computed tomography</GlossaryTermRef> (LDCT): A  procedure that uses low-dose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to make a series of very detailed pictures of areas inside the body using an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scans</GlossaryTermRef> the body in a spiral path. This procedure is also called spiral   scan or helical  scan.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef>: An x-ray of the organs and bones inside the chest.  An x-ray is a type of energy beam that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the body.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Sputum cytology</GlossaryTermRef>: Sputum cytology    is a procedure in which a sample of   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045883" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sputum</GlossaryTermRef>   (mucus  that is coughed up from the lungs) is viewed under a microscope to check for cancer cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><KeyPoint id="_28">Screening with LDCT  scans  has been shown to decrease the risk of dying from lung cancer in heavy smokers. </KeyPoint><Para id="_83">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000753856" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Lung Screening Trial</GlossaryTermRef>  studied people aged 55 years to 74 years who had smoked at least 1 pack of cigarettes per day for  30 years or more. Participants were either current smokers or former smokers who had quit within the last 15 years. The trial used chest x-rays or LDCT scans to check for signs of lung cancer.</Para><Para id="_88">Screening with LDCT once a year for three years was better than chest x-rays at finding <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561398" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">early-stage</GlossaryTermRef> lung cancer and decreased the risk of dying from lung cancer in current and former heavy smokers.</Para><Para id="_101">Current smokers whose LDCT scan result shows possible signs of cancer may be more likely to quit smoking. </Para><Para id="_105">Screening with LDCT can cause possible harms, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_106" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-positive test results</GlossaryTermRef>, which may lead to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257210" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">invasive procedures</GlossaryTermRef>  which are not needed</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000759894" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overdiagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> of some lung cancers, though it is not clear how often this  happens</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_107">For more information about these possible harms, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258019#_38" url="/types/lung/patient/lung-screening-pdq">Risks of Lung Cancer Screening</SummaryRef>  below.</Para><Para id="_93"> A <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/research/NLSTstudyGuidePatientsPhysicians.pdf">Guide</ExternalRef> is available for patients and doctors to learn more about the benefits and harms of    screening for lung cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_91"><KeyPoint id="_33">Screening with chest x-rays and/or sputum cytology does not decrease the risk of dying from lung cancer. </KeyPoint><Para id="_92">Chest x-ray and sputum cytology are two screening tests that have been used to check for signs of lung cancer. Screening with chest x-ray, sputum cytology, or both of these tests does not decrease the risk of dying from lung cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_103"><KeyPoint id="_104">Screening tests for lung cancer are being studied in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_103_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risks of screening</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Risks of Lung Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_39"><KeyPoint id="_40">Screening tests have risks.</KeyPoint><Para id="_41">Decisions about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests can be difficult. Not all screening tests are helpful and most have risks. Before having any screening test, you may
		  want to discuss  the test with your doctor.  It is important to know the risks of
		  the test and whether it has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from
		  cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><KeyPoint id="_43">The risks of lung cancer screening tests include the following:
		  </KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_50"><KeyPoint id="_51">Finding lung cancer may not improve health or help  you live
			 longer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_68">Screening
			 may not improve your health or help  you live longer if  you have       <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> that    has already spread to
			 other places in  your body. </Para><Para id="_73">When a screening test result leads to the diagnosis and treatment of a disease that may never have caused <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> or become life-threatening, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000759894" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overdiagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>. It is  not known if treatment of these cancers  would help you live longer than if no treatment  were given, and treatments for cancer may have serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>. Harms  of treatment may happen more often in people who have medical problems caused by heavy or long-term smoking.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_47"><KeyPoint id="_48">False-negative test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_49">Screening test results may appear to be normal even though lung cancer is
			 present. A person who receives a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-negative test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that
			 shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical care  even if there are symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_44"><KeyPoint id="_45">False-positive test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_69">Screening test results may appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> even though no
			 cancer is present. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-positive test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and is usually followed by more  tests  (such as
			  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>), which also have risks. A biopsy to diagnose lung cancer can cause part of the lung to collapse.  Sometimes  surgery is needed to reinflate the lung. Harms of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689569" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef> may happen more often in patients who have medical problems caused by heavy or long-term smoking. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><KeyPoint id="_54">Chest x-rays and  CT scans expose the chest to radiation.</KeyPoint><Para id="_55"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation</GlossaryTermRef> exposure
			 from  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chest x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> and low-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef>        <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scans</GlossaryTermRef> may increase the
			 risk of cancer. Younger people and people at low risk for lung cancer are more likely to develop lung cancer caused by radiation exposure from screening than to be spared death from lung cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_56"><KeyPoint id="_75"> Talk to your doctor     about your risk for lung cancer and your need for screening tests.</KeyPoint><Para id="_102">Talk to your doctor or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care provider</GlossaryTermRef> about your risk for lung cancer, whether a screening test is right for you, and about the benefits and harms of the screening test. You should take part in the decision about whether a screening test is right for you. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453888#_183" url="/about-cancer/screening/patient-screening-overview-pdq">Cancer Screening Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about lung cancer screening.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Lung Cancer Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/lung-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/lung-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389428]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062832"/><DateLastModified>2024-05-24</DateLastModified></Summary>
