<Summary id="CDR0000258033" LegacyPDQID="1067" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062683"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Retinoblastoma treatment may include cryosurgery, laser therapy (thermotherapy), chemotherapy, radiation therapy, high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue, and sometimes surgery. Learn more about newly diagnosed and recurrent retinoblastoma in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/retinoblastoma/patient/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq">Retinoblastoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/retinoblastoma/hp/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq">Retinoblastoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043733">retinoblastoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_288">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of retinoblastoma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_289">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>retinoblastoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Retinoblastoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Retinoblastoma Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Retinoblastoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Retinoblastoma</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Retinoblastoma is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form in
		  the tissues of the retina.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retina</GlossaryTermRef> is made of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> that lines the inside wall of the  back of the eye.  It receives light and converts the light into signals that travel down the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">optic nerve</GlossaryTermRef> to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef>. The brain decodes the signals so that you can <Emphasis>see</Emphasis> the image. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000543553" type="image/jpeg" alt="Eye anatomy; two-panel drawing showing the outside and inside of the eye. The top panel shows the outside of the eye, including the eyelid, pupil, sclera, and iris. The bottom panel shows the inside of the eye, including the cornea, lens, ciliary body, retina, choroid, optic nerve, and vitreous humor." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_141"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the eye, showing the outside and inside of the eye including the sclera, cornea, iris, ciliary body, choroid, retina, vitreous humor, and optic nerve. The vitreous humor is a gel that fills the center of the eye.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_5"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> may be in one eye  (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">unilateral</GlossaryTermRef>) or in both eyes (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046507" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilateral</GlossaryTermRef>). Cavitary retinoblastoma is a rare type of retinoblastoma in which <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavities</GlossaryTermRef> (hollow spaces) form within the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>.  </Para><Para id="_324">  Although <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> may occur at any age, it occurs most often in children younger than 2 years. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_245"><KeyPoint id="_246">Children with a family history of retinoblastoma should have eye exams to check for retinoblastoma. </KeyPoint><Para id="_300">A child with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of retinoblastoma should have regular eye exams beginning early in life to check for retinoblastoma, unless it is known that the child does not have the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> change. Early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> of retinoblastoma may mean the child will need less intense treatment. </Para><Para id="_325">Talk with your child’s doctor about the type of eye exam, how often eye exams are done, and at what age eye exams to check for retinoblastoma can stop.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Genetic aspects</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_7">Retinoblastoma occurs in heritable and nonheritable forms.
		  </KeyPoint><Para id="_241">A child is thought to have the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766802" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heritable</GlossaryTermRef> (inherited) form of retinoblastoma when there is a certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutation</GlossaryTermRef> (change) in the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> gene. The mutation in the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> gene may be passed from the parent to the child, or it may occur in the egg or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257221" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sperm</GlossaryTermRef> before <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conception</GlossaryTermRef> or soon after conception.</Para><Para id="_326">Other factors that suggest the child may have the heritable form of retinoblastoma include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_242" Style="bullet"><ListItem>There is a family history of retinoblastoma.</ListItem><ListItem>There is more than one tumor in the eye.</ListItem><ListItem>There is a tumor in both eyes.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_283">After heritable retinoblastoma has been diagnosed and treated, new tumors may continue to form for a few years. Regular eye exams to check for new tumors are usually done every 2 to 4 months for at least 28 months.</Para><Para id="_243">Most cases of retinoblastoma are the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766804" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nonheritable</GlossaryTermRef> form. Nonheritable retinoblastoma is not passed down from parents. This type of retinoblastoma is caused by mutations in the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> gene that occur by chance after a child is born. Nonheritable retinoblastoma usually occurs in one eye.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Genetic aspects</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_129">A child who has heritable retinoblastoma has an increased risk of trilateral retinoblastoma and other cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_130">A child with heritable retinoblastoma has an increased risk of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046675" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineal tumor</GlossaryTermRef> in the brain. When retinoblastoma and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumor</GlossaryTermRef> occur at the same time, it is called trilateral retinoblastoma. The brain tumor is usually diagnosed between 20 and 36 months of age. Regular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging) may be done for a child  thought to have heritable retinoblastoma or for a child with retinoblastoma in one eye and a family history of the disease. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT</GlossaryTermRef> (computerized tomography)   scans are usually not used for routine screening in order to avoid exposing the child  to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ionizing radiation</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_275">Heritable retinoblastoma also increases the child's risk of other types of cancer such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef> in later years. Regular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> exams are  important. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_249"><KeyPoint id="_250"> Genetic testing can determine whether a child has the heritable or nonheritable form of retinoblastoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_330">It is not always clear from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> whether a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> is inherited. Certain families may benefit from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic counselors</GlossaryTermRef> and other specially trained health professionals can help parents understand the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_331" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Their family medical history.</ListItem><ListItem>Their options for <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene testing</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The risk of retinoblastoma for the child and the child's brothers or sisters.</ListItem><ListItem>The risks and benefits of learning genetic information.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_332">Genetic counselors can also help people cope with their genetic testing results, including how to discuss the results with family members.</Para><Para id="_320">Once it is known  that the child has heritable retinoblastoma, other family members can be screened for the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> mutation. For one specific mutation, the risk of retinoblastoma in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000616710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sibling</GlossaryTermRef> may depend partly on whether the mutation is inherited from the mother or from the father.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_14">Signs and symptoms of retinoblastoma  include "white pupil" and eyes that appear to be looking in different directions (crossed eyes).</KeyPoint><Para id="_16">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by retinoblastoma or by other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>. Check with a doctor if your child has any of the  following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_17" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000546600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pupil</GlossaryTermRef> of the eye that appears white instead of red when  light shines into it. This may be seen in flash photographs of the child.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000800189" type="image/jpeg" alt="Close-up photograph showing the eyes of a child with retinoblastoma. The pupil of the eye on the left side of the photo appears white compared to the pupil of the eye on the right side of the photo." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_335"><Caption language="en">Close-up photograph showing the eyes of a child with retinoblastoma. The pupil of the eye on the left side of the photo appears white compared to the pupil of the eye on the right side of the photo. A "white pupil" may be a sign of retinoblastoma.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem>Eyes  that appear to be looking in different directions (crossed eyes).</ListItem><ListItem>Pain or redness in the eye.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Infection</GlossaryTermRef> around the eye. </ListItem><ListItem>Eyeball that is larger than normal. </ListItem><ListItem>Colored part of the eye and pupil look cloudy. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_19">Tests that examine the retina are used to diagnose retinoblastoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_20">The following tests and procedures may be used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health history</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An exam of the body to check general signs of health, including checking for signs of disease, such as lumps or anything else that seems unusual. A history of the patient’s health habits and past illnesses and treatments will also be taken. The doctor will ask if there is a family history of retinoblastoma.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Eye exam with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257207" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dilated</GlossaryTermRef> pupil</Strong>: An exam of the eye in which the pupil is dilated (opened wider)   with medicated eye drops to allow the doctor to look through the  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> and pupil to the retina. The inside of the eye, including the retina and the optic nerve, is examined with a  light. In young children, this exam may be done under <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anesthesia</GlossaryTermRef>.<Para id="_235">There are several types of eye exams that are done with the pupil dilated:</Para><ItemizedList id="_236" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000749897" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ophthalmoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An exam of the inside of the back of the eye to check the retina and optic nerve using a small magnifying lens and a light.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Fluorescein <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046531" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">angiography</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure to look at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> and the flow of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> inside the eye.   An orange fluorescent  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> called fluorescein is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a blood vessel in the arm and goes into the bloodstream. As the dye travels through blood vessels of the eye, a special camera takes pictures of the retina and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000534223" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">choroid</GlossaryTermRef> to find any blood vessels that are blocked or leaking.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Electroretinography</Strong>: An eye test that uses light and small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electrodes</GlossaryTermRef> to study the retina (the light-detecting part of the eye). This test measures and records  the faint electrical signals given off  by the cells in  the retina when exposed to different types and amounts of light. It can be used to assess the function of the retina during and after treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>RB1</GeneName> gene test</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> in which a sample of blood or tissue is tested for a change in the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> gene.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> exam of the eye</Strong>: A procedure in which high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) are bounced off the internal tissues of the eye to make echoes.   Eye drops are used to numb the eye and a small probe that sends and receives sound waves is  placed gently on the surface of the eye. The echoes make a picture of the inside of the eye and the distance from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044199" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cornea</GlossaryTermRef> to the retina is measured. The picture, called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>, shows  on the screen of the ultrasound <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454803" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monitor</GlossaryTermRef>. The picture can be printed to be looked at later.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>MRI (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the eye. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_22">Retinoblastoma can usually be diagnosed without a  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_274">When retinoblastoma is in one eye, it sometimes forms in the other eye. Exams of the unaffected eye are done until it is known that the retinoblastoma is the nonheritable form.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_105"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_106">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_107">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_108" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>Whether the cancer is in one or both eyes.</ListItem><ListItem>The size and number of  tumors.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the tumor has spread to the area around the eye, to the brain, or to other parts of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>The age of the child.</ListItem><ListItem>How likely it is that vision can be saved in one or both eyes.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether a second type of cancer has formed.</ListItem>
    
    
   <ListItem>Whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><Title>Stages of Retinoblastoma</Title><SummarySection id="_28"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_29">After retinoblastoma has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out
		  if cancer cells have spread within the eye or to other parts of the body.
		  </KeyPoint><Para id="_30">The process used to find out if <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> has spread within the eye or
		  to other parts of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. The information gathered from the staging
		  process determines whether <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> is only in the eye (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350232" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraocular</GlossaryTermRef>) or has spread outside the eye (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537398" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extraocular</GlossaryTermRef>). It is important to know
the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> in order to plan treatment. The results of the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258033#_18" url="/types/retinoblastoma/patient/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq">tests and procedures</SummaryRef> used to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> cancer are often also used to stage the disease.</Para><Para id="_240">The following tests and procedures may be used in the staging process:</Para><ItemizedList id="_31" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef>. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  A procedure to check if there are rapidly dividing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>, such as cancer cells, in the bone.  A very small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> material is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> and travels through the bloodstream.  The radioactive material collects in the bones with cancer and is detected by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> that also takes a picture of the body.

Areas of bone with cancer show up brighter in the picture because they take up more radioactive material than normal bone cells do.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775451" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides under the scanner, a technician operating the scanner, and a computer monitor that will show images made during the scan." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_311"><Caption language="en">Bone scan.  A small amount of radioactive material is injected into the child's vein and travels through the blood. The radioactive material collects in the bones. As the child lies on a table that slides under the scanner, the radioactive material is detected and images are made on a computer screen.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000669655" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> and a small piece of bone by inserting a hollow needle into the hipbone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000549425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breastbone</GlossaryTermRef>. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the bone marrow under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> to look for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer. A bone marrow aspiration and biopsy is done if the doctor thinks the cancer has spread outside of the eye.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775458" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy; drawing shows a child lying face down on a table and a bone marrow needle being inserted into the right hip bone. An inset shows the bone marrow needle being inserted through the skin into the bone marrow of the hip bone." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_336"><Caption language="en">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy. After a small area of skin is numbed, a bone marrow needle  is inserted into the child’s hip bone.  Samples of blood, bone, and bone marrow are removed for examination under a microscope.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046303" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lumbar puncture</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure used to collect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> (CSF) from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000396787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal column</GlossaryTermRef>. This is done by placing a needle between two bones in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef> and into the CSF around the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> and removing a sample of the fluid.  The sample of CSF is checked under a microscope for signs that the cancer has spread to the brain and spinal cord and sometimes it is also checked for a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor marker</GlossaryTermRef> called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044592" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ganglioside</GlossaryTermRef> GD2. This procedure is also called an LP or spinal tap.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_195"><KeyPoint id="_196">The International Retinoblastoma Staging System (IRSS) may be used for staging retinoblastoma. </KeyPoint><Para id="_216">There are several <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging systems</GlossaryTermRef> for retinoblastoma. The IRSS stages are based on how much cancer remains after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> and whether the cancer has spread. </Para><SummarySection id="_197"><KeyPoint id="_198">Stage 0</KeyPoint><Para id="_199"> 	
The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is in the eye only. The eye has not been removed and the tumor was treated without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_200"><KeyPoint id="_201">Stage I</KeyPoint><Para id="_202">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is in the eye only. The eye has been removed and no cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> remain. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_203"><KeyPoint id="_204">Stage II</KeyPoint><Para id="_205"> 	
The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is in the eye only. The eye has been removed and cancer cells remain that can be seen only with a microscope. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_206"><KeyPoint id="_207">Stage III</KeyPoint><Para id="_217"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage</GlossaryTermRef> III is divided into stage IIIa and stage IIIb:</Para><ItemizedList id="_218" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In stage IIIa, cancer has spread from the eye to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> around the eye socket.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIb, cancer has spread from the eye to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> near the ear or in the neck.  
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_210"><KeyPoint id="_211">Stage IV</KeyPoint><Para id="_219"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage</GlossaryTermRef> IV is divided into stage IVa and stage IVb:</Para><ItemizedList id="_220" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In stage IVa, cancer has spread to one or more parts of the body, such as the bone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IVb, cancer has spread to the brain or spinal cord. It also may have spread to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><KeyPoint id="_147">There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_146_md_69">Cancer can spread through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_146_md_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.
</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_192"><KeyPoint id="_193">Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_192_md_66">When cancer spreads to another part of the body, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer cells break away from where they began (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>) and travel through the lymph system or blood.</Para><ItemizedList id="_192_md_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer gets into the lymph system, travels through the lymph vessels, and forms a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer gets into the blood, travels through the blood vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_194">The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if  retinoblastoma spreads to the bone, the cancer cells in the bone are actually retinoblastoma cells. The disease is metastatic retinoblastoma, not bone cancer.</Para><EmbeddedVideo id="_314" ref="CDR0000787719" hosting="youtube" unique_id="fQwar_-QdiQ" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>metastasis: how cancer spreads</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Many cancer deaths are caused when cancer moves from the original tumor and spreads to other tissues and organs. This is called metastatic cancer. This animation shows how cancer cells travel from the place in the body where they first formed to other parts of the body.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_214"><KeyPoint id="_215">Treatment for retinoblastoma depends on whether it is intraocular (within the eye) or extraocular (outside the eye). </KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_35"><KeyPoint id="_36">Intraocular retinoblastoma
</KeyPoint><Para id="_37">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350232" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraocular</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> is found in  one or both eyes and may be in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retina</GlossaryTermRef> only or may also be in other parts of the eye such as   the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000534223" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">choroid</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000534222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ciliary body</GlossaryTermRef>,  or part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">optic nerve</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer has not spread to  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> around the outside of the eye or to other parts of the body. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><KeyPoint id="_39">Extraocular retinoblastoma
(metastatic)</KeyPoint><Para id="_40">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537398" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extraocular</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> has spread beyond the eye. It may be found in  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> around the eye (orbital retinoblastoma), or it may have spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> (brain and spinal cord) or to other parts of the body such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, bone, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_321"><KeyPoint id="_322">Treatment for retinoblastoma also depends on whether the cancer has progressed or recurred.</KeyPoint><Para id="_271"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045850" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Progressive</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> is cancer that continues to grow, spread or get worse. Progressive disease may be a sign that the cancer has become <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment.
</Para><Para id="_42"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> retinoblastoma is cancer that has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back)  after it has been treated. The cancer may recur in the eye,  in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> around the eye, or  in other places in the body, such as the liver, bone, bone marrow, or lymph nodes. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_44"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_45">There are different types of treatment for patients with retinoblastoma. </KeyPoint><Para id="_46">Different types of treatment are available for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>. Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some
		  are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.
		  A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help
		  improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients
		  with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the
		  standard treatment, the new
		  treatment may become the standard treatment. </Para><Para id="_140">Because cancer in children is rare, taking part in a clinical trial should be considered. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_49">Children with retinoblastoma should have their treatment
		  planned by a team of      health care providers who are experts in treating cancer in children.</KeyPoint><Para id="_50">The goals of treatment are to save the child's life, to save vision and the eye, and to prevent serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>. Treatment will be overseen by a
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>, a doctor who specializes
		  in treating children with cancer. The pediatric oncologist  works with
		  other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care providers</GlossaryTermRef> who are experts in treating children
		  with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444991" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">eye cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and who specialize
		  in certain areas of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef>. These may include a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000631048" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ophthalmologist</GlossaryTermRef> (children's eye doctor) who has a lot of experience in treating retinoblastoma and the following
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">specialists</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_51" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		   
		   
		   
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation
			 oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Social worker</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723337" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Geneticist</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic counselor</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_52"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_53">Six types of standard treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_61"><KeyPoint id="_62">Cryotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_63"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cryotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is the use of extreme cold to destroy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>.  A small metal probe is cooled below freezing and placed on the surface of the eye near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>, which freezes and kills cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>. Cryotherapy is usually used to treat small retinoblastoma tumors that are located toward the front of the eye. This type of treatment is also called cryosurgery.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><KeyPoint id="_68">Thermotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_69">     <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thermotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is the use of  heat to destroy cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>.  Thermotherapy may be given using a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045748" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laser</GlossaryTermRef> beam aimed through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257207" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dilated</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000546600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pupil</GlossaryTermRef>  or  onto the outside of the eyeball. Thermotherapy may be used alone for small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef> or combined with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> for larger tumors. This treatment is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045154" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laser therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_72"><KeyPoint id="_73">Chemotherapy </KeyPoint><Para id="_101">Chemotherapy is a cancer treatment that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.     The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer and where the cancer is in the body.</Para><Para id="_224">There are different types of chemotherapy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_225" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>: When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body. Systemic chemotherapy is given to shrink the tumor (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691331" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemoreduction</GlossaryTermRef>) and avoid surgery to remove the eye. After chemoreduction, other treatments may include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, cryotherapy, laser therapy, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. However, extraorbital disease requires <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000796903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intensive chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and may include consolidation with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">autologous stem cell transplantation</GlossaryTermRef> with or without radiation therapy.<Para id="_301">Systemic chemotherapy may also be given to kill any cancer cells that are left after the initial treatment or to kill cancer cells that are outside the eye. Treatment given after the initial treatment, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>Regional chemotherapy: When chemotherapy is placed directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>),  an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> (such as the eye), or a body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef>, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas. Several types of regional chemotherapy are used to treat retinoblastoma.<ItemizedList id="_226" Style="dash"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766465" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ophthalmic artery infusion</GlossaryTermRef> chemotherapy: Ophthalmic artery infusion chemotherapy carries anticancer drugs directly to the eye. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> is put into an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">artery</GlossaryTermRef> that leads to the eye and the anticancer drug is given through the catheter.  After the drug is given, a small balloon may be inserted into the artery to block it and keep most of the anticancer drug trapped near the tumor. This type of chemotherapy may be given as the initial treatment when the tumor is in the eye only or when the tumor has not responded to other types of treatment. Ophthalmic artery infusion chemotherapy is given at special retinoblastoma treatment centers. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766467" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intravitreal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>: Intravitreal chemotherapy is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> of anticancer drugs directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000570638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitreous humor</GlossaryTermRef> (jelly-like substance) inside of the eye. It is used to treat cancer that has spread to the vitreous humor and has not responded to treatment or has come back after treatment. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>: Intrathecal chemotherapy is the injection of anticancer drugs directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> (CSF). It is used to treat cancer that has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_179">See <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/retinoblastoma">Drugs Approved for Retinoblastoma</ExternalRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><KeyPoint id="_58">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_59">Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing.  There are two types of radiation therapy: </Para><ItemizedList id="_293" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External-beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.  <Para id="_327">Certain ways of giving radiation therapy can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy tissue. These types of radiation therapy include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_294" Style="dash">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>      (IMRT):  IMRT is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3-D) external radiation therapy that uses a computer to make pictures of  the size and shape of the tumor. Thin beams of radiation of different intensities (strengths) are aimed at the tumor from many angles.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Proton beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>: Proton beam radiation therapy is a type of high-energy, external radiation therapy that uses streams of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044715" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protons</GlossaryTermRef> (tiny particles with a positive charge) to kill tumor cells.  This type of treatment can lower the amount of radiation damage to healthy tissue near a tumor.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Internal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheters</GlossaryTermRef> that are placed directly into or near the cancer.  Certain ways of giving radiation therapy can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy tissue. This type of internal radiation therapy may include the following:<ItemizedList id="_295" Style="dash">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Plaque radiotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>: Radioactive seeds are attached to one side of a disk, called a plaque, and placed directly on the outside wall of the 
 eye near the tumor.  The 
side of the plaque with the seeds on it faces the eyeball, aiming  radiation at 
 the tumor. The plaque helps  protect other nearby tissue from the radiation.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000736669" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of a cross-section of the eye showing the sclera, choroid, retina, and optic nerve. An inset shows a plaque with radioactive seeds that is placed on the outside of the eye. The seeds are aimed at the cancer." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_191"><Caption language="en">Plaque radiotherapy is a type of radiation therapy used to treat eye cancer. Radioactive seeds are attached to one side of a thin piece of metal (usually gold) called a plaque.  The plaque is sewn onto the outside wall of the eye near the tumor.  The seeds give off radiation which kills the cancer. The plaque is removed at the end of treatment, which usually lasts for several days.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_286">Whether internal or external radiation therapy is given depends on the stage of the cancer being treated, where it is found in the body, and how the cancer responded to other treatments.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_302"><KeyPoint id="_303">High-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue</KeyPoint><Para id="_304">High <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells. Healthy cells, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>-forming cells, are also destroyed by the cancer treatment. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cell rescue</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment to replace the blood-forming cells. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> of the patient and are frozen and stored. After the patient completes chemotherapy, the stored stem cells are thawed and given back to the patient through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These reinfused stem cells grow into (and restore) the body's blood cells. Extraorbital disease requires intensive chemotherapy and may include consolidation with high-dose chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplantation with or without radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_305">See <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/retinoblastoma">Drugs Approved for Retinoblastoma</ExternalRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_306"><KeyPoint id="_307">Surgery (enucleation) </KeyPoint><Para id="_308"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Enucleation</GlossaryTermRef> is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove  the eye  and part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">optic nerve</GlossaryTermRef>. A sample of the eye tissue that is removed will be checked under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> to see if there are any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> that the cancer is likely to spread to other parts of the body. This should be done by an experienced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef>, who is familiar with retinoblastoma and other diseases of the eye. Enucleation is done if there is little or no chance that vision can be saved and when the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is large, did not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment, or comes back after treatment. The patient will be fitted for an artificial eye.</Para><Para id="_309">Close follow-up is needed for 2 years or more  to check for signs of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrence</GlossaryTermRef> in the area around the affected eye and to check the other eye.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_71">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_144">This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in clinical trials. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_315"><KeyPoint id="_316">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_317"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. Targeted therapies usually cause less harm to normal cells than chemotherapy or radiation therapy do.</Para><ItemizedList id="_328" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000615576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Oncolytic virus therapy</GlossaryTermRef>: This treatment uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045941" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">virus</GlossaryTermRef> that infects and breaks down cancer cells but not normal cells. An oncolytic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045992" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenovirus</GlossaryTermRef> targeting the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is injected into the tumor and may have anticancer effects in retinoblastoma. Targeted therapy is being studied for the treatment of retinoblastoma that has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progressed</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_131"><KeyPoint id="_312">Treatment for retinoblastoma may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_131_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_158"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Side effects</GlossaryTermRef> from cancer treatment that begin after treatment and continue for months or years are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef>. Late effects of treatment for retinoblastoma may include the following: 

</Para><ItemizedList id="_318" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Physical problems such as seeing or hearing problems.</ListItem><ListItem>If the eye is removed, there may be changes in the shape and size of the bone around the eye until an artificial eye is fitted. This is most likely to occur in children aged younger than 3 years.</ListItem><ListItem>Changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory. 
</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Second cancers</GlossaryTermRef> (new types of cancer), such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder cancers</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef>. 
 

</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_276">The following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> may increase the risk of having a second cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_277" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Having the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766802" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heritable</GlossaryTermRef> form of retinoblastoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Past treatment with radiation therapy, especially before age 1 year.</ListItem><ListItem>Having already had a previous second cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_160">It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the effects cancer treatment can have on your child. Regular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> by health professionals who are experts in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosing</GlossaryTermRef> and treating late effects is important. See the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summary on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><KeyPoint id="_149">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_148_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_148_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_148_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_150"><KeyPoint id="_151">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_150_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_150_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_152"><KeyPoint id="_153">Follow-up tests may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_152_md_55">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_152_md_56">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_329">In retinoblastoma, new tumors may form for a few years after treatment. Regular eye exams are done to check for tumors in both eyes. Children with the heritable form of retinoblastoma will also have imaging tests to check whether cancer has spread to the brain.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_323"><Title>Treatment of Unilateral, Bilateral, and Cavitary Retinoblastoma</Title><Para id="_313">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258033#_52" url="/types/retinoblastoma/patient/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_229">If it is likely that the eye can be saved, treatment may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_230" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766465" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ophthalmic artery infusion</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766467" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravitreal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, to shrink the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. This may be followed by one or more of the following:<ItemizedList id="_237" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cryotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thermotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Plaque radiotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External-beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046507" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilateral</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350232" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraocular</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> that does not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> to other treatments.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_284">If the tumor is large and it is not likely that the eye can be saved, treatment may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_285" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enucleation</GlossaryTermRef>). After surgery, systemic chemotherapy may be given to lower the risk that the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> will spread to other parts of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_221">When retinoblastoma is in both eyes, the treatment for each eye may be different, depending on the size of the tumor and whether it is likely that the eye can be saved. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> of systemic chemotherapy  is usually based on the eye that has more cancer.</Para><Para id="_337">Patients with cavitary retinoblastoma respond well to treatment and have favorable long-term outcomes, similar to patients with noncavitary retinoblastoma.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_89"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037767">extraocular retinoblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Extraocular Retinoblastoma </Title><Para id="_333">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258033#_52" url="/types/retinoblastoma/patient/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_172">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537398" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extraocular</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> (cancer has spread to the area around the eye) may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_182" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">external-beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Enucleation</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Systemic chemotherapy followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (enucleation). External-beam radiation therapy and more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> may be given after surgery.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_173">Treatment for extraocular retinoblastoma (cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef>) may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_174" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Systemic or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and external-beam radiation therapy to the brain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell rescue</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_234">It is not clear whether treatment with chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue helps patients with extraocular retinoblastoma live longer.</Para><Para id="_175">For trilateral retinoblastoma (retinoblastoma and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumor</GlossaryTermRef> that occur at the same time), treatment may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_183" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Systemic chemotherapy followed by surgery and high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue.</ListItem><ListItem>Systemic chemotherapy followed by surgery and external-beam radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_176">For retinoblastoma that has spread to other parts of the body, but not the brain, treatment may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_177" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Systemic chemotherapy followed by high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue and external-beam radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_89_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_93"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037768">recurrent retinoblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Progressive or Recurrent Retinoblastoma</Title><Para id="_334">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258033#_52" url="/types/retinoblastoma/patient/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_238">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045850" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progressive</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350232" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraocular</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_239" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External-beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plaque radiotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cryotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thermotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350235" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ophthalmic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">artery</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766467" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intravitreal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enucleation</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000615577" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oncolytic virus</GlossaryTermRef>  that targets the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> and is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial that checks a sample of the patient's tumor for certain gene changes. The type of targeted therapy that will be given to the patient depends on the type of gene change.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_272">Treatment of progressive or recurrent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537398" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extraocular</GlossaryTermRef> retinoblastoma may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_273" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Systemic chemotherapy and external-beam radiation therapy for retinoblastoma that comes back after surgery to remove the eye.</ListItem><ListItem>Systemic chemotherapy followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell rescue</GlossaryTermRef> and external-beam radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial that checks a sample of the patient's tumor for certain gene changes. The type of targeted therapy that will be given to the patient depends on the type of gene change.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_93_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_137"><Title>To Learn More About Childhood Cancer</Title><Para id="_164">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about the treatment of retinoblastoma, see the following: 

</Para><ItemizedList id="_178" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/retinoblastoma/patient/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq">Retinoblastoma Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery/cryosurgery">Cryosurgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/retinoblastoma">Drugs Approved for Retinoblastoma</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/genetic-testing-fact-sheet">Genetic Testing for Inherited Cancer Susceptibility Syndromes</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Cancer Therapies</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_137_md_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_137_md_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of retinoblastoma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Retinoblastoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/retinoblastoma/patient/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/retinoblastoma/patient/retinoblastoma-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389197]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062846"/><DateLastModified>2021-10-07</DateLastModified></Summary>
