<Summary id="CDR0000258008" LegacyPDQID="2583" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062798"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>There are five types of tests that are used to screen for colorectal cancer: fecal occult blood test, sigmoidoscopy, colonoscopy, virtual colonoscopy, and DNA stool test. Learn more about these and other tests in this expert-reviewed summary. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/colorectal/patient/colorectal-screening-pdq">Colorectal Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-screening-pdq">Colorectal Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039585">colorectal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_122">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about colorectal cancer screening. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_123">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>colorectal cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Colorectal Cancer Screening (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Colorectal Cancer Screening</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Colorectal Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>What Is Screening?</Title><Para id="_2"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Screening</GlossaryTermRef> is  looking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> before a person has any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. This can help find
		cancer at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> or cancer is found early, it may
		be easier to treat. By the time symptoms  appear, cancer may have begun
		to  spread.</Para><Para id="_3"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef>  are trying to better understand which
		people are more likely to get certain types of cancer. They also study the things
		we do and the things around us to see if they cause  cancer. This
		information helps doctors recommend who should be screened for cancer, which
		screening tests should be used, and how often the tests should be done.</Para><Para id="_4">It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily
		think you have cancer if he or she suggests a screening test. Screening
		tests are given when you have no cancer symptoms. Screening tests may be repeated on a regular basis.</Para><Para id="_69">If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045959" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>General Information About Colorectal Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_6"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_7">Colorectal cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer)
		  cells form in the tissues of the colon or the rectum.</KeyPoint><Para id="_8">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>  and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> are parts of the body's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046446" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive system</GlossaryTermRef>. The digestive system removes and
		  processes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carbohydrates</GlossaryTermRef>, fats, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef>, and
		  water) from foods and helps pass waste material out of the body. The digestive
		  system is made up of the mouth, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>,
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>, and the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">large
		  intestines</GlossaryTermRef>. The colon (large <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef>) is the first part of the large intestine and is about 5 feet long. Together, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044185" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anal</GlossaryTermRef> canal make up the last part of the large intestine and are 6 to 8 inches long. The anal
		  canal ends at the anus (the opening
		  of the large intestine to the outside of the body).<MediaLink ref="CDR0000415499" type="image/jpeg" alt="Gastrointestinal (digestive) system anatomy; drawing shows the esophagus, liver, stomach, colon, small intestine, rectum, and anus." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_87"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the lower gastrointestinal (digestive) system showing  the colon, rectum, and anus. Other organs that make up the digestive system are also shown.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_9"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> that begins in the colon is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, and cancer
		  that begins in the rectum is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000529764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer that begins in either of
		  these organs may also be called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_97">Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summaries containing information related to  colorectal  cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_98" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258007" url="/types/colorectal/patient/colorectal-prevention-pdq"> Colorectal Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062954" url="/types/colorectal/patient/colon-treatment-pdq">Colon Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062959" url="/types/colorectal/patient/rectal-treatment-pdq">Rectal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Colorectal Cancer</SummaryRef> (written for health professionals)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_11">Colorectal cancer is the second leading cause of death from
		  cancer in the United States.</KeyPoint><Para id="_187">Colorectal cancer is the third most common cancer worldwide and the second leading cause of cancer death in the United States when numbers for men and women are combined. Between 2012 and 2021, the number of new colorectal cancer cases in the United States decreased. This decline was largely driven by falling rates in adults aged 65 and older, who continue to have the highest overall rates of colorectal cancer. The drop in older adults may be due in part to increased colorectal cancer screening, which can detect and remove precancerous growths before they develop into cancer. However, trends vary by age group. Among adults younger than 50, the number of new cases of colorectal cancer rose by about 2.4% per year, the largest increase among all age groups. In people aged 50 to 64, the number of new cases increased slightly per year.</Para><Para id="_188">Since 1970, the death rate from colorectal cancer has declined in men and women. However, new cases and deaths from colorectal cancer remain higher among Black people than other racial groups. Studies show that Black people are not more likely than others to have precancerous growths.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_72"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_73">Different factors increase or decrease the risk of getting colorectal cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_16">Anything that increases your chance of getting a disease
		  is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Anything that decreases your chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factor</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_133">Learn more about risk factors and protective factors for colorectal cancer in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258007" url="/types/colorectal/patient/colorectal-prevention-pdq">Colorectal Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><Title> Colorectal Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Screening methods</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_15">Tests are used to screen for different types of cancer when a person does not have symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_76"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810044" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening tests</GlossaryTermRef> to find those with the fewest harms and most benefits. Cancer screening trials also are meant to show whether early detection (finding cancer before it causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>)  helps a person live longer or decreases a person's chance of dying from the disease. For some types of cancer, the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef> is better if the disease is found and treated at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_95"><KeyPoint id="_96">Studies show that some screening tests for colorectal cancer help find cancer at an early stage and may decrease the number of deaths from the disease.</KeyPoint></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><KeyPoint id="_19">The following types of tests are  used to screen for colorectal
		  cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_20"><KeyPoint id="_21">Fecal occult blood test</KeyPoint><Para id="_65">A fecal occult blood test (FOBT)  is a test to check <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046605" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stool</GlossaryTermRef> (solid waste) for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> that can only be seen with a microscope.   A small sample of stool is placed on a special card or in a special container and returned to the doctor or laboratory for testing. Blood in the stool may be a sign of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyps</GlossaryTermRef>, cancer, or other conditions.</Para><Para id="_134">There are two types of FOBTs:</Para><ItemizedList id="_135" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000759143" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Guaiac FOBT</GlossaryTermRef>:</Strong> The sample of stool on the special card is tested with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef>. If there is blood in the stool, the special card changes color.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000415502" type="image/jpeg" alt="Guaiac fecal occult blood test (FOBT) kit; shows card, applicator, and return envelope." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_88"><Caption language="en">A guaiac fecal occult blood test (FOBT) checks for occult (hidden) blood in the stool. Small samples of stool are placed on a special card and returned to a doctor or laboratory for testing.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000413931" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunochemical FOBT</GlossaryTermRef>:</Strong> A liquid is added to the stool sample. This mixture is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a machine that contains <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> that can detect blood in the stool. If there is blood in the stool, a line appears in a window in the machine. This test is also called fecal immunochemical test or FIT.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000784770" type="image/jpeg" alt="Fecal immunochemical test (FIT); drawing shows a FIT kit, which includes the package insert, the collection paper, and a collection tube with a small brush inside of it. Also shown are the biohazard bag, the return envelope, and a paper with information about colorectal cancer and colorectal cancer screening." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_142"><Caption language="en">A fecal immunochemical test (FIT) checks for occult (hidden) blood in the stool. A small sample of stool is placed in a special collection tube or on special cards and returned to a doctor or laboratory for testing.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><KeyPoint id="_27">Sigmoidoscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_66"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045880" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Sigmoidoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> is a procedure to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000357588" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sigmoid</GlossaryTermRef> (lower) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> for polyps, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas, or cancer. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046680" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sigmoidoscope</GlossaryTermRef>  is inserted through the rectum into the sigmoid colon.  A sigmoidoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove polyps or tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000415503" type="image/jpeg" alt="Sigmoidoscopy; drawing shows a sigmoidoscope inserted through the anus and rectum and into the sigmoid colon. An inset shows a patient lying on a table having a sigmoidoscopy." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_89"><Caption language="en">Sigmoidoscopy.  A thin, lighted tube is inserted through the anus and rectum and into the lower part of the colon to look for abnormal areas.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><KeyPoint id="_34">Colonoscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_68"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> is a procedure to look inside the rectum and colon for polyps, abnormal areas, or cancer. A colonoscope  is inserted through the rectum into the colon.  A colonoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove polyps or tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000415504" type="image/jpeg" alt="Colonoscopy; drawing shows a colonoscope inserted through the anus and rectum and into the colon. An inset shows a patient lying on a table having a colonoscopy." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_91"><Caption language="en">Colonoscopy.  A thin, lighted tube is inserted through the anus and rectum and into the colon to look for abnormal areas.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_127"><KeyPoint id="_128">Virtual colonoscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_129"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Virtual colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> is a procedure that uses a series of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">computed tomography</GlossaryTermRef> to make a series of pictures of the
				colon. A computer puts the pictures together to create detailed images that may
				show polyps and anything else that seems unusual on the inside surface of the colon. This test is also called computed tomography  colonography or CTC.</Para><Para id="_136"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> are comparing
				virtual colonoscopy with other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> screening tests. Some clinical trials are testing whether drinking a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">contrast material</GlossaryTermRef> that coats the stool, instead of using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laxatives</GlossaryTermRef> to empty the colon, shows polyps  clearly.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_124"><KeyPoint id="_125">DNA stool test</KeyPoint><Para id="_126">This test checks <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> in stool  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef>  changes that may be a sign of  colorectal cancer. Newer versions of this test are used to help screen for colorectal cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_119"><KeyPoint id="_120">Studies have shown that screening for colorectal cancer using digital rectal exam does not decrease the number of deaths from the disease.</KeyPoint><Para id="_121">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digital rectal exam</GlossaryTermRef> (DRE) is an exam of the rectum that may be done as part of a  routine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. A doctor or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nurse</GlossaryTermRef> inserts a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lubricated</GlossaryTermRef>, gloved finger into the lower part of the rectum to feel for lumps or anything else that seems unusual. Study results have shown that DRE does not work as a screening method for colorectal cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_143"><KeyPoint id="_144">Screening tests for colorectal cancer are being studied in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_143_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risks of screening</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Risks of Colorectal Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_49"><KeyPoint id="_50">Screening tests have risks.</KeyPoint><Para id="_51">Decisions about screening tests can be difficult. Not all screening tests are helpful and most have risks. Different screening tests have different risks or harms. Screening tests may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> when you are thinking about or getting ready for the test, or when there is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">positive test result</GlossaryTermRef>. Before having any screening test, you may
		  want to discuss  the test with your doctor.  It is important to know the risks of
		  the test, and whether it has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from
		  cancer.</Para><Para id="_137">Talk to your doctor about your risk for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and the need for screening tests.</Para><SummarySection id="_112"><KeyPoint id="_113">False-negative test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_114">Screening test results may appear to be normal even though colorectal cancer is present. A person who receives a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-negative test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that
			 shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical
			 care  even if there are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_115"><KeyPoint id="_116">False-positive test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_117">Screening test results may appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> even though no
			 cancer is present. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-positive test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause anxiety and is usually followed by more  tests  (such as
			  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>), which also have risks.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_52"><KeyPoint id="_53">The following  colorectal cancer screening tests have risks:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_105"><KeyPoint id="_106">Colonoscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_110">Serious problems caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef>  are rare, but can include tears in the lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> and bleeding. These problems can be serious and need to be treated in a hospital. Tearing of the lining of the colon and bleeding occur more often when a biopsy or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270865" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polypectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is done.</Para><Para id="_138"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Sedation</GlossaryTermRef> is used to decrease the discomfort from the procedure. Sedation may cause heart and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> problems, such as irregular heartbeat, heart attack, or trouble breathing.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_102"><KeyPoint id="_103">Sigmoidoscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_104">There are fewer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complications</GlossaryTermRef> with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045880" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sigmoidoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> than with a colonoscopy. Although tears in the lining of the colon and bleeding can occur, they are less common than with a colonoscopy. There is usually no sedation with sigmoidoscopy, lowering the risk of complications.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_108"><KeyPoint id="_109">Virtual colonoscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_111"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Virtual colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> has fewer possible physical harms than either colonoscopy or sigmoidoscopy. The harms of being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> used in virtual colonoscopy are not known. Virtual colonoscopy often finds problems with organs other than the colon, including the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef>, chest, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>. Some of these findings lead to more testing, such as colonoscopy, that may not improve the patient's health.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><KeyPoint id="_140">Fecal occult blood test (FOBT) or DNA stool test</KeyPoint></SummarySection><Para id="_141">The results of an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000357584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FOBT</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stool test</GlossaryTermRef> may appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> even though no cancer is found. A positive test result may lead to more testing, including colonoscopy.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about colorectal cancer screening.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Colorectal Cancer Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/colorectal/patient/colorectal-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/colorectal/patient/colorectal-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389230]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062753"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-02</DateLastModified></Summary>
