<Summary id="CDR0000258025" LegacyPDQID="1418" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062718"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Oropharyngeal cancer treatment options include radiation therapy, surgery, chemotherapy with radiation, chemotherapy alone, targeted therapy, and immunotherapy. Learn more about newly diagnosed and recurrent oropharyngeal cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/oropharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Oropharyngeal Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/oropharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Oropharyngeal Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038965">oropharyngeal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_205">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of oropharyngeal cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_206">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>oropharyngeal cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Oropharyngeal Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Oropharyngeal Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Oropharyngeal Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Oropharyngeal Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Oropharyngeal cancer is a type of head and neck cancer that starts in the tissues of the oropharynx.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1754">The pharynx is a hollow tube in the neck about 5 inches long that is made up of three parts:</Para><ItemizedList id="_309" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The nasopharynx is the upper part of the pharynx, located behind the nose. The nostrils are connected to the nasopharynx. Openings on each side of the nasopharynx lead to the ears.</ListItem><ListItem>The oropharynx is the middle part, located beneath the nasopharynx.</ListItem><ListItem>The hypopharynx is the lowermost part of the pharynx, opening up to both the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> (windpipe) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_203">When we breathe or swallow, the pharynx acts as a passageway for air to reach the lungs and food to reach the stomach. Oropharyngeal cancer commonly begins in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046056" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">squamous cells</GlossaryTermRef> that line the oropharynx.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000713970" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the pharynx; drawing shows the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and hypopharynx. Also shown are the nasal cavity, oral cavity, hyoid bone, larynx, esophagus, and trachea." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_217"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the pharynx. The pharynx is a hollow, muscular tube inside the neck that starts behind the nose and opens into the larynx and esophagus. The three parts of the pharynx are the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and hypopharynx.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_214">The oropharynx includes the:</Para><ItemizedList id="_204" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389466" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft palate</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>side and back walls of the throat</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tonsils</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>back one-third of the tongue</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000779437" type="image/jpeg" alt="Parts of the oropharynx; drawing shows the soft palate, side and back wall of the throat, tonsil, and the back one-third of the tongue." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_213"><Caption language="en">Parts of the oropharynx. The oropharynx includes the soft palate, the side and back walls of the throat, the tonsils, and the back one-third of the tongue.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_187">Sometimes, a person can have more than one cancer at the same time in the oropharynx and mouth, nose, throat, voice box (larynx), windpipe (trachea), or esophagus.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_7">Smoking or being infected with human papillomavirus (HPV) can increase the risk
		  of oropharyngeal cancer. </KeyPoint><Para id="_1731">Oropharyngeal cancer is caused by certain changes in how oropharyngeal cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. There are many risk factors for oropharyngeal cancer, but many do not directly cause cancer. Instead, they increase the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> damage in cells that may lead to oropharyngeal cancer. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_1732">A risk factor is anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease. Some risk factors for oropharyngeal cancer, like tobacco use, can be changed. Risk factors also include things you cannot change, like your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef>. Learning about risk factors for oropharyngeal cancer can help you make choices that might prevent or lower your risk of getting it. </Para><Para id="_188">The most common risk factors for oropharyngeal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_9" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>a history of smoking cigarettes for more than 10 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pack years</GlossaryTermRef> and other tobacco use</ListItem><ListItem>heavy alcohol use</ListItem><ListItem>being infected with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human papillomavirus</GlossaryTermRef> (HPV), especially HPV type 16</ListItem><ListItem>a personal history of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		   
		   
		<ListItem>chewing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">betel quid</GlossaryTermRef>, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450121" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stimulant</GlossaryTermRef> commonly used in parts of Asia</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1730">The number of cases of oropharyngeal cancers linked to HPV infection is increasing. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/infectious-agents/hpv-fact-sheet">HPV and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_11">Signs and symptoms of oropharyngeal cancer include a lump in the neck and a sore throat. </KeyPoint><Para id="_12">Sometimes oropharyngeal cancer does not cause early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. When signs and symptoms occur, they may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_13" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>a sore throat that does not go away</ListItem><ListItem>trouble swallowing</ListItem><ListItem>trouble opening the mouth fully</ListItem><ListItem>trouble moving the tongue</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>ear pain</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>a lump in the back of the mouth, throat, or neck</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>a white patch on the tongue or lining of the mouth that does not go away</ListItem><ListItem>coughing up blood</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_189">These problems may be caused by conditions other than oropharyngeal cancer. Check with your doctor if you have any of these problems to find out the cause and begin treatment, if needed.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_15">Tests that examine the mouth and throat are used to  diagnose and stage oropharyngeal cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1733">If you have symptoms that suggest oropharyngeal cancer, your doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. They will ask when the symptoms started and how often you have been having them. They will also ask about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>.   Based on these results, the doctor may recommend other tests. If you are diagnosed with oropharyngeal cancer, the results of these tests will help you and your doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_1734">The following tests and procedures are used to diagnose and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> oropharyngeal cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_17" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>During a <Strong>physical exam of the mouth and neck</Strong>, the doctor or dentist looks at the mouth and neck, under the tongue, and down the throat with a small,
			 long-handled mirror to check for abnormal areas.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>A <Strong>neurological exam</Strong> uses a series of questions and tests to check the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>,    and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve</GlossaryTermRef> function. The exam checks your mental status, coordination, and ability to walk normally, and how well the muscles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">senses</GlossaryTermRef>, and reflexes work. This may also be called a neuro exam or a neurologic exam. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000742485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET-CT scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> combines the pictures from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046218" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">positron emission tomography</GlossaryTermRef> (PET) scan and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">computed tomography</GlossaryTermRef> (CT) scan. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time with the same machine. The combined scans give more detailed pictures of areas inside the body than either scan gives by itself. <ItemizedList id="_199" Style="dash"><ListItem>For the PET scan, a small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. The scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body. Because cancer cells often take up more glucose than normal cells, the pictures can be used to find cancer cells in the body.</ListItem><ListItem>For the CT scan, a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the head, neck, chest, and lymph nodes, is taken from different angles.  A dye is injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.   </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem> 
		  
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fine-needle biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> is usually done to remove a sample of tissue using a thin needle.<Para id="_166">The following procedures may be used to remove samples of cells or tissue:</Para><ItemizedList id="_167" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body to check for abnormal areas.  An endoscope is inserted through an incision (cut) in the skin or opening in the body, such as the mouth or nose.  An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove abnormal tissue or lymph node samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of disease. The nose, throat, back of the tongue, esophagus, stomach, larynx, windpipe, and large airways will be checked.  The type of endoscopy is named for the part of the body that is being examined. For example, pharyngoscopy is an exam to check the pharynx. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Laryngoscopy</Strong> is a procedure in which the doctor checks the larynx (voice box) with a mirror or a laryngoscope to check for abnormal areas.

A laryngoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing the inside of the throat and voice box. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_191">If cancer is found, the following test may be done to study the cancer cells:</Para><ItemizedList id="_192" Style="bullet" Compact="No"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000752848" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HPV test</GlossaryTermRef> (human papillomavirus test)</Strong> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> used to check the sample of tissue for certain types of HPV infection, such as HPV type 16. This test is done because oropharyngeal cancer can be caused by HPV infection. This is important because HPV-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">positive</GlossaryTermRef> oropharyngeal cancer has a better <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and is treated differently than HPV-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">negative</GlossaryTermRef> oropharyngeal cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1755">Learn about the type of information that can be found in a pathologist's report about the cells or tissue removed during a biopsy at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/diagnosis/pathology-reports-fact-sheet">Pathology Reports</ExternalRef>.</Para></ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1735"><KeyPoint id="_1736">Some people may decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1737">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your oropharyngeal cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_1738">Learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_19">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance
		  of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_20">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> depends on: </Para><ItemizedList id="_118" Style="bullet"><ListItem> whether the person has HPV infection of the oropharynx</ListItem><ListItem>whether the person has a history of smoking cigarettes for  10 or more pack years</ListItem><ListItem> the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer</ListItem><ListItem>	the number and size of lymph nodes with cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_168">Oropharyngeal tumors related to HPV infection  have a better prognosis and are less likely to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recur</GlossaryTermRef> than tumors not linked to HPV infection.</Para><Para id="_119">Treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_120" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the stage  of the cancer</ListItem><ListItem>keeping the person's ability to speak and swallow as normal as possible</ListItem><ListItem>the person's general health</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_173">People with oropharyngeal  cancer have an increased risk of another cancer in the head or neck. This risk is increased if a person continues to smoke or drink alcohol after treatment.</Para><Para id="_200">For more information, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062889" url="/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-pdq">Cigarette Smoking:  Health Risks and How to Quit</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Stages of Oropharyngeal Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_23"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><SummarySection id="_1739"><KeyPoint id="_1740">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body. </KeyPoint><Para id="_1741">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. Knowing the cancer stage helps plan treatment.  </Para><Para id="_1742">There are several staging systems for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. Oropharyngeal cancer staging usually uses the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. The cancer may be described by this staging system in your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to the cancer. When talking to you about your diagnosis, your doctor may describe the cancer as one of these stages.</Para><Para id="_1743">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.  </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1669"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_1670">The following stages are used for HPV-positive oropharyngeal cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_1671"><KeyPoint id="_1672">Stage I (also called stage 1) oropharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_1673">In stage I, one of the following is true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1674" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>one or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> with cancer that is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HPV</GlossaryTermRef> 16–positive are found but the place where the cancer began is not known. The lymph nodes with cancer are 6 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller, on one side of the neck; or</ListItem><ListItem>cancer is found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharynx</GlossaryTermRef> (throat) and the tumor is 4 centimeters or smaller. Cancer may have spread to one or more lymph nodes that are 6 centimeters or smaller, on the same side of the neck as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1709"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1675"><KeyPoint id="_1676">Stage II (also called stage 2) oropharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_1677">In stage II, one of the following is true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1678" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>one or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> with cancer that is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HPV</GlossaryTermRef> 16–positive are found but the place where the cancer began is not known. The lymph nodes with cancer are 6 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller, on one or both sides of the neck; or</ListItem><ListItem>the tumor is 4 centimeters or smaller. Cancer has spread to lymph nodes that are 6 centimeters or smaller, on the opposite side of the neck as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> or on both sides of the neck; or

</ListItem><ListItem>the tumor is larger than 4 centimeters or cancer has spread to the top of the epiglottis (the flap that covers the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> during swallowing). Cancer may have spread to one or more lymph nodes that are 6 centimeters or smaller, anywhere in the neck.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1679"><KeyPoint id="_1680">Stage III (also called stage 3) oropharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_1681">In stage III, one of the following is true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1682" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046026" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">larynx</GlossaryTermRef> (voice box), front part of the roof of the mouth, lower jaw, muscles that move the tongue, or to other parts of the head or neck. Cancer may have spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the neck; or</ListItem><ListItem>the tumor is any size and cancer may have spread to the larynx, front part of the roof of the mouth, lower jaw, muscles that move the tongue, or to other parts of the head or neck. Cancer has spread to one or more lymph nodes that are larger than 6 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef>, anywhere in the neck.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1683"><KeyPoint id="_1684">Stage IV (also called stage 4) oropharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_1685">In stage IV, cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> or bone.</Para><Para id="_299">Stage IV oropharyngeal cancer is also called metastatic oropharyngeal cancer. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if oropharyngeal cancer spreads to the lung, the cancer cells in the lung are actually oropharyngeal cancer cells. The disease is called metastatic oropharyngeal cancer, not lung cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1686"><KeyPoint id="_1687">The following stages are used for HPV-negative oropharyngeal cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_1688"><KeyPoint id="_1689">Stage 0 (also called carcinoma in situ of the oropharynx) </KeyPoint><Para id="_1690">In stage 0, abnormal cells are found in the lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharynx</GlossaryTermRef> (throat). These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1691"><KeyPoint id="_1692">Stage I (also  called stage 1) oropharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_1693">In stage I, cancer has formed. The tumor is 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1708"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1694"><KeyPoint id="_1695">Stage II (also  called stage 2) oropharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_1696">In stage II, the tumor is larger than 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> but not larger than 4 centimeters. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1697"><KeyPoint id="_1698">Stage III (also  called stage 3) oropharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_1699">In stage III, the cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1700" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>is either larger than 4 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or has spread to the top of the epiglottis (the flap that covers the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> during swallowing); or</ListItem><ListItem>is any size. Cancer has spread to one <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> that is 3 centimeters or smaller, on the same side of the neck as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1701"><KeyPoint id="_1702">Stage IV (also  called stage 4) oropharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_1703">Stage IV is divided into stages IVA, IVB, and IVC.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1704" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In stage IVA, cancer:<ItemizedList id="_1705" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046026" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">larynx</GlossaryTermRef> (voice box), front part of the roof of the mouth, lower jaw, or muscles that move the tongue. Cancer may have spread to one <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> that is 3 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller, on the same side of the neck as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>; or</ListItem><ListItem>is any size and may have spread to the top of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046421" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epiglottis</GlossaryTermRef>, larynx, front part of the roof of the mouth, lower jaw, or muscles that move the tongue. Cancer has spread to one of the following:<ItemizedList id="_1706" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>one lymph node that is larger than 3 centimeters but not larger than 6 centimeters, on the same side of the neck as the primary tumor; or</ListItem><ListItem>more than one lymph node that is 6 centimeters or smaller, anywhere in the neck.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IVB, cancer:<ItemizedList id="_1707" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>has spread to the muscle that moves the lower jaw, the bone attached to the muscle that moves the lower jaw, the base of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef>, or to the area behind the nose or around the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000396786" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carotid artery</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer may have spread to lymph nodes in the neck; or</ListItem><ListItem>may be any size and may have spread to other parts of the head or neck. Cancer has spread to a lymph node that is larger than 6 centimeters or has spread through the outside covering of a lymph node into nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IVC, cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, or bone.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2991">Stage IV oropharyngeal cancer is also called metastatic oropharyngeal cancer. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if oropharyngeal cancer spreads to the lung, the cancer cells in the lung are actually oropharyngeal cancer cells. The disease is called metastatic oropharyngeal cancer, not lung cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1714"><KeyPoint id="_1715">Oropharyngeal cancer can recur (come back) after it has been treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1761">Recurrent oropharyngeal cancer is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. If oropharyngeal cancer comes back, it may come back in the oropharynx, lymph nodes, or other parts of the body, such as the lungs, bone, or liver. Tests will help determine where in the body the cancer has returned. The type of treatment that you have for recurrent oropharyngeal cancer will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_1762">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_49"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_50">There are different types of treatment for people with oropharyngeal
		  cancer. </KeyPoint><Para id="_1744">Different types of treatments are available for oropharyngeal cancer. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the stage of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment. </Para><Para id="_1745">Talking with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You'll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you'll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Your Treatment</ExternalRef>.    </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_54">People with oropharyngeal cancer should have their treatment planned by a team of doctors with expertise in treating head and neck cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_55">An oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating people with cancer, oversees treatment for oropharyngeal cancer. Because the oropharynx
		  helps in breathing, eating, and talking, you may need help
		  adjusting to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer and its treatment. The oncologist may refer you to other health care providers who are experts in treating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and also specialize in other areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_56" Style="bullet"><ListItem>head and neck surgeon</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046221" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plastic surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389460" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dentist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044661" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietitian</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044459" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">speech therapist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_58">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_59"><KeyPoint id="_60">Surgery </KeyPoint><Para id="_61">Surgery to remove the tumor is a common
			 treatment for all <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stages</GlossaryTermRef> of
			 oropharyngeal cancer. A surgeon may remove the cancer and some of the healthy
			 tissue around the cancer. After
			 the surgeon removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the
			 surgery, some people may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> after surgery to kill any cancer
			 cells that are left. Treatment given
			 after the surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called
			 adjuvant therapy.</Para><Para id="_182">New types of surgery, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000657867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transoral robotic surgery</GlossaryTermRef>, are being studied for the treatment of oropharyngeal cancer. Transoral robotic surgery may be used to remove cancer from hard-to-reach areas of the mouth and throat. Cameras attached to a robot give a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3D) image that a surgeon can see. Using a computer, the surgeon guides very small tools at the ends of the robot arms to remove the cancer. This procedure may also be done using an endoscope.</Para><Para id="_1756">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery">Surgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><KeyPoint id="_63">Radiation therapy
			 </KeyPoint><Para id="_64">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing by damaging their DNA.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000732667" type="image/jpeg" alt="External-beam radiation therapy of the head and neck; drawing shows a patient lying on a table under a machine that is used to aim high-energy radiation at the cancer. An inset shows a mesh mask that helps keep the patient's head and neck from moving during treatment. The mask has pieces of white tape with small ink marks on it. The ink marks are used to line up the radiation machine in the same position before each treatment." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_207"><Caption language="en">External-beam radiation therapy of the head and neck. A machine is used to aim high-energy radiation at the cancer. The machine can rotate around the patient, delivering radiation from many different angles to provide highly conformal treatment. A mesh mask helps keep the patient’s head and neck from moving during treatment. Small ink marks are put on the mask. The ink marks are used to line up the radiation machine in the same position before each treatment.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_1710">Certain ways of giving radiation therapy can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy tissue. These types of radiation therapy include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1711" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient"> Intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (IMRT):  IMRT is a  type of 3-dimensional (3-D) radiation therapy that uses a computer to make pictures of  the size and shape of the tumor. Thin beams of radiation of different intensities (strengths) are aimed at the tumor from many angles.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386233" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stereotactic body radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>:  Stereotactic body radiation therapy is a type of external radiation therapy. Special equipment is used to place the person in the same position for each radiation treatment. Once a day for several days, a radiation machine aims a larger than usual dose of radiation directly at the tumor. By having the person in the same position for each treatment, there is less damage to nearby healthy tissue.  This procedure is also called stereotactic external-beam radiation therapy and stereotaxic radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_175">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced</GlossaryTermRef> oropharyngeal cancer, dividing the daily dose of radiation into smaller-dose treatments improves the way the tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">responds</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment. This is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000484407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperfractionated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_65">Radiation therapy may work better in people who have
			 stopped smoking before beginning treatment. </Para><Para id="_125">If the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046036" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pituitary gland</GlossaryTermRef> are part of the radiation treatment area, the person has an increased risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044547" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypothyroidism</GlossaryTermRef> (too little <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid hormone</GlossaryTermRef>). A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688783" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood test</GlossaryTermRef> to check the thyroid hormone level in the body should be done before and after treatment.</Para><Para id="_2992">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_156"><KeyPoint id="_69">Chemotherapy </KeyPoint><Para id="_157">Chemotherapy uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Chemotherapy for oropharyngeal cancer is usually systemic, meaning it is taken by mouth or injected into a vein or muscle. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body.</Para><Para id="_1746">Chemotherapy drugs used to treat oropharyngeal  cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1747" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496383" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/docetaxel">docetaxel</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537894" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/fluorouracil">fluorouracil</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000502187" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/paclitaxel">paclitaxel</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1748">Combinations of these drugs may be used. Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_1749">Chemotherapy may be combined with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_1750">To learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_183"><KeyPoint id="_176">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_177"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells.  <DrugRef href="CDR0000491901" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cetuximab">Cetuximab</DrugRef> is a type of targeted therapy used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> oropharyngeal cancer.</Para><Para id="_1751">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1757"><KeyPoint id="_1758">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_1759"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment that uses a person's immune system to fight cancer.  Your doctor may suggest biomarker tests to help predict your response to certain immunotherapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.   </Para><Para id="_227"><DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">Pembrolizumab</DrugRef> and <DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef> are types of immunotherapy used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> oropharyngeal cancer.</Para><Para id="_1760">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_66"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_67">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical
		  trials. </KeyPoint><Para id="_66_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_66_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_66_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_219"><KeyPoint id="_220">Treatment for oropharyngeal cancer may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_219_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1752"><KeyPoint id="_1753">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1752_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_1752_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection><Para id="_202">After treatment is complete, it is important to have head and neck exams to look for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> that the cancer has come back. Check-ups will be done every 6 to 12 weeks in the first year, every 3 months in the second year, every 3 to 4 months in the third year, and every 6 months thereafter. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1717"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040133">stage I oropharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040135">stage II oropharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage I and Stage II Oropharyngeal Cancer</Title><Para id="_1718">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258025#_57" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/oropharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_1719">Treatment of  newly diagnosed stage I and stage II oropharyngeal cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1720" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation
			 therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>surgery</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_1717_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1721"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040136">stage III oropharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040137">stage IV oropharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III and Nonmetastatic Stage IV Oropharyngeal Cancer</Title><Para id="_1722">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258025#_57" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/oropharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_1723">Treatment of newly diagnosed stage III oropharyngeal
		  cancer and stage IV oropharyngeal cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1724" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> given at the same time, for people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem>radiation therapy alone for people who cannot have chemotherapy </ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy given at the same time as
			 radiation therapy</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>chemotherapy followed by radiation therapy given at the same time as more chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000767747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nivolumab</GlossaryTermRef>) with chemotherapy given at the same time as radiation therapy in people with cancer that has a higher risk of coming back</ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of transoral surgery followed by standard- or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">low-dose radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without chemotherapy in  people with HPV-positive oropharyngeal cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_1721_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1725"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040138">recurrent oropharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic Stage IV and Recurrent Oropharyngeal Cancer</Title><Para id="_1726">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258025#_57" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/oropharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_1727">Treatment of oropharyngeal
		cancer that has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046283" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasized</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharynx</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1728" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery, if the cancer does not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy, if the tumor was not completely removed by surgery and previous radiation has not been given</ListItem><ListItem>second surgery, if the tumor was not completely removed by the first surgery</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> for people with recurrent cancer that cannot be removed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy  given at the same time as  chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386233" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stereotactic body radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> given at the same time as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045467" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cetuximab</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000767747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nivolumab</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000764538" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pembrolizumab</GlossaryTermRef>) given after or during chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of targeted therapy, stereotactic body radiation therapy, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000484407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperfractionated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, or immunotherapy given at the same time as chemotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_1725_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><Title>To Learn More About Oropharyngeal Cancer</Title><Para id="_129">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about      oropharyngeal cancer, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_159" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck">Head and Neck  Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000593570" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/oral-prevention-pdq">Oral Cavity, Oropharyngeal, Hypopharyngeal, and Laryngeal Cancers Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000593427" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/oral-screening-pdq">Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers Screening</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062871" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-pdq">Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/infectious-agents/hpv-fact-sheet">HPV and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/head-neck">Drugs Approved for Head and Neck Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/head-neck-fact-sheet">Head and Neck Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco">Tobacco</ExternalRef> (includes help with quitting)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_128_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_128_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of oropharyngeal cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Oropharyngeal Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/oropharyngeal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/oropharyngeal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389310]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062924"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
