<Summary id="CDR0000258001" LegacyPDQID="854" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062946"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) starts in the bone marrow. Learn about the symptoms of childhood ALL and how it is diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/child-all-treatment-pdq">Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/child-all-treatment-pdq">Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039919">childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Philadelphia chromosome-positive childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>T-cell childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_179"><Title>What is childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia?</Title><Para id="_6">Childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (also called ALL or acute lymphocytic leukemia) is a cancer of the blood and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>.  This is the most common type of cancer in children. It accounts for about 25% of all childhood cancers in the United States and occurs most often in children aged 1 to 4 years.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000755927" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the bone; drawing shows spongy bone, red marrow, and yellow marrow. A cross section of the bone shows compact bone and blood vessels in the bone marrow. Also shown are red blood cells, white blood cells, platelets, and a blood stem cell." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_7"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the bone. The bone is made up of compact bone, spongy bone, and bone marrow. Compact bone makes up the outer layer of the bone. Spongy bone is found mostly at the ends of bones and contains red marrow. Bone marrow is found in the center of most bones and has many blood vessels. There are two types of bone marrow: red and yellow. Red marrow contains blood stem cells that can become red blood cells, white blood cells, or platelets. Yellow marrow is made mostly of fat.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_11">The bone marrow makes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765906" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> (immature cells) that become mature blood cells over time. A blood stem cell may become a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046279" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myeloid</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell</GlossaryTermRef> or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046298" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoid</GlossaryTermRef> stem cell.</Para><Para id="_12">A myeloid stem cell becomes one of three types of blood cells:</Para><ItemizedList id="_13" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> that carry <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> and other substances to all the tissues in the body</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">granulocytes</GlossaryTermRef> and other types of white blood cells that help the body's immune system respond to infection, allergens, and inflammation</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef> that help stop bleeding by forming clots</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_14">A lymphoid stem cell becomes a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302475" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoblast</GlossaryTermRef> cell and then one of three types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef> (white blood cells):</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044953" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">B lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef>, which make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to help fight infection</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">T lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef>, which help B lymphocytes make the antibodies that help fight infection</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044062" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">natural killer cells</GlossaryTermRef>, which attack cancer cells and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045941" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">viruses</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526538" type="image/jpeg" alt="Blood cell development; drawing shows the steps a blood stem cell goes through to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell. A myeloid stem cell becomes a red blood cell, a platelet, or a myeloblast, which then becomes a granulocyte (the types of granulocytes are eosinophils, basophils, and neutrophils). A lymphoid stem cell becomes a lymphoblast and then becomes a B-lymphocyte, T-lymphocyte, or natural killer cell." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_16"><Caption language="en">Blood cell development. A blood stem cell goes through several steps to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell. </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_17">ALL occurs because too many stem cells become lymphoblasts that do not mature into B lymphocytes or T lymphocytes. These cells are also called leukemia cells. Leukemia cells   are not able to fight infection very well.   Also, as the number of leukemia cells increases in the blood and bone marrow, there is less room for healthy red blood cells, platelets, and white blood cells.  This may lead to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef>, easy bleeding, and infection.</Para><Para id="_180">ALL usually worsens quickly if it is not  treated.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_181">Childhood ALL is caused by changes to how the blood stem cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. The exact cause of these cell changes is often unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_22">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with one or more of these risk factors will develop ALL. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. Risk factors may be genetic or due to other causes.</Para><Para id="_23">Possible genetic risk factors for ALL include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_25" Style="dash"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Down syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurofibromatosis type 1</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bloom syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fanconi anemia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ataxia-telangiectasia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046322" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Li-Fraumeni syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (<GeneName>TP53</GeneName> gene)</ListItem><ListItem>constitutional mismatch repair deficiency (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutations</GlossaryTermRef> in certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> that  stop  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> from repairing itself, which leads to the growth of cancers at an early age)</ListItem><ListItem>having certain changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosomes</GlossaryTermRef> or genes</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_182">Other possible risk factors for ALL include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_24" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		  <ListItem>being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> before birth</ListItem><ListItem>being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>past treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_183">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_184"><Title>Genetic counseling for children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_185">It is not always clear from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> whether a child with ALL has an inherited condition that increased their risk. Genetic counseling can assess the likelihood that your child's cancer is inherited and whether <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef> is needed. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic counselors</GlossaryTermRef> and other specially trained health professionals can discuss your child's diagnosis and family medical history to help you understand:</Para><ItemizedList id="_186" Style="bullet"><ListItem> the options for testing for changes in the <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> gene or other genes</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of other cancers for your child</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of ALL and other cancers for your child's siblings</ListItem><ListItem>the risks and benefits of learning genetic information</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_187">Genetic counselors can also help you cope with your child's genetic test results, including how to discuss the results with family members. They can advise you about whether other members of your family should receive genetic testing.</Para><Para id="_188">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/genetic-testing-fact-sheet">Genetic Testing for Inherited Cancer Risk</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Symptoms of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_28">Symptoms of childhood ALL are caused by not having enough red blood cells and platelets and by having too many white blood cells that don't work well. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_29" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>fever</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>easy bruising or bleeding</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>flat, pinpoint, dark-red spots under the skin caused by bleeding (petechiae)</ListItem><ListItem>weakness or  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pale skin or looks pale</ListItem><ListItem>bone or joint pain</ListItem><ListItem>shortness of breath or trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>painless lumps (swollen <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>) in the neck, underarm, stomach, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem>pain or a feeling of fullness below the ribs</ListItem> 
		<ListItem>loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>weight loss</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> pain</ListItem><ListItem>frequent infections or infections that do not go away</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_189">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than ALL. The only way to know is for your child to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_32">If your child has symptoms that suggest ALL, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other diagnostic tests. If your child is diagnosed with ALL, the results of these tests will help plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_236">The tests used to diagnose childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_190"><Title>Complete blood count (CBC)</Title><Para id="_191">A CBC checks a sample of blood for:</Para><ItemizedList id="_34" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the number of red blood cells and platelets</ListItem><ListItem>the number and type of white blood cells</ListItem><ListItem>the amount of hemoglobin (the protein that carries oxygen) in the red blood cells</ListItem><ListItem>the amount of hematocrit (whole blood that is made up of red blood cells)</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526546" type="image/jpeg" alt="Complete blood count (CBC); left panel shows blood being drawn from a vein on the inside of the elbow using a tube attached to a syringe; right panel shows a laboratory test tube with blood cells separated into layers: plasma, white blood cells, platelets, and red blood cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_35"><Caption language="en">Complete blood count (CBC). Blood is collected by inserting a needle into a vein and allowing the blood to flow into a tube. The blood sample is sent to the laboratory and the red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets are counted.  The CBC is used to test for, diagnose, and monitor many different conditions.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_192"><Title>Blood chemistry study</Title><Para id="_193"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry study</GlossaryTermRef> uses  a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_194"><Title>Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy</Title><Para id="_195">The removal of bone marrow and a small piece of bone by inserting a hollow needle into the hipbone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000549425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breastbone</GlossaryTermRef>. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the bone marrow and bone under a microscope to look for cancer.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775458" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy; drawing shows a child lying face down on a table and a bone marrow needle being inserted into the right hip bone. An inset shows the bone marrow needle being inserted through the skin into the bone marrow of the hip bone." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_36"><Caption language="en">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy. After a small area of skin is numbed, a bone marrow needle  is inserted into the child’s hip bone.  Samples of blood, bone, and bone marrow are removed for examination under a microscope.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_37">Tests done on blood or the bone marrow tissue that is removed include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_38" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Genetic tests</Strong>: Many leukemia cells have abnormalities in their genes which can be found by different types of genetic tests.  An example of a genetic test that is commonly used is cytogenetic analysis, in which the chromosomes in a sample of blood or bone marrow are counted and checked for any changes, such as broken, missing, rearranged, or extra chromosomes. Genetic testing of blood and bone marrow samples is used to help diagnose cancer, plan treatment, or find out how well treatment is working.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Immunophenotyping</Strong>: A laboratory test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to identify cancer cells based on the types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> on the surface of the cells. This test is used to help diagnose specific types of leukemia. For example, the cancer cells are checked to see if they are B lymphocytes or T lymphocytes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_196"><Title>Lumbar puncture</Title><Para id="_197">Lumbar puncture is a procedure used to collect a sample of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> (CSF) from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000396787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal column</GlossaryTermRef> (also called spine) to check for leukemia cells. This is done by placing a needle between two bones in the spine and into the lining around the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> to remove a sample of CSF.  The sample of CSF is checked under a microscope for signs that leukemia cells have spread to the brain and spinal cord. This procedure is also called an LP or spinal tap.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000503953" type="image/jpeg" alt="Lumbar puncture; drawing shows a patient lying in a curled position on a table and a spinal needle (a long, thin needle) being inserted into the lower back. Inset shows a close-up of the spinal needle inserted into the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in the lower part of the spinal column." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_40"><Caption language="en">Lumbar puncture. A patient lies in a curled position on a table. After a small area on the lower back is numbed, a spinal needle (a long, thin needle) is inserted into the lower part of the spinal column to remove cerebrospinal fluid (CSF, shown in blue). The fluid may be sent to a laboratory for testing.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_41">This procedure is done after leukemia is diagnosed to find out if leukemia cells have spread to the brain and spinal cord. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is given after the sample of fluid is removed to treat any leukemia cells that may have spread to the brain and spinal cord.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_198"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_199"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> that can go through the body and make pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.  The chest x-ray is done to see if leukemia cells have formed a lump in the middle of the chest.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_200"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_201">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the genetic test results, pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's tumor.</Para><Para id="_202">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/services">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you may want to ask at your child's appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Risk groups for childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_53">In childhood ALL, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk groups</GlossaryTermRef> are used to plan treatment. The three risk groups in childhood ALL include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_54" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Standard risk: Children aged 1 to younger than 10 years who have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cell</GlossaryTermRef> count less than 50,000 per microliter of blood  at the time of diagnosis.</ListItem><ListItem>High risk: Children 10 years and older and/or children who have a white blood cell count of 50,000 per microliter of blood  or more at the time of diagnosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Very high risk: Children younger than age 1, children with certain changes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef>, children who have a slow improvement from initial treatment, and children who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> of leukemia after the first 4 weeks of treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_55">Other factors that affect the risk group include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_56" Style="bullet"><ListItem>whether the leukemia cells began from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044953" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">B lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">T lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>whether there are certain changes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosomes</GlossaryTermRef> or genes of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>whether the leukemia cell count drops quickly and how low it drops after initial treatment</ListItem><ListItem>whether leukemia cells are found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> or the testes at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>having Down syndrome</ListItem><ListItem>receiving steroids before cancer treatment</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_57">It is important to know the risk group in order to plan treatment.  Children with high-risk or very high-risk ALL  usually receive  more  anticancer drugs and/or higher doses of anticancer drugs than children with standard-risk ALL.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><Title>Types of treatment for childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><SummarySection id="_237"><Title>Who treats children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia?</Title><Para id="_69">A
		  pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes
		  in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of ALL. The pediatric oncologist works with other pediatric health care providers who are experts in treating children
		  with leukemia and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_70" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046370" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hematologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medical
			 oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation
			 oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803670" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric intensivist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318819" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroradiologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_71"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment phases of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_73">The treatment of childhood ALL is done in three phases:</Para><ItemizedList id="_74" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Remission induction  is the first phase of treatment.  The goal is to kill the leukemia cells in the blood and bone marrow. This puts the leukemia into <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef> is the second phase of treatment. It begins once the leukemia is in remission.  The goal     of consolidation/intensification therapy is to kill any leukemia cells that remain in the body and may cause a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapse</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> is the third phase of treatment. The goal is to kill any remaining leukemia cells that may regrow and cause a relapse. Often the cancer treatments are given in lower doses than those used during the remission induction  and consolidation/intensification phases. This is also called the continuation therapy phase.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_241">Taking medicine as ordered by the doctor during maintenance therapy decreases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para><Para id="_46">Treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_47" Style="bullet"><ListItem>whether the leukemia cells began from B lymphocytes or T lymphocytes</ListItem><ListItem>if your child has standard-risk, high-risk, or very high-risk ALL</ListItem><ListItem>your child's age at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>whether there are certain changes in the chromosomes of lymphocytes, such as  the Philadelphia chromosome</ListItem><ListItem>whether your child was treated with dexamethasone or prednisone before the start of remission induction therapy</ListItem><ListItem>how quickly and how low the   leukemia cell count drops during treatment</ListItem><ListItem>if leukemia was found in the central nervous system</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_238">Types of treatment your child might have include:</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_77"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_79">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cells or stops them from dividing.  Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment.</Para><Para id="_206">For ALL, chemotherapy may be given a few ways. Chemotherapy that is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein enters the bloodstream and reaches cancer cells throughout the body.  Chemotherapy that is placed directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> (intrathecal chemotherapy) mainly affects cancer cells in this area.</Para><Para id="_80">The way the chemotherapy is given depends on your child's <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258001#_50" url="/types/leukemia/patient/child-all-treatment-pdq">risk group</SummaryRef>. Children with high-risk ALL receive more anticancer drugs and higher doses of anticancer drugs than children with standard-risk ALL. Intrathecal chemotherapy is used to treat childhood ALL that has spread, or may spread, to the brain and spinal cord.</Para><Para id="_207">Chemotherapy drugs used alone or in combination to treat ALL in children include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_243" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000717920" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/asparaginase-erwinia-chrysanthemi">asparaginase</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000540242" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cytarabine">cytarabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000649927" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/daunorubicinhydrochloride">daunorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000769031" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dexamethasone">dexamethasone</DrugRef> (steroid)</ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000542867" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/doxorubicinhydrochloride">doxorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000749756" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/mercaptopurine">mercaptopurine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000586940" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/methotrexate-sodium">methotrexate</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000492016" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nelarabine">nelarabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000652391" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/prednisone">prednisone</DrugRef> (steroid)</ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000771100" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/thioguanine">thioguanine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599877" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vincristinesulfate">vincristine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_209">Other drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_210">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_82"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_84">Radiation therapy uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing.  Childhood ALL is treated with external beam radiation therapy. This type of therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation therapy may be given alone or with other treatments.</Para><Para id="_85">External radiation therapy  may be used to treat childhood ALL that has spread, or may spread, to the brain, spinal cord, or testicles. It may also be used to prepare the bone marrow for a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_211">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_86"><Title>Stem cell transplant</Title><Para id="_88">High doses of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> is usually given with chemotherapy, but it is sometimes not given to infants and very young  children. These treatments destroy healthy cells, including blood-forming cells. Stem cell transplant is a treatment to replace the blood-forming cells. Stem cells (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or bone marrow of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef> and are frozen and stored. After the patient completes chemotherapy and radiation therapy, the stored stem cells are thawed and given to the patient through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These stem cells grow into (and restore) the body's blood cells. The donor stem cells may also find and kill any cancer cells left in the body.</Para><Para id="_89">Stem cell transplant is rarely used as initial treatment for children and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adolescents</GlossaryTermRef> with ALL. It is used more often as part of treatment for ALL that relapses (comes back after treatment).</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000765030" type="image/jpeg" alt="Donor stem cell transplant; (Panel 1): Drawing of stem cells being collected from a donor's bloodstream using an apheresis machine. Blood is removed from a vein in the donor's arm and flows through the machine where the stem cells are removed. The rest of the blood is then returned to the donor through a vein in their other arm. (Panel 2): Drawing of a health care provider giving a patient an infusion of chemotherapy through a catheter in the patient's chest. The chemotherapy is given to kill cancer cells and prepare the patient's body for the donor stem cells. (Panel 3): Drawing of a patient receiving an infusion of the donor stem cells through a catheter in the chest." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_91"><Caption language="en">Stem cell transplant. (Step 1): Blood is taken from a vein in the arm of the donor. The blood flows through a machine that removes the stem cells. Then the blood is returned to the donor through a vein in the other arm. (Step 2): The patient receives chemotherapy to kill blood-forming cells. The patient may receive radiation therapy (not shown). (Step 3): The patient receives stem cells through a catheter placed into a blood vessel in the chest.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_108"><Title>Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_110">Immunotherapy is a treatment that uses the patient's immune system to fight cancer. Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the body's natural defenses against cancer. Examples of immunotherapy used to treat childhood ALL include blinatumomab, rituximab, and CAR T-cell therapy.</Para><ItemizedList id="_111" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000767077" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/blinatumomab">Blinatumomab</DrugRef>: Blinatumomab works by bringing healthy T cells (immune cells that help kill cancer cells) and leukemia cells close together so the T cells can more effectively kill the leukemia. It does this by binding to a protein called CD3 on healthy T cells and a protein called CD19 on B cells (the immune cells that are cancerous in acute lymphoblastic leukemia). Blinatumomab is a type of targeted therapy drug called a bispecific T-cell engager (BiTE).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000771302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CAR T-cell therapy</GlossaryTermRef>: This treatment changes the patient's T-cells (a type of immune system cell) so they will attack certain proteins on the surface of cancer cells. T cells are taken from the patient and special <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">receptors</GlossaryTermRef> are added to their surface in the laboratory. The changed cells are called chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cells. The CAR T cells are grown in the laboratory and given to the patient by infusion. The CAR T cells multiply in the patient's blood and attack cancer cells. CAR T-cell therapy is being studied in the treatment of childhood ALL that has relapsed (come back) a second time.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000774647" type="image/jpeg" alt="CAR T-cell therapy; drawing of blood being removed from a vein in a patient’s arm to get T cells. Also shown is a special receptor called a chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) being made in the laboratory; the gene for CAR is inserted into the T cells and then millions of CAR T cells are grown. Drawing also shows the CAR T cells being given to the patient by infusion and binding to antigens on the cancer cells and killing them." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_112"><Caption language="en">CAR T-cell therapy. A type of treatment in which a patient’s T cells (a type of immune cell) are changed in the laboratory so they will bind to cancer cells and kill them. Blood from a vein in the patient’s arm flows through a tube to an apheresis machine (not shown), which removes the white blood cells, including the T cells, and sends the rest of the blood back to the patient. Then, the gene for a special receptor called a chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) is inserted into the T cells in the laboratory. Millions of the CAR T cells are grown in the laboratory and then given to the patient by infusion. The CAR T cells are able to bind to an antigen on the cancer cells and kill them.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495778" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/rituximab">Rituximab</DrugRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_220">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_92"><Title>Targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_94">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to block the action of specific enzymes, proteins, or other molecules involved in the growth and spread of cancer cells.  Often, targeted therapies are only used in specific ALL subtypes in which the specific target of the drug is present. Targeted therapy used or studied to treat childhood ALL includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_213" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000491682" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/bortezomib">bortezomib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495782" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dasatinib">dasatinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000487488" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/imatinibmesylate">imatinib mesylate</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000790694" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/inotuzumabozogamicin">inotuzumab ozogamicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000717928" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ruxolitinibphosphate">ruxolitinib</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_214">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_105"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_105_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_105_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_105_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_239"><Title>Treatment options for childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_65">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL). You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's age and overall health, and whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_205">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, visit our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_126"><Title>Treatment of standard-risk childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_128">Treatment of newly diagnosed standard-risk childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> phases always includes combination chemotherapy. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is given to prevent the spread of leukemia cells to the brain and spinal cord.</Para><Para id="_221">For children with a poor response to treatment who are in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef> after remission induction therapy, a  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> using stem cells from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef> may be done.</Para><Para id="_222">For children with a poor response to treatment who are not in remission after remission induction therapy, further treatment is usually the same treatment given to children with <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258001#_131" url="/types/leukemia/patient/child-all-treatment-pdq">high-risk ALL</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_223">Throughout treatment, it's important that your child take all medicines ordered by the doctor. Not taking the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_131"><Title>Treatment of high-risk childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_133">The treatment of newly diagnosed high-risk childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> phases always includes combination chemotherapy. Children in the high-risk ALL group are given more anticancer drugs and higher doses of anticancer drugs, especially during the consolidation/intensification phase, than children in the standard-risk group.</Para><Para id="_134"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are given to prevent or treat the spread of leukemia cells to the brain and spinal cord. Sometimes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain is also given.</Para><Para id="_224">Throughout treatment, it's important that your child take all medicines ordered by the doctor. Not taking the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><Title>Treatment of very high-risk childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_138">Treatment of newly diagnosed very high-risk childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> phases always includes combination chemotherapy. Children in the very high-risk ALL group are given more anticancer drugs than children in the high-risk group. It is not clear whether a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> during first <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef> will help the child live longer.</Para><Para id="_139"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are given to prevent or treat the spread of leukemia cells to the brain and spinal cord. Sometimes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain is also given.</Para><Para id="_225">Throughout treatment, it's important that your child take all medicines ordered by the doctor. Not taking the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_99"><Title>Treatment of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia in the brain and spinal cord or testicles</Title><Para id="_101">Chemotherapy to kill leukemia cells or prevent them from spreading to the brain and spinal cord (central nervous system; CNS) is called CNS-directed therapy. Standard doses of chemotherapy may not cross the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046504" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood-brain barrier</GlossaryTermRef> to get into the fluid that surrounds the brain and spinal cord.  Therefore, leukemia cells are able to hide in the CNS. Systemic chemotherapy given in high doses or intrathecal chemotherapy (into the cerebrospinal fluid) is   able to reach leukemia cells in the CNS. Sometimes external radiation therapy to the brain is also given.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000539773" type="image/jpeg" alt="Intrathecal chemotherapy; drawing shows the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in the brain and spinal cord, and an Ommaya reservoir (a dome-shaped container that is placed under the scalp during surgery; it holds the drugs as they flow through a small tube into the brain). Top section shows a syringe and needle injecting anticancer drugs into the Ommaya reservoir. Bottom section shows a syringe and needle injecting anticancer drugs directly into the cerebrospinal fluid in the lower part of the spinal column." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_102"><Caption language="en">Intrathecal chemotherapy. Anticancer drugs are injected into the intrathecal space, which is the space that holds the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF, shown in blue). There are two different ways to do this. One way, shown in the top part of the figure, is to inject the drugs into an Ommaya reservoir (a dome-shaped container that is placed under the scalp during surgery; it holds the drugs as they flow through a small tube into the brain). The other way, shown in the bottom part of the figure, is to inject the drugs directly into the CSF in the lower part of the spinal column, after a small area on the lower back is numbed.  </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_103">These treatments are given in addition to treatment that is used to kill leukemia cells in the rest of the body. All children with ALL receive CNS-directed therapy as part of induction therapy and consolidation/intensification therapy and sometimes during maintenance therapy.</Para><Para id="_104">If the leukemia cells spread to the testicles, treatment includes high doses of systemic chemotherapy and sometimes radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_242">Throughout treatment, it's important that your child take all medicines ordered by the doctor. Not taking the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_143"><Title>Treatment of T-cell childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_144">Treatment of  newly diagnosed T-cell childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL) during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> phases always includes combination chemotherapy. Children with T-ALL are given more anticancer drugs and higher doses of anticancer drugs than children in the newly diagnosed standard-risk group.</Para><Para id="_145"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are given to prevent or treat the spread of leukemia cells to the brain and spinal cord. Sometimes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain is also given.</Para><Para id="_226">Throughout treatment, it's important that your child take all medicine ordered by the doctor. Not taking the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><Title>Treatment of infants with acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_227">Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) diagnosed in infancy is uncommon. Infants with ALL usually have more symptoms and need more medical support when they are diagnosed. They have a higher risk of relapse than older children.</Para><Para id="_147">Treatment of infants with  newly diagnosed ALL during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> phases always includes combination chemotherapy. Infants with ALL are given different anticancer drugs and higher doses of anticancer drugs than children 1 year and older in the standard-risk group. It is not clear whether a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> during first <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef> will help your child live longer.</Para><Para id="_148"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are given to prevent or treat the spread of leukemia cells to the brain and spinal cord.</Para><Para id="_228">Throughout treatment, it's important that you give your child all medicines ordered by the doctor. Not giving the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_149"><Title>Treatment of adolescents and young adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_229"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adolescents</GlossaryTermRef> and young adults are usually considered to  have high-risk acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL).</Para><Para id="_150">Treatment of  newly diagnosed ALL in adolescents and young adults during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> phases always includes combination chemotherapy. Adolescents and young adults with ALL are given more anticancer drugs and higher doses of anticancer drugs than children in the standard-risk group.</Para><Para id="_151"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are given to prevent or treat the spread of leukemia cells to the brain and spinal cord. Sometimes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain is also given.</Para><Para id="_230">Throughout treatment, it's important that your child take all medicines ordered by the doctor. Not taking the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_153"><Title>Treatment of children with Down syndrome and acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_154">Treatment of newly diagnosed acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) in children, adolescents, and young adults with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Down syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> phases always includes combination chemotherapy. Children with Down syndrome and ALL are treated based on their risk group. Children with Down syndrome and ALL may experience more side effects from treatment than other children. Sometimes children with Down syndrome may receive lower doses of anticancer drugs to lower the risk of side effects from treatment.</Para><Para id="_155"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are given to prevent or treat the spread of leukemia cells to the brain and spinal cord. Sometimes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain is also given.</Para><Para id="_231">Throughout treatment, it's important that your child take all medicines ordered by the doctor. Not taking the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_157"><Title>Treatment of childhood Philadelphia chromosome–positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_232">Philadelphia chromosome–positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) is uncommon in young children. It occurs more often in adolescence and with increasing age.</Para><Para id="_158">Treatment of  newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044179" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Philadelphia chromosome</GlossaryTermRef>–positive  childhood ALL during the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission induction</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consolidation/intensification</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance</GlossaryTermRef> phases always includes combination chemotherapy. Treatment also includes targeted therapy (imatinib mesylate or dasatinib) with or without a stem cell transplant using stem cells from a donor.</Para><Para id="_160"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are given to prevent or treat the spread of leukemia cells to the brain and spinal cord.</Para><Para id="_233">Throughout treatment, it's important that your child take all medicines ordered by the doctor. Not taking the medicines as directed increases the chance the cancer will come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_162"><Title>Treatment of relapsed or refractory childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_60">Refractory childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) is cancer that does not respond to initial treatment.</Para><Para id="_61">Relapsed childhood ALL is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. The leukemia may come back in the blood and bone marrow, brain, spinal cord, testicles, or other parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_164">Treatment of relapsed childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) that comes back in the bone marrow may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_165" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (blinatumomab) and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef>, using stem cells from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_167">Other treatments for refractory or relapsed childhood ALL may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_168" Style="bullet"><ListItem>targeted therapy (inotuzumab, imatinib, or dasatinib)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000771301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T-cell therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_169">Treatment of relapsed childhood ALL that comes back outside the bone marrow may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_170" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain and/or spinal cord for cancer that comes back in the brain and spinal cord only</ListItem><ListItem>stem cell transplant for cancer that has relapsed in the brain and/or spinal cord, especially if relapse occurs soon after initial diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>combination chemotherapy and radiation therapy for cancer that comes back in the testicles only</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Prognostic factors for childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</Title><Para id="_203">If your child has been diagnosed with ALL, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_440">The prognosis depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_450" Style="bullet"><ListItem>how quickly and how low the   leukemia cell count drops after the first month of treatment</ListItem><ListItem>your child's age at the time of diagnosis, sex, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">race</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ethnic background</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the number of white blood cells in the blood at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>whether the leukemia cells began from B lymphocytes or T lymphocytes</ListItem><ListItem>whether there are certain changes in the chromosomes or genes of the leukemia cells</ListItem><ListItem>whether your child has Down syndrome</ListItem><ListItem>whether leukemia cells are found in the cerebrospinal fluid at diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>your child's weight at the time of diagnosis and during treatment</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_48">For leukemia that comes back after treatment, your child's prognosis depends partly on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_49" Style="bullet"><ListItem>how long it is between the time of diagnosis and when the leukemia comes back</ListItem><ListItem>whether the leukemia comes back in the bone marrow or in other parts of the body</ListItem><ListItem>your child's age at relapse</ListItem><ListItem>your child's risk group at initial diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>your child's initial response to treatment for the relapsed leukemia</ListItem><ListItem>whether the leukemia cells began from B lymphocytes or T lymphocytes</ListItem><ListItem>whether there are certain changes in the chromosomes or genes in the leukemia cells</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_204">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_113"><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_240">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_113_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_115"> Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects.</Para><Para id="_116">Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_117" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Physical problems, including problems with the heart, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, or bones, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory. Children younger than 4 years who have received radiation therapy to the brain have a higher risk of these effects.</ListItem><ListItem>Second cancers (new types of cancer) or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelodysplastic syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_118">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_123"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_98">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_990">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back).</Para><Para id="_125"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046505" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone marrow aspiration</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046506" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> are done during initial phases of treatment to see how well the treatment is working. Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy are typically not done after treatment has ended, unless there is concern that the leukemia might have come back.</Para><Para id="_991">Learn more about the follow-up tests in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258001#_30" url="/types/leukemia/patient/child-all-treatment-pdq">Tests to diagnose childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_234"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_235">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_173"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/stem-cell-transplant">Stem Cell Transplants in Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/research/car-t-cells">CAR T Cells: Engineering Patients' Immune Cells to Treat Their Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/child-all-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/child-all-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389385]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062923"/><DateLastModified>2025-04-15</DateLastModified></Summary>
