<Summary id="CDR0000258021" LegacyPDQID="376" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062691"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumor treatment options include surgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy, and hormone therapy. Treatment for carcinoid syndrome includes hormonal treatment, interferon, and other medications to control symptoms. Learn more in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment (Adult)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/hp/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment (Adult)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038092">gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_263">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_264">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Treatment  (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">A gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor is cancer that  forms in the lining of the gastrointestinal tract.</KeyPoint><Para id="_255">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) tract</GlossaryTermRef> is part of the body's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046446" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive system</GlossaryTermRef>, a series of hollow, muscular organs joined in a long, twisting tube from the mouth to the anus. The digestive tract processes nutrients in foods that are eaten and helps pass waste material out of the body:</Para><ItemizedList id="_280" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	Food moves from the throat to the stomach through a tube called the esophagus.</ListItem><ListItem>	After food enters the stomach, it is broken down by stomach muscles that mix the food and liquid with digestive juices.</ListItem><ListItem>	After leaving the stomach, partly digested food passes into the small intestine and then into the large intestine.</ListItem><ListItem>	The end of the large intestine, called the rectum, stores the waste from the digested food until it is pushed out of the anus during a bowel movement.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000741567" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of the gastrointestinal tract showing the stomach, small intestine (including the duodenum, jejunum, and ileum), appendix, colon, and rectum." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_256"><Caption language="en">Gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors form in the lining of the gastrointestinal tract, most often in the small intestine, appendix, or rectum.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_4"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> (also called gastrointestinal carcinoid tumors) form from a certain type of   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045803" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroendocrine</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> (a type of cell that is like a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve cell</GlossaryTermRef> and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef>-making cell).  These cells  are scattered throughout the chest and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> but most are found in the GI tract.  Neuroendocrine cells make hormones that help control digestive juices and the muscles used in moving food through the stomach and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestines</GlossaryTermRef>. A GI neuroendocrine tumor  may also make hormones and release them into the body.</Para><Para id="_6">GI neuroendocrine tumors are rare and most grow very slowly. Most of them occur in the small intestine, rectum, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044753" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appendix</GlossaryTermRef>.  Sometimes more than one <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> will form. </Para><Para id="_217">See the following for information about other types of neuroendocrine tumors:</Para><ItemizedList id="_279" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062678" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pnet-treatment-pdq">Pancreatic Neuroendocrine Tumors (Islet Cell Tumors) Treatment</SummaryRef> </ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000798747" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/child-gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Childhood Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_8"> Health history  can affect the risk of   GI neuroendocrine tumors. 

</KeyPoint><Para id="_244">Anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop GI neuroendocrine tumors, and they can develop in people who don't have any known risk factors. Talk to your doctor if you think you may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_166">Risk factors for GI neuroendocrine tumors include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_163" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Having certain  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef> that affect the stomach's ability to make stomach <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acid</GlossaryTermRef>, such as atrophic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330169" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastritis</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046235" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pernicious anemia</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044262" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Zollinger-Ellison syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_219"><KeyPoint id="_220">Some GI neuroendocrine tumors have no signs or symptoms in the early stages. </KeyPoint><Para id="_221"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by  the growth of the tumor and/or the hormones the tumor makes. Some tumors, especially tumors of the stomach or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044753" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appendix</GlossaryTermRef>, may not cause signs or symptoms. Neuroendocrine tumors are often found during tests or treatments for other conditions.</Para><Para id="_231"> Neuroendocrine tumors in the small intestine (duodenum, jejunum, and ileum), colon, and rectum sometimes cause signs or symptoms as they grow or because of the hormones they make. Other conditions may cause the same signs or symptoms. Check with your doctor if you have:</Para><ItemizedList id="_222" Style="simple"><ListItem><Strong>Duodenum</Strong><Para id="_223">Signs and symptoms of GI neuroendocrine tumors in the duodenum (first part of the small intestine, that connects to the stomach) may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_224" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> pain.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Constipation</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Change in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046605" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stool</GlossaryTermRef> color.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nausea</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vomiting</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Jaundice</GlossaryTermRef> (yellowing of the skin and whites of the eyes).</ListItem><ListItem>Heartburn.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Jejunum and ileum</Strong><Para id="_225">Signs and symptoms of GI neuroendocrine tumors in the jejunum (middle part of the small intestine) and ileum (last part of the small intestine, that connects to the colon) may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_226" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Weight loss for no known reason.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling very tired.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling bloated</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nausea</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Vomiting.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Colon</Strong><Para id="_227">Signs and symptoms of GI neuroendocrine tumors in the colon may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_228" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Abdominal pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Weight loss for no known reason.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Rectum</Strong><Para id="_229">Signs and symptoms of GI neuroendocrine tumors in the rectum may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_230" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood</GlossaryTermRef> in the stool.</ListItem><ListItem>Pain in the rectum.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Constipation</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_16"> Carcinoid syndrome may occur if the tumor spreads to the liver or other parts of the body. </KeyPoint><Para id="_17">The hormones made by GI neuroendocrine tumors are usually destroyed by  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> in the blood. If the tumor has spread to the liver and the liver enzymes cannot destroy the extra hormones made by the tumor,  high amounts of these hormones may remain in the body and cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoid syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>. This can also happen if tumor cells enter the blood. Signs and symptoms of carcinoid syndrome include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>Redness or a feeling of warmth in the face and neck.</ListItem><ListItem>Abdominal pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling bloated.</ListItem><ListItem>Diarrhea.</ListItem><ListItem>Wheezing or other trouble breathing.</ListItem><ListItem>Fast heartbeat.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_134">These signs and symptoms may be caused by GI neuroendocrine tumors or by other conditions. Talk to your doctor if you have any of these signs or symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Imaging studies and tests that examine the blood and  urine are used to diagnose GI neuroendocrine tumors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_159">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as hormones,  released into the blood by organs and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.  The blood sample is  checked to see if it contains a  hormone produced by neuroendocrine tumors. This test is  used to help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> carcinoid syndrome. 
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000732562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumor marker test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a sample of blood, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef>, or tissue is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000721302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromogranin A</GlossaryTermRef>, made by organs, tissues, or tumor cells in the body. Chromogranin A is a tumor marker. It has been linked to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044904" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> when found in increased levels in the body. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Twenty-four-hour urine test</Strong>: A test in which urine is collected for 24 hours to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as       <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044314" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">5-HIAA</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serotonin</GlossaryTermRef> (hormone). An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the organ or tissue that makes it. This test is  used to help diagnose carcinoid syndrome.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000736798" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MIBG scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure used to find neuroendocrine tumors. A very small amount of radioactive material called MIBG (metaiodobenzylguanidine) is injected into a vein and travels through the bloodstream. Neuroendocrine tumors take up the radioactive material and are detected by a device that measures radiation.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> tumor cells in the body.  A small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef> (sugar) is injected into a vein.  The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body.  Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046602" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopic ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> (EUS)</Strong>: A procedure in which an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscope</GlossaryTermRef>  is inserted into the body, usually through the mouth or rectum.  An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. A probe at the end of the endoscope is used to bounce high-energy sound waves (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef>) off internal tissues or organs, such as the stomach, small intestine, colon, or rectum, and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>.  This procedure is also called endosonography. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000470253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Upper endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  A procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas.  An endoscope  is inserted through the mouth and passed through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef> into the stomach.  Sometimes the endoscope also is passed from the stomach into the small intestine. An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> samples, which are checked under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> for signs of disease. </ListItem><ListItem> <Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure to look inside the rectum and colon for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyps</GlossaryTermRef>, abnormal areas, or cancer. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046463" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colonoscope</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted through the rectum into the colon. A colonoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove polyps or tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000749900" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Capsule endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure used to see  all of the small intestine. The patient swallows a  capsule that contains a tiny camera. As the capsule moves through the gastrointestinal tract, the camera takes pictures and sends them to a receiver worn on the outside of the body.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope to check for signs of cancer. Tissue samples may be taken during endoscopy and colonoscopy. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_124"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_125">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_126">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_127" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>Where the tumor is in the gastrointestinal tract.</ListItem><ListItem>The size of the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer has spread from the stomach and intestines to other parts of the body, such as the liver or lymph nodes.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the patient has carcinoid syndrome or has carcinoid heart syndrome.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer can be completely removed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem>
    
    
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><Title>Stages of Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors </Title><SummarySection id="_28"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_29">After a gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the stomach and intestines or to other parts of the body. </KeyPoint><Para id="_160"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Staging</GlossaryTermRef> is the process used to find out how far the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> has spread. The information gathered from the staging process determines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease.  The results of tests and procedures used to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> may also be used for staging. See the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021#_19" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef> section for a description of these tests and procedures. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone scan</GlossaryTermRef> may be done to check if there are rapidly dividing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cells, in the bone.  A very small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> material is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> and travels through the bloodstream.  The radioactive material collects in the bones with cancer and is detected by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_182"><KeyPoint id="_183">There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_182_md_69">Cancer can spread through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_182_md_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.
</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_260"><KeyPoint id="_261">Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_260_md_66">When cancer spreads to another part of the body, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer cells break away from where they began (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>) and travel through the lymph system or blood.</Para><ItemizedList id="_260_md_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer gets into the lymph system, travels through the lymph vessels, and forms a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer gets into the blood, travels through the blood vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_262">The metastatic tumor is the same type of tumor as the primary tumor. For example, if  a GI neuroendocrine tumor spreads to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, the tumor cells in the liver are actually GI neuroendocrine tumor cells. The disease is metastatic GI neuroendocrine tumor, not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><EmbeddedVideo id="_267" ref="CDR0000787719" hosting="youtube" unique_id="fQwar_-QdiQ" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>metastasis: how cancer spreads</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Many cancer deaths are caused when cancer moves from the original tumor and spreads to other tissues and organs. This is called metastatic cancer. This animation shows how cancer cells travel from the place in the body where they first formed to other parts of the body.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_39">The plan for cancer treatment depends on where the neuroendocrine tumor is found and whether it can be removed by surgery.</KeyPoint><Para id="_241">For many cancers it is important to know the stage of the cancer in order to plan treatment. However, the treatment of  GI neuroendocrine tumors is not based on the stage of the cancer. Treatment depends mainly on whether the tumor can be removed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> and if the tumor has spread.</Para><Para id="_242">Treatment is based on whether the tumor:</Para><ItemizedList id="_243" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Can be completely removed by surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Has spread to other parts of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Has come back after treatment. The tumor may come back in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestines</GlossaryTermRef> or in other parts of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Has not gotten better with treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_58"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_59">There are different types of treatment for patients with
		  gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_60">Different types of treatment are available for patients with
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal neuroendocrine (GI) tumors</GlossaryTermRef>. Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef>
		  (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>. A
		  treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current
		  treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.
		  When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the
		  standard treatment, the new
		  treatment may become the standard treatment. Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_63">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_64"><KeyPoint id="_65">Surgery </KeyPoint><Para id="_66">Treatment of GI neuroendocrine tumors usually includes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>. One of the following surgical procedures may be used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_135" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>: Surgery to remove a small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> that is on the inside lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000532343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">GI</GlossaryTermRef> tract. An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscope</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted through the mouth and passed through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef> to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> and sometimes, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">duodenum</GlossaryTermRef>. An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing, and a tool for removing tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Local</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269459" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excision</GlossaryTermRef>: Surgery to remove the tumor and a small amount of normal tissue around it.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Resection</GlossaryTermRef>: Surgery to remove part or all of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> that contains cancer. Nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> may also be removed.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cryosurgery</GlossaryTermRef>: A treatment that uses an instrument to freeze and destroy the tumor. This type of treatment is also called cryotherapy. The doctor may use <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> to guide the instrument.</ListItem><ListItem>	<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044865" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiofrequency ablation</GlossaryTermRef>: The use of a special probe with tiny electrodes that release high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef> (similar to microwaves) that kill cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>. The probe may be inserted through the skin or through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> (cut) in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>	<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Liver</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef>: Surgery to remove the whole liver and replace it with a healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donated</GlossaryTermRef> liver.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hepatic artery</GlossaryTermRef>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embolization</GlossaryTermRef>: A procedure to  embolize (block) the hepatic artery, which is the main <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessel</GlossaryTermRef> that brings <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> into the liver. Blocking the flow of blood to the liver helps kill cancer cells growing there.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_68"><KeyPoint id="_69">Radiation therapy
			 </KeyPoint><Para id="_130"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. There are two types of radiation therapy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_265" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Internal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheters</GlossaryTermRef> that are placed directly into or near the cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_245"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiopharmaceutical</GlossaryTermRef> therapy is a type of internal radiation therapy. Radiation is given to the tumor using a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef> that has a radioactive substance, such as iodine I 131, attached to it. The radioactive substance kills the tumor cells.</Para><Para id="_266">External and internal radiation therapy are used to treat GI neuroendocrine tumors that have spread to other parts of the body.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_71"><KeyPoint id="_72">Chemotherapy </KeyPoint><Para id="_131"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping the cells from dividing.   When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>). When chemotherapy is placed directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef>, an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef>, or a body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef> such as the abdomen, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).  </Para><Para id="_136"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemoembolization</GlossaryTermRef> of the hepatic artery is a type of regional chemotherapy that may be used to treat a  GI neuroendocrine tumor that has spread to the liver. The anticancer drug is injected into the hepatic artery through a catheter (thin tube). The drug is  mixed with a substance that embolizes (blocks) the artery and cuts off blood flow to the tumor. Most of the anticancer drug is trapped near  the tumor and only a small amount of the drug reaches other parts of the body. The blockage may be temporary or permanent, depending on the substance used to block the artery. The tumor is prevented from getting the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef> it needs to grow. The liver continues to receive blood from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044564" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic portal vein</GlossaryTermRef>, which carries blood from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestine</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_137">The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the type and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer being treated.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_170"><KeyPoint id="_171">Hormone therapy
			 </KeyPoint><Para id="_172"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with a somatostatin <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044919" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analog</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment that stops extra <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef> from being made. GI neuroendocrine tumors are treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045141" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">octreotide</GlossaryTermRef> or lanreotide which are injected under the skin or into the muscle. Octreotide and lanreotide may also have a small effect on stopping tumor growth.    </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_246"><KeyPoint id="_247">Treatment for carcinoid syndrome may also be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_248">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoid syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_249" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Hormone therapy with a somatostatin analog stops extra hormones from being made. Carcinoid syndrome is treated with octreotide or lanreotide to lessen flushing and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>. Octreotide and lanreotide may also help slow tumor growth. </ListItem><ListItem>	<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Interferon</GlossaryTermRef> therapy stimulates the body's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to work better and lessens flushing and diarrhea. Interferon may also help slow tumor growth.</ListItem><ListItem>Taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef> for diarrhea.</ListItem><ListItem>Taking medicine for skin rashes.</ListItem><ListItem>Taking medicine to breathe easier.</ListItem><ListItem>Taking medicine before having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anesthesia</GlossaryTermRef> for a medical procedure.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_250">Other ways to help treat carcinoid syndrome include avoiding things that cause flushing or difficulty breathing such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef>, nuts, certain cheeses and foods with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045377" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsaicin</GlossaryTermRef>, such as chili peppers. Avoiding <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stressful</GlossaryTermRef> situations and certain types of physical activity can also help treat carcinoid syndrome.</Para><Para id="_251">For some patients with carcinoid heart syndrome,  a heart valve replacement may be done.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_86"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_87">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.
		  </KeyPoint><Para id="_95">This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in clinical trials. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about  clinical trials is available from the
			 <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_190"><KeyPoint id="_191">Targeted therapy

</KeyPoint><Para id="_192"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. Several types of targeted therapy are being studied in the treatment of GI neuroendocrine tumors.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_268"><KeyPoint id="_269">Treatment for gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_268_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_184"><KeyPoint id="_185">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_184_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_184_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_184_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_186"><KeyPoint id="_187">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_186_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_186_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_188"><KeyPoint id="_189">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_188_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_188_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_233"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038099">localized gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038106">regional gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Neuroendocrine Tumors in the Stomach</Title><Para id="_270">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021#_62" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_194"> 

Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_195" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>) for small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery (resection) to remove part or all of the stomach. Nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> for larger tumors, tumors that grow deep into the stomach wall, or tumors that are growing and spreading quickly may also be removed.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_252">For patients with GI neuroendocrine tumors in the stomach and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MEN1 syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>, treatment may also include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_253" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgery (resection) to remove tumors in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">duodenum</GlossaryTermRef> (first part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>, that connects to the stomach).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_233_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_234"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038099">localized gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038106">regional gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Neuroendocrine Tumors in the Small Intestine</Title><Para id="_271">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021#_62" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_197">It is not clear what the best treatment is for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">duodenum</GlossaryTermRef> (first part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>, that connects to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>). Treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_205" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>) for small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269459" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excision</GlossaryTermRef>) to remove slightly larger tumors.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery (resection) to remove the tumor and nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_198">Treatment of GI neuroendocrine tumors in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000751987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">jejunum</GlossaryTermRef> (middle part of the small intestine) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000751989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ileum</GlossaryTermRef> (last part of the small intestine, that connects to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>) may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_210" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	Surgery (resection) to remove the tumor and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046294" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">membrane</GlossaryTermRef> that connects the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestines</GlossaryTermRef> to the back of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> wall. Nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> are also removed.</ListItem><ListItem>A second surgery to remove the membrane that connects the intestines to the back of the abdominal wall, if any tumor remains or the tumor continues to grow.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_234_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_235"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038099">localized gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038106">regional gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Neuroendocrine Tumors in the Appendix</Title><Para id="_272">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021#_62" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_200">Treatment of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044753" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appendix</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_207" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>) to remove the appendix.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery (resection) to remove the right side of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> including the appendix. Nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> are also removed.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_235_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_236"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038099">localized gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038106">regional gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Neuroendocrine Tumors in the Colon</Title><Para id="_273">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021#_62" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_202">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_254" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>) to remove part of the colon and nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, in order to remove as much of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> as possible.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_236_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_237"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038099">localized gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038106">regional gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Neuroendocrine Tumors in the Rectum</Title><Para id="_274">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021#_62" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_204">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_209" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>) for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef> that are smaller than 1 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeter</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery (resection) for tumors that are larger than 2 centimeters or that have spread to the muscle layer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044083" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectal</GlossaryTermRef> wall. This may be either:<ItemizedList id="_257" Style="dash"><ListItem>surgery to remove part of the rectum; or</ListItem><ListItem> surgery to remove  the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anus</GlossaryTermRef>, the rectum, and part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> made in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_258">It is not clear what the best treatment is for tumors that are 1 to 2 centimeters. Treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_259" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Endoscopic surgery (resection).</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery (resection) to remove part of the rectum.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery (resection) to remove the anus, the rectum, and part of the colon through an incision made in the abdomen.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_237_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_278"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038117">metastatic gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors</Title><Para id="_275">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021#_62" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_155"><Strong>Distant metastases</Strong></Para><Para id="_156">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045670" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distant metastases</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> is usually <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>. Treatment   may include:
</Para><ItemizedList id="_211" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>) to remove as much of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> as possible.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiopharmaceutical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> that has spread to the bone, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of a new treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_213"><Strong>Liver metastases</Strong></Para><Para id="_214">Treatment of cancer that has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_212" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269459" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excision</GlossaryTermRef>) to remove the tumor from the liver.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hepatic artery</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embolization</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cryosurgery</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044865" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiofrequency ablation</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Liver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_278_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_276"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038130">recurrent gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors</Title><Para id="_277">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021#_62" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_114">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal (GI) neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_115" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269459" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excision</GlossaryTermRef>) to remove part or all of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of a new treatment.</ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_276_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_176"><Title>To Learn More About Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors</Title><Para id="_177">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_239" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-carcinoid-tumors/">Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery/cryosurgery">Cryosurgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_176_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_176_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389212]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062893"/><DateLastModified>2025-02-20</DateLastModified></Summary>
