<Summary id="CDR0000258020" LegacyPDQID="1381" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062714"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary (unknown primary) treatment options include surgery, radiation therapy, or a combination of both. Learn more about the diagnosis and treatment of these tumors in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq">Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq">Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038945">metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_108">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_109">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary is a
		  disease in which squamous cell cancer spreads  to
		  lymph nodes in the neck and it is not known where the cancer first formed in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_65">Squamous cells are thin, flat cells found in tissues that form the surface of the skin and  the lining of body cavities such as the mouth,  hollow organs such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef>, and the lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044490" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respiratory</GlossaryTermRef> (breathing) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive tracts</GlossaryTermRef>. Some organs with squamous cells are the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef>, and uterus. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> can begin in squamous cells anywhere in the
		  body and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046283" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasize</GlossaryTermRef> (spread) through the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_59">When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046595" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">squamous cell cancer</GlossaryTermRef> spreads to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the neck or around the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collarbone</GlossaryTermRef>, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> squamous neck cancer. The doctor will try to find the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (the cancer that first formed in the body), because
		  treatment for metastatic cancer is the same as treatment for the
		  primary tumor.
		  For example, when <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> spreads to the neck, the cancer cells in the neck are lung cancer cells and they are
		  treated the same as the cancer in the lung. Sometimes doctors cannot find where in the body the cancer first began to grow.  When tests cannot find a primary tumor,  it is called an
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">occult (hidden) primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. In many cases, the primary tumor is never found.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_6">Signs and symptoms of metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult
		  primary include a lump or pain in the neck or throat.</KeyPoint><Para id="_7">Check with your doctor if you have a lump or pain in your neck or
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef> that doesn't go away. These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by
		  metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary. Other conditions may cause the same signs and symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_9">Tests that examine the tissues of the neck, respiratory tract,  and upper part of the digestive tract are used
		  to detect (find) and diagnose metastatic squamous neck cancer and the 
		  primary tumor.</KeyPoint><Para id="_10">Tests will include checking for a primary tumor in the organs and tissues of the respiratory tract (part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef>), the upper part of the digestive tract (including the lips, mouth, tongue, nose, throat, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vocal cords</GlossaryTermRef>, and part of the esophagus), and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046381" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genitourinary system</GlossaryTermRef>. In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_11" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> or tested in the laboratory to check for signs of cancer.  <Para id="_102">Three types of  biopsy may be done:</Para><ItemizedList id="_66" Style="dash"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fine-needle aspiration (FNA) biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of  tissue or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef> using a thin needle.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641799" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Core needle biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of tissue using a wide needle.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046411" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Excisional biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of an entire lump of tissue.  </ListItem></ItemizedList> <Para id="_103">The following procedures are used to remove samples of cells or tissue:</Para><ItemizedList id="_104" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Tonsillectomy</Strong>: Surgery to remove both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tonsils</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas.  An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscope</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> (cut) in the skin or opening in the body, such as the mouth or nose.  An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove abnormal tissue or lymph node samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of disease. The nose, throat, back of the tongue, esophagus, stomach, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000520366" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">voice box</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044379" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">windpipe</GlossaryTermRef>, and large airways will be checked. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_105">One or more of the following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory tests</GlossaryTermRef> may be done to study the tissue samples:</Para><ItemizedList id="_106" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000653117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunohistochemistry</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient’s blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the blood or bone marrow, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044052" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Light</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electron microscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A test in which cells in a sample of tissue are viewed under regular and high-powered microscopes to look for certain changes in the cells.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef> (EBV) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human papillomavirus</GlossaryTermRef> (HPV) test</Strong>: A test that checks the cells in a sample of tissue for EBV and HPV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an x-ray machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000753850" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck; drawing shows a patient lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_110"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck. The patient lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> cells in the body.  A small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive glucose</GlossaryTermRef> (sugar) is injected into a vein.  The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body.  Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do. A whole body PET scan and a CT scan are done at the same time to look for where the cancer first formed. If there is any cancer, this increases the chance that it will be found.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_70">A diagnosis of occult primary tumor is made if the primary tumor is not found during testing or treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_60"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_61">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_62">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_63" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>The number and size of  lymph nodes that have cancer in them.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">responded</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back).</ListItem><ListItem>How different from normal the cancer cells look under a microscope.</ListItem><ListItem>The patient's age and general health.</ListItem>
    
    
   </ItemizedList><Para id="_78">Treatment options also depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_79" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Which part of the neck the cancer is in.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether certain tumor markers are found.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><Title>Stages of Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult
		Primary</Title><SummarySection id="_85"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_86">After metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_87">The process used to find out if cancer has spread  to other parts of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. There is no standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging
		  system</GlossaryTermRef> for metastatic squamous neck cancer with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">occult primary</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on whether the cancer was caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000811775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human papillomavirus 16</GlossaryTermRef>  or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef>, oropharyngeal or nasopharyngeal cancer staging may be used.  To learn more, visit the section called <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062919#_16" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq">Stage Information for Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary</SummaryRef> in the health professional version of this page.</Para><Para id="_119">The results from <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258020#_8" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq">tests and procedures</SummaryRef> used to detect and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> are also used to find out if cancer has spread to other parts of the body.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_91"><KeyPoint id="_92">There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_91_md_69">Cancer can spread through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_91_md_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.
</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_120"><KeyPoint id="_121">Metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary can recur (come back) after it has been treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_122">The cancer may come back in the neck or in other parts of the body.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_21"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_22"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_23">There are different types of treatment for patients with
		  metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary.</KeyPoint><Para id="_24">Different types of treatment are available for patients with
		  metastatic squamous neck <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">occult primary</GlossaryTermRef>. Some treatments are
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.  A
		  treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current
		  treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer.
		  When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the
		  standard treatment, the new
		  treatment may become the standard treatment. Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_27">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_28"><KeyPoint id="_29">Surgery </KeyPoint><Para id="_73">Surgery may include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046281" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neck dissection</GlossaryTermRef>. There are different types of neck dissection, based on the amount of tissue that is removed.</Para><ItemizedList id="_74" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Radical neck dissection: Surgery to remove tissues in one or both sides of the neck between the jawbone and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collarbone</GlossaryTermRef>, including:<ItemizedList id="_75" Style="dash"><ListItem>All <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The jugular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Muscles and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef> that are used for face, neck, and shoulder movement, speech, and swallowing.</ListItem></ItemizedList>The patient may need <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical therapy</GlossaryTermRef> of the throat, neck, shoulder, and/or arm after radical neck dissection. Radical neck dissection may be used when cancer has spread widely in the neck.</ListItem><ListItem>Modified radical neck dissection: Surgery to remove all the lymph nodes in one or both sides of the neck without removing  the neck muscles. The nerves and/or the jugular vein may be removed. 

 

</ListItem><ListItem>Partial neck dissection: Surgery to remove some of the lymph nodes in the neck. 

This is also called  selective neck dissection.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_30">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the
			 time of surgery, some patients may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> after surgery to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment
			 given after surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant
			 therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><KeyPoint id="_33">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_53">Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (IMRT) is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3-D) external radiation therapy that uses a computer to make pictures of the size and shape of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. Thin beams of radiation of different intensities (strengths) are aimed at the tumor from many angles. This type of radiation therapy  is less likely to cause dry mouth, trouble swallowing, and  damage to the skin.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000732667" type="image/jpeg" alt="External-beam radiation therapy of the head and neck; drawing shows a patient lying on a table under a machine that is used to aim high-energy radiation at the cancer. An inset shows a mesh mask that helps keep the patient's head and neck from moving during treatment. The mask has pieces of white tape with small ink marks on it. The ink marks are used to line up the radiation machine in the same position before each treatment." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_123"><Caption language="en">External-beam radiation therapy of the head and neck. A machine is used to aim high-energy radiation at the cancer. The machine can rotate around the patient, delivering radiation from many different angles to provide highly conformal treatment. A mesh mask helps keep the patient’s head and neck from moving during treatment. Small ink marks are put on the mask. The ink marks are used to line up the radiation machine in the same position before each treatment.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_35">Radiation therapy to the neck may change the way the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid gland</GlossaryTermRef> works. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688783" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood tests</GlossaryTermRef> may be done to check the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid hormone</GlossaryTermRef> level in the body
			 before treatment and at regular checkups after treatment.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_37">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_90">This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in clinical trials. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about clinical trials is available from the     <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_38"><KeyPoint id="_39">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_54"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><KeyPoint id="_68">Hyperfractionated radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_69"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000484407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hyperfractionated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of external radiation treatment in which a smaller than usual total daily <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> of radiation is divided into two doses and the treatments are given twice a day.  Hyperfractionated radiation therapy is given over the same period of time (days or weeks) as standard radiation therapy.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_116"><KeyPoint id="_117">Treatment for metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult
		primary may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_116_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_93"><KeyPoint id="_94">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_93_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_93_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_93_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_95"><KeyPoint id="_96">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_95_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_95_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_97"><KeyPoint id="_98">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_97_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_97_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_124"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039088">untreated metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Untreated Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary</Title><Para id="_125">Patients with untreated metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary have not been treated, except to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> caused by the cancer. For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258020#_26" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_126">Treatment of untreated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> squamous neck cancer with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">occult primary</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_127" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery.</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem>Radiation therapy followed by surgery.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> followed by radiation
			 therapy.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>A clinical trial of chemotherapy given at the same time as
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000484407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperfractionated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>Clinical trials of  new treatments.</ListItem>
		  
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_124_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039089">recurrent metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary</Title><Para id="_129">For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258020#_26" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_130">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> squamous neck cancer with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">occult primary</GlossaryTermRef> that recurs (comes back) after treatment is usually within a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_128_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_80"><Title>To Learn More About Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary</Title><Para id="_81">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_82" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary">Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck">Head and Neck Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062871" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-pdq">Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_80_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_80_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of metastatic squamous neck cancer with occult primary.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389176]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062919"/><DateLastModified>2025-03-14</DateLastModified></Summary>
