<Summary id="CDR0000258179" LegacyPDQID="831" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062943"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Anal cancer treatment options include radiation therapy, chemotherapy, and/or surgery. Get detailed information about newly diagnosed and recurrent anal cancer including risk factors, symptoms, diagnosis, prognosis, and treatment in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/anal/patient/anal-treatment-pdq">Anal Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/anal/hp/anal-treatment-pdq">Anal Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039550">anal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_186">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of anal cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_187">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>anal cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Anal Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Anal Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Anal Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Anal Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Anal cancer is a type of cancer that forms in
		  the tissues of the anus.</KeyPoint><Para id="_146">The anus is the end of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">large intestine</GlossaryTermRef>. It is where stool (solid waste) leaves the body. The anus is formed partly from the outer skin layers of the body and partly from the intestine. The anus is connected to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> by the anal canal, which is about 1 to 1½ inches long. This area is controlled by two ring-like sphincter muscles, which contract to hold stool in and relax to allow its passage out of the body.  <MediaLink ref="CDR0000415499" type="image/jpeg" alt="Gastrointestinal (digestive) system anatomy; drawing shows the esophagus, liver, stomach, colon, small intestine, rectum, and anus." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_162"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the lower gastrointestinal (digestive) system showing  the colon, rectum, and anus. Other organs that make up the digestive system are also shown.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_115">Anal cancer can start in the lining of the anal canal, called the mucosa, or in the perianal skin, the squamous cells outside of the anus that contain hair follicles and sweat glands.</Para><Para id="_639">   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumors</GlossaryTermRef> of the perianal skin that do not involve the anal
sphincter  are usually  treated the same as anal cancers, although local therapy (treatment directed to a limited area of skin) may be used for some.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_8">Most anal cancers are related to human papillomavirus (HPV) infection.</KeyPoint><Para id="_643">Anal cancer is caused by certain changes to the way anal cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. There are many risk factors for anal cancer, but many do not directly cause cancer. Instead, they increase the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> damage in cells that may lead to anal cancer. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_648">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Some risk factors for anal cancer can be changed. However, risk factors also include things people cannot change, like getting older and their health history. Learning about risk factors for anal cancer can help you make changes that might lower your risk of getting it.</Para><Para id="_118">Risk factors for anal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_119" Style="bullet"><ListItem>being <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infected</GlossaryTermRef> with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000753084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-risk human papillomavirus</GlossaryTermRef> (HPV), especially HPV type 16 or 18. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/infectious-agents/hpv-fact-sheet">HPV and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>having a condition or disease that causes a weakened <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HIV</GlossaryTermRef> or an organ <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vulvar</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000523460" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaginal</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having many sexual partners</ListItem><ListItem>having receptive anal intercourse (anal sex)</ListItem><ListItem>smoking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cigarettes</GlossaryTermRef>. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco">Tobacco</ExternalRef> (includes help with quitting).</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_646">Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_16">Signs of anal cancer include bleeding from the anus or rectum or a lump near the anus.</KeyPoint><Para id="_132">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by anal cancer or by other conditions. Check with your doctor if you have:</Para><ItemizedList id="_117" Style="bullet"><ListItem>bleeding from the anus or rectum</ListItem><ListItem>a lump near the anus</ListItem><ListItem>pain or pressure in the area around the anus</ListItem><ListItem>itching or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443583" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">discharge</GlossaryTermRef> from the anus</ListItem><ListItem>a change in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef> habits</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Tests that examine the rectum and anus are used to diagnose anal  cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_320"> In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet">
			 <ListItem><Strong>Digital rectal examination (DRE)</Strong> is an exam of the anus and rectum. The doctor or nurse inserts a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lubricated</GlossaryTermRef>, gloved finger into the lower part of the rectum to feel for lumps or anything else that seems unusual.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000457840" type="image/jpeg" alt="Digital rectal exam; drawing shows a side view of the male reproductive anatomy and the urinary anatomy, including the prostate, rectum, and bladder. Also shown is a gloved, lubricated finger inserted into the rectum to feel the rectum, anus, and prostate." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_182"><Caption language="en">Digital rectal exam (DRE). The doctor inserts a gloved, lubricated finger into the rectum and feels the rectum, anus, and prostate (in males) to check for anything abnormal.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Anoscopy</Strong> is an exam of the anus and lower rectum using a short, lighted tube called an anoscope.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Proctoscopy</Strong> is a procedure to look inside the rectum and anus to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas, using a proctoscope. A proctoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing the inside of the rectum and anus. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Endo-anal or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000357580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endorectal ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure in which an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367430" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound transducer</GlossaryTermRef> (probe) is inserted into the anus or rectum and used to bounce high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.</ListItem>
			 
			 <ListItem> <Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer. If an abnormal area is seen during the anoscopy, a biopsy may be done at that time.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_621"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_622">After anal cancer has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the anus or to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_623">The process used to find out if cancer has spread within the anus or to other
parts of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. The information gathered from this
staging process determines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease. It is important to know
the stage in order to plan treatment. The following tests may be used in the staging process:</Para><ItemizedList id="_624" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, or chest. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs.  A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong> uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong> uses a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> sugar (also called radioactive glucose) that is injected into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes pictures of where glucose is being used in the body. Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pelvic exam</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an exam of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>.    A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046588" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">speculum</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted into the vagina and the doctor or nurse looks at the vagina and cervix for signs of disease.  A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045978" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pap test</GlossaryTermRef> of the cervix is usually done.  The doctor or nurse also inserts one or two lubricated, gloved fingers of one hand into the vagina and places the other hand over the lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> to feel the size, shape, and position of the uterus and ovaries. The doctor or nurse also inserts a lubricated, gloved finger into the rectum to feel for lumps or abnormal areas.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000609924" type="image/jpeg" alt="Pelvic exam; drawing shows a side view of the female reproductive anatomy during a pelvic exam. The uterus, left fallopian tube, left ovary, cervix, vagina, bladder, and rectum are shown. Two gloved fingers of one hand of the doctor or nurse are shown inserted into the vagina, while the other hand is shown pressing on the lower abdomen. The inset shows a woman covered by a drape on an exam table with her legs apart and her feet in stirrups." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_631"><Caption language="en">Pelvic exam. A doctor or nurse inserts one or two lubricated, gloved fingers of one hand into the vagina and presses on the lower abdomen with the other hand. This is done to feel the size, shape, and position of the uterus and ovaries. The vagina, cervix,  fallopian tubes, and rectum are also checked.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_636"><KeyPoint id="_647">Some people decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_637">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your anal cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_638">Learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_24">Certain factors affect the prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_147">The prognosis depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_148" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the size of the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_25">The treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_149" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer</ListItem><ListItem> where the tumor  is in the anus</ListItem><ListItem>whether the person has HIV</ListItem><ListItem>whether cancer remains  after initial treatment or has recurred (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Stages of Anal Cancer</Title><Para id="_640">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of the anal cancer to plan the best treatment.</Para><Para id="_641">There are several staging systems for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. Anal cancer staging usually uses the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. The cancer may be described by this staging system in your pathology report. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to your cancer. When talking to you about your diagnosis, your doctor may describe the cancer as one of these stages.</Para><Para id="_642">Learn about  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258179#_621" url="/types/anal/patient/anal-treatment-pdq">tests to stage anal cancer</SummaryRef>. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_31"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_32">The following stages are used for anal cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_271"><KeyPoint id="_272">Stage 0 (carcinoma in situ)</KeyPoint><Para id="_273">In stage 0, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> cells are found in the mucosa (innermost layer) of the anus. These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. Stage 0 is also called high-grade  intraepithelial lesion (HSIL).</Para></SummarySection><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_163"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink><SummarySection id="_36"><KeyPoint id="_37">Stage I (also called stage 1) anal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_38">In stage I,  cancer has formed and the  tumor is  2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_39"><KeyPoint id="_40">Stage II (also called stage 2) anal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_274">Stage II anal cancer is divided into stages IIA and IIB.</Para><ItemizedList id="_282" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>In stage IIA, the tumor is larger than 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> but not larger than 5 centimeters.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIB, the tumor is larger than 5 centimeters.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_277"><KeyPoint id="_278">Stage III (also called stage 3) anal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_279">Stage III anal cancer is divided into stages IIIA, IIIB, and IIIC.</Para><ItemizedList id="_280" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>In stage IIIA, the tumor is 5 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller and has spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> near the anus or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIB, the tumor is any size and has spread to nearby organs, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046640" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urethra</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer has not spread to lymph nodes.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIC, the tumor is any size and may have spread to nearby organs. Cancer has spread to lymph nodes near the anus or groin.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><KeyPoint id="_46">Stage IV (also called stage 4) anal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_281">In stage IV, the tumor is any size. Cancer may have spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> or nearby organs and has spread to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_625">Stage IV anal cancer is also called metastatic anal cancer. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if anal cancer spreads to the liver, the cancer cells in the liver are actually anal cancer cells. The disease is called metastatic anal cancer, not liver cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_317"><KeyPoint id="_318">Anal cancer can recur (come back) after it has been treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_626">Recurrent anal cancer is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. If anal cancer comes back, it may come back in the anus or in other parts of the body, such as the liver or
		lungs. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned. The type of treatment for recurrent anal cancer will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_627">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_51"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_52">There are different types of treatment for  people with anal cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_628">Different types of treatments are available for anal cancer. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the stage of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment.</Para><Para id="_629">Talking with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You'll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you'll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_55"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_56">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_57"><KeyPoint id="_58">Surgery</KeyPoint><ItemizedList id="_145" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Local resection is a  surgical procedure in which the tumor is cut from the anus along with some of the healthy tissue around it. Local resection may be used if the cancer is small and has not spread. This procedure may save the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sphincter</GlossaryTermRef> muscles so the person can still control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef> movements. Tumors that form in the lower part of the anus can often be removed with local resection.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000377733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Abdominoperineal resection</GlossaryTermRef> is a surgical procedure in which the anus, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>, and part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000357588" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sigmoid colon</GlossaryTermRef> are removed through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> made in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>. The doctor sews the end of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestine</GlossaryTermRef> to an opening, called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stoma</GlossaryTermRef>, made in the surface of the abdomen so body waste can be collected in a disposable bag outside of the body. This is called a  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colostomy</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> that contain cancer may also be removed during this operation. This procedure   is used only  for cancer that remains or comes back after treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and chemotherapy.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000415509" type="image/jpeg" alt="Three-panel drawing showing anal cancer surgery with colostomy; first panel shows area of anus with cancer, middle panel shows cancer and nearby tissue removed and stoma created, last panel shows a colostomy bag attached to the stoma." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_164"><Caption language="en">Resection of the colon with colostomy. Part of the colon containing the cancer and nearby healthy tissue are removed, a stoma is created, and a colostomy bag is attached to the stoma.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><KeyPoint id="_62">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_63"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. There are two types of radiation therapy used to treat anal cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_188" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>  uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Internal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheters</GlossaryTermRef> that are placed directly into or near the cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_620">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy">Radiation Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_64"><KeyPoint id="_65">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_66">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping the cells from dividing.   When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para><Para id="_632">Chemotherapy drugs used to treat anal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_633" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496354" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/capecitabine">capecitabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537894" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/fluorouracil">fluorouracil</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000712481" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/mitomycin">mitomycin</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_634">Combinations of these drugs may be used. Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_635">Chemotherapy may be combined with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_630">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_80">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_79_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_79_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_79_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_267"><KeyPoint id="_268">Treatment for anal cancer may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_267_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_177"><KeyPoint id="_178">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_177_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_177_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043540">stage 0 anal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage 0 (carcinoma in situ)</Title><Para id="_91">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000413881" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage 0</GlossaryTermRef> is usually <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_321">Learn more about this treatment in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258179#_55" url="/types/anal/patient/anal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_139_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040600">stage I anal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stages I, II, and III Anal Cancer</Title><Para id="_95">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045306" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045307" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045310" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III anal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_96" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef> for tumors of the skin around the outside of the anus and tumors inside the anal opening that do not involve the anal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sphincter</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
	  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">external beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
	  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> alone</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000377733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominoperineal resection</GlossaryTermRef>, if cancer  remains or comes back after treatment with radiation therapy and chemotherapy, or  other options that may include treatment  with additional <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306495" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemoradiation</GlossaryTermRef> therapy, chemotherapy alone, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
	  </ItemizedList><Para id="_141">Those who have had treatment that   saves the sphincter muscles may receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> exams every 3 months for the first 2 years, including  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectal exams</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>,  as needed to check  for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrence</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_322">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258179#_55" url="/types/anal/patient/anal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_140_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043438">stage IV anal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IV Anal Cancer</Title><Para id="_107">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046656" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IV anal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_108" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative</GlossaryTermRef> surgery to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
	  <ListItem>palliative <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
	  <ListItem>palliative chemotherapy with or without radiation therapy</ListItem> 
	  </ItemizedList><Para id="_323">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258179#_55" url="/types/anal/patient/anal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_106_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_309"><Title>Treatment of HIV and Anal Cancer</Title><Para id="_310">In general, treatment for people who have anal cancer and  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HIV</GlossaryTermRef> is similar   to treatment for other people, and these patients have similar outcomes. However, this treatment can further damage the weakened <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune systems</GlossaryTermRef> of people who have HIV. Treatment for people  with a history of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">AIDS</GlossaryTermRef>-related complications may require lower doses of anticancer drugs and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> than doses used for patients who do not have HIV.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_110"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043482">recurrent anal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Anal Cancer</Title><Para id="_111">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> anal cancer  may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_112" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and chemotherapy, for recurrence after surgery</ListItem><ListItem>surgery, for recurrence after radiation therapy and/or chemotherapy</ListItem>
	  
	  
	  
	  
	  </ItemizedList><Para id="_324">Learn more about these treatments  in  the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258179#_55" url="/types/anal/patient/anal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_110_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_165"><Title>To Learn More About Anal Cancer</Title><Para id="_166">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  anal cancer, visit the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/anal">Anal Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_165_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_165_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of anal cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Anal Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/anal/patient/anal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/anal/patient/anal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389368]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062898"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
