<Summary id="CDR0000269124" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Anxiety and distress are some of the many different emotions that patients may experience throughout their cancer illness, treatment, and beyond. Get detailed information about emotional and psychological distress, anxiety, and coping skills in this expert-reviewed information summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-pdq">Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-hp-pdq">Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000257623">adjustment disorder</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000042479">anxiety disorder</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_296">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about normal adjustment issues, and the pathophysiology and treatment of psychosocial distress and the adjustment disorders. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_297">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adjustment disorder</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>anxiety disorder</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_228"><Title>Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_167"><KeyPoint id="_168">People with cancer  have different levels of distress.</KeyPoint><Para id="_169">Some people with cancer have a low level of distress, and others have higher levels of distress. The level of distress ranges from being able to adjust to living with cancer to having a serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mental health</GlossaryTermRef> disorder, such as major depression.</Para><Para id="_313">This summary describes the milder levels of distress in adults with cancer, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_170" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Normal adjustment: A condition in which a person makes changes in his or her life to manage a stressful event such as a cancer diagnosis. In normal adjustment, a person learns to  cope well with emotional distress and solve  problems related to cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Psychological</GlossaryTermRef> and social distress: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> in which a person has some trouble making changes in their life to manage a stressful event such as a cancer diagnosis. The feelings of distress may range from normal feelings of vulnerability and sadness to feelings that affect quality of life, such as depression, panic, and spiritual crisis. Help from a professional to learn new <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coping skills</GlossaryTermRef> may be needed.</ListItem>                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adjustment disorder</GlossaryTermRef>: A condition in which a person has a lot of trouble making changes in his or her life to manage a stressful event such as a cancer diagnosis. Symptoms such as depression, anxiety, or other emotional, social, or behavioral problems occur and worsen the person's quality of life. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Medicine</GlossaryTermRef> and counseling to manage these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be needed.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797031" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Anxiety disorder</GlossaryTermRef>: A condition in which a person has severe anxiety. It may be caused by  a stressful event like a cancer diagnosis, or the cause may be unknown. Symptoms of anxiety disorder include extreme worry, fear, and dread. When the symptoms are severe, it affects a person's ability to lead a normal life. There are many types of anxiety disorders, including: 

 <ItemizedList id="_295" Style="dash"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476551" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Generalized anxiety disorder</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Panic disorder</GlossaryTermRef> (a condition that causes sudden feelings of panic).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750803" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Agoraphobia</GlossaryTermRef> (fear of open places or situations in which it might be hard to get help if needed).</ListItem><ListItem>Social anxiety disorder (fear of social situations).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454806" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Phobia</GlossaryTermRef> (fear of a specific object or situation).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Obsessive-compulsive disorder</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440112" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Post-traumatic stress disorder</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_287"><KeyPoint id="_288">There are certain risk factors for high levels of distress in people with cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_283"> Nearly half of people with cancer report having a lot of distress. In general, the type of cancer does not make a difference in the amount of distress reported. Factors that increase the risk of anxiety and distress are not always related to the cancer.</Para><Para id="_314"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> for high levels of distress in people with cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_291" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Trouble doing the usual <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430401" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">activities of daily living</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Physical problems and side effects of treatment (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, nausea, or pain).</ListItem><ListItem>Problems at home.</ListItem><ListItem>Unmet social and spiritual needs.</ListItem><ListItem>Depression, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000770485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer-related post-traumatic stress</GlossaryTermRef>, or other emotional problems.</ListItem><ListItem>Being diagnosed with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced-stage cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Having experienced childhood abuse.</ListItem><ListItem>Being younger, female, or non-White.</ListItem><ListItem>Having a lower level of education.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_298">People who have a high level of distress when they are diagnosed with cancer are more likely to have continued high levels of distress after their diagnosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_281"><KeyPoint id="_282">Your doctor will screen you to find out if you need help adjusting to cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_292">Screening is usually  done by asking about how you feel, your energy level, relationships, work, and finances. Your doctor may refer you to a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef>, mental health
professional, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative care</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">specialist</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454705" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pastoral counselor</GlossaryTermRef> for further evaluation and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_294"><Para id="_285">For information on depression and post-traumatic stress related to cancer, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_286" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062806" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">Depression</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062831" url="/about-cancer/coping/survivorship/new-normal/ptsd-pdq">Cancer-Related Post-Traumatic  Stress</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Normal Adjustment</Title><SummarySection id="_230"><KeyPoint id="_231">Each person will cope in different ways.</KeyPoint><Para id="_316">The way people with cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cope</GlossaryTermRef> is usually linked to their personality traits (such as whether they usually expect the best versus the worst, or if they are shy versus outgoing).</Para><Para id="_232">You may find it easier to adjust if you carry on with  your usual routine and work, and keep doing activities that matter  to you. People who adjust well to coping with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> continue to find meaning and importance in their lives. People who do not adjust well may withdraw from relationships or situations and feel hopeless.</Para><Para id="_317">If you are having trouble coping with cancer you may find it helpful to talk with a professional about your concerns and worries.  These <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">specialists</GlossaryTermRef> include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_318" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mental health</GlossaryTermRef> professionals, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologists</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychiatrists</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Social workers</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Palliative care</GlossaryTermRef> specialists.</ListItem><ListItem>Religious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688836" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counselors</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_253"><KeyPoint id="_254">People who are adjusting to the changes  caused by cancer may have distress.</KeyPoint><Para id="_255"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Distress</GlossaryTermRef> can occur when you feel you are unable to manage or control changes caused by cancer.    People with the same <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> or treatment can have different levels of distress. People have less  distress when they feel the demands of the diagnosis and treatment are low or the amount of support they get is  high. For example,  a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care professional</GlossaryTermRef> can help the person adjust to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> by giving <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_244"><KeyPoint id="_245">People with cancer  need different coping skills  at different points in time.</KeyPoint><Para id="_333">Living with a diagnosis of cancer involves many life adjustments. Normal adjustment involves learning to cope with emotional distress and solve problems caused by having cancer.</Para><Para id="_334">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coping skills</GlossaryTermRef> needed will change at different points in your cancer journey, such as when you:</Para><ItemizedList id="_335" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Hear the diagnosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Receive cancer treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Finish cancer treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Learn that the cancer is in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Learn that the cancer has come back.</ListItem><ListItem>Decide to stop cancer treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Become a cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivor</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_75"><KeyPoint id="_76">Hearing the diagnosis</KeyPoint><Para id="_77">The process of adjusting to cancer begins before people hear the                                                                      diagnosis.  You may feel worried and afraid when you have unexplained <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> or are having tests done to find out if you have cancer.</Para><Para id="_299">A diagnosis of cancer can cause people to have more distress when their fears become true. It may be difficult for people to understand what the doctors are telling them  during this time. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000630144" url="/about-cancer/coping/adjusting-to-cancer/communication-pdq">Communication in Cancer Care</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_300">Additional  help from health professionals for problems such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, trouble sleeping,  and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef> may be needed during this time.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_95"><KeyPoint id="_96">Being treated for cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_301">As people go through cancer treatment, they use coping skills (also known as coping strategies) to  adjust to the stress of treatment.</Para><Para id="_319">Adjusting to cancer treatment might involve coping skills that help the person change their thoughts or behaviors. For example, changing a daily  routine or work schedule to manage the side effects of cancer treatment is a coping skill.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_98"><KeyPoint id="_99">Remission after treatment</KeyPoint><Para id="_100">People will be glad when treatment has ended but may feel increased anxiety as  they see their treatment team less often.  Other concerns include returning to work and family life and being worried about any change in their health.</Para><Para id="_186">During remission, people may become distressed before <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> medical visits because they  worry that the cancer has come back. Waiting for test results can be very  stressful.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_303"><KeyPoint id="_304">Learning that the cancer has come back</KeyPoint><Para id="_305">Cancer that comes back after treatment may cause an increase in distress from having:</Para><ItemizedList id="_321" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>A return of symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem>A sense of hopelessness.</ListItem><ListItem>A negative view of the cancer or caregiving.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_322">A person's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> may be improved if they are able to manage their cancer and have support from friends and family.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_105"><KeyPoint id="_106">Stopping cancer treatment</KeyPoint><Para id="_107">Sometimes cancer comes back or does not get better with treatment. The treatment plan then changes from one that is meant to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cure</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer to one that gives comfort and relieves symptoms. This may cause the person to have an increase in anxiety or depression. For more information, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062806" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">Depression</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062831" url="/about-cancer/coping/survivorship/new-normal/ptsd-pdq">Cancer-Related Post-Traumatic Stress</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_306">People who adjust to the return of cancer often keep up  hope in meaningful life activities. Some people look to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spirituality</GlossaryTermRef> or religious beliefs to help keep up their quality of life. For more information, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000301599" url="/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality/spirituality-pdq">Spirituality in Cancer Care</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_108"><KeyPoint id="_109">Becoming a long-term cancer survivor</KeyPoint><Para id="_110">People adjust to finishing cancer treatment and being long-term cancer survivors over many years.  Some common problems reported by cancer survivors as they face the future include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_189" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Feeling anxious that the cancer will come back.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling a loss of control.</ListItem><ListItem>Having anxiety and nausea in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454799" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>  to reminders  of chemotherapy  (such as smells or sights).</ListItem><ListItem>Having symptoms of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000770485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">post-traumatic stress</GlossaryTermRef>, such as being unable to stop thinking about cancer or its treatment or feeling alone or separate from others.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling tired all of the time.</ListItem><ListItem>Being concerned about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">body image</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476620" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sexuality</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_337">Regular exercise and individual or group <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counseling</GlossaryTermRef> may help improve these problems and  the person's quality of life.</Para><Para id="_190">Most people adjust well and some even say that surviving cancer has given them a greater appreciation for life, a better understanding of what is most important in their life, and stronger spiritual or religious beliefs.</Para><Para id="_266">Some people may have  more trouble adjusting because of   medical problems, fewer  friends and family members who give  support, money problems, or mental health problems not related to the cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_237"><Title>Psychological and Social Distress</Title><SummarySection id="_191"><KeyPoint id="_192">Feelings of physical, emotional, social,  or spiritual distress can make it hard to cope with cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_113">Almost all people living with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>   have  feelings of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>. Feelings of distress range from sadness and fears to more serious problems  such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454704" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">panic</GlossaryTermRef>, feeling uncertain about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef> beliefs, or feeling alone or separate from friends and family.</Para><Para id="_247">People who are in distress during any phase of cancer  need treatment and support. People are more likely to need to be checked and treated for distress:</Para><ItemizedList id="_194" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Soon after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>At the start of treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>At the end of  treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>During <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>If the cancer comes back.</ListItem><ListItem>If the goal of treatment changes from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curing</GlossaryTermRef> or controlling cancer to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_51"><KeyPoint id="_197">Different kinds of emotional and social support help with distress.</KeyPoint><Para id="_53">Studies have shown that people who are having trouble adjusting to cancer are helped by treatments that give them emotional and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440116" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social support</GlossaryTermRef>, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_54" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044723" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Relaxation training</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Counseling</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000457962" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">talk therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer education sessions.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Existential therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (focuses on the human condition, including what humans are capable of, as well as their limitations).</ListItem><ListItem>Social support in a group setting.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_201">Benefits from these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef> include  having lower levels of depression, anxiety, and cancer- and treatment-related symptoms, as well as  feeling more hopeful.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_56"><Title>Adjustment Disorders</Title><SummarySection id="_204"><KeyPoint id="_205">Adjustment disorders may cause serious problems in daily  life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_206">An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjustment disorder</GlossaryTermRef> occurs when a person's reaction to a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stressful</GlossaryTermRef> event:</Para><ItemizedList id="_257" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Is more severe than the expected amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Affects relationships or causes problems at home or work.</ListItem><ListItem>Includes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> or other emotional, social, or behavioral problems.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_207">Stressful events for people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>, treatment, cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrence</GlossaryTermRef>, and when <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> occur. People who have trouble <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coping</GlossaryTermRef> with these events may develop an adjustment disorder. An adjustment disorder usually begins within 3 months of a stressful event.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_209"><KeyPoint id="_210">Counseling and other activities can help people with adjustment disorders.</KeyPoint><Para id="_211">Individual (one-to-one) and group <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counseling</GlossaryTermRef> have been shown to help people with cancer who have adjustment disorders. Counseling may include treatment that focuses on the person's thoughts, feelings, and behaviors.</Para><Para id="_327">Other activities that may help  people cope include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_307" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044723" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Relaxation training</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cognitive behavior therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Problem-solving.</ListItem><ListItem>Support from friends and family.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Meditation</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000532135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Yoga</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689577" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Guided imagery</GlossaryTermRef> exercises.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044675" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hypnosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>	Positive thoughts about coping.</ListItem><ListItem>Breathing exercises.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><KeyPoint id="_213">Counseling may be combined with antianxiety or antidepressant medicine.</KeyPoint><Para id="_63">People who are having trouble adjusting to cancer should try counseling before <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef>. Counseling may not help everyone, and some people may have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mental health</GlossaryTermRef> disorder, such as severe anxiety or major depression. These people may need <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000486601" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antianxiety</GlossaryTermRef> or antidepressant medicine along with counseling.  Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062806" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">Depression</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_114"><Title>Anxiety Disorders</Title><SummarySection id="_115"><KeyPoint id="_239">Anxiety disorders are strong fears that may be caused by physical or psychological stress.</KeyPoint><Para id="_240">Studies show that almost half of all people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> say  they feel some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and about one-fourth of all people with cancer say they feel a great deal of anxiety.  A person may become more anxious as cancer
spreads or treatment becomes more aggressive.</Para><Para id="_241">  
For some people, anxiety may feel like it is more than they can handle and this may affect their cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_323">Symptoms of anxiety disorders include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_219" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Shortness of breath.</ListItem><ListItem>Fast heartbeat.</ListItem><ListItem>Sweating.</ListItem><ListItem>Restlessness.</ListItem><ListItem>Muscle tightness.</ListItem><ListItem>Fainting or dizziness.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nausea</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Irritability.</ListItem><ListItem>Fear that they are having a heart attack.</ListItem><ListItem>Fear that they are "going crazy."</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_242">People are more likely to have anxiety disorders during cancer treatment if they have:</Para><ItemizedList id="_243" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A history of an anxiety disorder.</ListItem><ListItem>A history of physical or emotional <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454807" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trauma</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Anxiety at the time of diagnosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Few family members or friends to give them support.</ListItem><ListItem>Severe pain or other physical symptoms that are not controlled well.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer that is not getting better with treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Trouble taking care of their personal needs such as bathing or eating.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_154"><KeyPoint id="_155">Anxiety disorders affect a person’s quality of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_220">An anxiety disorder diagnosis is based on how  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of anxiety affect  the person's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of  life</GlossaryTermRef>,  what kinds of symptoms began since the cancer diagnosis or treatment, when the symptoms occur, and how long they last.</Para><Para id="_248">Anxiety disorders can affect day-to-day life in many ways, such as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_249" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Feeling worried all the time.</ListItem><ListItem>Not being able to learn new information.</ListItem><ListItem>Not being able to "turn off thoughts" most of the time.</ListItem><ListItem>Having trouble sleeping most nights.</ListItem><ListItem>Crying frequently.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling afraid most of the time.</ListItem><ListItem>Having  symptoms such as fast heartbeat, dry mouth, shaky hands, restlessness, or feeling on edge.</ListItem><ListItem>Having anxiety that is not relieved by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044663" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distraction</GlossaryTermRef> by staying busy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_215"><KeyPoint id="_216">There are different causes of anxiety disorders in people with cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_217">In addition to anxiety caused by a cancer diagnosis, other causes of anxiety disorder in people with cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_218" Style="bullet">  <ListItem><Strong>Pain</Strong>:  People with uncontrolled pain  feel anxious, and
anxiety can increase pain.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Other medical problems</Strong>: <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Sepsis</GlossaryTermRef>, a low <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> level, heart failure, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044338" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electrolyte</GlossaryTermRef> imbalances can also cause anxiety. Anxiety  may be a warning sign of a change in  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> (such as low <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658770" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood sugar</GlossaryTermRef>), a    heart attack, severe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pneumonia</GlossaryTermRef>, or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clot</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Certain types of tumors</Strong>: Certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adrenal gland</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pituitary gland</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046036" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef> can cause symptoms of anxiety and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454704" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">panic</GlossaryTermRef> attacks. Tumors that have spread to the brain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>
and tumors in the lungs can    also cause symptoms of anxiety.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Taking certain drugs</Strong>: Certain types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">corticosteroids</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000533434" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroxine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476099" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bronchodilators</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468794" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antihistamines</GlossaryTermRef>,  can cause restlessness, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462659" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">agitation</GlossaryTermRef>,  or anxiety.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Withdrawing from  habit-forming drugs</Strong>: Withdrawal from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef>,   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nicotine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045054" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">opioids</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antidepressants</GlossaryTermRef> can cause agitation or anxiety.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_223">Anxiety from these causes is usually managed by treating the cause of the anxiety.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_221"><KeyPoint id="_222">There are different types of anxiety disorders.</KeyPoint><Para id="_324">People who have intense fear, have trouble understanding information about their cancer, or are unable to cooperate with medical tests should be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screened</GlossaryTermRef> for the following types of anxiety disorders:</Para><ItemizedList id="_325" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454806" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Phobias</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>. Phobias are  fears about a situation or an object that lasts over time.  People
with phobias usually feel intense anxiety and avoid the situation or object they are afraid of.    Phobias may make it hard for people to follow through with tests and procedures or treatment. For example, people with a phobia of needle sticks may avoid having blood drawn for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory tests</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Panic disorder</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>. People with a panic disorder feel sudden intense anxiety, known as panic attacks. A panic attack usually lasts for 10 to 20 minutes, but the fear of having another panic attack may cause feelings of discomfort to continue for longer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476551" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Generalized anxiety disorder</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>. People with a generalized anxiety disorder may feel extreme and constant anxiety or worry. A person who has generalized anxiety may feel irritable, restless, or dizzy, have tense muscles, shortness of breath, a fast heartbeat, sweating, or get tired quickly.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Obsessive-compulsive disorder</GlossaryTermRef> (OCD)</Strong>. OCD is diagnosed when a person uses persistent (obsessive) thoughts, ideas, or images and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compulsions</GlossaryTermRef> (intentional repeated behaviors) to manage feelings of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>. The obsessions and compulsions affect the person's ability to function at work, school, or in social situations. Examples of compulsions include frequent hand washing or door checking to make sure it is locked.<Para id="_326">People with cancer who have OCD  may be unable to follow through with treatment because of persistent thoughts and behaviors. They  may also have obsessive thoughts about their cancer coming back. OCD is rare in people with cancer who did not have an anxiety disorder before being diagnosed with cancer.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Health anxiety disorder</Strong>. Cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> may develop health anxiety disorder related to their fears about their cancer coming back. This may include being highly alert to any possible physical symptoms, extreme focus on their cancer status, and requesting medical tests and visits with their doctor more often or earlier than needed.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440112" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Post-traumatic stress disorder</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>. Post-traumatic stress can come from feelings of shock, fear, helplessness, and horror at the time of cancer diagnosis. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062831" url="/about-cancer/coping/survivorship/new-normal/ptsd-pdq">Cancer-Related Post-Traumatic  Stress</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_328"><KeyPoint id="_329">There are different kinds of treatment for anxiety disorders.</KeyPoint><Para id="_330">People with anxiety disorders need   information and
support  to understand their cancer and treatment choices.   Some helpful <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef> treatments may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_331" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Individual (one-to-one) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counseling</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Couple and family counseling.</ListItem><ListItem>Crisis counseling.</ListItem><ListItem>Group <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Self-help groups.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cognitive behavior therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044723" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Relaxation training</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044675" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypnosis</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meditation</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689577" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">guided imagery</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044647" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biofeedback</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_332">Using different methods together may be helpful for some people. For more information, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269124#_237" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-pdq">Psychological and Social Distress</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_161"><KeyPoint id="_162">Medicine may be used alone or combined with other types of treatment for  anxiety disorders.</KeyPoint><Para id="_163"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000486601" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Antianxiety medicines</GlossaryTermRef> may be used alone or combined with other psychological  therapies. These medicines relieve symptoms of anxiety, such as feelings of fear, dread, uneasiness, and muscle tightness. They may relieve daytime distress and lessen trouble sleeping.</Para><Para id="_164">Studies show that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antidepressants</GlossaryTermRef> are useful in treating anxiety disorders. Children and teenagers being treated with antidepressants have an increased risk of thinking about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">suicide</GlossaryTermRef> and must be watched closely. For more information, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062806#_8" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">Treatment</SummaryRef> section in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062806" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">Depression</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_336"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000257623">adjustment disorder</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042479">anxiety disorder</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_336_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about normal adjustment issues, and the pathophysiology and treatment of psychosocial distress and the adjustment disorders.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Adjustment to Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389325]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062891"/><DateFirstPublished>2002-11-24</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-14</DateLastModified></Summary>
