<Summary id="CDR0000269299" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062693"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatment for malignant mesothelioma may include surgery, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy, as well as targeted therapy and immunotherapy. The type of treatment you receive depends on many factors, including where the cancer is found and at what stage. Find out about treatment options for malignant mesothelioma.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/patient/mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Malignant Mesothelioma (PDQ®): Treatment </SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/hp/mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Malignant Mesothelioma (PDQ®): Treatment </SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038142">malignant mesothelioma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_217">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult malignant mesothelioma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_218">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>malignant mesothelioma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Malignant Mesothelioma Treatment  (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Malignant Mesothelioma Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Malignant Mesothelioma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Malignant Mesothelioma</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Malignant mesothelioma is a type of cancer that forms in
		  the thin layer of tissue that covers organs in the chest or abdomen.</KeyPoint><Para id="_381">Malignant mesothelioma may be found in one or more of the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_382" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the pleura,  a thin layer of tissue that lines the chest cavity and covers the lungs </ListItem><ListItem>the peritoneum, a thin layer of tissue that lines the abdomen and covers most of the organs in the abdomen </ListItem><ListItem>the pericardium,  a thin layer of tissue that surrounds the heart </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_383">Malignant mesothelioma may also form in the heart or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046611" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testicles</GlossaryTermRef>, but this is rare.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000770045" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows parts of the body where malignant mesothelioma may form, including the pleura (the tissue that lines the chest cavity and covers the lungs), the pericardium (the tissue that surrounds the heart), the peritoneum (the tissue that lines the abdomen and covers most of the organs in the abdomen), and the testicles. The heart and lungs are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_211"><Caption language="en">Malignant mesothelioma forms in the tissue that lines the chest or abdomen, including the pleura (the tissue that lines the chest cavity and covers the lungs) and the peritoneum (the tissue that lines the abdomen and covers most of the organs in the abdomen). Malignant mesothelioma may also form in the pericardium (the tissue that surrounds the heart) or the testicles, but this is rare.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_8">Being exposed to asbestos can increase the risk of malignant mesothelioma. </KeyPoint><Para id="_384">Malignant mesothelioma is caused by certain changes to the way the cells that line the organs function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of the cell change is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_385">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Most people with malignant mesothelioma have worked or lived in places where they <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhaled</GlossaryTermRef> or swallowed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046528" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">asbestos</GlossaryTermRef>, which has been used in the building and textile industries. After being exposed to asbestos, it usually takes a long time for malignant mesothelioma to form.  Living with a person who works near asbestos is also a risk factor for malignant mesothelioma. Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop malignant mesothelioma. And it can develop in some people who don't have any known risk factors.</Para><Para id="_155">Talk to your doctor if you think you may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_16">Signs and symptoms of malignant mesothelioma include shortness of breath and pain under the rib cage. </KeyPoint><Para id="_17">Sometimes the cancer causes fluid to collect in the chest or in the abdomen. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by the fluid, malignant mesothelioma, or other conditions.  Check with your doctor if you have any of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		  <ListItem>trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>cough</ListItem><ListItem>pain under the rib cage</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>pain or swelling in the abdomen</ListItem> 
		   
		<ListItem>lumps in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem> problems with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clots</GlossaryTermRef> (clots form when they shouldn't)</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>fatigue (feeling very tired)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Tests that examine the inside of the chest and abdomen are used to diagnose malignant mesothelioma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_21">Sometimes it is hard to tell the difference between malignant mesothelioma in the chest and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. If you have symptoms that suggest mesothelioma, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or to another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often you have been having them. They will also ask about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If you are diagnosed with mesothelioma, the results of these tests will help you and your doctor plan treatment. </Para><Para id="_386">The tests and procedures used to diagnose mesothelioma may include:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet">
			 <ListItem> <Strong>Chest x-ray</Strong> is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000428438" type="image/jpeg" alt="Chest x-ray; drawing shows a patient standing with their back to the x-ray machine. X-rays pass through the patient's body onto film or a computer and take pictures of the structures and organs inside the chest." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_145"><Caption language="en">A chest x-ray is used to take pictures of the structures and organs inside the chest. X-rays pass through the patient's body onto film or a computer.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Biopsy</Strong> is the removal of cells or tissues from the pleura or peritoneum so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for signs of cancer. <Para id="_198">Procedures used to collect the cells or tissues include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_140" Style="dash"><ListItem><Strong>Fine-needle (FNA) aspiration biopsy of the lung</Strong> uses a thin needle to remove tissue or fluid. An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045720" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging procedure</GlossaryTermRef> is used to locate the abnormal tissue or fluid in the lung. A small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> may be made in the skin where the biopsy needle is inserted into the abnormal tissue or fluid, and a sample is removed.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000531057" type="image/jpeg" alt="Fine-needle aspiration biopsy of the lung; drawing shows a patient lying on a table that slides through the computed tomography (CT) machine with an x-ray picture of a cross-section of the lung on a monitor above the patient. Drawing also shows a doctor using the x-ray picture to help place the biopsy needle through the chest wall and into the area of abnormal lung tissue. Inset shows a side view of the chest cavity and lungs with the biopsy needle inserted into the area of abnormal tissue." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_148"><Caption language="en">Fine-needle aspiration biopsy of the lung. The patient lies on a table that slides through the computed tomography (CT) machine, which takes x-ray pictures of the inside of the body. The x-ray pictures help the doctor see where the abnormal tissue is in the lung. A biopsy needle is inserted through the chest wall and into the area of abnormal lung tissue. A small piece of tissue is removed through the needle and checked under the microscope for signs of cancer. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Thoracoscopy</Strong> is surgery to look at the organs inside the chest to check for abnormal areas. An incision (cut) is made between two ribs, and a thoracoscope (a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing) is inserted into the chest.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Thoracotomy</Strong> is surgery to look inside the chest. An incision (cut) is made between two ribs to check inside the chest for signs of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Peritoneoscopy</Strong> is surgery to look inside the abdomen. An incision (cut) is made in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> wall, and a peritoneoscope (a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing) is inserted into the abdomen to check for signs of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335492" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Open biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is surgery to remove abnormal tissues so a pathologist can check it under a microscope for signs of disease.  An incision (cut) is made through the skin to expose and remove the tissues. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_201">The following tests may be done on the cells and tissue samples that are taken:</Para><ItemizedList id="_200" Style="dash"><ListItem>A <Strong>cytologic exam</Strong> is a laboratory test to view cells under a microscope to check for anything abnormal.  For mesothelioma, fluid is taken from the chest or the abdomen.  A pathologist checks  the fluid for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Immunohistochemistry</Strong> is a laboratory test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient's tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Electron microscopy</Strong> is a laboratory test in which cells in a sample of tissue are viewed under a high-powered microscope to look for certain changes in the cells. An electron microscope  shows tiny details better than  other types of microscopes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem>
			 
			 
			 
			 
			 </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_387"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_392">After malignant mesothelioma has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread to other parts of the body. </KeyPoint><Para id="_388">The process used to find out if cancer has spread outside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045842" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pleura</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef> is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. The information  gathered from the
staging process determines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease. It is important to know whether the cancer has spread in order to plan treatment. </Para><Para id="_389">The following tests and procedures may be used in the staging process:</Para><ItemizedList id="_390" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest and abdomen. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong> uses a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive sugar</GlossaryTermRef> that is injected into a vein.  The PET scanner rotates around the body to make detailed, computerized pictures of areas inside the body where the glucose is taken up. Because cancer cells often take up more glucose than normal cells, the pictures can be used to find cancer cells in the body.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong> uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046602" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient"/>Endoscopic ultrasound (EUS)</Strong> is a procedure in which an endoscope is inserted into the body. An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. A probe at the end of the endoscope is used to bounce high-energy sound waves (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef>) off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. This procedure is also called endosonography. EUS may be used to guide <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fine-needle aspiration (FNA) biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> of the lung, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, or other areas. 
<MediaLink ref="CDR0000466552" type="image/jpeg" alt="Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration biopsy; drawing shows an endoscope with an ultrasound probe and biopsy needle inserted through the mouth and into the esophagus. Also shown are the lymph nodes near the esophagus and cancer in one lung. An inset shows the ultrasound probe locating the lymph nodes with cancer and the biopsy needle removing tissue from one of the lymph nodes near the esophagus." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_391"><Caption language="en">Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration biopsy. An endoscope that has an ultrasound probe and a biopsy needle is inserted through the mouth and into the esophagus. The probe bounces sound waves off body tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture) of the lymph nodes near the esophagus. The sonogram helps the doctor see where to place the biopsy needle to remove tissue from the lymph nodes.  This tissue is checked under a microscope for signs of cancer. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Laparoscopy</Strong> is surgery to look at the organs inside the abdomen to check for signs of disease. Small incisions (cuts) are made in the wall of the abdomen, and a laparoscope (a thin, lighted tube) is inserted into one of the incisions. Other instruments may be inserted through the same or other incisions to perform procedures such as taking tissue samples to be checked under a microscope for signs of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of all or part of a lymph node. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the lymph node tissue under a microscope to check for cancer cells.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046287" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mediastinoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is surgery to look at the organs, tissues, and lymph nodes between the lungs for abnormal areas.  An incision (cut) is made at the top of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000549425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breastbone</GlossaryTermRef>, and a mediastinoscope is inserted into the chest.  A mediastinoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue or lymph node samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_650"><KeyPoint id="_648">Some people decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_649">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_645">Learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_135">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_136">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on: </Para><ItemizedList id="_137" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer </ListItem><ListItem>the size of the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor can be removed completely by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>the amount of fluid in the chest or abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>the patient's age</ListItem><ListItem>the patient's activity level</ListItem><ListItem>the patient's general health, including lung and heart health</ListItem>
    
    <ListItem>the type of mesothelioma cells and how they look under a microscope</ListItem><ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> and how much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemoglobin</GlossaryTermRef> is in the blood</ListItem><ListItem>whether the patient is male or female</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back)</ListItem>
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Stages of Malignant Mesothelioma</Title><SummarySection id="_31"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_651">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_393">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of mesothelioma to plan the best treatment.</Para><Para id="_394">There are several staging systems for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. Malignant mesothelioma staging usually uses the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. The cancer may be described by this staging system in your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to your cancer. When talking to you about your diagnosis, your doctor may describe the cancer as one of these stages.</Para><Para id="_395">Learn about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269299#_387" url="/types/mesothelioma/patient/mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">tests to stage mesothelioma</SummaryRef>. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_310"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_166">The following stages are used for malignant mesothelioma of the lung:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_167"><KeyPoint id="_168">Stage I (also called stage 1) malignant mesothelioma</KeyPoint><Para id="_169"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage I</GlossaryTermRef> is divided into stages IA and IB:</Para><ItemizedList id="_231" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In stage IA, cancer is found in the inside lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chest wall</GlossaryTermRef> on one side of the chest. On the same side of the chest, cancer may also be found in one or more of the following:<ItemizedList id="_232" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the thin layer of tissue that covers the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the thin layer of tissue that covers the organs between the lungs</ListItem><ListItem>the thin layer of tissue that covers the top of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diaphragm</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IB, cancer is found in the inside lining of the chest wall, and in each of the thin layers of tissue that cover the lung, the organs between the lungs, and the top of the diaphragm on one side of the chest. On the same side of the chest, cancer has also spread into one or more of the following:<ItemizedList id="_233" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>diaphragm</ListItem><ListItem>lung tissue</ListItem><ListItem>tissue between the ribs and the inside lining of the chest wall</ListItem><ListItem>fat in the area between the lungs</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissues</GlossaryTermRef> of the chest wall</ListItem><ListItem>sac around the heart</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_171"><KeyPoint id="_172">Stage II (also called stage 2) malignant mesothelioma</KeyPoint><Para id="_234">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046727" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II</GlossaryTermRef>, cancer is found in the inside lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chest wall</GlossaryTermRef> on one side of the chest. On the same side of the chest, cancer may also be found in one or more of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_235" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the thin layer of tissue that covers the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the thin layer of tissue that covers the organs between the lungs</ListItem><ListItem>the thin layer of tissue that covers the top of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diaphragm</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_236">Cancer has spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> along the center of the chest on the same side of the chest as the tumor.</Para><Para id="_237"><Emphasis><Strong>or</Strong></Emphasis></Para><Para id="_238">Cancer is found in the inside lining of the chest wall, and in each of the thin layers of tissue that cover the lung, the organs between the lungs, and the top of the diaphragm on one side of the chest. On the same side of the chest, cancer has also spread into one or both of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_239" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>diaphragm</ListItem><ListItem>lung tissue</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_240">Cancer has spread to lymph nodes along the center of the chest on the same side of the chest as the tumor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_174"><KeyPoint id="_175">Stage III (also called stage 3) malignant mesothelioma</KeyPoint><Para id="_241"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046728" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage III</GlossaryTermRef> is divided into stages IIIA and IIIB.</Para><ItemizedList id="_242" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>In stage IIIA, cancer is found in the inside lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chest wall</GlossaryTermRef>, and in each of the thin layers of tissue that cover the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, the organs between the lungs, and the top of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diaphragm</GlossaryTermRef> on one side of the chest. On the same side of the chest, cancer has also spread into one or more of the following:<ItemizedList id="_243" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>tissue between the ribs and the inside lining of the chest wall</ListItem><ListItem>fat in the area between the lungs</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissues</GlossaryTermRef> of the chest wall</ListItem><ListItem>sac around the heart</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_244">Cancer has spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> along the center of the chest on the same side of the chest as the tumor.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIB, cancer is found in the inside lining of the chest wall, and may also be found in the thin layers of tissue that cover the lung, the organs between the lungs, and/or the top of the diaphragm on one side of the chest. On the same side of the chest, cancer may have also spread into one or more of the following:<ItemizedList id="_245" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>diaphragm</ListItem><ListItem>lung tissue</ListItem><ListItem>tissue between the ribs and the inside lining of the chest wall</ListItem><ListItem>fat in the area between the lungs</ListItem><ListItem>soft tissues of the chest wall</ListItem><ListItem>sac around the heart</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_246">Cancer has spread to lymph nodes above the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collarbone</GlossaryTermRef> on either side of the chest or cancer has spread to lymph nodes along the center of the chest on the opposite side of the chest as the tumor.</Para><Para id="_247"><Strong><Emphasis>or</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_248">Cancer is found in the inside lining of the chest wall, and in each of the thin layers of tissue that cover the lung, the organs between the lungs, and the top of the diaphragm on one side of the chest. Cancer has also spread to one or more of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_249" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the chest wall and may be found in the rib</ListItem><ListItem>through the diaphragm into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the tissue lining the chest on the opposite side of the body as the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>the organs in the area between the lungs (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046616" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thymus</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>through the sac around the heart or into the heart muscle</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_250">Cancer may have spread to lymph nodes.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_180"><KeyPoint id="_181">Stage IV (also called stage 4) malignant mesothelioma</KeyPoint><Para id="_251">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IV</GlossaryTermRef>, cancer has spread to the tissue covering the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> or the lung on the opposite side of the chest, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef>, bones, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> outside the chest, or to other parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_653">Stage IV malignant mesothelioma is also called metastatic mesothelioma. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. For example, if malignant mesothelioma spreads to the liver, the cancer cells in the liver are actually malignant mesothelioma cells. The disease is called metastatic mesothelioma, not liver cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_252"><KeyPoint id="_253">Malignant mesothelioma can recur (come back) after it has been treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_254">Recurrent malignant mesothelioma is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. If mesothelioma comes back, it may come back in the chest or in other parts of the body, such as the liver, lungs, or both. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned. The type of treatment for recurrent mesothelioma will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_396">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_51"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_52">There are different types of treatment for  patients with malignant mesothelioma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_53">Different types of treatments are available for  malignant mesothelioma. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the stage of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment. </Para><Para id="_397">Talking with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You’ll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you’ll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Treatment</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_60">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_61"><KeyPoint id="_62">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_63"> The following surgical treatments may be used for malignant mesothelioma in the chest:</Para><ItemizedList id="_113" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Wide local excision is surgery to remove the cancer and some of the healthy tissue around it.  The amount of healthy tissue removed depends on how deep or how large the tumor being removed is.</ListItem><ListItem>Pleurectomy and decortication is surgery to remove part of the covering of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef> and lining of the chest and part of the outside surface of the lungs.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367446" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Extrapleural pneumonectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is surgery to remove one whole lung and part of the lining of the chest, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diaphragm</GlossaryTermRef>, and the lining of the sac around the heart.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044294" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pleurodesis</GlossaryTermRef> is surgery that uses chemicals or drugs  to make a scar in the space between the layers of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045842" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pleura</GlossaryTermRef>. Fluid is first drained from the space using a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> or chest tube and the chemical or drug is put into the space. The scarring stops the build-up of fluid in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pleural cavity</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_64">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some people may receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after the surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><KeyPoint id="_66">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_67">Radiation therapy uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. It may also be used as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative care</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve symptoms and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_68"><KeyPoint id="_69">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_70">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.  Combination chemotherapy  is the use of more than one anticancer drug.</Para><Para id="_398"><Strong>Systemic chemotherapy</Strong> is when chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body.</Para><Para id="_399"><Strong>Regional chemotherapy</Strong> is when chemotherapy is placed directly into an organ or a body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef>, such as the chest or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef>. When given this way, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809547" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (HIPEC) is a type of regional chemotherapy used to treat  malignant mesothelioma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_400" Style="bullet"><ListItem>HIPEC may be used to treat mesothelioma that has spread to the peritoneum (tissue that lines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> and covers most of the organs in the abdomen). After the surgeon removes all the cancer that can be seen, a  solution containing anticancer drugs is heated and pumped into and out of the abdomen to kill cancer cells that remain. Heating the anticancer drugs may kill more cancer cells. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_204">The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the type and stage of the cancer being treated.</Para><Para id="_401">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_184">Visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/mesothelioma">Drugs Approved for Malignant  Mesothelioma</ExternalRef> for  more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_375"><KeyPoint id="_376">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_402">Immunotherapy helps a person's immune system fight cancer. Your doctor may suggest biomarker tests to help predict your response to certain immunotherapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_403">Immunotherapy drugs used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced</GlossaryTermRef> mesothelioma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_652" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000698294" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ipilimumab">ipilimumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_654">Other immunotherapy drugs, such as <DrugRef href="CDR0000788795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/durvalumab">durvalumab</DrugRef>, are being studied in malignant mesothelioma.</Para><Para id="_406">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_221"><KeyPoint id="_222">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_407">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. <DrugRef href="CDR0000487564" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/bevacizumab">Bevacizumab</DrugRef> is a targeted therapy drug used to treat malignant mesothelioma.</Para><Para id="_409">Other targeted therapies, such as <DrugRef href="CDR0000760376" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ramucirumab">ramucirumab</DrugRef>, are being studied in malignant mesothelioma.</Para><Para id="_410">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_83"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_84">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials. </KeyPoint><Para id="_422">Joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with mesothelioma. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using existing treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment. 

 

</Para><Para id="_423">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting participants. This search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. 

Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_424">Learn more about clinical trials at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_227"><KeyPoint id="_228">Treatment for malignant mesothelioma may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_227_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_163"><KeyPoint id="_164">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_163_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_163_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_255"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038143">localized malignant mesothelioma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Localized Malignant Mesothelioma (Stage I)</Title><Para id="_95">If <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I malignant mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef> is  in  one part of the chest lining, treatment may include surgery to remove the cancer and  the tissue around it.</Para><Para id="_420">Treatment of stage I <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intracavitary</GlossaryTermRef> mesothelioma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_421" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a surgery called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367446" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extrapleural pneumonectomy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>palliative surgery with pleurectomy and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044275" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">decortication</GlossaryTermRef>, which may be followed by radiation therapy, to relieve symptoms and improve quality of life</ListItem><ListItem>palliative radiation therapy to relieve symptoms and improve quality of life</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_419">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269299#_59" url="/types/mesothelioma/patient/mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_255_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_256"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038149">advanced malignant mesothelioma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Advanced Malignant Mesothelioma (Stages II, III, and IV)  </Title><Para id="_99">If <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046727" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046728" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IV</GlossaryTermRef> malignant mesothelioma is found in the chest, treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_100" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>immunotherapy (<DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef> and <DrugRef href="CDR0000698294" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ipilimumab">ipilimumab</DrugRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>combination chemotherapy with or without targeted therapy (<DrugRef href="CDR0000487564" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/bevacizumab">bevacizumab</DrugRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>combination chemotherapy and palliative care, which may be followed by maintenance chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative care</GlossaryTermRef>, which may include draining fluid from the chest, a procedure to prevent fluid from collecting in the chest (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044294" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pleurodesis</GlossaryTermRef>), surgery, or radiation therapy, to relieve symptoms and improve quality of life</ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy placed directly into the chest or abdominal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef>  to shrink the tumors and keep fluid from building up</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_208">If stage II, stage III, or stage IV malignant mesothelioma is found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef>, treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_209" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>surgery to remove the tumor followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809547" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_411">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269299#_59" url="/types/mesothelioma/patient/mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_256_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_257"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038160">recurrent malignant mesothelioma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Malignant Mesothelioma</Title><Para id="_412">When malignant mesothelioma recurs (comes back), the treatment strategy often involves options that weren’t used in the initial treatment. If you haven’t received systemic therapy before, treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_413" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>a combination of chemotherapy and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>immunotherapy alone</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_414">If you have received systemic therapy, treatment might include the following, given alone or in combination: </Para><ItemizedList id="_415" Style="bullet"><ListItem>chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>immunotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_417">For certain people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally recurrent cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, surgery to remove the affected part of the chest wall may be an option. </Para><Para id="_418">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269299#_59" url="/types/mesothelioma/patient/mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_257_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_149"><Title>To Learn More About Malignant Mesothelioma</Title><Para id="_150">For more  from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  malignant mesothelioma, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_151" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/">Malignant Mesothelioma Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/mesothelioma">Drugs Approved for Malignant  Mesothelioma</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/substances/asbestos/asbestos-fact-sheet">Asbestos Exposure and Cancer Risk</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_149_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_149_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult malignant mesothelioma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Malignant Mesothelioma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/patient/mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/patient/mesothelioma-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389166]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062895"/><DateFirstPublished>2005-04-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
