<Summary id="CDR0000269596"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Mistletoe, a semiparasitic plant that grows on several types of trees such as apple, oak, pine and elm, is commonly used in cancer patients in Europe. Read about laboratory and human studies of extracts, such as Iscador and Eurixor, and their effects on quality of life, survival and symptom relief in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">Mistletoe Extracts (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/mistletoe-pdq">Mistletoe Extracts (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041724">mistletoe extract</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_243">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of mistletoe extracts in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_244">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>mistletoe extract</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Mistletoe Extracts (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Mistletoe Extracts (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Mistletoe Extracts</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_2">This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summary provides an overview of the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mistletoe</GlossaryTermRef> as a treatment for people with cancer. The summary includes a brief history of mistletoe research, the results of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, and possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of mistletoe use.</Para><Para id="_3">This summary contains the following key information:</Para><ItemizedList id="_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Mistletoe is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044075" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">semiparasitic</GlossaryTermRef> plant that has been used for centuries to treat numerous human ailments.</ListItem><ListItem>Mistletoe is used commonly in Europe, where a variety of different extracts are manufactured and marketed as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injectable</GlossaryTermRef> prescription drugs. These  injectable drugs are not available commercially in the United States and are not approved as a  treatment for people with cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Mistletoe is one of the most widely studied CAM therapies for cancer. In certain European countries, the preparations made from European mistletoe (<ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName>, Loranthaceae) are among the most prescribed drugs offered to cancer patients.</ListItem><ListItem>Although mistletoe plants and berries are considered poisonous to humans, few serious side effects have been associated with mistletoe extract use.       </ListItem><ListItem>  
The use of mistletoe as a treatment for people with cancer has been investigated in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical studies</GlossaryTermRef>. Reports of improved survival and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> have been common, but many of the studies had major weaknesses that raise doubts about the reliability of the findings.</ListItem><ListItem>At present, the use of mistletoe cannot be recommended outside the context of well-designed clinical trials. Such trials will be valuable to determine more clearly whether mistletoe can be useful in the treatment of specific subsets of cancer patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_5">Many of the medical and scientific terms used in this summary are hypertext linked (at first use in each section) to the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>, which is oriented toward nonexperts. When a linked term is clicked, a definition will appear in a separate window. </Para><Para id="_6">Reference citations in some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> cancer information summaries may include links to external websites that are operated by individuals or organizations for the purpose of marketing or advocating the use of specific treatments or products. These reference citations are included for informational purposes only. Their inclusion should not be viewed as an endorsement of the content of the websites, or of any treatment or product,            by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_9"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mistletoe</GlossaryTermRef>, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044075" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">semiparasitic</GlossaryTermRef> plant, holds interest as a potential anticancer agent because <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> derived from it have been shown to kill <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis>    

<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> to down-regulate central <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> involved in tumor progression, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045771" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignancy</GlossaryTermRef>, and cell migration and invasion, such as TGF-beta and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">matrix-metalloproteinases</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>
 Mistletoe extracts have been shown to do the following:<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_273" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Enforce <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044062" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">natural killer cell</GlossaryTermRef>-mediated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> cell <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lysis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Reduce the migratory and invasive potential of tumor cells.</ListItem><ListItem>Stimulate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> cells both <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis>  and <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_274">Three components of mistletoe, namely <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044094" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">viscotoxins</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polysaccharides</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044051" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lectins</GlossaryTermRef>, may be responsible for these effects.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/>  Viscotoxins are small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef> that exhibit cell-killing activity and possible immune system–stimulating activity.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/> Lectins are complex <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef> made of both protein and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carbohydrates</GlossaryTermRef> that are capable of binding to the outside of cells (e.g., immune system cells) and inducing biochemical changes in them.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/>
<Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/></Para><Para id="_275">In view of mistletoe’s ability to stimulate the immune system, it has been classified as a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045616" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biological response modifier</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="42"/> Biological response modifiers constitute a diverse group of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biological</GlossaryTermRef> molecules that have been used individually, or in combination with other agents, to treat cancer or to lessen the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of anticancer drugs. Mistletoe extracts have been demonstrated in preclinical settings to have other mechanisms of action, such as antiangiogenesis.<Reference refidx="29"/></Para><Para id="_10">Preparations from mistletoe extracts are  most frequently used in the treatment of cancer patients in German-speaking countries.<Reference refidx="46"/>              Commercially available extracts are marketed under a variety of brand names, including Iscador (see explanation of suffixes below), Eurixor, Helixor, Isorel, Iscucin, Plenosol, and abnobaVISCUM. Some extracts are marketed under more than one name.  Iscador, Isorel, and Plenosol are also sold as Iscar, Vysorel, and Lektinol, respectively. All of these products are prepared from  <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> (Loranthaceae)  (<ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> L. or European mistletoe). They are not sold as a drug in the United States. Eurixor, Isorel, and Vysorel are no longer commercially available.</Para><Para id="_100">In addition to European mistletoe, extracts from a type of Korean mistletoe (<ScientificName>Viscum album </ScientificName>var. <ScientificName>coloratum</ScientificName> [Kom.] Ohwi) have demonstrated <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> and  <Emphasis>in vivo</Emphasis> cytotoxicity in laboratory studies.<Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/></Para><Para id="_11">Mistletoe grows on several types of trees, and the chemical composition of extracts derived from it depends on the following:<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/><Reference refidx="55"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_276" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Species of the host tree (e.g., apple, elm, oak, pine, poplar, and spruce).</ListItem><ListItem>Time of year harvested.</ListItem><ListItem>How the extracts are prepared.</ListItem><ListItem>The commercial producer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_12">Mistletoe extracts are prepared as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aqueous</GlossaryTermRef> solutions or solutions of water and alcohol, and they can be fermented or unfermented.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="56"/><Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="59"/> Some extracts are prepared according to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">homeopathic</GlossaryTermRef> principles, and others are not. Accordingly, as homeopathic preparations, they are typically not chemically standardized extracts.<Reference refidx="10"/> <Reference refidx="60"/> In addition, the commercial products can be subdivided according to the species of host tree, which is typically indicated in the product name by a suffix letter.  Iscador, a fermented aqueous extract of <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> L. that is prepared as a homeopathic drug, is marketed as one of the following:<Reference refidx="57"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_277" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>IscadorM (from apple trees; <ScientificName>Malus domestica</ScientificName>).</ListItem><ListItem>IscadorP (from pine trees; <ScientificName>Pinus sylvestris</ScientificName>).</ListItem><ListItem>IscadorQu (from oak trees; <ScientificName>Quercus robur</ScientificName>).</ListItem><ListItem>IscadorU (from elm trees; <ScientificName>Ulmus minor</ScientificName>).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_278">Helixor, an unfermented aqueous extract of <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> L. that is standardized by its biological effect on human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> cells <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis>, is marketed as one of the following:<Reference refidx="57"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_279" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>HelixorA (from spruce trees; <ScientificName>Picea abies</ScientificName>).</ListItem><ListItem>HelixorM (from apple trees).</ListItem><ListItem>HelixorP (from pine trees; <ScientificName>Pinus sylvestris</ScientificName>).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_280">Eurixor (which is no longer commercially available), an unfermented aqueous extract of <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> L. harvested from poplar trees, is reportedly standardized to contain a specific amount of one of mistletoe’s lectins (i.e., the lectin ML-1).<Reference refidx="57"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269596#_17" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">History</SummaryRef> section. Some proponents contend the choice of extract should depend on the type of tumor and the sex of the patient.<Reference refidx="55"/><Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="61"/><Reference refidx="62"/></Para><Para id="_101">A recombinant ML-1 from <ScientificName>Escherichia coli</ScientificName>     bacteria known as rViscumin or aviscumine has been studied in the laboratory and in phase I clinical trials.   Because this is not an extract of mistletoe,        it is out of the purview of this summary.<Reference refidx="63"/></Para><Para id="_13">Mistletoe extracts are usually given by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subcutaneous</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef>, although administration by other routes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285972" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrapleural</GlossaryTermRef>, intratumoral, and intravenous) has been described.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="55"/><Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="60"/><Reference refidx="64"/><Reference refidx="65"/><Reference refidx="66"/><Reference refidx="67"/><Reference refidx="68"/><Reference refidx="69"/><Reference refidx="70"/> In most reported studies, subcutaneous injections were given 2 to 3 times a week, but the overall duration of treatment varied considerably.</Para><Para id="_14"><ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> is listed in the Homeopathic Pharmacopoeia of the United States, which is the officially recognized compendium for homeopathic drugs in this country.<Reference refidx="71"/> Although the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) has regulatory authority over homeopathic drugs,  this  authority is usually not exercised unless the drugs are formulated for injection, such as the mistletoe product described in this summary.</Para><Para id="_16">In this summary, the mistletoe extract or product used in each study will be specified wherever  possible.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2344587" MedlineID="90263038">Jung ML, Baudino S, Ribéreau-Gayon G, et al.: Characterization of cytotoxic proteins from mistletoe (Viscum album L.). Cancer Lett 51 (2): 103-8, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2345458" MedlineID="90265114">Kuttan G, Vasudevan DM, Kuttan R: Effect of a preparation from Viscum album on tumor development in vitro and in mice. J Ethnopharmacol 29 (1): 35-41, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2257937" MedlineID="91078479">Walzel H, Jonas L, Rosin T, et al.: Relationship between internalization kinetics and cytotoxicity of mistletoe lectin I to L1210 leukaemia cells. Folia Biol (Praha) 36 (3-4): 181-8, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="8292069" MedlineID="94121687">Janssen O, Scheffler A, Kabelitz D: In vitro effects of mistletoe extracts and mistletoe lectins. Cytotoxicity towards tumor cells due to the induction of programmed cell death (apoptosis). Arzneimittelforschung 43 (11): 1221-7, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="8233280" MedlineID="94051001">Jurin M, Zarković N, Hrzenjak M, et al.: Antitumorous and immunomodulatory effects of the Viscum album L. preparation Isorel. Oncology 50 (6): 393-8, 1993 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Schaller G, Urech K, Giannattasio M: Cytotoxicity of different viscotoxins and extracts from the European subspecies Viscum album L. Phytother Res  10 (6): 473-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="11296616" MedlineID="21191330">Gabius HJ, Darro F, Remmelink M, et al.: Evidence for stimulation of tumor proliferation in cell lines and histotypic cultures by clinically relevant low doses of the galactoside-binding mistletoe lectin, a component of proprietary extracts. Cancer Invest 19 (2): 114-26, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11984083" MedlineID="21978681">Maier G, Fiebig HH: Absence of tumor growth stimulation in a panel of 16 human tumor cell lines by mistletoe extracts in vitro. Anticancer Drugs 13 (4): 373-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="3543782" MedlineID="87116899">Franz H: Mistletoe lectins and their A and B chains. Oncology 43 (Suppl 1): 23-34, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="12168816" MedlineID="22158496">Mengs U, Göthel D, Leng-Peschlow E: Mistletoe extracts standardized to mistletoe lectins in oncology: review on current status of preclinical research. Anticancer Res 22 (3): 1399-407, 2002 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="23133496">Podlech O, Harter PN, Mittelbronn M, et al.: Fermented mistletoe extract as a multimodal antitumoral agent in gliomas. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 2012: 501796, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="28101577">Schötterl S, Hübner M, Armento A, et al.: Viscumins functionally modulate cell motility-associated gene expression. Int J Oncol 50 (2): 684-696, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="8933823" MedlineID="97087884">Hostanska K, Hajto T, Spagnoli GC, et al.: A plant lectin derived from Viscum album induces cytokine gene expression and protein production in cultures of human peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Nat Immun 14 (5-6): 295-304, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="8929248" MedlineID="96109468">Beuth J, Stoffel B, Ko HL, et al.: Immunomodulating ability of galactoside-specific lectin standardized and depleted mistletoe extract. Arzneimittelforschung 45 (11): 1240-2, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="9042260" MedlineID="97194822">Lenartz D, Stoffel B, Menzel J, et al.: Immunoprotective activity of the galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe after tumor destructive therapy in glioma patients. Anticancer Res 16 (6B): 3799-802, 1996 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="9191874" MedlineID="97335208">Fischer S, Scheffler A, Kabelitz D: Oligoclonal in vitro response of CD4 T cells to vesicles of mistletoe extracts in mistletoe-treated cancer patients. Cancer Immunol Immunother 44 (3): 150-6, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="17">Preisfeld A: Influence of aqueous mistletoe preparations on humoral immune parameters with emphasis on the cytotoxicity of human complement in breast cancer patients. Forsch Komplementarmed  4 (4): 224-8, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="18">Chernyshov VP, Omelchenko LI, Heusser P, et al.: Immunomodulatory actions of Viscum album (Iscador) in children with recurrent respiratory disease as a result of the Chernobyl nuclear accident. Complement Ther Med  5 (3): 141-6, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="9568181" MedlineID="98229602">Heiny BM, Albrecht V, Beuth J: Correlation of immune cell activities and beta-endorphin release in breast carcinoma patients treated with galactose-specific lectin standardized mistletoe extract. Anticancer Res 18 (1B): 583-6, 1998 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="9878694" MedlineID="99096484">Stein GM, Schaller G, Pfüller U, et al.: Characterisation of granulocyte stimulation by thionins from European mistletoe and from wheat. Biochim Biophys Acta 1426 (1): 80-90, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="10368652" MedlineID="99297033">Stein GM, Schaller G, Pfüller U, et al.: Thionins from Viscum album L: influence of the viscotoxins on the activation of granulocytes. Anticancer Res 19 (2A): 1037-42, 1999 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="22">Mistletoe. In: Murray MT: The Healing Power of Herbs. Prima Publishing, 1995, pp 253-9.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="10928154" MedlineID="20383289">Lenartz D, Dott U, Menzel J, et al.: Survival of glioma patients after complementary treatment with galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe. Anticancer Res 20 (3B): 2073-6, 2000 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="11165126" MedlineID="21094742">Steuer-Vogt MK, Bonkowsky V, Ambrosch P, et al.: The effect of an adjuvant mistletoe treatment programme in resected head and neck cancer patients: a randomised controlled clinical trial. Eur J Cancer 37 (1): 23-31, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="12050495" MedlineID="22045521">Goebell PJ, Otto T, Suhr J, et al.: Evaluation of an unconventional treatment modality with mistletoe lectin to prevent recurrence of superficial bladder cancer: a randomized phase II trial. J Urol 168 (1): 72-5, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="12232491" MedlineID="22218560">Stauder H, Kreuser ED: Mistletoe extracts standardised in terms of mistletoe lectins (ML I) in oncology: current state of clinical research. Onkologie 25 (4): 374-80, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="27428940">Saha C, Das M, Stephen-Victor E, et al.: Differential Effects of Viscum album Preparations on the Maturation and Activation of Human Dendritic Cells and CD4⁺ T Cell Responses. Molecules 21 (7): , 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="22028854">Hegde P, Maddur MS, Friboulet A, et al.: Viscum album exerts anti-inflammatory effect by selectively inhibiting cytokine-induced expression of cyclooxygenase-2. PLoS One 6 (10): e26312, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="19661299">Elluru SR, VAN Huyen JP, Delignat S, et al.: Antiangiogenic properties of viscum album extracts are associated with endothelial cytotoxicity. Anticancer Res 29 (8): 2945-50, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="18533025">Elluru SR, Duong van Huyen JP, Delignat S, et al.: Induction of maturation and activation of human dendritic cells: a mechanism underlying the beneficial effect of Viscum album as complimentary therapy in cancer. BMC Cancer 8: 161, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="16927527">Elluru S, Duong Van Huyen JP, Delignat S, et al.: Molecular mechanisms underlying the immunomodulatory effects of mistletoe (Viscum album L.) extracts Iscador. Arzneimittelforschung 56 (6A): 461-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="32">Frohne D, Pfander HJ: Viscum album. In: Frohne D, Pfander HJ: Giftpflanzen: ein Handbuch für Apotheker, Ärzte,
                      Toxikologen und Biologen. 3rd rev. ed. Wissenschaftliche Verlagsgesellschaft, 1987, pp 179-80.</Citation><Citation idx="33">Pusztai A, Grant G, Pfuller U, et al.: Nutritional and metabolic effects of mistletoe lectin ML-1 (type 2 RIP) in the rat. In: European Cooperation in the Field of Scientific and Technical Research: COST 98: Effects of Antinutrients on the Nutritional Value of Legume Diets. European Commission, Directorate-General XII, Science, Research and Development, 1998, pp 164-7.</Citation><Citation idx="34">Pusztai A, Grant G, Gelencsér E, et al.: Effects of an orally administered mistletoe (type-2 RIP) lectin on growth, body composition, small intestinal structure, and insulin levels in young rats. J Nutr Biochem  9 (1): 31-6, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="35">Ewen SWB, Bardocz S, Grant G, et al.: The effects of PHA and mistletoe lectin binding to epithelium of rat and mouse gut. In: European Cooperation in the Field of Scientific and Technical Research: COST 98: Effects of Antinutrients on the Nutritional Value of Legume Diets. European Commission, Directorate-General XII, Science, Research and Development, 1998, pp 221-5.</Citation><Citation idx="36">Pryme IF, Bardocz S, Grant G, et al.: The plant lectins PHA and ML-1 suppress the growth of a lymphosarcoma tumour in mice. In: European Cooperation in the Field of Scientific and Technical Research: COST 98: Effects of Antinutrients on the Nutritional Value of Legume Diets. European Commission, Directorate-General XII, Science, Research and Development, 1998, pp 215-20.</Citation><Citation idx="37">Tubeuf  KFv, Neckel G, Marzell H: Monographie der Mistel. R. Oldenbourg, 1923.</Citation><Citation idx="38">Teuscher E: Viscum album. In: Hansel R, Keller K, Rimpler H, et al.: Hagers Handbuch der Pharmazeutischen Praxis, Vol. 6. 5th ed. Springer-Verlag, 1994, pp 1160-83.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="11347286" MedlineID="21245848">Grossarth-Maticek R, Kiene H, Baumgartner SM, et al.: Use of Iscador, an extract of European mistletoe (Viscum album), in cancer treatment: prospective nonrandomized and randomized matched-pair studies nested within a cohort study. Altern Ther Health Med 7 (3): 57-66, 68-72, 74-6 passim, 2001 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="40">Capernaros Z: The golden bough: the case for mistletoe. Eur J Herbal Med  1 (1):19-24, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="1710983" MedlineID="91266934">Schrader G, Apel K: Isolation and characterization of cDNAs encoding viscotoxins of mistletoe (Viscum album). Eur J Biochem 198 (3): 549-53, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="8134410" MedlineID="94181605">Gabius HJ, Gabius S, Joshi SS, et al.: From ill-defined extracts to the immunomodulatory lectin: will there be a reason for oncological application of mistletoe? Planta Med 60 (1): 2-7, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="43">Samtleben R, Hajto T, Hostanska K, et al.: Mistletoe lectins as immunostimulants (chemistry, pharmacology and clinic). In: Wagner H, ed.: Immunomodulatory Agents from Plants. Birkhauser Verlag, 1999, pp 223-41.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="9407559" MedlineID="98071464">Abdullaev FI, de Mejia EG: Antitumor effect of plant lectins. Nat Toxins 5 (4): 157-63, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="10367282" MedlineID="99295358">Kilpatrick DC: Mechanisms and assessment of lectin-mediated mitogenesis. Mol Biotechnol 11 (1): 55-65, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="18425885">Horneber MA, Bueschel G, Huber R, et al.: Mistletoe therapy in oncology. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (2): CD003297, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="17569116">Khil LY, Kim W, Lyu S, et al.: Mechanisms involved in Korean mistletoe lectin-induced apoptosis of cancer cells. World J Gastroenterol 13 (20): 2811-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="12850239">Kim MS, Lee J, Lee KM, et al.: Involvement of hydrogen peroxide in mistletoe lectin-II-induced apoptosis of myeloleukemic U937 cells. Life Sci 73 (10): 1231-43, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="14969342">Choi SH, Lyu SY, Park WB: Mistletoe lectin induces apoptosis and telomerase inhibition in human A253 cancer cells through dephosphorylation of Akt. Arch Pharm Res 27 (1): 68-76, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="14580196">Romagnoli S, Fogolari F, Catalano M, et al.: NMR solution structure of viscotoxin C1 from Viscum album species Coloratum ohwi: toward a structure-function analysis of viscotoxins. Biochemistry 42 (43): 12503-10, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="14609136">Yoon TJ, Yoo YC, Kang TB, et al.: Antitumor activity of the Korean mistletoe lectin is attributed to activation of macrophages and NK cells. Arch Pharm Res 26 (10): 861-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="3808575" MedlineID="87116900">Ribéreau-Gayon G, Jung ML, Di Scala D, et al.: Comparison of the effects of fermented and unfermented mistletoe preparations on cultured tumor cells. Oncology 43 (Suppl 1): 35-41, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="7575759" MedlineID="96045360">Jäggy C, Musielski H, Urech K, et al.: Quantitative determination of lectins in mistletoe preparations. Arzneimittelforschung 45 (8): 905-9, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="54">Zee-Cheng RK: Anticancer research on Loranthaceae plants. Drugs Future  22 (5): 519-30, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="9597967" MedlineID="98260258">Kaegi E: Unconventional therapies for cancer: 3. Iscador. Task Force on Alternative Therapies of the Canadian Breast Cancer Research Initiative. CMAJ 158 (9): 1157-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="7988621" MedlineID="95080321">Stein G, Berg PA: Non-lectin component in a fermented extract from Viscum album L. grown on pines induces proliferation of lymphocytes from healthy and allergic individuals in vitro. Eur J Clin Pharmacol 47 (1): 33-8, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="57">Kleijnen J, Knipschild P: Mistletoe treatment for cancer: review of controlled trials in humans. Phytomedicine  1: 255-60, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="3027640" MedlineID="87116897">Wagner H, Jordan E, Feil B: Studies on the standardization of mistletoe preparations. Oncology 43 (Suppl 1): 16-22, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="11279798" MedlineID="21175028">Zarkovic N, Vukovic T, Loncaric I, et al.: An overview on anticancer activities of the Viscum album extract Isorel. Cancer Biother Radiopharm 16 (1): 55-62, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="2813459" MedlineID="90046959">Mellor D: Mistletoe in homoeopathic cancer treatment. Prof Nurse 4 (12): 605-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="61">Fellmer KE: A clinical trial of Iscador: follow-up treatment of irradiated genital carcinomata for the prevention of recurrences. Br Homeopath J  57: 43-7, 1968.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="2477047" MedlineID="90000868">Kjaer M: Mistletoe (Iscador) therapy in stage IV renal adenocarcinoma. A phase II study in patients with measurable lung metastases. Acta Oncol 28 (4): 489-94, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="15550588">Schöffski P, Riggert S, Fumoleau P, et al.: Phase I trial of intravenous aviscumine (rViscumin) in patients with solid tumors: a study of the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer New Drug Development Group. Ann Oncol 15 (12): 1816-24, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="64">Matthes HF, Schad F, Buchwald D, et al.: Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle Injection of Viscum album L. (mistletoe; Helixor M) in the therapy of primary inoperable pancreas cancer:  a pilot study. [Abstract] Gastroenterology  128 (Suppl 2): A-T988, A433-A434, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="65">Matthes HF, Schad F, Schenk G: Viscum album in the therapy of primary inoperable hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). [Abstract] Gastroenterology  126 (Suppl 2): A-755, A101-A102, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="66">Schaefermeyer G, Schaefermeyer H: Treatment of pancreatic cancer with Viscum album (Iscador): a retrospective study of 292 patients 1986-1996. Complement Ther Med  6 (4): 172-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="67">Kleeberg UR, Brocker EB, Lejeune F, et al.: Adjuvant trial in melanoma patients comparing rlFN-alpha to rlFN-gamma to Iscador to a control group after curative resection of high risk primary (&gt;=3mm) or regional lymphnode metastasis (EORTC 18871). [Abstract] Eur J Cancer  35 (Suppl 4): A-264, s82, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="68">Heiny BM, Albrecht V, Beuth J: Stabilization of quality of life with mistletoe lectin-1-standardized extract in advanced colorectal carcinoma. Onkologe  4 (Suppl 1): S35-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="69">Wetzel D, Schäfer M: Results of a randomised placebo-controlled multicentre study with PS76A2 (standardised mistletoe preparation) in patients with breast cancer receiving adjuvant chemotherapy. [Abstract] Phytomedicine  7 (Suppl 2): A-SL-66, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="26639937">Cho JS, Na KJ, Lee Y, et al.: Chemical Pleurodesis Using Mistletoe Extraction (ABNOVAviscum(®) Injection) for Malignant Pleural Effusion. Ann Thorac Cardiovasc Surg 22 (1): 20-6, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="71">Viscum album. In: Homoeopathic Pharmacopoeia Convention of the United States: Homoeopathic Pharmacopoeia of the United States. 2002, Monograph 9444 Visc.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_17"><Title>History</Title><Para id="_18"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mistletoe</GlossaryTermRef> has been used for centuries for its medicinal properties.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> It was reportedly used by the Druids and the ancient Greeks, and it appears in legend and folklore as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">panacea</GlossaryTermRef>. It has been used in various forms to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044028" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epilepsy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infertility</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopausal</GlossaryTermRef> symptoms, nervous tension, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440101" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">asthma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044038" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypertension</GlossaryTermRef>, headache, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045667" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dermatitis</GlossaryTermRef>. The use of mistletoe in the treatment of cancer is about 100 years old, and its use in the treatment of other  indications is much older. Modern interest in mistletoe as an anticancer treatment  began in the 1920s.   Most of the results of clinical studies have been published exclusively in German. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269596#_35" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">Human/Clinical Studies</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_19"> Another reported activity of mistletoe that may be relevant to optimum functioning of the immune system in individuals with cancer is stabilization of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044393" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, including white blood cells that have been exposed to DNA-damaging <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> drugs.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></Para><Para id="_20">Mistletoe has been shown to stimulate increases in the number and the activity of various types of white blood cells.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/> Immune system–enhancing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046130" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytokines</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350231" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-1</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044045" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-6</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor necrosis factor</GlossaryTermRef>-alpha, are released by white blood cells after exposure to mistletoe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/> Other evidence suggests that mistletoe exerts its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic</GlossaryTermRef> effects by interfering with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> synthesis in target cells <Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="55"/><Reference refidx="56"/><Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="59"/><Reference refidx="60"/><Reference refidx="61"/><Reference refidx="62"/><Reference refidx="63"/> and by inducing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">apoptosis</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="64"/><Reference refidx="65"/><Reference refidx="66"/> Mistletoe may also serve a bridging function, bringing together immune system <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">effector cells</GlossaryTermRef> and tumor cells.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="67"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Capernaros Z: The golden bough: the case for mistletoe. Eur J Herbal Med  1 (1):19-24, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Mistletoe. In: Murray MT: The Healing Power of Herbs. Prima Publishing, 1995, pp 253-9.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Samtleben R, Hajto T, Hostanska K, et al.: Mistletoe lectins as immunostimulants (chemistry, pharmacology and clinic). In: Wagner H, ed.: Immunomodulatory Agents from Plants. Birkhauser Verlag, 1999, pp 223-41.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="7142144" MedlineID="83056810">Olsnes S, Stirpe F, Sandvig K, et al.: Isolation and characterization of viscumin, a toxic lectin from Viscum album L. (mistletoe). J Biol Chem 257 (22): 13263-70, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3808574" MedlineID="87116898">Becker H: Botany of European mistletoe (Viscum album L.). Oncology 43 (Suppl 1): 2-7, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="9455311" MedlineID="98116489">Watkins D: A berry Christmas. Nurs Times 93 (51): 28-9, 1997 Dec 17-23.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="7880615" MedlineID="95186245">Büssing A, Azhari T, Ostendorp H, et al.: Viscum album L. extracts reduce sister chromatid exchanges in cultured peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Eur J Cancer 30A (12): 1836-41, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="7893276" MedlineID="95200406">Büssing A, Lehnert A, Schink M, et al.: Effect of Viscum album L. on rapidly proliferating amniotic fluid cells. Sister chromatid exchange frequency and proliferation index. Arzneimittelforschung 45 (1): 81-3, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="7634248" MedlineID="95360896">Büssing A, Regnery A, Schweizer K: Effects of Viscum album L. on cyclophosphamide-treated peripheral blood mononuclear cells in vitro: sister chromatid exchanges and activation/proliferation marker expression. Cancer Lett 94 (2): 199-205, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Bussing A, Jungmann H, Suzart K, et al.: Suppression of sister chromatid exchange-inducing DNA lesions in cultured peripheral blood mononuclear cells by Viscum album L. J Exp Clin Cancer Res  15 (2): 107-14, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8564930" MedlineID="96152606">Büssing A, Suzart K, Bergmann J, et al.: Induction of apoptosis in human lymphocytes treated with Viscum album L. is mediated by the mistletoe lectins. Cancer Lett 99 (1): 59-72, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="7453129" MedlineID="81097391">Rentea R, Lyon E, Hunter R: Biologic properties of iscador: a Viscum album preparation I. Hyperplasia of the thymic cortex and accelerated regeneration of hematopoietic cells following X-irradiation. Lab Invest 44 (1): 43-8, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="7163417" MedlineID="83144788">Bloksma N, Schmiermann P, de Reuver M, et al.: Stimulation of humoral and cellular immunity by Viscum preparations. Planta Med 46 (4): 221-7, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="2433654" MedlineID="87116902">Hajto T: Immunomodulatory effects of iscador: a Viscum album preparation. Oncology 43 (Suppl 1): 51-65, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="3951791" MedlineID="86147827">Hajto T, Lanzrein C: Natural killer and antibody-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity activities and large granular lymphocyte frequencies in Viscum album-treated breast cancer patients. Oncology 43 (2): 93-7, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="3583510" MedlineID="87221090">Hamprecht K, Handgretinger R, Voetsch W, et al.: Mediation of human NK-activity by components in extracts of Viscum album. Int J Immunopharmacol 9 (2): 199-209, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="2758413" MedlineID="89336692">Hajto T, Hostanska K, Gabius HJ: Modulatory potency of the beta-galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe extract (Iscador) on the host defense system in vivo in rabbits and patients. Cancer Res 49 (17): 4803-8, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="2708032" MedlineID="89213333">Mueller EA, Hamprecht K, Anderer FA: Biochemical characterization of a component in extracts of Viscum album enhancing human NK cytotoxicity. Immunopharmacology 17 (1): 11-8, 1989 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="2334925" MedlineID="90242326">Hajto T, Hostanska K, Frei K, et al.: Increased secretion of tumor necrosis factors alpha, interleukin 1, and interleukin 6 by human mononuclear cells exposed to beta-galactoside-specific lectin from clinically applied mistletoe extract. Cancer Res 50 (11): 3322-6, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="1392440" MedlineID="93005414">Beuth J, Ko HL, Gabius HJ, et al.: Behavior of lymphocyte subsets and expression of activation markers in response to immunotherapy with galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe in breast cancer patients. Clin Investig 70 (8): 658-61, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="1394116" MedlineID="93007844">Kuttan G, Kuttan R: Immunological mechanism of action of the tumor reducing peptide from mistletoe extract (NSC 635089) cellular proliferation. Cancer Lett 66 (2): 123-30, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="1398778" MedlineID="93013938">Kuttan G, Kuttan R: Immunomodulatory activity of a peptide isolated from Viscum album extract (NSC 635 089). Immunol Invest 21 (4): 285-96, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="1622124" MedlineID="92321663">Gabius HJ, Walzel H, Joshi SS, et al.: The immunomodulatory beta-galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe: partial sequence analysis, cell and tissue binding, and impact on intracellular biosignalling of monocytic leukemia cells. Anticancer Res 12 (3): 669-75, 1992 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="8110981" MedlineID="94154186">Beuth J, Ko HL, Tunggal L, et al.: Thymocyte proliferation and maturation in response to galactoside-specific mistletoe lectin-1. In Vivo 7 (5): 407-10, 1993 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="8392351" MedlineID="93319679">Timoshenko AV, Gabius HJ: Efficient induction of superoxide release from human neutrophils by the galactoside-specific lectin from Viscum album. Biol Chem Hoppe Seyler 374 (4): 237-43, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="8267383" MedlineID="94091786">Timoshenko AV, Kayser K, Drings P, et al.: Modulation of lectin-triggered superoxide release from neutrophils of tumor patients with and without chemotherapy. Anticancer Res 13 (5C): 1789-92, 1993 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="8262566" MedlineID="94086035">Kuttan G: Tumoricidal activity of mouse peritoneal macrophages treated with Viscum album extract. Immunol Invest 22 (6-7): 431-40, 1993 Aug-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="7772751" MedlineID="95290659">Beuth J, Ko HL, Tunggal L, et al.: Immunoprotective activity of the galactoside-specific mistletoe lectin in cortisone-treated BALB/c-mice. In Vivo 8 (6): 989-92, 1994 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="8067703" MedlineID="94346767">Heiny BM, Beuth J: Mistletoe extract standardized for the galactoside-specific lectin (ML-1) induces beta-endorphin release and immunopotentiation in breast cancer patients. Anticancer Res 14 (3B): 1339-42, 1994 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="7988621" MedlineID="95080321">Stein G, Berg PA: Non-lectin component in a fermented extract from Viscum album L. grown on pines induces proliferation of lymphocytes from healthy and allergic individuals in vitro. Eur J Clin Pharmacol 47 (1): 33-8, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="7753919" MedlineID="95273486">Timoshenko AV, Gabius HJ: Influence of the galactoside-specific lectin from Viscum album and its subunits on cell aggregation and selected intracellular parameters of rat thymocytes. Planta Med 61 (2): 130-3, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="7647287" MedlineID="95375218">Timoshenko AV, Cherenkevich SN, Gabius HJ: Viscum album agglutinin-induced aggregation of blood cells and the lectin effects on neutrophil function. Biomed Pharmacother 49 (3): 153-8, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="8933823" MedlineID="97087884">Hostanska K, Hajto T, Spagnoli GC, et al.: A plant lectin derived from Viscum album induces cytokine gene expression and protein production in cultures of human peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Nat Immun 14 (5-6): 295-304, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="8929248" MedlineID="96109468">Beuth J, Stoffel B, Ko HL, et al.: Immunomodulating ability of galactoside-specific lectin standardized and depleted mistletoe extract. Arzneimittelforschung 45 (11): 1240-2, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="9042260" MedlineID="97194822">Lenartz D, Stoffel B, Menzel J, et al.: Immunoprotective activity of the galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe after tumor destructive therapy in glioma patients. Anticancer Res 16 (6B): 3799-802, 1996 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="9191874" MedlineID="97335208">Fischer S, Scheffler A, Kabelitz D: Oligoclonal in vitro response of CD4 T cells to vesicles of mistletoe extracts in mistletoe-treated cancer patients. Cancer Immunol Immunother 44 (3): 150-6, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="37">Preisfeld A: Influence of aqueous mistletoe preparations on humoral immune parameters with emphasis on the cytotoxicity of human complement in breast cancer patients. Forsch Komplementarmed  4 (4): 224-8, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="38">Chernyshov VP, Omelchenko LI, Heusser P, et al.: Immunomodulatory actions of Viscum album (Iscador) in children with recurrent respiratory disease as a result of the Chernobyl nuclear accident. Complement Ther Med  5 (3): 141-6, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="9568181" MedlineID="98229602">Heiny BM, Albrecht V, Beuth J: Correlation of immune cell activities and beta-endorphin release in breast carcinoma patients treated with galactose-specific lectin standardized mistletoe extract. Anticancer Res 18 (1B): 583-6, 1998 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="9878694" MedlineID="99096484">Stein GM, Schaller G, Pfüller U, et al.: Characterisation of granulocyte stimulation by thionins from European mistletoe and from wheat. Biochim Biophys Acta 1426 (1): 80-90, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="10368652" MedlineID="99297033">Stein GM, Schaller G, Pfüller U, et al.: Thionins from Viscum album L: influence of the viscotoxins on the activation of granulocytes. Anticancer Res 19 (2A): 1037-42, 1999 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="12168816" MedlineID="22158496">Mengs U, Göthel D, Leng-Peschlow E: Mistletoe extracts standardized to mistletoe lectins in oncology: review on current status of preclinical research. Anticancer Res 22 (3): 1399-407, 2002 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="8346712" MedlineID="93348812">Bocci V: Mistletoe (viscum album) lectins as cytokine inducers and immunoadjuvant in tumor therapy. A review. J Biol Regul Homeost Agents 7 (1): 1-6, 1993 Jan-Mar.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="8134410" MedlineID="94181605">Gabius HJ, Gabius S, Joshi SS, et al.: From ill-defined extracts to the immunomodulatory lectin: will there be a reason for oncological application of mistletoe? Planta Med 60 (1): 2-7, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="45">Zee-Cheng RK: Anticancer research on Loranthaceae plants. Drugs Future  22 (5): 519-30, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="9597967" MedlineID="98260258">Kaegi E: Unconventional therapies for cancer: 3. Iscador. Task Force on Alternative Therapies of the Canadian Breast Cancer Research Initiative. CMAJ 158 (9): 1157-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="10928154" MedlineID="20383289">Lenartz D, Dott U, Menzel J, et al.: Survival of glioma patients after complementary treatment with galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe. Anticancer Res 20 (3B): 2073-6, 2000 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="12050495" MedlineID="22045521">Goebell PJ, Otto T, Suhr J, et al.: Evaluation of an unconventional treatment modality with mistletoe lectin to prevent recurrence of superficial bladder cancer: a randomized phase II trial. J Urol 168 (1): 72-5, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="49">Schaefermeyer G, Schaefermeyer H: Treatment of pancreatic cancer with Viscum album (Iscador): a retrospective study of 292 patients 1986-1996. Complement Ther Med  6 (4): 172-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="9654190" MedlineID="98316762">Kunze E, Schulz H, Gabius HJ: Inability of galactoside-specific mistletoe lectin to inhibit N-methyl-N-nitrosourea-induced tumor development in the urinary bladder of rats and to mediate a local cellular immune response after long-term administration. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 124 (2): 73-87, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="10741906" MedlineID="20203950">Kunze E, Schulz H, Adamek M, et al.: Long-term administration of galactoside-specific mistletoe lectin in an animal model: no protection against N-butyl-N-(4-hydroxybutyl)-nitrosamine-induced urinary bladder carcinogenesis in rats and no induction of a relevant local cellular immune response. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 126 (3): 125-38, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="11131663" MedlineID="21014296">Mengs U, Schwarz T, Bulitta M, et al.: Antitumoral effects of an intravesically applied aqueous mistletoe extract on urinary bladder carcinoma MB49 in mice. Anticancer Res 20 (5B): 3565-8, 2000 Sep- Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="12232491" MedlineID="22218560">Stauder H, Kreuser ED: Mistletoe extracts standardised in terms of mistletoe lectins (ML I) in oncology: current state of clinical research. Onkologie 25 (4): 374-80, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="54">Kleijnen J, Knipschild P: Mistletoe treatment for cancer: review of controlled trials in humans. Phytomedicine  1: 255-60, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="7142145" MedlineID="83056811">Stirpe F, Sandvig K, Olsnes S, et al.: Action of viscumin, a toxic lectin from mistletoe, on cells in culture. J Biol Chem 257 (22): 13271-7, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="2257937" MedlineID="91078479">Walzel H, Jonas L, Rosin T, et al.: Relationship between internalization kinetics and cytotoxicity of mistletoe lectin I to L1210 leukaemia cells. Folia Biol (Praha) 36 (3-4): 181-8, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="3543782" MedlineID="87116899">Franz H: Mistletoe lectins and their A and B chains. Oncology 43 (Suppl 1): 23-34, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="8263931" MedlineID="94087743">Sweeney EC, Palmer RA, Pfüller U: Crystallization of the ribosome inactivating protein ML1 from Viscum album (mistletoe) complexed with beta-D-galactose. J Mol Biol 234 (4): 1279-81, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="2344587" MedlineID="90263038">Jung ML, Baudino S, Ribéreau-Gayon G, et al.: Characterization of cytotoxic proteins from mistletoe (Viscum album L.). Cancer Lett 51 (2): 103-8, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="11296616" MedlineID="21191330">Gabius HJ, Darro F, Remmelink M, et al.: Evidence for stimulation of tumor proliferation in cell lines and histotypic cultures by clinically relevant low doses of the galactoside-binding mistletoe lectin, a component of proprietary extracts. Cancer Invest 19 (2): 114-26, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="1450445" MedlineID="93081837">Dietrich JB, Ribéreau-Gayon G, Jung ML, et al.: Identity of the N-terminal sequences of the three A chains of mistletoe (Viscum album L.) lectins: homology with ricin-like plant toxins and single-chain ribosome-inhibiting proteins. Anticancer Drugs 3 (5): 507-11, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="7575759" MedlineID="96045360">Jäggy C, Musielski H, Urech K, et al.: Quantitative determination of lectins in mistletoe preparations. Arzneimittelforschung 45 (8): 905-9, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="11497284" MedlineID="21388244">Burger AM, Mengs U, Schüler JB, et al.: Anticancer activity of an aqueous mistletoe extract (AME) in syngeneic murine tumor models. Anticancer Res 21 (3B): 1965-8, 2001 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="8292069" MedlineID="94121687">Janssen O, Scheffler A, Kabelitz D: In vitro effects of mistletoe extracts and mistletoe lectins. Cytotoxicity towards tumor cells due to the induction of programmed cell death (apoptosis). Arzneimittelforschung 43 (11): 1221-7, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="11279798" MedlineID="21175028">Zarkovic N, Vukovic T, Loncaric I, et al.: An overview on anticancer activities of the Viscum album extract Isorel. Cancer Biother Radiopharm 16 (1): 55-62, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="11984083" MedlineID="21978681">Maier G, Fiebig HH: Absence of tumor growth stimulation in a panel of 16 human tumor cell lines by mistletoe extracts in vitro. Anticancer Drugs 13 (4): 373-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="2407685" MedlineID="90170353">Mueller EA, Anderer FA: Chemical specificity of effector cell/tumor cell bridging by a Viscum album rhamnogalacturonan enhancing cytotoxicity of human NK cells. Immunopharmacology 19 (1): 69-77, 1990 Jan-Feb.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><Para id="_24">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>–stimulating and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic</GlossaryTermRef> properties of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mistletoe</GlossaryTermRef> have     been investigated in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_21"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044094" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Viscotoxins</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044051" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lectins</GlossaryTermRef> have  been investigated as active components in mistletoe; most research has focused on the lectins.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> Purified <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mistletoe lectins</GlossaryTermRef> have demonstrated cytotoxic and immune system–stimulating activities. Four different lectins have been identified in mistletoe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_281" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>ML-1.</ListItem><ListItem>ML-2.</ListItem><ListItem>ML-3.</ListItem><ListItem><ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285965" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chitin</GlossaryTermRef>-binding <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285953" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">agglutinin</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_282">ML-1 (or viscumin) may be responsible for many of mistletoe’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biological</GlossaryTermRef> effects. When a laboratory method was used to selectively deplete ML-1 from <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> extracts, their cytotoxic and immune system–stimulating properties were markedly reduced.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> It should be noted that fermentation eliminates most of the ML-1 in mistletoe extracts. Iscador, and other fermented mistletoe extracts, contain only the mistletoe lectins ML-2 and ML-3, whereas the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef> of the ML-1 complex are missing.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Polysaccharide</GlossaryTermRef> and oligosaccharide components of mistletoe extracts with substantial immune-stimulating properties have been reviewed.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_61">The molecular structure of ML-1 consists of an alpha chain and a beta chain, which can be separated from one another.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/> Each chain type appears to mediate a subset of the activities described for the intact lectin. Cytotoxicity is associated mainly with the alpha chain. In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory 
studies</GlossaryTermRef>, the ML-1 alpha chain has been coupled to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046066" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monoclonal antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to produce  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotoxins</GlossaryTermRef> that target and kill specific cell types.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_104"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044619" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Recombinant</GlossaryTermRef> ML-1, rML (also known as rViscumin or aviscumine) appears to have the same <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> as plant-based ML-1 in laboratory studies.<Reference refidx="22"/> Because this is not an extract of mistletoe, it is out of the purview of this summary.</Para><Para id="_105">The beta chain of ML-1 is responsible for binding to the surface of a target cell.<Reference refidx="23"/>    Studies of mistletoe lectin binding to cancer cells have examined whether the extent of cell binding can predict disease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or survival.  Studies show that the prognostic value of ML-1 binding depends on the type of cancer.<Reference refidx="24"/> For human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cells, the amount of lectin-bound cells correlates positively with disease outcome.  However, for human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, there is no correlation between the amount of lectin-bound cells and disease survival.<Reference refidx="25"/> Though much research has looked at this particular aspect, there have not been studies that directly link the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentration</GlossaryTermRef> of that component to any clinical activity of mistletoe.</Para><Para id="_25">Laboratory studies have shown that mistletoe extracts can stimulate the activity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> and cause them to release <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef> thought to be important for anticancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune responses</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/>   In addition, mistletoe extracts have demonstrated cytotoxic activity against a variety of mouse, rat, and human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/>   </Para><Para id="_118">There are conflicting reports concerning the stimulation of cancer cell growth <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis>. In one study,    the <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> growth of several types of human cancer cells was stimulated by treatment with low <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of the purified <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044051" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lectin</GlossaryTermRef> ML-1.<Reference refidx="1"/> However, various other  studies found that ML-1     and mistletoe extracts did not induce <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell proliferation</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/></Para><Para id="_255"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Preclinical   studies</GlossaryTermRef> demonstrating biological effects on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000695994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer cell lines</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal models</GlossaryTermRef> are summarized in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269596#_257" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269596#_258" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>.</Para><Table id="_257"><Title>Table 1.  <Emphasis>In Vitro</Emphasis> Studies<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec Align="Left" ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="36.17%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="30.39%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.43%"/><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">IscadorQu =  IscadorQ; ML-1 = mistletoe extracts with mistletoe lectins I.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For more information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Iscador</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Cell Line</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Various human cancer cell
lines</entry><entry>Iscador preparations containing a high lectin concentration (15 μg/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mL</GlossaryTermRef>)  showed  &gt;70% growth inhibition in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mammary</GlossaryTermRef> cancer cell line (MAXF 401NL) compared with untreated control cells;  30%–70% growth inhibition in three <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> cell lines (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> RPMI 8226, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-small cell lung</GlossaryTermRef> LXFE 66NL, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445094" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterine</GlossaryTermRef> UXF 1138L) for IscadorM  and in seven tumor cell lines (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> SF268, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454513" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastric</GlossaryTermRef> GXF 251L, non-small cell lung LXFE 66NL and LXFL 529L, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef> PC3M, renal RXF 944L, and uterine UXF 1138L) for IscadorQu</entry><entry><Reference refidx="35"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Human
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045780" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medulloblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> cells
Daoy, D341,  D425, and UW 228-2 </entry><entry><ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> preparations (0.1–100 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">µg</GlossaryTermRef>/mL) induced cell death through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">apoptosis</GlossaryTermRef>. Growth-inhibition correlated with the lectin content of the used preparation</entry><entry><Reference refidx="37"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Various human cancer cell lines:  SF268 (central nervous system); GXF 251 (gastric); H460, LXFA 629L, LXFE 66NL, LXFL 529L (lung); CCRFCEM, MOLT-4, HL-60, K562, U937, RPMI 8226 (leukemia and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>); MCF7, MAXF 401NL (mammary); HT144, MALME-3M, SK-MEL28, MEXF 462NL, MEXF 514L (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef>); PC3M (prostate); RXF 393NL, RXF 944L (renal); Hs729, SK-LMS-1, SK-UT-1B (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>); and UXF 1138L (uterus)</entry><entry>IscadorM and IscadorQu with a high lectin content demonstrated  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antitumor</GlossaryTermRef> activity <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis>  at high test concentrations (15–150 µg/mL)</entry><entry><Reference refidx="38"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Human cell lines: HCC1937, HCC1143 (breast), PA-TU-8902 (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>), DU145 (prostate), NCI-H460 (lung)</entry><entry>Cell proliferation inhibition was detected with a mistletoe dose at 100 μg/mL in cell lines PA-TU-8902 and NCI-H460, and a dose at  ≥10 μg/mL in cell lines HCC1937, HCC1143, and DU145</entry><entry><Reference refidx="40"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Glioblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> cells: LNT-229, LN-308</entry><entry>Cell growth was reduced with IscadorQ  and IscadorM at lectin concentrations of 100 µg/mL</entry><entry><Reference refidx="41"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Helixor</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Cell Line</Strong> </entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Various human cancer cell lines</entry><entry>Helixor mistletoe preparations (15–150 µg/mL) and ML-1 (10–100 ng/mL) did not induce cell proliferation</entry><entry><Reference refidx="39"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>abnobaVISCUM</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Cell Line</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Human tumor cell lines: <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045611" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">B-cell</GlossaryTermRef> hybridomas, P815, EL-4, Ke37, MOLT-4, and U937</entry><entry>Growth arrest was caused by the induction of apoptosis (50% of U937 cells at 100 ng/mL of ML-1 and 40% of B-cell hybridomas  and EL-4 cells at concentrations as low as 1 ng/mL  of ML-1)</entry><entry><Reference refidx="10"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_256">Studies of the ability of mistletoe to inhibit cancer cell growth in animals have yielded mixed and inconsistent results.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/> In most of these studies, mistletoe extracts were administered either by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subcutaneous</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> or by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046339" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraperitoneal</GlossaryTermRef> injection; some of the differences in results may have resulted from the difference in route of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef>. For example, IscadorM administration was associated with a prolonged survival of female Swiss mice when the route of administration was intraperitoneal <Reference refidx="51"/> but not when the route was subcutaneous.<Reference refidx="52"/> Other differences between these two studies were the number of cells used in the Ehrlich <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045601" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ascites</GlossaryTermRef> inoculum and the doses of IscadorM administered.</Para><Table id="_258"><Title>Table 2.  <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">In Vivo</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> Studies<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="32.91%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="31.64%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="35.44%"/><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">ALL = acute lymphoblastic leukemia; ME-A = mistletoe extracts (fir tree <ScientificName>Abies</ScientificName>); ME-M = mistletoe extracts (apple tree <ScientificName>Malus</ScientificName>); ML-1 = mistletoe extracts with mistletoe lectins I; ML-3 = mistletoe extracts with mistletoe lectins III; MT-A = mistletoe extracts obtained from fir trees; MT-P = mistletoe extracts obtained from pine trees; NK = natural killer.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For more information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Iscador</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Animal Model</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Mice</entry><entry>Antiproliferative and antimetastatic effects in melanoma cell line MV3 were only achieved with low-dose ML-1 (30 ng/kg body weight) and not with higher doses (150 ng/kg and 500 ng/kg); increased number of infiltrating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044948" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dendritic cells</GlossaryTermRef> suggests stimulation of the immune system</entry><entry><Reference refidx="44"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Mice</entry><entry><ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> extract (20 µg/mouse/d) mediated inhibition of B16F1 melanoma cells tumor growth was associated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367426" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunomodulation</GlossaryTermRef> via induction of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">IL-12</GlossaryTermRef> secretion leading to enhanced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">T-cell</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044439" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NK-cell</GlossaryTermRef> functions</entry><entry><Reference refidx="45"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Mice</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Organ</GlossaryTermRef> colonization was investigated on day 14 after RAW 117 H 10 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> cell and L-1 sarcoma cell  inoculation and demonstrated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef> (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05) reductions of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">experimental</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> and lung <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastases</GlossaryTermRef> for standardized <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aqueous</GlossaryTermRef> mistletoe extract–treated mice (2 µg, 20 µg, 100 µg, and 500 µg per  mouse)</entry><entry><Reference refidx="47"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Mice (Nude and VMDk mice)</entry><entry>Glioblastoma tumor growth was reduced (cell lines LNT-229 and LN-308), the expression of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> associated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor progression</GlossaryTermRef> was reduced, and  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044439" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NK cell</GlossaryTermRef> mediated glioblastoma cell <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lysis</GlossaryTermRef> was enhanced when IscadorQ and IscadorM 100 µg/mL was administered by an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044603" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intratumoral</GlossaryTermRef> injection</entry><entry><Reference refidx="41"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>BDF and Swiss albino mice</entry><entry>Treatment with IscadorM (50 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/kg/d and 100 mg/kg/d) increased the survival time of mice that had been implanted with Ehrlich ascites mouse cancer cells, but not L1210 leukemia or B16 melanoma cancer cells</entry><entry><Reference refidx="51"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Swiss albino mice</entry><entry>No antitumor effect or improvement in survival was observed when IscadorM (15.75 mg, 750 mg, 10.5 mg, 500 mg) was used to treat rats bearing chemically induced mammary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045963" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinomas</GlossaryTermRef> or tumors formed from rat Walker 256 carcinosarcoma cells; IscadorM (5 mg, 200 mg, 150 mg, 3.75 mg) was also not effective in treating mice that had been injected with Ehrlich ascites cells; in addition, IscadorP (135 mg) was found ineffective in treating rats with tumors formed from rat L5222 leukemia cells</entry><entry><Reference refidx="52"/></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Left" NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Helixor</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Animal Model</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000615419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">SCID</GlossaryTermRef> mice</entry><entry>Despite a considerably lower ML-3 content, MT-A (50 mg/kg and 100 mg/kg)  was more effective and less <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxic</GlossaryTermRef> than MT-P (50 mg/kg) in a human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>  cell line (NALM-6);  both were given intraperitoneally in mice inoculated with human ALL</entry><entry><Reference refidx="43"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046441" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ductal</GlossaryTermRef> breast carcinoma cell line BT474</entry><entry>As compared with tumors of control mice, tumors of the ME-A– and ME-M–treated groups (5 mg intratumoral injection) showed a decreased cell proliferation rate, as well as an increased cell <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">necrosis</GlossaryTermRef> and apoptosis rate</entry><entry><Reference refidx="46"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>abnobaVISCUM</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Animal Model</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Nude mice</entry><entry>Intratumoral injections of mistletoe extract (abnobaVISCUM Fraxini-2, 8 mg/kg body weight and lectin at 5.3 µg/kg body weight) demonstrated more antitumor activity than did <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508951" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gemcitabine</GlossaryTermRef> when injected into mice bearing xenografts of human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic adenocarcinoma cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (PAXF 736)</entry><entry><Reference refidx="53"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Isorel</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Animal Model</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Mice</entry><entry>In mice <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplanted</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046403" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fibrosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> (CMC-2), when IsorelM (140 mg/kg)  was used alone, no effect on either tumor growth or animal survival was observed. When IsorelM (140 mg/kg)  was combined with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray therapy</GlossaryTermRef> of tumors, there was substantial improvements in survival of mice compared with survival of mice treated with x-ray therapy (43 Gy) alone</entry><entry><Reference refidx="54"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Eurixor</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Animal Model</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Mice</entry><entry>Aqueous mistletoe extract (30  ng/mL or 300 ng/mL)  showed antitumoral activity on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinary</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> carcinoma (MB49)  in mice, which was considered to be mainly caused by the cytotoxic properties of mistletoe lectins</entry><entry><Reference refidx="6"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Lektinol</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Animal Model</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Outcome</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Mice</entry><entry>Treatment with Lektinol (0.3, 3, 30, or 300 ng/mL/kg/d) slowed the growth of tumors formed in mice from implants of three types of mouse cancers (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> adenocarcinoma 38, Renca <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000661352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>, and F9 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046611" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testicular</GlossaryTermRef> carcinoma) but not from two other mouse cancers (B16 melanoma and Lewis lung carcinoma)</entry><entry><Reference refidx="7"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11296616" MedlineID="21191330">Gabius HJ, Darro F, Remmelink M, et al.: Evidence for stimulation of tumor proliferation in cell lines and histotypic cultures by clinically relevant low doses of the galactoside-binding mistletoe lectin, a component of proprietary extracts. Cancer Invest 19 (2): 114-26, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10928154" MedlineID="20383289">Lenartz D, Dott U, Menzel J, et al.: Survival of glioma patients after complementary treatment with galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe. Anticancer Res 20 (3B): 2073-6, 2000 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11165126" MedlineID="21094742">Steuer-Vogt MK, Bonkowsky V, Ambrosch P, et al.: The effect of an adjuvant mistletoe treatment programme in resected head and neck cancer patients: a randomised controlled clinical trial. Eur J Cancer 37 (1): 23-31, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12050495" MedlineID="22045521">Goebell PJ, Otto T, Suhr J, et al.: Evaluation of an unconventional treatment modality with mistletoe lectin to prevent recurrence of superficial bladder cancer: a randomized phase II trial. J Urol 168 (1): 72-5, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10741906" MedlineID="20203950">Kunze E, Schulz H, Adamek M, et al.: Long-term administration of galactoside-specific mistletoe lectin in an animal model: no protection against N-butyl-N-(4-hydroxybutyl)-nitrosamine-induced urinary bladder carcinogenesis in rats and no induction of a relevant local cellular immune response. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 126 (3): 125-38, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11131663" MedlineID="21014296">Mengs U, Schwarz T, Bulitta M, et al.: Antitumoral effects of an intravesically applied aqueous mistletoe extract on urinary bladder carcinoma MB49 in mice. Anticancer Res 20 (5B): 3565-8, 2000 Sep- Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="11497284" MedlineID="21388244">Burger AM, Mengs U, Schüler JB, et al.: Anticancer activity of an aqueous mistletoe extract (AME) in syngeneic murine tumor models. Anticancer Res 21 (3B): 1965-8, 2001 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12168816" MedlineID="22158496">Mengs U, Göthel D, Leng-Peschlow E: Mistletoe extracts standardized to mistletoe lectins in oncology: review on current status of preclinical research. Anticancer Res 22 (3): 1399-407, 2002 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Samtleben R, Hajto T, Hostanska K, et al.: Mistletoe lectins as immunostimulants (chemistry, pharmacology and clinic). In: Wagner H, ed.: Immunomodulatory Agents from Plants. Birkhauser Verlag, 1999, pp 223-41.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="8292069" MedlineID="94121687">Janssen O, Scheffler A, Kabelitz D: In vitro effects of mistletoe extracts and mistletoe lectins. Cytotoxicity towards tumor cells due to the induction of programmed cell death (apoptosis). Arzneimittelforschung 43 (11): 1221-7, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8929248" MedlineID="96109468">Beuth J, Stoffel B, Ko HL, et al.: Immunomodulating ability of galactoside-specific lectin standardized and depleted mistletoe extract. Arzneimittelforschung 45 (11): 1240-2, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="3027640" MedlineID="87116897">Wagner H, Jordan E, Feil B: Studies on the standardization of mistletoe preparations. Oncology 43 (Suppl 1): 16-22, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Mistletoe. In: Murray MT: The Healing Power of Herbs. Prima Publishing, 1995, pp 253-9.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="7575759" MedlineID="96045360">Jäggy C, Musielski H, Urech K, et al.: Quantitative determination of lectins in mistletoe preparations. Arzneimittelforschung 45 (8): 905-9, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="12553059">Stein GM, Büssing A, Schietzel M: Stimulation of the maturation of dendritic cells in vitro by a fermented mistletoe extract. Anticancer Res 22 (6C): 4215-9, 2002 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="14969350">Lyu SY, Kwon YJ, Joo HJ, et al.: Preparation of alginate/chitosan microcapsules and enteric coated granules of mistletoe lectin. Arch Pharm Res 27 (1): 118-26, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="8392351" MedlineID="93319679">Timoshenko AV, Gabius HJ: Efficient induction of superoxide release from human neutrophils by the galactoside-specific lectin from Viscum album. Biol Chem Hoppe Seyler 374 (4): 237-43, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="1450445" MedlineID="93081837">Dietrich JB, Ribéreau-Gayon G, Jung ML, et al.: Identity of the N-terminal sequences of the three A chains of mistletoe (Viscum album L.) lectins: homology with ricin-like plant toxins and single-chain ribosome-inhibiting proteins. Anticancer Drugs 3 (5): 507-11, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="1988131" MedlineID="91105723">Wiedłocha A, Sandvig K, Walzel H, et al.: Internalization and action of an immunotoxin containing mistletoe lectin A-chain. Cancer Res 51 (3): 916-20, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="1722193" MedlineID="92104744">Tonevitsky AG, Toptygin AYu, Pfuller U, et al.: Immunotoxin with mistletoe lectin I A-chain and ricin A-chain directed against CD5 antigen of human T-lymphocytes; comparison of efficiency and specificity. Int J Immunopharmacol 13 (7): 1037-41, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="8346712" MedlineID="93348812">Bocci V: Mistletoe (viscum album) lectins as cytokine inducers and immunoadjuvant in tumor therapy. A review. J Biol Regul Homeost Agents 7 (1): 1-6, 1993 Jan-Mar.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="12565000">Habeck M: Mistletoe compound enters clinical trials. Drug Discov Today 8 (2): 52-3, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="15520251">Müthing J, Meisen I, Kniep B, et al.: Tumor-associated CD75s gangliosides and CD75s-bearing glycoproteins with Neu5Acalpha2-6Galbeta1-4GlcNAc-residues are receptors for the anticancer drug rViscumin. FASEB J 19 (1): 103-5, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="15154645">Fritz P, Dippon J, Kierschke T, et al.: Impact of mistletoe lectin binding in breast cancer. Anticancer Res 24 (2C): 1187-92, 2004 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="16101142">Blonski K, Schumacher U, Burkholder I, et al.: Binding of recombinant mistletoe lectin (aviscumine) to resected human adenocarcinoma of the lung. Anticancer Res 25 (5): 3303-7, 2005 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="8267383" MedlineID="94091786">Timoshenko AV, Kayser K, Drings P, et al.: Modulation of lectin-triggered superoxide release from neutrophils of tumor patients with and without chemotherapy. Anticancer Res 13 (5C): 1789-92, 1993 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="7753919" MedlineID="95273486">Timoshenko AV, Gabius HJ: Influence of the galactoside-specific lectin from Viscum album and its subunits on cell aggregation and selected intracellular parameters of rat thymocytes. Planta Med 61 (2): 130-3, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="7647287" MedlineID="95375218">Timoshenko AV, Cherenkevich SN, Gabius HJ: Viscum album agglutinin-induced aggregation of blood cells and the lectin effects on neutrophil function. Biomed Pharmacother 49 (3): 153-8, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="8933823" MedlineID="97087884">Hostanska K, Hajto T, Spagnoli GC, et al.: A plant lectin derived from Viscum album induces cytokine gene expression and protein production in cultures of human peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Nat Immun 14 (5-6): 295-304, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="9191874" MedlineID="97335208">Fischer S, Scheffler A, Kabelitz D: Oligoclonal in vitro response of CD4 T cells to vesicles of mistletoe extracts in mistletoe-treated cancer patients. Cancer Immunol Immunother 44 (3): 150-6, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="9878694" MedlineID="99096484">Stein GM, Schaller G, Pfüller U, et al.: Characterisation of granulocyte stimulation by thionins from European mistletoe and from wheat. Biochim Biophys Acta 1426 (1): 80-90, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="10368652" MedlineID="99297033">Stein GM, Schaller G, Pfüller U, et al.: Thionins from Viscum album L: influence of the viscotoxins on the activation of granulocytes. Anticancer Res 19 (2A): 1037-42, 1999 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="16160399">Hallek M: Interleukin-6-mediated cell growth in multiple myeloma--a role for Viscum album extracts? Onkologie 28 (8-9): 387, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="34">Schaller G, Urech K, Giannattasio M: Cytotoxicity of different viscotoxins and extracts from the European subspecies Viscum album L. Phytother Res  10 (6): 473-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="11984083" MedlineID="21978681">Maier G, Fiebig HH: Absence of tumor growth stimulation in a panel of 16 human tumor cell lines by mistletoe extracts in vitro. Anticancer Drugs 13 (4): 373-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="11279798" MedlineID="21175028">Zarkovic N, Vukovic T, Loncaric I, et al.: An overview on anticancer activities of the Viscum album extract Isorel. Cancer Biother Radiopharm 16 (1): 55-62, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="17094471">Zuzak TJ, Rist L, Eggenschwiler J, et al.: Paediatric medulloblastoma cells are susceptible to Viscum album (Mistletoe) preparations. Anticancer Res 26 (5A): 3485-92, 2006 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="16927523">Kelter G, Fiebig HH: Absence of tumor growth stimulation in a panel of 26 human tumor cell lines by mistletoe (Viscum album L.) extracts Iscador in vitro. Arzneimittelforschung 56 (6A): 435-40, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="17352237">Kelter G, Schierholz JM, Fischer IU, et al.: Cytotoxic activity and absence of tumor growth stimulation of standardized mistletoe extracts in human tumor models in vitro. Anticancer Res 27 (1A): 223-33, 2007 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="24397864">Weissenstein U, Kunz M, Urech K, et al.: Interaction of standardized mistletoe (Viscum album) extracts with chemotherapeutic drugs regarding cytostatic and cytotoxic effects in vitro. BMC Complement Altern Med 14: 6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="23133496">Podlech O, Harter PN, Mittelbronn M, et al.: Fermented mistletoe extract as a multimodal antitumoral agent in gliomas. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 2012: 501796, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="18570233">Cebović T, Spasić S, Popović M: Cytotoxic effects of the Viscum album L. extract on Ehrlich tumour cells in vivo. Phytother Res 22 (8): 1097-103, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="18314258">Seifert G, Jesse P, Laengler A, et al.: Molecular mechanisms of mistletoe plant extract-induced apoptosis in acute lymphoblastic leukemia in vivo and in vitro. Cancer Lett 264 (2): 218-28, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="18026191">Thies A, Dautel P, Meyer A, et al.: Low-dose mistletoe lectin-I reduces melanoma growth and spread in a scid mouse xenograft model. Br J Cancer 98 (1): 106-12, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="16412563">Van Huyen JP, Delignat S, Bayry J, et al.: Interleukin-12 is associated with the in vivo anti-tumor effect of mistletoe extracts in B16 mouse melanoma. Cancer Lett 243 (1): 32-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="17201168">Beuth J, Ko HL, Schneider H, et al.: Intratumoral application of standardized mistletoe extracts down regulates tumor weight via decreased cell proliferation, increased apoptosis and necrosis in a murine model. Anticancer Res 26 (6B): 4451-6, 2006 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="12553054">Braun JM, Ko HL, Schierholz JM, et al.: Standardized mistletoe extract augments immune response and down-regulates local and metastatic tumor growth in murine models. Anticancer Res 22 (6C): 4187-90, 2002 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="11820217">Pryme IF, Bardocz S, Pusztai A, et al.: Dietary mistletoe lectin supplementation and reduced growth of a murine non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Histol Histopathol 17 (1): 261-71, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="11251952" MedlineID="21149996">Elsässer-Beile U, Ruhnau T, Freudenberg N, et al.: Antitumoral effect of recombinant mistletoe lectin on chemically induced urinary bladder carcinogenesis in a rat model. Cancer 91 (5): 998-1004, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="12232491" MedlineID="22218560">Stauder H, Kreuser ED: Mistletoe extracts standardised in terms of mistletoe lectins (ML I) in oncology: current state of clinical research. Onkologie 25 (4): 374-80, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="3543783" MedlineID="87116901">Khwaja TA, Dias CB, Pentecost S: Recent studies on the anticancer activities of mistletoe (Viscum album) and its alkaloids. Oncology 43 (Suppl 1): 42-50, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="6853588" MedlineID="83213622">Berger M, Schmähl D: Studies on the tumor-inhibiting efficacy of Iscador in experimental animal tumors. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 105 (3): 262-5, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="16158932">Rostock M, Huber R, Greiner T, et al.: Anticancer activity of a lectin-rich mistletoe extract injected intratumorally into human pancreatic cancer xenografts. Anticancer Res 25 (3B): 1969-75, 2005 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="8233280" MedlineID="94051001">Jurin M, Zarković N, Hrzenjak M, et al.: Antitumorous and immunomodulatory effects of the Viscum album L. preparation Isorel. Oncology 50 (6): 393-8, 1993 Nov-Dec.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Human/Clinical Studies</Title><Para id="_36"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mistletoe</GlossaryTermRef> has been evaluated as a treatment for people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> in numerous <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical studies</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/>  </Para><Para id="_108">The mistletoe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> and products studied in clinical trials were Iscador, Eurixor, Helixor, Lektinol, Isorel,  abnobaVISCUM,<Reference refidx="21"/> and recombinant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044051" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lectin</GlossaryTermRef> ML-1. For more information, see   the appropriate subsections and   tables  in this section.</Para><Para id="_197">The findings from more than 50 clinical trials of mistletoe extracts in patients with cancer have been published, and several systematic reviews and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meta-analyses</GlossaryTermRef> of the results of these studies have been performed.  Three of the most recent systematic reviews addressed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> (QOL), survival, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptom</GlossaryTermRef> relief in patients with various cancer types.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="22"/>  Most studies reported an improvement in QOL, as did a noncontrolled, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044160" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nonrandomized</GlossaryTermRef>, real-world
study that analyzed patient registry data.<Reference refidx="23"/> </Para><Para id="_198">In one systematic review that examined 26 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled trials</GlossaryTermRef> (RCTs), 22 trials reported an improvement in QOL. All 10 of the nonRCTs also reported the same benefit. Improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>, emotional well-being, and concentration were reported. Some of the studies were well designed, while others reported weaknesses.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_203"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumor</GlossaryTermRef> response, QOL, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> were measured in a review of 21 RCTs of various cancers in which  different mistletoe preparations were used either alone, with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, or with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="18"/>  Survival times were included in 13 of the studies.  Most of the studies reported benefits for patients, although this review was limited by small sample size and methodological weaknesses. Thus, the authors were unable to suggest practice guidelines for the use of mistletoe.</Para><Para id="_204">The oldest of these three reviews investigated the results of 10 RCTs that used a variety of mistletoe extracts in patients with various malignancies. There was no difference in survival or other benefits for cancer patients who received mistletoe. Therefore, mistletoe was not recommended as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curative</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supportive care</GlossaryTermRef> therapy.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_37">A systematic review of all controlled clinical studies of mistletoe found consistent improvement in chemotherapy-associated fatigue as well as other QOL measures.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_38">Although mistletoe was found to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutically</GlossaryTermRef> effective in most of the reported studies, many of the studies had one or more major design weaknesses as mentioned above that raised doubts about the reliability of the findings. These weaknesses include the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_283" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Registration of small numbers of patients.</ListItem><ListItem>Presence of large numbers of patients who either were not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044029" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">evaluable</GlossaryTermRef> or were otherwise excluded from the analyses.</ListItem><ListItem>Failure to adequately document mistletoe use, mistletoe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef>, and/or interruptions of mistletoe use.</ListItem><ListItem>Absence of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control subjects</GlossaryTermRef> or use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044596" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">historical control subjects</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem>Use of inadequate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322881" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomization</GlossaryTermRef> procedures.</ListItem><ListItem>Absence of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285982" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">treatment blinding</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Extensive use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285981" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subset analysis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The measurement of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean</GlossaryTermRef> as opposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044941" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">median</GlossaryTermRef> survival.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_284">In addition, evaluation of the studies is often hindered by incomplete descriptions of the study design and by incomplete reporting of clinical data, including data about previous and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concurrent therapies</GlossaryTermRef> received by the patients. Note: In studies with small numbers of patients, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285974" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean survival time</GlossaryTermRef> can be greatly exaggerated if one or more patients exhibit unusually long survival; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655249" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">median survival</GlossaryTermRef>, therefore, is a less biased measure. </Para><Para id="_292">A selection of studies is discussed below, organized by the type of mistletoe extract used. Studies on Iscador are summarized in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269596#_194" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">Table  3</SummaryRef>. Studies on Helixor, abnobaVISCUM, Eurixor, Isorel, and Lektinol are summarized in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269596#_71" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">Table  4</SummaryRef>. Eurixor, Isorel, and Vysorel are no longer available  on the market for sale.</Para><SummarySection id="_125"><Title>Iscador</Title><SummarySection id="_301"><Title>Quality of life</Title><SummarySection id="_302"><Title>Miscellaneous cancers  </Title><Para id="_303">Although the quality of literature is limited by methodological flaws, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prospective</GlossaryTermRef> and controlled studies that explored the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of Iscador use on QOL in patients with cancer generally report positive effects in favor of complementary treatment. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meta-analysis</GlossaryTermRef> of several studies (RCTs: n = 9; non-RCTs: n = 4; patients n = 734) reported a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef> overall treatment effect in favor of Iscador application (standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean</GlossaryTermRef> deviation [SMD], 0.56; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.41–0.71; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="24"/> Tumor localization and  study design were not  significantly associated with a better or worse study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> following multivariable regression.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_304"><Title>Breast cancer</Title><Para id="_305">A randomized study of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043980" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postoperative</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446564" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">early-stage breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> patients (T1, 3N0, 2M0) who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclophosphamide,</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346515" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adriamycin</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluorouracil</GlossaryTermRef>  found that patients who also received IscadorM treatment, a <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> extract harvested from apple (Mali) trees  (n = 30), had significantly superior QOL ratings compared with patients who received chemotherapy alone (n = 31) (95% CI, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> ≤ .017).<Reference refidx="7"/> Significant improvements were noted in physical functioning, role functioning, emotional functioning, and social functioning. Improvements were also noted in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef>, nausea and vomiting, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>, fatigue, pain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046183" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dyspnea</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">insomnia,</GlossaryTermRef> and financial difficulties.<Reference refidx="7"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_306"><Title>Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) </Title><Para id="_307">At least two RCTs have assessed the QOL of patients with advanced NSCLC. Patients   who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carboplatin</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508951" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gemcitabine</GlossaryTermRef> or carboplatin/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pemetrexed</GlossaryTermRef>  and were randomly assigned to receive open-label IscadorQu treatment, a <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> extract harvested from oak (<ScientificName>Quercus</ScientificName>) trees, did not report statistically significant improvements in QOL  when compared with NSCLC patients who received carboplatin-based combinations alone.<Reference refidx="25"/> An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assessment</GlossaryTermRef> of QOL was performed in a study of  patients with NSCLC who received adjuvant chemotherapy with IscadorQu and IscadorU (harvested from elm [<Emphasis>Ulmi</Emphasis>] trees) or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin</GlossaryTermRef> B mixture (control) over 2 years.<Reference refidx="26"/> A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330183" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subjective improvement</GlossaryTermRef> in general well-being was more often seen in patients treated with Iscador.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_308"><Title>Osteosarcoma</Title><Para id="_309">QOL was assessed as a secondary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoint</GlossaryTermRef> in a small  (n = 20) study of patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>. Patients were  free from disease after their second <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapse</GlossaryTermRef> and  were randomly assigned to receive either open-label IscadorP <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, a <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> extract harvested from pine (Pini) trees, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">etoposide</GlossaryTermRef>. Patients who received Iscador therapy experienced significant improvements in overall (global) and individual QOL domains when compared with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">baseline</GlossaryTermRef> functioning (global health/QOL; 95% CI, 2.62–19.72; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .013).<Reference refidx="27"/> Improvements over baseline values were also reported in the following areas:</Para><ItemizedList id="_310" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Physical functioning (95% CI, 0.15–14.44; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .046).</ListItem><ListItem>Social functioning (95% CI, 4.64–18.88; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003).</ListItem><ListItem>Fatigue (95% CI, −16.31 to  −3.38; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .005).</ListItem><ListItem>Pain (95% CI, −18.83 to  −2.60; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .012).</ListItem><ListItem>Dyspnea (95% CI, −16.94 to  −8.32; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001). </ListItem><ListItem>Financial difficulties (95% CI, −16.21 to  −6.70; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_311"><Title>Ovarian cancer </Title><Para id="_312"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445074" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ovarian cancer</GlossaryTermRef> patients without metastases (n = 21 pairs) were randomly assigned  to receive adjuvant Iscador (host tree unspecified) or no further treatment. Significant improvements in QOL were noted, as assessed by the degree of <Emphasis>psychosomatic self-regulation</Emphasis>, described as the capacity for autonomous regulation of emotional, social, and psychological factors, within 12 months of treatment (estimated median difference: 0.58; 95% CI, 0.30–0.90; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0002).<Reference refidx="11"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_313"><Title>Uterine cancer </Title><Para id="_314">Secondary endpoint <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445094" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterine cancer</GlossaryTermRef> patients without metastases (randomized: n = 30 pairs; nonrandomized: n = 103 pairs) who  received adjuvant Iscador displayed significant improvements in psychosomatic self-regulation within 12 months of treatment when compared with women who received conventional oncological therapy alone (estimated median difference and 95% CI, 0.40 [0.15–0.70]; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0012; and 0.70 [0.25–1.15], <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0037, respectively).<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_315"><Title>Symptom management</Title><SummarySection id="_316"><Title>Breast cancer</Title><Para id="_317">In a study of postoperative early-stage breast cancer patients (T1, 3N0, 2M0) who were randomly assigned to receive open-label IscadorM therapy after chemotherapy (n = 30), a secondary endpoint analysis did not demonstrate statistically significant improvements in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045361" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neutropenia</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046270" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neutrophil</GlossaryTermRef> count &lt;1,000/µL) when compared with patients who received chemotherapy alone (n = 31).<Reference refidx="7"/>  </Para><Para id="_318">Another study (retrolective design) of postoperative early-stage breast cancer patients (T2, 4N0, 2M0) who received adjuvant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conventional treatment</GlossaryTermRef> (chemotherapy, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046367" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormonal therapy</GlossaryTermRef>) (n = 710) compared the outcomes of patients who received Iscador with patients who did not  receive any added therapy. Patients who received Iscador developed significantly less adverse <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef> reactions  associated with  conventional treatment compared with women treated with conventional therapy alone (n = 732) (16% vs. 54.0%, respectively; adjusted <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000618610" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">odds ratio</GlossaryTermRef> [OR], 0.47; 95% CI, 0.32–0.67; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/> Relief or significant reductions in nausea, vomiting, loss of appetite, headache, fatigue, depression, skin and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucosal</GlossaryTermRef> reactions (including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045789" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucositis</GlossaryTermRef>),  disturbed concentration and memory, and irritability were observed.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_319"><Title>Head and neck cancers</Title><Para id="_320">After <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046056" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">squamous cell</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesions</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046026" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">larynx</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046061" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharynx</GlossaryTermRef>, male patients who were randomly assigned to receive complementary IscadorQu treatment (n = 10) displayed significantly fewer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> from chemotherapy and radiation therapy (radiation therapy with 50–60 Gy, chemotherapy with cisplatin and fluorouracil) on the microcirculation and immunological capacities of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>  compared with men who received conventional treatment alone (n = 10) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .05).<Reference refidx="31"/>  Patients who received adjuvant IscadorQu treatment also displayed significant accelerations in the restitution process when compared with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control group</GlossaryTermRef> (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .05).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_321"><Title>Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) </Title><Para id="_322">Patients with advanced NSCLC who received carboplatin/gemcitabine or carboplatin/pemetrexed and  were randomly assigned to receive open-label IscadorQu treatment (n = 33) displayed the following reactions when compared with patients who received chemotherapy alone (n  = 39):<Reference refidx="25"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_346" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Significantly fewer hospitalizations (24% of Iscador-treated patients vs. 54% of control patients; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .016).</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy dose reductions (13% of Iscador-treated patients vs. 44% of control patients; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .005).</ListItem><ListItem>Grades 3 and 4 nonhematological toxicities (16% of Iscador-treated patients vs. 41% of control patients; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .043).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_347">The grades 3 and 4 hematological <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> was not significantly different between the groups.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_323"><Title>Survival</Title><SummarySection id="_324"><Title>Miscellaneous cancers </Title><Para id="_325">A systematic review and meta-analysis of several studies published from 1963 to 2014, including RCTs, found that adjuvant treatment with Iscador is associated with improved cancer survival outcomes when compared with conventional treatment alone.<Reference refidx="32"/> Pooled analysis of controlled clinical studies (32 studies; total n = 13,745) that investigated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overall survival</GlossaryTermRef> (OS) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">event-free survival</GlossaryTermRef> (EFS) (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disease-free survival</GlossaryTermRef> [DFS], <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044782" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression-free survival</GlossaryTermRef> [PFS] or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapse-free survival</GlossaryTermRef>, or the time until these events occurred in cancer patients), demonstrates a statistically significant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000618612" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hazard ratio</GlossaryTermRef> (HR) of 0.59 (95% CI, 0.53–0.65; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) in favor of Iscador treatment.  A significant difference in survival between cancer types was noted (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01), with the strongest association of Iscador use and general survival found in in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (HR, 0.43) and more modest outcomes in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (HR, 0.84). In the meta-analysis, randomization was performed in only 14 studies. While subgroup analysis displayed a greater association between EFS and OS in patients who received Iscador in nonrandomized clinical trials (HR, 0.56; CI, 0.50–0.62) compared with patients who were randomized (HR, 0.68; CI, 0.55–0.83); this difference is not statistically significant (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .13).<Reference refidx="32"/> Many of the studies used study designs, analytical methods, and/or cancer treatment <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimens</GlossaryTermRef> that were outdated. While moderate heterogeneity between study results was noted (I<Superscript>2</Superscript>,  50.9%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001), neither differences in design, sample size, nor publication year demonstrated significant effects on these survival outcomes. The reviewed studies were blinded; therefore, they ran the risk of performance <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bias</GlossaryTermRef>, given the knowledge of allocated interventions. It is  unlikely that performance bias affected study outcomes associated with general survival (which is the reason why the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> does not mandate blinding in survival studies); however, performance bias may exist for those reporting on EFS.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_326"><Title>Breast cancer</Title><Para id="_327">Primary breast cancer patients (without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrences</GlossaryTermRef>, lymphatic metastases, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415317" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distant metastases</GlossaryTermRef> at the initiation of study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045981" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">observation</GlossaryTermRef>; n = 84 pairs) who received Iscador therapy adjuvant to conventional treatment (surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy,  or hormone therapy) displayed prolonged cancer-specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survival rates</GlossaryTermRef> when matched to paired individuals with similar prognostic criteria who received conventional treatment alone (HR, 0.43; 95% CI, 0.27–0.68).<Reference refidx="8"/> In the same report, patients with breast cancer who were randomly assigned to receive Iscador did not demonstrate a significant extension of OS  when compared with  their matched pairs.<Reference refidx="8"/> </Para><Para id="_328">In another study,  OS was evaluated as a secondary endpoint in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nonmetastatic</GlossaryTermRef> breast cancer (T2, 4N0, 2M0) who underwent adjuvant  treatment <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concomitant</GlossaryTermRef> with regimented Iscador <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injections</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/> Women treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subcutaneous</GlossaryTermRef> Iscador therapy complementary to their conventional treatment regimen (n = 710) displayed significant extensions of overall <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496502" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mortality</GlossaryTermRef> when compared with patients treated with conventional therapy alone (n = 732) (adjusted HR, 0.46; 95% CI, 0.22–0.96; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .038).<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_329"><Title>Cervical cancer</Title><Para id="_330">Patients with metastatic (n = 66) or local (n = 102) cervical cancer who elected to receive Iscador in addition to conventional oncological treatment demonstrated significant extensions of OS when compared with women with similar prognostic criteria who received conventional treatment alone (HR and 95% CI, 0.37 [0.17–0.80] and 0.23 [0.14–0.39], respectively).<Reference refidx="9"/> However, this finding was not seen when women with metastatic cervical cancer were randomly assigned to receive open-label adjuvant Iscador.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_331"><Title>Colorectal cancer</Title><Para id="_332">Patients with surgically-treated, nonmetastatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (CRC) (stages I–III) (n = 429) who received Iscador treatment with conventional aftercare displayed a statistically significant extension of DFS (HR, 0.60; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .013)  when compared with CRC patients who received conventional therapy alone (n = 375) after a median observation period of 58 months for patients who received Iscador and 51 months for patients who received conventional therapy alone.<Reference refidx="33"/>  A secondary analysis of this data was preformed specific to CRC patients who received IscadorQu extract, a <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> extract harvested from oak (<ScientificName>Quercus</ScientificName>) trees. Patients who had specifically received IscadorQu extract (n = 106) displayed an estimated 69% risk reduction in metastasis formation (HR, 0.31; 95% CI, 0.13–0.711; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006) relative to conventionally-treated controls (n = 212).<Reference refidx="34"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_333"><Title>Melanoma </Title><Para id="_334">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045833" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase III</GlossaryTermRef> study of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef> patients (n = 102) with high-risk primary disease (stage II, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000681119" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Breslow thickness</GlossaryTermRef> &gt;3mm) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> metastasis (stage III, after curative dissection) treated with IscadorM found no clinical benefit of low-dose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef> in the disease-free interval  when compared with the control group (n = 102) after one year of treatment (or until <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor progression</GlossaryTermRef>).<Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_335"><Title>Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC)</Title><Para id="_336"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph node</GlossaryTermRef>–positive NSCLC patients (n = 87) who were randomly assigned to receive Iscador therapy (without concurrent treatment) displayed significant extensions in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655249" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">median survival</GlossaryTermRef> rates when compared with untreated controls.<Reference refidx="35"/> Clinical benefit in median survival was not observed in patients with nonmetastatic NSCLC.<Reference refidx="35"/> Similarly, a three-arm comparison with a sheep <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285966" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glycopeptide</GlossaryTermRef>, reported to be an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunostimulant</GlossaryTermRef> and an inhibitor of tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044131" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glycolysis</GlossaryTermRef>, and a vitamin B preparation (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef>) (n = 107), found no clinical benefit in median survival above placebo in patients with advanced NSCLC who were randomly assigned to receive IscadorQu and IscadorU (n = 105) after two years of open-label treatment.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_337"><Title>Osteosarcoma</Title><Para id="_338">Osteosarcoma patients who underwent a complete surgical resection after a second relapse were randomly assigned to receive IscadorP <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (subcutaneous injections three times a week) (n = 9) for 1 year. After a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> period of 12 years, patients displayed a 71% reduced risk of relapse (measured as postrelapse DFS; HR, 0.287; 95% CI, 0.076–0.884; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03) when compared with patients who received 6 months of oral etoposide treatment  (50 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> a day for 21 days, every 28 days) (n = 10).<Reference refidx="36"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_339"><Title>Ovarian cancer </Title><Para id="_340">Primary ovarian cancer patients without distant metastases (n = 21 pairs) who received Iscador therapy after conventional treatment (surgery and chemotherapy) displayed prolonged OS rates when compared with patients with similar prognostic criteria who received conventional treatment alone (HR, 0.47; 95% CI, 0.31–0.69; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0002).<Reference refidx="11"/> Patients who were randomized to receive Iscador treatment  did not display a significant difference in OS when compared with matched controls.  Patients with metastatic ovarian cancer, randomly assigned to receive complementary Iscador therapy (n = 20 pairs), also demonstrated a significant extension of OS when compared with matched pairs (HR, 0.33; 95% CI, 0.12–0.92; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .033), although a significant extension in OS was not observed in the nonrandomized arm.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_341"><Title>Pancreatic cancer </Title><Para id="_342">Patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> or metastatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (UICC stage III or stage IV) who were randomly assigned to receive open-label Iscador therapy as an adjuvant to <Emphasis>best supportive care</Emphasis> methods (n = 110) demonstrated prolonged survival when compared with patients under similar prognostic criteria who received supportive care alone (n = 110). The median OS was  4.8 months for patients  who received Iscador  and 2.2 months for patients who received supportive care alone (prognosis-adjusted HR, 0.49; 95% CI, 0.36–0.65; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="37"/> </Para><Para id="_482">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044120" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retrospective</GlossaryTermRef> analysis investigated the effects of mistletoe and chemotherapy with  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468790" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperthermia</GlossaryTermRef> versus mistletoe and chemotherapy in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative treatment</GlossaryTermRef> of patients with pancreatic cancer. The results of the analysis found a significant improvement in survival rates for patients who received all three treatments. Weaknesses of the analysis include the retrospective nature of the study, multiple types of chemotherapy (gemcitabine/nab-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045258" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paclitaxel</GlossaryTermRef>, 34%; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000711871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FOLFIRINOX</GlossaryTermRef>, 36%; gemcitabine, 30%) and mistletoe (e.g., Iscador, Abnoba viscum, or Helixor) regimens used, and the lack of a study arm for hyperthermia and chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="38"/> Furthermore, the study was not stratified despite enrolling patients who were previously treated with 1 to 3 lines of therapy, making the group median survival rates clinically insignificant.</Para><Para id="_343">In a retrospective analysis of patients with stages I to IV pancreatic cancer (n = 292) who received Iscador (host tree unspecified) therapy alone or adjuvant to conventional treatment (surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy, hormone therapy, or a combination) (n = 61),  a median survival of 6.58 months was reported.<Reference refidx="39"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_344"><Title>Uterine cancer </Title><Para id="_345">Patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">corpus uteri</GlossaryTermRef> cancer without distant metastases (n = 30 pairs) were randomly assigned to receive Iscador therapy adjuvant to conventional treatment (surgery or radiation therapy). Patients had longer OS (time from initial <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> to tumor-related death) than matched pairs of patients with similar prognostic criteria who received conventional treatment alone (HR, 0.36; 95% CI, 0.16–0.82; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .014).<Reference refidx="10"/>  However, corpus uteri cancer patients with distant metastases randomly assigned to receive adjuvant Iscador did not display a significant difference in OS when compared with matched controls who were randomly assigned to conventional oncologic care only.  In the nonrandomized portion of the study, corpus uteri cancer patients, with (n = 95 pairs) or without (n = 103 pairs) distant metastases, who  previously  received the complementary therapy, demonstrated a significant extension of OS when compared with matched pairs of similar prognostic criteria who received conventional treatment alone (prognosis-adjusted HR and 95% CI, 0.61 [0.39–0.93], <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .023 and 0.41 [0.26–0.63], <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001, respectively).<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><Table id="_194"><Title>Table 3.  Use of Iscador in Cancer Treatment: Clinical Reports Describing Therapeutic End Points<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="7"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="14.57%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="15.92%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="13.03%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="13.32%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="21.71%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="9.65%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="7" ColWidth="11.77%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference </entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design </entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Condition</GlossaryTermRef> or Cancer Type </entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)<Superscript>b</Superscript> </entry><entry Align="Center">Results</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Concurrent Therapy</GlossaryTermRef> Used<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Level of Evidence</GlossaryTermRef> Score<Superscript>d</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1">DFS = disease-free survival; LN+ = lymph node–positive disease; No. = number; OS = overall survival; QOL = quality of life.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For more information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Number of patients treated plus number of patients controlled may not equal number of patients enrolled; number of patients enrolled = number of patients initially recruited/considered by the researchers who conducted a study; number of patients treated = number of enrolled patients who were administered the treatment being studied and for whom results were reported; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044596" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">historical control subjects</GlossaryTermRef> are not included in number of patients enrolled.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Chemotherapy, radiation therapy, hormonal therapy, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytokine therapy</GlossaryTermRef> administered/allowed at the same time as mistletoe therapy.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>d</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>e</Superscript>Control patients were treated with a vitamin B mixture as a placebo; 100 additional evaluable patients were treated with Polyerga Neu, a sheep spleen glycopeptide reported to be an immunostimulant and an inhibitor of tumor cell glycolysis; treatment with Polyerga Neu was not found to be beneficial.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>f</Superscript>Radiation therapy for metastases distant from the site of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> was permitted; radiation therapy to the primary tumor site or use of other anticancer treatment was not permitted.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>g</Superscript>Among 10,226 cancer patients enrolled in a retrospective matched-pair, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case-control study</GlossaryTermRef>, 1,751 had been treated with Iscador or another mistletoe product and 8,475 had not been treated with mistletoe; from the 8,475 untreated patients, two sets of matched pairs were formed for prospective studies; in the prospective studies, one member of each pair was randomly assigned to be treated with Iscador and the other member served as a control subject.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>h</Superscript>Patients were strictly matched according to sex, year of birth ± 3 years, year of diagnosis ± 3 years, type of tumor, stage of disease, and conventional therapy received.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="26"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Lung, non-small cell, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285970" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inoperable</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>408; 105; 107<Superscript>e</Superscript></entry><entry>Subjective improvement in QOL</entry><entry>Yes<Superscript>f</Superscript></entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335125" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiA</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="35"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Lung, non-small cell, stages I–IV </entry><entry>218; 87; 96</entry><entry>Improved median survival, LN+ patients only</entry><entry>No</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335125" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiA</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="5"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Melanoma, stages II–III</entry><entry>204; 102; 102</entry><entry>No improvement in DFS or OS rates</entry><entry>No</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335125" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiA</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="40"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Pancreatic, advanced or metastatic</entry><entry>220; 110; 110</entry><entry>Improved OS </entry><entry>No</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335125" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiA</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="27"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Osteosarcoma, second metastatic relapse</entry><entry>20; 9 (viscum); 11 (etoposide)</entry><entry>Improved DFS compared with etoposide group</entry><entry>No</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335129" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiDii</LOERef> </entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="41"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Breast</entry><entry>95; 30 (IscadorM) and 34 (HelixorA); 31</entry><entry>No differences in the primary outcome between groups</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="29"/></entry><entry>Comparative, retrolective, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285673" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cohort study</GlossaryTermRef> </entry><entry>Breast, stages I–IV</entry><entry>1,442; 710; 732</entry><entry>Fewer adverse drug reactions with mistletoe</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335133" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2B</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="28"/></entry><entry>Comparative, retrolective, cohort study </entry><entry>Melanoma, stages II–III</entry><entry>686; 329; 357</entry><entry>Improved overall disease-specific  survival</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335132" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2A</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>Cohort study</entry><entry>Breast, stage III</entry><entry>8,475<Superscript>g</Superscript>; 17<Superscript>h</Superscript>; 17<Superscript>h</Superscript> </entry><entry>Improved mean survival</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>Cohort study </entry><entry>Various types, stages I–IV</entry><entry>8,475<Superscript>g</Superscript>; 39<Superscript>h</Superscript>; 39<Superscript>h</Superscript></entry><entry>Improved mean survival</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>Cohort study </entry><entry>Various types, stages I–IV</entry><entry>10,226<Superscript>g</Superscript>; 396<Superscript>h</Superscript>; 396<Superscript>h</Superscript></entry><entry>Improved mean survival</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="33"/></entry><entry>Retrospective, observational, cohort study </entry><entry>Nonmetastatic colorectal</entry><entry>804; 429; 375</entry><entry>Lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046145" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incidence</GlossaryTermRef> of diarrhea, nausea, loss of appetite, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045667" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dermatitis</GlossaryTermRef>, fatigue, and mucositis</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="38"/></entry><entry>Retrospective analysis study</entry><entry>Pancreatic</entry><entry>206 (subgroup of 142 using survival data on 124); 25 (chemotherapy alone); 48 (chemotherapy and mistletoe), 50 (chemotherapy, mistletoe, and hyperthermia); 1 (chemotherapy and hyperthermia)</entry><entry> Improved  survival was reported in the triplet arm</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335132" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2A</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="39"/></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044575" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nonconsecutive case series</GlossaryTermRef> </entry><entry>Pancreatic </entry><entry>292; 292; various historical controls</entry><entry>Improved median survival</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335150" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iiiA</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_126"><Title>Helixor</Title><SummarySection id="_478"><Title>Safety</Title><Para id="_479">The first <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) trial of mistletoe (HelixorM) is completed.<Reference refidx="42"/>  A standard 3 + 3 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I</GlossaryTermRef> design was used. The study included 21 patients with heavily pretreated metastatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solid tumors</GlossaryTermRef>.  A dose of 600 mg IV 3 times a week was determined to be the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000546597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maximum tolerated dose</GlossaryTermRef> recommended for future <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045831" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase II</GlossaryTermRef> trials.  Three patients had tumor shrinkage, though none met <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691009" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RECIST</GlossaryTermRef> criteria for a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045819" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">partial response</GlossaryTermRef>.  The disease control rate was 23.8% and the median <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045884" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stable disease</GlossaryTermRef> was 15 weeks. Two patients had stable disease for almost 6 months. The most common treatment-related adverse events were fatigue (28.6%), nausea (9.5%), and chills (9.5%). A secondary endpoint analysis found that QOL was significantly improved during treatment as measured by the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-General assessment, with a change in score from 79.7 to 93 between week 1 and week 4.<Reference refidx="42"/>  Future research should be conducted to examine the effect of mistletoe on chemotherapy tolerability and to gather more information about its effect on QOL, PFS, and OS.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_417"><Title>Quality  of life</Title><SummarySection id="_418"><Title>Miscellaneous cancers</Title><Para id="_419">Patients with cancer (breast, n = 67; ovarian, n = 66; NSCLC, n = 91) were randomly assigned to receive open-label treatment with HelixorA (<ScientificName>viscum album</ScientificName> abietis) concurrent with standard chemotherapy (n = 115). These patients demonstrated significant improvements in QOL (as assessed by Functional Living Index-Cancer, Karnofsky Performance Index, and Traditional Chinese Medicine Index  questionnaires) when compared with patients in the control group,  who received conventional oncologic treatment and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lentinan</GlossaryTermRef>, an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000739791" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunomodulating agent</GlossaryTermRef> derived from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285741" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">shiitake mushroom</GlossaryTermRef> (n = 109) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05).<Reference refidx="43"/> Patients who received HelixorA also experienced  fewer adverse events (AEs) from chemotherapy when compared with  the control group (52 AEs reported in the HelixorA and chemotherapy group  vs. 90 AEs in the control group).</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_420"><Title>Symptom management  </Title><SummarySection id="_421"><Title>Malignant pleural effusion</Title><Para id="_422"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044294" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pleurodesis</GlossaryTermRef> with HelixorM   (<ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> mali) may be an effective procedure to control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000524207" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant pleural effusions</GlossaryTermRef> (MPE) in patients with advanced lung cancer.<Reference refidx="44"/> Over half (52%) of lung cancer patients treated with HelixorM pleurodesis (n = 42) were free from recurrence of MPE one month after the procedure.  Neither patient characteristics (including age, gender, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467841" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">histopathology</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic treatment</GlossaryTermRef>), nor MPE characteristics (including location and chemistry) was deemed significantly associated with the outcome of HelixorM pleurodesis in this study.<Reference refidx="44"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_423"><Title>Survival</Title><SummarySection id="_424"><Title>Breast cancer</Title><Para id="_425">Patients with breast cancer (T1–3, N0–3, M0; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local recurrence</GlossaryTermRef>) were randomly assigned to receive Helixor adjuvant to conventional therapy (i.e., surgery and radiation therapy) (n = 192). These patients demonstrated a significant extension in 5-year survival when compared with patients who received conventional treatment alone (n = 274) (5-year survival rates, 69.1% vs. 59.7%, respectively) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .048).<Reference refidx="45"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_426"><Title>Colorectal cancer </Title><Para id="_427">Patients with metastatic CRC were randomly assigned to receive Helixor adjuvant to chemotherapy (n = 20). These patients demonstrated significant extensions in mean survival (26.7 ± 11.9 months in complete/partial responders) when compared with patients randomly assigned to receive chemotherapy alone (n = 20) (13.6 ± 4.4 months in complete/partial responders).<Reference refidx="46"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_428"><Title>abnobaVISCUM</Title><SummarySection id="_429"><Title>Quality of life</Title><SummarySection id="_430"><Title>Breast cancer</Title><Para id="_431">As per QLQ-C30 function scales, health-related QOL in patients with breast cancer (stages I–III) who received abnobaVISCUMM concurrent with chemotherapy (n = 270) remained stable throughout the course of chemotherapy and significantly improved 4 weeks after treatment (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) when compared with the initial visit.<Reference refidx="47"/>   Patients also showed significant improvements above baseline in all parameters of the QLQ-BR23 function scale (a QOL module specific to breast cancer) at final examination (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_432"><Title>Stomach cancer</Title><Para id="_433">Postoperative patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454513" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastric cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (stage IB or stage II) were randomly assigned to receive abnobaVISCUMQ adjuvant to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (n = 15). These patients  demonstrated a significant improvement in <Emphasis>global health status</Emphasis> (a parameter constructed by totaling scores on two questions from the QLQ-C30 questionnaire) at week 16 and at completion of treatment (week 24), when compared with patients who received oral chemotherapy alone (n = 14) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0098).<Reference refidx="48"/>  All other function and symptom scales of the QLQ-C30 and the QLQ-STO22 (a QOL module specific to stomach cancer) did not show statistical significance when  abnobaVISCUMQ treatment was added.<Reference refidx="48"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_434"><Title>Symptom management </Title><SummarySection id="_435"><Title>Miscellaneous cancers</Title><Para id="_436">Patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef>  were treated with abnobaVISCUM pleurodesis for MPE (n = 62). These patients demonstrated a significant improvement in mean <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response rate</GlossaryTermRef> (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) when compared with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reference values</GlossaryTermRef> (97% and 64%, respectively).<Reference refidx="49"/> Forty-nine patients (79%) demonstrated a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045652" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complete response</GlossaryTermRef> (no recurrence of MPE at least 4 weeks after treatment) and 11 patients (18%) demonstrated partial response (reaccumulation of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045843" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pleural effusion</GlossaryTermRef> under 50% of the pretreatment volume), while 2 patients (3.23%) did not respond (recurrence of pleural effusion within 4 weeks after treatment) to mistletoe-mediated pleurodesis with abnobaVISCUM.<Reference refidx="49"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_437"><Title>Colorectal cancer </Title><Para id="_438"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Symptomatic</GlossaryTermRef> relief was reported by 40% of patients with metastatic CRC who were resistant to ﬂuorouracil and leucovorin (5-FU/LV)-based chemotherapy and received abnobaVISCUMQ therapy (n = 25). Symptomatic relief was  assessed as a secondary endpoint measure for a median duration of 14 weeks.<Reference refidx="50"/> Relief of the following symptoms was reported:</Para><ItemizedList id="_439" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Nausea and vomiting (24% of patients).</ListItem><ListItem>Diarrhea (12% of patients).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Constipation</GlossaryTermRef> (8% of patients).</ListItem><ListItem>Fatigue (24% of patients).</ListItem><ListItem>Dyspnea (8% of patients).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_440"><Title>Stomach cancer</Title><Para id="_441">In one study, postoperative patients with gastric cancer (stage IB or stage II) were randomly assigned to receive abnobaVISCUMQ adjuvant to oral chemotherapy (n = 15). The secondary endpoint analyses demonstrated a significant improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046067" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukocyte</GlossaryTermRef> (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">eosinophil</GlossaryTermRef>  (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0036) counts when compared with patients who received oral chemotherapy alone (n = 14) after a 24-week <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">treatment cycle</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="48"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_442"><Title>Survival</Title><SummarySection id="_443"><Title>Bladder cancer</Title><Para id="_444">A marker tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef> rate of 55.6% (95% CI, 38.1–72.1) was achieved in 20 of 36 patients with nonmuscle-invasive bladder cancer (Ta G1/G2 or T1 G1/G2) 12 weeks after beginning bladder <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">instillation</GlossaryTermRef> therapy with abnobaVISCUMF (once a week for 6 weeks).<Reference refidx="51"/> Of the 19 evaluable patients, 14 (73.7%) did not have recurrent tumor at 1 year after initiation of treatment (95% CI, 48.8%–90.9%), corresponding to a 1-year recurrence rate of 26.3% (95% CI, 9.1%–51.2%).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_445"><Title>Colorectal cancer</Title><Para id="_446">Objective tumor response was not observed in a phase II study of patients with metastatic CRC who were resistant to 5-FU/LV-based chemotherapy and received abnobaVISCUMQ therapy for a median time period of 14 weeks. Stable disease was noted in 21 of 25 patients (84%), lasting for a median of 2.5 months (range; 1.5–7 months).<Reference refidx="50"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_447"><Title>Eurixor</Title><Para id="_448">Eurixor is no longer available on the market for sale.</Para><SummarySection id="_449"><Title>Quality of life</Title><SummarySection id="_450"><Title>Colorectal cancer</Title><Para id="_451">Patients with metastatic CRC were randomly assigned to receive Eurixor adjuvant to standard cancer treatment (n = 38). These patients demonstrated improved QOL (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0001) when compared with patients randomly assigned to receive standard treatment alone (n = 41).<Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_452"><Title>Symptom management</Title><SummarySection id="_453"><Title>Breast cancer</Title><Para id="_454">Patients with breast cancer (UICC stages I–IIIB) underwent postoperative chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or hormone therapy, and received complementary treatment with Eurixor (n = 219) for a median time period of 270 days. These patients demonstrated significant improvements in disease- or therapy-induced adverse reactions (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) when compared with patients who received standard cancer therapy alone (n = 470) at up to 285 days of follow-up.<Reference refidx="54"/>  Significant improvements in nausea, appetite reduction, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> pain, fatigue, depression, memory, and irritability/restlessness were reported (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001, in each subgroup).</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_455"><Title>Survival</Title><SummarySection id="_456"><Title>Bladder cancer</Title><Para id="_457">Patients with bladder cancer (pTa G1/G2) (n = 45) received subcutaneous Eurixor injections after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transurethral resection</GlossaryTermRef>. These patients did not demonstrate differences in time-to-first recurrence, total number of recurrences, or recurrence-free outcomes at up to 18 months after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000589417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary treatment</GlossaryTermRef> compared with patients who were randomly assigned to receive no adjuvant treatment.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_458"><Title>Head and neck cancers</Title><Para id="_459">Patients treated with Eurixor before and after resection of squamous cell carcinomas of the head and neck, with or without follow-up radiation therapy, demonstrated no difference in DFS when compared with patients who received surgery alone or surgery followed by radiation therapy, without adjuvant Eurixor treatment.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_460"><Title>Isorel</Title><Para id="_461">Isorel is no longer available on the market for sale.</Para><SummarySection id="_462"><Title>Biomarker study</Title><SummarySection id="_463"><Title>Gastrointestinal cancers</Title><Para id="_464"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044076" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Perioperative</GlossaryTermRef> use of Isorel in patients with cancer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive tract</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046414" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophageal</GlossaryTermRef>, stomach, pancreatic, ileac, colorectal) has been shown to increase the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphocyte</GlossaryTermRef> count in patients within 14 days of administration.<Reference refidx="55"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_465"><Title>Survival</Title><SummarySection id="_466"><Title>Colorectal cancer</Title><Para id="_467">Patients with advanced CRC (Dukes C and D) were randomly assigned to receive Isorel along with adjuvant  postoperative chemotherapy with 5-FU (6 cycles) (n = 29). These patients demonstrated prolonged survival (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05) when compared with patients who  received postoperative chemotherapy only (n = 21) and patients who received surgery only (n = 14) without postoperative chemotherapy or Isorel treatment (n = 14).<Reference refidx="56"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_468"><Title>Lektin/Lektinol</Title><SummarySection id="_469"><Title>Quality of life</Title><SummarySection id="_470"><Title>Breast cancer</Title><Para id="_471">Patients with breast cancer  were randomly assigned to receive open-label PS76A (an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aqueous</GlossaryTermRef> mistletoe extract standardized to the galactoside-specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mistletoe lectin</GlossaryTermRef> [ML]) adjuvant to chemotherapy (n = 176). These patients demonstrated improved QOL when compared with patients who received chemotherapy alone.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_472">In a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045673" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">double-blind study</GlossaryTermRef>, patients with breast cancer (stages II–III) were randomly assigned to receive PS76A2 (Lektinol; 30 ng ML/mL) adjuvant to cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, and fluorouracil (CMF) chemotherapy (4 cycles) for a period of 15 consecutive weeks (n = 65). These patients demonstrated statistically significant improvements in self-assessments of QOL (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0121 and <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0021 for GLQ-8 and Spitzer’s uniscale, respectively) when compared with patients who were randomly assigned to receive chemotherapy treatment alone (n = 66).<Reference refidx="57"/> Only the medium dose (30 ng ML/mL) indicated a significant preventative effect against placebo; no treatment effect of low- or high-dose Lektinol (10 ng ML/mL or 70 ng ML/mL) was established against the placebo.  In a second confirmatory study, superiority of complementary Lektinol (30 ng ML/mL) (n = 176) over the  placebo (n = 176) was observed according to  three FACT-G subscales (physical, emotional, and functional well-being) assessed during the fourth CMF cycle (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="58"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_407"><Title>Systematic Reviews/Meta-analyses of Various <ScientificName>Viscum Album</ScientificName> Extract (VAE) Types</Title><SummarySection id="_408"><Title>Quality of life</Title><SummarySection id="_409"><Title>Miscellaneous cancers</Title><Para id="_410">Some systematic reviews have found that studies of better methodological quality typically show that  <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> extracts (VAEs) have few beneficial effects on QOL in cancer,<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="59"/> while others studies suggest that mistletoe extracts produce a significant, though medium-sized, effect on QOL in cancer patients (mean difference  = 0.61; 95% CI, 0.41–0.81, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00001).<Reference refidx="60"/></Para><Para id="_411">However, another systematic review reached different conclusions. In a review consisting of 26 RCTs, 22 reported a benefit of mistletoe therapy (supplied with or without concomitant surgery, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy), whereas 3 reported no difference, and 1 did not indicate a result.<Reference refidx="22"/> All 10 nonRCTs  reported a benefit of VAE treatment, whether it was supplied with or without concomitant therapy.<Reference refidx="22"/> Among the studies designated as higher in methodological quality, most reported a benefit of VAE treatment, whereas one reported no difference from standard oncological treatment. Most consistently, studies reported improvements regarding the following:<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_412" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> Coping.</ListItem><ListItem>Fatigue.</ListItem><ListItem>Sleep.</ListItem><ListItem>Exhaustion.</ListItem><ListItem>Energy.</ListItem><ListItem>Nausea.</ListItem><ListItem>Vomiting.</ListItem><ListItem>Appetite.</ListItem><ListItem>Depression.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Anxiety</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Ability to work.</ListItem><ListItem>Emotional and functional well-being.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_413"><Title>Survival</Title><SummarySection id="_414"><Title>Miscellaneous cancers</Title><Para id="_415">Systematic reviews reported inconsistent results regarding the efficacy of mistletoe treatment on survival outcomes on the basis of methodological quality of the study.<Reference refidx="61"/>  In a review that consisted of 28 publications (n = 2,639) investigating a wide range of cancers (bladder, breast, cervix, lungs, uterus, ovaries, colon, stomach, pancreas, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gliomas</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef>, melanomas, and osteosarcomas), most studies did not show that adjuvant mistletoe had an effect on survival, especially those of high methodological quality.<Reference refidx="62"/>  This finding is consistent with other review articles. In an investigation of 13 RCTs, 6 showed evidence of a survival benefit, but none of these studies were of high methodological quality.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_416">In another review of 23 controlled clinical studies (16 randomized, 2 quasi-randomized, and 5 nonrandomized) that investigated the use of VAE in patients with cancers of the breast, lung, stomach, colon, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>, head and neck, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476624" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genitals</GlossaryTermRef>, bladder, melanomas, and gliomas, positive effects on survival were indicated in 8 studies and tumor remission was supported by 1 study.<Reference refidx="16"/> Four studies reported no effect on survival, one indicated no effect on DFS, two reported no benefit of treatment on tumor recurrence, and three indicated no effect on cancer remission.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><Table id="_71"><Title>Table 4.     Use of Other Mistletoe Products in Cancer Treatment: Clinical Reports Describing Therapeutic End Points<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="8"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="21.35%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="7.05%"/><ColSpec ColName="col03" ColNum="3" ColWidth="14.02%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="4.64%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="9.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="6" ColWidth="11.88%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="7" ColWidth="6.22%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="8" ColWidth="25.53%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference </entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design</entry><entry Align="Center">Product Tested</entry><entry Align="Center">Condition or Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry Align="Center">Results</entry><entry Align="Center">Concurrent Therapy Used<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry><entry Align="Center">Level of Evidence Score<Superscript>d</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1" RowSep="0">DFS = disease-free  survival; No. =  number; QOL = quality of life.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1" RowSep="0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For more information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary     of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef> for additional information and definition of terms.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1" RowSep="0"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Number of patients treated plus number of patients controlled may not equal number of patients enrolled; number of patients enrolled = number of patients initially  recruited/considered by the researchers who conducted a study; number of patients treated = number of enrolled patients who were administered the treatment being studied and for whom results were reported; historical control subjects are not included in number of patients enrolled.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1" RowSep="0"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Chemotherapy, radiation therapy, hormonal therapy, or cytokine therapy administered/allowed at the same time as mistletoe therapy.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1" RowSep="0"><Superscript>d</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>e</Superscript>This was a four-arm trial; patients were randomly assigned to surgery only or to surgery plus radiation therapy, followed by a second randomization to no mistletoe treatment or to treatment with Eurixor; the resulting treatment groups contained the following numbers of evaluable patients: surgery only  = 105, surgery plus Eurixor = 97, surgery plus radiation therapy = 137, and surgery plus radiation therapy plus 
Eurixor = 138; radiation therapy and Eurixor treatment overlapped; no treatment approach was superior in terms of disease-free survival, disease-specific survival, improvement in QOL, or stimulation of 
the immune system; in the table, mistletoe-treated and nontreated (control) patients were grouped (i.e., number treated = 97 + 138 = 235, and number control = 105 + 137 = 242).</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="3"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Eurixor</entry><entry>Bladder, noninvasive</entry><entry>45; 23; 22</entry><entry>DFS did not vary between groups</entry><entry>No</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335128" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiDi</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="63"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Eurixor</entry><entry>Brain, glioma; 74% of patients, stages III–IV; 26% of 
		             patients,
		             no stage
		          information
</entry><entry>47;        20; 18</entry><entry>Improved survival,
		             					          stages
                                          					          III–IV
				         			         patients
                                           				           	           only
</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335125" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiA</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Eurixor</entry><entry>Colorectal, metastatic</entry><entry>107; 38; 41</entry><entry>Improved QOL</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="2"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Eurixor</entry><entry>Head and neck,
                                          squamous
                                              cell,
                                            stages
                                             I–IV
</entry><entry>495; 235<Superscript>e</Superscript>;  242<Superscript>e</Superscript></entry><entry>No differences in DFS between groups</entry><entry>Yes<Superscript>e</Superscript></entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335128" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiDi</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="45"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Helixor</entry><entry>Breast, stages I–III</entry><entry>692; 192 (Helixor) and 177 (chemotherapy); 274</entry><entry>Improved survival</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335125" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiA</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="46"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Helixor</entry><entry>Colorectal, metastatic</entry><entry>60; 20; 20</entry><entry>Improved mean survival</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335125" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiA</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="43"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Helixor</entry><entry>Breast, ovarian, and non-small cell lung </entry><entry>224; 115; 109</entry><entry>Improved QOL</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="41"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>HelixorA, IscadorM</entry><entry>Breast</entry><entry>95; 34 (HelixorA) and 30 (IscadorM); 31</entry><entry>No differences in the primary outcome between groups</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>Randomized controlled trial</entry><entry>PS76A (Lektin)</entry><entry>Breast</entry><entry>352; 176; 176</entry><entry>Improved QOL</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="57"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Lektinol</entry><entry>Breast</entry><entry>261; 195; 66</entry><entry>Improved QOL</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="58"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Lektinol</entry><entry>Breast</entry><entry>352; 176; 176</entry><entry>Improved QOL</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="56"/></entry><entry>Randomized trial</entry><entry>Isorel</entry><entry>Colorectal</entry><entry>64; 50; 14 </entry><entry>Improved survival and tolerance to either adjuvant or palliative treatment</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335125" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiA</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="55"/></entry><entry>Nonrandomized controlled trial</entry><entry>Isorel</entry><entry>Digestive tract</entry><entry>70; 40; 30</entry><entry>Enhanced cellular immunity and improved QOL</entry><entry>No</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="50"/></entry><entry>Nonrandomized controlled trial</entry><entry>abnobaVISCUM <ScientificName>Quercus</ScientificName></entry><entry>Metastatic colorectal</entry><entry>25; 25; none</entry><entry>No objective tumor response</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335137" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Diii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="21"/></entry><entry>Nonrandomized controlled trial</entry><entry><ScientificName>Viscum fraxini</ScientificName>-2</entry><entry>Hepatocellular carcinoma</entry><entry>23; 23; none</entry><entry>Improved survival </entry><entry>No</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335136" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Dii</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_35_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_35_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10928154" MedlineID="20383289">Lenartz D, Dott U, Menzel J, et al.: Survival of glioma patients after complementary treatment with galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe. Anticancer Res 20 (3B): 2073-6, 2000 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11165126" MedlineID="21094742">Steuer-Vogt MK, Bonkowsky V, Ambrosch P, et al.: The effect of an adjuvant mistletoe treatment programme in resected head and neck cancer patients: a randomised controlled clinical trial. Eur J Cancer 37 (1): 23-31, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="12050495" MedlineID="22045521">Goebell PJ, Otto T, Suhr J, et al.: Evaluation of an unconventional treatment modality with mistletoe lectin to prevent recurrence of superficial bladder cancer: a randomized phase II trial. J Urol 168 (1): 72-5, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11347286" MedlineID="21245848">Grossarth-Maticek R, Kiene H, Baumgartner SM, et al.: Use of Iscador, an extract of European mistletoe (Viscum album), in cancer treatment: prospective nonrandomized and randomized matched-pair studies nested within a cohort study. Altern Ther Health Med 7 (3): 57-66, 68-72, 74-6 passim, 2001 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="14746858">Kleeberg UR, Suciu S, Bröcker EB, et al.: Final results of the EORTC 18871/DKG 80-1 randomised phase III trial. rIFN-alpha2b versus rIFN-gamma versus ISCADOR M versus observation after surgery in melanoma patients with either high-risk primary (thickness &gt;3 mm) or regional lymph node metastasis. Eur J Cancer 40 (3): 390-402, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Viscum album. In: Homoeopathic Pharmacopoeia Convention of the United States: Homoeopathic Pharmacopoeia of the United States. 2002, Monograph 9444 Visc.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Tröger W, Jezdić S, Ždrale Z, et al.: Quality of life and neutropenia in patients with early stage breast cancer: a randomized pilot study comparing additional treatment with mistletoe extract to chemotherapy alone
. Breast Cancer: Basic and Clinical Research  3: 35-45, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="17057389">Grossarth-Maticek R, Ziegler R: Prospective controlled cohort studies on long-term therapy of breast cancer patients with a mistletoe preparation (Iscador). Forsch Komplementmed 13 (5): 285-92, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="17596694">Grossarth-Maticek R, Ziegler R: Prospective controlled cohort studies on long-term therapy of cervical cancer patients with a mistletoe preparation (Iscador). Forsch Komplementmed 14 (3): 140-7, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="18499556">Grossarth-Maticek R, Ziegler R: Randomized and non-randomized prospective controlled cohort studies in matched pair design for the long-term therapy of corpus uteri cancer patients with a mistletoe preparation (Iscador). Eur J Med Res 13 (3): 107-20, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="18074761">Grossarth-Maticek R, Ziegler R: Prospective controlled cohort studies on long-term therapy of ovairian cancer patients with mistletoe (Viscum album L.) extracts iscador. Arzneimittelforschung 57 (10): 665-78, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="16739342">Bar-Sela G, Goldberg H, Beck D, et al.: Reducing malignant ascites accumulation by repeated intraperitoneal administrations of a Viscum album extract. Anticancer Res 26 (1B): 709-13, 2006 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Wetzel D, Schäfer M: Results of a randomised placebo-controlled multicentre study with PS76A2 (standardised mistletoe preparation) in patients with breast cancer receiving adjuvant chemotherapy. [Abstract] Phytomedicine  7 (Suppl 2): A-SL-66, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="15550588">Schöffski P, Riggert S, Fumoleau P, et al.: Phase I trial of intravenous aviscumine (rViscumin) in patients with solid tumors: a study of the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer New Drug Development Group. Ann Oncol 15 (12): 1816-24, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="12232491" MedlineID="22218560">Stauder H, Kreuser ED: Mistletoe extracts standardised in terms of mistletoe lectins (ML I) in oncology: current state of clinical research. Onkologie 25 (4): 374-80, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="12730032">Kienle GS, Berrino F, Büssing A, et al.: Mistletoe in cancer - a systematic review on controlled clinical trials. Eur J Med Res 8 (3): 109-19, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="19519890">Kienle GS, Glockmann A, Schink M, et al.: Viscum album L. extracts in breast and gynaecological cancers: a systematic review of clinical and preclinical research. J Exp Clin Cancer Res 28: 79, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="18425885">Horneber MA, Bueschel G, Huber R, et al.: Mistletoe therapy in oncology. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (2): CD003297, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="17507307">Kienle GS, Kiene H: Complementary cancer therapy: a systematic review of prospective clinical trials on anthroposophic mistletoe extracts. Eur J Med Res 12 (3): 103-19, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="12949804">Ernst E, Schmidt K, Steuer-Vogt MK: Mistletoe for cancer? A systematic review of randomised clinical trials. Int J Cancer 107 (2): 262-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="14710208">Mabed M, El-Helw L, Shamaa S: Phase II study of viscum fraxini-2 in patients with advanced hepatocellular carcinoma. Br J Cancer 90 (1): 65-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="20483874">Kienle GS, Kiene H: Review article: Influence of Viscum album L (European mistletoe) extracts on quality of life in cancer patients: a systematic review of controlled clinical studies. Integr Cancer Ther 9 (2): 142-57, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="32478590">Oei SL, Thronicke A, Kröz M, et al.: Impact of Oncological Therapy and Viscum album L Treatment on Cancer-Related Fatigue and Internal Coherence in Nonmetastasized Breast Cancer Patients. Integr Cancer Ther 19: 1534735420917211, 2020 Jan-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="21747894">Büssing A, Raak C, Ostermann T: Quality of life and related dimensions in cancer patients treated with mistletoe extract (iscador): a meta-analysis. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 2012: 219402, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="23218588">Bar-Sela G, Wollner M, Hammer L, et al.: Mistletoe as complementary treatment in patients with advanced non-small-cell lung cancer treated with carboplatin-based combinations: a randomised phase II study. Eur J Cancer 49 (5): 1058-64, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="26">Dold U, Edler L, Mäurer HCh, et al., eds.: [Adjuvant Cancer Therapy in Advanced Non-Small Cell Bronchial Cancer: Multicentric Controlled Studies To Test the Efficacy of Iscador and Polyerga]. Georg Thieme Verlag, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="24803944">Longhi A, Reif M, Mariani E, et al.: A Randomized Study on Postrelapse Disease-Free Survival with Adjuvant Mistletoe versus Oral Etoposide in Osteosarcoma Patients. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 2014: 210198, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="15727163">Augustin M, Bock PR, Hanisch J, et al.: Safety and efficacy of the long-term adjuvant treatment of primary intermediate- to high-risk malignant melanoma (UICC/AJCC stage II and III) with a standardized fermented European mistletoe (Viscum album L.) extract. Results from a multicenter, comparative, epidemiological cohort study in Germany and Switzerland. Arzneimittelforschung 55 (1): 38-49, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="15353899">Bock PR, Friedel WE, Hanisch J, et al.: Retrolective, comparative, epidemiological cohort study with parallel groups design for evaluation of efficacy and safety of drugs with "well-established use". Forsch Komplementarmed Klass Naturheilkd 11 (Suppl 1): 23-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="15460213">Bock PR, Friedel WE, Hanisch J, et al.: [Efficacy and safety of long-term complementary treatment with standardized European mistletoe extract (Viscum album L.) in addition to the conventional adjuvant oncologic therapy in patients with primary non-metastasized mammary carcinoma. Results of a multi-center, comparative, epidemiological cohort study in Germany and Switzerland] Arzneimittelforschung 54 (8): 456-66, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="15816634">Klopp R, Schmidt W, Werner E, et al.: Influence of complementary Viscum album (Iscador) administration on microcirculation and immune system of ear, nose and throat carcinoma patients treated with radiation and chemotherapy. Anticancer Res 25 (1B): 601-10, 2005 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="31927541">Ostermann T, Appelbaum S, Poier D, et al.: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis on the Survival of Cancer Patients Treated with a Fermented Viscum album L. Extract (Iscador): An Update of Findings. Complement Med Res 27 (4): 260-271, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="19883529">Friedel WE, Matthes H, Bock PR, et al.: Systematic evaluation of the clinical effects of supportive mistletoe treatment within chemo- and/or radiotherapy protocols and long-term mistletoe application in nonmetastatic colorectal carcinoma: multicenter, controlled, observational cohort study. J Soc Integr Oncol 7 (4): 137-45, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="34">Zaenker KS, Matthes H, Bock PR, et al.: A specific mistletoe preparation (Iscador-Qu) in colorectal cancer (CRC) 
patients: more than just supportive care? Journal of Cancer Science &amp; Therapy  4 (9): 264–270, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="35">Salzer G, Danmayr E, Wutzholfer F, et al.: [Adjuvant Iscador® treatment of non-small cell bronchial carcinoma. Results of a randomized study]. Dtsch Z Onkol  23 (4): 93-8, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="32398946">Longhi A, Cesari M, Serra M, et al.: Long-Term Follow-up of a Randomized Study of Oral Etoposide versus Viscum album Fermentatum Pini as Maintenance Therapy in Osteosarcoma Patients in Complete Surgical Remission after Second Relapse. Sarcoma 2020: 8260730, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="23890767">Tröger W, Galun D, Reif M, et al.: Viscum album [L.] extract therapy in patients with locally advanced or metastatic pancreatic cancer: a randomised clinical trial on overall survival. Eur J Cancer 49 (18): 3788-97, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="37894296">Hohneck AL, Sadikaj L, Heinemann L, et al.: Patients with Advanced Pancreatic Cancer Treated with Mistletoe and Hyperthermia in Addition to Palliative Chemotherapy: A Retrospective Single-Center Analysis. Cancers (Basel) 15 (20): , 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="39">Schaefermeyer G, Schaefermeyer H: Treatment of pancreatic cancer with Viscum album (Iscador): a retrospective study of 292 patients 1986-1996. Complement Ther Med  6 (4): 172-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="25142075">Tröger W, Galun D, Reif M, et al.: Quality of life of patients with advanced pancreatic cancer during treatment with mistletoe: a randomized controlled trial. Dtsch Arztebl Int 111 (29-30): 493-502, 33 p following 502, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="30247950">Pelzer F, Tröger W, Nat DR: Complementary Treatment with Mistletoe Extracts During Chemotherapy: Safety, Neutropenia, Fever, and Quality of Life Assessed in a Randomized Study. J Altern Complement Med 24 (9-10): 954-961, 2018 Sep/Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="36860652">Paller CJ, Wang L, Fu W, et al.: Phase I Trial of Intravenous Mistletoe Extract in Advanced Cancer. Cancer Res Commun 3 (2): 338-346, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="15015612">Piao BK, Wang YX, Xie GR, et al.: Impact of complementary mistletoe extract treatment on quality of life in breast, ovarian and non-small cell lung cancer patients. A prospective randomized controlled clinical trial. Anticancer Res 24 (1): 303-9, 2004 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="30218188">Lee YG, Jung I, Koo DH, et al.: Efficacy and safety of Viscum album extract (Helixor-M) to treat malignant pleural effusion in patients with lung cancer. Support Care Cancer 27 (5): 1945-1949, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="45">Gutsch J, Berger H, Scholz G, et al.: [Prospective study in radically operated breast cancer with polychemotherapy, Helixor® and untreated controls]. Dtsch Z Onkol  21: 94-101, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="46">Douwes FR, Wolfrum DI, Migeod F: [Results of a prospective randomized study: chemotherapy versus chemotherapy plus "biological response modifier" in metastasizing colorectal carcinoma]. Dtsch Z Onkol  18 (6): 155-64, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="20724129">Eisenbraun J, Scheer R, Kröz M, et al.: Quality of life in breast cancer patients during chemotherapy and concurrent therapy with a mistletoe extract. Phytomedicine 18 (2-3): 151-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="23033982">Kim KC, Yook JH, Eisenbraun J, et al.: Quality of life, immunomodulation and safety of adjuvant mistletoe treatment in patients with gastric carcinoma - a randomized, controlled pilot study. BMC Complement Altern Med 12: 172, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="26639937">Cho JS, Na KJ, Lee Y, et al.: Chemical Pleurodesis Using Mistletoe Extraction (ABNOVAviscum(®) Injection) for Malignant Pleural Effusion. Ann Thorac Cardiovasc Surg 22 (1): 20-6, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="15456952">Bar-Sela G, Haim N: Abnoba-viscum (mistletoe extract) in metastatic colorectal carcinoma resistant to 5-fluorouracil and leucovorin-based chemotherapy. Med Oncol 21 (3): 251-4, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="25910967">Rose A, El-Leithy T, vom Dorp F, et al.: Mistletoe Plant Extract in Patients with Nonmuscle Invasive Bladder Cancer: Results of a Phase Ib/IIa Single Group Dose Escalation Study. J Urol 194 (4): 939-43, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="52">Heiny BM, Albrecht V, Beuth J: Stabilization of quality of life with mistletoe lectin-1-standardized extract in advanced colorectal carcinoma. Onkologe  4 (Suppl 1): S35-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="53">Sauer H: Quality of life stabilization with mistletoe-1-standardized extract in advanced colorectal carcinoma [Letter]. Onkologe  4: 1180, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="14981970">Schumacher K, Schneider B, Reich G, et al.: Influence of postoperative complementary treatment with lectin-standardized mistletoe extract on breast cancer patients. A controlled epidemiological multicentric retrolective cohort study. Anticancer Res 23 (6D): 5081-7, 2003 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="16334146">Enesel MB, Acalovschi I, Grosu V, et al.: Perioperative application of the Viscum album extract Isorel in digestive tract cancer patients. Anticancer Res 25 (6C): 4583-90, 2005 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="12667306">Cazacu M, Oniu T, Lungoci C, et al.: The influence of isorel on the advanced colorectal cancer. Cancer Biother Radiopharm 18 (1): 27-34, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="15154663">Semiglasov VF, Stepula VV, Dudov A, et al.: The standardised mistletoe extract PS76A2 improves QoL in patients with breast cancer receiving adjuvant CMF chemotherapy: a randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicentre clinical trial. Anticancer Res 24 (2C): 1293-302, 2004 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="16619567">Semiglazov VF, Stepula VV, Dudov A, et al.: Quality of life is improved in breast cancer patients by Standardised Mistletoe Extract PS76A2 during chemotherapy and follow-up: a randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicentre clinical trial. Anticancer Res 26 (2B): 1519-29, 2006 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="30673872">Freuding M, Keinki C, Kutschan S, et al.: Mistletoe in oncological treatment: a systematic review : Part 2: quality of life and toxicity of cancer treatment. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 145 (4): 927-939, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="32690087">Loef M, Walach H: Quality of life in cancer patients treated with mistletoe: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Complement Med Ther 20 (1): 227, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="19729932">Melzer J, Iten F, Hostanska K, et al.: Efficacy and safety of mistletoe preparations (Viscum album) for patients with cancer diseases. A systematic review. Forsch Komplementmed 16 (4): 217-26, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="30673873">Freuding M, Keinki C, Micke O, et al.: Mistletoe in oncological treatment: a systematic review : Part 1: survival and safety. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 145 (3): 695-707, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="9042260" MedlineID="97194822">Lenartz D, Stoffel B, Menzel J, et al.: Immunoprotective activity of the galactoside-specific lectin from mistletoe after tumor destructive therapy in glioma patients. Anticancer Res 16 (6B): 3799-802, 1996 Nov-Dec.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_52"><Title>Adverse Effects</Title><Para id="_53">Although a number of different <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mistletoe</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> have been used in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human studies</GlossaryTermRef>, the reported <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> have generally been minimal and not life threatening. Common side effects include the following:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_291" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Soreness and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammation</GlossaryTermRef> at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> sites.</ListItem><ListItem>Headache.</ListItem><ListItem>Fever.</ListItem><ListItem>Chills.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_205">One <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meta-analysis</GlossaryTermRef> using <ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> L. and isolated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mistletoe lectins</GlossaryTermRef> included both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal</GlossaryTermRef> and human studies.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Doses</GlossaryTermRef> and application forms varied. No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044041" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunosuppressive</GlossaryTermRef> effects were reported. Side effects included local reactions at the injection site and flu-like symptoms such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef>, chills, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, mild <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> symptoms, and headache.  High doses of recombinantly-produced mistletoe lectins (not available in commercial products) resulted in reversible hepatotoxicity in some cases.<Reference refidx="5"/> Another review reported adverse reactions that included local reactions at the injection site, fever, increased intracerebral pressure, headache, circulatory problems, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046615" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thrombophlebitis</GlossaryTermRef>, swelling of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">allergic reactions</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_206"> A few cases of severe allergic reactions, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285952" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaphylactic shock</GlossaryTermRef>, have been reported.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_295">Although from an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000286105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">observational</GlossaryTermRef> cohort study, three types of mistletoe (Iscador, Helixor, and abnobaVISCUM) that were given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044603" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intratumorally</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenously</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subcutaneously</GlossaryTermRef> were found to be  safe in a small group of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> patients with autoimmune diseases such as Graves disease, Hashimoto <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455472" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroiditis</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045493" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulcerative colitis</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psoriasis</GlossaryTermRef>, and some rheumatic diseases.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="9597967" MedlineID="98260258">Kaegi E: Unconventional therapies for cancer: 3. Iscador. Task Force on Alternative Therapies of the Canadian Breast Cancer Research Initiative. CMAJ 158 (9): 1157-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11720654" MedlineID="21577454">Hutt N, Kopferschmitt-Kubler M, Cabalion J, et al.: Anaphylactic reactions after therapeutic injection of mistletoe (Viscum album L.). Allergol Immunopathol (Madr) 29 (5): 201-3, 2001 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="12232491" MedlineID="22218560">Stauder H, Kreuser ED: Mistletoe extracts standardised in terms of mistletoe lectins (ML I) in oncology: current state of clinical research. Onkologie 25 (4): 374-80, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="24955100">Steele ML, Axtner J, Happe A, et al.: Safety of Intravenous Application of Mistletoe (Viscum album L.) Preparations in Oncology: An Observational Study. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 2014: 236310, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21871125">Kienle GS, Grugel R, Kiene H: Safety of higher dosages of Viscum album L. in animals and humans--systematic review of immune changes and safety parameters. BMC Complement Altern Med 11: 72, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12949804">Ernst E, Schmidt K, Steuer-Vogt MK: Mistletoe for cancer? A systematic review of randomised clinical trials. Int J Cancer 107 (2): 262-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="30808274">Oei SL, Thronicke A, Kröz M, et al.: Use and Safety of Viscum album L Applications in Cancer Patients With Preexisting Autoimmune Diseases: Findings From the Network Oncology Study. Integr Cancer Ther 18: 1534735419832367, 2019 Jan-Dec.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_55"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Mistletoe Extracts</Title><Para id="_474">To assist readers in evaluating the results of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human studies</GlossaryTermRef> of integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of
evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever
possible.  To qualify for a level of evidence <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef>, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_475" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Be published in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed scientific journal</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Report on a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Describe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> findings in sufficient detail that a meaningful evaluation can be made.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_476">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score. For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis for cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_56"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mistletoe</GlossaryTermRef> is one of the most widely studied <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary and alternative medicine</GlossaryTermRef> therapies for cancer. In certain European countries, the preparations made from European mistletoe (<ScientificName>Viscum album</ScientificName> L.) are among the most prescribed drugs offered to cancer patients. Mistletoe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> have been evaluated in numerous <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> and improvements in survival, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>, and/or stimulation of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> have been frequently reported. However, most clinical studies conducted have had one or more major weaknesses that raise doubts about the reliability of the findings. In addition, no evidence exists to support the notion that stimulation of the immune system by mistletoe leads to an improved ability to fight cancer. Because all patients in the reported clinical studies appear to have been adults, no information is available about the use of mistletoe as a treatment for children with cancer. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/06/2024)</Title><Para id="_63">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_487">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269596#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of mistletoe extracts in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Mistletoe Extracts. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mistletoe-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389489]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2002-12-21</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-06</DateLastModified></Summary>
