<Summary id="CDR0000270720" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062701"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Types of treatment for gallbladder cancer include surgery, radiation, and chemotherapy. Treatment of gallbladder cancer that has spread to other parts of the body, cannot be removed by surgery, or has come back after treatment is often within a clinical trial. Find out about treatment options for gallbladder cancer.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gallbladder/patient/gallbladder-treatment-pdq">Gallbladder Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gallbladder/hp/gallbladder-treatment-pdq">Gallbladder Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038747">gallbladder cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_227">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of gallbladder cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_228">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>gallbladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Gallbladder Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Gallbladder Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Gallbladder Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Gallbladder Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Gallbladder cancer is a rare type of cancer that starts in the tissues of the gallbladder.</KeyPoint><Para id="_118">Gallbladder cancer occurs when cells in the gallbladder start to grow out of control. The gallbladder is a pear-shaped organ that lies just under the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> in the upper <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>. The gallbladder stores <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef>, a fluid made by the liver to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463707" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digest</GlossaryTermRef> fat. When food is being broken down in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestines</GlossaryTermRef>, bile is released from the gallbladder through a tube called the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046466" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">common bile duct</GlossaryTermRef>, which connects the gallbladder and liver to the first part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000658899" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the gallbladder; shows the liver, common hepatic duct, cystic duct, common bile duct, pancreas, and small intestine. The inset shows the liver, bile ducts, gallbladder, pancreas, and small intestine." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_198"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the gallbladder. The gallbladder is just below the liver. Bile is stored in the gallbladder and flows through the cystic duct and the common bile duct into the small intestine when food is being digested. </Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_139">The wall of the gallbladder  has  4 main layers of tissue:</Para><ItemizedList id="_140" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucosal</GlossaryTermRef>   (inner) layer</ListItem><ListItem>muscle layer</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef> layer</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454933" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serosal</GlossaryTermRef> (outer) layer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_164"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Primary</GlossaryTermRef> gallbladder cancer starts in the inner layer and spreads through the outer layers as it grows.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_16">Signs and symptoms of gallbladder cancer include jaundice, fever, and pain.</KeyPoint><Para id="_17">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by gallbladder cancer or by other conditions. Check with your doctor if you have:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">jaundice</GlossaryTermRef> (yellowing of the skin and whites of the eyes)</ListItem><ListItem>pain above the stomach</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bloating</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>lumps in the abdomen</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_121"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_122">Gallbladder cancer is difficult to detect (find) and diagnose early.</KeyPoint><Para id="_134">Gallbladder cancer is difficult to detect and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> because:</Para><ItemizedList id="_123" Style="bullet"><ListItem>People rarely have signs or symptoms in the early
			 stages of gallbladder
			 cancer.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>The symptoms of gallbladder cancer, when present, are like the
			 symptoms of many other illnesses.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>The gallbladder is hidden behind the liver.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_124"> Gallbladder cancer is sometimes found when the gallbladder is removed for other reasons. Although <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallstones</GlossaryTermRef> are the most common <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef> for developing gallbladder cancer, the overall risk is low. Most people with gallstones do not develop gallbladder cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Tests that examine the gallbladder and nearby organs are used to detect (find), diagnose, and stage gallbladder cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_21"> Procedures
		  that  make pictures of the gallbladder and the area around it help diagnose gallbladder cancer and show how far the cancer has spread. The process used
		  to find out if cancer cells have spread within and around the gallbladder is
		  called staging.</Para><Para id="_168">To plan treatment, it is important to know  if the gallbladder cancer can be removed by
		  surgery. Tests and procedures
		  to detect, diagnose, and stage gallbladder cancer are usually done at the same
		  time. In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet">
			  
		  <ListItem><Strong>Liver function tests</Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by the liver.  A higher-than-normal amount of a substance can  be a sign of liver disease that may be caused by gallbladder cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT
			 scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest, abdomen, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine.  A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Ultrasound exam</Strong>: A procedure in which high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) are bounced off internal tissues or organs and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>. An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> ultrasound is done to diagnose gallbladder cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>PTC (percutaneous
			 transhepatic cholangiography)</Strong>: A procedure used to x-ray the liver and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile ducts</GlossaryTermRef>.  A thin needle is inserted through the skin below the ribs and into the liver.  Dye is injected into the liver or bile ducts and an x-ray is taken.  If a blockage is found, a thin, flexible tube called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stent</GlossaryTermRef> is sometimes left in the liver to drain bile into the small intestine or a collection bag outside the body.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>ERCP (endoscopic
			 retrograde cholangiopancreatography)</Strong>: A procedure used to x-ray the
			 ducts (tubes) that carry
			 bile from the liver to the
			 gallbladder and from the gallbladder to the small intestine. Sometimes gallbladder cancer
			 causes these ducts to narrow and block or slow the flow of bile, causing
			 jaundice. An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscope</GlossaryTermRef> (a thin, lighted tube) is passed through the
			 mouth, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>, and stomach into the first part of the small intestine. A
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> (a smaller tube) is then
			 inserted through the endoscope into the bile ducts. A dye is injected
			 through the catheter into the ducts and an x-ray is taken. If the ducts are
			 blocked by a tumor, a fine
			 tube may be inserted into the duct to unblock it. This tube (or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stent</GlossaryTermRef>) may be left in
			 place to keep the duct open. Tissue samples may also be taken.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging) with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597153" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gadolinium</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. A substance called gadolinium is injected into  a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Endoscopic ultrasound (EUS)</Strong>: A procedure in which an endoscope  is inserted into the body, usually through the mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>.  An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. A probe at the end of the endoscope is used to bounce high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) off internal tissues or organs and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.  This procedure is also called endosonography.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Laparoscopy</Strong>: A surgical procedure to look at the organs inside the abdomen to check for signs of disease.  Small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incisions</GlossaryTermRef> (cuts)  are made in the wall of the abdomen and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laparoscope</GlossaryTermRef> (a thin, lighted tube) is inserted into one of the incisions. Other instruments may be inserted through the same or other incisions to perform procedures such as removing organs or taking tissue samples for biopsy.  Laparoscopy helps to find out if the
			 cancer is within the gallbladder only or has spread to nearby tissues and if it
			 can be removed by surgery.</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer. The biopsy may be done after surgery to remove the tumor. If the tumor clearly cannot be removed by surgery, the biopsy may be done using a fine needle to remove cells from the tumor. </ListItem> 
		   
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_24">Certain factors affect the prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_25">The  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_141" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the stage of the cancer (whether the cancer has spread from the gallbladder to other places in the body)</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer can be completely removed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>the type of gallbladder cancer (how the cancer cell looks under a microscope)</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has recurred (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_165">Treatment may also depend on the age and general health of the patient and whether the cancer is causing signs or symptoms.</Para><Para id="_125">Gallbladder cancer can be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cured</GlossaryTermRef> only if it is found before it
		  has spread, when it can be removed by surgery. If the cancer has spread,
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative treatment</GlossaryTermRef> can improve the patient's
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> by controlling the
		  symptoms and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complications</GlossaryTermRef> of this disease.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Stages of Gallbladder Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_27"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_28">Tests and procedures to stage gallbladder cancer are usually
		  done at the same time as diagnosis. </KeyPoint><Para id="_166">Learn more about tests and procedures used to detect, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> gallbladder cancer in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000270720#_19" url="/types/gallbladder/patient/gallbladder-treatment-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_190"><KeyPoint id="_191">There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_190_md_69">Cancer can spread through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_190_md_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.
</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_224"><KeyPoint id="_225">Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_224_md_66">When cancer spreads to another part of the body, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer cells break away from where they began (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>) and travel through the lymph system or blood.</Para><ItemizedList id="_224_md_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer gets into the lymph system, travels through the lymph vessels, and forms a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer gets into the blood, travels through the blood vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_226">The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if  gallbladder cancer spreads to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, the cancer cells in the liver are actually gallbladder cancer cells. The disease is metastatic gallbladder cancer, not liver cancer.</Para><EmbeddedVideo id="_246" ref="CDR0000787719" hosting="youtube" unique_id="fQwar_-QdiQ" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>metastasis: how cancer spreads</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Many cancer deaths are caused when cancer moves from the original tumor and spreads to other tissues and organs. This is called metastatic cancer. This animation shows how cancer cells travel from the place in the body where they first formed to other parts of the body.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_142"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_143">The following stages are used for gallbladder cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_144"><KeyPoint id="_145">Stage 0 (Carcinoma in Situ)</KeyPoint><Para id="_231">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000413895" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage 0</GlossaryTermRef>, abnormal cells are found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucosa</GlossaryTermRef> (innermost layer) of the gallbladder wall. These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. Stage 0 is also called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma in situ</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_200"><KeyPoint id="_201">Stage I</KeyPoint><Para id="_232">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000721699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I</GlossaryTermRef>, cancer has formed in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucosa</GlossaryTermRef> (innermost layer) of the gallbladder wall and may have spread to the muscle layer of the gallbladder wall.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_203"><KeyPoint id="_204">Stage II</KeyPoint><Para id="_233"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000721701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage II</GlossaryTermRef> is divided into stages IIA and IIB, depending on where the cancer has spread in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallbladder</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><ItemizedList id="_234" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>In stage IIA, cancer has spread through the muscle layer to the connective tissue layer of the gallbladder wall on the side of the gallbladder that is not near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIB, cancer has spread through the muscle layer to the connective tissue layer of the gallbladder wall on the same side as the liver. Cancer has not spread to the liver.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_235"><KeyPoint id="_236">Stage III</KeyPoint><Para id="_237"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000413912" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage III</GlossaryTermRef> is divided into stages IIIA and IIIB, depending on where the cancer has spread.</Para><ItemizedList id="_240" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>In stage IIIA, cancer has spread through the connective tissue layer of the gallbladder wall and one or more of the following is true:<ItemizedList id="_239" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454933" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serosa</GlossaryTermRef> (layer of tissue that covers the gallbladder).</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to one nearby organ or structure (such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>, or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile ducts</GlossaryTermRef> outside the liver).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIB, cancer has formed in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucosa</GlossaryTermRef> (innermost layer) of the gallbladder wall and may have spread to the muscle, connective tissue, or serosa (layer of tissue that covers the gallbladder) and may have also spread to the liver or to one nearby organ or structure (such as the stomach, small intestine, colon, pancreas, or the bile ducts outside the liver). Cancer has spread to one to three nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_241"><KeyPoint id="_242">Stage IV</KeyPoint><Para id="_243"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000413913" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage IV</GlossaryTermRef> is divided into stages IVA and IVB.</Para><ItemizedList id="_244" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>In stage IVA, cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">portal vein</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic artery</GlossaryTermRef> or to two or more organs or structures other than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer may have spread to one to three nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IVB, cancer may have spread to nearby organs or structures. Cancer has spread:<ItemizedList id="_245" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>to four or more nearby lymph nodes; or</ListItem><ListItem>to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef> and liver.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_32">For gallbladder cancer, stages are also grouped according to how the cancer may be treated. There are    two treatment groups:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_33"><KeyPoint id="_34">Localized (Stage I) </KeyPoint><Para id="_35">
Cancer is found in the wall of the  gallbladder and  can be completely removed by surgery. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><KeyPoint id="_37">Unresectable, recurrent, or metastatic (Stage II, Stage III, and Stage IV)</KeyPoint><Para id="_38"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045936" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Unresectable</GlossaryTermRef> cancer cannot be removed completely by surgery. Most patients with gallbladder cancer have unresectable cancer. </Para><Para id="_220"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> cancer is cancer that has recurred (come back) after it has been treated. Gallbladder cancer may come back  in the gallbladder  or in  other parts of   the body.</Para><Para id="_221"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Metastasis</GlossaryTermRef> is the spread of cancer from the primary site (place where it started) to other places in the body. Metastatic gallbladder cancer may spread  to  surrounding  tissues, organs,  throughout the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef>, or to distant parts of the body.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_51"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_52">There are different types of treatment for  patients with gallbladder cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_53">Different types of treatments are available for  patients with gallbladder cancer. Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>. A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the  standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment. Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_60">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_61"><KeyPoint id="_62">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_133">Gallbladder cancer may be treated with a  cholecystectomy, surgery to remove the gallbladder and some of the tissues around it. Nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> may be removed. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laparoscope</GlossaryTermRef> is sometimes used to guide gallbladder surgery. The laparoscope is attached to a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045940" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">video camera</GlossaryTermRef> and inserted through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> (port) in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>.  Surgical instruments are inserted through  other ports to perform the surgery. Because there is a risk that gallbladder cancer cells may spread to  these ports,    tissue surrounding the port sites may also be removed.</Para><Para id="_63">If the cancer has spread and cannot be removed, the following types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative</GlossaryTermRef> surgery may relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_127" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biliary bypass</GlossaryTermRef>: If the tumor is blocking the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile duct</GlossaryTermRef>
				and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef> is building up in the
				gallbladder, a biliary bypass may be done. During this operation,  the doctor will cut the gallbladder or bile duct  in the area before the blockage and sew it  to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef> to
				create a new pathway around the blocked area. </ListItem> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stent</GlossaryTermRef> placement: If the  tumor is blocking the
				bile duct, surgery may be done to put in a stent (a thin tube) to drain bile
				that has built up in the area. The  doctor may place the stent through a
				<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> that drains the bile into a bag on the outside
				of the body or the stent may go around the blocked area and drain the bile into
				the small intestine. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000377729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage</GlossaryTermRef>: A procedure done to drain bile when there is a blockage and endoscopic stent placement is not possible.  An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> and bile ducts is done to locate the blockage. Images made by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> are used to guide placement of a stent, which is left in the liver to drain bile into the small intestine or a collection bag outside the body. This procedure may be done to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">jaundice</GlossaryTermRef> before surgery.</ListItem> 
			  
		  </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><KeyPoint id="_66">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_67"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy x-rays or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward area of the body with cancer. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_68"><KeyPoint id="_69">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_70"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping the cells from dividing. When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (systemic therapy).  </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_83"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_84">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials. </KeyPoint><Para id="_189">This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in clinical trials. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_85"><KeyPoint id="_86">Radiation  sensitizers</KeyPoint><Para id="_222">Clinical trials are studying ways to improve the effect of
			 radiation therapy on tumor cells, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_223" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046263" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hyperthermia therapy</GlossaryTermRef>: A treatment in which body tissue is exposed
				to high temperatures to damage and kill cancer cells or to make cancer cells
				more sensitive to the effects of radiation therapy  and certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639945" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anticancer</GlossaryTermRef>
				drugs.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiosensitizers</GlossaryTermRef>: Drugs that make tumor cells more
				sensitive to radiation therapy. Giving radiation therapy together with radiosensitizers may kill more
				tumor cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_258"><KeyPoint id="_259">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_260"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific  cancer cells. The following targeted therapies are  being studied in patients with gallbladder cancer that is  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> and cannot be removed by surgery or has spread to other parts of the body:</Para><ItemizedList id="_261" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ivosidenib</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of targeted therapy that blocks a specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutation</GlossaryTermRef> in  a gene called <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794150" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">IDH1</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName>. It works by slowing or stopping the growth of cancer cells.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000801467" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pemigatinib</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of targeted therapy that  blocks specific changes in a   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> called <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FGFR2</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName>. This may help keep cancer cells from growing and may kill them.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_262"><KeyPoint id="_263">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_264"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment that uses the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to fight cancer.  Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the body's natural defenses against cancer.  </Para><Para id="_412"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000772606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immune checkpoint inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of immunotherapy that may be used to treat gallbladder cancer.</Para><ItemizedList id="_413" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000777027" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PD-1</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797389" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PD-L1</GlossaryTermRef> inhibitor therapy: PD-1 is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> on the surface of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">T cells</GlossaryTermRef> that helps keep the body's immune responses in check. PD-L1 is a protein found on some types of cancer cells. When PD-1 attaches to PD-L1, it stops the T cell from killing the cancer cell. PD-1 and PD-L1 inhibitors keep PD-1 and PD-L1 proteins from attaching to each other. This allows the T cells to kill cancer cells. <ItemizedList id="_414" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000764538" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pembrolizumab</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of PD-1 inhibitor that may be used  in patients whose cancer  is  locally advanced and cannot be removed by surgery or has spread to other parts of the body.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000788775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Durvalumab</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of PD-L1 inhibitor that is being studied in combination with chemotherapy  in  previously untreated patients whose cancer is locally advanced, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef>, or has spread to other parts of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem>
     </ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000774646" type="image/jpeg" alt="Immune checkpoint inhibitor; the panel on the left shows the binding of proteins PD-L1 (on the tumor cell) to PD-1 (on the T cell), which keeps T cells from killing tumor cells in the body. Also shown are a tumor cell antigen and T cell receptor. The panel on the right shows immune checkpoint inhibitors (anti-PD-L1 and anti-PD-1) blocking the binding of PD-L1 to PD-1, which allows the T cells to kill tumor cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_306"><Caption language="en">Immune checkpoint inhibitor. Checkpoint proteins, such as PD-L1 on tumor cells and PD-1 on T cells, help keep immune responses in check. The binding of PD-L1 to PD-1 keeps T cells from killing tumor cells in the body (left panel). Blocking the binding of PD-L1 to PD-1 with an immune checkpoint inhibitor (anti-PD-L1 or anti-PD-1) allows the T cells to kill tumor cells (right panel).</Caption></MediaLink><EmbeddedVideo id="_312" ref="CDR0000795515" hosting="youtube" unique_id="GIUu239FWMg" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>immune checkpoint inhibitors</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Immunotherapy uses the body’s immune system to fight cancer. This animation explains one type of immunotherapy that uses immune checkpoint inhibitors to treat cancer.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_247"><KeyPoint id="_248">Treatment for gallbladder cancer may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_247_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_192"><KeyPoint id="_193">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_192_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_192_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_192_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_194"><KeyPoint id="_195">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_194_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_194_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_196"><KeyPoint id="_197">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_196_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_196_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_250"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038748">localized gallbladder cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Localized  and Locally Advanced Gallbladder Cancer</Title><Para id="_251">For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000270720#_59" url="/types/gallbladder/patient/gallbladder-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_252">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045120" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">localized</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> gallbladder cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_253" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallbladder</GlossaryTermRef> and some of the tissue around it. 
Part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> and nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> may also be removed. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> may follow surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy with or without   chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of radiation therapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiosensitizers</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_250_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_254"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038749">unresectable gallbladder cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038751">recurrent gallbladder cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000709297">metastatic gallbladder cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Unresectable, Metastatic, or Recurrent Gallbladder Cancer</Title><Para id="_255">For information about the treatments listed below, visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000270720#_59" url="/types/gallbladder/patient/gallbladder-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_256">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045121" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">unresectable</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> gallbladder cancer is usually within a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>. Treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_257" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000377729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage</GlossaryTermRef>  or the placement of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stents</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> caused by  blocked <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile ducts</GlossaryTermRef>.  This may be followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery as palliative treatment  to relieve symptoms caused by blocked bile ducts.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of new ways to give palliative radiation therapy, such as giving it together with  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046263" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperthermia therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiosensitizers</GlossaryTermRef>, or chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutations</GlossaryTermRef> (changes) in certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_254_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_185"><Title>To Learn More About Gallbladder Cancer</Title><Para id="_186">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  gallbladder cancer, visit the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gallbladder">Gallbladder Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_185_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_185_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of gallbladder cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Gallbladder Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gallbladder/patient/gallbladder-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/gallbladder/patient/gallbladder-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389400]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062904"/><DateFirstPublished>2004-03-24</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-04-10</DateLastModified></Summary>
