<Summary id="CDR0000299612" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Familial prostate cancer is associated with certain inherited gene variants. Learn about the hereditary prostate cancer genes, genetic testing, and clinical management in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Prostate Cancer (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038782">prostate cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1337">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of prostate cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_1338">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>prostate cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Genetics of Prostate Cancer (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Genetics of Prostate Cancer (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Genetics of Prostate Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1392"><Title>Executive Summary</Title><Para id="_1398">This executive summary reviews the topics covered in Genetics of Prostate Cancer and provides hyperlinks to detailed sections that describe available evidence on each topic.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1393" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1762" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Introduction</SummaryRef></Strong><Para id="_2013">Prostate cancer is highly heritable. Up to 60% of prostate cancer risk is caused by inherited factors. This inherited risk is comprised of risk from common genetic variants and risk from pathogenic variants in moderate-risk and high-risk genes.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_2002" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Risk Factors for Prostate Cancer</SummaryRef></Strong><Para id="_2014">Risk factors for prostate cancer include age, a family history of prostate cancer and other cancers, genetics, and ancestry  (such as West African ancestry). </Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1841" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Risk Assessment for Prostate Cancer</SummaryRef></Strong><Para id="_2015">Risk assessment for prostate cancer primarily includes intake of an individual's personal cancer history, family cancer history, and ancestry. These factors are then incorporated into recommendations for prostate cancer screening.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1842" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Indications for Prostate Cancer Germline Genetic Testing</SummaryRef></Strong><Para id="_2016">Hereditary prostate cancer genetic testing criteria are based on one or more of the following: an individual's family history and/or genetic test results, personal/disease characteristics, and tumor sequencing results. Criteria for  prostate cancer genetic testing vary based on current guidelines and expert opinion. </Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1851" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Genetic Testing Approach for Prostate Cancer</SummaryRef></Strong><Para id="_2017">Since next-generation sequencing (NGS) has become readily available and patent restrictions have been eliminated, several clinical laboratories offer multigene panel testing at a cost that is comparable to that of single-gene testing.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1770" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Germline Genetics for Prostate Cancer</SummaryRef></Strong><Para id="_2018">The bulk of inherited prostate cancer risk is conferred by hundreds of genetic polymorphisms, which are common in the general population. Each of these polymorphisms provides a slight increase in prostate cancer risk. For a subset of individuals, prostate cancer risk is caused by rare, deleterious variants located in specific genes.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1874" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Prostate Cancer Genetics: Screening, Surveillance, and Treatment</SummaryRef></Strong><Para id="_2019">This section focuses on the impacts of genetics on prostate cancer screening, surveillance, and treatment. Genetic test results are increasingly driving targeted therapy options and strategies for treatment in oncology.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1762"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_1854">Prostate cancer is highly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781848" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heritable</GlossaryTermRef>. Up to 60% of prostate cancer risk is caused by inherited factors.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> The inherited risk is comprised of risk from common genetic variants and risk from pathogenic variants in moderate-risk and high-risk genes. As with breast and colon cancers, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> clustering of prostate cancer has been reported frequently.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_1855">Prostate cancer clusters with particular intensity in some families. Highly to moderately <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic variants</GlossaryTermRef>  are thought to be associated with prostate cancer risk in these families. Members of these families may benefit from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef>. Additionally, polygenic risk scores derived from combinations of single nucleotide polymorphisms, in addition to other risk factors like family history, race, and age/stage of prostate cancer diagnosis, have also been developed.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Recommendations and guidelines for genetic counseling referrals are based on an individual's age at prostate cancer diagnosis,   prostate cancer stage at diagnosis, and specific patterns of cancer in the family  history.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> However, uptake of genetic testing based on an individual's family history of prostate cancer and/or a diagnosis of prostate cancer is variably implemented across practice settings and geographical regions.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> For more information about genetic testing criteria for prostate cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1845" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="36610996">Houlahan KE, Livingstone J, Fox NS, et al.: A polygenic two-hit hypothesis for prostate cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst 115 (4): 468-472, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="26746459">Mucci LA, Hjelmborg JB, Harris JR, et al.: Familial Risk and Heritability of Cancer Among Twins in Nordic Countries. JAMA 315 (1): 68-76, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="36609003">Seibert TM, Garraway IP, Plym A, et al.: Genetic Risk Prediction for Prostate Cancer: Implications for Early Detection and Prevention. Eur Urol 83 (3): 241-248, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="36305680">Pagadala MS, Lynch J, Karunamuni R, et al.: Polygenic risk of any, metastatic, and fatal prostate cancer in the Million Veteran Program. J Natl Cancer Inst 115 (2): 190-199, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="35152271">Huynh-Le MP, Karunamuni R, Fan CC, et al.: Prostate cancer risk stratification improvement across multiple ancestries with new polygenic hazard score. Prostate Cancer Prostatic Dis 25 (4): 755-761, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="6">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic. Version 2.2024. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_bop.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="7">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Prostate Cancer Early Detection. Version 2.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/prostate_detection.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed November 30, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="36322272">Clark NM, Flanagan MR: ASO Author Reflections: Low Genetic Testing Utilization Among Patients with Breast, Ovarian, Pancreatic, and Prostate Cancers. Ann Surg Oncol 30 (3): 1327-1328, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="35201622">Giri VN, Morgan TM, Morris DS, et al.: Genetic testing in prostate cancer management: Considerations informing primary care. CA Cancer J Clin 72 (4): 360-371, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="35449224">Russo J, Giri VN: Germline testing and genetic counselling in prostate cancer. Nat Rev Urol 19 (6): 331-343, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2002"><Title>Risk Factors for Prostate Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_2003"><Title>Age</Title><Para id="_2004">Prostate cancer risk correlates with age.  Prostate cancer is rarely seen in men younger than 40 years. The incidence rises rapidly with each decade thereafter.  For example, the probability of being diagnosed with prostate cancer is 1 in 468 for men aged 49 years or younger, 1 in 26 for men aged 50 through 64 years, 1 in 9 for men aged 65 through 84 years, and 1 in 31 for men aged 85 years and older. Lifetime  risk of developing prostate cancer is 1 in 8.<Reference refidx="1"/> Approximately 10% of prostate cancer cases are diagnosed in men younger than 56 years and represent early-onset prostate cancer. Data from the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program show that early-onset prostate cancer diagnosis rates are  increasing, and there is evidence that cases may be more aggressive in this subpopulation.<Reference refidx="2"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2005"><Title>Ancestry</Title><Para id="_2006">The risk of developing prostate cancer is dramatically higher in Black American individuals, who predominantly have West African ancestry (191.5 cases/100,000 men) when compared with other racial and ethnic groups in the United States: </Para><ItemizedList id="_2023" Style="bullet"><ListItem>White: 114.5 cases/100,000 men.</ListItem><ListItem>Asian American or Pacific Islander: 63.1 cases/100,000 men.</ListItem><ListItem>American Indian or Alaska Native: 99.1 cases/100,000 men.</ListItem><ListItem>Hispanic or Latino: 92.9 cases/100,000 men.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2024"> Prostate cancer mortality rates in Black individuals (37.2 deaths/100,000 men) are higher than those in other racial and ethnic groups in the United States:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2026" Style="bullet"><ListItem>White: 18.1 deaths/100,000 men.</ListItem><ListItem>Asian American or Pacific Islander: 8.8 deaths/100,000 men.</ListItem><ListItem>American Indian or Alaska Native: 21.2 deaths/100,000 men.</ListItem><ListItem>Hispanic or Latino: 15.4 deaths/100,000 men.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2025">Globally, prostate cancer incidence and mortality rates also vary widely from country to country.<Reference refidx="3"/>   The etiology of this variation in prostate cancer risk is likely multifactorial and may be due to  biological factors, access to health care, and other social determinants of health.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2007"><Title>Family History of Prostate Cancer and Other Cancers</Title><Para id="_1865">Results from several large case-control studies and cohort studies representing various populations suggest that family history is a major risk factor in prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/>  A family history of a brother or father with prostate cancer increases the risk of prostate cancer, and the risk is inversely related to the age of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">affected</GlossaryTermRef> relative.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/>    Risk is increased when a first-degree relative (FDR) was diagnosed with prostate cancer before age 65 years.</Para><Para id="_1866">A meta-analysis of 33 epidemiological case-control and cohort-based studies has provided detailed information regarding risk ratios related to family history of prostate cancer (for more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1867" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Table id="_1867"><Title>Table 1.   Relative Risk (RR) Related to Family History of Prostate Cancer<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Risk Group</entry><entry Align="Center">RR for Prostate Cancer (95% CI)</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row RowSep="0"><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1" RowSep="1">CI = confidence interval; FDR = first-degree relative.</entry></Row><Row RowSep="0"><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1" RowSep="0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Kiciński et al.<Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Brother(s) with prostate cancer diagnosed at any age</entry><entry>3.14 (2.37–4.15)</entry></Row><Row><entry>Father with prostate cancer diagnosed at any age</entry><entry>2.35 (2.02–2.72)</entry></Row><Row><entry>One affected FDR diagnosed at any age</entry><entry>2.48 (2.25–2.74)</entry></Row><Row><entry>Affected  FDRs diagnosed  &lt;65 y</entry><entry>2.87 (2.21–3.74)</entry></Row><Row><entry>Affected  FDRs diagnosed  ≥65 y</entry><entry>1.92 (1.49–2.47)</entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000485395" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Second-degree relatives</GlossaryTermRef> diagnosed at any age</entry><entry>2.52 (0.99–6.46)</entry></Row><Row><entry>Two or more affected  FDRs diagnosed at any age</entry><entry>4.39 (2.61–7.39)</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1870">A family history of breast cancer is also associated with increased prostate cancer risk. In the Health Professionals Follow-up Study (HPFS), comprising over 40,000 men, those with a family history of breast cancer had a 21% higher risk of developing prostate cancer overall and a 34% increased risk of developing a lethal form of prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="10"/> This is consistent with findings from previous cohorts,<Reference refidx="15"/> though, notably, not all series have detected this association.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/> The HPFS and other studies have also shown that men with a family history of both prostate and breast/ovarian cancers were at an even higher risk of prostate cancer compared with men with a family history of either prostate or breast/ovarian cancer alone.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="16"/> A proportion of the increased prostate cancer risk associated with family history of breast cancer is likely due to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> damage repair pathway, most commonly <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/> For more information, see the <GeneName><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1881" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">BRCA1 and BRCA2</SummaryRef></GeneName>  section. The association between prostate and breast cancers in families appears bidirectional. Among women, a family history of prostate cancer is likewise associated with increased risk of breast cancer.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/></Para><Para id="_1871">An association also exists between prostate cancer risk and colon cancer. Men with germline variants in DNA mismatch repair genes are at increased risk of developing prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="24"/>
One study reported an approximately twofold increased risk of prostate cancer among first- and second-degree relatives of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460211" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">probands</GlossaryTermRef> with colorectal cancer meeting Amsterdam I or Amsterdam II criteria for Lynch syndrome.<Reference refidx="25"/> For more information on Amsterdam criteria, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_1100" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Defining Lynch syndrome families</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer.</Para><Para id="_1872">Family history has been shown to be a risk factor for men of different races and ethnicities.  In a population-based case-control study of prostate cancer among African American, White, and Asian American individuals in the United States  (Los Angeles, San Francisco, and Hawaii) and Canada (Vancouver and Toronto),<Reference refidx="26"/>   5% of controls and 13% of all cases reported a father, brother, or son with prostate cancer.  These prevalence estimates were somewhat lower among Asian American individuals than among African American or White individuals.  A positive family history was associated with a twofold to threefold increase in relative risk (RR) in each of the three ethnic groups.  The overall odds ratio (OR) associated with a family history of prostate cancer was 2.5 (95% confidence interval [CI], 1.9–3.3) with adjustment for age and ethnicity.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para><Para id="_1873">Evidence shows that a family history of prostate cancer can be associated with inferior clinical outcomes. When  patients were referred for prostate biopsy (typically due to elevated prostate-specific antigen [PSA]), men with a family history of the disease were at increased risk for high-grade prostate cancer when compared with patients without a family history.<Reference refidx="27"/> A large population-based study from Utah reported that men with either of the following were at an increased risk for early-onset prostate cancer: 1) three or more  FDRs diagnosed with prostate cancer, or 2) two or more FDRs  or second-degree relatives with prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="28"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2008"><Title>Genetics</Title><Para id="_2009">There are multiple germline pathogenic variants and single nucleotide variants  that are associated with prostate cancer risk. For more information about these genetic variants, see the National Human Genome Research Institute's<ExternalRef xref="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/"> GWAS catalog</ExternalRef>. Germline genetic testing may be indicated to assess prostate cancer risk and/or inform therapeutic decision-making in men diagnosed with prostate cancer. Prostate cancer risks vary depending on  the specific gene and pathogenic variant involved.<Reference refidx="29"/> Prostate cancer heritability  (when considering low, moderate, and high-penetrant genetic factors) can be as high 57% (95% CI, 51%–63%).<Reference refidx="30"/> Genetic variants that contribute to this risk are continuously being identified.<Reference refidx="28"/> Prostate cancer heritability rates may also vary in different racial and ethnic populations.<Reference refidx="31"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1770" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Germline Genetics for Prostate Cancer</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="24818853">Salinas CA, Tsodikov A, Ishak-Howard M, et al.: Prostate cancer in young men: an important clinical entity. Nat Rev Urol 11 (6): 317-23, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="33538338">Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, et al.: Global Cancer Statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN Estimates of Incidence and Mortality Worldwide for 36 Cancers in 185 Countries. CA Cancer J Clin 71 (3): 209-249, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="30171227">Krimphove MJ, Cole AP, Fletcher SA, et al.: Evaluation of the contribution of demographics, access to health care, treatment, and tumor characteristics to racial differences in survival of advanced prostate cancer. Prostate Cancer Prostatic Dis 22 (1): 125-136, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="32232449">Fletcher SA, Marchese M, Cole AP, et al.: Geographic Distribution of Racial Differences in Prostate Cancer Mortality. JAMA Netw Open 3 (3): e201839, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="1565627" MedlineID="92228786">Carter BS, Beaty TH, Steinberg GD, et al.: Mendelian inheritance of familial prostate cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 89 (8): 3367-71, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="8630920" MedlineID="96223344">Grönberg H, Damber L, Damber JE: Familial prostate cancer in Sweden. A nationwide register cohort study. Cancer 77 (1): 138-43, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="8">Cannon L, Bishop DT, Skolnick M, et al.: Genetic epidemiology of prostate cancer in the Utah Mormon genealogy. Cancer Surv  1 (1): 47-69, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="25274038">Saarimäki L, Tammela TL, Määttänen L, et al.: Family history in the Finnish Prostate Cancer Screening Trial. Int J Cancer 136 (9): 2172-7, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="30082473">Barber L, Gerke T, Markt SC, et al.: Family History of Breast or Prostate Cancer and Prostate Cancer Risk. Clin Cancer Res 24 (23): 5910-5917, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="9096649" MedlineID="97250966">Ghadirian P, Howe GR, Hislop TG, et al.: Family history of prostate cancer: a multi-center case-control study in Canada. Int J Cancer 70 (6): 679-81, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11588848" MedlineID="21473358">Stanford JL, Ostrander EA: Familial prostate cancer. Epidemiol Rev 23 (1): 19-23, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="11405327" MedlineID="21298134">Matikaine MP, Pukkala E, Schleutker J, et al.: Relatives of prostate cancer patients have an increased risk of prostate and stomach cancers: a population-based, cancer registry study in Finland. Cancer Causes Control 12 (3): 223-30, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="22073129">Kiciński M, Vangronsveld J, Nawrot TS: An epidemiological reappraisal of the familial aggregation of prostate cancer: a meta-analysis. PLoS One 6 (10): e27130, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="9950240" MedlineID="99133739">Cerhan JR, Parker AS, Putnam SD, et al.: Family history and prostate cancer risk in a population-based cohort of Iowa men. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 8 (1): 53-60, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="11068306" MedlineID="20522184">Kalish LA, McDougal WS, McKinlay JB: Family history and the risk of prostate cancer. Urology 56 (5): 803-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="9766560" MedlineID="98437950">Damber L, Grönberg H, Damber JE: Familial prostate cancer and possible associated malignancies: nation-wide register cohort study in Sweden. Int J Cancer 78 (3): 293-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="17700570">Agalliu I, Karlins E, Kwon EM, et al.: Rare germline mutations in the BRCA2 gene are associated with early-onset prostate cancer. Br J Cancer 97 (6): 826-31, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="12474142" MedlineID="22375663">Edwards SM, Kote-Jarai Z, Meitz J, et al.: Two percent of men with early-onset prostate cancer harbor germline mutations in the BRCA2 gene. Am J Hum Genet 72 (1): 1-12, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="7907678" MedlineID="94180617">Ford D, Easton DF, Bishop DT, et al.: Risks of cancer in BRCA1-mutation carriers. Breast Cancer Linkage Consortium. Lancet 343 (8899): 692-5, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="10969800" MedlineID="20424201">Gayther SA, de Foy KA, Harrington P, et al.: The frequency of germ-line mutations in the breast cancer predisposition genes BRCA1 and BRCA2 in familial prostate cancer. The Cancer Research Campaign/British Prostate Group United Kingdom Familial Prostate Cancer Study Collaborators. Cancer Res 60 (16): 4513-8, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="25754547">Beebe-Dimmer JL, Yee C, Cote ML, et al.: Familial clustering of breast and prostate cancer and risk of postmenopausal breast cancer in the Women's Health Initiative Study. Cancer 121 (8): 1265-72, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="7990161" MedlineID="95082045">Sellers TA, Potter JD, Rich SS, et al.: Familial clustering of breast and prostate cancers and risk of postmenopausal breast cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst 86 (24): 1860-5, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="31337882">Dominguez-Valentin M, Sampson JR, Seppälä TT, et al.: Cancer risks by gene, age, and gender in 6350 carriers of pathogenic mismatch repair variants: findings from the Prospective Lynch Syndrome Database. Genet Med 22 (1): 15-25, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="28772302">Samadder NJ, Smith KR, Wong J, et al.: Cancer Risk in Families Fulfilling the Amsterdam Criteria for Lynch Syndrome. JAMA Oncol 3 (12): 1697-1701, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="7535977" MedlineID="95225272">Whittemore AS, Wu AH, Kolonel LN, et al.: Family history and prostate cancer risk in black, white, and Asian men in the United States and Canada. Am J Epidemiol 141 (8): 732-40, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="34980493">Clements MB, Vertosick EA, Guerrios-Rivera L, et al.: Defining the Impact of Family History on Detection of High-grade Prostate Cancer in a Large Multi-institutional Cohort. Eur Urol 82 (2): 163-169, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="32208047">Beebe-Dimmer JL, Kapron AL, Fraser AM, et al.: Risk of Prostate Cancer Associated With Familial and Hereditary Cancer Syndromes. J Clin Oncol 38 (16): 1807-1813, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="36609003">Seibert TM, Garraway IP, Plym A, et al.: Genetic Risk Prediction for Prostate Cancer: Implications for Early Detection and Prevention. Eur Urol 83 (3): 241-248, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="26746459">Mucci LA, Hjelmborg JB, Harris JR, et al.: Familial Risk and Heritability of Cancer Among Twins in Nordic Countries. JAMA 315 (1): 68-76, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="34210495">Bree KK, Hensley PJ, Pettaway CA: Germline Predisposition to Prostate Cancer in Diverse Populations. Urol Clin North Am 48 (3): 411-423, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1841"><Title>Risk Assessment for Prostate Cancer</Title><Para id="_1993">Risk assessment for prostate cancer primarily involves the intake of a patient's family cancer history. Family history intake includes the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_2028" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Information about cancers<Superscript>*</Superscript> in male and female blood relatives on maternal and paternal sides of the family.</ListItem><ListItem>Ages at cancer diagnoses.</ListItem><ListItem>Ages of death from cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>The number of relatives with metastatic prostate cancer.</ListItem><ListItem> The number of relatives who died of prostate cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Information on relatives who are undergoing cancer screening, if known.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2029">*Cancers include, but are not limited to, the following: prostate, breast, pancreas, colorectal, uterine, ovarian, upper gastrointestinal (GI), and skin cancers.</Para><Para id="_1994">Ancestry is also an important component of the family history. Ashkenazi Jewish ancestry on either side of the family may prompt greater suspicion for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783962" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">founder pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in <GeneName>BRCA1 </GeneName>and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, which could lead to  increased cancer risk in a family. Men of African descent (Black men) also have a higher risk for prostate cancer. Within the United States, Black men (191.5 cases/100,000 men) have approximately a 67% higher incidence rate of prostate cancer  than White  men (114.5 cases/100,000 men).<Reference refidx="1"/>  Black men also have more than twice the rate of prostate cancer–specific death (37.2 deaths/100,000 men) than White men (18.1 deaths/100,000 men).<Reference refidx="1"/> This increased prostate cancer risk may be due to  challenges, including the following: 1) access to care,  2) limited awareness of prostate cancer screening programs, 3) limited engagement in prostate cancer screening/genetic testing, and 4)  the presence of specific genetic markers that can increase prostate cancer risk.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_1995">These familial risk factors are then incorporated into recommendations for prostate cancer screening. National guidelines recommend discussing prostate cancer screening with prostate-specific antigen (PSA) and digital rectal exam between the ages of 45 and 75 years  for individuals at average risk for prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_2034">In contrast, prostate cancer screening is recommended to start at age 40 years for  individuals in these high-risk groups:</Para><Para id="_2030"><Strong>Men of Black/African descent.</Strong></Para><Para id="_2031"><Strong>Men with germline pathogenic variants that increase prostate cancer risk.</Strong></Para><Para id="_2032"><Strong>Men who have family histories with features suggestive of hereditary cancer syndromes like the following:</Strong></Para><ItemizedList id="_2033" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Hereditary breast and ovarian cancer syndrome:</Strong> Family members with ovarian cancer, pancreatic cancer, metastatic/high-risk prostate cancer, male breast cancer, and/or  breast cancer diagnosed at or before age 50 years.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Lynch syndrome: </Strong>Family members with colorectal or endometrial cancer diagnosed at or before age 50 years, ovarian cancer, pancreatic cancer, urothelial cancer, and/or upper GI cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Hereditary prostate cancer: </Strong>Multiple generations with prostate cancer, deaths from prostate cancer, and/or family members with metastatic prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1996">The role of additional markers, such as polygenic risk scores, in prostate cancer risk assessment is evolving. Additional screening strategies,   like multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging (mpMRI), are also being studied. </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="37046071">Liadi Y, Campbell T, Dike P, et al.: Prostate cancer metastasis and health disparities: a systematic review. Prostate Cancer Prostatic Dis 27 (2): 183-191, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="34798639">Nair SS, Chakravarty D, Dovey ZS, et al.: Why do African-American men face higher risks for lethal prostate cancer? Curr Opin Urol 32 (1): 96-101, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="4">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic. Version 2.2024. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_bop.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="5">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Prostate Cancer Early Detection. Version 2.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/prostate_detection.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed November 30, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="6">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Prostate Cancer. Version 4.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/prostate.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed November 30, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1842"><Title>Indications for Prostate Cancer Germline Genetic Testing</Title><Para id="_1843">The criteria for consideration of genetic testing for prostate cancer varies depending on the current guidelines and expert opinion consensus, as summarized in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1845" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  Hereditary prostate cancer genetic testing criteria are  based on an individual's family history, personal/disease characteristics, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000768570" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">tumor sequencing</GlossaryTermRef> results.  The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> recommended for genetic testing vary based on national  guidelines and consensus conference recommendations. Precision therapy has emerged as a major driver for germline genetic testing and may be a separate reason to pursue testing beyond the criteria stated in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1845" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>. The National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) Prostate Cancer guidelines recommend testing  for at least <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK2, </GeneName><GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, <GeneName>HOXB13,</GeneName> <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, and <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName> for men meeting specific testing indications.<Reference refidx="4"/> A consensus conference in 2019 addressed the role of genetic testing for inherited prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="6"/>  Family history–based indications for genetic testing included testing for <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> mismatch repair (MMR) genes, and <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>. Tumor sequencing that identifies variants that may be germline in origin, like variants  in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, DNA MMR genes, or <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> and other genes, warrants confirmatory <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> testing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Somatic</GlossaryTermRef> findings for which germline testing is considered include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1844" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Somatic variants</GlossaryTermRef> that are associated with germline susceptibility.</ListItem><ListItem>Hypermutated tumors, which are indicative of DNA MMR. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> rearrangements in specific tumors.</ListItem><ListItem>High-variant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339337" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">allele</GlossaryTermRef> frequency (percent of sequence reads that have the identified variant). Variant allele frequency can be altered for reasons not associated with germline variants such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000464169" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">loss of heterozygosity</GlossaryTermRef>, ploidy (copy number variants), tumor heterogeneity, and tumor sample purity.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2051">It is recommended that  germline genetic testing candidates undergo genetic education and counseling before participating in testing. Genetic counseling provides information about genetic testing and possible testing outcomes (including risks, benefits, limitations, and familial, psychological, and health care–based implications that vary depending on results). Genetic education and counseling help individuals make informed decisions about whether they should undergo germline genetic testing. For more information on genetic education and genetic counseling, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling</SummaryRef>.</Para><Table id="_1845"><Title>Table 2.  Indications for Prostate Cancer Genetic Testing</Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="14.14%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="22.16%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="10.03%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="40.52%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="13.13%"/><THead><Row><entry/><entry>Philadelphia Prostate Cancer Consensus Conference (Giri et al. 2020)<Superscript>a</Superscript> <Reference refidx="6"/> </entry><entry>Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic (Version 2.2024)<Superscript>b</Superscript> <Reference refidx="3"/></entry><entry>NCCN Prostate Cancer (Version 4.2023)<Superscript>c </Superscript><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>European Advanced Prostate Cancer Consensus Conference (Gillessen et al. 2017 <Reference refidx="2"/> and Gillessen 2020 <Reference refidx="8"/>)<Superscript>d</Superscript>  </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1">dMMR = mismatch repair deficient; FDR = first-degree relative; HBOC = hereditary breast and ovarian cancer; MMR = mismatch repair; MSI = microsatellite instability; NCCN = National Comprehensive Cancer Network; SDR= second-degree relative; TDR= third-degree relative.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Giri et al.: Specific genes to test include <GeneName>BRCA1/BRCA2</GeneName>, DNA MMR genes, <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, and <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> depending on various testing indications.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>NCCN Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic guidelines state that prostate cancer risk management is indicated for <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef>, but evidence for risk management is insufficient for other genes.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>NCCN Prostate Cancer guidelines specify that germline multigene testing includes at least the following genes: <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, and <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName>. Including additional genes may be appropriate based on  clinical context.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>d</Superscript>Gillessen et al. endorsed the use of large panel testing including homologous recombination and DNA MMR genes.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="6"><Strong>Family History Criteria </Strong></entry><entry>All men with prostate cancer from families meeting established testing or syndromic criteria for HBOC, hereditary prostate cancer, or Lynch syndrome </entry><entry>Men affected with prostate cancer who have a family history of the following: ≥1 FDR, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000485395" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">SDR</GlossaryTermRef>, or TDR (on the same side of the family) with breast cancer at age ≤50 y or with any of the following: triple-negative breast cancer, ovarian cancer, pancreatic cancer, high- or very-high-risk prostate cancer, male breast cancer, or metastatic prostate cancer at any age</entry><entry>Men  affected with prostate cancer who have the following: ≥1 FDR, SDR, or TDR (on the same side of the family) with breast cancer at age ≤50 y, colorectal or endometrial cancer at age ≤50 y, male breast cancer at any age, ovarian cancer at any age, exocrine pancreatic cancer at any age, or metastatic, regional, very-high-risk, high-risk prostate cancer at any age  </entry><entry>Men with a positive family history of prostate cancer <Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Men affected with prostate cancer who have &gt;2 close biological relatives with a cancer associated with HBOC, hereditary prostate cancer, or Lynch syndrome </entry><entry>Men affected with prostate cancer who have ≥3 FDRs, SDRs, or TDRs (on the same side of the family) with breast cancer or prostate cancer (any grade) at any age</entry><entry>Men affected with prostate cancer who have  ≥1 FDR with prostate cancer at age ≤60 y (exclude relatives with clinically localized Grade Group 1 disease)</entry><entry>Men with a positive family history of other cancer syndromes (HBOC and/or pancreatic cancer and/or Lynch syndrome) <Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Men with an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460150" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">FDR</GlossaryTermRef> who was diagnosed with prostate cancer at &lt;60 y </entry><entry>Men with or without prostate cancer with an FDR who meets any of the criteria listed above (except when a man without prostate cancer has relatives who meet the above criteria solely for systemic therapy decision-making; these criteria may also be extended to an affected TDR if he/she is related to the patient through two male relatives) </entry><entry>Men affected with prostate cancer who have ≥2 FDRs, SDRs, or TDRs (on the same side of the family) with breast cancer or  prostate cancer at any age (exclude relatives with clinically localized Grade Group 1 disease)</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Men with relatives who died of prostate cancer</entry><entry/><entry>Men affected with prostate cancer who have ≥3 FDRs or SDRs (on the same side of the family) with  the following Lynch syndrome-related cancers, especially if diagnosed at age &lt;50 y: colorectal, endometrial, gastric, ovarian, exocrine pancreas,  upper tract urothelial, glioblastoma, biliary tract, and small intestine </entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Men with a metastatic prostate cancer in an FDR</entry><entry/><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Consider genetic testing in men with prostate cancer and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460127" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Ashkenazi Jewish</GlossaryTermRef> ancestry </entry><entry>Men with prostate cancer and Ashkenazi Jewish ancestry</entry><entry>Men with prostate cancer and Ashkenazi Jewish ancestry  </entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Men with prostate cancer and a known family history of a pathogenic or likely pathogenic variant in one of the following genes: <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName>, or <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName></entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3"><Strong>Clinical/Pathological Features</Strong></entry><entry>Men with metastatic prostate cancer</entry><entry>Men with metastatic prostate cancer </entry><entry>Men with metastatic prostate cancer</entry><entry>Men with newly diagnosed metastatic prostate cancer (62% of panel voted in favor of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef>/testing in a minority of selected patients) <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Men with stage T3a or higher prostate cancer</entry><entry>Men with high- or very-high-risk prostate cancer  </entry><entry>Men with high-risk prostate cancer,  very-high-risk prostate cancer, high-risk localized prostate cancer, or regional (node-positive) prostate cancer</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Men with prostate cancer that has intraductal/ductal histology</entry><entry>Testing may be considered in men who have intermediate-risk prostate cancer with intraductal/cribriform histology at any age </entry><entry>Germline testing may be considered in men who have intermediate-risk prostate cancer with intraductal/cribriform histology at any age </entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Germline testing may be considered in men with prostate cancer AND a prior personal history of any of the following cancers: exocrine pancreatic, colorectal, gastric, melanoma, upper tract urothelial, glioblastoma, biliary tract, and small intestinal</entry><entry>Men with prostate cancer diagnosed at age &lt;60 y <Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"><Strong>Tumor Sequencing Characteristics </Strong></entry><entry>Men with prostate cancer whose somatic testing reveals the possibility of a germline variant in a cancer risk gene, especially <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, and DNA MMR genes</entry><entry>Men with a pathogenic variant found on tumor genomic testing that may have clinical implications if it is also identified in the germline </entry><entry>Recommend tumor testing for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in homologous recombination genes  in men with metastatic disease; consider tumor testing in men with regional prostate cancer</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry> Recommend <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285933" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">MSI</GlossaryTermRef>-high or dMMR tumor testing  in men with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer; consider testing in men with regional or castration-sensitive metastatic  prostate cancer</entry><entry/></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="29236593">Giri VN, Knudsen KE, Kelly WK, et al.: Role of Genetic Testing for Inherited Prostate Cancer Risk: Philadelphia Prostate Cancer Consensus Conference 2017. J Clin Oncol 36 (4): 414-424, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="28655541">Gillessen S, Attard G, Beer TM, et al.: Management of Patients with Advanced Prostate Cancer: The Report of the Advanced Prostate Cancer Consensus Conference APCCC 2017. Eur Urol 73 (2): 178-211, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="3">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic. Version 2.2024. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_bop.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="4">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Prostate Cancer. Version 4.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/prostate.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed November 30, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="5">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Prostate Cancer Early Detection. Version 2.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/prostate_detection.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed November 30, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="32516092">Giri VN, Knudsen KE, Kelly WK, et al.: Implementation of Germline Testing for Prostate Cancer: Philadelphia Prostate Cancer Consensus Conference 2019. J Clin Oncol 38 (24): 2798-2811, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26590952">Raymond VM, Gray SW, Roychowdhury S, et al.: Germline Findings in Tumor-Only Sequencing: Points to Consider for Clinicians and Laboratories. J Natl Cancer Inst 108 (4): , 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="32001144">Gillessen S, Attard G, Beer TM, et al.: Management of Patients with Advanced Prostate Cancer: Report of the Advanced Prostate Cancer Consensus Conference 2019. Eur Urol 77 (4): 508-547, 2020.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1851"><Title>Genetic Testing Approach for Prostate Cancer</Title><Para id="_1852">Since <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763024" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">next-generation sequencing</GlossaryTermRef> (NGS) has become readily available and patent restrictions have been eliminated, several clinical laboratories offer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775581" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">multigene panel</GlossaryTermRef> testing at a cost that is comparable to that of single-gene testing. Three types of genetic test results can be reported: 1) pathogenic/likely pathogenic variants, 2)  variants of uncertain significance (VUS), or 3) negative results. Patients need pretest genetic counseling or informed consent to understand germline genetic testing results. For example, patients should understand that VUS can be reported, that VUS do not immediately impact care/inform cancer risk, and that VUS may be reclassified  as either pathogenic/likely pathogenic or benign/likely benign when more data are acquired. For more information on genetic counseling considerations and research associated with multigene testing, see the  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865#_1320" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Multigene (panel) testing</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1770"><Title>Germline Genetics for Prostate Cancer</Title><Para id="_2011">Prostate cancer is highly heritable. More than half of an individual's prostate cancer risk is inherited from one's parents.<Reference refidx="1"/> Considerable work has been performed to identify and characterize inherited germline  variants that contribute to the genetic portion of prostate cancer risk. For most patients, the bulk of inherited risk is conferred by hundreds of genetic polymorphisms, which are common in the general population. Each of these polymorphisms  slightly increases prostate cancer risk. For a small subset of patients, prostate cancer risk is generated by rare, deleterious variants located in specific genes. In this section, we will describe the specific genes implicated in inherited prostate cancer risk and the many common polymorphisms (which are typically located in the genomic space between genes) that create a risk profile for most patients.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000746226" type="image/jpeg" alt="Graph shows relative risk on the x-axis and allele frequency on the y-axis. A line depicts the general finding of a low relative risk associated with common, low-penetrance genetic variants and a higher relative risk associated with rare, high-penetrance genetic variants." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_2035"><Caption language="en">Genetic architecture of cancer risk. This graph depicts the general finding of a low relative risk associated with common, low-penetrance genetic variants, such as single-nucleotide polymorphisms identified in genome-wide association studies, and a higher relative risk associated with rare, high-penetrance genetic variants, such as mutations in the <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/ <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> genes associated with hereditary breast and ovarian cancer and the mismatch repair genes associated with Lynch syndrome.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><SummarySection id="_2010"><Title>Clinically Relevant Genes for Prostate Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_1881"><Title><GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName></Title><Para id="_1882">Studies of male carriers of <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>  pathogenic variants demonstrate that these individuals have a higher risk of prostate cancer and other cancers.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Prostate cancer, in particular, has been observed at higher rates in male  carriers of <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants than in the general population.<Reference refidx="4"/> For more information about <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811356" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/brca-genes-hp-pdq">BRCA1 and BRCA2: Cancer Risks and Management</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_1883"><Title><GeneName>BRCA</GeneName>–associated prostate cancer risk</Title><Para id="_1884">The risk of prostate cancer in carriers of <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> pathogenic variants has been studied in various settings.</Para><Para id="_1885">In an effort to clarify the relationship between <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> pathogenic variants and prostate cancer risk, findings from a systematic review and meta-analysis are summarized in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_2053" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 3</SummaryRef> .</Para><Table id="_2053"><Title>Table 3.  <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants in Prostate Cancer<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="12.04%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="27.95%"/><THead><Row><entry>Population

</entry><entry>Number of Studies</entry><entry>Fixed-Effect Pooled Prostate Cancer RR (95% CI)</entry><entry>Random-Effect Pooled Prostate Cancer RR (95% CI)</entry><entry>I<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1">CI = confidence interval; RR = relative risk.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Nyberg et al.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry>All </entry><entry>20</entry><entry>1.57 (1.30–1.91)</entry><entry>1.69 (1.30–2.20)</entry><entry>30%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Unselected for age, aggressive prostate cancer, or prostate cancer family history</entry><entry>15</entry><entry>1.43 (1.71–1.75)</entry><entry>1.47 (1.13–1.91)</entry><entry>25%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Unselected for age, aggressive prostate cancer, or prostate cancer family history <Strong>and</Strong> did not use historical controls</entry><entry>13			</entry><entry>1.32 (1.07–1.64)</entry><entry>1.33 (1.05–1.69)</entry><entry>8%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Prostate cancer diagnosed &lt;65 y</entry><entry>4		</entry><entry>2.21 (1.47–3.30)</entry><entry>	2.19 (1.21–3.98)	</entry><entry>57%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Prostate cancer diagnosed &gt;65 y</entry><entry>3		</entry><entry>1.18 (0.83–1.70)	</entry><entry>1.43 (0.71–2.87)</entry><entry>65%</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry>All</entry><entry>21		</entry><entry>5.24 (4.63–5.49)</entry><entry>3.94 (2.79–5.56)	</entry><entry>83%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Unselected for age, aggressive prostate cancer, or prostate cancer family history</entry><entry>15			</entry><entry>3.87 (3.34–4.47)</entry><entry>3.33 (2.57–4.33)</entry><entry>58%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Prostate cancer diagnosed &lt;65 y</entry><entry>5			</entry><entry>6.37 (4.81–8.43)</entry><entry>5.28 (3.10–9.00)</entry><entry>63%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Prostate cancer diagnosed &gt;65 y</entry><entry>3			</entry><entry>3.74 (2.82–4.96)</entry><entry>3.74 (2.82–4.96)</entry><entry>0%</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1889"><Title>Prevalence of <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> founder pathogenic variants in men with prostate cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_1890"><Title>Ashkenazi Jewish population</Title><Para id="_1891">Several studies in Israel and in North America have analyzed the frequency of <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783962" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">founder pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> among Ashkenazi Jewish (AJ) men with prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> Two specific <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> pathogenic variants (185delAG and 5382insC) and one <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variant (6174delT) are common in individuals of AJ ancestry. Carrier frequencies for these pathogenic variants in the general Jewish population are 0.9% (95% CI, 0.7%–1.1%) for the 185delAG pathogenic variant, 0.3% (95% CI, 0.2%–0.4%) for the 5382insC pathogenic variant, and 1.3% (95% CI, 1.0%–1.5%) for the <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> 6174delT pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> In these studies, the relative risks (RRs) were commonly greater than 1, but only a few were statistically significant. Many of these studies were not sufficiently powered to rule out a lower, but clinically significant, risk of prostate cancer in carriers of Ashkenazi <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> founder pathogenic variants.</Para><Para id="_2022"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_2054" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 4</SummaryRef> summarizes the findings from a systemic review and meta-analysis, which help clarify the relationship between <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> pathogenic variants and prostate cancer risk in individuals of Ashkenazi Jewish heritage.</Para><Table id="_2054"><Title>Table 4.  <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants in Ashkenazi Jewish Populations with Prostate Cancer<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="19.97%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="19.97%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="20.11%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="13.77%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="26.17%"/><THead><Row><entry>Population			</entry><entry>Number of Studies</entry><entry>Fixed-Effect Pooled Prostate Cancer RR (95% CI)	</entry><entry>Random-Effect Pooled Prostate Cancer RR (95% CI)</entry><entry>I<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1">CI = confidence interval; RR = relative risk.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Nyberg et al.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry>All				</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>1.12 (0.55–2.31)</entry><entry>1.12 (0.55–2.31)</entry><entry>0%</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry>All				</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>2.08 (1.38–3.12)</entry><entry>2.08 (1.38–3.12)</entry><entry>0%</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1895">This systematic review and meta-analysis provide further evidence that prostate cancer occurs more often in Ashkenazi Jewish <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> founder variant carriers and suggests that prostate cancer risk may be greater in men with <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> 6174delT founder pathogenic variants  than in men  with <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> 85delAG or <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> 5382insC founder pathogenic variants.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1896"><Title>Other populations</Title><Para id="_1897">The association between prostate cancer and pathogenic variants in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> has also been studied in other populations.  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_2055" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 5</SummaryRef>  summarizes studies from a systematic review and meta-analysis. This table reports  the prevalence of <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> pathogenic variants in men with prostate cancer from other varied populations.</Para><Table id="_2055"> <Title>Table 5.  Case-Control Studies in Varied Populations With <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants and Prostate Cancer Risk<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="20.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Population			</entry><entry>Number of Studies</entry><entry>Fixed-Effect Pooled Prostate Cancer RR (95% CI)	</entry><entry>Random-Effect Pooled Prostate Cancer RR (95% CI)</entry><entry>I<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1">CI = confidence interval; RR = relative risk.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Nyberg et al.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry>Non-Ashkenazi European Ancestry			</entry><entry>8</entry><entry>1.30 (1.03–1.64)</entry><entry>1.30 (0.95–1.79)</entry><entry>30%</entry></Row><Row><entry>African Ancestry		</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>1.11 (0.09–13.61)</entry><entry>1.11 (0.09–13.61)</entry><entry>-</entry></Row><Row><entry>Asian Ancestry		</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2.27 (0.92–5.59)</entry><entry>2.27 (0.92–5.59)</entry><entry>-</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry>Non-Ashkenazi European Ancestry			</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>4.07 (3.45–4.80)</entry><entry>3.69 (2.71–5.04)</entry><entry>66%</entry></Row><Row><entry>African Ancestry		</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>10.30 (1.28–82.73)</entry><entry>10.30 (1.28–82.73)</entry><entry>-</entry></Row><Row><entry>Asian Ancestry		</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>5.65 (3.49–9.15)</entry><entry>5.65 (3.49–9.15)</entry><entry>-</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1903"><Title>Prostate cancer aggressiveness in carriers of <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> pathogenic variants</Title><Para id="_1904">A systematic review and meta-analysis  found that <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> showed differences in prostate cancer aggressiveness.<Reference refidx="3"/> The pooled, random-effects RRs of aggressive prostate cancer (using any definition of aggressiveness) were the following for <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2040" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>: RR, 1.98 (1.35–2.90; I² = 0%).</ListItem><ListItem><GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: RR, 6.08 (3.44–10.8; I² = 82%). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1906">Men harboring pathogenic variants in the United Kingdom and Ireland were prospectively followed for prostate cancer diagnoses (<GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> [n = 16/376] and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> [n = 26/447]; median follow-up, 5.9 y and 5.3 y, respectively).<Reference refidx="12"/> The prostate cancers identified covered the spectrum of Gleason scores from less than 6 to greater than 8; however, they  differed by gene: </Para><ItemizedList id="_1907" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> Gleason score less than 6; standardized incidence ratio (SIR), 3.50 (95% CI, 1.67–7.35) and Gleason score greater than 7; SIR, 1.80 (95% CI, 0.89–3.65).</ListItem><ListItem><GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> Gleason score less than 6; SIR, 3.03 (95% CI, 1.24–7.44) and Gleason score greater than 7; SIR, 5.07 (95% CI, 3.20–8.02).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2049">This study was followed by a large, retrospective, international study of men diagnosed with prostate cancer who had pathogenic variants in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> (n = 3,453) and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> (n = 3,051).<Reference refidx="13"/> In <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, there were no statistically significant associations between overall prostate cancer risk/prostate cancer with a Gleason score of 8 or higher <Strong>and</Strong> pathogenic sequence variant types, pathogenic variant function, or the region of the gene in which a pathogenic variant occurred, such as RING or <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> C-terminal (BRCT) domains. In contrast,  two prostate cancer cluster regions were identified in <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 1) 3’ of <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> c.7914 (hazard ratio [HR],1.78; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.25–2.52; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001),  and 2) <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> c.756–c.1000 (HR, 2.83; 95% CI, 1.71–4.68; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 4.0 x 10<Superscript>-5</Superscript>).</Para><Para id="_1908">These studies suggest that prostate cancer in <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> carriers is associated with aggressive disease features including a high Gleason score, and a high tumor stage and/or grade at diagnosis. This is a finding that warrants consideration when patients undergo cancer risk assessment and genetic counseling.<Reference refidx="14"/> Research is under way to gain insight into the biological basis of aggressive prostate cancer in carriers of <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> pathogenic variants. One study of 14 <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> germline pathogenic variant carriers reported that <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>-associated prostate cancers  harbor increased genomic instability and a mutational profile that more closely resembles metastatic prostate cancer than localized disease, with genomic and epigenomic dysregulation of the <GeneName>MED12L</GeneName>/<GeneName>MED12</GeneName> axis similar to metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1909"><Title><GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> and survival outcomes</Title><Para id="_1910">Analyses of prostate cancer cases in families with known <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> or <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants have been examined for survival. A meta-analysis that examined <GeneName>BRCA1/BRCA2</GeneName> prostate cancer risk, <GeneName>BRCA1/BRCA2</GeneName> frequency in patients with prostate cancer, and prostate cancer mortality found that <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers who were diagnosed with prostate cancer had decreased cancer-specific survival (HR, 2.53; 95% CI, 1.98–3.22; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) when compared with noncarriers.<Reference refidx="16"/> Similarly, prostate cancer overall survival (OS) was lower in men with  <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants (HR, 2.08; 95% CI, 1.55–2.79; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001). <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers had decreased  cancer-specific survival (HR, 2.63; 95% CI, 2.00–3.47; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) and OS (HR, 2.21; 95% CI, 1.64–2.99; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) values when compared with noncarriers. <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers (<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, 71.1%; 95% CI, 31.4%–93.0%) were also more likely to have prostate cancer with a Gleason score of 7 or greater than <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> carriers (<GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, 36.3%; 95% CI, 20.0%–56.5%). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1916"><Title>HOXB13</Title><SummarySection id="_1917"><Title>Key points</Title><Para id="_1918"><GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> was the first gene found to be associated with hereditary prostate cancer. The <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E variant has been extensively studied because of its association with prostate cancer risk.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1919" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Overall risk of prostate cancer with the G84E variant ranges from 3- to 5-fold, with a higher risk of early-onset prostate cancer with the G84E variant of up to 10-fold.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> for carriers of the G84E variant is an approximate 60% lifetime risk of prostate cancer by age 80 years.</ListItem><ListItem>There is no clear association of the G84E variant with aggressive prostate cancer or other cancers.</ListItem><ListItem>Preliminary studies suggest additional variants in <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> may be relevant for prostate cancer risk in diverse populations.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1920"><Title>Background</Title><Para id="_1921">Linkage to 17q21-22 was initially reported by the UM-PCGP from 175 pedigrees of families with hereditary prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="17"/> Fine-mapping of this region provided strong evidence of linkage (LOD score, 5.49) and a narrow candidate interval (15.5 Mb) for a putative susceptibility gene among 147 families with four or more affected men and average age at diagnosis of 65 years or younger.<Reference refidx="18"/>  The exons of 200 genes  in the 17q21-22 region were sequenced in DNA from 94 unrelated patients from hereditary prostate cancer families (from the UM-PCGP and Johns Hopkins University).<Reference refidx="19"/>    <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460211" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Probands</GlossaryTermRef> from four families were discovered to have a recurrent pathogenic variant (G84E) in <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName>, and 18 men with prostate cancer from these four families carried the pathogenic variant.  The pathogenic variant status was determined in 5,083 additional cases and 2,662 controls. Carrier frequencies and ORs for prostate cancer risk were as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1922" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Men with a positive family history of prostate cancer,  2.2% versus negative, 0.8% (OR, 2.8; 95% CI, 1.6–5.1; <Emphasis>P </Emphasis> = 1.2 × 10<Superscript>-4</Superscript>).</ListItem><ListItem>Men younger than 55 years at diagnosis, 2.2% versus older than 55 years, 0.8% (OR, 2.7; 95% CI, 1.6–4.7; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 1.1 × 10<Superscript>-4</Superscript>).</ListItem><ListItem>Men with a positive family history of prostate cancer and younger than 55 years at diagnosis, 3.1% versus   a negative  family history of prostate cancer and age at diagnosis older than 55 years, 0.6% (OR, 5.1; 95% CI, 2.4–12.2; <Emphasis>P </Emphasis>= 2.0 × 10<Superscript>-6</Superscript>).</ListItem><ListItem>Men with a positive family history of prostate cancer and older than 55 years at diagnosis, 1.2%.</ListItem><ListItem>Controls,  0.1% to 0.2%.<Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1923">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803523" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">clinical  utility</GlossaryTermRef> of genetic testing for the <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E variant is evolving.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1924"><Title>Validation and confirmatory studies</Title><Para id="_1925">A validation study from the International Consortium of Prostate Cancer Genetics confirmed <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> as a susceptibility gene for prostate cancer risk.<Reference refidx="22"/>  Within carrier families, the G84E pathogenic variant was more common among men with prostate cancer than among <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460224" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">unaffected</GlossaryTermRef> men (OR, 4.42; 95% CI, 2.56–7.64).  The G84E pathogenic variant was also significantly overtransmitted from parents to affected offspring (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 6.5 × 10<Superscript>-6</Superscript>). </Para><Para id="_1926">Additional studies have emerged that better define the carrier frequency and prostate cancer risk associated with the <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/> This pathogenic variant appears to be restricted to White men, primarily of European descent.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/> The highest carrier frequency of 6.25% was reported in Finnish early-onset cases.<Reference refidx="26"/> A pooled analysis of European Americans that included 9,016 cases and 9,678 controls found an overall G84E pathogenic variant frequency of 1.34% among cases and 0.28% among controls.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_1927">Risk of prostate cancer by <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E pathogenic variant status has been reported to vary by age of onset, family history, and geographical region.  A validation study in an independent cohort of 9,988 cases and 61,994 controls from six studies of men of European ancestry, including 4,537 cases and 54,444 controls from Iceland whose genotypes were largely imputed, reported an OR of 7.06 (95% CI, 4.62–10.78; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 1.5 × 10<Superscript>−19</Superscript>) for prostate cancer risk by G84E carrier status.<Reference refidx="29"/>  A pooled analysis reported a prostate cancer OR of 4.86 (95% CI, 3.18–7.69; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 3.48  × 10<Superscript>-17</Superscript>) in men with <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> pathogenic variants compared with noncarriers; this increased to an OR of 8.41 (95% CI, 5.27–13.76; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 2.72 ×10<Superscript>-22</Superscript>) among men diagnosed with prostate cancer at age 55 years or younger.  The OR was 7.19 (95% CI, 4.55–11.67; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 9.3 × 10<Superscript>-21</Superscript>) among men with a
positive family history of prostate cancer and  3.09 (95% CI, 1.83–5.23; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 6.26 × 10<Superscript>-6</Superscript>) among men with a negative family history of prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="27"/>  A meta-analysis that included 24,213 cases and 73,631 controls of European descent revealed an overall OR for prostate cancer by carrier status of  4.07 (95% CI, 3.05–5.45; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00001).  Risk of prostate cancer varied by geographical region:  United States (OR, 5.10; 95% CI, 3.21–8.10; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00001), Canada (OR, 5.80; 95% CI, 1.27–26.51; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02), Northern Europe (OR, 3.61; 95% CI, 2.81–4.64; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00001), and Western Europe (OR, 8.47; 95% CI, 3.68–19.48; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00001).<Reference refidx="24"/> In addition, the association between the G84E pathogenic variant and prostate cancer risk was higher for early-onset cases (OR, 10.11; 95% CI, 5.97–17.12).  There was no significant association with aggressive disease in the meta-analysis. </Para><Para id="_1928">Another meta-analysis that included 11 case-control studies also reported higher risk estimates for prostate cancer in <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E carriers (OR, 4.51; 95% CI, 3.28–6.20; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00001) and found a stronger association between <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E  and early-onset disease (OR, 9.73; 95% CI, 6.57–14.39; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00001).<Reference refidx="30"/> An additional meta-analysis of 25 studies that included 51,390 cases and 93,867 controls revealed an OR for prostate cancer of 3.248 (95% CI, 2.121–3.888). The association was most significant in White individuals (OR, 2.673; 95% CI, 1.920–3.720), especially those of European descent. No association was found for breast or colorectal cancer.<Reference refidx="31"/> One population-based, case-control study from the United States confirmed the association of the G84E pathogenic variant with prostate cancer (OR, 3.30; 95% CI, 1.21–8.96) and reported a suggestive association with  aggressive disease.<Reference refidx="32"/>  In addition, one study identified no men of AJ ancestry who carried the G84E pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="33"/> A case-control study from the United Kingdom that included 8,652 cases and 5,252 controls also confirmed the association of <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E with  prostate cancer (OR, 2.93; 95% CI, 1.94–4.59; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 6.27 × 10<Superscript>-8</Superscript>).<Reference refidx="34"/> The risk was higher among men with a family history  of the disease (OR, 4.53; 95% CI, 2.86–7.34; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 3.1 × 10<Superscript>−8</Superscript>) and in early-onset prostate cancer (diagnosed at age 55 y or younger) (OR,  3.11; 95% CI, 1.98–5.00; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 6.1 × 10<Superscript>−7</Superscript>).  No association was found between carrier status and Gleason score, cancer stage, OS, or cancer-specific survival.</Para><Para id="_1929">However, a 2018 publication of a study combining multiple prostate cancer cases and controls of Nordic origin along with functional analysis reported that simultaneous presence of <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> (G84E) and <GeneName>CIP2A</GeneName> (R229Q) predisposes men to an increased risk of prostate cancer (OR, 21.1; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .000024).<Reference refidx="35"/> Furthermore, dual carriers had elevated risk for high Gleason score (OR, 2.3; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .025) and worse prostate cancer–specific survival (hazard ratio [HR], 3.9; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .048). Clinical validation is needed.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1930"><Title><GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> pathogenic variants in diverse populations</Title><Para id="_1931">A study of Chinese men with and without prostate cancer failed to identify the <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E pathogenic variant; however, there was an excess of a novel variant, G135E, in cases compared with controls.<Reference refidx="36"/> A large study of approximately 20,000 Japanese men with and without prostate cancer identified another novel <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> variant, G132E, which was associated with prostate cancer with an OR of 6.08 (95% CI, 3.39–11.59).<Reference refidx="37"/></Para><Para id="_1932">Two studies confirmed the association between the <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> X285K variant and increased prostate cancer risk in African American men after this variant was identified in Martinique.<Reference refidx="38"/> One of these was a  single-institution study, which sequenced <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> in a clinical patient population of 1,048 African American men undergoing prostatectomy for prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="39"/> The <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> X285K variant was identified in eight patients.  In a case–case analysis, X285K variant carriers were at increased risk of developing clinically significant prostate cancer (1.2% X285K carrier rate in  prostate cancers with a Gleason score ≥7  vs. 0% X285K carrier rate in prostate cancers with Gleason score &lt;7; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .028). Similarly, X285K variant carriers also had an increased chance of developing prostate cancer at an early age (2.4% X285K carrier rate in patients &lt;50 years vs. 0.5% X285K carrier rate in patients ≥50 years; OR, 5.25; 95% CI, 1.00–28.52; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03). A second study included  11,688 prostate cancer cases and 10,673 controls from multiple large consortia.<Reference refidx="40"/> The <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> X285K variant was only present in men of West African ancestry and was associated with a 2.4-fold increased chance of developing prostate cancer (95% CI, 1.5–3.9; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 2 x 10<Superscript>-4</Superscript>). Individuals with the  X285K variant were also more likely to have aggressive and advanced prostate cancer (Gleason score ≥8: OR, 4.7; 95% CI, 2.3–9.5; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 2 x 10<Superscript>-5</Superscript>; stage T3/T4: OR, 4.5; 95% CI, 2.0–10.0; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 2 x 10<Superscript>-4</Superscript>; metastatic disease: OR, 5.1; 95% CI, 1.9–13.7; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001). This information is important to consider when developing genetic tests for <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> pathogenic variants in broader populations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1933"><Title>Penetrance</Title><Para id="_1934">Penetrance estimates for prostate cancer development in carriers of the <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E pathogenic variant are also being reported.  One study from Sweden estimated a 33% lifetime risk of prostate cancer among G84E carriers.<Reference refidx="41"/>  Another study from Australia reported an age-specific cumulative risk of prostate cancer of up to 60% by age 80 years.<Reference refidx="42"/> A study in the United Kingdom that included <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> genotype data from nearly 12,000 men with prostate cancer enrolled between 1993 and 2014 reported that the average predicted risk of prostate cancer by age 85 years is 62% (95% CI, 47%–76%) for carriers of the G84E pathogenic variant.  The risk of developing prostate cancer in variant carriers increased if the men had affected family members, especially those diagnosed at an early age.<Reference refidx="43"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1935"><Title>Biology</Title><Para id="_1936"><GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> plays a role in prostate cancer development  and interacts with the androgen receptor; however, the mechanism by which it contributes to the pathogenesis of prostate cancer remains unknown. This is the first gene identified to account for a fraction of hereditary prostate cancer, particularly early-onset prostate cancer. The clinical utility and implications for genetic counseling regarding <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> G84E or other pathogenic variants have yet to be defined.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1937"><Title>DNA mismatch repair genes (Lynch syndrome)</Title><Para id="_1938">Five genes are implicated in mismatch repair (MMR), namely <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName>.  Germline pathogenic variants in these five  genes have been associated with Lynch syndrome, which manifests by cases of nonpolyposis colorectal cancer and a constellation of other cancers in families, including endometrial, ovarian, duodenal cancers, and transitional cell cancers of the ureter and renal pelvis. For more information about other cancers that are associated with Lynch syndrome,  see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_2986" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Lynch syndrome</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer. Reports have suggested that prostate cancer may be observed in men harboring an MMR gene pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/> The first quantitative study described nine cases of prostate cancer occurring in a population-based cohort of 106 Norwegian male carriers of MMR gene pathogenic variants or obligate carriers.<Reference refidx="46"/> The expected number of cases among these 106 men was 1.52 (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01); the men were younger at the time of diagnosis (60.4 y vs. 66.6 y; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006) and had more evidence of Gleason score of 8 to 10 (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00001) than the cases from the Norwegian Cancer Registry.  Kaplan-Meier analysis revealed that the cumulative risk of prostate cancer diagnosis by age 70 years was 30% in carriers of MMR gene pathogenic variants and 8% in the general population.  This finding awaits confirmation in additional populations. A population-based case-control study examined haplotype-tagging SNVs in three MMR genes (<GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName>). This study provided some evidence supporting the contribution of genetic variation in <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName> and overall risk of prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="47"/>  To assess the contribution of prostate cancer as a feature of Lynch syndrome, one study performed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285933" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">microsatellite instability</GlossaryTermRef> (MSI) testing on prostate cancer tissue blocks from families enrolled in a prostate cancer family registry who also reported a history of colon cancer.  Among 35 tissue blocks from 31 distinct families, two tumors from families with MMR gene pathogenic variants were found to be MSI-high. The authors conclude that MSI is rare in hereditary prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="48"/> Other studies are attempting to characterize rates of prostate cancer in Lynch syndrome families and correlate molecular features with prostate cancer risk.<Reference refidx="49"/></Para><Para id="_1939">One study that included two familial cancer registries found an increased cumulative incidence and risk of prostate cancer among  198 independent families with MMR gene pathogenic variants and Lynch syndrome.<Reference refidx="50"/> The cumulative lifetime risk of prostate cancer (to age 80 y) was 30.0% (95% CI, 16.54%–41.30%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .07) in carriers of MMR gene pathogenic variants, whereas it was 17.84% in the general population, according to the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program estimates. There was a trend of increased  prostate cancer risk  in carriers of pathogenic variants by age 50 years, where the risk was 0.64% (95% CI, 0.24%–1.01%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .06),  compared with a risk of 0.26% in the general population. Overall, the HR (to age 80 y) for prostate cancer in carriers of MMR gene pathogenic variants in the combined data set was 1.99 (95% CI, 1.31–3.03; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0013). Among men aged 20 to 59 years, the HR  was 2.48 (95% CI, 1.34–4.59; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0038).</Para><Para id="_1940">A systematic review and meta-analysis that included 23 studies (6 studies with molecular characterization and 18 risk studies, of which 12 studies quantified risk for prostate cancer) reported an association of prostate cancer with Lynch syndrome.<Reference refidx="51"/> In the six molecular studies included in the analysis, 73% (95% CI, 57%–85%) of prostate cancers in carriers of MMR gene pathogenic variants were MMR deficient. The RR of prostate cancer in carriers of MMR gene pathogenic variants was estimated to be 3.67 (95% CI, 2.32–6.67). Of the twelve risk studies, the RR of prostate cancer ranged from 2.11 to 2.28, compared with  that seen in the general population depending on carrier status, prior diagnosis of colorectal cancer, or unknown male carrier status from families with a known pathogenic variant. </Para><Para id="_1941">A study from three sites participating in the Colon Cancer Family Registry examined 32 cases of prostate cancer (mean age at diagnosis, 62 y; standard deviation,  8 y) in men with a documented MMR gene pathogenic variant (23 <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName> carriers, 5 <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName> carriers, and 4 <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName> carriers).<Reference refidx="52"/> Seventy-two percent (n = 23) had a previous diagnosis of colorectal cancer. Immunohistochemistry was used to assess MMR protein loss, which was observed in 22 tumors (69%);   the pattern of loss of protein expression was 100% concordant with the germline pathogenic variant. The RR of prostate cancer was highest in carriers of <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName> pathogenic variants (RR, 5.8; 95% CI, 2.6–20.9); the RRs in carriers of <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName> and <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName> pathogenic variants were 1.7 (95% CI, 1.1–6.7) and 1.3 (95% CI, 1.1–5.3), respectively.  Gleason scores ranged from 5 to 10; two tumors had a Gleason score of 5; 22 tumors had a Gleason score of  6 or 7; and eight tumors had a Gleason score higher than 8.  Sixty-seven percent (12 of 18) of the tumors were found to have perineural invasion, and 47% (9 of 19) had extracapsular invasion. A large observational cohort study, which included more than 6,000 MMR-variant carriers, reported an increased cumulative incidence of prostate cancer by age 70 years for specific MMR genes, as follows: <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName> (7.0; 95% CI, 4.2–11.9), <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName> (15.9; 95% CI, 11.2–22.5), and <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName> (4.6; 95% CI, 0.8–67.5). No significant increase in prostate cancer incidence was reported for <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="53"/></Para><Para id="_1942">Although the risk of prostate cancer appears to be elevated in families with Lynch syndrome, strategies for germline testing for MMR gene pathogenic variants in index prostate cancer patients remain to be determined. </Para><Para id="_1943">A study of 1,133 primary prostate adenocarcinomas and 43 neuroendocrine prostate cancers (NEPC) conducted screening by MSH2 immunohistochemistry with conﬁrmation by NGS.<Reference refidx="54"/>  MSI was assessed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044798" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">polymerase chain reaction</GlossaryTermRef> and NGS. Of primary adenocarcinomas and NEPC, 1.2% (14/1,176) had MSH2 loss. Overall, 8% (7/91) of adenocarcinomas with primary Gleason pattern 5 (Gleason score 9–10) had MSH2 loss compared with 0.4% (5/1,042) of tumors with any other Gleason scores (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05). Three patients had germline variants in <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, of whom two had a primary Gleason score of 5.  Pending further confirmation, these findings may support universal MMR screening of prostate cancer with a Gleason score of 9 to 10 to identify men who may be eligible for immunotherapy and germline testing.  </Para><Para id="_2001"><GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName> testing has been included in some multigene panels likely due to <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName> variants silencing <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>.  Specific large genomic rearrangement variants at the 3’ end of <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName> (which lies near the <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName> gene) induce methylation of the <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName> promoter, resulting in MSH2 protein loss.<Reference refidx="55"/>  Pathogenic variants in <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName> are associated with Lynch syndrome and an  increase in prostate cancer risk.<Reference refidx="52"/>  For more information on <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName> and <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_2938" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Gene-specific considerations and associated CRC risk</SummaryRef> section or the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_2986" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Lynch Syndrome</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer.  Thus far, studies have not found an association between increased prostate cancer  risk and <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="56"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1947"><Title><GeneName>ATM</GeneName></Title><Para id="_1948">Ataxia telangiectasia (AT) is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339339" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal recessive</GlossaryTermRef> disorder characterized by
neurological deterioration, telangiectasias, immunodeficiency states, and
hypersensitivity to ionizing radiation.  It is estimated that 1%
of the general population may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339341" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef> carriers of <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="57"/> In the presence of DNA damage, the ATM protein is involved in mediating cell cycle arrest, DNA repair, and apoptosis.<Reference refidx="58"/> Given evidence of other cancer risks in heterozygous <GeneName>ATM </GeneName>carriers, evidence of an association with prostate cancer susceptibility continues to emerge. A prospective case series of 10,317 Danish individuals who had a  36-year follow-up period, during which 2,056 individuals developed cancer, found that the <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> Ser49Cys  variant was associated with increased prostate cancer risk (HR, 2.3; 95% CI, 1.1–5.0).<Reference refidx="58"/> A retrospective case series of 692 men with metastatic prostate cancer, who were not selected  based on a family history of cancer or the patient's age at cancer diagnosis, found that 1.6% of participants (11 of 692) had an <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="56"/> Multiple independent reports have shown that the <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> P1054R variant, which is found in 2% of Europeans, is associated with increased prostate cancer risk.<Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="59"/><Reference refidx="60"/> For example, the Prostate Cancer Association Group to Investigate Cancer Associated Alterations in the Genome  (PRACTICAL) consortium found  an OR of 1.16  (95% CI, 1.10–1.22)  for the <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> P1054 variant's association with prostate cancer risk.<Reference refidx="61"/> A subsequent PRACTICAL consortium study had  14 groups (five from North America, six from Europe, and two from Australia) and 8,913 participants (5,560 cases and 3,353 controls). Next-generation <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> sequencing data were standardized and ClinVar classifications were used to categorize the variants as Tier 1 (likely pathogenic) or Tier 2 (potentially deleterious). Prostate cancer risk in Tier 1 variants had an OR of 4.4 (95% CI, 2.0–9.5).<Reference refidx="62"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1949"><Title><GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName></Title><Para id="_1950"><GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName> has also been investigated for a potential association with prostate cancer risk. For more information on other cancers associated with <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName> pathogenic variants, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062855#_1309" url="/types/breast/hp/breast-ovarian-genetics-pdq"><GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName></SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Breast and Gynecologic Cancers and the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_3583" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq"><GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName></SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer. A retrospective case series of 692 men with metastatic prostate cancer unselected for cancer family history or age at diagnosis found 1.9%  (10 of 534 [men with data]) were found to have a <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName> pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="56"/> A systematic review and meta-analysis from eight retrospective cohort studies examining the relationship between <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName> variants (1100delC, IVS2+1G&gt;A, I157T) and prostate cancer confirmed the association of the 1100delC  (OR, 3.29; 95% CI, 1.85–5.85; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .00) and I157T (OR, 1.80; 95% CI, 1.51–2.14; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .00)  variants with prostate cancer susceptibility.<Reference refidx="63"/> A genome-wide association study (GWAS) focusing on African American cases and controls identified a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense variant</GlossaryTermRef>, I448S, which is associated with prostate cancer (risk allele frequency, 1.5%; OR, 1.62; 95% CI, 1.39–1.89, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 7.50 × 10<Superscript>-10</Superscript>).<Reference refidx="64"/> Further studies of <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName> in large diverse populations are warranted.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1951"><Title><GeneName>TP53</GeneName></Title><Para id="_1952"><GeneName>TP53</GeneName> has also been investigated for a potential association with prostate cancer risk. For more information about other cancers associated with <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> pathogenic variants, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062855#_3755" url="/types/breast/hp/breast-ovarian-genetics-pdq">Li-Fraumeni Syndrome</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Breast and Gynecologic Cancers. In a case series of 286 individuals from 107 families with a deleterious <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variant, 403 cancer diagnoses were reported, of which 211 were the first primary cancer including two prostate cancers diagnosed after age 45 years. Prostate cancer was also reported in 4 of 61 men with a second primary cancer.<Reference refidx="65"/> In a Dutch case series of 180 families meeting either classic Li-Fraumeni syndrome (LFS) or Li-Fraumeni–like (LFL) family history criteria, a deleterious <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variant was identified in 24 families with one case of prostate cancer found in each group (LFS or LFL). Prostate cancer risks varied on the basis of the family history criteria with LFS (RR, 0.50; 95% CI, 0.01–3.00) and LFL (RR, 4.90; 95% CI, 0.10–27.00).<Reference refidx="66"/>  In a French case series of 415 families with a deleterious <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variant, four prostate cancers were reported, with a mean age at diagnosis of 63 years (range, 57–71 y).<Reference refidx="67"/></Para><Para id="_1953">Germline <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> pathogenic variants have also been identified in men with prostate cancer who have undergone tumor testing. A prospective case series of 42 men with either localized, biochemically recurrent, or metastatic prostate cancer unselected for cancer family history or age at diagnosis undergoing tumor-only somatic testing found  that 2 of 42 men (5%) were found to have a suspected <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> germline pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="68"/></Para><Para id="_1954">Further evidence supports an association between prostate cancer and germline <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="69"/><Reference refidx="70"/><Reference refidx="71"/> A retrospective study of 163 men (&gt;18 y) with  <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> pathogenic/likely pathogenic variants from 132 known <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> families found that 19% (n = 31/163) of participants had diagnoses of prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="72"/> Of these participants, 48% (n = 31) were older than age 50 years. The median age of prostate cancer diagnosis was 56 years (range, 50–64 y).  Locally advanced prostate cancer or de novo metastatic disease was found in 19% (n = 4) of men. Additionally, 40% (n = 8/20) of participants had high-grade  prostate cancer (Gleason score, &gt;8) at the time of diagnosis. This study also combined the existing cohort with a prostate cancer cohort that had documented germline <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> pathogenic/likely pathogenic variants.  This combined cohort had a prostate cancer relative risk of 9.1 (95% CI, 6.2–14; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001). </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1955"><Title><GeneName>NBN</GeneName></Title><Para id="_1956"><GeneName>NBN</GeneName>, which is also known as <GeneName>NBS1</GeneName>, has been investigated due to a potential association with prostate cancer risk, with the literature constantly evolving. Studies mostly from Polish populations reported that the <GeneName>NBN</GeneName> 657del5 variant is associated with  prostate cancer risk (OR, 2.5; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001), mortality (HR, 1.6; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001),  and familial prostate cancer (OR, 4.6; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="73"/><Reference refidx="74"/> One of these studies (from Poland) reported adverse survival when individuals with the <GeneName>NBN</GeneName> 657del5 variant  also carried the <GeneName>NBN</GeneName> E185Q GG genotype (HR,1.9; <Emphasis>P </Emphasis>= .0004).<Reference refidx="73"/> In the metastatic setting, a retrospective case series of 692 men with metastatic prostate cancer (unselected for cancer family history or age at diagnosis) found that 0.3% (2 of 692 men) had an <GeneName>NBN</GeneName> pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="56"/> Some clinical genetic testing laboratories do not include <GeneName>NBN</GeneName> on their prostate cancer panels, since <GeneName>NBN</GeneName>'s association with prostate cancer is based on preliminary evidence. Further data will be required to fully understand the role and generalizability of <GeneName>NBN</GeneName> and its association with prostate cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1957"><Title>Multigene testing studies in prostate cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_1958"><Title>Prevalence of pathogenic variants with prostate cancer risk on multigene panel testing</Title><Para id="_1959">The following section gives information about additional genes that may be on hereditary prostate cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763019" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">panel</GlossaryTermRef> tests.</Para><Para id="_1961">One retrospective case series of 692 men with metastatic prostate cancer unselected for cancer family history or age at diagnosis assessed the incidence of germline pathogenic variants in 16 DNA repair genes.  Pathogenic variants were identified in 11.8% (82 of 692), a rate higher than in men with localized prostate cancer (4.6%, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001), suggesting that genetic aberrations are more commonly observed in men with aggressive forms of disease.<Reference refidx="56"/> Two studies were published using data from a clinical testing laboratory database. The first study evaluated 1,328 men with prostate cancer and reported an overall pathogenic variant rate of 15.6%, including 10.9% in DNA repair genes.<Reference refidx="75"/> A second study involved a larger cohort of 3,607 men with prostate cancer, some of whom had been included in the prior publication.<Reference refidx="76"/> The reported pathogenic variant rate was 17.2%. Overall, pathogenic variant rates by gene were consistently reported between the two studies and were as follows: <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, 4.74%; <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName>, 2.88%; <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, 2.03%; and <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, 1.25%.<Reference refidx="76"/> The most commonly aberrant gene in this cohort was <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>. The first publication reported associations between family history of breast cancer and high Gleason score (≥8).<Reference refidx="75"/> The second publication focused on the percentage of men with pathogenic variants who met National Comprehensive Cancer Network national guidelines for genetic testing and found that 229 individuals (37%) with pathogenic variants in this cohort did not meet guidelines for genetic testing.<Reference refidx="76"/>  A systematic evidence review examined the median prevalence of pathogenic germline variants in the DNA damage-response pathway, including <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>ATR</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName>, <GeneName>FANCA</GeneName>, <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MRE11A</GeneName>, <GeneName>NBN</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>RAD51C</GeneName>. The overall prevalence was 18.6% (range, 17.2%–19%; n = 1,712) for general prostate cancer, 11.6% (range, 11.4%–11.8%; n = 1,261) for metastatic prostate cancer, 8.3% (range, 7.5%–9.1%; n = 738) for metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer, and 29.3% (range, 7.3%–92.67%; n = 327) for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="77"/></Para><Para id="_1962">A case-control study in a Japanese population of 7,636 men with prostate cancer and 12,366 men without prostate cancer evaluated pathogenic variants in eight genes (<GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName>, <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>NBN</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName>, and <GeneName>BRIP1</GeneName>) for an association with prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="37"/>  The study found strong associations for <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> (OR, 5.65; 95% CI, 3.55–9.32), <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> (OR, 4.73; 95% CI, 2.84–8.19), and <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> (OR, 2.86; 95% CI, 1.63–5.15). The study supports a population-specific assessment of the genetic contribution to prostate cancer risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1963"><Title>Germline pathogenic variants associated with metastatic prostate cancer</Title><Para id="_1977">The metastatic prostate cancer setting is also contributing insights into the germline pathogenic variant spectrum of prostate cancer. Clinical sequencing of 150 metastatic tumors from men with castrate-resistant prostate cancer identified alterations in genes involved in DNA repair in 23% of men.<Reference refidx="78"/> Interestingly, 8% of these variants were pathogenic and present in the germline. Another study focused on tumor-normal sequencing of advanced and metastatic cancers identified germline pathogenic variants in 19.6% of men (71 of 362) with prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="79"/> Germline pathogenic variants were found in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName>, <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRIP1</GeneName>, <GeneName>NBN</GeneName>, as well as other genes. These and other studies are summarized in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1978" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 6</SummaryRef>. The contribution of germline variants identified from large sequencing efforts to inherited prostate cancer predisposition requires molecular confirmation of genes not classically linked to prostate cancer risk. </Para><Table id="_1978"><Title>Table 6.  Summary of Tumor Sequencing Studies With Germline Findings</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="13.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="17.23%" RowSep="1"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColSep="0" ColWidth="1.73%" RowSep="0"/><ColSpec ColName="col04" ColNum="4" ColSep="1" ColWidth="25.81%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColSep="1" ColWidth="5.15%" RowSep="1"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="36.39%"/><THead><Row RowSep="1"><entry>Study</entry><entry>Cohort</entry><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">Germline Results for Prostate Cancer</entry><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col4">Comments</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1">mCRPC = metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer. </entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Potential overlap of cohorts.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row RowSep="1"><entry MoreRows="3" RowSep="1">Robinson et al. (2015)<Superscript>a</Superscript> <Reference refidx="78"/></entry><entry MoreRows="3" RowSep="1"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740459" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Whole-exome</GlossaryTermRef> and transcriptome sequencing
of bone or soft tissue tumor biopsies
from a cohort of 150 men with mCRPC
</entry><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">8% had germline pathogenic variants:   </entry><entry ColSep="0" MoreRows="3" NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col4" RowSep="1"/></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 9/150 (6.0%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>: 2/150 (1.3%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>: 1/150 (0.7%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry MoreRows="3">Pritchard et al. (2016)<Superscript>a</Superscript> <Reference refidx="56"/></entry><entry MoreRows="3">692 men with metastatic prostate cancer, unselected for family history; 
analysis focused on 20 genes involved in maintaining DNA integrity and associated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> cancer–predisposing syndromes
</entry><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">82/692 (11.8%) had germline pathogenic variants:   </entry><entry ColSep="1" MoreRows="3" NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col4" RowSep="1">Frequency of germline
pathogenic variants in DNA repair genes among men with metastatic prostate cancer significantly
exceeded the prevalence of 4.6% among 499 men with localized prostate
cancer in the Cancer Genome Atlas (<Emphasis>P </Emphasis> &lt; .001)
</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 37/692 (5.3%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>: 11/692 (1.6%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>: 6/692 (0.9%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry MoreRows="5">Schrader et al. (2016) <Reference refidx="80"/></entry><entry MoreRows="5" RowSep="1">1,566 patients undergoing tumor profiling (341 genes) with matched normal DNA at a single institution; 97 cases of prostate cancer included</entry><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">10/97 (10.3%) had germline pathogenic variants:
    </entry><entry MoreRows="5" NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col4"/></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 6/97 (6.2%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>: 1/97 (1.0%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>: 1/97 (1.0%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>MUTYH</GeneName>: 1/97 (1.0%)</entry></Row><Row RowSep="1"><entry ColSep="1" NameEnd="col04" NameSt="col3" RowSep="1">— <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName>: 1/97 (1.0%)</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1782"><Title>Common Risk Variants and Polygenic Risk Scores for Prostate Cancer</Title><Para id="_2012">The most prevalent prostate cancer risk variants in the human genome were discovered in genome-wide association studies (GWAS). GWAS evaluate the millions of common single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the human population (typically &gt;5% prevalence) and ask if each variant is enriched in individuals with a given disease. With great statistical rigor, GWAS have revealed over 250 prostate cancer risk variants. Each single SNP confers a very modest prostate cancer risk. However, when compounded, these SNPs comprise a substantial portion of inherited prostate cancer risk.  Research continues to translate these discoveries into clinical practice,  with use in tools like polygenic risk scores (PRS).</Para><SummarySection id="_1783"><Title>GWAS and SNPs</Title><ItemizedList id="_881" Style="bullet"><ListItem>GWAS can identify inherited genetic variants that influence a specific phenotype, such as risk of a particular disease.</ListItem><ListItem>For complex diseases, such as prostate cancer, risk of developing the disease is the product of multiple genetic and environmental factors; each individual factor contributes relatively little to overall risk.</ListItem><ListItem>To date, GWAS have discovered more than 250 common genetic variants associated with prostate cancer risk.</ListItem><ListItem>Individuals can be genotyped for all known prostate cancer risk markers relatively easily; but, to date, studies have not demonstrated that this information substantially refines risk estimates from commonly used variables, such as family history.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>The clinical relevance of variants identified from GWAS remains unclear.</Strong></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1809">Although the statistical evidence for an association between genetic variation at these loci and prostate cancer risk is overwhelming, the clinical relevance of the variants and the mechanism(s) by which they lead to increased risk are unclear and will require further characterization. Additionally, these loci are associated with very modest risk estimates and explain only a fraction of overall inherited risk. However, when combined into a PRS, these confirmed genetic risk variants may prove to be useful for prostate cancer risk stratification and to identify men for targeted screening and early detection. Further work will include genome-wide analysis of rarer alleles catalogued via sequencing efforts. Disease-associated alleles with frequencies of less than 1% in the population may prove to be more highly penetrant and clinically useful. In addition, further work is needed to describe the landscape of genetic risk in non-European populations. Finally, until the individual and collective influences of genetic risk alleles are evaluated prospectively, their clinical utility will remain difficult to fully assess.</Para><Para id="_1810">Beginning in 2006, multiple genome-wide studies seeking associations with prostate cancer risk converged on the same chromosomal locus, 8q24.<Reference refidx="81"/><Reference refidx="82"/><Reference refidx="83"/><Reference refidx="84"/><Reference refidx="85"/><Reference refidx="86"/><Reference refidx="87"/><Reference refidx="88"/><Reference refidx="89"/><Reference refidx="90"/><Reference refidx="91"/><Reference refidx="92"/> <Reference refidx="93"/><Reference refidx="94"/> Since that time, more than ten genetic polymorphisms, all independently associated with disease, reside within five distinct 8q24 risk regions. The population-attributable risk of prostate cancer from the 8q24 risk alleles reported to date is 9.4%.<Reference refidx="95"/></Para><Para id="_1811">Since prostate cancer risk loci have been discovered at 8q24, more than 250 variants have been identified at other chromosomal risk loci. These chromosomal risk loci were detected by multistage GWAS, which were comprised of thousands of cases and controls and were validated in independent cohorts.<Reference refidx="96"/> The most convincing associations reported to date for men of European ancestry are annotated in the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/">National Human Genome Research Institute GWAS catalog</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1812">Most prostate cancer GWAS data generated to date have been derived from populations of European descent. This shortcoming is profound, considering that linkage disequilibrium structure, SNV frequencies, and incidence of disease differ across ancestral groups. To provide meaningful genetic data to all patients, well-designed, adequately powered GWAS must be aimed at specific ethnic groups.<Reference refidx="97"/> Most work in this regard has focused on African American, Chinese, and Japanese men. The most convincing associations reported to date for men of non-European ancestry are annotated in the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/">National Human Genome Research Institute GWAS catalog</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1813">The African American population is of particular interest because American men with West African ancestry are at higher risk of prostate cancer than any other group.  A handful of studies have sought to determine whether GWAS findings in men of European ancestry are applicable to men of African ancestry.<Reference refidx="64"/><Reference refidx="98"/><Reference refidx="99"/> The majority of risk alleles (approximately 83%) are shared across African American and European American populations.  Three independent associations were subsequently replicated. All three variants were within or near long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) previously associated with prostate cancer, and two of the variants were unique to men of African ancestry.<Reference refidx="100"/>  </Para><Para id="_1814">Statistically well-powered GWAS have also been launched to examine inherited cancer risk in Japanese and Chinese populations.  Investigators discovered that these populations share many risk regions observed in African American men.<Reference refidx="101"/><Reference refidx="102"/><Reference refidx="103"/><Reference refidx="104"/> Additionally, risk regions that are unique to these ancestral groups were identified (for more information, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gwas/">National Human Genome Research Institute GWAS catalog</ExternalRef>). Ongoing work in larger cohorts will validate and expand upon these findings.</Para><SummarySection id="_1815"><Title>Polygenic risk scores for prostate cancer</Title><Para id="_1816">Current GWAS findings account for an estimated 58% of heritable prostate cancer risk. Another 6% of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> prostate cancer risk is attributed to rare genetic variants.<Reference refidx="105"/> Efforts have been made to translate these discoveries into clinically useful metrics for risk stratification and early detection. PRS were devised to measure prostate cancer risk based on the burden of genetic risk variants that an individual inherits. Associations between PRS and disease risk clearly exist. However, it remains unclear whether screening PRS can appreciably influence long-term outcomes.</Para><Para id="_2038">In a 2023 study, PRS were created for a multi-ethnic cohort of over 150,000 prostate cancer cases and over 750,000 controls.<Reference refidx="106"/> A PRS was based on 451 prostate cancer risk variants validated via GWAS. The study accounted for genetic dose (i.e., homozygosity vs. heterozygosity). When focusing on men in the top quintile of PRS scores and comparing them to men in the middle of the distribution, men of European ancestry had an OR of  greater than 2-fold  for developing prostate cancer when compared with men who had average PRS scores. In men of African ancestry, those who belonged to the upper 16% of the PRS had a greater than 2-fold increased risk to develop prostate cancer before age 66 years when compared with those who had average PRS scores. Men in the upper quintile of the PRS represented over 50% of prostate cancer cases, including clinically aggressive cases. In contrast, those in the lowest quintile of the PRS represented fewer than 5% of prostate cancer cases.  These data suggest that PRS could inform prostate cancer screening.<Reference refidx="107"/><Reference refidx="108"/> Studies that were conducted prior to this 2023 study analyzed multi-ethnic cohorts and began validating models.<Reference refidx="109"/><Reference refidx="110"/><Reference refidx="111"/><Reference refidx="112"/><Reference refidx="113"/><Reference refidx="114"/><Reference refidx="115"/><Reference refidx="116"/><Reference refidx="117"/><Reference refidx="118"/><Reference refidx="119"/><Reference refidx="120"/> Further research is needed to determine whether a PRS devised using prostate cancer  risk SNPs can help identify clinically aggressive disease.<Reference refidx="121"/></Para><Para id="_1822">As GWAS elucidate these networks, it is hoped that new therapies and chemopreventive strategies will follow.<Reference refidx="122"/><Reference refidx="123"/><Reference refidx="124"/><Reference refidx="125"/><Reference refidx="126"/><Reference refidx="127"/><Reference refidx="128"/><Reference refidx="129"/><Reference refidx="130"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1784"><Title>Germline SNPs associated with prostate cancer aggressiveness</Title><Para id="_1823">Prostate cancer is biologically and clinically heterogeneous. Many tumors are indolent and are successfully managed with observation alone. Other tumors are quite aggressive and prove deadly. Several variables are used to determine prostate cancer aggressiveness at the time of diagnosis, such as Gleason score and PSA, but these are imperfect. Additional markers are needed because sound treatment decisions depend on accurate prognostic information. Germline genetic variants are attractive markers because they are present, easily detectable, and static throughout life. </Para><Para id="_1824">Findings regarding inherited risk of aggressive disease are considered preliminary. Further work is needed to validate findings and assess these associations prospectively.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26746459">Mucci LA, Hjelmborg JB, Harris JR, et al.: Familial Risk and Heritability of Cancer Among Twins in Nordic Countries. JAMA 315 (1): 68-76, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="12237281" MedlineID="22222645">Thompson D, Easton DF; Breast Cancer Linkage Consortium: Cancer Incidence in BRCA1 mutation carriers. J Natl Cancer Inst 94 (18): 1358-65, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="34963702">Nyberg T, Tischkowitz M, Antoniou AC: BRCA1 and BRCA2 pathogenic variants and prostate cancer risk: systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Cancer 126 (7): 1067-1081, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25224030">Mersch J, Jackson MA, Park M, et al.: Cancers associated with BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations other than breast and ovarian. Cancer 121 (2): 269-75, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10398279" MedlineID="99327008">Nastiuk KL, Mansukhani M, Terry MB, et al.: Common mutations in BRCA1 and BRCA2 do not contribute to early prostate cancer in Jewish men. Prostate 40 (3): 172-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="10945492" MedlineID="20399589">Vazina A, Baniel J, Yaacobi Y, et al.: The rate of the founder Jewish mutations in BRCA1 and BRCA2 in prostate cancer patients in Israel. Br J Cancer 83 (4): 463-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9743298" MedlineID="98414230">Lehrer S, Fodor F, Stock RG, et al.: Absence of 185delAG mutation of the BRCA1 gene and 6174delT mutation of the BRCA2 gene in Ashkenazi Jewish men with prostate cancer. Br J Cancer 78 (6): 771-3, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="7550349" MedlineID="96024657">Struewing JP, Abeliovich D, Peretz T, et al.: The carrier frequency of the BRCA1 185delAG mutation is approximately 1 percent in Ashkenazi Jewish individuals. Nat Genet 11 (2): 198-200, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="8841192" MedlineID="96438857">Oddoux C, Struewing JP, Clayton CM, et al.: The carrier frequency of the BRCA2 6174delT mutation among Ashkenazi Jewish individuals is approximately 1%. Nat Genet 14 (2): 188-90, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="8841191" MedlineID="96438856">Roa BB, Boyd AA, Volcik K, et al.: Ashkenazi Jewish population frequencies for common mutations in BRCA1 and BRCA2. Nat Genet 14 (2): 185-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="9145676" MedlineID="97274028">Struewing JP, Hartge P, Wacholder S, et al.: The risk of cancer associated with specific mutations of BRCA1 and BRCA2 among Ashkenazi Jews. N Engl J Med 336 (20): 1401-8, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="31495749">Nyberg T, Frost D, Barrowdale D, et al.: Prostate Cancer Risks for Male BRCA1 and BRCA2 Mutation Carriers: A Prospective Cohort Study. Eur Urol 77 (1): 24-35, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="31723001">Patel VL, Busch EL, Friebel TM, et al.: Association of Genomic Domains in BRCA1 and BRCA2 with Prostate Cancer Risk and Aggressiveness. Cancer Res 80 (3): 624-638, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="14">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic. Version 2.2024. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_bop.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="28067867">Taylor RA, Fraser M, Livingstone J, et al.: Germline BRCA2 mutations drive prostate cancers with distinct evolutionary trajectories. Nat Commun 8: 13671, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="30900310">Oh M, Alkhushaym N, Fallatah S, et al.: The association of BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations with prostate cancer risk, frequency, and mortality: A meta-analysis. Prostate 79 (8): 880-895, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="14601029">Lange EM, Gillanders EM, Davis CC, et al.: Genome-wide scan for prostate cancer susceptibility genes using families from the University of Michigan prostate cancer genetics project finds evidence for linkage on chromosome 17 near BRCA1. Prostate 57 (4): 326-34, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="17120048">Lange EM, Robbins CM, Gillanders EM, et al.: Fine-mapping the putative chromosome 17q21-22 prostate cancer susceptibility gene to a 10 cM region based on linkage analysis. Hum Genet 121 (1): 49-55, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="22236224">Ewing CM, Ray AM, Lange EM, et al.: Germline mutations in HOXB13 and prostate-cancer risk. N Engl J Med 366 (2): 141-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="23036981">Schroeck FR, Zuhlke KA, Siddiqui J, et al.: Testing for the recurrent HOXB13 G84E germline mutation in men with clinical indications for prostate biopsy. J Urol 189 (3): 849-53, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="21">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Prostate Cancer Early Detection. Version 2.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/prostate_detection.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed November 30, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="23064873">Xu J, Lange EM, Lu L, et al.: HOXB13 is a susceptibility gene for prostate cancer: results from the International Consortium for Prostate Cancer Genetics (ICPCG). Hum Genet 132 (1): 5-14, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="23393222">Chen Z, Greenwood C, Isaacs WB, et al.: The G84E mutation of HOXB13 is associated with increased risk for prostate cancer: results from the REDUCE trial. Carcinogenesis 34 (6): 1260-4, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="23518396">Shang Z, Zhu S, Zhang H, et al.: Germline homeobox B13 (HOXB13) G84E mutation and prostate cancer risk in European descendants: a meta-analysis of 24,213 cases and 73, 631 controls. Eur Urol 64 (1): 173-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="24310616">Handorf E, Crumpler N, Gross L, et al.: Prevalence of the HOXB13 G84E mutation among unaffected men with a family history of prostate cancer. J Genet Couns 23 (3): 371-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="23292082">Laitinen VH, Wahlfors T, Saaristo L, et al.: HOXB13 G84E mutation in Finland: population-based analysis of prostate, breast, and colorectal cancer risk. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 22 (3): 452-60, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="23396964">Witte JS, Mefford J, Plummer SJ, et al.: HOXB13 mutation and prostate cancer: studies of siblings and aggressive disease. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 22 (4): 675-80, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="26108461">Beebe-Dimmer JL, Hathcock M, Yee C, et al.: The HOXB13 G84E Mutation Is Associated with an Increased Risk for Prostate Cancer and Other Malignancies. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 24 (9): 1366-72, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="23104005">Gudmundsson J, Sulem P, Gudbjartsson DF, et al.: A study based on whole-genome sequencing yields a rare variant at 8q24 associated with prostate cancer. Nat Genet 44 (12): 1326-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="24026887">Huang H, Cai B: G84E mutation in HOXB13 is firmly associated with prostate cancer risk: a meta-analysis. Tumour Biol 35 (2): 1177-82, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="26517352">Cai Q, Wang X, Li X, et al.: Germline HOXB13 p.Gly84Glu mutation and cancer susceptibility: a pooled analysis of 25 epidemiological studies with 145,257 participates. Oncotarget 6 (39): 42312-21, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="23129385">Stott-Miller M, Karyadi DM, Smith T, et al.: HOXB13 mutations in a population-based, case-control study of prostate cancer. Prostate 73 (6): 634-41, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="23475555">Alanee S, Shah S, Vijai J, et al.: Prevalence of HOXB13 mutation in a population of Ashkenazi Jewish men treated for prostate cancer. Fam Cancer 12 (4): 597-600, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="25595936">Kote-Jarai Z, Mikropoulos C, Leongamornlert DA, et al.: Prevalence of the HOXB13 G84E germline mutation in British men and correlation with prostate cancer risk, tumour characteristics and clinical outcomes. Ann Oncol 26 (4): 756-61, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="30181389">Sipeky C, Gao P, Zhang Q, et al.: Synergistic Interaction of HOXB13 and CIP2A Predisposes to Aggressive Prostate Cancer. Clin Cancer Res 24 (24): 6265-6276, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="22718278">Lin X, Qu L, Chen Z, et al.: A novel germline mutation in HOXB13 is associated with prostate cancer risk in Chinese men. Prostate 73 (2): 169-75, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="31214711">Momozawa Y, Iwasaki Y, Hirata M, et al.: Germline Pathogenic Variants in 7636 Japanese Patients With Prostate Cancer and 12 366 Controls. J Natl Cancer Inst 112 (4): 369-376, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="32040869">Marlin R, Créoff M, Merle S, et al.: Mutation HOXB13 c.853delT in Martinican prostate cancer patients. Prostate 80 (6): 463-470, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="34799695">Na R, Wei J, Sample CJ, et al.: The HOXB13 variant X285K is associated with clinical significance and early age at diagnosis in African American prostate cancer patients. Br J Cancer 126 (5): 791-796, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="35031163">Darst BF, Hughley R, Pfennig A, et al.: A Rare Germline HOXB13 Variant Contributes to Risk of Prostate Cancer in Men of African Ancestry. Eur Urol 81 (5): 458-462, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="22841674">Karlsson R, Aly M, Clements M, et al.: A population-based assessment of germline HOXB13 G84E mutation and prostate cancer risk. Eur Urol 65 (1): 169-76, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="23457453">MacInnis RJ, Severi G, Baglietto L, et al.: Population-based estimate of prostate cancer risk for carriers of the HOXB13 missense mutation G84E. PLoS One 8 (2): e54727, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="30527799">Nyberg T, Govindasami K, Leslie G, et al.: Homeobox B13 G84E Mutation and Prostate Cancer Risk. Eur Urol 75 (5): 834-845, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="12910497">Soravia C, van der Klift H, Bründler MA, et al.: Prostate cancer is part of the hereditary non-polyposis colorectal cancer (HNPCC) tumor spectrum. Am J Med Genet 121A (2): 159-62, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="24434690">Haraldsdottir S, Hampel H, Wei L, et al.: Prostate cancer incidence in males with Lynch syndrome. Genet Med 16 (7): 553-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="19723918">Grindedal EM, Møller P, Eeles R, et al.: Germ-line mutations in mismatch repair genes associated with prostate cancer. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 18 (9): 2460-7, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="20056646">Langeberg WJ, Kwon EM, Koopmeiners JS, et al.: Population-based study of the association of variants in mismatch repair genes with prostate cancer risk and outcomes. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 19 (1): 258-64, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="20872076">Bauer CM, Ray AM, Halstead-Nussloch BA, et al.: Hereditary prostate cancer as a feature of Lynch syndrome. Fam Cancer 10 (1): 37-42, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="27013479">Dominguez-Valentin M, Joost P, Therkildsen C, et al.: Frequent mismatch-repair defects link prostate cancer to Lynch syndrome. BMC Urol 16: 15, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="23530095">Raymond VM, Mukherjee B, Wang F, et al.: Elevated risk of prostate cancer among men with Lynch syndrome. J Clin Oncol 31 (14): 1713-8, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="24425144">Ryan S, Jenkins MA, Win AK: Risk of prostate cancer in Lynch syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 23 (3): 437-49, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="25117503">Rosty C, Walsh MD, Lindor NM, et al.: High prevalence of mismatch repair deficiency in prostate cancers diagnosed in mismatch repair gene mutation carriers from the colon cancer family registry. Fam Cancer 13 (4): 573-82, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="31337882">Dominguez-Valentin M, Sampson JR, Seppälä TT, et al.: Cancer risks by gene, age, and gender in 6350 carriers of pathogenic mismatch repair variants: findings from the Prospective Lynch Syndrome Database. Genet Med 22 (1): 15-25, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="28790115">Guedes LB, Antonarakis ES, Schweizer MT, et al.: MSH2 Loss in Primary Prostate Cancer. Clin Cancer Res 23 (22): 6863-6874, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="19177550">Kovacs ME, Papp J, Szentirmay Z, et al.: Deletions removing the last exon of TACSTD1 constitute a distinct class of mutations predisposing to Lynch syndrome. Hum Mutat 30 (2): 197-203, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="27433846">Pritchard CC, Mateo J, Walsh MF, et al.: Inherited DNA-Repair Gene Mutations in Men with Metastatic Prostate Cancer. N Engl J Med 375 (5): 443-53, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="7792600" MedlineID="95312868">Savitsky K, Bar-Shira A, Gilad S, et al.: A single ataxia telangiectasia gene with a product similar to PI-3 kinase. Science 268 (5218): 1749-53, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="18565893">Dombernowsky SL, Weischer M, Allin KH, et al.: Risk of cancer by ATM missense mutations in the general population. J Clin Oncol 26 (18): 3057-62, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="15280931">Angèle S, Falconer A, Edwards SM, et al.: ATM polymorphisms as risk factors for prostate cancer development. Br J Cancer 91 (4): 783-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="17502119">Meyer A, Wilhelm B, Dörk T, et al.: ATM missense variant P1054R predisposes to prostate cancer. Radiother Oncol 83 (3): 283-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="29892016">Schumacher FR, Al Olama AA, Berndt SI, et al.: Association analyses of more than 140,000 men identify 63 new prostate cancer susceptibility loci. Nat Genet 50 (7): 928-936, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="33436325">Karlsson Q, Brook MN, Dadaev T, et al.: Rare Germline Variants in ATM Predispose to Prostate Cancer: A PRACTICAL Consortium Study. Eur Urol Oncol 4 (4): 570-579, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="26629066">Wang Y, Dai B, Ye D: CHEK2 mutation and risk of prostate cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Clin Exp Med 8 (9): 15708-15, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="29117387">Conti DV, Wang K, Sheng X, et al.: Two Novel Susceptibility Loci for Prostate Cancer in Men of African Ancestry. J Natl Cancer Inst 109 (8): , 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="27496084">Mai PL, Best AF, Peters JA, et al.: Risks of first and subsequent cancers among TP53 mutation carriers in the National Cancer Institute Li-Fraumeni syndrome cohort. Cancer 122 (23): 3673-3681, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="20522432">Ruijs MW, Verhoef S, Rookus MA, et al.: TP53 germline mutation testing in 180 families suspected of Li-Fraumeni syndrome: mutation detection rate and relative frequency of cancers in different familial phenotypes. J Med Genet 47 (6): 421-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="26014290">Bougeard G, Renaux-Petel M, Flaman JM, et al.: Revisiting Li-Fraumeni Syndrome From TP53 Mutation Carriers. J Clin Oncol 33 (21): 2345-52, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="27324988">Cheng HH, Klemfuss N, Montgomery B, et al.: A Pilot Study of Clinical Targeted Next Generation Sequencing for Prostate Cancer: Consequences for Treatment and Genetic Counseling. Prostate 76 (14): 1303-11, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="21946351">Stacey SN, Sulem P, Jonasdottir A, et al.: A germline variant in the TP53 polyadenylation signal confers cancer susceptibility. Nat Genet 43 (11): 1098-103, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="21565625">Mittal RD, George GP, Mishra J, et al.: Role of functional polymorphisms of P53 and P73 genes with the risk of prostate cancer in a case-control study from Northern India. Arch Med Res 42 (2): 122-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="20875869">Xu B, Xu Z, Cheng G, et al.: Association between polymorphisms of TP53 and MDM2 and prostate cancer risk in southern Chinese. Cancer Genet Cytogenet 202 (2): 76-81, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="34863587">Maxwell KN, Cheng HH, Powers J, et al.: Inherited TP53 Variants and Risk of Prostate Cancer. Eur Urol 81 (3): 243-250, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="30590007">Rusak B, Kluźniak W, Wokołorczykv D, et al.: Inherited NBN Mutations and Prostate Cancer Risk and Survival. Cancer Res Treat 51 (3): 1180-1187, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="32875559">Wokołorczyk D, Kluźniak W, Huzarski T, et al.: Mutations in ATM, NBN and BRCA2 predispose to aggressive prostate cancer in Poland. Int J Cancer 147 (10): 2793-2800, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="75" PMID="30450585">Giri VN, Hegarty SE, Hyatt C, et al.: Germline genetic testing for inherited prostate cancer in practice: Implications for genetic testing, precision therapy, and cascade testing. Prostate 79 (4): 333-339, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="30730552">Nicolosi P, Ledet E, Yang S, et al.: Prevalence of Germline Variants in Prostate Cancer and Implications for Current Genetic Testing Guidelines. JAMA Oncol 5 (4): 523-528, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="31322208">Lang SH, Swift SL, White H, et al.: A systematic review of the prevalence of DNA damage response gene mutations in prostate cancer. Int J Oncol 55 (3): 597-616, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="26000489">Robinson D, Van Allen EM, Wu YM, et al.: Integrative clinical genomics of advanced prostate cancer. Cell 161 (5): 1215-28, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="79" PMID="28873162">Mandelker D, Zhang L, Kemel Y, et al.: Mutation Detection in Patients With Advanced Cancer by Universal Sequencing of Cancer-Related Genes in Tumor and Normal DNA vs Guideline-Based Germline Testing. JAMA 318 (9): 825-835, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="80" PMID="26556299">Schrader KA, Cheng DT, Joseph V, et al.: Germline Variants in Targeted Tumor Sequencing Using Matched Normal DNA. JAMA Oncol 2 (1): 104-11, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="81" PMID="16682969">Amundadottir LT, Sulem P, Gudmundsson J, et al.: A common variant associated with prostate cancer in European and African populations. Nat Genet 38 (6): 652-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="82" PMID="17409400">Schumacher FR, Feigelson HS, Cox DG, et al.: A common 8q24 variant in prostate and breast cancer from a large nested case-control study. Cancer Res 67 (7): 2951-6, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="83" PMID="17416775">Suuriniemi M, Agalliu I, Schaid DJ, et al.: Confirmation of a positive association between prostate cancer risk and a locus at chromosome 8q24. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 16 (4): 809-14, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="84" PMID="17409399">Wang L, McDonnell SK, Slusser JP, et al.: Two common chromosome 8q24 variants are associated with increased risk for prostate cancer. Cancer Res 67 (7): 2944-50, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="85" PMID="17401363">Yeager M, Orr N, Hayes RB, et al.: Genome-wide association study of prostate cancer identifies a second risk locus at 8q24. Nat Genet 39 (5): 645-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="86" PMID="17925536">Zheng SL, Sun J, Cheng Y, et al.: Association between two unlinked loci at 8q24 and prostate cancer risk among European Americans. J Natl Cancer Inst 99 (20): 1525-33, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="87" PMID="17925532">Savage SA, Greene MH: The evidence for prostate cancer risk loci at 8q24 grows stronger. J Natl Cancer Inst 99 (20): 1499-501, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="88" PMID="18483343">Salinas CA, Kwon E, Carlson CS, et al.: Multiple independent genetic variants in the 8q24 region are associated with prostate cancer risk. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 17 (5): 1203-13, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="89" PMID="19866473">Zheng SL, Hsing AW, Sun J, et al.: Association of 17 prostate cancer susceptibility loci with prostate cancer risk in Chinese men. Prostate 70 (4): 425-32, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="90" PMID="20700145">Zeegers MP, Khan HS, Schouten LJ, et al.: Genetic marker polymorphisms on chromosome 8q24 and prostate cancer in the Dutch population: DG8S737 may not be the causative variant. Eur J Hum Genet 19 (1): 118-20, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="91" PMID="17401366">Gudmundsson J, Sulem P, Manolescu A, et al.: Genome-wide association study identifies a second prostate cancer susceptibility variant at 8q24. Nat Genet 39 (5): 631-7, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="92" PMID="17401364">Haiman CA, Patterson N, Freedman ML, et al.: Multiple regions within 8q24 independently affect risk for prostate cancer. Nat Genet 39 (5): 638-44, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="93" PMID="19767755">Yeager M, Chatterjee N, Ciampa J, et al.: Identification of a new prostate cancer susceptibility locus on chromosome 8q24. Nat Genet 41 (10): 1055-7, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="94" PMID="19767752">Al Olama AA, Kote-Jarai Z, Giles GG, et al.: Multiple loci on 8q24 associated with prostate cancer susceptibility. Nat Genet 41 (10): 1058-60, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="95" PMID="30397198">Matejcic M, Saunders EJ, Dadaev T, et al.: Germline variation at 8q24 and prostate cancer risk in men of European ancestry. Nat Commun 9 (1): 4616, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="96" PMID="33398198">Conti DV, Darst BF, Moss LC, et al.: Trans-ancestry genome-wide association meta-analysis of prostate cancer identifies new susceptibility loci and informs genetic risk prediction. Nat Genet 53 (1): 65-75, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="97" PMID="24185611">Cook MB, Wang Z, Yeboah ED, et al.: A genome-wide association study of prostate cancer in West African men. Hum Genet 133 (5): 509-21, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="98" PMID="21637779">Haiman CA, Chen GK, Blot WJ, et al.: Characterizing genetic risk at known prostate cancer susceptibility loci in African Americans. PLoS Genet 7 (5): e1001387, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="99" PMID="25044450">Han Y, Signorello LB, Strom SS, et al.: Generalizability of established prostate cancer risk variants in men of African ancestry. Int J Cancer 136 (5): 1210-7, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="100" PMID="26823525">Han Y, Rand KA, Hazelett DJ, et al.: Prostate Cancer Susceptibility in Men of African Ancestry at 8q24. J Natl Cancer Inst 108 (7): , 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="101" PMID="20676098">Takata R, Akamatsu S, Kubo M, et al.: Genome-wide association study identifies five new susceptibility loci for prostate cancer in the Japanese population. Nat Genet 42 (9): 751-4, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="102" PMID="22366784">Akamatsu S, Takata R, Haiman CA, et al.: Common variants at 11q12, 10q26 and 3p11.2 are associated with prostate cancer susceptibility in Japanese. Nat Genet 44 (4): 426-9, S1, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="103" PMID="23023329">Xu J, Mo Z, Ye D, et al.: Genome-wide association study in Chinese men identifies two new prostate cancer risk loci at 9q31.2 and 19q13.4. Nat Genet 44 (11): 1231-5, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="104" PMID="31562322">Takata R, Takahashi A, Fujita M, et al.: 12 new susceptibility loci for prostate cancer identified by genome-wide association study in Japanese population. Nat Commun 10 (1): 4422, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="105" PMID="29348298">Benafif S, Kote-Jarai Z, Eeles RA, et al.: A Review of Prostate Cancer Genome-Wide Association Studies (GWAS). Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 27 (8): 845-857, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="106" PMID="37945903">Wang A, Shen J, Rodriguez AA, et al.: Characterizing prostate cancer risk through multi-ancestry genome-wide discovery of 187 novel risk variants. Nat Genet 55 (12): 2065-2074, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="107" PMID="36126957">Chou A, Darst BF, Wilkens LR, et al.: Association of Prostate-Specific Antigen Levels with Prostate Cancer Risk in a Multiethnic Population: Stability Over Time and Comparison with Polygenic Risk Score. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 31 (12): 2199-2207, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="108" PMID="37264206">Kachuri L, Hoffmann TJ, Jiang Y, et al.: Genetically adjusted PSA levels for prostate cancer screening. Nat Med 29 (6): 1412-1423, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="109" PMID="36493335">Nyberg T, Brook MN, Ficorella L, et al.: CanRisk-Prostate: A Comprehensive, Externally Validated Risk Model for the Prediction of Future Prostate Cancer. J Clin Oncol 41 (5): 1092-1104, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="110" PMID="37062910">Dite GS, Spaeth E, Murphy NM, et al.: Development and validation of a simple prostate cancer risk prediction model based on age, family history, and polygenic risk. Prostate 83 (10): 962-969, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="111" PMID="33258481">Black MH, Li S, LaDuca H, et al.: Validation of a prostate cancer polygenic risk score. Prostate 80 (15): 1314-1321, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="112" PMID="36360276">Yoon BW, Shin HT, Seo JH: Risk Allele Frequency Analysis and Risk Prediction of Single-Nucleotide Polymorphisms for Prostate Cancer. Genes (Basel) 13 (11): , 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="113" PMID="37178708">Huntley C, Torr B, Sud A, et al.: Utility of polygenic risk scores in UK cancer screening: a modelling analysis. Lancet Oncol 24 (6): 658-668, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="114" PMID="34127801">Karunamuni RA, Huynh-Le MP, Fan CC, et al.: Performance of African-ancestry-specific polygenic hazard score varies according to local ancestry in 8q24. Prostate Cancer Prostatic Dis 25 (2): 229-237, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="115" PMID="36872133">Chen F, Madduri RK, Rodriguez AA, et al.: Evidence of Novel Susceptibility Variants for Prostate Cancer and a Multiancestry Polygenic Risk Score Associated with Aggressive Disease in Men of African Ancestry. Eur Urol 84 (1): 13-21, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="116" PMID="34965922">Zhang W, Nicholson T, Zhang K: Deciphering the Polygenic Basis of Racial Disparities in Prostate Cancer By an Integrative Analysis of Genomic and Transcriptomic Data. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 15 (3): 161-171, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="117" PMID="35996327">Ruan X, Huang D, Huang J, et al.: Application of European-specific polygenic risk scores for predicting prostate cancer risk in different ancestry populations. Prostate 83 (1): 30-38, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="118" PMID="37311464">Darst BF, Shen J, Madduri RK, et al.: Evaluating approaches for constructing polygenic risk scores for prostate cancer in men of African and European ancestry. Am J Hum Genet 110 (7): 1200-1206, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="119" PMID="36243664">Siltari A, Lönnerbro R, Pang K, et al.: How Well do Polygenic Risk Scores Identify Men at High Risk for Prostate Cancer? Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Clin Genitourin Cancer 21 (2): 316.e1-316.e11, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="120" PMID="35801699">Chen F, Darst BF, Madduri RK, et al.: Validation of a multi-ancestry polygenic risk score and age-specific risks of prostate cancer: A meta-analysis within diverse populations. Elife 11: , 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="121" PMID="37415201">Ruan X, Huang D, Huang J, et al.: Genetic risk assessment of lethal prostate cancer using polygenic risk score and hereditary cancer susceptibility genes. J Transl Med 21 (1): 446, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="122" PMID="21614091">Freedman ML, Monteiro AN, Gayther SA, et al.: Principles for the post-GWAS functional characterization of cancer risk loci. Nat Genet 43 (6): 513-8, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="123" PMID="19549893">Pomerantz MM, Beckwith CA, Regan MM, et al.: Evaluation of the 8q24 prostate cancer risk locus and MYC expression. Cancer Res 69 (13): 5568-74, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="124" PMID="19680443">Jia L, Landan G, Pomerantz M, et al.: Functional enhancers at the gene-poor 8q24 cancer-linked locus. PLoS Genet 5 (8): e1000597, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="125" PMID="20453196">Ahmadiyeh N, Pomerantz MM, Grisanzio C, et al.: 8q24 prostate, breast, and colon cancer risk loci show tissue-specific long-range interaction with MYC. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 107 (21): 9742-6, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="126" PMID="20133699">Sotelo J, Esposito D, Duhagon MA, et al.: Long-range enhancers on 8q24 regulate c-Myc. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 107 (7): 3001-5, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="127" PMID="21814516">Meyer KB, Maia AT, O'Reilly M, et al.: A functional variant at a prostate cancer predisposition locus at 8q24 is associated with PVT1 expression. PLoS Genet 7 (7): e1002165, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="128" PMID="26398868">Spisák S, Lawrenson K, Fu Y, et al.: CAUSEL: an epigenome- and genome-editing pipeline for establishing function of noncoding GWAS variants. Nat Med 21 (11): 1357-63, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="129" PMID="24497837">Hazelett DJ, Rhie SK, Gaddis M, et al.: Comprehensive functional annotation of 77 prostate cancer risk loci. PLoS Genet 10 (1): e1004102, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="130" PMID="24564736">Jiang J, Cui W, Vongsangnak W, et al.: Post genome-wide association studies functional characterization of prostate cancer risk loci. BMC Genomics 14 (Suppl 8): S9, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1874"><Title>Prostate Cancer Genetics: Screening, Surveillance, and Treatment</Title><Para id="_2000">This section addresses the impact of genetics on prostate cancer screening, surveillance, and treatment. For more information about prostate cancer screening, surveillance, and treatment, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062755" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-screening-pdq">Prostate Cancer Screening</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062910" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-treatment-pdq">Prostate Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_1875"><Title>Prostate Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_1979"><Title>Background</Title><Para id="_1980">Decisions about risk-reducing interventions for patients with an inherited predisposition to prostate cancer, as with any disease, are best guided by randomized controlled clinical trials and knowledge of the underlying natural history of the process. However, existing studies of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> for prostate cancer in high-risk men (men with a positive family history of prostate cancer and African American men) are predominantly based on retrospective case series or retrospective cohort analyses. Because awareness of a positive family history can lead to more frequent work-ups for cancer and result in apparently earlier prostate cancer detection, assessments of disease progression rates and survival after diagnosis are subject to selection, lead time, and length biases. This section focuses on screening and risk reduction of prostate cancer among men predisposed to the disease; data relevant to screening in high-risk men are primarily extracted from studies performed in the general population.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1981"><Title>Screening</Title><Para id="_1982">Information is limited about the efficacy of commonly available screening tests such as the digital rectal exam (DRE) and serum prostate-specific antigen (PSA) in men <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460153" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetically predisposed</GlossaryTermRef> to developing prostate cancer. Furthermore, comparing the results of studies that have examined the efficacy of screening for prostate cancer is difficult because studies vary with regard to the cutoff values chosen for an elevated PSA test. For a given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322883" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sensitivity</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322884" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">specificity</GlossaryTermRef> of a screening test, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460206" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">positive predictive value</GlossaryTermRef> (PPV) increases as the underlying prevalence of disease rises. Therefore, it is theoretically possible that the PPV and diagnostic yield will be higher for the DRE and for PSA in men with a genetic predisposition than in average-risk populations.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_1983">Most retrospective analyses of prostate cancer screening cohorts have reported PPV for PSA, with or without DRE, among high-risk men in the range of 23% to 75%.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> Screening strategies (frequency of PSA measurements or inclusion of DRE) and PSA cutoff for biopsy varied among these studies, which may have influenced this range of PPV.  Cancer detection rates among high-risk men have been reported to be in the range of 4.75% to 22%.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  Most cancers detected were of intermediate Gleason score (5–7), with Gleason scores of 8 or higher being detected in some high-risk men. Overall, there is limited information about the net benefits and harms of screening men at higher risk of prostate cancer. In addition, there is little evidence to support specific screening approaches in prostate cancer families at high risk. Risks and benefits of routine screening in the general population are discussed in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062755" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-screening-pdq">Prostate Cancer Screening</SummaryRef>.  On the basis of the available data, most professional societies and organizations recommend that high-risk men engage in shared decision-making with their health care providers and develop individualized plans for prostate cancer screening based on their risk factors.  A summary of prostate cancer screening recommendations for high-risk men by professional organizations is shown in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1984" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 7</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1985" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 8</SummaryRef>.</Para><Table id="_1984"> <Title>Table 7. Available Recommendations for Prostate Cancer Screening in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> Carriers<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="28.42%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="2" ColWidth="34.31%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="3" ColWidth="37.26%"/><THead><Row><entry/><entry>Age to Begin PSA Screening</entry><entry>Screening Interval</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">PSA = prostate-specific antigen.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561402" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> other than <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> (including <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> and Lynch syndrome <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef>), it is reasonable to consider beginning shared decision-making about PSA screening at age 40 years and to consider screening at annual intervals, rather than every other year.<Reference refidx="7"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Strong> <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Carriers</GlossaryTermRef> </Strong></entry><entry>Consider screening <Reference refidx="8"/>  or shared-decision making about screening <Reference refidx="7"/> at age 40 years or 10 years before the youngest  prostate cancer diagnosis in the family <Reference refidx="8"/>  </entry><entry>Consider annual screening rather than screening every other year <Reference refidx="7"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong><GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> Carriers</Strong> </entry><entry>Recommend screening at age 40 years <Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> or 10 years before the youngest prostate cancer diagnosis in the family <Reference refidx="8"/></entry><entry>Consider annual screening rather than screening every other year <Reference refidx="7"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong><GeneName>HOXB13</GeneName> Carriers</Strong></entry><entry>Consider shared-decision making about screening at age 40 years <Reference refidx="7"/></entry><entry>Consider annual screening rather than screening every other year <Reference refidx="7"/>  </entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_1985"><Title>Table 8.  Summary of Prostate Cancer Screening Recommendations for Men Based on Family History, Race, and Ethnicity</Title><TGroup Cols="6"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="19.48%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="18.94%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="12.27%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="10.76%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColWidth="18.19%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColWidth="20.34%"/><THead><Row><entry>Screening Recommendation Source</entry><entry>Population</entry><entry>Test</entry><entry>Age Screening Initiated</entry><entry>Frequency</entry><entry>Comments</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col0">DRE = digital rectal exam; FDR = first-degree relative; NCCN = National Comprehensive Cancer Network; PSA = prostate-specific antigen; SDR = <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000485395" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">second-degree relative</GlossaryTermRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>DRE is recommended in addition to PSA test for men with hypogonadism.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>b</Superscript>A suspicious family history includes, but is not limited to, an FDR or SDR with metastatic prostate cancer, ovarian cancer, male breast cancer, female breast cancer at age ≤45 y, colorectal or endometrial cancer at age ≤50 y, or pancreatic cancer; this may also include two or more FDRs or SDRs with breast, prostate (excluding clinically localized Grade Group 1 disease), colorectal, or endometrial cancer at any age.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>United States Preventive Services Task Force (2018)  <Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry>Men aged 55–69 y </entry><entry>PSA</entry><entry>N/A</entry><entry>N/A</entry><entry>In determining whether PSA-based screening is appropriate in individual cases, patients and clinicians should consider the  benefits and harms of PSA screening based on family history, race and ethnicity, comorbid medical conditions, patient values about the benefits and harms of screening and treatment-specific outcomes, and other health needs

</entry></Row><Row><entry>American Urological Association (2023) <Reference refidx="10"/></entry><entry>African American men, men with germline pathogenic variants in hereditary prostate cancer genes, and men with strong  family histories of prostate cancer</entry><entry>PSA</entry><entry>40 to 45 y</entry><entry>Screening is individualized based on the patient's personal preferences and an informed discussion regarding the uncertainty of benefit and associated harms</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">American Cancer Society (2023) <Reference refidx="11"/></entry><entry>African American men</entry><entry>PSA with or without DRE<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>≥45 y </entry><entry MoreRows="2">   Screen every 2 y if PSA is &lt;2.5 ng/mL;  screen annually if PSA level is ≥2.5 ng/mL; if PSA levels are between 2.5–4.0 ng/mL, an individualized risk assessment can be performed, which incorporates other  prostate cancer risk factors (particularly for high-grade cancer, which may be used for a referral recommendation)</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Counseling consists of a review of the benefits and limitations of testing so that a clinician-assisted, informed decision about testing can be made. It is recommended that prostate cancer screening be accompanied by an informed decision-making process</entry></Row><Row><entry>Men with an FDR who was diagnosed with prostate cancer at &lt;65 y </entry><entry>PSA with or without DRE<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>≥45 y</entry></Row><Row><entry>Men with multiple FDRs who were diagnosed with prostate cancer at &lt;65 y</entry><entry>PSA with or without DRE<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>≥40 y</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">NCCN Prostate Cancer Early Detection (Version 2.2023) <Reference refidx="7"/></entry><entry>African American men </entry><entry>Baseline PSA</entry><entry>40 y </entry><entry>Consider screening at annual intervals rather than every other year</entry><entry>The panel states that it
is
reasonable
for
African American
men
to
consider beginning shared decision-making about
PSA
screening
with
their
providers
at age 40 y</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Men with a suspicious family history<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry MoreRows="1">Baseline PSA</entry><entry MoreRows="1">40 y</entry><entry>Screen every 2–4 y if PSA level &lt;1 ng/mL, DRE normal; if the family history is concerning, NCCN recommends shared decision-making to determine the frequency of PSA screening</entry><entry MoreRows="1"> Referral
to
a
cancer genetics
professional is recommended for those with a known or suspected pathogenic variant in a cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460209" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">susceptibility gene</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="7"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Screen every 1–2 y if PSA level ≤3 ng/mL, DRE normal (if done)</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1986"><LOERef href="CDR0000526280" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: 5</LOERef></Para><SummarySection id="_1987"><Title>Screening in carriers of <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> pathogenic variants</Title><Para id="_1988"><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00261456">IMPACT</ProtocolRef> (Identification of Men with a genetic predisposition to ProstAte Cancer) is  an international study focused on prostate cancer screening in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef> of <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>  pathogenic variants versus <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556483" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">noncarriers</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="12"/>
  The study recruited 2,481 men (791 <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> carriers, 531 <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> noncarriers; 731 <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers, 428 <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> noncarriers). A total of 199 men (8%) presented with PSA levels higher than 3.0 ng/mL, which was the study PSA cutoff for recommending a biopsy.  The overall cancer detection rate was 36.4% (59 prostate cancers diagnosed among 162 biopsies).   Prostate cancer by <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> pathogenic variant status was as follows: <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> carriers (n = 18), <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> noncarriers (n = 10); <GeneName>BRCA2 </GeneName>carriers (n = 24), <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> noncarriers (n = 7). Using published stage and grade criteria for risk classification,<Reference refidx="13"/> intermediate- or high-risk tumors were diagnosed in 11 of 18 <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> carriers (61%), 8 of 10 <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> noncarriers (80%), 17 of 24 <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers (71%), and 3 of 7 <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> noncarriers (43%).   The PPV of PSA with a biopsy threshold of 3.0 ng/mL was 48% in carriers of <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants, 33.3% in <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> noncarriers, 37.5% in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> carriers, and 23.3% in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> noncarriers.   Ninety-five percent of the men were White; therefore, the results cannot be generalized to all ethnic groups.</Para><Para id="_1989">Interim results from the IMPACT study (now comprising 2,932 participants including 919 <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> carriers and 902 <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers) demonstrated a cancer incidence rate (per 1,000 person-years) that was higher in <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers compared with noncarriers (19 vs. 12; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03).  There was no statistical difference in the cancer incidence rates between <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> carriers and noncarriers. Cancer in <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers, but not in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> carriers, was diagnosed at an earlier age and was more likely to be clinically significant.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_1265"><LOERef href="CDR0000531825" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence (screening in carriers of BRCA pathogenic variants): 3</LOERef></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1878"><Title>Impact of Germline Genetics on Management and Treatment of Metastatic Prostate Cancer </Title><Para id="_1879">	Targeted therapies on the basis of genetic results are increasingly driving options and strategies for treatment in oncology. These therapeutic approaches include candidacy for targeted therapy (such as poly [ADP-ribose] polymerase [PARP] inhibitors or immune checkpoint inhibitors), use of platinum-based chemotherapy, and sequencing of androgen-signaling therapy versus chemotherapy. Multiple genetically informed  clinical trials are under way for men with prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="15"/>  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1880" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Table 9</SummaryRef> summarizes some of the published precision oncology and precision management studies. </Para><Table id="_1880"><Title>Table 9.  Summary of Precision Oncology or Precision Management Studies Involving Germline Pathogenic Variant Status</Title><TGroup Cols="6"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="11.24%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="12.09%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="11.65%"/><ColSpec ColName="col04" ColNum="4" ColWidth="1.97%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="28.54%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="6" ColWidth="34.48%"/><THead><Row><entry>Study</entry><entry>Cohort</entry><entry>Germline Results</entry><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Intervention</entry><entry>Outcomes and Comments</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">ADT = androgen deprivation therapy; AR = androgen receptor; CI = confidence interval; CSS = cause-specific survival; DDR = DNA damage repair; FDA = U.S. Food and Drug Administration; HR = hazard ratio; HRR = homologous recombination repair; mCRPC = metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer; mPC = metastatic prostate cancer; ORR = objective response rate; OS = overall survival; PARP = poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase; PC = prostate cancer; PFS = progression-free survival; PSA = prostate-specific antigen; RR = relative risk.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>This study reported both germline and somatic genetic test results.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Retrospective</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Annala et al. (2017) <Reference refidx="16"/> </entry><entry MoreRows="4">319 men with mCRPC; performed germline sequencing of 22 DNA repair genes; all participants previously received ADT and their PCs progressed</entry><entry>24/319 (7.5%) had DDR germline pathogenic variants:           </entry><entry MoreRows="2" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients <Strong>with</Strong> mCRPC and a germline pathogenic variant received the following as a
first-line AR-targeted therapy: docetaxel/cabazitaxel (41%),
enzalutamide (23%), or 
abiraterone (36%)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Patients with DNA repair defects had decreased responses to ADT: </entry></Row><Row><entry> — <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 16/319 (5.0%) </entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>: 1/319 (0.3%)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">— Time from ADT initiation to mCRPC: Germline positive, 11.8 mo (n = 22) vs. germline negative, 19.0 mo (n = 113) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .031) </entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>: 1/319 (0.3%) </entry><entry MoreRows="1" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients with mCRPC but <Strong>without</Strong> a germline pathogenic variant received the following as a 
first-line AR-targeted therapy: 
docetaxel/cabazitaxel (33%),
enzalutamide (18%),
abiraterone (39%), or
other (10%) 
</entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>: 2/319 (0.6%) </entry><entry>— PFS on first-line AR-targeted therapy: Germline positive, 3.3 mo vs. germline negative, 6.2 mo (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Pomerantz et al. (2017) <Reference refidx="17"/></entry><entry MoreRows="1">141 men with mCRPC treated with docetaxel</entry><entry MoreRows="1">8/141 (5.7%)  had <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants</entry><entry MoreRows="1" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received at least two doses of carboplatin and docetaxel</entry><entry>6/8 men with <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants (75%) had PSA levels that declined by  50%  vs. 23/133 in men without <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants (17%) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001)</entry></Row><Row><entry> A small case series (n = 3) showed a response to platinum chemotherapy with biallelic inactivation of <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, defined as either biallelic somatic <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants or a germline pathogenic variant plus a somatic <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variant <Reference refidx="18"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Mateo et al. (2018) <Reference refidx="19"/></entry><entry MoreRows="5">390 men with  mPC; retrospective review</entry><entry MoreRows="2">60/390 (15.4%) had DDR germline pathogenic variants:</entry><entry MoreRows="5" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received abiraterone, enzalutamide, and docetaxel; an exploratory subgroup analysis was done for PARP inhibitors/platinum chemotherapy
</entry><entry>Similar findings were observed for DDR pathogenic variant carriers and noncarriers for several outcome measures:</entry></Row><Row><entry>— Median OS from castration resistance (3.2 y in carriers vs 3.0 y in noncarriers; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .73)</entry></Row><Row><entry>— Median docetaxel PFS  (6.8 mo in carriers vs. 5.1 mo in noncarriers)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">— <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 37/390 (9.5%)</entry><entry>— RRs for PC (61% in carriers vs. 54% in noncarriers)</entry></Row><Row><entry>— Median PFS on first-line abiraterone/enzalutamide (8.3 mo in both carriers and noncarriers)</entry></Row><Row><entry>— RR of PC on first-line abiraterone/enzalutamide (46% in carriers vs. 56% in noncarriers)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Carter et al. (2019)  <Reference refidx="20"/></entry><entry MoreRows="2">1,211 men with PC on active surveillance</entry><entry MoreRows="2">2.1% of patients had germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName></entry><entry MoreRows="2" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients were put on active surveillance</entry><entry>289 patients had their PC tumor grades reclassified: 11/26 patients had pathogenic variants in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName>  and 278/1,185 patients did not have a pathogenic variant in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName> (noncarriers); adjusted HR, 1.96 (95% CI, 1.004–3.84; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .04) 
 </entry></Row><Row><entry>Tumor reclassification occurred in 6/11 <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>  carriers and 283/1,200 noncarriers; adjusted HR, 2.74 (95% CI, 1.26–5.96; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01)</entry></Row><Row><entry>Of the men who had their PCs reclassified, 3.8% had a <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, or  <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> pathogenic variant, and  2.1% only had a <GeneName>BRCA2 </GeneName>pathogenic variant. Of the men whose PCs were not reclassified, 1.6% had a <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, or <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> pathogenic variant, and 0.5% only had a <GeneName>BRCA2 </GeneName>pathogenic variant. The <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> value for <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName> carriers with PCs reclassified versus those without PCs reclassified was .04. The <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> value for <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers with PCs reclassified versus those without PCs reclassified was .03  </entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Marshall et al. (2019)  <Reference refidx="21"/></entry><entry MoreRows="1">46 men with mCRPC were offered olaparib; 23 men had germline pathogenic variants  (13 men were not tested)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">23 men had germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName>; 2 men had <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> pathogenic variants, 15 men had <GeneName>BRCA2 </GeneName>pathogenic variants, and 6 men had <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> pathogenic variants </entry><entry MoreRows="1" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received olaparib</entry><entry>When patients were given olaparib, PSA levels were reduced by 50% in 13/17 (76%)  men with <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants and in 0/6 (0%) men with <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> pathogenic variants (Fisher's exact test; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002)
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Patients with <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2 </GeneName>pathogenic variants had a median PFS of 12.3 mo, while patients with <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> pathogenic variants had a median PFS of 2.4 mo  (HR, 0.17; 95% CI, 0.05–0.57; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .004)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Sokolova et al. (2021) <Reference refidx="22"/></entry><entry MoreRows="2">90 men with PC; 76/90 had metastatic disease when their PC was diagnosed; participants were matched for PC stage and year of germline testing; participants had similar ages, Gleason grades, and PSA levels at diagnosis</entry><entry MoreRows="2">45 men with <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> germline  pathogenic variants; 45 men with <GeneName>BRCA2 </GeneName> germline pathogenic variants</entry><entry MoreRows="2" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received various systemic therapies</entry><entry>No changes were observed when different groups were given abiraterone, enzalutamide, or docetaxel  </entry></Row><Row><entry>When patients were given PARP inhibitors, PSA levels were reduced by 50% in 0/7 men with <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> germline  pathogenic variants  and in 12/14 men with <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> germline  pathogenic variants (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001); this response was significant</entry></Row><Row><entry>Study limitations included the following: retrospective study, no zygosity data</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Prospective</Strong> </entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Antonarakis et al. (2018) <Reference refidx="23"/></entry><entry MoreRows="1">172 men with mCRPC began treatment with abiraterone or enzalutamide</entry><entry>22/172 (12.8%) 

had DDR germline pathogenic variants:</entry><entry MoreRows="1" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received first-line hormonal therapy (abiraterone or enzalutamide)</entry><entry>In propensity score–weighted multivariable analyses, outcomes were superior in men with germline <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName> variants with respect to PSA-PFS (HR, 0.48; 95% CI, 0.25–0.92; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .027), PFS (HR, 0.52; 95% CI, 0.28–0.98; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .044), and OS (HR, 0.34; 95% CI, 0.12–0.99; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .048). 
These results were not observed for men with non-<GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName> germline variants (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &gt; .10)</entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName>: 9/172 (5.2%)</entry><entry>Study limitations included the following:  only 9  patients with <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>ATM</GeneName>  pathogenic variants</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Castro et al. (2019) <Reference refidx="24"/></entry><entry MoreRows="4">419 men with mCRPC were enrolled when they were diagnosed with  mPC</entry><entry>68/419 (16.2%) had DDR germline  pathogenic variants:
</entry><entry MoreRows="4" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received an androgen-signaling inhibitor (abiraterone or enzalutamide) as a first-line therapy and a taxane (docetaxel was given in 96.3% of patients) as a second-line therapy

<Strong>or</Strong>

patients received a taxane as a first-line therapy and an androgen-signaling inhibitor (abiraterone or enzalutamide) as a second-line therapy</entry><entry MoreRows="1">CSS between <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>/<GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers and noncarriers was not statistically significant (23.3 mo vs. 33.2 mo; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .264) 
 
  </entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName>2: 14/419 (3.3%) </entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>: 8/419 (1.9%) </entry><entry>CSS was halved in <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers (17.4 mo vs. 33.2 mo; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .027), and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were identified as an independent prognostic factor for CSS (HR, 2.11; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .033)</entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>: 4/419 (1%) </entry><entry>Significant interactions between <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> status and treatment type (androgen-signaling inhibitor vs. taxane therapy) were observed (CSS-adjusted <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .014; PFS-adjusted <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .005)</entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>: None </entry><entry>CSS (24.0 mo vs. 17.0 mo) and PFS (18.9 mo vs. 8.6 mo) were greater in <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> carriers treated with first-line abiraterone or enzalutamide when compared with first-line taxanes</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">de Bono et al. (2020) <Reference refidx="25"/></entry><entry MoreRows="2">387 men in the PROfound study who had mCRPC with disease progression while receiving a new hormonal agent (e.g., enzalutamide or abiraterone)</entry><entry>Currently, the FDA has approved olaparib for use in patients with mCRPC who have a somatic or germline pathogenic variant in an HRR gene. The PROfound study cited data from <ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26510020/">Mateo et al. 2015</ExternalRef>, which discovered that about half of the HRR gene variants in patient tumors were germline in nature. Results in this study reported on olaparib response in individuals with somatic variants. Data on germline pathogenic variants will be reported in the future</entry><entry MoreRows="2" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Randomized, open-label, phase III trial in which patients received   olaparib (300 mg twice per day) <Strong>or</Strong> the  physician’s choice of enzalutamide (160 mg once per day) or abiraterone (1,000 mg once per day) plus prednisone (5 mg twice per day)</entry><entry MoreRows="2">In cohort A, imaging-based PFS was significantly longer in
the olaparib group than in the control group (median, 7.4 mo vs. 3.6 mo;
HR for progression or death, 0.34; 95% CI, 0.25–0.47;
<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). The median OS in cohort A was 18.5 mo in the olaparib group and 15.1 mo in the control group; 81% of the patients in the control group who had disease progression
crossed over to receive olaparib</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cohort A: 245 men with &gt;1 somatic variant in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, or <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> </entry></Row><Row><entry>Cohort B: 142 men with &gt;1 somatic variant in any of the following genes: <GeneName>BRIP1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BARD1</GeneName>, <GeneName>CDK12</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK1</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName>, <GeneName>FANCL</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, <GeneName>PPP2R2A</GeneName>, <GeneName>RAD51B</GeneName>, <GeneName>RAD51C</GeneName>, <GeneName>RAD51D</GeneName>, or <GeneName>RAD54L</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Hussain  et al. (2020) <Reference refidx="26"/></entry><entry MoreRows="2">387 men with mCRPC in the PROfound study; PC progressed when taking enzalutamide, abiraterone, or both</entry><entry>Currently, the FDA has approved olaparib for use in patients with mCRPC who have a somatic or germline pathogenic variant in an HRR gene. The PROfound study cited data from <ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26510020/">Mateo et al. 2015</ExternalRef>, which discovered that about half of the HRR gene variants in patient tumors were germline in nature. Results in this study reported on olaparib response in individuals with somatic variants. Data on germline pathogenic variants will be reported in the future</entry><entry MoreRows="2" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received treatment that was randomly assigned in a 2:1 ratio for olaparib versus control therapy; control therapy consisted of the provider's choice of enzalutamide or abiraterone, plus prednisone. Crossover to olaparib was permitted when PC progressed on imaging</entry><entry>The median OS in cohort A was 19.1 mo with olaparib and 14.7 mo with control therapy. The HR for death (adjusted for crossover from control therapy) was 0.42 (95% CI, 0.19–0.91)</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cohort A: 245 men with &gt;1  somatic variant in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, or <GeneName>ATM</GeneName></entry><entry MoreRows="1">The median OS in cohort B was 14.1 mo for olaparib and 11.5 mo for control therapy. The HR for death (adjusted for crossover from control therapy) was 0.83 (95% CI, 0.11–5.98)</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cohort B: 142 men with &gt;1 somatic variant in any of the following genes: <GeneName>BRIP1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BARD1</GeneName>, <GeneName>CDK12</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK1</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName>, <GeneName>FANCL</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, <GeneName>PPP2R2A</GeneName>, <GeneName>RAD51B</GeneName>, <GeneName>RAD51C</GeneName>, <GeneName>RAD51D</GeneName>, or <GeneName>RAD54L</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Abida et al. (2020)<Superscript>a</Superscript> <Reference refidx="27"/></entry><entry MoreRows="5">115 men with mCRPC from the TRITON2 study  with a deleterious somatic or germline pathogenic variant in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>; patients had mCRPCs that progressed after treatment with one to two lines of next-generation AR-directed therapy and one taxane-based chemotherapy</entry><entry>44/115 (38%) had <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants:</entry><entry MoreRows="5" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received one or more doses of rucaparib (600 mg)</entry><entry MoreRows="2">The ORR was 43.5% in men with measurable disease and 50.8% in men without measurable disease. ORRs were similar for men with germline and somatic variants and for men with <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants</entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>: 5/115 (4%)</entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 39/115 (34%)</entry></Row><Row><entry>71/115 (62%) had <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> somatic variants:</entry><entry>63/115 men had a confirmed PSA response (54.8%), which differed by gene; however, the <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> group was small:</entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>: 8/115 (7%)</entry><entry>—<GeneName> BRCA1</GeneName>: 2/13 (15.4%)</entry></Row><Row><entry>— <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 63/115 (55%)</entry><entry>—<GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: 61/102 (59.8%)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">De Bono et al. (2021)<Superscript>a</Superscript><Reference refidx="28"/></entry><entry MoreRows="1">104 men with progressive mCRPC and pathogenic variants in DDR-HRR genes; patients received at least one dose of talazoparib </entry><entry> 25/71 (25%) patients had germline pathogenic  variants: 13 in <GeneName>BRCA2, </GeneName> 4 in <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, and 8 in other genes</entry><entry MoreRows="1" NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col04">Patients received one or more doses of talazoparib per day (received 1 mg per day or 0.75 mg per day if the patient had moderate renal impairment)</entry><entry>The ORR was observed in 7/28 (25%) men with germline pathogenic variants</entry></Row><Row><entry>Patients also had somatic variants in the following genes: 61 in <GeneName>BRCA1/2</GeneName>, 57 in <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, 4 in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, 17 in <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, 22 in other genes (<GeneName>ATR</GeneName>, <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName>, <GeneName>FANCA</GeneName>, <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MRE11A</GeneName>, <GeneName>NBN</GeneName>, and <GeneName>RAD51C</GeneName>)</entry><entry>After a median follow-up period of 16.4 mo (range, 11.1–22.1), the ORR for patients with somatic variants was 29.8% (31 of 104 patients; 95% CI, 21.2%–39.6%). Clinical benefit (defined as patients with complete response, partial response, or stable disease for ≥6 months from treatment start) varied between individuals with different pathogenic variants: <GeneName>BRCA1/2</GeneName> (56%), <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> (56%), <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> (25%), <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> (24%), other (0%)

</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="8935621" MedlineID="97089713">Sartor O: Early detection of prostate cancer in African-American men with an increased familial risk of disease. J La State Med Soc 148 (4): 179-85, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10389909" MedlineID="99316771">Matikainen MP, Schleutker J, Mörsky P, et al.: Detection of subclinical cancers by prostate-specific antigen screening in asymptomatic men from high-risk prostate cancer families. Clin Cancer Res 5 (6): 1275-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="12394689">Catalona WJ, Antenor JA, Roehl KA, et al.: Screening for prostate cancer in high risk populations. J Urol 168 (5): 1980-3; discussion 1983-4, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12131293">Valeri A, Cormier L, Moineau MP, et al.: Targeted screening for prostate cancer in high risk families: early onset is a significant risk factor for disease in first degree relatives. J Urol 168 (2): 483-7, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7585019">Narod SA, Dupont A, Cusan L, et al.: The impact of family history on early detection of prostate cancer. Nat Med 1 (2): 99-101, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="17868726">Giri VN, Beebe-Dimmer J, Buyyounouski M, et al.: Prostate cancer risk assessment program: a 10-year update of cancer detection. J Urol 178 (5): 1920-4; discussion 1924, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="7">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Prostate Cancer Early Detection. Version 2.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/prostate_detection.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed November 30, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="8">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic. Version 2.2024. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_bop.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="9">U.S. Preventative Services Task Force: Screening for prostate cancer: U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommendation statement. Rockville, Md: U.S. Preventative Services Task Force, 2018. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.uspreventiveservicestaskforce.org/uspstf/recommendation/prostate-cancer-screening#fullrecommendationstart">Available online.</ExternalRef> Last accessed May 8, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="37096582">Wei JT, Barocas D, Carlsson S, et al.: Early Detection of Prostate Cancer: AUA/SUO Guideline Part I: Prostate Cancer Screening. J Urol 210 (1): 46-53, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="11">American Cancer Society: American Cancer Society Recommendations for Prostate Cancer Early Detection. American Cancer Society, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/types/prostate-cancer/detection-diagnosis-staging/acs-recommendations.html">Available online.</ExternalRef> Last accessed May 8, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="24484606">Bancroft EK, Page EC, Castro E, et al.: Targeted prostate cancer screening in BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers: results from the initial screening round of the IMPACT study. Eur Urol 66 (3): 489-99, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="13">National Collaborating Centre for Cancer (UK): Prostate Cancer: Diagnosis and Treatment. Cardiff, UK: National Collaborating Centre for Cancer, 2008. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK49533/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed May 8, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="31537406">Page EC, Bancroft EK, Brook MN, et al.: Interim Results from the IMPACT Study: Evidence for Prostate-specific Antigen Screening in BRCA2 Mutation Carriers. Eur Urol 76 (6): 831-842, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="30761386">Carlo MI, Giri VN, Paller CJ, et al.: Evolving Intersection Between Inherited Cancer Genetics and Therapeutic Clinical Trials in Prostate Cancer: A White Paper From the Germline Genetics Working Group of the Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Consortium. JCO Precis Oncol 2018: , 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="28259476">Annala M, Struss WJ, Warner EW, et al.: Treatment Outcomes and Tumor Loss of Heterozygosity in Germline DNA Repair-deficient Prostate Cancer. Eur Urol 72 (1): 34-42, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="28608931">Pomerantz MM, Spisák S, Jia L, et al.: The association between germline BRCA2 variants and sensitivity to platinum-based chemotherapy among men with metastatic prostate cancer. Cancer 123 (18): 3532-3539, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="26724258">Cheng HH, Pritchard CC, Boyd T, et al.: Biallelic Inactivation of BRCA2 in Platinum-sensitive Metastatic Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer. Eur Urol 69 (6): 992-5, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="29429804">Mateo J, Cheng HH, Beltran H, et al.: Clinical Outcome of Prostate Cancer Patients with Germline DNA Repair Mutations: Retrospective Analysis from an International Study. Eur Urol 73 (5): 687-693, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="30309687">Carter HB, Helfand B, Mamawala M, et al.: Germline Mutations in ATM and BRCA1/2 Are Associated with Grade Reclassification in Men on Active Surveillance for Prostate Cancer. Eur Urol 75 (5): 743-749, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="30797618">Marshall CH, Sokolova AO, McNatty AL, et al.: Differential Response to Olaparib Treatment Among Men with Metastatic Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer Harboring BRCA1 or BRCA2 Versus ATM Mutations. Eur Urol 76 (4): 452-458, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="34516663">Sokolova AO, Marshall CH, Lozano R, et al.: Efficacy of systemic therapies in men with metastatic castration resistant prostate cancer harboring germline ATM versus BRCA2 mutations. Prostate 81 (16): 1382-1389, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="29439820">Antonarakis ES, Lu C, Luber B, et al.: Germline DNA-repair Gene Mutations and Outcomes in Men with Metastatic Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer Receiving First-line Abiraterone and Enzalutamide. Eur Urol 74 (2): 218-225, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="30625039">Castro E, Romero-Laorden N, Del Pozo A, et al.: PROREPAIR-B: A Prospective Cohort Study of the Impact of Germline DNA Repair Mutations on the Outcomes of Patients With Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer. J Clin Oncol 37 (6): 490-503, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="32343890">de Bono J, Mateo J, Fizazi K, et al.: Olaparib for Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer. N Engl J Med 382 (22): 2091-2102, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="32955174">Hussain M, Mateo J, Fizazi K, et al.: Survival with Olaparib in Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer. N Engl J Med 383 (24): 2345-2357, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="32795228">Abida W, Patnaik A, Campbell D, et al.: Rucaparib in Men With Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer Harboring a BRCA1 or BRCA2 Gene Alteration. J Clin Oncol 38 (32): 3763-3772, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="34388386">de Bono JS, Mehra N, Scagliotti GV, et al.: Talazoparib monotherapy in metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer with DNA repair alterations (TALAPRO-1): an open-label, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 22 (9): 1250-1264, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><Title>Psychosocial Issues in Familial Prostate Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_77"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_78">The psychological impact of a family history of prostate cancer and/or a positive genetic test for hereditary prostate cancer may influence well-being and screening/prevention behaviors. Important psychosocial issues that have been investigated include perceived risk of prostate cancer, distress, and prostate cancer screening behaviors. Most of this evidence is based on hereditary risk from family history, rather than the results of genetic testing. If known, this section  includes data from studies of men who tested positive for hereditary prostate cancer genes. The presence of a prostate cancer family history  is important, since most cases of hereditary prostate cancer  have unknown etiologies, are polygenic, or cannot  be explained by  clinical multigene panel tests.<Reference refidx="1"/> For more information about polygenic risk, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1815" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Polygenic risk scores for prostate cancer</SummaryRef> section. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_251"><Title>Prostate Cancer Risk Perception</Title><Para id="_2042">Understanding drivers of prostate cancer risk perception is important because it can influence other psychological characteristics and is widely regarded as a predictor of health behaviors. Studies  that have analyzed the influence of a family history of prostate cancer on perceived cancer risk have had mixed results.</Para><Para id="_253">Although family histories of prostate cancer can increase perceived prostate cancer risk in some men,<Reference refidx="2"/> other studies found that men with family histories of prostate cancer considered their risk to be the same as, or less than, that of the average man.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  Other factors, including being married, were associated with increased prostate cancer risk perception.<Reference refidx="5"/> Perceived risk may  be positively correlated with levels of concern about developing prostate cancer,<Reference refidx="3"/> depression,<Reference refidx="6"/> and/or the number of relatives who were diagnosed with prostate cancer in a family.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Confusion regarding the differences between benign prostatic hyperplasia and prostate cancer are confounders in prostate cancer risk perception.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_2043">An international study of men with personal and/or family histories of <GeneName>BRCA1/BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants found that risk perception was associated with intrusive thoughts, avoidance coping, prostate cancer–related anxiety, and worry about prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2044"><Title>Psychological Distress</Title><Para id="_2045"> Although up to 50% of first-degree relatives (FDRs) of prostate cancer patients expressed concern about developing prostate cancer in some studies,<Reference refidx="3"/> the level of anxiety reported by these individuals was relatively low and was related to lifetime risk, rather than short-term risk.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="6"/> This concern was higher in men who were younger than their FDRs   when their prostate cancers were diagnosed.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Unmarried FDRs may have worried more about developing prostate cancer than married men did.<Reference refidx="3"/> In a Swedish study, only 3% of participants (n = 110) said that worry about prostate cancer affected their daily lives fairly much, and 28% said that it affected their daily lives slightly.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_2046">In men who self-referred for free prostate cancer screening, general– and prostate cancer–related distress did not differ significantly between men who were  FDRs of prostate cancer patients and men who were not.<Reference refidx="2"/> In a Swedish study, male  FDRs  who reported higher levels of worry about developing prostate cancer had higher Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) scores than men with lower levels of worry. In FDRs, the average HADS score was in the 75<Superscript>th</Superscript> percentile.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_187"> A study measured anxiety and general quality-of-life in 220 men with family histories of prostate cancer who were undergoing prostate cancer screening with prostate-specific antigen (PSA) tests.<Reference refidx="8"/> In this group, 20% of participants experienced a moderate deterioration in their anxiety scores, and 20% experienced a minimal deterioration in health-related quality-of-life (HRQOL) scores. The average period between assessments was 35 days, which encompassed PSA testing and a wait for results that averaged 15.6 days. Only men with normal PSA values (4 ng/mL or less) were assessed.  Factors associated with HRQOL deterioration included being  50 to  60 years old, having more than two relatives with prostate cancer, having an anxious personality, being well-educated, and not having children living at home. The authors stressed that analysis of prostate cancer screening impact on  FDRs should not rely solely on mean changes in HRQOL scores.  Since a subset of  men who received normal results experienced screening-associated distress, interventions  may be needed to encourage men with increased hereditary risk to comply with repeated screening requests.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_95"><Title>Screening for Prostate Cancer</Title><Para id="_176">For more information about prostate cancer screening in the general population, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062755" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-screening-pdq">Prostate Cancer Screening</SummaryRef>, and for more information about screening individuals with hereditary prostate cancer syndromes, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1875" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Prostate Cancer Screening</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_2047">For most cancer types, knowing that an individual has hereditary risk leads to recommendations for approved (if not proven) screening. This complicates prostate cancer screening, because there is a lack of clear recommendations for many high-risk men and men in the general population.  This creates uncertainty about the clinical and  psychosocial factors related to prostate cancer screening.</Para><Para id="_2048">Several small studies have examined the behavioral correlates of prostate cancer screening at average and increased prostate cancer risk, based on family history.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> In general, results differed regarding whether men with a family histories of prostate cancer were  more likely to be screened than those  without  hereditary prostate cancer risk. It is unclear if the prostate cancer  screening implemented in each group was appropriate for its risk status.  Most studies had a relatively small numbers of subjects, and the prostate cancer screening criteria were not uniform across studies, making generalizations difficult. Notably, all of these studies predate the  era of hereditary cancer testing, and there is a paucity   of research about prostate cancer screening behaviors in males who have undergone  hereditary prostate cancer genetic testing.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="33486571">Ni Raghallaigh H, Eeles R: Genetic predisposition to prostate cancer: an update. Fam Cancer 21 (1): 101-114, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10189136" MedlineID="99203019">Taylor KL, DiPlacido J, Redd WH, et al.: Demographics, family histories, and psychological characteristics of prostate carcinoma screening participants. Cancer 85 (6): 1305-12, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="15042690">Beebe-Dimmer JL, Wood DP, Gruber SB, et al.: Risk perception and concern among brothers of men with prostate carcinoma. Cancer 100 (7): 1537-44, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11436545">Miller SM, Diefenbach MA, Kruus LK, et al.: Psychological and screening profiles of first-degree relatives of prostate cancer patients. J Behav Med 24 (3): 247-58, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="12914830">Montgomery GH, Erblich J, DiLorenzo T, et al.: Family and friends with disease: their impact on perceived risk. Prev Med 37 (3): 242-9, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="10741283" MedlineID="20205456">Bratt O, Damber JE, Emanuelsson M, et al.: Risk perception, screening practice and interest in genetic testing among unaffected men in families with hereditary prostate cancer. Eur J Cancer 36 (2): 235-41, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="29802810">Bancroft EK, Saya S, Page EC, et al.: Psychosocial impact of undergoing prostate cancer screening for men with BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutations. BJU Int 123 (2): 284-292, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12686816">Cormier L, Reid K, Kwan L, et al.: Screening behavior in brothers and sons of men with prostate cancer. J Urol 169 (5): 1715-9, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15159306">Vadaparampil ST, Jacobsen PB, Kash K, et al.: Factors predicting prostate specific antigen testing among first-degree relatives of prostate cancer patients. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 13 (5): 753-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="12946749">Bock CH, Peyser PA, Gruber SB, et al.: Prostate cancer early detection practices among men with a family history of disease. Urology 62 (3): 470-5, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="14872526">Jacobsen PB, Lamonde LA, Honour M, et al.: Relation of family history of prostate cancer to perceived vulnerability and screening behavior. Psychooncology 13 (2): 80-5, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="15036671">Roumier X, Azzouzi R, Valéri A, et al.: Adherence to an annual PSA screening program over 3 years for brothers and sons of men with prostate cancer. Eur Urol 45 (3): 280-5; author reply 285-6, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16411222">Weinrich SP: Prostate cancer screening in high-risk men: African American Hereditary Prostate Cancer Study Network. Cancer 106 (4): 796-803, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="16080666">Ross LE, Uhler RJ, Williams KN: Awareness and use of the prostate-specific antigen test among African-American men. J Natl Med Assoc 97 (7): 963-71, 2005.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/09/2025)</Title><Para id="_140">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above. </Para><Para id="_2086"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_2002" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Risk Factors for Prostate Cancer</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_2087">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_2004" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with new cancer cases and deaths for 2025 (cited American Cancer Society as reference 1).</Para><Para id="_2088">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_2006" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cancer cases and deaths for different racial and ethnic groups in 2025.</Para><Para id="_2089"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1841" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">Risk Assessment for Prostate Cancer</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_2090">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_1994" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cancer cases and deaths for different racial and ethnic groups in 2025 (cited American Cancer Society as reference 1).</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000299612#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of prostate cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Genetics of Prostate Cancer are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Kathleen A. Calzone, PhD, RN, AGN-BC, FAAN (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Veda N. Giri, MD (Yale University)</ListItem><ListItem>Suzanne C. O'Neill, PhD (Georgetown University)</ListItem><ListItem>Mark Pomerantz, MD (Dana-Farber Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>John M. Quillin, PhD, MPH, MS (Virginia Commonwealth University)</ListItem><ListItem>Charite Ricker, MS, CGC (University of Southern California)</ListItem><ListItem>Catharine Wang, PhD, MSc (Boston University School of Public Health)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ Genetics of Prostate Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/prostate/hp/prostate-genetics-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389227]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2003-11-20</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-09</DateLastModified></Summary>
