<Summary id="CDR0000301599" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Spirituality and religion help patients, families, and caregivers cope with cancer and spiritual distress. Learn how religious and spiritual needs are met during treatment and improve a patient’s quality of life in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality/spirituality-pdq">Spirituality in Cancer Care (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality/spirituality-hp-pdq">Spirituality in Cancer Care (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000330082">spiritual concerns</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_72">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about religious and spiritual coping in cancer care. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_73">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>spiritual concerns</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Spirituality in Cancer Care (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Spirituality in Cancer Care</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Spirituality in Cancer Care</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Spirituality</Title><SummarySection id="_66"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Supportive care issues</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_67">Religious and spiritual values are important to patients coping with cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4">Studies have shown that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000489395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">religious</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef> values are important to   Americans. Most American adults say that they believe in God and that their  religious beliefs affect how they live their lives. However, people have different ideas about life after death, belief in miracles,  and other religious beliefs. Such beliefs may be based on  sex, education, and ethnic background. </Para><Para id="_58">Many patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>  rely on spiritual or religious beliefs and practices to help them <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cope</GlossaryTermRef> with their disease.  This is called spiritual coping. Many <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">caregivers</GlossaryTermRef> also  rely on spiritual coping.   Each person may have different spiritual needs, depending on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476357" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cultural</GlossaryTermRef> and religious traditions. For some seriously ill patients, spiritual well-being may affect how much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> they feel about death. For others, it may affect what  they decide about end-of-life treatments. Some patients and their family caregivers may want doctors to talk about spiritual concerns, but may feel unsure about how to bring up the subject. </Para><Para id="_59">Some studies show that  doctors' support of spiritual well-being in very ill patients  helps improve their   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Health care providers</GlossaryTermRef>  who treat patients coping with cancer are looking at new ways to   help them with religious and spiritual concerns. Doctors may  ask patients which  spiritual issues  are important to them during treatment as well as near the end of life. When patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef> receive spiritual support from the medical team, they may be more likely to choose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hospice</GlossaryTermRef> care and less <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046053" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aggressive</GlossaryTermRef> treatment at the end of life. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2"><KeyPoint id="_3">Spirituality and religion may have different meanings.</KeyPoint><Para id="_68">
The terms spirituality and religion are often used in place of each other, but for many people they have different meanings. Religion may be defined as a specific set of beliefs and practices, usually within an organized group. Spirituality may be defined as an individual's sense of peace, purpose, and connection to others, and beliefs about the meaning of life. Spirituality may be found and expressed through an organized religion or in other ways. Patients may think of themselves as spiritual or religious or both. 

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><KeyPoint id="_9">Serious illness, such as cancer, may cause spiritual distress. </KeyPoint><Para id="_10">Serious illnesses like cancer may cause patients or family caregivers to have doubts about their beliefs or religious values and cause much  spiritual <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>.  Some studies show that patients with cancer may feel that they are being punished by God or may have a loss of faith after being <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef>. Other patients may have mild feelings of spiritual distress when coping with cancer.</Para><Para id="_70">This summary is about spirituality and religion in adults with cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Supportive care issues</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Spirituality and Quality of Life</Title><SummarySection id="_54"><KeyPoint id="_13">Spiritual and religious well-being  may help improve quality of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_14">It is not known for sure how <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spirituality</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000489395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">religion</GlossaryTermRef> are related to health. Some studies show that spiritual or religious beliefs and practices create a positive mental attitude that may help a patient feel better and improve the well-being of  family <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">caregivers</GlossaryTermRef>. Spiritual and religious well-being  may help  improve health and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> in the following ways:</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Decrease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>,  anger, and discomfort.</ListItem><ListItem>Decrease the sense of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">isolation</GlossaryTermRef> (feeling alone) and the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">suicide</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Decrease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454752" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug abuse</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef> and the risk of heart disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Help the patient adjust to the effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and its treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Increase the ability to enjoy life during cancer treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Give a feeling of personal growth as a result of living with cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Increase positive feelings, including:<ItemizedList id="_69" Style="dash"><ListItem>Hope and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000640063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">optimism</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Freedom from regret.</ListItem><ListItem>Satisfaction with life.</ListItem><ListItem>A sense of inner peace.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_60">Spiritual and religious well-being may also help a patient live longer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><KeyPoint id="_17">Spiritual distress may also affect health.</KeyPoint><Para id="_18">Spiritual <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> may make it harder for patients to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cope</GlossaryTermRef> with cancer and cancer treatment. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Health care providers</GlossaryTermRef> may encourage patients to meet with experienced spiritual or religious leaders to help deal with their spiritual issues. This may improve their health, quality of life, and ability to cope.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Supportive care issues</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Spiritual Assessment</Title><SummarySection id="_55"><KeyPoint id="_21">A spiritual assessment may help the doctor understand how religious or spiritual beliefs will affect the way a  patient copes with cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_22">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assessment</GlossaryTermRef> is a method or tool used by doctors to understand  the role that religious and spiritual beliefs have in the patient's life. This may help the doctor understand how these beliefs affect the way the patient responds to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> and decisions about cancer treatment. Some doctors or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">caregivers</GlossaryTermRef> may wait for the patient to bring up spiritual concerns. Others may use  an  interview or a questionnaire.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><KeyPoint id="_24">A spiritual assessment explores religious  beliefs and spiritual practices. </KeyPoint><Para id="_26">A spiritual assessment may include questions about  the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_27" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>Religious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476288" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">denomination</GlossaryTermRef>, if any.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Beliefs or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441255" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">philosophy</GlossaryTermRef> of life.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Important spiritual practices or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476412" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rituals</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Using spirituality or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000489395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">religion</GlossaryTermRef> as a source of strength.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Being part of  a community of support.</ListItem>
    
    <ListItem>Using prayer or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meditation</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Loss of faith.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Conflicts between spiritual or religious beliefs and cancer treatments.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Ways that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care providers</GlossaryTermRef> and caregivers may help with the patient's spiritual needs.</ListItem>
   <ListItem>Concerns about death and  afterlife.</ListItem><ListItem>Planning for the end of life.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_65">The health care team may not ask about every issue the patient feels is important. Patients should bring up other spiritual or religious issues that they think may affect their cancer care.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Supportive care issues</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Meeting the Patient's Spiritual and Religious Needs</Title><SummarySection id="_29"><KeyPoint id="_30">To help patients with  spiritual needs during cancer care, medical staff will listen to  the wishes of the patient.</KeyPoint><Para id="_31"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Spirituality</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000489395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">religion</GlossaryTermRef> are very personal issues. Patients should expect doctors and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">caregivers</GlossaryTermRef> to respect their religious and spiritual beliefs and concerns.   Patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> who rely on spirituality to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cope</GlossaryTermRef> with the disease should be able to count on the health care team to give them  support. This may include giving patients information about people or groups that can help with spiritual or religious needs. Most hospitals have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430477" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chaplains</GlossaryTermRef>, but not all <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044520" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outpatient</GlossaryTermRef> settings do. Patients who do not want to discuss spirituality during cancer care should also be able to count on the health care team to respect  their wishes.</Para><Para id="_56">Doctors and  caregivers will try to respond to their patients' concerns,  but may not take part in patients' religious practices or discuss specific religious beliefs.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><KeyPoint id="_57">The health care team will help with a patient's spiritual needs when setting goals and planning treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_34">The health care team may help with a patient's spiritual needs in the following ways:</Para><ItemizedList id="_35" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>Suggest goals and options for care that honor the patient's spiritual and/or religious views.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Support the patient's use of spiritual coping during the illness.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Encourage the patient to speak with his/her religious or spiritual leader.</ListItem>
   <ListItem>Refer the patient  to a hospital chaplain or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045917" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">support group</GlossaryTermRef> that can help with spiritual issues during illness.</ListItem><ListItem>Refer the patient  to other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef> that have been shown to increase spiritual well-being. These include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000377712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mindfulness relaxation</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000532135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">yoga</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meditation</GlossaryTermRef>, or  creative arts programs, such as writing, drawing, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000640061" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">music therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_71"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000330082">spiritual concerns</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_71_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_74"><Title>To Learn More About Spirituality in Cancer Care</Title><Para id="_75">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> 
        about spirituality in cancer care, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_76" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality">Your Faith and Spirituality</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about religious and spiritual coping in cancer care.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Spirituality in Cancer Care. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality/spirituality-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality/spirituality-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389462]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000328116"/><DateFirstPublished>2003-08-24</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-02-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
