<Summary id="CDR0000304521" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062887"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Esophageal cancer screening is not currently considered to be a routine part of cancer screening. Not all screening tests are helpful, and many have risks. Learn more about esophageal cancer risk factors and tests to detect it in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-screening-pdq">Esophageal Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/hp/esophageal-screening-pdq">Esophageal Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043615">esophageal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_87">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about esophageal cancer screening. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_88">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>esophageal cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Esophageal Cancer Screening (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Esophageal Cancer Screening</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Esophageal Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>What Is Screening?</Title><Para id="_2">Screening is  looking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> before a person has any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. This can help find
		cancer at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> tissue or cancer is found early, it may
		be easier to treat. By the time symptoms  appear, cancer may have begun
		to  spread.</Para><Para id="_3">Scientists  are trying to better understand which
		people are more likely to get certain types of cancer. They also study the things
		we do and the things around us to see if they cause  cancer. This
		information helps doctors recommend who should be screened for cancer, which
		screening tests should be used, and how often the tests should be done.</Para><Para id="_4">It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily
		think you have cancer if he or she suggests a  screening test. Screening
		tests are given when you  have no cancer symptoms.</Para><Para id="_5">If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689569" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Esophageal Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_8"><KeyPoint id="_9">Esophageal cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer)
		  cells form in the tissues of the esophagus.</KeyPoint><Para id="_10">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef> is the hollow, muscular tube that moves food and
		  liquid from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef> to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>. The wall of the esophagus is made up of several tissue layers,
		  including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucous membrane</GlossaryTermRef>, muscle, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Esophageal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>
		  starts in the inside lining of the esophagus and spreads outward through the
		  other layers as it grows.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000428446" type="image/jpeg" alt="Gastrointestinal (digestive) system anatomy; drawing shows the esophagus, liver, stomach, small intestine, and large intestine." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_83"><Caption language="en">The esophagus and stomach are part of the upper gastrointestinal (digestive) system.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_11">The two most common types of esophageal cancer are named for the
		  type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> that become cancerous:</Para><ItemizedList id="_12" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046595" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Squamous cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>: Cancer forms in the thin, flat cells lining the inside of the esophagus. This cancer is most often found
			 in the upper and middle part of the esophagus but can occur anywhere along the esophagus. This is also called epidermoid
			 carcinoma.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>: Cancer begins in
			 glandular cells.
			 Glandular cells in the lining of the esophagus produce and release fluids such
			 as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046274" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucus</GlossaryTermRef>. Adenocarcinoma usually forms in the lower part of the esophagus, near
			 the stomach.</ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_85">Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summaries  containing information related to esophageal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_86" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062888" url="/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-prevention-pdq"> Esophageal Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062960" url="/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-treatment-pdq">Esophageal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_14">Esophageal cancer is found more often in men.</KeyPoint><Para id="_15">Men are about four times more likely than women to develop esophageal cancer. There are more new  cases of esophageal adenocarcinoma each year and fewer new cases of squamous  cell carcinoma. Although the rates of squamous cell carcinoma are  declining overall, they  remain much higher  in Black men than in White men. The chance of developing esophageal cancer increases with age in all racial and ethnic groups. White men are more likely to develop esophageal cancer at higher rates than   Black men in all age groups. In women, the rates of developing this disease are higher in Black women until age 74 years, after which White women have higher rates.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">Smoking, heavy alcohol use, and Barrett esophagus can affect the risk of developing esophageal cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_18">Anything that increases the chance of getting a disease
		  is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Having a risk factor does not mean that you will get cancer; not having risk factors doesn’t mean that you will not get cancer. People who think they may be at risk should discuss this with their doctor.</Para><Para id="_82">Risk factors for squamous cell esophageal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem>using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439432" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tobacco</GlossaryTermRef>
</ListItem><ListItem>drinking a lot of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>being malnourished  (lacking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef> and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044651" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">calories</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human papillomavirus</GlossaryTermRef> (HPV) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having tylosis (a rare inherited disorder that causes thickening of the skin on the hands and feet and is associated with an increased risk of squamous cell esophageal cancer)</ListItem><ListItem>having achalasia (a rare condition that affects the ability of food and liquids to pass from the esophagus into the stomach)</ListItem><ListItem>having swallowed lye (a chemical found in some cleaning fluids)</ListItem><ListItem>drinking very hot liquids on a regular basis</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_49">Risk factors for esophageal adenocarcinoma  include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_50" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastroesophageal reflux disease</GlossaryTermRef> (GERD)</ListItem><ListItem>having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Barrett esophagus</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">history</GlossaryTermRef> of using drugs that relax the lower esophageal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sphincter</GlossaryTermRef> (the ring of muscle that opens and closes the opening between the esophagus and the stomach)</ListItem><ListItem>having excess body weight (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overweight</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Screening methods</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Esophageal Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_20"><KeyPoint id="_21">Tests are used to screen for different types of cancer when a person does not have symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_46">Scientists study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests to find those with the fewest harms and most benefits. Cancer screening trials also are meant to show whether early detection (finding cancer before it causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>)  helps a person live longer or decreases a person's chance of dying from the disease. For some types of cancer, the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef> is better if the disease is found and treated at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_54"><KeyPoint id="_55">There is no standard or routine screening test for esophageal cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_91">Although there are no standard or routine screening tests for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophageal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the following tests are being used or studied to screen for it:</Para><SummarySection id="_23"><KeyPoint id="_24">Esophagoscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_25">A procedure to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef> to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas. An esophagoscope  is inserted through the mouth or nose and down the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef> into the esophagus. An esophagoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000433289" type="image/jpeg" alt="Esophagoscopy; shows endoscope inserted through the mouth and into the esophagus. Inset shows patient on table having an esophagoscopy." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_84"><Caption language="en">Esophagoscopy.  A thin, lighted tube is inserted through the mouth and into the esophagus to look for abnormal areas.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><KeyPoint id="_60">Biopsy</KeyPoint><Para id="_61">The removal of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer. Taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045619" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy samples</GlossaryTermRef> from several different areas in the  lining of the lower part of the esophagus may detect early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Barrett esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>. This procedure may be used for patients who have  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> for Barrett esophagus. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_73"><KeyPoint id="_74">Brush cytology</KeyPoint><Para id="_75">A procedure in which cells are brushed from the lining of the esophagus and viewed under a microscope to see if they are abnormal. This may be done during an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagoscopy</GlossaryTermRef>.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><KeyPoint id="_27">Balloon cytology</KeyPoint><Para id="_28">A procedure in which cells are collected from the lining of the esophagus using a deflated balloon that is swallowed by the patient. The balloon is then inflated and pulled out of the esophagus. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046414" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Esophageal</GlossaryTermRef> cells on  the balloon are viewed under a  microscope to see if they are abnormal. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><KeyPoint id="_63">Chromoendoscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_64">A procedure in which a  dye is sprayed onto the lining of the esophagus during esophagoscopy. Increased staining of certain areas of the lining may be a sign of  early Barrett esophagus.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><KeyPoint id="_66">Fluorescence spectroscopy</KeyPoint><Para id="_67">A procedure that uses a special light to view tissue in the lining of the esophagus. The light probe is passed through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscope</GlossaryTermRef> and shines on the lining of the esophagus. The light given off by the cells lining the esophagus is then measured. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Malignant</GlossaryTermRef> tissue gives off less light than normal tissue. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_89"><KeyPoint id="_90">Screening tests for esophageal cancer are being studied in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_89_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_29"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risks of screening</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Risks of Esophageal Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_30"><KeyPoint id="_31">Screening tests have risks.</KeyPoint><Para id="_32">Decisions about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests can be difficult. Not all screening tests are helpful, and most have risks. Before having any screening test, you may
		  want to discuss  the test with your doctor.  It is important to know the risks of
		  the test and whether it has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from
		  cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><KeyPoint id="_34">The risks of esophageal cancer screening tests include:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_39"><KeyPoint id="_40">Finding esophageal cancer may not improve health or help a person live
			 longer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_41">Screening
			 may not improve your health or help  you live longer if  you have   advanced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophageal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or if it has already spread to
			 other places in  your body.</Para><Para id="_71">Some cancers  never  cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>
			 or become life-threatening, but if    found by a screening
			 test,  the cancer may be treated. It is  not known if treatment of these cancers  will help you live longer than if no treatment  were given, and treatments for cancer may have serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><KeyPoint id="_77">False-negative test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_78">Screening test results may appear to be normal even though esophageal cancer is present. A person who receives a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-negative test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical care even if there are  symptoms.

 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><KeyPoint id="_80">False-positive test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_81">Screening test results may appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> even though no cancer is present. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-positive test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and is usually followed by more tests (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>), which also have risks.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><KeyPoint id="_37">Side  effects  may be caused by  the test itself.</KeyPoint><Para id="_38">There are rare but serious side effects that may occur with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> and biopsy. These include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a small hole (puncture) in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>problems with breathing</ListItem><ListItem>heart attack</ListItem><ListItem>passage of food, water, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acid</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomit</GlossaryTermRef> into the airway</ListItem><ListItem>severe bleeding that may need to be treated in a hospital</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about esophageal cancer screening.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Esophageal Cancer Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389194]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062877"/><DateFirstPublished>2004-10-25</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-12-11</DateLastModified></Summary>
