<Summary id="CDR0000343585" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062730"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter treatment is primarily surgery. In the case that the cancer has spread or come back, chemotherapy is sometimes used.  Learn more about the treatment for these cancers in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/transitional-cell-treatment-pdq">Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/hp/transitional-cell-treatment-pdq">Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040478">transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_173">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_174">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Transitional Cell Cancer (Kidney/Ureter) Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Transitional Cell Cancer (Kidney/Ureter) Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter is a type of cancer that forms in the transitional cells of 
		  the renal pelvis  and  ureter.</KeyPoint><Para id="_665"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046630" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Transitional cells</GlossaryTermRef> are a type of cell that lines the inside of the renal pelvis, ureters, and other organs. These cells are able to stretch when the renal pelvis or bladder is full of urine and shrink when it is emptied. Transitional  cell cancer can form in the renal pelvis, the ureters, or both.</Para><Para id="_652">The renal pelvis is the area at the center of the kidney. It collects urine before it flows into the ureters, which are long tubes that connect the kidney to the bladder. There are two kidneys, one on each  side of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415915" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">backbone</GlossaryTermRef>, above the waist. The kidneys of an adult are about 5 inches long and 3 inches wide and are shaped like a kidney bean. </Para><Para id="_653">The kidneys play an important role in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000801549" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinary system</GlossaryTermRef>: </Para><ItemizedList id="_654" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The kidneys filter and clean the blood by taking out waste products and extra water as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem>The  urine collects in the middle of each kidney in the renal pelvis.</ListItem><ListItem>Urine passes from the renal pelvis through the ureter into the bladder. </ListItem><ListItem>The bladder holds the urine until it passes through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046640" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urethra</GlossaryTermRef> and leaves the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000765031" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the male urinary system (left panel) and female urinary system (right panel); two-panel drawing showing the right and left kidneys, the ureters, the bladder filled with urine, and the urethra. The inside of the left kidney shows the renal pelvis. An inset shows the renal tubules and urine. Also shown are the prostate and penis (left panel) and the uterus (right panel)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_172"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the male urinary system (left panel) and female urinary  system (right panel) showing the kidneys, ureters, bladder, and urethra. The inside of the left kidney shows the renal pelvis. An inset shows the renal tubules and urine. Also shown are the prostate and penis (left panel) and the uterus (right panel). Urine is made in the renal tubules and collects in the renal pelvis of each kidney. The urine flows from the kidneys through the ureters to the bladder. The urine is stored in the bladder until it leaves the body through the urethra.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_115"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044988" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Renal cell cancer</GlossaryTermRef> is a more common type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000276462" url="/types/kidney/patient/kidney-treatment-pdq">Renal Cell Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_5"> A personal history of bladder cancer and smoking can increase the risk of transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter. </KeyPoint><Para id="_655">Transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter is caused by certain changes to the way transitional cells in the renal pelvis and ureters function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. There are many risk factors for transitional cell cancer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef>, but many do not directly cause cancer. Instead, they increase the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> damage in cells that may lead to cancer. To learn more about how cancer develops, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_656">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Some risk factors for transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter, like smoking, can be changed. However, risk factors may also include things you cannot change, like your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal medical history</GlossaryTermRef>. Learning about risk factors for transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter can help you make changes that might lower your risk of getting it. </Para><Para id="_658">Risk       
		  factors for transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_7" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		  <ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>smoking cigarettes</ListItem><ListItem>taking a lot of  certain pain medicines, such as phenacetin</ListItem><ListItem>being exposed to certain dyes and chemicals used in making leather goods, textiles, plastics, and rubber</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_659">Having one or more of these risk factors does not mean that you will get transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter. Many people with risk factors never develop this type of cancer, while others with no known risk factors do. Talk with your doctor if you think you might be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_12">Signs and symptoms of transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter include blood in the  urine and back pain.</KeyPoint><Para id="_13">  In the early stages, there may be no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter. Symptoms may appear as the tumor grows and may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_14" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>blood in the urine</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>a pain in the back that doesn't go away</ListItem><ListItem>extreme tiredness</ListItem><ListItem> 
weight loss with no known reason 
</ListItem><ListItem>painful or frequent urination</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_660"> These  symptoms may be caused by transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter or by other conditions. It’s important to check with your doctor if you have any of these symptoms to find out the cause and begin treatment if needed. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_16">Tests that examine the abdomen and kidneys are used to diagnose transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter.</KeyPoint><Para id="_203">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Urinalysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a test to check the color of urine and its contents, such as sugar, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef>, blood, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bacteria</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ureteroscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure to look inside the ureter and renal pelvis to check for abnormal areas.  A ureteroscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. The ureteroscope is inserted  through the urethra into the bladder, ureter, and renal pelvis.  A tool may be inserted through the ureteroscope to take tissue samples to be checked under a microscope for signs of disease.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000649520" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of a female and male ureteroscopy showing the lower pelvis of a female, including the right and left kidneys, renal pelvis, ureter, uterus, bladder, and urethra, and the lower pelvis of a male, including the ureter, bladder, prostate, urethra, and penis. In both the female and male figures, a ureteroscope (a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing) is shown passing through the urethra into the bladder and ureter. In the female figure, the ureteroscope is also shown passing into the renal pelvis. There is also an inset that shows a person lying on an examination table with their knees bent and legs apart, covered by a drape, and a doctor looking at an image of the inside of the ureter and/or renal pelvis on a computer monitor." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_165"><Caption language="en">A ureteroscopy is a procedure that uses a ureteroscope (a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing) to look inside the ureter and renal pelvis to check for abnormal areas. The ureteroscope is inserted through the urethra into the bladder, ureter, and renal pelvis. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem> <Strong>Urine cytology</Strong> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> in which a sample of urine is checked under a microscope for abnormal cells. Cancer in the kidney, bladder, or ureter may shed cancer cells into the urine.</ListItem> <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT
			 scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body from different angles. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>. An ultrasound of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> may be done to help diagnose cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter.</ListItem>
			 <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong> uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer. This may be done during a ureteroscopy or surgery.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_643"><KeyPoint id="_24">After transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the renal pelvis and ureter or to other parts of the body. </KeyPoint><Para id="_25">The process used to find out if the cancer has spread within the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef> or to other
parts of the body is called staging. The information gathered from the
staging process determines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease. The results  of the diagnostic and staging tests will also help you and your doctor plan treatment. </Para><Para id="_176">The following tests and
procedures may also be used in the staging process:</Para><ItemizedList id="_26" Style="bullet"> 
		   <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an x-ray of the organs and bones inside the chest.  An x-ray is a type of energy beam that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the body.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong> uses a small amount of radioactive sugar (also called glucose) that is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. Then a scanner is used to make detailed, computerized pictures of areas inside the body where the glucose is taken up. Because cancer cells often take up more glucose than normal cells, the pictures can be used to find cancer cells in the body. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is used to check if there are rapidly dividing cells, such as cancer cells, in the bone.  A very small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> material is injected into a vein and travels through the bloodstream.  The radioactive material collects in the bones with cancer and is detected by a scanner.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		   
		  </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_644"><KeyPoint id="_641">Some people decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_645">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_646">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI’s Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_21">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> depends on the stage and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grade</GlossaryTermRef> of the tumor.</Para><Para id="_118">The treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_119" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the stage and grade of the tumor</ListItem><ListItem> where the tumor is</ListItem><ListItem>whether the patient's  other kidney is healthy</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has recurred (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_133">Most transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter can be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cured</GlossaryTermRef> if found early.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Stages of Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter</Title><SummarySection id="_23"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_640">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter to plan the best treatment.   </Para><Para id="_663">There are several staging systems for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. Transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter staging usually uses the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. You may see your cancer described by this staging system in your pathology report. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to your cancer. When talking to you about your cancer, your doctor may describe it as one of these stages. </Para><Para id="_642">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_28">The following stages are used for transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and/or ureter:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_29"><KeyPoint id="_30">Stage 0 (Noninvasive Papillary Carcinoma and Carcinoma in Situ)  </KeyPoint><Para id="_139">In stage 0,  abnormal cells are found in tissue lining the inside of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef>. These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. Stage 0 is divided into stages 0a and 0is, depending on the type of  tumor:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_177" Style="bullet" Compact="No"><ListItem>Stage 0a is also called noninvasive papillary carcinoma, which may look like long, thin growths that grow out from the tissue lining the inside of the renal pelvis or ureter.</ListItem><ListItem>Stage 0is is also called carcinoma in situ, which is a flat tumor on the tissue lining the inside of the renal pelvis or ureter.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><KeyPoint id="_33">Stage I (also called stage 1)</KeyPoint><Para id="_178">In stage I, cancer has formed and has spread from the tissue lining the inside of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef> to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef> layer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><KeyPoint id="_36">Stage II (also called stage 2)</KeyPoint><Para id="_179">In stage III, cancer has spread to the muscle layer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><KeyPoint id="_39">Stage III (also called stage 3)</KeyPoint><Para id="_40">In stage III, cancer has spread:</Para><ItemizedList id="_180" Style="bullet" Compact="No"><ListItem>from the muscle layer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> to fat around the renal pelvis or to tissue in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>; or</ListItem><ListItem>from the muscle layer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef> to fat around the ureter.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_41"><KeyPoint id="_42">Stage IV (also called stage 4)</KeyPoint><Para id="_43">In stage IV, cancer has spread to at least one of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_181" Style="bullet" Compact="No"><ListItem>a nearby organ. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, or bone.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_207">Stage IV transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter is also called metastatic cancer. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the lymphatic system or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if transitional cell cancer renal pelvis and ureter spreads to the liver, the cancer cells in the liver are actually transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter. The disease is called metastatic transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter, not liver cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_121"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_122">Transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter is also described as localized, regional, metastatic, or recurrent: </KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_123"><KeyPoint id="_124">Localized</KeyPoint><Para id="_125">The cancer is  found only in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_126"><KeyPoint id="_127">Regional</KeyPoint><Para id="_128">The cancer has spread to  tissues around the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef> and to nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_129"><KeyPoint id="_130">Metastatic</KeyPoint><Para id="_131">The cancer has spread to other parts of the body. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_200"><KeyPoint id="_201">Recurrent</KeyPoint><Para id="_661">Recurrent cancer is cancer that has recurred
		(come back) after it has been treated. If transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter comes back, it may come
		back in the renal pelvis, ureter, or in other
		parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, or bone. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned. The type of treatment for recurrent transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_662">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_46"><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter</Title><SummarySection id="_47"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_48">There are different types of treatment for  patients with transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter.</KeyPoint><Para id="_647">Different types of treatments are available for people with transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the stage of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment. </Para><Para id="_648">Talking with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You’ll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you’ll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Treatment</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_51"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_52">The following type of treatment is used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_53"><KeyPoint id="_54">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_134">One of the following surgical procedures may be used to treat transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter:</Para><ItemizedList id="_135" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Nephroureterectomy is surgery to remove the entire <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>, the ureter, and the bladder cuff (tissue that connects the ureter to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef>). Most people with transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter  undergo nephroureterectomy.</ListItem><ListItem>Segmental resection of the ureter is a surgical procedure to remove the part of the ureter that contains cancer and some of the healthy tissue around it. The ends of the ureter are then reattached. 
This treatment  is used when the cancer is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">superficial</GlossaryTermRef> and in the lower third of  the ureter only, near the bladder.   </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_664"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_76">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_664_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_664_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_664_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_152">This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in clinical trials. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. </Para><SummarySection id="_77"><KeyPoint id="_78">Fulguration</KeyPoint><Para id="_79"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fulguration</GlossaryTermRef> is a surgical procedure that destroys tissue using an electric current. A tool with a small wire loop on the end is used to remove the cancer or to burn away the tumor with electricity.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_80"><KeyPoint id="_81">Segmental resection of the renal pelvis</KeyPoint><Para id="_82">This is a surgical procedure to remove <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">localized</GlossaryTermRef> cancer from the renal pelvis without removing the entire kidney. Segmental resection may be done to  save <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000725230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney function</GlossaryTermRef> when the other kidney is damaged or has already been removed. 
</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_75"><SummarySection id="_136"><KeyPoint id="_137">Laser surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_138">A laser beam (narrow beam of intense light) is used as a knife to remove the cancer. A laser beam can also be used to kill the cancer cells. This procedure may also be called laser fulguration.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_141"><KeyPoint id="_142">Regional chemotherapy and regional immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_649">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping the cells from dividing. To learn more about chemotherapy, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_636">Immunotherapy helps a person’s immune system fight cancer. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_650">Regional treatment for transitional cell cancer of renal pelvis and ureter is a method of placing the chemotherapy or immunotherapy drug directly into the renal pelvis or the ureter to mainly affect cancer cells in those areas. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_183"><KeyPoint id="_184">Treatment for transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_183_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_157"><KeyPoint id="_158">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_157_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_157_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_186"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040615">localized transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Localized Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter </Title><Para id="_187">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">localized</GlossaryTermRef> transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_188" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354466" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nephroureterectomy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">segmental resection</GlossaryTermRef> of ureter)</ListItem>
     
     <ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fulguration</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laser surgery</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of segmental resection of the renal pelvis</ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or regional immunotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_204">To learn more about these treatments, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343585#_51" url="/types/kidney/patient/transitional-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_186_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_189"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040658">regional transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Regional Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter</Title><Para id="_190">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045865" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional</GlossaryTermRef> transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter is usually done in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_205">To learn more about clinical trials, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343585#_51" url="/types/kidney/patient/transitional-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_189_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_191"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040251">metastatic transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040844">recurrent transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter</Title><Para id="_192">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter is usually done in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>, which may include  chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_206">To learn more about clinical trials, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343585#_51" url="/types/kidney/patient/transitional-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_191_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><Title>To Learn More About Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter</Title><Para id="_147">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_149" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney">Kidney Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco">Tobacco</ExternalRef> (includes help with quitting)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_146_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_146_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of transitional cell cancer of the renal pelvis and ureter.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/transitional-cell-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/transitional-cell-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389285]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062937"/><DateFirstPublished>2004-02-20</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
