<Summary id="CDR0000347008"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Milk thistle is available in the United States as a dietary supplement. Human clinical trials have investigated milk thistle in hepatitis or cirrhosis, although small studies have been reported in some cancers. Get detailed information on studies of milk thistle in cancer in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/milk-thistle-pdq">Milk Thistle (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/milk-thistle-pdq">Milk Thistle (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000284684">silymarin</TermRef></MainTopics><SecondaryTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000042022">complementary or alternative medicine procedure</TermRef></SecondaryTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_135">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of milk thistle in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_136">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>complementary or alternative medicine procedure</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>silymarin</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Milk Thistle (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Milk Thistle (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Milk Thistle</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_243"><Strong>NOTE: There is either no new research on this topic or the recent published research is weak and not appropriate for inclusion in the summary. Therefore, the information in this summary is no longer being updated and is provided for reference purposes only.</Strong></Para><Para id="_2">This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summary provides an overview of the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">milk thistle</GlossaryTermRef> as a treatment and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367454" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjunct agent</GlossaryTermRef> for people with cancer.</Para><Para id="_3">The summary includes a brief history of milk thistle, a review of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory studies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, and a description of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> associated with milk thistle use.</Para><Para id="_4">This summary contains the following key information:</Para><ItemizedList id="_5" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Milk thistle is a plant whose fruit and seeds have been used for more than 2,000 years as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044970" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biliary</GlossaryTermRef> disorders.</ListItem><ListItem> The active substance in milk thistle, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340936" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">silymarin</GlossaryTermRef>, is a complex mixture of flavonolignans.  Silymarin's primary constituents are  the flavonolignan <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">isomers</GlossaryTermRef> silybins A and B, isosilybins A and B, silychristin (also known as silichristin), silydianin (also known as silidianin), and their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">flavonoid</GlossaryTermRef> precursor, taxifolin. In the literature, the mixture of the silybins A and B is often referred to as silibinin.</ListItem><ListItem>Laboratory studies demonstrate that silymarin stabilizes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cellular</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046294" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">membranes</GlossaryTermRef>, stimulates <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">detoxification</GlossaryTermRef> pathways, stimulates <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390247" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regeneration</GlossaryTermRef> of liver tissue, inhibits the growth of certain cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044016" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell lines</GlossaryTermRef>, exerts direct <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic</GlossaryTermRef> activity toward certain cancer cell lines, and possibly increases the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044009" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy agents</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Human clinical trials have investigated milk thistle or silymarin primarily in individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045478" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cirrhosis</GlossaryTermRef>, although small studies have been reported about individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatocellular carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem>Few adverse <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> have been reported for milk thistle, but little information about interactions with anticancer medications, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, or other drugs is available.</ListItem><ListItem>Milk thistle is available in the United States as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplement</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_6">Many of the medical and scientific terms used in this summary are hypertext linked (at first use in each section) to the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary   of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>, which is oriented toward nonexperts. When a linked term is clicked, a definition will appear in a separate window. </Para><Para id="_10">Reference citations in some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> cancer information summaries may include links to external websites that are operated by individuals or organizations for the purpose of marketing or advocating the use of specific treatments or products. These reference citations are included for informational purposes only. Their inclusion should not be viewed as an endorsement of the content of the websites, or of any treatment or product, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board or the National Cancer Institute.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_9">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367458" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">botanical</GlossaryTermRef> name for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">milk thistle</GlossaryTermRef> is <ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372948" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Silybum marianum</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName> (L.) Gaertn. Milk thistle is also referred to as the following:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_237" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Holy thistle.</ListItem><ListItem>Marian thistle.</ListItem><ListItem>Mary thistle.</ListItem><ListItem>Our Lady’s thistle.</ListItem><ListItem>St. Mary thistle.</ListItem><ListItem>Wild artichoke.</ListItem><ListItem>Mariendistel (German).</ListItem><ListItem>Chardon-Marie (French).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_238">The plant is indigenous to Europe but can also be found in the United States and South America. Traditionally, the leaves have been used in salads, and the fruit of the flower has been roasted as a coffee substitute. The seed-like fruits (achenes) of milk thistle are the medicinal parts of the plant.<Reference refidx="1"/> The active constituent of milk thistle is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340936" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">silymarin</GlossaryTermRef>, which is a complex mixture of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">flavonoids</GlossaryTermRef> and flavonoid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">derivatives</GlossaryTermRef>, the flavonolignans. The major constituents of silymarin are the three diastereomeric pairs, silybins A and B (also called silibinin), isosilybins A and B, silychristin, isosilychristin, and silydianin.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Most supplements are standardized according to their  silybin content. Special formulations of  silymarin and/or the silybins have been developed to enhance their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef> by conjugation with phosphatidylcholine. Because of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lipophilic</GlossaryTermRef> nature of its active constituents, milk thistle is usually administered as an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef> in capsule or tablet form rather than as an herbal tea. In Europe, silybin is administered <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenously</GlossaryTermRef> as the only effective antidote for <ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367455" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Amanita phalloides</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName> (Fr.).<Reference refidx="4"/> Humans exposed to this mushroom <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxin</GlossaryTermRef> develop serious liver failure that progresses to death.</Para><Para id="_11">Several companies distribute milk thistle as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplement</GlossaryTermRef>. In the United States, dietary supplements are regulated as foods, not drugs. Therefore, premarket evaluation and approval by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) are not required unless specific disease prevention or treatment claims are made. Because dietary supplements are not formally reviewed for manufacturing consistency, ingredients may vary considerably from lot to lot and there is no guarantee that ingredients claimed on product labels are present (or are present in the specified amounts). The FDA has not approved the use of milk thistle as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or any other medical condition.</Para><Para id="_13">Despite milk thistle’s long history of being used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044970" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biliary</GlossaryTermRef> complaints, it was not until 1968 that silymarin was isolated from the seeds of the plant, and it was proposed that silymarin might be the active ingredient.<Reference refidx="5"/> Researchers have investigated the role that silibinin may play in the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045478" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cirrhosis</GlossaryTermRef>. Most studies have investigated the isolated compound silymarin or its most active isomer silybin, rather than the herbal plant in its whole form.</Para><Para id="_14">Silymarin is most well known for its purported effects on the liver. In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory studies</GlossaryTermRef>, silymarin has been found  to stabilize <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046294" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">membranes</GlossaryTermRef>, thus preventing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxic</GlossaryTermRef> chemicals from entering the cell.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> Laboratory studies have also demonstrated that silymarin stimulates synthesis and activity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> responsible for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">detoxification</GlossaryTermRef> pathways.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/> Specifically, silymarin has been shown to stimulate the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373012" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glutathione S-transferase</GlossaryTermRef> pathway and alter the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044047" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intracellular</GlossaryTermRef> concentration of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glutathione</GlossaryTermRef> (a potent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef>). Silymarin has also been shown to neutralize a wide range of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044030" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">free radicals</GlossaryTermRef>. Reports that associate the flavonolignans with potential estrogenic effect (e.g., via mediation of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046409" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estrogen receptor</GlossaryTermRef>) are sparse and currently not supported by <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> or <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> experimental evidence.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><Para id="_15">Laboratory experiments conducted using cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044016" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell lines</GlossaryTermRef> have suggested that silibinin enhances the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef> against <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044984" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovarian</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef> cancer cells.<Reference refidx="20"/> Silybin appears to have direct anticancer effects against <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef>, breast, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372926" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ectocervical</GlossaryTermRef> tumor cells.<Reference refidx="21"/>  Silybin may also affect the cell cycle in cancer cells by slowing down cell growth, as demonstrated with prostate cancer cell lines.<Reference refidx="22"/> Laboratory studies using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> cell lines found that silybin did not stimulate growth of leukemia cells.<Reference refidx="23"/></Para><Para id="_16">Most clinical trials have investigated silymarin’s effectiveness in the treatment of patients with hepatitis, cirrhosis, or biliary disorders.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/> These studies have employed a wide range of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> (120–560 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/day) and have yielded conflicting results.<Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/> The most commonly reported <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> are a mild <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laxative</GlossaryTermRef> effect and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> upset.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">PDR® for Herbal Medicines™. 2nd ed. Medical Economics, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="14510591">Lee DY, Liu Y: Molecular structure and stereochemistry of silybin A, silybin B, isosilybin A, and isosilybin B, Isolated from Silybum marianum (milk thistle). J Nat Prod 66 (9): 1171-4, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23461697">Napolitano JG, Lankin DC, Graf TN, et al.: HiFSA fingerprinting applied to isomers with near-identical NMR spectra: the silybin/isosilybin case. J Org Chem 78 (7): 2827-39, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6862461" MedlineID="83236428">Hruby K, Csomos G, Fuhrmann M, et al.: Chemotherapy of Amanita phalloides poisoning with intravenous silibinin. Hum Toxicol 2 (2): 183-95, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="5755805" MedlineID="69109563">Wagner H, Hörhammer L, Münster R: [On the chemistry of silymarin (silybin), the active principle of the fruits from Silybum marianum (L.) Gaertn. (Carduus marianus L.)] Arzneimittelforschung 18 (6): 688-96, 1968.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2813577" MedlineID="90047196">Campos R, Garrido A, Guerra R, et al.: Silybin dihemisuccinate protects against glutathione depletion and lipid peroxidation induced by acetaminophen on rat liver. Planta Med 55 (5): 417-9, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="10623491" MedlineID="20091035">Farghali H, Kameniková L, Hynie S, et al.: Silymarin effects on intracellular calcuim and cytotoxicity: a study in perfused rat hepatocytes after oxidative stress injury. Pharmacol Res 41 (2): 231-7, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="2353942" MedlineID="90282767">Lettéron P, Labbe G, Degott C, et al.: Mechanism for the protective effects of silymarin against carbon tetrachloride-induced lipid peroxidation and hepatotoxicity in mice. Evidence that silymarin acts both as an inhibitor of metabolic activation and as a chain-breaking antioxidant. Biochem Pharmacol 39 (12): 2027-34, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="10545412" MedlineID="20014762">Zhao J, Agarwal R: Tissue distribution of silibinin, the major active constituent of silymarin, in mice and its association with enhancement of phase II enzymes: implications in cancer chemoprevention. Carcinogenesis 20 (11): 2101-8, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="3562659" MedlineID="87176088">Valenzuela A, Guerra R, Videla LA: Antioxidant properties of the flavonoids silybin and (+)-cyanidanol-3: comparison with butylated hydroxyanisole and butylated hydroxytoluene. Planta Med  (6): 438-40, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="3432421" MedlineID="88125454">Valenzuela A, Guerra R, Garrido A: Silybin dihemisuccinate protects rat erythrocytes against phenylhydrazine-induced lipid peroxidation and hemolysis. Planta Med 53 (5): 402-5, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="2813578" MedlineID="90047197">Valenzuela A, Aspillaga M, Vial S, et al.: Selectivity of silymarin on the increase of the glutathione content in different tissues of the rat. Planta Med 55 (5): 420-2, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="3508133" MedlineID="89212131">Mira ML, Azevedo MS, Manso C: The neutralization of hydroxyl radical by silibin, sorbinil and bendazac. Free Radic Res Commun 4 (2): 125-9, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="8080448" MedlineID="94361695">Mira L, Silva M, Manso CF: Scavenging of reactive oxygen species by silibinin dihemisuccinate. Biochem Pharmacol 48 (4): 753-9, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="3990442" MedlineID="85187124">Koch HP, Löffler E: Influence of silymarin and some flavonoids on lipid peroxidation in human platelets. Methods Find Exp Clin Pharmacol 7 (1): 13-8, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="1682911" MedlineID="92051831">Garrido A, Arancibia C, Campos R, et al.: Acetaminophen does not induce oxidative stress in isolated rat hepatocytes: its probable antioxidant effect is potentiated by the flavonoid silybin. Pharmacol Toxicol 69 (1): 9-12, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="1635893" MedlineID="92342576">Bosisio E, Benelli C, Pirola O: Effect of the flavanolignans of Silybum marianum L. on lipid peroxidation in rat liver microsomes and freshly isolated hepatocytes. Pharmacol Res 25 (2): 147-54, 1992 Feb-Mar.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="1345204" MedlineID="94262485">Altorjay I, Dalmi L, Sári B, et al.: The effect of silibinin (Legalon) on the the free radical scavenger mechanisms of human erythrocytes in vitro. Acta Physiol Hung 80 (1-4): 375-80, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="19577454">El-Shitany NA, Hegazy S, El-Desoky K: Evidences for antiosteoporotic and selective estrogen receptor modulator activity of silymarin compared with ethinylestradiol in ovariectomized rats. Phytomedicine 17 (2): 116-25, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="9081370" MedlineID="96273517">Scambia G, De Vincenzo R, Ranelletti FO, et al.: Antiproliferative effect of silybin on gynaecological malignancies: synergism with cisplatin and doxorubicin. Eur J Cancer 32A (5): 877-82, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="10660092" MedlineID="20123488">Bhatia N, Zhao J, Wolf DM, et al.: Inhibition of human carcinoma cell growth and DNA synthesis by silibinin, an active constituent of milk thistle: comparison with silymarin. Cancer Lett 147 (1-2): 77-84, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="10377442" MedlineID="99307437">Zi X, Agarwal R: Silibinin decreases prostate-specific antigen with cell growth inhibition via G1 arrest, leading to differentiation of prostate carcinoma cells: implications for prostate cancer intervention. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 96 (13): 7490-5, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="9150762" MedlineID="97295110">Duthie SJ, Johnson W, Dobson VL: The effect of dietary flavonoids on DNA damage (strand breaks and oxidised pyrimdines) and growth in human cells. Mutat Res 390 (1-2): 141-51, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="24">Vailati A, Aristia L, Sozzé E, et al.: Randomized open study of the dose-effect relationship of a short course of IdB 1016 in patients with viral or alcoholic hepatitis. Fitoterapia  64 (3), 219-28, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="6753109" MedlineID="83040974">Salmi HA, Sarna S: Effect of silymarin on chemical, functional, and morphological alterations of the liver. A double-blind controlled study. Scand J Gastroenterol 17 (4): 517-21, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="9566830" MedlineID="98226482">Parés A, Planas R, Torres M, et al.: Effects of silymarin in alcoholic patients with cirrhosis of the liver: results of a controlled, double-blind, randomized and multicenter trial. J Hepatol 28 (4): 615-21, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="27">Moscarella S, Giusti A, Marra F, et al.: Therapeutic and antilipoperoxidant effects of silybin-phosphatidylcholine complex in chronic liver disease: preliminary results. Current Therapeutic Research  53 (1): 98-102.</Citation><Citation idx="28">Marena C, Lampertico M: Preliminary clinical development of silipide: a new complex of silybin in toxic liver disorders. Planta Med  57 (Suppl 2): A124-5, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="29">Marcelli R, Bizzoni P, Conte D, et al.: Randomized controlled study of the efficacy and tolerability of a short course of IdB 1016 in the treatment of chronic persistent hepatitis. European Bulletin of Drug Research  1 (3): 131-5, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="9356866" MedlineID="98019714">Flisiak R, Prokopowicz D: Effect of misoprostol on the course of viral hepatitis B. Hepatogastroenterology 44 (17): 1419-25, 1997 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="11205179" MedlineID="21076617">Ferenci P: [Therapy of chronic hepatitis C] Wien Med Wochenschr 150 (23-24): 481-5, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="32">Buzzelli G, Moscarella S, Giusti A, et al.: Therapeutic effects of a new silybin complex in chronic active hepatitis (CAH). [Abstract] Hellenic Journal of Gastroenterology  5 (Suppl): A-151, 38, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="33">Albrecht M, Frerick H, Kuhn U, et al.: Therapy of toxic liver pathologies with Legalon®. Z Klin Med  47: 87-92, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="17943794">Rambaldi A, Jacobs BP, Gluud C: Milk thistle for alcoholic and/or hepatitis B or C virus liver diseases. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (4): CD003620, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="25247194">Yang Z, Zhuang L, Lu Y, et al.: Effects and tolerance of silymarin (milk thistle) in chronic hepatitis C virus infection patients: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Biomed Res Int 2014: 941085, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_17"><Title>History</Title><Para id="_18"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Milk thistle</GlossaryTermRef> has been used for more than 2,000 years, primarily as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390268" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dysfunction</GlossaryTermRef>. The oldest reported use of milk thistle was by Dioscorides (A.D. 40–90), who recommended the herb as a treatment for serpent bites.<Reference refidx="1"/> Pliny the Elder (A.D. 23–79) reported that the juice of the plant mixed with honey is indicated for “carrying off bile.”<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> In the Middle Ages, milk thistle was revered as an antidote for liver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxins</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> The British herbalist Culpepper reported milk thistle to be effective for relieving obstructions of the liver.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> In 1898, eclectic physicians Felter and Lloyd stated the herb was good for congestion of the liver, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> American Indian or Alaska Native people use milk thistle to treat boils and other skin diseases. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Homeopathic</GlossaryTermRef> practitioners use preparations from the seeds to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">jaundice</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallstones</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritonitis</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemorrhage</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046495" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bronchitis</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372949" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">varicose veins</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/> The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">German Commission E</GlossaryTermRef> recommends milk thistle use for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044200" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dyspeptic</GlossaryTermRef> complaints, toxin-induced liver damage, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045478" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cirrhosis</GlossaryTermRef>, and as a supportive therapy for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef> liver conditions.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="9468229" MedlineID="98127747">Flora K, Hahn M, Rosen H, et al.: Milk thistle (Silybum marianum) for the therapy of liver disease. Am J Gastroenterol 93 (2): 139-43, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Foster S: Milk Thistle: Silybum marianum. Rev. ed. American Botanical Council, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Blumenthal M, Busse WR, et al., eds.: The Complete German Commission E Monographs: Therapeutic Guide to Herbal Medicines. American Botanical Council, 1998.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><Para id="_20">Research studies conducted in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> have investigated the properties of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340936" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">silymarin</GlossaryTermRef> or its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">isomer</GlossaryTermRef> silybin using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044016" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell lines</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal models</GlossaryTermRef>. Other substances in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">milk thistle</GlossaryTermRef> have not been extensively studied.</Para><Para id="_21">Several research studies have investigated the effects of silymarin or silybin in a noncancer context. These studies have tested silymarin or silybin:</Para><ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In healthy animal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>As a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046538" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prophylaxis</GlossaryTermRef> against <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxic</GlossaryTermRef> chemicals.</ListItem><ListItem>In stimulating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">detoxification</GlossaryTermRef> pathways (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> concentrations and activity).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_23">Silymarin or  silybin has also been investigated in cancer models. The effects of silymarin and/or  silybin have been  investigated in the following cell lines:</Para><ItemizedList id="_239" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Prostate</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DU 145</GlossaryTermRef>, LNCaP, PC-3).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Breast</GlossaryTermRef> (MDA-MB 468, MCF-7).<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hepatic</GlossaryTermRef> (HepG2).<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem><ListItem> Epidermoid (A431).<Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Colon</GlossaryTermRef> (Caco-2).<Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044984" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ovarian</GlossaryTermRef> (OVCA 433, A2780).<Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem><ListItem>   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Histiocytic lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> (U-937).<Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (HL-60).<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_240"> In animal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor models</GlossaryTermRef>, tongue cancer,<Reference refidx="17"/> skin cancer,<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> cancer,<Reference refidx="24"/> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the colon <Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="26"/> have been investigated. These studies have tested the ability of silymarin or silibinin to:</Para><ItemizedList id="_33" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390299" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mitigate</GlossaryTermRef> the toxicity associated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044009" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy agents</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Enhance the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of chemotherapy agents.</ListItem><ListItem>Inhibit the growth of cancer cell lines and inhibit <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390314" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor initiation</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390316" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor promotion</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_230">Laboratory data suggest that silymarin and  silybin protect the liver from damage induced by toxic chemicals. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> have found that liver cells treated with  silybin and then exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxins</GlossaryTermRef> do not incur cell damage or death at the same rate as liver cells that are not treated with  silybin. This finding suggests that  silybin  can prevent toxins from entering the cell or effectively exports toxins out of the cell before damage ensues.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/> Alternatively, this may be related to the effect of silymarin on detoxification systems. <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">In vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> data have shown  silybin  to stimulate and/or inhibit <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390309" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I detoxification</GlossaryTermRef> pathways in  silybin-treated human liver cells. 
However, this effect was found to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose-dependent</GlossaryTermRef>, and these levels are not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045837" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physiologically</GlossaryTermRef> attainable with the current manufacturer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> recommendations.<Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/></Para><Para id="_225"> Silymarin and silybin have also been found to accelerate cell <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390247" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regeneration</GlossaryTermRef> in the liver through stimulation of precursors to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044393" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> synthesis and enhancement of production of the cellular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> required for DNA synthesis.<Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/>  Silymarin has been shown to mitigate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxidative stress</GlossaryTermRef> in cells treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372940" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pro-oxidant</GlossaryTermRef> compounds.<Reference refidx="40"/></Para><Para id="_226">While some reports exist about the estrogenic effects assigned to silybin and silybin-containing materials,<Reference refidx="41"/> the observed effects are moderate, and the molecular mechanisms are not yet understood. Some evidence exists about the positive impact of these milk thistle compounds on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone density</GlossaryTermRef> in rats and mice that have undergone ovariectomy.<Reference refidx="42"/></Para><Para id="_231">Silibinin inhibits prostate cancer cell–induced osteoclastogenesis, suggesting that silibinin may be useful clinically for the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045317" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone metastases</GlossaryTermRef>. Silibinin targets prostate cancer cell–induced osteoclast <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">differentiation</GlossaryTermRef> and activity of murine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044054" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">macrophage</GlossaryTermRef> cells.<Reference refidx="43"/></Para><Para id="_34">Although many of these studies have produced encouraging results, none of the findings have been <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044621" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">replicated</GlossaryTermRef> in human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Table id="_228"><Title>Table 1.  Inhibit the Growth of Cancer Cell Lines and Inhibit Tumor Initiation</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Study Type/Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Outcome</GlossaryTermRef></entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry><ScientificName>In vitro</ScientificName> <Reference refidx="7"/></entry><entry>Prostate, breast, cervical</entry><entry>Cancer chemopreventive and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044272" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anticarcinogenic</GlossaryTermRef> effects of silymarin were reported</entry></Row><Row><entry><ScientificName>In vitro</ScientificName> <Reference refidx="15"/></entry><entry>Leukemia</entry><entry>Silybinin stimulated HL-60 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046477" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell differentiation</GlossaryTermRef> along the monocytic pathway</entry></Row><Row><entry><ScientificName>In vitro</ScientificName> <Reference refidx="44"/></entry><entry>Epidermal</entry><entry>Silymarin inhibited cell growth by inducing G1 and G2-M arrest in cell cycle progression </entry></Row><Row><entry><ScientificName>In vitro</ScientificName> <Reference refidx="45"/></entry><entry>Epidermal</entry><entry>Silymarin inhibited <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell proliferation</GlossaryTermRef> and induced cell growth arrest </entry></Row><Row><entry><ScientificName>In vitro</ScientificName> <Reference refidx="46"/></entry><entry>Colon</entry><entry>Silibinin suppressed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cell growth and progression, possibly through its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anti-inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef> activity, by interfering with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000773861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nuclear factor-kappa B</GlossaryTermRef> (NF-kappa B) activation; In human colorectal cancer SW480, LoVo, and HT29 cells, silibinin treatment strongly inhibited <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor necrosis factor</GlossaryTermRef> alpha–induced NF-kappa B activation and  decreased nuclear levels of both p65 and p50 subunits </entry></Row><Row><entry><ScientificName>In vivo</ScientificName> <Reference refidx="2"/>;<Reference refidx="19"/>;<Reference refidx="24"/>;<Reference refidx="47"/>;<Reference refidx="48"/>;<Reference refidx="49"/></entry><entry>Various</entry><entry>Inhibited <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor volume</GlossaryTermRef>; reduced tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046145" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incidence</GlossaryTermRef>; exerted protective and preventive effects against tumor promotion </entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_232">Several <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> studies have explored anticancer effects of milk thistle extracts. Silybinin has been shown to inhibit cell proliferation by inducing cell cycle arrest at the G1 and  G2-M transition in epidermal,<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/> prostate,<Reference refidx="7"/> breast,<Reference refidx="7"/> and cervical <Reference refidx="7"/> cancer cell lines. One study also demonstrated that growth of colon cancer cell lines was inhibited by silibinin, apparently through suppression of NF-kappa B.<Reference refidx="46"/> Finally, silymarin has also been shown to induce differentiation in a human leukemia cell line.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Table id="_229">
     <Title>Table 2.  Enhance the Efficacy of Chemotherapy Agents (<ScientificName>In Vitro</ScientificName> Studies)</Title>
      <TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Outcome</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry> <Reference refidx="50"/></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Glioma</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Silibinin potentiated the effect of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">etoposide</GlossaryTermRef> but not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635811" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">irinotecan</GlossaryTermRef> in LN229 cells</entry></Row><Row><entry> <Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>Ovarian, breast</entry><entry>Silybin potentiated the cytotoxic effect of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef> and doxorubicin in MCF-7 and A2780 cells</entry></Row><Row><entry> <Reference refidx="51"/></entry><entry>Ovarian</entry><entry>Silybin potentiated the cytotoxic effect of cisplatin in A2780 cells</entry></Row><Row><entry> <Reference refidx="52"/></entry><entry>Prostate</entry><entry>Silybin potentiated the cytotoxic effect of DU145 cells</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup>
     </Table><Para id="_233">Other <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> studies have demonstrated that components of milk thistle extract can enhance the effects of certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic agents</GlossaryTermRef> against various cancer types (i.e., etoposide against LN229 glioma cells,<Reference refidx="50"/> cisplatin against A2780 ovarian cancer cells <Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="51"/> and MCF-7 breast cancer cells,<Reference refidx="13"/> and tumor necrosis factor alpha against DU145 prostate cancer cells <Reference refidx="52"/>).</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10377442" MedlineID="99307437">Zi X, Agarwal R: Silibinin decreases prostate-specific antigen with cell growth inhibition via G1 arrest, leading to differentiation of prostate carcinoma cells: implications for prostate cancer intervention. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 96 (13): 7490-5, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="12036915" MedlineID="22032762">Singh RP, Dhanalakshmi S, Tyagi AK, et al.: Dietary feeding of silibinin inhibits advance human prostate carcinoma growth in athymic nude mice and increases plasma insulin-like growth factor-binding protein-3 levels. Cancer Res 62 (11): 3063-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11059749" MedlineID="20511556">Zi X, Zhang J, Agarwal R, et al.: Silibinin up-regulates insulin-like growth factor-binding protein 3 expression and inhibits proliferation of androgen-independent prostate cancer cells. Cancer Res 60 (20): 5617-20, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="9581834" MedlineID="98240990">Zi X, Grasso AW, Kung HJ, et al.: A flavonoid antioxidant, silymarin, inhibits activation of erbB1 signaling and induces cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitors, G1 arrest, and anticarcinogenic effects in human prostate carcinoma DU145 cells. Cancer Res 58 (9): 1920-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="11346885" MedlineID="21244464">Sharma Y, Agarwal C, Singh AK, et al.: Inhibitory effect of silibinin on ligand binding to erbB1 and associated mitogenic signaling, growth, and DNA synthesis in advanced human prostate carcinoma cells. Mol Carcinog 30 (4): 224-36, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20127732">Flaig TW, Glodé M, Gustafson D, et al.: A study of high-dose oral silybin-phytosome followed by prostatectomy in patients with localized prostate cancer. Prostate 70 (8): 848-55, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="10660092" MedlineID="20123488">Bhatia N, Zhao J, Wolf DM, et al.: Inhibition of human carcinoma cell growth and DNA synthesis by silibinin, an active constituent of milk thistle: comparison with silymarin. Cancer Lett 147 (1-2): 77-84, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11006131" MedlineID="20462964">Jiang C, Agarwal R, Lü J: Anti-angiogenic potential of a cancer chemopreventive flavonoid antioxidant, silymarin: inhibition of key attributes of vascular endothelial cells and angiogenic cytokine secretion by cancer epithelial cells. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 276 (1): 371-8, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9563902" MedlineID="98223391">Zi X, Feyes DK, Agarwal R: Anticarcinogenic effect of a flavonoid antioxidant, silymarin, in human breast cancer cells MDA-MB 468: induction of G1 arrest through an increase in Cip1/p21 concomitant with a decrease in kinase activity of cyclin-dependent kinases and associated cyclins. Clin Cancer Res 4 (4): 1055-64, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="9862414" MedlineID="99077230">Saliou C, Rihn B, Cillard J, et al.: Selective inhibition of NF-kappaB activation by the flavonoid hepatoprotector silymarin in HepG2. Evidence for different activating pathways. FEBS Lett 440 (1-2): 8-12, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8688194" MedlineID="96245828">Shear NH, Malkiewicz IM, Klein D, et al.: Acetaminophen-induced toxicity to human epidermoid cell line A431 and hepatoblastoma cell line Hep G2, in vitro, is diminished by silymarin. Skin Pharmacol 8 (6): 279-91, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="9150762" MedlineID="97295110">Duthie SJ, Johnson W, Dobson VL: The effect of dietary flavonoids on DNA damage (strand breaks and oxidised pyrimdines) and growth in human cells. Mutat Res 390 (1-2): 141-51, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="9081370" MedlineID="96273517">Scambia G, De Vincenzo R, Ranelletti FO, et al.: Antiproliferative effect of silybin on gynaecological malignancies: synergism with cisplatin and doxorubicin. Eur J Cancer 32A (5): 877-82, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="10586080" MedlineID="20054570">Manna SK, Mukhopadhyay A, Van NT, et al.: Silymarin suppresses TNF-induced activation of NF-kappa B, c-Jun N-terminal kinase, and apoptosis. J Immunol 163 (12): 6800-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="11377378" MedlineID="21271765">Kang SN, Lee MH, Kim KM, et al.: Induction of human promyelocytic leukemia HL-60 cell differentiation into monocytes by silibinin: involvement of protein kinase C. Biochem Pharmacol 61 (12): 1487-95, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="10547532" MedlineID="20016287">Clinton SK: The dietary antioxidant network and prostate carcinoma. Cancer 86 (9): 1629-31, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="12016151" MedlineID="22011760">Yanaida Y, Kohno H, Yoshida K, et al.: Dietary silymarin suppresses 4-nitroquinoline 1-oxide-induced tongue carcinogenesis in male F344 rats. Carcinogenesis 23 (5): 787-94, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="8020140" MedlineID="94291246">Agarwal R, Katiyar SK, Lundgren DW, et al.: Inhibitory effect of silymarin, an anti-hepatotoxic flavonoid, on 12-O-tetradecanoylphorbol-13-acetate-induced epidermal ornithine decarboxylase activity and mRNA in SENCAR mice. Carcinogenesis 15 (6): 1099-103, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="9106644" MedlineID="97260524">Katiyar SK, Korman NJ, Mukhtar H, et al.: Protective effects of silymarin against photocarcinogenesis in a mouse skin model. J Natl Cancer Inst 89 (8): 556-66, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="9973210" MedlineID="99137495">Lahiri-Chatterjee M, Katiyar SK, Mohan RR, et al.: A flavonoid antioxidant, silymarin, affords exceptionally high protection against tumor promotion in the SENCAR mouse skin tumorigenesis model. Cancer Res 59 (3): 622-32, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="11895866" MedlineID="21892770">Singh RP, Tyagi AK, Zhao J, et al.: Silymarin inhibits growth and causes regression of established skin tumors in SENCAR mice via modulation of mitogen-activated protein kinases and induction of apoptosis. Carcinogenesis 23 (3): 499-510, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="10569809" MedlineID="20038166">Zhao J, Sharma Y, Agarwal R: Significant inhibition by the flavonoid antioxidant silymarin against 12-O-tetradecanoylphorbol 13-acetate-caused modulation of antioxidant and inflammatory enzymes, and cyclooxygenase 2 and interleukin-1alpha expression in SENCAR mouse epidermis: implications in the prevention of stage I tumor promotion. Mol Carcinog 26 (4): 321-33, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="10753220" MedlineID="20216861">Zhao J, Lahiri-Chatterjee M, Sharma Y, et al.: Inhibitory effect of a flavonoid antioxidant silymarin on benzoyl peroxide-induced tumor promotion, oxidative stress and inflammatory responses in SENCAR mouse skin. Carcinogenesis 21 (4): 811-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="11802807" MedlineID="21661985">Vinh PQ, Sugie S, Tanaka T, et al.: Chemopreventive effects of a flavonoid antioxidant silymarin on N-butyl-N-(4-hydroxybutyl)nitrosamine-induced urinary bladder carcinogenesis in male ICR mice. Jpn J Cancer Res 93 (1): 42-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="12216075" MedlineID="22204131">Kohno H, Tanaka T, Kawabata K, et al.: Silymarin, a naturally occurring polyphenolic antioxidant flavonoid, inhibits azoxymethane-induced colon carcinogenesis in male F344 rats. Int J Cancer 101 (5): 461-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="8074460" MedlineID="94354584">Gershbein LL: Action of dietary trypsin, pressed coffee oil, silymarin and iron salt on 1,2-dimethylhydrazine tumorigenesis by gavage. Anticancer Res 14 (3A): 1113-6, 1994 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="2813577" MedlineID="90047196">Campos R, Garrido A, Guerra R, et al.: Silybin dihemisuccinate protects against glutathione depletion and lipid peroxidation induced by acetaminophen on rat liver. Planta Med 55 (5): 417-9, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="10623491" MedlineID="20091035">Farghali H, Kameniková L, Hynie S, et al.: Silymarin effects on intracellular calcuim and cytotoxicity: a study in perfused rat hepatocytes after oxidative stress injury. Pharmacol Res 41 (2): 231-7, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="2353942" MedlineID="90282767">Lettéron P, Labbe G, Degott C, et al.: Mechanism for the protective effects of silymarin against carbon tetrachloride-induced lipid peroxidation and hepatotoxicity in mice. Evidence that silymarin acts both as an inhibitor of metabolic activation and as a chain-breaking antioxidant. Biochem Pharmacol 39 (12): 2027-34, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="3432421" MedlineID="88125454">Valenzuela A, Guerra R, Garrido A: Silybin dihemisuccinate protects rat erythrocytes against phenylhydrazine-induced lipid peroxidation and hemolysis. Planta Med 53 (5): 402-5, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="3174702" MedlineID="89017370">Campos R, Garrido A, Guerra R, et al.: Acetaminophen hepatotoxicity in rats is attenuated by silybin dihemisuccinate. Prog Clin Biol Res 280: 375-8, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="12410543" MedlineID="22297939">Zuber R, Modrianský M, Dvorák Z, et al.: Effect of silybin and its congeners on human liver microsomal cytochrome P450 activities. Phytother Res 16 (7): 632-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="11038151" MedlineID="20493197">Venkataramanan R, Ramachandran V, Komoroski BJ, et al.: Milk thistle, a herbal supplement, decreases the activity of CYP3A4 and uridine diphosphoglucuronosyl transferase in human hepatocyte cultures. Drug Metab Dispos 28 (11): 1270-3, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="976944" MedlineID="77027528">Sonnenbichler J, Mattersberger J, Rosen H: [Stimulation of RNA synthesis in rat liver and isolated hepatocytes by silybin, an antihepatotoxic agent from Silybum marianum L. Gaertn (author's transl)] Hoppe Seylers Z Physiol Chem 357 (8): 1171-80, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="6469218" MedlineID="84287393">Sonnenbichler J, Zetl I: [Mechanism of action of silibinin. V. Effect of silibinin on the synthesis of ribosomal RNA, mRNA and tRNA in rat liver in vivo] Hoppe Seylers Z Physiol Chem 365 (5): 555-66, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="2424029" MedlineID="86233541">Sonnenbichler J, Zetl I: Biochemical effects of the flavonolignane silibinin on RNA, protein and DNA synthesis in rat livers. Prog Clin Biol Res 213: 319-31, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="3004503" MedlineID="86130726">Sonnenbichler J, Goldberg M, Hane L, et al.: Stimulatory effect of Silibinin on the DNA synthesis in partially hepatectomized rat livers: non-response in hepatoma and other malign cell lines. Biochem Pharmacol 35 (3): 538-41, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="844797" MedlineID="77139606">Machicao F, Sonnenbichler J: Mechanism of the stimulation of RNA synthesis in rat liver nuclei by silybin. Hoppe Seylers Z Physiol Chem 358 (2): 141-7, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="8666328" MedlineID="96230098">Dehmlow C, Erhard J, de Groot H: Inhibition of Kupffer cell functions as an explanation for the hepatoprotective properties of silibinin. Hepatology 23 (4): 749-54, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="22354081">Malekinejad H, Rahmani F, Valivande-Azar S, et al.: Long-term administration of Silymarin augments proinflammatory mediators in the hippocampus of rats: evidence for antioxidant and pro-oxidant effects. Hum Exp Toxicol 31 (9): 921-30, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="19577454">El-Shitany NA, Hegazy S, El-Desoky K: Evidences for antiosteoporotic and selective estrogen receptor modulator activity of silymarin compared with ethinylestradiol in ovariectomized rats. Phytomedicine 17 (2): 116-25, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="23781510">Kim JL, Kim YH, Kang MK, et al.: Antiosteoclastic activity of milk thistle extract after ovariectomy to suppress estrogen deficiency-induced osteoporosis. Biomed Res Int 2013: 919374, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="23115104">Kavitha CV, Deep G, Gangar SC, et al.: Silibinin inhibits prostate cancer cells- and RANKL-induced osteoclastogenesis by targeting NFATc1, NF-κB, and AP-1 activation in RAW264.7 cells. Mol Carcinog 53 (3): 169-80, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="10491326" MedlineID="99423497">Zi X, Agarwal R: Modulation of mitogen-activated protein kinase activation and cell cycle regulators by the potent skin cancer preventive agent silymarin. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 263 (2): 528-36, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="9642119" MedlineID="98308109">Ahmad N, Gali H, Javed S, et al.: Skin cancer chemopreventive effects of a flavonoid antioxidant silymarin are mediated via impairment of receptor tyrosine kinase signaling and perturbation in cell cycle progression. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 247 (2): 294-301, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="22086675">Raina K, Agarwal C, Agarwal R: Effect of silibinin in human colorectal cancer cells: targeting the activation of NF-κB signaling. Mol Carcinog 52 (3): 195-206, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="9345320" MedlineID="98005131">Zi X, Mukhtar H, Agarwal R: Novel cancer chemopreventive effects of a flavonoid antioxidant silymarin: inhibition of mRNA expression of an endogenous tumor promoter TNF alpha. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 239 (1): 334-9, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="23447564">Lee MH, Huang Z, Kim DJ, et al.: Direct targeting of MEK1/2 and RSK2 by silybin induces cell-cycle arrest and inhibits melanoma cell growth. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 6 (5): 455-65, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="20628792">Velmurugan B, Gangar SC, Kaur M, et al.: Silibinin exerts sustained growth suppressive effect against human colon carcinoma SW480 xenograft by targeting multiple signaling molecules. Pharm Res 27 (10): 2085-97, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="25750273">Elhag R, Mazzio EA, Soliman KF: The effect of silibinin in enhancing toxicity of temozolomide and etoposide in p53 and PTEN-mutated resistant glioma cell lines. Anticancer Res 35 (3): 1263-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="11883719" MedlineID="21880596">Giacomelli S, Gallo D, Apollonio P, et al.: Silybin and its bioavailable phospholipid complex (IdB 1016) potentiate in vitro and in vivo the activity of cisplatin. Life Sci 70 (12): 1447-59, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="11896607" MedlineID="21893675">Dhanalakshmi S, Singh RP, Agarwal C, et al.: Silibinin inhibits constitutive and TNFalpha-induced activation of NF-kappaB and sensitizes human prostate carcinoma DU145 cells to TNFalpha-induced apoptosis. Oncogene 21 (11): 1759-67, 2002.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><Title>Human/Clinical Studies</Title><Para id="_129">Several small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">studies</GlossaryTermRef> have investigated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340936" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">silymarin</GlossaryTermRef> for its direct treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or for its effects on treatment-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_202">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I</GlossaryTermRef> study was designed to determine the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000546597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maximum tolerated dose</GlossaryTermRef> per day of silybin phosphatidylcholine (Siliphos) in patients with advanced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatocellular carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> (HCC) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390268" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dysfunction</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/>
 Three patients were enrolled in this single-institution trial. All patients who were enrolled consumed 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">g</GlossaryTermRef>/d of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044734" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">study agent</GlossaryTermRef> in divided <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses.</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Serum</GlossaryTermRef> concentrations of silibinin and silibinin glucuronide increased within 1 to 3 weeks. In all three patients, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> function <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormalities</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor marker</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046208" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alpha-fetoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> progressed, but after day 56, the third patient showed some improvement in liver function abnormalities and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biomarkers</GlossaryTermRef>. All three patients died within 23 to 69 days of enrolling in the trial, likely from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic</GlossaryTermRef> failure, but it could not be ruled out that deaths were possibly caused by the study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef>. This patient population may have been too ill to benefit from an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intervention</GlossaryTermRef> designed to improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390293" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver function tests</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_99">In a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045673" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">double-blind</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef> trial, 50 children who were undergoing treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>, and who had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>-related hepatotoxicity, were randomly assigned to receive silymarin or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> for a 4-week period.<Reference refidx="2"/> Four weeks after completion of the intervention, the silymarin group had a significantly lower aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .05) and a trend towards a significantly lower alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .07).  Fewer chemotherapy dose reductions were observed in the silymarin group compared with the placebo group; however, the difference was not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">significant</GlossaryTermRef>.  No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse events</GlossaryTermRef> were reported.</Para><Para id="_130">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef> placebo-controlled study of 37 men, who had a status of post–radical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046549" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostatectomy</GlossaryTermRef>, investigated whether a 6-month daily <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> of a silymarin and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">selenium</GlossaryTermRef> combination would alter basic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> chemistry, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxidative stress</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>, and improve the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality-of-life</GlossaryTermRef> (QOL) score in men after radical prostatectomy.<Reference refidx="3"/> The 6-month daily administration of silymarin and selenium improved the QOL score, decreased low-density lipoproteins and total <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cholesterol</GlossaryTermRef>, and increased serum selenium levels. The combination had no effect on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef> status and no influence on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045581" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testosterone</GlossaryTermRef> level. No adverse events were recorded. No improvement was found in the placebo group.</Para><Para id="_201">Another randomized placebo-controlled study of 30 patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef> investigated a 6-week course of silymarin for the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>–associated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045789" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucositis</GlossaryTermRef>. Mucositis scores (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454794" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">World Health Organization</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> Common Toxicity Criteria) were significantly lower in the silymarin group.<Reference refidx="4"/> Delay in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression</GlossaryTermRef> to mucositis was also observed.</Para><Para id="_131">In a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044160" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nonrandomized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000286105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">observational</GlossaryTermRef> trial of 101 women with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> who had undergone <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast-conserving surgery</GlossaryTermRef> followed by radiation therapy with 50.4 Gy plus a boost of 9 Gy to 16 Gy, a silymarin-based cream (Leviaderm) was tested in 51 women compared with panthenol-containing cream, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard of care</GlossaryTermRef> (SOC), which was given interventionally if local skin <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesions</GlossaryTermRef> occurred and administered to 50 women.<Reference refidx="5"/> The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute</GlossaryTermRef> skin reactions were classified according to the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467874" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">visual analog scale</GlossaryTermRef> scores. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044941" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">median</GlossaryTermRef> time to toxicity was prolonged significantly with the silymarin-based cream (45 vs. 29 days [SOC], <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001). Only 9.8% of patients using the silymarin-based cream showed grade 2 toxicity in week 5 of radiation therapy, compared with 52% in the SOC group. At the end of radiation therapy, 23.5% of the women in the silymarin-based study group developed no skin reactions compared with 2% of the women in the SOC group, while grade 3 toxicity occurred in only 2% of women in the silymarin-based group and in 28% of women in the SOC group.</Para><SummarySection id="_203"><Title>Hepatitis</Title><Para id="_204">Most clinical trials of milk thistle have been conducted in patients with either <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045478" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cirrhosis</GlossaryTermRef>. Other studies have investigated the use of milk thistle in patients with hyperlipidemia, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044911" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diabetes</GlossaryTermRef>, and <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367455" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Amanita phalloides</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> (Fr.) mushroom poisoning. Ten randomized trials  <Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> have been reported in patients with hepatitis or cirrhosis, and one randomized trial has reported  the use of silymarin as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046538" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prophylaxis</GlossaryTermRef> to iatrogenic hepatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="15"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endpoints</GlossaryTermRef> for these trials have  included serum levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044518" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilirubin</GlossaryTermRef> and/or the liver enzymes         AST and          ALT, as higher levels are an indicator of liver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammation</GlossaryTermRef>, damage, or disease. The lowering of these serum levels is a sign of an improving condition. In patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000472904" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis A</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046146" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis B</GlossaryTermRef>, one clinical trial found silymarin (140 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef> daily for 3–4 wk) resulting in lower levels of  AST, ALT, and bilirubin by day 5, compared with a placebo group.<Reference refidx="16"/> In another randomized, placebo-controlled study of patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044629" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">viral</GlossaryTermRef> hepatitis B, silymarin (210 mg/d) had no effect on course of disease or enzyme levels.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_205">A randomized, controlled trial supported by the  National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases examined patients  with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044139" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis C</GlossaryTermRef> who had failed previous <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antiviral</GlossaryTermRef> therapy.  All patients had advanced chronic liver disease consisting of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">histologic</GlossaryTermRef> evidence of either marked <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045690" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fibrosis</GlossaryTermRef> or cirrhosis. The  Hepatitis C Antiviral Long-Term Treatment Against Cirrhosis     trial used a half dose of pegylated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interferon</GlossaryTermRef> versus no treatment; the treatment was to be administered for 3.5 years.<Reference refidx="14"/>                           The aim was to reduce progression of chronic hepatitis C, particularly in the development of HCC.  Among 1,145 study participants, 56% had never taken <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbal</GlossaryTermRef> products, 21% admitted past use, and 23% were using herbal products at enrollment. Silymarin constituted 72% of the 60 herbal products used at enrollment.  Users had significantly fewer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and a better QOL than did nonusers. In  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef>, silymarin use was associated with reduced progression of fibrosis to cirrhosis but without an impact on clinical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_206">Although there are many reports on the use of herbals for the treatment of chronic liver diseases, most treatment trials have suffered because of  the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_241" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Poor scientific design.</ListItem><ListItem>Uncertainty about the required dosage of herbals.</ListItem><ListItem>An insufficient number of study participants.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_242">A review of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary and alternative medications</GlossaryTermRef> (CAM) to treat liver diseases focused on classification,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epidemiology</GlossaryTermRef>, and the philosophy of CAM and reviewed the criteria needed to conduct a scientifically valid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> focusing on herbal products.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_207">There has been skepticism regarding the evidence that silymarin has a direct impact on the hepatitis C virus (HCV)—some studies suggest that  it does, but most studies cannot confirm these reports.  However, at least two articles in major journals have suggested that silymarin or its congeners may  inhibit HCV.  In one report, investigators found that a standardized silymarin <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef> inhibited <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor necrosis factor</GlossaryTermRef>-alpha  in anti-CD3–stimulated human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peripheral blood</GlossaryTermRef> mononuclear cells and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000773861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nuclear factor-kappa B</GlossaryTermRef>–dependent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef> in human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046661" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatoma</GlossaryTermRef> Huh-7 cells.<Reference refidx="19"/>         Silymarin also displayed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256574" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prophylactic</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> effects against HCV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>, and when combined with interferon-alpha, was more inhibitory of HCV replication than was interferon alone.  This indicates that silymarin has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anti-inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef> and antiviral effects in patients with chronic hepatitis C.</Para><Para id="_208">In a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044006" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case series</GlossaryTermRef>/phase I study, patients with HCV were treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) silibinin with and without PEG-interferon and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045293" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ribavirin</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="20"/>  In the case series, 16 HCV nonresponder patients were administered IV silibinin in a dose of 10 mg/kg/d for 7 days. Subjects then began treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> silibinin in combination with PEG-interferon and 
ribavirin for 12 weeks.  At the end of the study period, all patients were positive for HCV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046568" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RNA</GlossaryTermRef>, but 5  of 13 completed patients had reductions in HCV RNA.  Significance was not reported.  In the same study, the authors presented results of a phase I study in which 20 patients were administered 5 mg/kg, 10 mg/kg, 15 mg/kg, or 20 mg/kg of silibinin for 14 days in combination with PEG-interferon and ribavirin (initiated on day 8).       A significant drop in HCV  RNA was observed on day 7 in patients administered silibinin doses of 10 mg/kg, 15 mg/kg, and 20 mg/kg.  Further declines were observed in HCV RNA with administration of PEG-interferon and ribavirin. Except for mild <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastroenteritis</GlossaryTermRef>, IV silibinin <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> was well tolerated.</Para><Para id="_209">Patients in a phase I <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetics</GlossaryTermRef> study for the evaluation of absorption characteristics and determination of effective doses received  increasing oral doses of silymarin.<Reference refidx="21"/> A subsequent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multicenter</GlossaryTermRef>, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, involving 154 patients with chronic HCV infection who had previously failed interferon-based treatment and had raised ALT levels, was performed.<Reference refidx="22"/> Patients were randomly assigned to receive 420 mg of silymarin, 700 mg of silymarin, or a matching placebo orally 3 times per day for 24 weeks, with the aim of reducing ALT levels to less than 40 U/L or less than 65 U/L if this was at least a 50% decline from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">baseline</GlossaryTermRef> level. In this  study, silymarin given orally in higher-than-usual doses failed to significantly reduce serum ALT levels. No significant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> were associated with silymarin. In one of the largest observational studies involving 2,637 patients with chronic liver disease, 8 weeks of treatment with 560 mg of silymarin per day resulted in reductions of serum AST, ALT, and gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase (GGT, a marker of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile duct</GlossaryTermRef> disease), and a decrease in the frequency of palpable <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373016" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatomegaly</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="23"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_210"><Title>Mushroom Poisoning</Title><Para id="_211">Another published report describes the use of  silibinin as the only effective antidote in patients with liver damage from <ScientificName>Amanita phalloides</ScientificName> (Fr.) poisoning.<Reference refidx="24"/> Patients were administered doses of 35 to 55 mg/kg of body weight, with no reports of adverse events. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044120" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retrospective</GlossaryTermRef> review of the treatment for <ScientificName>Amanita phalloides</ScientificName> (Fr.) poisoning suggests that silymarin has been shown to be an effective drug in the treatment of this mushroom poisoning.<Reference refidx="25"/> The beneficial effect of silymarin on liver histology suggests it has a role in the prevention of hepatitis and/or HCC; however, no clinical trials in humans have investigated these uses of silymarin.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_212"><Title>Iron Chelation</Title><Para id="_213">Silymarin was found to be beneficial as an adjunct to the iron chelator desferrioxamine in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transfusion</GlossaryTermRef>-dependent beta-thalassemia major.<Reference refidx="26"/>


 In a study of 97 patients, significant decreases in markers of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000626381" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iron overload</GlossaryTermRef> (serum <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ferritin</GlossaryTermRef>, serum iron, hepcidin, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soluble</GlossaryTermRef> transferring receptor) were observed in the patients who received silymarin as compared with those who received a placebo.</Para></SummarySection><Table id="_223"><Title>Table 3.  Clinical Studies Investigating Silymarin or Its Components</Title><TGroup Cols="7"><ColSpec ColName="col01" ColNum="1" ColWidth="16.54%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="2" ColWidth="15.10%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="13.90%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="11.99%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="13.06%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="6" ColWidth="17.02%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="7" ColWidth="12.35%"/><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01">ALL = acute lymphoblastic leukemia; ALT = alanine aminotransferase; AST = aspartate aminotransferase; HCV = hepatitis C virus; IV = intravenous; LFT = liver function test; No. = number; QOL = quality of life; SGOT = serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase; SGPT = serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Number of patients treated plus number of patients controlled may not equal number of patients enrolled; number of patients enrolled = number of patients initially recruited/considered by the researchers who conducted a study; number of patients treated = number of enrolled patients who were administered the treatment being studied <Strong>AND</Strong> for whom results were reported; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044596" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">historical control subjects</GlossaryTermRef> are not included in number of patients enrolled.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Nine patients were excluded from the final analysis (seven patients missed appointments, and two patients were missing data requirements).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Study investigated dose-response relationships. Patients were randomly assigned to receive 80 mg 2 times a day (n = 20), 120 mg 2 times a day (n = 20), or 120 mg 3 times a day (n = 20). The effective dose was 120 mg 2 times a day and 120 mg 3 times a day.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>d</Superscript>Patients were randomly assigned to the misoprostol and silymarin groups. Twelve nonrandomized patients served as controls.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>e</Superscript>Fifteen patients were lost to follow-up, 18 patients were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476461" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">deceased</GlossaryTermRef>, and 42 patients withdrew from the study (adverse events, noncompliance, and voluntary withdrawal).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>f</Superscript>Eleven patients did not complete the trial (voluntary withdrawal, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disease progression</GlossaryTermRef>, and one adverse event).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>g</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Strong>Prevention or Treatment of Liver Disease/Dysfunction</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Condition or Cancer Type  </Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Trial Design</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Route of Administration and Dose</Strong>
</entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)<Superscript>a</Superscript></Strong> </entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Results</Strong> </entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Level of Evidence</GlossaryTermRef> Score</Strong><Superscript>g</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="7"/></entry><entry>Acute and subacute liver disease </entry><entry>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin;
420 mg/d;
oral (tablets)
</entry><entry>106<Superscript>b</Superscript>; 47; 50</entry><entry>Decreased LFTs; improved histology</entry><entry>1iDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="1"/></entry><entry>Advanced hepatocellular carcinoma and hepatic dysfunction </entry><entry>Phase I, open-label, dose-escalation trial</entry><entry>Silybin phosphatidylcholine;
3 g/d in 3 divided doses;
oral (powder mixed in applesauce)
</entry><entry>3; 3; none</entry><entry>No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044170" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose-limiting</GlossaryTermRef> toxicity was identified</entry><entry>2D</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry>Viral hepatitis B </entry><entry>Controlled, randomized trial</entry><entry>Silymarin;
210 mg/d; oral
</entry><entry>52<Superscript>d</Superscript>; 20-silymarin, 20-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045571" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">misoprostol</GlossaryTermRef>; 12</entry><entry>Silymarin did not have an effect on the course of disease, but misoprostol reduced the degree of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatocyte</GlossaryTermRef> damage during the course of the disease</entry><entry>1iiDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="6"/></entry><entry>Viral or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcoholic</GlossaryTermRef> hepatitis </entry><entry>Phase II, randomized, open trial</entry><entry>Silybin and phosphatidylcholine; 80 mg twice/d, 120 mg twice/d, or 120 mg 3 times/d;
oral
</entry><entry>60<Superscript>c</Superscript>; 60; 0</entry><entry>Reduction in ALT and gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase</entry><entry>1iiDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry><entry>Chronic hepatitis C </entry><entry>Randomized, controlled trial</entry><entry>Silymarin; no dose listed;
oral
</entry><entry>1145; 195; 772</entry><entry>Decreased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef>, liver pain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anorexia</GlossaryTermRef>, and muscle and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">joint</GlossaryTermRef> pain</entry><entry>1iiC</entry></Row><Row><entry> <Reference refidx="20"/></entry><entry>HCV nonresponder patients</entry><entry>Nonrandomized, controlled trial</entry><entry>Silibinin; 
10 mg/kg/d;
IV
</entry><entry>16; 16; 0 (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protocol</GlossaryTermRef> 1) and 20; 20; 0 (protocol 2)</entry><entry>Increased antiviral effect with silibinin when antiviral therapy began after silibinin was started</entry><entry>2D</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="11"/></entry><entry>Cirrhosis </entry><entry>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin; 
140 mg/d;
oral
</entry><entry>170; 87; 83</entry><entry>Decrease in 
SGOT and SGPT in silymarin-treated group</entry><entry>1iB</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>Diabetic patients with cirrhosis </entry><entry>Controlled, randomized trial</entry><entry>Silymarin;
600 mg (200 mg 3 times/d);
oral
</entry><entry>60; 30; 30</entry><entry>Decrease in 
SGOT and SGPT in silymarin-treated group</entry><entry>1iiDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="12"/></entry><entry>Alcohol-induced cirrhosis </entry><entry>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin; 
450 mg (150 mg 3 times/d); oral
</entry><entry>60<Superscript>f</Superscript>; 24; 25</entry><entry>No significant differences in liver function tests</entry><entry>1iDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="8"/></entry><entry>Alcohol-induced cirrhosis </entry><entry>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin;
450 mg (150 mg 3 times/d);
oral
</entry><entry>200<Superscript>e</Superscript>; 58; 67</entry><entry>No significant differences in liver function tests</entry><entry>1iB</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="10"/></entry><entry>Primary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748975" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biliary cirrhosis</GlossaryTermRef> </entry><entry>Nonrandomized, pilot clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin;
420 mg (140 mg 3 times/d);
oral
</entry><entry>27; 27; 0</entry><entry>No significant differences in liver function tests</entry><entry>2C</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="15"/></entry><entry>Prevention of drug-induced hepatic damage </entry><entry>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin;
800 mg (divided in 2 doses);
oral
</entry><entry>60; 15 psychotropic drug + silymarin; 15 silymarin alone; 15 psychotropic drug + placebo; 15 placebo alone</entry><entry>Silymarin effective at reducing  ALT and AST levels when psychotropic drug use was suspended</entry><entry>1iC</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="2"/></entry><entry>Children with ALL experiencing elevated LFTs </entry><entry>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical trial</entry><entry>Silibinin and soy phosphatidylcholine;
dose ranges: 15–20 kg = 80 mg/d; 21–40 kg = 160 mg/d; 41–60 kg = 240 mg/d; 61–70 kg = 320 mg/d;
oral</entry><entry>50; 24; 26</entry><entry>Significant decrease in AST; trend towards reduction in ALT</entry><entry>1iDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col01"><Strong>Prevention or Treatment of Non-Liver Disease</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Reference</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Condition or Cancer Type</Strong>  </entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Trial Design</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Route of Administration and Dose</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)<Superscript>a</Superscript></Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Results</Strong> </entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>Level of Evidence Score</Strong><Superscript>g</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>Radiation therapy–associated mucositis </entry><entry>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin;
420 mg (140 mg 3 times/d);
oral
</entry><entry>30; 13; 14</entry><entry>Lower mucositis scores</entry><entry>1iC</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="3"/></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> </entry><entry>Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin;
570 mg (190 mg 3 times/d);
oral
</entry><entry>37; 19; 18</entry><entry>Increased QOL, decreased low-density lipoproteins, decreased total cholesterol, and increased selenium levels</entry><entry>1iC</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="5"/></entry><entry>Breast cancer </entry><entry>Nonrandomized, observational clinical trial</entry><entry>Silymarin (Silybum marianum, content 0.25%); topical</entry><entry>101; 51; 50</entry><entry>Decreased dermatitis</entry><entry>2C</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_27_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_27_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="23757319">Siegel AB, Narayan R, Rodriguez R, et al.: A phase I dose-finding study of silybin phosphatidylcholine (milk thistle) in patients with advanced hepatocellular carcinoma. Integr Cancer Ther 13 (1): 46-53, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="20014183">Ladas EJ, Kroll DJ, Oberlies NH, et al.: A randomized, controlled, double-blind, pilot study of milk thistle for the treatment of hepatotoxicity in childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL). Cancer 116 (2): 506-13, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="21048810">Vidlar A, Vostalova J, Ulrichova J, et al.: The safety and efficacy of a silymarin and selenium combination in men after radical prostatectomy - a six month placebo-controlled double-blind clinical trial. Biomed Pap Med Fac Univ Palacky Olomouc Czech Repub 154 (3): 239-44, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27555604">Elyasi S, Hosseini S, Niazi Moghadam MR, et al.: Effect of Oral Silymarin Administration on Prevention of Radiotherapy Induced Mucositis: A Randomized, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial. Phytother Res 30 (11): 1879-1885, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21786113">Becker-Schiebe M, Mengs U, Schaefer M, et al.: Topical use of a silymarin-based preparation to prevent radiodermatitis : results of a prospective study in breast cancer patients. Strahlenther Onkol 187 (8): 485-91, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Vailati A, Aristia L, Sozzé E, et al.: Randomized open study of the dose-effect relationship of a short course of IdB 1016 in patients with viral or alcoholic hepatitis. Fitoterapia  64 (3), 219-28, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="6753109" MedlineID="83040974">Salmi HA, Sarna S: Effect of silymarin on chemical, functional, and morphological alterations of the liver. A double-blind controlled study. Scand J Gastroenterol 17 (4): 517-21, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9566830" MedlineID="98226482">Parés A, Planas R, Torres M, et al.: Effects of silymarin in alcoholic patients with cirrhosis of the liver: results of a controlled, double-blind, randomized and multicenter trial. J Hepatol 28 (4): 615-21, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9356866" MedlineID="98019714">Flisiak R, Prokopowicz D: Effect of misoprostol on the course of viral hepatitis B. Hepatogastroenterology 44 (17): 1419-25, 1997 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="11050036" MedlineID="20504241">Angulo P, Patel T, Jorgensen RA, et al.: Silymarin in the treatment of patients with primary biliary cirrhosis with a suboptimal response to ursodeoxycholic acid. Hepatology 32 (5): 897-900, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2671116" MedlineID="89360424">Ferenci P, Dragosics B, Dittrich H, et al.: Randomized controlled trial of silymarin treatment in patients with cirrhosis of the liver. J Hepatol 9 (1): 105-13, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11841050" MedlineID="21824730">Lucena MI, Andrade RJ, de la Cruz JP, et al.: Effects of silymarin MZ-80 on oxidative stress in patients with alcoholic cirrhosis. Results of a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical study. Int J Clin Pharmacol Ther 40 (1): 2-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="9126802" MedlineID="97271957">Velussi M, Cernigoi AM, De Monte A, et al.: Long-term (12 months) treatment with an anti-oxidant drug (silymarin) is effective on hyperinsulinemia, exogenous insulin need and malondialdehyde levels in cirrhotic diabetic patients. J Hepatol 26 (4): 871-9, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="18157835">Seeff LB, Curto TM, Szabo G, et al.: Herbal product use by persons enrolled in the hepatitis C Antiviral Long-Term Treatment Against Cirrhosis (HALT-C) Trial. Hepatology 47 (2): 605-12, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="15">Palasciano G, Portincasa P, Palmieri V, et al.: The effect of silymarin on plasma levels of malon-dialdehyde in patients receiving long-term treatment with psychotropic drugs. Current Therapeutic Research  55 (5): 537-45.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="353464" MedlineID="78223071">Magliulo E, Gagliardi B, Fiori GP: [Results of a double blind study on the effect of silymarin in the treatment of acute viral hepatitis, carried out at two medical centres (author's transl)] Med Klin 73 (28-29): 1060-5, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="21083592">Freedman ND, Curto TM, Morishima C, et al.: Silymarin use and liver disease progression in the Hepatitis C Antiviral Long-Term Treatment against Cirrhosis trial. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 33 (1): 127-37, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="17241377">Azzam HS, Goertz C, Fritts M, et al.: Natural products and chronic hepatitis C virus. Liver Int 27 (1): 17-25, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="17484885">Polyak SJ, Morishima C, Shuhart MC, et al.: Inhibition of T-cell inflammatory cytokines, hepatocyte NF-kappaB signaling, and HCV infection by standardized Silymarin. Gastroenterology 132 (5): 1925-36, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="18771667">Ferenci P, Scherzer TM, Kerschner H, et al.: Silibinin is a potent antiviral agent in patients with chronic hepatitis C not responding to pegylated interferon/ribavirin therapy. Gastroenterology 135 (5): 1561-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="19841158">Hawke RL, Schrieber SJ, Soule TA, et al.: Silymarin ascending multiple oral dosing phase I study in noncirrhotic patients with chronic hepatitis C. J Clin Pharmacol 50 (4): 434-49, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="22797645">Fried MW, Navarro VJ, Afdhal N, et al.: Effect of silymarin (milk thistle) on liver disease in patients with chronic hepatitis C unsuccessfully treated with interferon therapy: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA 308 (3): 274-82, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="23">Albrecht M, Frerick H, Kuhn U, et al.: Therapy of toxic liver pathologies with Legalon®. Z Klin Med  47: 87-92, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="6862461" MedlineID="83236428">Hruby K, Csomos G, Fuhrmann M, et al.: Chemotherapy of Amanita phalloides poisoning with intravenous silibinin. Hum Toxicol 2 (2): 183-95, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="12475187" MedlineID="22362747">Enjalbert F, Rapior S, Nouguier-Soulé J, et al.: Treatment of amatoxin poisoning: 20-year retrospective analysis. J Toxicol Clin Toxicol 40 (6): 715-57, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="23278124">Moayedi B, Gharagozloo M, Esmaeil N, et al.: A randomized double-blind, placebo-controlled study of therapeutic effects of silymarin in β-thalassemia major patients receiving desferrioxamine. Eur J Haematol 90 (3): 202-9, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_29"><Title>Adverse Effects</Title><Para id="_30"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Human studies</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340936" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">silymarin</GlossaryTermRef> have shown minimal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> in multiple large, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285982" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blinded</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322881" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef> studies. Silymarin is well tolerated, with only rare reports of a mild <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laxative</GlossaryTermRef> effect. Mild allergic reactions have been seen at high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> (&gt;1,500 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/day), although the details of these allergic reactions were not reported.<Reference refidx="1"/> A case report from Australia described a reaction to a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">milk thistle</GlossaryTermRef> extract that included intermittent episodes of sweating, abdominal cramping, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>, and weakness.<Reference refidx="2"/> All symptoms resolved when the silymarin was discontinued. The authors suggested that the capsules were contaminated; the type of contamination was unknown.</Para><Para id="_46">According to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">German Commission E</GlossaryTermRef>, there are no reported <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> with milk thistle when the recommended doses are used. Rare cases of milk thistle producing a laxative effect have been reported. Human studies have reported stomach upset, heartburn, and transient headaches; however, none of these symptoms were attributed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplementation</GlossaryTermRef> with milk thistle, and supplementation was not discontinued.<Reference refidx="3"/> One human dosing study reported  nausea, heartburn, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044200" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dyspepsia</GlossaryTermRef> in patients treated with 160 mg/day, dyspepsia in patients treated with 240 mg/day, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postprandial</GlossaryTermRef> nausea and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372931" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meteorism</GlossaryTermRef> in patients treated with 360 mg/day. None of these side effects were dose related.</Para><Para id="_47">Silymarin has been well tolerated in high doses. Silymarin has been used in pregnant women with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046337" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrahepatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373083" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cholestasis</GlossaryTermRef> at doses of 560 mg/day for 16 days,       with no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> to the patient or the fetus.<Reference refidx="4"/> The published data on silymarin use in children focuses on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> doses of 20 to 50 mg/kg of body weight for mushroom poisoning.<Reference refidx="5"/> Silymarin has also proved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044509" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nontoxic</GlossaryTermRef> in rats and mice when administered in doses as high as 5,000 mg/kg of body weight. Rats and dogs have received silymarin at doses of 50  to 2,500 mg/kg of body weight for a 12-month period. Investigations, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372938" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmortem</GlossaryTermRef> analyses, showed no evidence of toxicity.</Para><Para id="_48">It is not known whether milk thistle may reduce, enhance, or have no impact on the effectiveness of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. <ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">In vitro</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName> studies show that silymarin decreases the components of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytochrome P450 enzyme system</GlossaryTermRef>, which is involved in the clearance of certain chemotherapy drugs.<Reference refidx="6"/> However, the dose at which inhibition is observed is high and not achieved with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> intake of silymarin.<Reference refidx="7"/> One study investigated the effects of silymarin on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetics</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635811" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">irinotecan</GlossaryTermRef>.  Oral administration of milk thistle (200 mg, a clinically relevant dose, 3 times per day) had no significant effects on the pharmacokinetics of irinotecan.  The authors concluded that  the recommended doses of milk thistle are too low to affect activity of CYP3A4 or UGT1A1 enzyme pathways.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_100">Theoretically, milk thistle may also interact adversely with chemotherapy drugs that exert their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic</GlossaryTermRef> effects through the generation of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044030" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">free radicals</GlossaryTermRef>. Silymarin and its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolite</GlossaryTermRef> inhibit  p-glycoprotein–mediated cellular efflux, leading to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330176" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">potentiation</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef> cytotoxicity.<Reference refidx="9"/> No trials have been performed to support or negate these theoretical considerations. No effects on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045520" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">indinavir</GlossaryTermRef> and alcohol pharmacokinetics have been observed. Enhancement of the antiarrhythmic effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642962" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">amiodarone</GlossaryTermRef> in rats has been observed.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">PDR® for Herbal Medicines™. 2nd ed. Medical Economics, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10092919" MedlineID="99192879">An adverse reaction to the herbal medication milk thistle (Silybum marianum). Adverse Drug Reactions Advisory Committee. Med J Aust 170 (5): 218-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Vailati A, Aristia L, Sozzé E, et al.: Randomized open study of the dose-effect relationship of a short course of IdB 1016 in patients with viral or alcoholic hepatitis. Fitoterapia  64 (3), 219-28, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6927150" MedlineID="85191607">Hernández R, Nazar E: [Effect of silymarin in intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy (preliminary communication)] Rev Chil Obstet Ginecol 47 (1): 22-9, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="6862461" MedlineID="83236428">Hruby K, Csomos G, Fuhrmann M, et al.: Chemotherapy of Amanita phalloides poisoning with intravenous silibinin. Hum Toxicol 2 (2): 183-95, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11038151" MedlineID="20493197">Venkataramanan R, Ramachandran V, Komoroski BJ, et al.: Milk thistle, a herbal supplement, decreases the activity of CYP3A4 and uridine diphosphoglucuronosyl transferase in human hepatocyte cultures. Drug Metab Dispos 28 (11): 1270-3, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="12410543" MedlineID="22297939">Zuber R, Modrianský M, Dvorák Z, et al.: Effect of silybin and its congeners on human liver microsomal cytochrome P450 activities. Phytother Res 16 (7): 632-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="16278402">van Erp NP, Baker SD, Zhao M, et al.: Effect of milk thistle (Silybum marianum) on the pharmacokinetics of irinotecan. Clin Cancer Res 11 (21): 7800-6, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15916450">Hu Z, Yang X, Ho PC, et al.: Herb-drug interactions: a literature review. Drugs 65 (9): 1239-82, 2005.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Milk Thistle</Title><Para id="_51">To assist readers in evaluating the results of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human studies</GlossaryTermRef> of integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies for cancer, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever possible. To qualify for a level of evidence analysis, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_52" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Be published in a peer-reviewed scientific journal.</ListItem><ListItem>Report on    <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> outcome or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Describe clinical findings in sufficient detail for a meaningful evaluation to be made.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_53">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and scientific strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score. For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis of CAM treatments for cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_54">Given the limited amount of human data, the use of milk thistle/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340936" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">silymarin</GlossaryTermRef> as a treatment for cancer patients cannot be recommended outside the context of well-designed clinical trials.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_24"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (02/17/2022)</Title><Para id="_25">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_236">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000347008#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/milk-thistle-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of milk thistle in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Milk Thistle. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/milk-thistle-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/milk-thistle-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389223]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2003-12-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2022-02-17</DateLastModified></Summary>
