<Summary id="CDR0000350260" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062700"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Small intestine cancer treatment involves surgery when possible, and sometimes radiation therapy and chemotherapy. Learn more about the treatment options for newly diagnosed and recurrent small intestine cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/small-intestine/patient/small-intestine-treatment-pdq">Small Intestine Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/small-intestine/hp/small-intestine-treatment-pdq">Small Intestine Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038736">small intestine cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_188">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of small intestine cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_189">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>small intestine cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Small Intestine Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Small Intestine Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Small Intestine Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Small  Intestine Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Small  intestine cancer is a rare disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form in the tissues of the small  intestine.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef> is part of the
		  body’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046446" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive system</GlossaryTermRef>, which also includes the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>,
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">large
		  intestine</GlossaryTermRef>.  The
		  digestive system removes and processes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>,
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carbohydrates</GlossaryTermRef>, fats, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef>, and water) from foods and helps pass waste
		  material out of the body. The small intestine is a long tube that connects the stomach to the large intestine.   It folds many times to fit inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000751388" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of the small intestine showing the duodenum, jejunum, and ileum. Also shown are the stomach, appendix, large intestine, and rectum." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_184"><Caption language="en">The small intestine is a long tube-like organ that connects the stomach to the large intestine. The small intestine includes the duodenum, jejunum, and ileum.
</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_155"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_156">There are  five types of small intestine cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_157">The types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> found in the small intestine are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044904" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>. This summary discusses adenocarcinoma and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046027" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leiomyosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> (a type of  sarcoma). </Para><Para id="_130">Adenocarcinoma starts in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glandular</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> in the lining of the small intestine and is the most common type of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Most of these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef> occur in the part of the small intestine near the stomach. They may grow and block the intestine.</Para><Para id="_133">Leiomyosarcoma starts in the smooth muscle cells of the small intestine. Most of these tumors occur in the part of the small intestine near the large intestine. </Para><Para id="_158">For more information on small intestine cancer, see the following: 
</Para><ItemizedList id="_127" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258021" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000658500" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/patient/gist-treatment-pdq">Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_8">Diet and health history can affect the risk of developing small  intestine cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_9">Anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease is called 
         a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>.  Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop small intestine cancer, and it will develop in some people who don't have any known risk factors. Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk.  Risk factors for small intestine cancer include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_10" Style="bullet"> 
    <ListItem>Eating a  high-fat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045661" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Crohn disease</GlossaryTermRef>. 

</ListItem><ListItem>Having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000377726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">celiac disease</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem> Having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">familial adenomatous polyposis</GlossaryTermRef> (FAP).</ListItem> 
     
     
     
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_16">Signs and symptoms of small  intestine cancer include unexplained weight loss and abdominal pain.</KeyPoint><Para id="_17">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by small  intestine cancer or by other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>.  Check with your doctor if you have any of the  following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_18" Style="bullet"> 
    <ListItem>Pain or cramps in the middle of the abdomen.</ListItem><ListItem>Weight loss with no known reason.
</ListItem><ListItem>A lump in the abdomen.
</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046605" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stool</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
     
     
     
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Tests that examine the small intestine are used to diagnose and stage small  intestine cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_163"> Procedures
		  that make pictures of the small intestine and the area around it help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> small intestine cancer and show how far the cancer has spread. The process used
		  to find out if cancer cells have spread within and around the small intestine is
		  called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_164"> 
In order to plan treatment, it is important to know  the type of small intestine cancer and whether the tumor can be removed by
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>. Tests and procedures
		  to detect, diagnose, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> small intestine cancer are usually done at the same
		  time. In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures: </Para><ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390293" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Liver function tests</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>.  A higher than normal amount of a substance can  be a sign of liver disease that may be caused by small intestine cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  A procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas. There are different types of endoscopy:<ItemizedList id="_183" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000470253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Upper endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure to look at the inside of the esophagus, stomach, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">duodenum</GlossaryTermRef> (first part of the small intestine, near the stomach). An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscope</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted  through the mouth and into the esophagus, stomach, and duodenum.  An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000749900" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Capsule endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure to look at the inside of the small intestine. A capsule that is about the size of a large pill and contains a light and a tiny wireless camera is swallowed by the patient. The capsule travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive tract</GlossaryTermRef>, including the small intestine, and sends many pictures of the inside of the digestive tract to a recorder that is worn around the waist or over the shoulder. The pictures are sent from the recorder to a computer and viewed by the doctor who checks for signs of cancer. The capsule passes out of the body during a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651179" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel movement</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000749903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Double balloon endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure to look at the inside of the small intestine. A special instrument made up of two tubes (one inside the other) is inserted through the mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> and into the small intestine. The inside  tube (an endoscope with a light and lens for viewing) is moved through part of the small intestine and a balloon at the end of it is inflated to keep the endoscope in place. Next, the outer tube is moved through the small intestine to reach the end of the endoscope, and a balloon at the end of the outer tube is inflated to keep it in place. Then, the balloon at the end of the endoscope is deflated and the endoscope is moved through the next part of the small intestine. These steps are repeated many times as the tubes move through the small intestine. The doctor is able to see the inside of the small intestine through the endoscope and use a tool to remove samples of abnormal tissue. The tissue samples are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer. This procedure may be done if the results of a capsule endoscopy are abnormal. This procedure is also called double balloon enteroscopy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Laparotomy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgical</GlossaryTermRef> procedure in which an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> (cut) is made in the wall of the abdomen to check the inside of the abdomen for signs of disease. The size of the incision depends on the reason the laparotomy is being done. Sometimes organs or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> are removed or tissue samples are taken and checked under a microscope for signs of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed   under a microscope to check for signs of cancer.  This may be done during an endoscopy or laparotomy.  The  sample is checked by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to see if it contains cancer cells. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Upper GI series</GlossaryTermRef> with small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef> follow-through</Strong>: A series of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> of the esophagus, stomach, and  small bowel.  The patient drinks a liquid that contains <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000739782" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">barium</GlossaryTermRef> (a silver-white <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metallic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compound</GlossaryTermRef>).  The liquid coats the esophagus, stomach, and  small bowel.  X-rays are  taken at different times as the barium travels through the upper <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">GI tract</GlossaryTermRef> and small bowel.  </ListItem>
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>:  A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an x-ray machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem>
    
    
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_24">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_25">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on the following:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_153" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The type of small intestine cancer. </ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer is in the inner lining of the small intestine only or has spread into or beyond the wall of the small intestine.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer has spread to other places in the body, such as the lymph nodes, liver, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef> (tissue that lines the wall of the abdomen and covers most of the organs in the abdomen).</ListItem><ListItem> Whether the cancer can be completely removed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_29"><Title>Stages of Small  Intestine Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_134"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_31">Tests and procedures to stage small intestine cancer are  usually done at the same time as diagnosis. </KeyPoint><Para id="_161"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Staging</GlossaryTermRef> is used to find out how far the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> has spread, but treatment decisions are not based on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. See the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000350260#_19" url="/types/small-intestine/patient/small-intestine-treatment-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef> section for a description of tests and procedures used to detect, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef>, and stage <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef> cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_174"><KeyPoint id="_175">There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_174_md_69">Cancer can spread through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_174_md_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.
</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_185"><KeyPoint id="_186">Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_185_md_66">When cancer spreads to another part of the body, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer cells break away from where they began (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>) and travel through the lymph system or blood.</Para><ItemizedList id="_185_md_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer gets into the lymph system, travels through the lymph vessels, and forms a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer gets into the blood, travels through the blood vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_187">The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if  small intestine cancer spreads to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, the cancer cells in the liver are actually small intestine cancer cells. The disease is metastatic small intestine cancer, not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><EmbeddedVideo id="_192" ref="CDR0000787719" hosting="youtube" unique_id="fQwar_-QdiQ" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>metastasis: how cancer spreads</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Many cancer deaths are caused when cancer moves from the original tumor and spreads to other tissues and organs. This is called metastatic cancer. This animation shows how cancer cells travel from the place in the body where they first formed to other parts of the body.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_34"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_125">Small intestine cancer is  grouped according to whether or not the tumor can be completely removed by surgery.</KeyPoint><Para id="_160">Treatment depends on whether the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> can be removed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> and if the cancer is being treated as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> or is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_196"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_197">Small intestine cancer can recur (come back) after it has been treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_198">The cancer may come back in the small intestine or in other parts of the body.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_54"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_55">There are different types of treatment for patients with small  intestine cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_56">Different types of treatments are available for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small  intestine</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.  A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the   standard treatment,  the new treatment may become the standard treatment. Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_63">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_64"><KeyPoint id="_65">
     Surgery
    </KeyPoint><Para id="_66"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> is the most common treatment of small intestine cancer.
			 One of the following types of surgery may be done:</Para><ItemizedList id="_139" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Resection</GlossaryTermRef>:  Surgery to remove part or all of an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> that contains cancer. The resection may include the small intestine and nearby organs (if the cancer has spread). The doctor may remove the section of the  small intestine that contains cancer and perform an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046534" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anastomosis</GlossaryTermRef> (joining the cut ends of the intestine
				together). The doctor will usually remove <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> near the small intestine and examine them under
				a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> to see whether they contain cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046498" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bypass</GlossaryTermRef>: Surgery to allow food in the small intestine to go around (bypass) a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> that is blocking the intestine but cannot be removed.
  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_67">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some patients may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> after surgery to kill any cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> that are left. Treatment given after the surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_68"><KeyPoint id="_69">
     Radiation therapy
    </KeyPoint><Para id="_70">Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para><Para id="_191">External radiation therapy is used to treat small intestine cancer. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_71"><KeyPoint id="_72">
     Chemotherapy
    </KeyPoint><Para id="_73"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.   When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_86"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_87">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials. </KeyPoint><Para id="_173">This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in clinical trials. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_77"><KeyPoint id="_78">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_79"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment that uses the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to fight cancer.  Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the body's natural defenses against cancer.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_91"><KeyPoint id="_92">Radiation therapy with radiosensitizers
</KeyPoint><Para id="_93"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiosensitizers</GlossaryTermRef> are drugs that make tumor cells more sensitive to radiation therapy. Combining radiation therapy with radiosensitizers may kill more tumor cells.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_193"><KeyPoint id="_194">Treatment for small intestine cancer may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_193_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_176"><KeyPoint id="_177">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_176_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_176_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_176_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_178"><KeyPoint id="_179">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_178_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_178_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_180"><KeyPoint id="_181">Follow-up tests may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_180_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_180_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_199"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038744">small intestine adenocarcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Small Intestine Adenocarcinoma</Title><Para id="_200">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000350260#_62" url="/types/small-intestine/patient/small-intestine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_201">When possible, treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small  intestine</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> will be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> and some of the normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> around it.</Para><Para id="_202">Treatment of small  intestine adenocarcinoma that cannot be removed by surgery may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_141" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046498" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bypass</GlossaryTermRef> the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve the patient's  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of radiation therapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiosensitizers</GlossaryTermRef>, with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of new anticancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_199_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_203"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038746">small intestine leiomyosarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Small  Intestine Leiomyosarcoma</Title><Para id="_204">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000350260#_62" url="/types/small-intestine/patient/small-intestine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_205">When possible, treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046027" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leiomyosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> will be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> and some of the normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> around it.</Para><Para id="_206">Treatment of small  intestine leiomyosarcoma that cannot be removed by surgery may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_146" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery (to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046498" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bypass</GlossaryTermRef> the tumor) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery, radiation therapy, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>  as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of new anticancer drugs.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_203_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_207"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038757">recurrent small intestine cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Small  Intestine Cancer</Title><Para id="_208">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000350260#_62" url="/types/small-intestine/patient/small-intestine-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_209">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> that has spread to other parts of the body is usually a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of new anticancer drugs or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_210">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally</GlossaryTermRef> recurrent small  intestine cancer may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_119" Style="bullet">
   <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem>
   <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of radiation therapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiosensitizers</GlossaryTermRef>, with or without chemotherapy.</ListItem>
   
   
   
  </ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_207_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_168"><Title>To Learn More About Small Intestine Cancer</Title><Para id="_169">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  small intestine cancer, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_211" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/small-intestine/">Small Intestine Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_168_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_168_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of small intestine cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Small Intestine Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/small-intestine/patient/small-intestine-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/small-intestine/patient/small-intestine-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389461]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062902"/><DateFirstPublished>2004-03-24</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2023-05-17</DateLastModified></Summary>
