<Summary id="CDR0000373791" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>The treatment of cancer may cause health problems (late effects) for childhood cancer survivors months or years after successful treatment has ended. Get information about the long-term physical, psychological and social effects of treatment for childhood cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-hp-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041394">long-term effects secondary to cancer therapy in children</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_965">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the late effects of treatment for childhood cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_966">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Childhood cancer late effects</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Late effects childhood cancer survivors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Late effects childhood cancer treatment</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Late effects childhood cancers</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>long-term effects secondary to cancer therapy in children</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_387"><Title>General Information About Late Effects</Title><SummarySection id="_485"><KeyPoint id="_486">Late effects are health problems that occur months or years after cancer treatment has ended.</KeyPoint><Para id="_566">Cancer treatments may harm the body's organs, tissues, or bones and cause health problems later in life. They may include physical, mental, and social problems and second cancers. These health problems are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_956">Treatments that may cause late effects include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_944" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_395">Doctors are studying the late effects caused by cancer treatment. They are working to  improve cancer treatments and stop or lessen late effects. While most late effects are not life-threatening, they may cause serious problems that  affect health and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_391"><KeyPoint id="_392">Late effects in childhood cancer survivors affect the body and mind.</KeyPoint><Para id="_520">Late effects in childhood cancer survivors may  affect:</Para><ItemizedList id="_393" Style="bullet"><ListItem>organs, tissues, and body function</ListItem><ListItem>growth and development</ListItem><ListItem>mood, feelings, and actions </ListItem><ListItem>thinking, learning, and memory</ListItem><ListItem>social and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef> adjustment</ListItem><ListItem>risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">second cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_523"><KeyPoint id="_524">There are three important factors that affect the risk of late effects. </KeyPoint><Para id="_533">Many childhood cancer survivors will have late effects. The risk of late effects depends on factors related to the tumor, treatment, and patient. These include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_534" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Cancer-related factors</Strong><ItemizedList id="_535" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>type of cancer</ListItem><ListItem>the organs and tissues that were affected by the cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Treatment-related factors</Strong> <ItemizedList id="_536" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>type of radiation therapy, part of the body treated, and dose</ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy type, dose, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">schedule</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>type of surgery</ListItem><ListItem>stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem>how the use of two or more treatments at the same time affects the body</ListItem><ListItem>whether transplanted stem cells attack the body's healthy cells, a condition known as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">graft-versus-host disease</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Patient-related factors</Strong><ItemizedList id="_12" Style="dash"><ListItem>the childhood cancer survivor's sex</ListItem> 
    <ListItem>health problems the childhood cancer survivor had before being diagnosed with cancer or developed during or after treatment</ListItem><ListItem>the age and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">developmental stage</GlossaryTermRef> when diagnosed and treated for childhood cancer</ListItem><ListItem>length of time since diagnosis and treatment</ListItem><ListItem>changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef> levels</ListItem><ListItem>the ability of healthy tissue affected by cancer treatment to repair itself</ListItem><ListItem>certain changes in the childhood cancer survivor's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> or a family history of cancer or other conditions</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000806201" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">socioeconomic status</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>health habits</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_381"><KeyPoint id="_382">The chance of having late effects increases over time.</KeyPoint><Para id="_383">New treatments for childhood cancer have decreased the number of deaths from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Because childhood cancer survivors are living longer, they are having more late effects after cancer treatment.  Survivors may not live as long as people who did not have cancer. The most common causes of death in childhood cancer survivors are:</Para><ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet"> 
    <ListItem>the primary cancer comes back</ListItem> 
    <ListItem>a second (different) primary cancer forms</ListItem> 
    <ListItem>heart and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> damage</ListItem> 
   </ItemizedList><Para id="_20"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Studies</GlossaryTermRef> of the causes of late effects have led to changes in treatment. This has improved the quality of life for cancer survivors and helps <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> illness and death from late effects.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><KeyPoint id="_28">Regular follow-up care is very important for survivors of childhood cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_567">Regular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> by health professionals who are trained to find and treat late effects is important for the long-term health of childhood cancer survivors. Follow-up care will be different for each person who has been treated for cancer. The care plan the cancer survivor receives will depend on their general health and health habits, the type of cancer, the type of treatment, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> factors, and other medical conditions. Follow-up care includes checking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of late effects and health education on how to prevent or lessen late effects.</Para><Para id="_568">It is important that childhood cancer survivors have an exam at least once a year. The exams should be done by a health professional  who knows the survivor's risk for late effects and can recognize the early signs of late effects. Blood and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging tests</GlossaryTermRef> may also be done.</Para><Para id="_32">Long-term follow-up may improve the health and quality of life for cancer survivors. It also helps doctors study the late effects of cancer treatments so that safer therapies for newly diagnosed children may be developed. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_526"><KeyPoint id="_527">Good health habits are also important for survivors of childhood cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_528">The quality of life for cancer survivors may be improved by behaviors that promote health and well-being. These include a healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef>, exercise, and regular medical and dental check-ups. These self-care behaviors are especially important for cancer survivors because of their risk of health problems related to treatment. Healthy behaviors may make late effects less severe and lower the risk of other diseases.</Para><Para id="_529">Avoiding behaviors that are damaging to health is also important. Smoking, excess alcohol use,  illegal drug use, not following good sun protection measures, or not being physically active may worsen organ damage related to treatment and may increase the risk of second cancers.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><Title>Second Cancers</Title><SummarySection id="_37"><KeyPoint id="_38">Childhood cancer survivors have an increased risk of a second cancer later in life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_484">A different <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary cancer</GlossaryTermRef> that occurs at least two months after cancer treatment ends is called a second cancer. A second cancer may occur months or years after  treatment is completed. The type of second cancer that occurs depends in part on the original type of cancer and the cancer treatment. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Benign tumors</GlossaryTermRef> (not cancer) may also occur. </Para><Para id="_517">Second cancers that may occur after cancer treatment include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_518" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelodysplastic syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solid tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_959">Myelodysplastic syndrome and acute myeloid leukemia may appear less than 10 years after a primary cancer diagnosis of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000427310" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system (CNS) tumor</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef>  and treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> that included:</Para><ItemizedList id="_960" Style="bullet"><ListItem>an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alkylating agent</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclophosphamide</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ifosfamide</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046603" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mechlorethamine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melphalan</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045410" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">busulfan</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045976" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carmustine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lomustine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046048" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chlorambucil</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045260" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dacarbazine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723879" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">topoisomerase II inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> agent, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">etoposide</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1000">Children treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> without chemotherapy may also have an increased risk of second acute myeloid leukemia.</Para><Para id="_957">Solid tumors that may appear more than 10 years after a primary cancer diagnosis and treatment include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_958" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Survivors of childhood, adolescent, and young adult cancers  who received high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> radiation therapy to the chest have an increased risk of developing breast cancer. Certain chemotherapy drugs, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alkylating agents</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anthracyclines</GlossaryTermRef>, also increase a person's risk of breast cancer. Risk is highest for female survivors of Hodgkin lymphoma, sarcoma, and leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thyroid cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Thyroid cancer may occur after radiation therapy to the neck for Hodgkin lymphoma, acute lymphoblastic leukemia, or brain tumors; after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045855" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive iodine</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for neuroblastoma; after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> as part of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef>; or after chemotherapy alone.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef>. Brain tumors may occur after radiation therapy to the head and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> using methotrexate for a primary brain tumor or for cancer that has spread to the brain or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>, such as acute lymphocytic leukemia or non-Hodgkin lymphoma. When intrathecal chemotherapy using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef> and radiation treatment are given together, the risk of a brain tumor is even higher. </ListItem><ListItem>Bone and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue</GlossaryTermRef> tumors. There is an increased risk of bone and soft tissue tumors after radiation treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hereditary</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046031" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ewing sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, and other cancers of the bone, with risks increasing at higher <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef>. Chemotherapy with anthracyclines or alkylating agents also increases the risk of bone and soft tissue tumors, with risk increasing at higher doses.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. There is an increased risk of lung cancer after radiation treatment to the chest for Hodgkin lymphoma or bone cancer, especially in patients who smoke.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445087" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stomach</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Stomach, liver, or colorectal cancer may occur after receiving radiation therapy to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, chemotherapy, or both. Survivors of Wilms tumor and Hodgkin lymphoma have the highest risk of these second cancers. The risk  increases with higher doses of radiation. There is also an increased risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyps</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046261" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nonmelanoma skin cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046515" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">basal cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046595" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">squamous cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>). There is an increased risk of nonmelanoma skin cancer after radiation treatment, and it usually appears in the area where radiation was given. Being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044472" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">UV radiation</GlossaryTermRef> may increase this risk. Patients who develop nonmelanoma skin cancer after radiation treatment have an increased chance of developing other types of cancers in the future. The risk of basal cell carcinoma is also increased after treatment with chemotherapy drugs, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000615324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vincristine</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000637631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vinblastine</GlossaryTermRef> (called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046156" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vinca alkaloids</GlossaryTermRef>). Survivors of hereditary retinoblastoma may have an increased risk of developing nonmelanoma skin cancer. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Malignant melanoma</GlossaryTermRef>. Malignant melanoma may occur after radiation  or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with alkylating agents and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antimitotic drugs</GlossaryTermRef> (such as vincristine and vinblastine). Survivors of Hodgkin lymphoma,  hereditary retinoblastoma, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046147" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gonadal</GlossaryTermRef> tumors are more likely to be at a higher risk of having malignant melanoma. Malignant melanoma as a second cancer is less common than nonmelanoma skin cancer. Survivors of hereditary retinoblastoma may have an increased risk of developing melanoma.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641672" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Oral</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445040" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laryngeal</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446528" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">salivary gland cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Oral cancer may occur after stem cell transplant with a history of chronic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">graft-versus-host disease</GlossaryTermRef>, radiation therapy, or chemotherapy. Survivors of leukemia, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, Hodgkin lymphoma, and soft tissue sarcoma have the highest risk of oral cancers. Childhood, adolescent, and young adult cancer survivors may also be at increased risk of developing oral cancers related to infection with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human papillomavirus</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Kidney cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. There is an increased risk of kidney cancer after treatment for neuroblastoma, radiation treatment to the middle of the back, or chemotherapy such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carboplatin</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bladder cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and genital cancer. Bladder cancer may occur after chemotherapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclophosphamide</GlossaryTermRef>. Survivors of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766802" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heritable</GlossaryTermRef> retinoblastoma have an increased risk of developing bladder cancer. Female survivors have an increased risk of cancer in the uterus or vulva.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_41"><KeyPoint id="_42"> Certain genetic patterns or syndromes may increase the risk of a second cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_43">Some childhood cancer survivors may have an increased risk of developing a second cancer because they have  a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer, an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef>  cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046322" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Li-Fraumeni syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>, or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutation</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurofibromatosis type 1</GlossaryTermRef>. Problems with the way <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> is repaired in cells and the way anticancer drugs are used by the body may also affect the risk of second cancers.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_542"><KeyPoint id="_543">People who have been treated for cancer need regular screening tests to check for a second cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_544">It is important for people who have been treated for cancer to be checked for a second cancer before <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> appear. This is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> and may help find a second cancer when it is smaller and has not spread. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> tissue or cancer is found early, it may be easier to treat. By the time symptoms appear, cancer may have begun to spread.</Para><Para id="_545">It is important to remember that the doctor does not necessarily think a childhood cancer survivor has cancer if he or she suggests a screening test. Screening tests are given when the cancer survivor has no cancer symptoms.

If a screening test result is abnormal, more tests may be done to find out if there is a second cancer. These are called diagnostic tests.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_546"><KeyPoint id="_547">The kind of test used to screen for a second cancer depends in part on  the kind of cancer treatment the survivors had in the past.</KeyPoint><Para id="_548">Childhood cancer survivors should have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medical history</GlossaryTermRef> done once a year. A physical exam of the body is done to see how healthy the person is and to check for signs of disease, such as lumps, changes in the skin, or anything else that seems unusual. A medical history is taken to learn about the cancer survivor's health habits and past illnesses and treatments.</Para><Para id="_553">Childhood cancer survivors who received radiation therapy may have the following tests and procedures to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skin</GlossaryTermRef>, breast, or colorectal cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_554" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Skin exam</Strong> is when a doctor or nurse checks the skin for bumps or spots that look abnormal in color, size, shape, or texture, especially in the area where radiation was given. 
It is suggested that a skin exam be done once a year to check for signs of skin cancer. The doctor will also provide information about sun protection behaviors to reduce the risk of skin cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Breast self-exam</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an exam of the breast by the patient. The patient carefully feels the breasts and under the arms for lumps or anything else that seems unusual. It is suggested that women treated with a higher dose of radiation therapy to the chest do a monthly breast self-exam beginning at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">puberty</GlossaryTermRef>. Talk to the doctor about when breast self-exams should begin.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304715" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical breast exam</GlossaryTermRef> (CBE)</Strong> is an exam of the breast by a doctor or other health professional. The doctor will carefully feel the breasts and under the arms for lumps or anything else that seems unusual.

It is suggested that women treated with a higher dose of radiation therapy to the chest have a clinical breast exam every year beginning at puberty until age 25. After age 25 or 8 years after radiation treatments end (whichever is first), clinical breast exams are done every 6 months. Talk to the doctor about when clinical breast exams should begin.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mammogram</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> of the breast.  A mammogram may be done in women who had a higher dose of radiation to the chest and who do not have dense breasts.

It is suggested that these women have a mammogram once a year starting 8 years after treatment or at age 25, whichever is later. Talk to the doctor about when mammograms to check for breast cancer should begin.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Breast <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of the breast. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). An MRI may be done in women who had a higher dose of radiation to the chest and who have dense breasts. It is suggested that these women have an MRI once a year starting 8 years after treatment or at age 25, whichever is later. Talk to the doctor about whether an MRI of the breast to check for breast cancer is needed.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> for polyps, abnormal areas, or cancer. A colonoscope  is inserted through the rectum into the colon.  A colonoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a  tool to remove polyps or tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer. It is suggested that childhood cancer survivors who had a higher dose of radiation to the abdomen, pelvis, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef> have a colonoscopy every 5 years. This begins at age 30 or 5 years after treatment ended, whichever is later. Talk to your doctor about when colonoscopies to check for colorectal cancer should begin.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Multitarget <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046605" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stool</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> test</Strong> is a test to collect stool to check for cancer cells. This test may be done every 3 years beginning at age 30 or 5 years after treatment ended.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_44"><Title>Cardiovascular System</Title><SummarySection id="_489"><KeyPoint id="_490">Heart and blood vessel late effects are more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_491">Cardiovascular disease occurs at a younger age in childhood cancer survivors. Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause heart and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessel</GlossaryTermRef> late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_492" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (AML)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> tumors</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_120"><KeyPoint id="_121">Radiation to the chest and certain types of chemotherapy increase the risk of heart and blood vessel late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_480">The risk of health problems involving the heart and blood vessels increases after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_481" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to the chest, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>, brain, neck, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> (TBI) as part of a stem cell transplant. The risk of problems depends on the area of the body that was exposed to radiation, the amount of radiation given, and whether the radiation was given in small or large <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem>Certain types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. Chemotherapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anthracyclines</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000583859" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">daunorubicin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">idarubicin</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000523457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epirubicin</GlossaryTermRef>, and with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045595" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anthraquinones</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045192" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mitoxantrone</GlossaryTermRef> increase the risk of heart and blood vessel problems. The risk of problems depends on the total dose of chemotherapy given and the type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef> used. It also depends on whether treatment with anthracyclines was given to a child younger than 13 years and whether a drug called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572255" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dexrazoxane</GlossaryTermRef> was given during treatment with anthracyclines. Dexrazoxane may lessen heart and blood vessel damage up to 5 years after treatment. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ifosfamide</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclophosphamide</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045339" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">asparaginase</GlossaryTermRef>, and chemotherapy with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045841" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platinum</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carboplatin</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef>, may also cause heart and blood vessel late effects.</ListItem><ListItem>Stem cell transplant.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nephrectomy</GlossaryTermRef> (surgery to remove all or part of a kidney).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_556">Childhood cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> who were treated with both  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the heart or blood vessels and certain types of chemotherapy are at greatest risk. </Para><Para id="_122">Other factors that may also increase the risk of heart and blood vessel late effects include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_123" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Longer time since treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef> or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> for heart disease, such as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of heart disease, having excess body weight, smoking, high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cholesterol</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044911" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diabetes</GlossaryTermRef>. When these risk factors are combined, the risk of late effects is even higher. </ListItem><ListItem>Having lower than normal amounts of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538639" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">growth</GlossaryTermRef>, or sex <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_945">New treatments that decrease the amount of  radiation given, use  lower doses of chemotherapy or less harmful chemotherapy drugs,  and incorporate dexrazoxane may be leading to a lower  risk of heart and blood vessel late effects in childhood cancer survivors.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><KeyPoint id="_46">Late effects that affect the heart and blood vessels may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_479">Childhood cancer survivors who received radiation or certain types of chemotherapy have an increased risk of late effects to the heart and blood vessels and related health problems.  These include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_119" Style="bullet"><ListItem>abnormal heartbeat</ListItem><ListItem>weakened heart muscle</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflamed</GlossaryTermRef> heart or sac around the heart</ListItem><ListItem>damage to  the heart valves</ListItem><ListItem>hardening of the heart <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">arteries</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439400" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coronary artery disease</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045143" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">congestive heart failure</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>high blood pressure</ListItem><ListItem>chest pain or heart attack</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clots</GlossaryTermRef> or one or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">strokes</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000396786" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carotid artery</GlossaryTermRef> disease</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_562"><KeyPoint id="_563">Possible symptoms of heart and blood vessel late effects include trouble breathing and chest pain.

</KeyPoint><Para id="_564">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by heart and blood vessel late effects or by other problems:</Para><ItemizedList id="_565" Style="bullet"><ListItem>trouble breathing, especially when lying down</ListItem><ListItem>heartbeat that is too slow, too fast, or different from the heart's normal rhythm
</ListItem><ListItem>chest pain or pain in the arm or leg</ListItem><ListItem>swelling of the feet, ankles, legs, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>when exposed to cold or having strong emotions, the fingers, toes, ears, or nose become white and then turn blue, and sometimes the fingers will also have pain or tingling</ListItem><ListItem>sudden numbness or weakness of the face, arm, or leg (especially on one side of the body)</ListItem><ListItem>sudden confusion or trouble speaking or understanding speech</ListItem><ListItem>sudden trouble seeing with one or both eyes</ListItem><ListItem>sudden trouble walking or feeling dizzy</ListItem><ListItem>sudden loss of balance or coordination</ListItem><ListItem>sudden severe headache for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>pain, warmth, or redness in one area of the arm or leg, especially the back of the lower leg</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_569">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by heart and blood vessel late effects is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_557"><KeyPoint id="_558">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the heart and blood vessels.

</KeyPoint><Para id="_1001">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_560" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Electrocardiogram (EKG)</Strong> is a recording of the heart's electrical activity to check its rate and rhythm. A number of small pads (electrodes) are placed on the patient's chest, arms, and legs, and are connected by wires to the EKG machine. Heart activity is then recorded as a line graph on paper. Electrical activity that is faster or slower than normal may be a sign of heart disease or damage.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Echocardiogram</Strong> is a procedure in which high-energy sound waves (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef>) are bounced off the heart and nearby tissues or organs and make echoes. A moving picture is made of the heart and heart valves as blood is pumped through the heart.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Ultrasound exam</Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs such as the heart and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. 

</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Magnetic resonance imaging</GlossaryTermRef> (MRI)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). This procedure is done to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clots</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs.  A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is done to check for blood clots. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnetic resonance angiography (MRA)</Strong> uses radio waves and a powerful magnet linked to a computer to create detailed pictures of the blood vessels and blood flow inside the body. A dye may be injected into a vein to make the blood vessels and blood flow easier to see. This may be used to check for blood clots or other blood vessel problems.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lipid</GlossaryTermRef> profile studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of triglycerides, cholesterol, and low- and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol

in the blood.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_570">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of heart and blood vessel late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_840"><KeyPoint id="_841">Health habits that promote a healthy heart and blood vessels are important for survivors of childhood cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_842">Childhood cancer survivors may lower their risk of heart and blood vessel late effects by having a healthy lifestyle, which includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_843" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a healthy weight</ListItem><ListItem>a heart-healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef>, high in vegetables, fruits, whole grains, fish, and poultry, and low in red or processed meats</ListItem><ListItem>regular exercise</ListItem><ListItem>not smoking</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_493"><Title>Central Nervous System</Title><SummarySection id="_503"><KeyPoint id="_504">Brain and spinal cord late effects are more likely to occur after treatment of brain tumors and acute lymphoblastic leukemia.</KeyPoint><Para id="_505">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause brain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_506" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (AML)</ListItem><ListItem>brain and spinal cord tumors</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef>, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_499"><KeyPoint id="_500">Radiation to the brain increases the risk of brain and spinal cord late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_501">The risk of health problems that affect the brain or spinal cord increases after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_502" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> (especially high doses) to the brain or spinal cord or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> given as part of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046144" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraventricular</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy with high-dose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045155" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytarabine</GlossaryTermRef> that can cross the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046504" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood-brain barrier</GlossaryTermRef> (protective lining around the brain) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> given as part of a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem>surgery to remove a tumor on the brain or spinal cord</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_573">When radiation to the brain and intrathecal chemotherapy are given at the same time, the risk of late effects is higher.</Para><Para id="_571">The following may also increase the risk of brain and spinal cord  late effects in childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_572" Style="bullet"><ListItem>where the tumor formed in the brain and spinal cord</ListItem><ListItem>being 5 years old or younger at the time of treatment </ListItem><ListItem>being female</ListItem><ListItem>having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045498" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrocephalus</GlossaryTermRef> and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046579" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">shunt</GlossaryTermRef> placed to remove the extra fluid from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ventricles</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having hearing loss</ListItem><ListItem>having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebellar mutism</GlossaryTermRef> following surgery to remove the  brain tumor</ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stroke</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seizures</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>socioeconomic status</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_494"><KeyPoint id="_495">Late effects that affect the brain and spinal cord may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_496">Childhood cancer survivors who received radiation, certain types of chemotherapy, or surgery to the brain or spinal cord have an increased risk of late effects to the brain and spinal cord and related health problems. A child may develop these problems soon after treatment or years later in adulthood. Brain and spinal cord late effects include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_497" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>headaches that may go away after vomiting</ListItem><ListItem>loss of balance, lack of coordination, or trouble walking</ListItem><ListItem>dizziness</ListItem> <ListItem>seizures</ListItem><ListItem>loss of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046276" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelin</GlossaryTermRef> sheath that covers <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046401" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fibers</GlossaryTermRef> in the brain</ListItem><ListItem>movement <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disorders</GlossaryTermRef> that affect the legs and eyes or the ability to speak and swallow</ListItem><ListItem>nerve damage in the hands or feet</ListItem><ListItem>stroke, with an increased risk for a second stroke for survivors who received radiation to the brain, have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef>, or were older than  40 years  when they had their first stroke</ListItem><ListItem> a small amount of bleeding in the brain (brain microbleeds)</ListItem><ListItem>daytime sleepiness</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045498" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrocephalus</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef> control</ListItem><ListItem>clusters of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> (cavernomas)</ListItem><ListItem>back pain</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_498">Survivors may also have late effects that affect thinking, learning, memory, emotions, and behavior.</Para><Para id="_921">New ways of using more targeted and lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of radiation  to the brain may lessen  the  risk of brain and spinal cord late effects.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_574"><KeyPoint id="_575">Possible symptoms of brain and spinal cord late effects include headaches, loss of coordination, and seizures.</KeyPoint><Para id="_576">These <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by brain and spinal cord late effects or by other problems: 

</Para><ItemizedList id="_577" Style="bullet"><ListItem>trouble speaking or swallowing</ListItem><ListItem>trouble with having the  eyes work together</ListItem><ListItem>numbness, tingling, or weakness in the hands or feet</ListItem><ListItem>being unable to bend the ankle to lift the foot up</ListItem><ListItem>sudden numbness or weakness of the face, arm, or leg (especially on one side of the body)</ListItem><ListItem>unusual sleepiness or change in activity level</ListItem><ListItem>unusual changes in personality or behavior</ListItem><ListItem>a change in bowel habits or trouble <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinating</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>increase in head size (in infants)</ListItem><ListItem>sudden <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">confusion</GlossaryTermRef> or trouble speaking or understanding speech</ListItem><ListItem>sudden trouble seeing with one or both eyes</ListItem><ListItem>sudden severe headache for no known reason 
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_578">Other symptoms include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_579" Style="bullet"><ListItem>problems with memory</ListItem><ListItem>problems with paying attention</ListItem><ListItem>trouble with solving problems</ListItem><ListItem>trouble with organizing thoughts and tasks</ListItem><ListItem>slower ability to learn and use new information</ListItem><ListItem>trouble learning to read, write, or do math</ListItem><ListItem>trouble coordinating movement between the eyes, hands, and other muscles</ListItem><ListItem>delays in normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">development</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>social withdrawal or trouble getting along with others</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_778">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by brain and spinal cord late effects is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_580"><KeyPoint id="_581">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the brain and spinal cord.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1002">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_583" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Neurological exam</Strong> is a series of questions and tests to check the brain, spinal cord, and nerve function. The exam checks a person's mental status, coordination, and ability to walk normally, and how well the muscles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">senses</GlossaryTermRef>, and reflexes work. This may also be called a neuro exam or a neurologic exam.
In some cases, a more complete exam may be done by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurologist</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurosurgeon</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Neuropsychological <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assessment</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a series of tests to examine the patient's mental processes  and behavior. Areas that are checked usually  include: 

<ItemizedList id="_584" Style="dash"><ListItem>knowing who and where you are and what day it is</ListItem><ListItem>ability to learn and remember new information </ListItem><ListItem>intelligence</ListItem><ListItem>ability to solve problems</ListItem><ListItem>use of spoken and written language</ListItem><ListItem>eye-hand coordination</ListItem><ListItem>ability to organize information and tasks</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_787">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of brain and spinal cord late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_507"><KeyPoint id="_508">Survivors of childhood cancer have an increased risk of mental health disorders.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1021">Survivors of childhood cancer are more likely to be diagnosed with mental health disorders than their peers who have not had cancer. These disorders include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1019" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>autism spectrum disorder</ListItem><ListItem>bipolar disorder</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">obsessive-compulsive disorder</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440112" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">post-traumatic stress disorder</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_509">Having a mental health disorder may cause problems with personal relationships, education, employment, and health, and cause thoughts of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">suicide</GlossaryTermRef>. As a result, survivors may be less likely to live  on their own as adults.</Para><Para id="_868">Follow-up care for childhood cancer survivors should include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment for possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> or mental health disorders.</Para><Para id="_976">For more information about psychological distress and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coping skills</GlossaryTermRef>  for people with cancer, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_999" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000269124" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-pdq">Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062806" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">Depression</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_510"><KeyPoint id="_511">Some childhood cancer survivors have post-traumatic stress disorder.</KeyPoint><Para id="_512">Being diagnosed and treated for a life-threatening disease may be traumatic. This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454807" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trauma</GlossaryTermRef> may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440112" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">post-traumatic stress disorder</GlossaryTermRef> (PTSD). PTSD is defined as having certain behaviors following a stressful event that involved death or the threat of death, serious injury, or a threat to oneself or others. </Para><Para id="_514">PTSD can affect cancer survivors in the following ways:</Para><ItemizedList id="_515" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>constantly reliving or thinking about the time they were diagnosed and treated for cancer</ListItem><ListItem>having nightmares or flashbacks</ListItem><ListItem>avoiding places, events, and people that remind them of the cancer experience</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_513">In general, childhood cancer survivors show low levels of PTSD, depending in part on their coping style and the coping style of their parents. Survivors who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the head when younger than 4 years or survivors who received intensive treatment may be at higher risk of PTSD. Family problems, little or no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440116" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social support</GlossaryTermRef> from family or friends, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef> not related to the cancer may increase the chances of having PTSD. </Para><Para id="_516">Because avoiding places and people connected to the cancer may be part of PTSD, survivors with PTSD may not get the medical treatment they need.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_844"><KeyPoint id="_845">Adolescents who are diagnosed with cancer may have social problems later in life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_846"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adolescents</GlossaryTermRef> who are diagnosed with cancer may reach fewer social milestones or reach them later in life than adolescents not diagnosed with cancer. Social milestones include having a first boyfriend or girlfriend, getting married, and having a child. They may also have trouble getting along with other people or feel like they are not liked by others their age.</Para><Para id="_869"> Cancer survivors in this age group have  reported being less satisfied with their health and their lives in general compared with  others of the same age who did not have cancer. Adolescents and young adults who survived cancer need special programs that give psychological, educational, and job support.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_152"><Title>Digestive System</Title><Para id="_1022">Treatment with chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or surgery may cause problems throughout the digestive system, which starts at the mouth and ends at the rectum.</Para><SummarySection id="_153"><KeyPoint id="_154">Teeth and jaws</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_585"><KeyPoint id="_586">Problems with the teeth and jaws are more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_587">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef> of the teeth and jaws:</Para><ItemizedList id="_588" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> that spreads to the brain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharyngeal cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> (TBI) as part of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_159"><KeyPoint id="_160">Radiation to the head and neck and certain types of chemotherapy increase the risk of late effects to the teeth and jaws.</KeyPoint><Para id="_161">The risk of health problems that affect the teeth and jaws increases after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_162" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the head and neck</ListItem><ListItem>TBI as part of  a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, especially  with higher <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alkylating agents</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclophosphamide</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>surgery in the head and neck area</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_163">Risk is also increased in survivors who were younger than 5 years at the time of treatment because their permanent teeth had not fully formed.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_155"><KeyPoint id="_156">Late effects that affect the teeth and jaws may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_157">Teeth and jaws late effects and related health problems include:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_158" Style="bullet"><ListItem>teeth that are not normal</ListItem><ListItem>tooth decay (including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavities</GlossaryTermRef>) and gum disease </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">salivary glands</GlossaryTermRef> that do not make enough <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257526" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">saliva</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>death of the bone cells in the jaw</ListItem><ListItem>changes in the way the face, jaw, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef> form</ListItem><ListItem>a second cancer in the mouth</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_599"><KeyPoint id="_600">Possible symptoms of late effects of the teeth and jaws include tooth decay (cavities) and jaw pain.</KeyPoint><Para id="_601">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by late effects of the teeth and jaws or by other problems:</Para><ItemizedList id="_602" Style="bullet"><ListItem>teeth are small or do not have a normal shape</ListItem><ListItem>missing permanent teeth</ListItem><ListItem>permanent teeth come in at a later than normal age</ListItem><ListItem>teeth have less enamel than normal</ListItem><ListItem>more tooth decay (cavities) and gum disease than normal</ListItem><ListItem>dry mouth</ListItem><ListItem>trouble chewing, swallowing, and speaking</ListItem><ListItem>jaw pain</ListItem><ListItem>jaws do not open and close the way they should</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_779">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by late effects of the teeth and jaws is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_592"><KeyPoint id="_593">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the mouth and jaws.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1003">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_595" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Dental exam</Strong> is an exam of the teeth, mouth, and jaws to check general signs of dental health, including checking for signs of disease, such as cavities or anything that seems unusual. This may also be called a dental check-up.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Panorex x-ray</Strong> is an x-ray of all of the teeth and their roots.  An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>X-ray of the jaws</Strong> is an x-ray of the jaws.  An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the head and neck. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Magnetic resonance imaging</GlossaryTermRef> (MRI)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the head and neck. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the tumor so that a pathologist can view it under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_788">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of teeth and jaw late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_596"><KeyPoint id="_597">Regular dental care is very important for survivors of childhood cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_598">Doctors suggest that survivors of childhood cancer have a dental check-up and a cleaning and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044670" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluoride</GlossaryTermRef> treatment every 6 months. Children who had radiation therapy to the oral cavity may also see an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">orthodontist</GlossaryTermRef> or an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046252" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">otolaryngologist</GlossaryTermRef>.  If <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesions</GlossaryTermRef> are present in the mouth, a biopsy may be needed.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_169"><KeyPoint id="_170">Digestive tract</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_603"><KeyPoint id="_604">Digestive tract late effects are  more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_605">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause late effects of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive tract</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">large intestines</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anus</GlossaryTermRef>):

</Para><ItemizedList id="_606" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ cell tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>Hodgkin lymphoma</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>neuroblastoma</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rhabdomyosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef>, or near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046611" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testicles</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_607"><KeyPoint id="_608">Radiation to the bladder, prostate, or testicles and certain types of chemotherapy increase the risk of digestive tract late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_609">The risk of health problems that affect the digestive tract increases after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_610" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Radiation therapy to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> or areas near the abdomen, such as the esophagus, bladder, prostate, or testicles, may cause digestive tract problems that begin quickly  and last for  a short time. In some patients, however, digestive tract problems are delayed and long-lasting. These late effects are caused by radiation therapy that damages the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef>. Receiving higher doses of radiation therapy or receiving chemotherapy such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dactinomycin</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anthracyclines</GlossaryTermRef>  together with radiation therapy may increase this risk.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> surgery or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045087" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvic</GlossaryTermRef> surgery to remove the bladder.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy with alkylating agents such as cyclophosphamide, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635746" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">procarbazine</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ifosfamide</GlossaryTermRef>, or with  anthracyclines such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000583859" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">daunorubicin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">idarubicin</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000523457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epirubicin</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Stem cell transplant.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_832">The following may also increase the risk of digestive tract late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_833" Style="bullet"><ListItem>older age at diagnosis or when treatment begins</ListItem><ListItem>treatment with both radiation therapy and chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>a history of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">graft-versus-host disease</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_171"><KeyPoint id="_172">Late effects that affect the digestive tract may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_173">Digestive tract late effects and related health problems include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_174" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a narrowing of the esophagus or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the muscles of the esophagus do not work well</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reflux</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>diarrhea, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373943" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fecal incontinence</GlossaryTermRef>, or blocked <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>bowel perforation (a hole in the intestine)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammation</GlossaryTermRef> of the intestines</ListItem><ListItem>death of part of the intestine</ListItem><ListItem>intestine is not able to absorb <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef> from food</ListItem><ListItem>a second cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_611"><KeyPoint id="_612">Possible symptoms of digestive tract late effects include abdominal pain and diarrhea.</KeyPoint><Para id="_613">These and other symptoms may be caused by digestive tract late effects or by other problems:</Para><ItemizedList id="_614" Style="bullet"><ListItem>trouble swallowing or feeling like food is stuck in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>heartburn</ListItem><ListItem>fever with severe pain in the abdomen and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pain in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>a change in bowel habits (constipation or diarrhea)</ListItem><ListItem>nausea and vomiting</ListItem><ListItem>frequent gas pains, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bloating</GlossaryTermRef>, fullness, or cramps</ListItem><ListItem>reflux</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_780">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by digestive late effects is to see  a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_615"><KeyPoint id="_616">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the digestive tract.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1004">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_618" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Digital rectal exam</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an exam where the doctor or nurse inserts a lubricated, gloved finger into the rectum to feel for lumps or anything else that seems unusual.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a test that uses a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Kidney</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef>, and bladder x-ray</Strong> is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of the abdomen, kidney,  ureter, or bladder to check for signs of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CT scan (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Barium swallow</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a series of x-rays of the throat, esophagus, stomach, and the first part of the small intestine (duodenum). For this procedure, the patient drinks a liquid that contains barium (a silver-white metallic compound). The barium coats the esophagus and stomach which helps them show up more clearly in x-rays. This procedure is also called an upper GI series.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_789">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of digestive tract late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_182"><KeyPoint id="_183">Liver and bile ducts</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_619"><KeyPoint id="_620">Liver and bile duct late effects are more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_621">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile duct</GlossaryTermRef> late effects:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_622" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>Wilms tumor</ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_623"><KeyPoint id="_624">Certain types of chemotherapy and radiation to the liver or bile ducts increase the risk of late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_625">The risk of liver or bile duct late effects may be increased in childhood cancer survivors treated with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_626" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery to remove part of the liver or a liver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy  that includes high-dose cyclophosphamide as part of a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046639" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">6-mercaptopurine</GlossaryTermRef>, 6-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thioguanine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef>, and dactinomycin</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy to the liver and bile ducts, with the risk depending on:<ItemizedList id="_627" Style="dash"><ListItem>the dose of radiation  and how much of the liver is treated</ListItem><ListItem>age when treated (the younger the age, the higher the risk)</ListItem><ListItem>whether there was surgery to remove part of the liver</ListItem><ListItem>whether chemotherapy, such as doxorubicin or dactinomycin, was given together with radiation therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_978">The following may also increase the risk of liver and bile duct late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_979" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046146" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis B</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044139" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis C</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>history of chronic graft-versus-host disease</ListItem><ListItem>liver damage caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044806" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">veno-occlusive disease</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sinusoidal obstruction syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>tissue and organ damage from the buildup of extra <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iron</GlossaryTermRef> after having many <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045991" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood transfusions</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_184"><KeyPoint id="_185">Late effects that affect the liver and bile ducts may cause certain health problems.
</KeyPoint><Para id="_186">Liver and bile duct late effects and related health problems include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_187" Style="bullet"><ListItem>liver dysfunction</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallstones</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045614" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign</GlossaryTermRef> liver lesions</ListItem><ListItem>an overgrowth of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef> in the liver (liver  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045690" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fibrosis</GlossaryTermRef>) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045478" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cirrhosis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>fatty liver with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">insulin</GlossaryTermRef> resistance (a condition in which the body makes insulin but cannot use it well) </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_629"><KeyPoint id="_630">Possible symptoms of liver and bile duct late effects include abdominal pain and jaundice.</KeyPoint><Para id="_631"> These and other symptoms may be caused by liver and bile duct late effects or by other problems:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_632" Style="bullet"><ListItem>weight gain or weight loss</ListItem><ListItem>swelling of the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>nausea and vomiting</ListItem><ListItem>pain in the abdomen that may occur near the ribs, often on the right side after eating a fatty meal</ListItem><ListItem>yellowing of the skin and whites of the eyes (jaundice)
</ListItem><ListItem>light-colored bowel movements</ListItem><ListItem>diarrhea</ListItem><ListItem>dark-colored <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>a lot of gas</ListItem><ListItem>lack of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>feeling tired or weak</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_781">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by liver and bile duct late effects is to see a doctor.</Para><Para id="_934">Sometimes there are no signs or symptoms of liver or bile duct late effects and treatment may not be needed.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_633"><KeyPoint id="_634">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the liver and bile duct.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1005">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_636" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Blood chemistry studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease. For example, there may be a higher level of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044518" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilirubin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alanine aminotransferase</GlossaryTermRef> (ALT), and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372942" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aspartate aminotransferase</GlossaryTermRef> (AST) in the body if the liver has been damaged.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ferritin</GlossaryTermRef> level</Strong> uses a blood sample to measure the amount of ferritin. Ferritin is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> that binds to iron and stores it for use by the body. After a stem cell transplant, a high ferritin level may be a sign of liver disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045107" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Complete blood count</GlossaryTermRef> (CBC)</Strong> is when a sample of blood is drawn and checked for:<ItemizedList id="_980" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemoglobin</GlossaryTermRef> (the protein that carries <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef>) in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the portion of the blood sample made up of red blood cells</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_981">This test is used to check the amount of platelets in the body.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Prothrombin time (PT) test</Strong> measures how long it takes for the blood to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clot</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Hepatitis assay</Strong> uses a blood sample to check for pieces of the hepatitis <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045941" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">virus</GlossaryTermRef>. The blood sample may also be used to measure how much hepatitis virus is in the blood. All patients who had a blood transfusion before 1972 should have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> test for hepatitis B. Patients who had a blood transfusion before 1993 should have a screening test for hepatitis C.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Ultrasound exam</Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs, such as the gall bladder, and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. 
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CT scan (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs and tissue show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_790">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of liver or bile duct late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_638"><KeyPoint id="_639">Health habits that promote a healthy liver are important for survivors of childhood cancer. </KeyPoint><Para id="_640">Childhood cancer survivors with liver late effects should take care to protect their health, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_641" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having a healthy weight</ListItem><ListItem>not drinking alcohol</ListItem><ListItem>getting <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045938" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaccines</GlossaryTermRef> for hepatitis A and hepatitis B viruses</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_893"><KeyPoint id="_894">Pancreas</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_896"><KeyPoint id="_904">Radiation therapy increases the risk of pancreatic late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_909">The risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044074" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic</GlossaryTermRef> late effects may be increased in childhood cancer survivors after treatment with:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_910" Style="bullet"><ListItem>radiation therapy to the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>total-body irradiation as part of a stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_897"><KeyPoint id="_905">Late effects that affect the pancreas may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_912">Pancreatic late effects and related health problems include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_898" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Insulin resistance</Strong> is a condition in which the body does not use insulin the way it should. Insulin is needed to help control the amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef> (a type of sugar) in the body. Because the insulin does not work the way it should, glucose and fat levels rise.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Diabetes mellitus</Strong> is a disease in which the body does not make enough insulin or does not use it the way it should. When there is not enough insulin, the amount of glucose in the blood increases and the kidneys make a large amount of urine. Survivors also have an increased risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000812873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prediabetes</GlossaryTermRef>, which can lead to diabetes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_899"><KeyPoint id="_906">Possible symptoms of pancreatic late effects include frequent urination and being thirsty.</KeyPoint><Para id="_913">These and other symptoms may be caused by pancreatic late effects or by other problems:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_914" Style="bullet"><ListItem>frequent urination</ListItem><ListItem>feeling very thirsty</ListItem><ListItem>feeling very hungry</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>feeling very tired</ListItem><ListItem>frequent infections, especially of the skin, gums, or bladder</ListItem><ListItem>blurred vision</ListItem><ListItem>cuts or bruises that are slow to heal</ListItem><ListItem>numbness or tingling in the hands or feet</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_915">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by pancreatic late effects is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_900"><KeyPoint id="_907">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the pancreas.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1006">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_917" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Glycated hemoglobin (A1C) test</Strong> uses a sample of blood to measure the amount of glucose that is attached to red blood cells. A higher-than-normal amount of glucose attached to red blood cells can be a sign of diabetes mellitus. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Fasting blood sugar test</Strong> uses a blood sample to measure the amount of glucose in the blood. This test is done after the patient has had nothing to eat overnight. A higher-than-normal amount of glucose in the blood can be a sign of diabetes mellitus. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_198"><Title>Endocrine System</Title><SummarySection id="_870"><KeyPoint id="_871">Thyroid gland</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_642"><KeyPoint id="_643">Thyroid late effects are more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_644">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046036" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef> late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_645" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_646"><KeyPoint id="_647">Radiation therapy to the head and neck increases the risk of thyroid late effects. </KeyPoint><Para id="_911">The risk of thyroid late effects may be increased in childhood cancer survivors after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_649" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the thyroid as part of radiation therapy to the head and neck or to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pituitary gland</GlossaryTermRef> in the brain </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> as part of a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem>MIBG (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045855" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive iodine</GlossaryTermRef>) therapy for neuroblastoma</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alkylating agents</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anthracyclines</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000637625" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bleomycin</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>surgery to remove part of the thyroid</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_650">The risk also is  increased in females, in survivors who were a young age at the time of treatment, in survivors who had a higher radiation <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef>, and as the time since diagnosis and treatment gets longer. Risk for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endocrine</GlossaryTermRef> problems also depends on the location of the tumor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_398"><KeyPoint id="_199">Late effects that affect the thyroid may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_200">Thyroid late effects and related health problems include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_201" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044547" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hypothyroidism</GlossaryTermRef> (not enough <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid hormone</GlossaryTermRef>)</Strong>: There is a  higher risk of hypothyroidism in survivors treated with head and neck radiation involving  the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid gland</GlossaryTermRef>, especially survivors of Hodgkin lymphoma. This is the most common thyroid late effect. It usually occurs 2 to 5 years after treatment ends but may occur more than 25 years after radiation therapy. It is more common in girls than boys. Children, adolescents, and young adults treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proton beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may have a lower risk of developing hypothyroidism.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045717" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hyperthyroidism</GlossaryTermRef> (too much thyroid hormone)</Strong>: The risk of hyperthyroidism increases with higher doses of radiation therapy to the thyroid gland. Hyperthyroidism  is less common than hypothyroidism. It usually occurs 5 years after treatment ends, but may occur more than 25 years after radiation therapy. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Lumps in the thyroid</Strong>: Higher radiation dose and longer time since diagnosis are linked to an increased risk of developing thyroid lumps. These growths may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045614" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign</GlossaryTermRef> (not cancerous) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> (cancer). It is more common in girls than boys. An enlarged thyroid (goiter) may be caused by lumps in the thyroid.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_651"><KeyPoint id="_652">Symptoms of thyroid late effects depend on whether there is too little or too much thyroid hormone in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_653">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by thyroid late effects or by other problems:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_654" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>Hypothyroidism (too little thyroid hormone)</ListTitle><ListItem>feeling tired or weak</ListItem><ListItem>being more sensitive to cold</ListItem><ListItem>pale, dry skin</ListItem><ListItem>coarse and thinning hair</ListItem><ListItem>brittle fingernails</ListItem><ListItem>hoarse voice</ListItem><ListItem>puffy face</ListItem><ListItem>muscle  and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">joint</GlossaryTermRef> aches and stiffness</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045784" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menstrual periods</GlossaryTermRef> that are irregular or heavier than normal</ListItem><ListItem>weight gain for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef> or trouble with memory or being able to concentrate
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_924">Rarely, hypothyroidism does not cause any symptoms.</Para><ItemizedList id="_655" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>Hyperthyroidism (too much thyroid hormone)</ListTitle><ListItem>feeling nervous, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxious</GlossaryTermRef>, or moody</ListItem><ListItem>trouble sleeping</ListItem><ListItem>feeling tired or weak</ListItem><ListItem>having shaky hands</ListItem><ListItem>having a fast heartbeat</ListItem><ListItem>having red, warm skin that may be itchy</ListItem><ListItem>having fine, soft hair that is falling out</ListItem><ListItem>having frequent or loose bowel movements</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>being more sensitive to heat</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_782">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by thyroid late effects is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_656"><KeyPoint id="_657">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the thyroid.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1007">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_659" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Blood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef> studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain hormones released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the organ or tissue that makes it. The blood may be checked for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid-stimulating hormone</GlossaryTermRef> (TSH) or free <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000533434" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroxine</GlossaryTermRef> (T4). </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Ultrasound exam</Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. This procedure can show the size of the thyroid and whether there are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044502" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nodules</GlossaryTermRef> (lumps) on the thyroid.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_791">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of thyroid late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_430"><KeyPoint id="_890">Hypothalamus and pituitary gland</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_441"><KeyPoint id="_442">Neuroendocrine late effects may be caused after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_443">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045803" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroendocrine</GlossaryTermRef> system is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446114" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468796" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endocrine system</GlossaryTermRef> working together.  </Para><Para id="_925">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause neuroendocrine late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_444" Style="bullet"><ListItem>acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain and spinal cord tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>head and neck cancers</ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_431"><KeyPoint id="_432">Treatment that affects the hypothalamus or pituitary gland increases the risk of neuroendocrine system late effects. 
</KeyPoint><Para id="_445">Childhood cancer survivors have an increased risk for neuroendocrine late effects. These effects are caused by radiation therapy to treat cancer in the brain near  the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046359" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypothalamus</GlossaryTermRef> or used as total-body irradiation before a stem cell transplant. The hypothalamus controls the way  hormones are made and released into the bloodstream by the pituitary gland. These effects are also caused by surgery in the area of the hypothalamus, pituitary gland, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000637726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">optic pathways</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_720"><KeyPoint id="_721">Late effects that affect the hypothalamus may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_722">Childhood cancer survivors who have neuroendocrine late effects may have abnormal levels of hormones made in the pituitary gland and released into the blood. Neuroendocrine late effects and related health problems include:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_723" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Growth hormone deficiency</Strong>: Growth hormone helps promote growth and control metabolism. A low level of growth hormone is a common late effect of radiation to the brain in childhood cancer survivors. The higher the radiation dose and the longer the time since treatment, the greater the risk of this late effect. A low level of growth hormone may also occur in childhood ALL and stem cell transplant survivors who received radiation therapy to the brain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> and/or chemotherapy. <Para id="_926">A low level  of growth hormone in childhood results in  adult height that is shorter than normal. If the child's bones have not fully developed, low growth hormone levels may be treated with growth <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046127" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone replacement therapy</GlossaryTermRef> beginning one year after the end of treatment.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Adrenocorticotropin    deficiency (ACTH)</Strong>: Adrenocorticotropic hormone controls the making of glucocorticoids. A low level of adrenocorticotropic hormone is an uncommon late effect. It may occur in survivors: <ItemizedList id="_1023" Style="bullet"><ListItem>of childhood brain tumors, other tumors, or blood cancers</ListItem><ListItem>with  low growth hormone levels or central hypothyroidism</ListItem><ListItem>who received radiation therapy to the brain </ListItem><ListItem>who received steroid hormone therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_927">Symptoms of  adrenocorticotropin deficiency may not be severe and may not be noticed. Symptoms include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_928" Style="dash"><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>not feeling hungry</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>vomiting</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> pain</ListItem><ListItem>low <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>feeling tired</ListItem><ListItem>dizziness</ListItem><ListItem>muscle or joint pains</ListItem><ListItem>darkening of the skin</ListItem><ListItem>pale skin</ListItem><ListItem>low blood sugar</ListItem><ListItem>craving salts</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_929">Low levels of adrenocorticotropin may be treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045205" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrocortisone</GlossaryTermRef> therapy.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Hyperprolactinemia</Strong>: Prolactin controls the making of breast milk and has many other effects in the body. A high level of the hormone prolactin may occur after a high dose of radiation to the brain or surgery that affects part of the pituitary gland. A high level of prolactin may cause:<ItemizedList id="_922" Style="dash"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">puberty</GlossaryTermRef> at a later age than normal</ListItem><ListItem>flow of breast milk in a woman who is not pregnant or breastfeeding</ListItem><ListItem>less frequent or no menstrual periods or menstrual periods with a very light flow</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256567" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hot flashes</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>inability to become pregnant</ListItem><ListItem>inability to have an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373933" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">erection</GlossaryTermRef> needed for sexual intercourse</ListItem><ListItem>lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sex drive</GlossaryTermRef> (in men and women)</ListItem><ListItem>low bone mineral density (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteopenia</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_930">Sometimes there are no signs and symptoms. Treatment is rarely needed.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thyroid-stimulating hormone</GlossaryTermRef> (TSH) deficiency</Strong>: Thyroid-stimulating hormone controls the making of thyroid hormones. A low level of thyroid hormone may occur very slowly over time after radiation therapy to the brain. Thyroid-stimulating hormone deficiency may also be called central hyphothyroidism.<Para id="_931">Sometimes the symptoms of thyroid-stimulating hormone deficiency are not noticed. Low thyroid hormone levels may cause slow growth and delayed puberty, as well as other symptoms. Learn more about the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791#_651" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">symptoms of hypothyroidism</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_1024">A low level of thyroid hormone may be treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000563955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid hormone replacement therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Luteinizing hormone  or follicle-stimulating hormone  imbalance</Strong>: Luteinizing hormone and follicle-stimulating hormone control reproduction. Abnormal levels of these hormones can cause different health problems. The type of problem depends on the radiation dose and whether hormone levels are higher or lower than normal.  <Para id="_932">Childhood cancer survivors  who had brain tumors near the hypothalamus or pituitary gland, who were  treated with lower doses of radiation to the brain, or who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045498" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrocephalus</GlossaryTermRef> may develop central precocious puberty (a condition that causes puberty to start before age 8 in girls and 9 in boys). Central precocious puberty happens when the brain releases luteinizing and follicle-stimulating hormones too soon in the child's development. This condition may be treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) agonist</GlossaryTermRef>  therapy to delay puberty and help the child's growth. </Para><Para id="_933">Childhood cancer survivors who were treated with higher doses of radiation to the brain may have low levels of luteinizing hormone or follicle-stimulating hormone. This condition may be treated with  sex hormone replacement therapy. The dose will depend on the child's age and whether the child has reached puberty.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Central <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683346" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diabetes insipidus</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: Central diabetes insipidus may be caused by the absence of or low amounts of all of the hormones made in the front part of the pituitary gland and released into the blood. It may occur in childhood cancer survivors treated with surgery in the area of the hypothalamus or pituitary gland. Symptoms of central diabetes insipidus may include:<ItemizedList id="_954" Style="bullet"><ListItem>making large amounts of urine</ListItem><ListItem>feeling very thirsty</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1025">Symptoms of central diabetes insipidus in infants may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1026" Style="bullet"><ListItem>vomiting</ListItem><ListItem>diarrhea</ListItem><ListItem>irritability</ListItem><ListItem>slowed growth and development</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_724"><KeyPoint id="_725">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the neuroendocrine system.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1008">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_727" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry study</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef>, released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Blood hormone studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain hormones released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the organ or tissue that makes it. The blood may be checked for abnormal levels of follicle-stimulating hormone, luteinizing hormone, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estradiol</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045581" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testosterone</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cortisol</GlossaryTermRef>, or free thyroxine (T4).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lipid</GlossaryTermRef> profile studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of triglycerides, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cholesterol</GlossaryTermRef>, and low- and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol

in the blood.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_794">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of neuroendocrine late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_847"><KeyPoint id="_848">Metabolic syndrome</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_849"><KeyPoint id="_850">Metabolic syndrome is more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_851"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643126" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Metabolic syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> is a group of medical conditions that includes having too much fat around the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> and at least two of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_852" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>high levels of triglycerides and low levels of high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol in the blood</ListItem><ListItem>high levels of glucose (sugar) in the blood</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_853">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause metabolic syndrome to occur later in life:</Para><ItemizedList id="_854" Style="bullet"><ListItem>acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with radiation to the abdomen, such as Wilms tumor or neuroblastoma</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_855"><KeyPoint id="_856">Radiation therapy increases the risk of metabolic syndrome.</KeyPoint><Para id="_962">The risk of metabolic syndrome may be increased in childhood cancer survivors after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_963" Style="bullet"><ListItem>radiation therapy to the brain, abdomen, or pelvis</ListItem><ListItem>total-body irradiation (TBI) as part of a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy, such as alkylating agents</ListItem><ListItem>older age</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_946"><KeyPoint id="_947">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose metabolic syndrome.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1009">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_949" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Blood chemistry studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as glucose, released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Lipid profile studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of triglycerides, cholesterol, and low- and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol

in the blood.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_950">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of metabolic syndrome. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_857"><KeyPoint id="_858">Metabolic syndrome may cause heart and blood vessel disease and diabetes.</KeyPoint><Para id="_859">Metabolic syndrome is linked to an increased risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748138" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart and blood vessel disease</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044911" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diabetes</GlossaryTermRef>. Health habits that decrease these risks include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_951" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having a healthy weight</ListItem><ListItem>eating a heart-healthy diet</ListItem><ListItem>exercising regularly</ListItem><ListItem>not smoking</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_885"><KeyPoint id="_886">Weight changes and frailty</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_248"><KeyPoint id="_249">Weight changes and frailty are late effects that are more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.

</KeyPoint><Para id="_1042">Weight changes include being underweight or having excess body weight or obesity.  Frailty is a condition that usually affects older adults and includes having fatigue, slow walking speed, and muscle weakness.</Para><Para id="_250">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause a change in weight or frailty:</Para><ItemizedList id="_251" Style="bullet"><ListItem>acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem>brain tumors, especially <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046131" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">craniopharyngiomas</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>bone tumors</ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with radiation to the brain, including TBI as part of a stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_982"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Graft-versus-host disease</GlossaryTermRef> may also cause a change in weight for patients treated with a stem cell transplant.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_244"><KeyPoint id="_245">Radiation therapy increases the risk of weight changes and frailty.</KeyPoint><Para id="_967">The risk of being underweight increases after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_968" Style="bullet"><ListItem>TBI for females</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy to the abdomen for males</ListItem><ListItem>certain types of chemotherapy (alkylating agents and anthracyclines)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1038">The following may also increase the risk of being underweight:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1039" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>being female</ListItem><ListItem>having a low household income</ListItem><ListItem>having a chronic illness</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_246">The risk of having excess body weight or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">obesity</GlossaryTermRef> increases after treatment with:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_247" Style="bullet"><ListItem>radiation therapy to the brain</ListItem><ListItem>surgery that damages the hypothalamus or pituitary gland, such as surgery to remove a craniopharyngioma brain tumor</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_829">The following may also increase the risk of obesity:</Para><ItemizedList id="_830" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having excess body weight at the time of a cancer diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>being diagnosed with cancer between the ages of 5 and 9</ListItem><ListItem>being female</ListItem><ListItem>having growth hormone deficiency or low levels of the hormone <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766473" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leptin</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>lack of physical activity</ListItem><ListItem>taking an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antidepressant</GlossaryTermRef> called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paroxetine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_902">Childhood cancer survivors who get enough exercise and have a normal amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> have a lower risk of obesity.</Para><Para id="_1040">The risk of frailty increases after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1041" Style="bullet"><ListItem>radiation therapy to the brain</ListItem><ListItem>TBI</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_716"><KeyPoint id="_717">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose a change in weight.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1010">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_719" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Blood chemistry studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as glucose, released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.

</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Lipid profile studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of triglycerides, cholesterol, and low- and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol

in the blood.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_964">Being underweight, having excess body weight, or having obesity may be measured by weight, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455136" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">body mass index</GlossaryTermRef>, percent of body fat, or size of the abdomen (belly fat).</Para><Para id="_793">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of a change in weight. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_211"><Title>Immune System</Title><SummarySection id="_660"><KeyPoint id="_661">Cancer treatments and surgery to remove the spleen increase the risk of immune system late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_662">The risk of health problems that affect the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> increases after treatment that affects the spleen, including:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_663" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440106" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose radiation</GlossaryTermRef> therapy to the spleen that causes the spleen to stop working</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">graft-versus-host disease</GlossaryTermRef> that causes the spleen to stop working</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1027">The risk of health problems that affect the immune system may increase after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1028" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>stem cell transplant with or without graft-versus-host disease</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_664"><KeyPoint id="_665">Late effects that affect the immune system may cause infection.</KeyPoint><Para id="_666">Late effects that affect the immune system may increase the risk of viral infections or very serious bacterial infections. This risk is higher in younger children than in older children and in children who have decreased vaccine coverage after cancer treatment. The risk may be greater in the early years after the spleen stops working or is removed by surgery. These <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by infection:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_667" Style="bullet"><ListItem>redness, swelling, or warmth of a part of the body</ListItem><ListItem>pain that is in one part of the body, such as the eye, ear, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>fever</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_668">An infection may cause other symptoms that depend on the part of the body affected. For example, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> infection may cause a cough and trouble breathing.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_670"><KeyPoint id="_671">Children who have had their spleen removed or have lost vaccine immunity may need antibiotics or booster vaccine doses to lessen the risk of infection.</KeyPoint><Para id="_919">Daily <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibiotics</GlossaryTermRef> may be prescribed for children younger than 5 years whose spleen is no longer working or for at least 1 year after surgery to remove the spleen. For certain high-risk patients, daily antibiotics may be prescribed throughout childhood and into adulthood. </Para><Para id="_673">In addition, children with an increased risk of infection should be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044841" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaccinated</GlossaryTermRef> on a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">schedule</GlossaryTermRef>  through adolescence against:</Para><ItemizedList id="_674" Style="bullet"><ListItem>pneumococcal disease</ListItem><ListItem>meningococcal disease</ListItem><ListItem><ScientificName>Haemophilus influenzae</ScientificName> type b (Hib) disease</ListItem><ListItem>diphtheria-tetanus-pertussis (DTaP)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046146" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis B</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>measles</ListItem><ListItem>mumps</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_864">Some children may lose the protection they had from vaccines during their cancer treatments. Talk to the doctor about whether childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaccinations</GlossaryTermRef> given before cancer treatment need to be repeated.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_459"><Title>Musculoskeletal System</Title><SummarySection id="_675"><KeyPoint id="_676">Bone and joint late effects are more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_677">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause bone and joint late effects:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_678" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000434562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> tumors</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046031" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ewing sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rhabdomyosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_939">Poor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrition</GlossaryTermRef> and not enough exercise may also cause bone late effects.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_679"><KeyPoint id="_680">Radiation therapy, surgery, chemotherapy, and other treatments increase the risk of bone and joint late effects.</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_697"><KeyPoint id="_698">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_699"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> can stop or slow the growth of bone and muscle. The type of bone and joint late effects depends on the part of the body that received radiation therapy. Radiation therapy may cause:</Para><ItemizedList id="_700" Style="bullet"><ListItem>changes in the way  the face or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef> form, especially when <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440106" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose radiation</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is given to children before age 5 years  </ListItem><ListItem>short stature (being shorter than normal)</ListItem><ListItem>curving of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723831" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scoliosis</GlossaryTermRef>) or rounding of the spine (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723841" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kyphosis</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>one arm or leg is shorter than the other arm or leg</ListItem><ListItem>weak or thin bones that can break easily (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteoporosis</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>parts of a bone to die from a lack of blood flow (osteoradionecrosis), especially the jaw</ListItem><ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign tumor</GlossaryTermRef> of the bone (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723860" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteochondroma</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_701"><KeyPoint id="_702">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_703"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046210" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Amputation</GlossaryTermRef> or  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689062" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">limb-sparing surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the cancer and prevent it from coming back may cause late effects depending on where the tumor was, age of the patient, and type of surgery. Health problems after amputation or limb-sparing surgery may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_704" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having problems with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430401" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">activities of daily living</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>not being able to be as active as normal</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044654" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic pain</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>problems with the way <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046542" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prosthetics</GlossaryTermRef> fit or work</ListItem><ListItem>broken bone</ListItem><ListItem>additional surgeries later in life</ListItem><ListItem>the bone not healing well after surgery</ListItem><ListItem>one arm or leg is shorter than the other</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_706">Studies show no difference in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> for childhood cancer survivors who had amputation compared to those who had limb-sparing surgery.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_707"><KeyPoint id="_708">Chemotherapy and other drug therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_709">Risk may be increased in childhood cancer survivors who received cancer treatment that included <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">corticosteroids</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045295" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucocorticoids</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045262" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dexamethasone</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Drug therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may cause:</Para><ItemizedList id="_710" Style="bullet"><ListItem>weak or thin bones that can break easily (osteoporosis)</ListItem><ListItem>one or more parts of a bone to die from a lack of blood flow (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723852" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteonecrosis</GlossaryTermRef>), especially in the hip or knee</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_711"><KeyPoint id="_712">Stem cell transplant</KeyPoint><Para id="_713">A stem cell transplant can affect the bone and joints in different ways: </Para><ItemizedList id="_714" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> given as part of a stem cell transplant may affect the body's ability to make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538639" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">growth hormone</GlossaryTermRef> and cause short stature (being shorter than normal). It may also cause weak or thin bones that can break easily (osteoporosis) and the formation of a benign tumor called osteochondroma. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chronic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">graft-versus-host disease</GlossaryTermRef> that may occur after a stem cell transplant can cause the muscles around joints to tighten, leading to stiff joints (joint contractures). Chronic graft-versus-host disease may also cause one or more parts of a bone to die from a lack of blood flow (osteonecrosis).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_687"><KeyPoint id="_688">Possible symptoms of bone and joint late effects include swelling over a bone or bone and joint pain.</KeyPoint><Para id="_689">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by bone and joint late effects or by other problems:</Para><ItemizedList id="_690" Style="bullet"><ListItem>swelling over a bone or bony part of the body</ListItem><ListItem>pain in a bone or joint</ListItem><ListItem>redness or warmth over a bone or joint</ListItem><ListItem>joint stiffness or trouble moving normally</ListItem><ListItem>a bone that breaks easily or for no known reason
</ListItem><ListItem>short stature (being shorter than normal)</ListItem><ListItem>one side of the body looks higher than the other side or the body tilts to one side</ListItem><ListItem>always sitting or standing in a slouching position or having the appearance of a  hunched back</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_783">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by bone and joint late effects is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_691"><KeyPoint id="_692">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the bone and joint.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1011">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_694" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000562728" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone mineral density scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging test</GlossaryTermRef> that measures <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone density</GlossaryTermRef> (the amount of bone mineral in a certain amount of bone) by passing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> with two different energy levels through the bone. It is used to diagnose osteoporosis (weak or thin bones that can break easily). Also called BMD scan, DEXA, DEXA scan, dual energy x-ray absorptiometric scan, dual x-ray absorptiometry, and DXA. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>X-ray</Strong> is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of areas inside the body, such as bones.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Vitamin D test</Strong> uses a sample of blood to measure the amount of vitamin D in the body. Vitamin D is a nutrient the body needs to build and maintain strong bones.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Calcium blood test</Strong> uses a sample of blood to measure the amount of calcium in the body. Calcium is a mineral the body needs to build and maintain strong bones.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_792">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of bone and joint late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_417"><Title>Reproductive System</Title><SummarySection id="_1029"><KeyPoint id="_1030">Reproductive system late effects are more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_278">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046611" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testicular</GlossaryTermRef> late effects:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_483" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046031" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ewing sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ cell tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rhabdomyosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testicular cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_736">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044984" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovarian</GlossaryTermRef> late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_737" Style="bullet"><ListItem>acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem>germ cell tumors</ListItem><ListItem>Hodgkin lymphoma</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_269"><KeyPoint id="_270">Surgery, radiation therapy, and certain types of chemotherapy increase the risk of late effects that affect the reproductive system. </KeyPoint><Para id="_728">The risk of health problems that affect the reproductive system increases after treatment with:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_729" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery, such as the removal of a testicle, part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, or one or both ovaries</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alkylating agents</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclophosphamide</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045260" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dacarbazine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635746" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">procarbazine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ifosfamide</GlossaryTermRef>, mechlorethamine, cisplatin, lomustine, and busulfan</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the abdomen, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, lower back, testicles, ovaries, uterus, or in the area of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046359" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypothalamus</GlossaryTermRef> in the brain</ListItem><ListItem>total-body irradiation, high-dose chemotherapy, or both before a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy to the abdomen or pelvis with alkylating agents</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1031">In female survivors who had radiation therapy to the abdomen, the damage to the ovaries depends on the radiation dose, age at the time of treatment, and whether all or part of the abdomen received radiation.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_267"><KeyPoint id="_268">Testicles</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_730"><KeyPoint id="_731">Late effects that affect the testicles may cause certain health problems. </KeyPoint><Para id="_732">Late effects of the testicles and related health problems include:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_733" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Low <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sperm count</GlossaryTermRef>: A zero <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257221" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sperm</GlossaryTermRef> count or a low sperm count may be temporary or permanent. This depends on the radiation <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">schedule</GlossaryTermRef>, the area of the body treated, and the age when treated.</ListItem><ListItem>Low testosterone levels: This can lead to underdeveloped testicles, infertility, and sexual problems in adulthood.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Infertility</GlossaryTermRef>: The inability to father a child.</ListItem><ListItem>Retrograde <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046433" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ejaculation</GlossaryTermRef>: Very little or no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">semen</GlossaryTermRef> comes out of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">penis</GlossaryTermRef> during <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">orgasm</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_943">After treatment with chemotherapy or radiation, the body's ability to make sperm may come back over time.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_983"><KeyPoint id="_984">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the testicles.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1012">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests:</Para><ItemizedList id="_986" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Blood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef> studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain hormones released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the organ or tissue that makes it. The blood may be checked for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643012" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follicle-stimulating hormone</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">luteinizing hormone</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045581" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testosterone</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Semen analysis (sperm count)</Strong> measures the amount and quality of semen and sperm to see if there are problems that are causing infertility.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_418"><KeyPoint id="_419">Ovaries</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_420"><KeyPoint id="_421">Late effects that affect the ovaries may cause certain health problems.
</KeyPoint><Para id="_422">Ovarian late effects and other health-related problems include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_423" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449953" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">early menopause</GlossaryTermRef>, especially in women who had their ovaries removed or were treated with both an alkylating agent and radiation therapy to the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045784" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menstrual periods</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>infertility (inability to conceive a child)</ListItem><ListItem>puberty does not begin</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1032">Hormone replacement therapy can be used to start puberty.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_739"><KeyPoint id="_740">Possible symptoms of ovarian late effects include irregular or absent menstrual periods and hot flashes.</KeyPoint><Para id="_741">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by ovarian late effects or by other problems:</Para><ItemizedList id="_742" Style="bullet"><ListItem>irregular or no menstrual periods</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256567" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hot flashes</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>drenching night sweats</ListItem><ListItem>trouble sleeping</ListItem><ListItem>mood changes</ListItem><ListItem>lowered <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sex drive</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044308" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaginal</GlossaryTermRef> dryness</ListItem><ListItem>sex traits, such as developing arm, pubic, and leg  hair or having the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breasts</GlossaryTermRef> enlarge, do not occur at puberty</ListItem><ListItem>weak or thin bones that can break easily (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteoporosis</GlossaryTermRef>)
</ListItem><ListItem>inability to get  pregnant</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_784">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by late effects to the ovaries is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_987"><KeyPoint id="_988">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the ovaries.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1013">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following test.</Para><ItemizedList id="_990" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Blood hormone studies</Strong> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain hormones released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the organ or tissue that makes it. The blood may be checked for abnormal levels of follicle-stimulating hormone, luteinizing hormone, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estradiol</GlossaryTermRef>, or TSH.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_299"><KeyPoint id="_300">Fertility and reproduction</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_301"><KeyPoint id="_302">Childhood cancer survivors may have late effects that affect pregnancy. </KeyPoint><Para id="_303">Late effects on pregnancy include increased risk of:</Para><ItemizedList id="_304" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044911" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diabetes</GlossaryTermRef> during pregnancy</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>miscarriage or stillbirth</ListItem><ListItem>low birth-weight babies</ListItem><ListItem>early labor and/or delivery</ListItem><ListItem>impaired blood flow to the uterus</ListItem><ListItem>delivery by Cesarean section</ListItem><ListItem>the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046400" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fetus</GlossaryTermRef> is not in the right position for birth (for example, the foot or buttock is in position to come out before the head)</ListItem><ListItem>peripartum cardiomyopathy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_975">Long-term survivors of childhood, adolescent, and young adult cancers who have received radiation therapy or certain types of chemotherapy are at risk of a rare type of heart failure during pregnancy called peripartum cardiomyopathy. It may occur during late pregnancy and up to 5 months after giving birth. If cancer treatments have caused damage to the heart, these patients may also be at risk of congestive heart failure during pregnancy. Patients at risk of these conditions should be closely followed for weakness of the heart muscle during pregnancy.</Para><Para id="_973">Some studies have not shown an increased risk of late effects on pregnancy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_309"><KeyPoint id="_310">There are methods that may be used to help childhood cancer survivors have children.</KeyPoint><Para id="_311">The following methods may be used so that childhood cancer survivors can have children: </Para><ItemizedList id="_312" Style="bullet"><ListItem>freezing the eggs or sperm before cancer treatment in patients who have reached puberty (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000779589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">egg</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043974" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sperm banking</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>preventing damage to the ovaries before radiation therapy by moving one or both ovaries and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef> out of the field of radiation and attaching them to the wall of the abdomen (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000780385" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovarian transposition</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>removing a small amount of tissue containing sperm from the testicle (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774376" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testicular sperm extraction</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>fertilizing an egg outside the body by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injecting</GlossaryTermRef> a sperm into it (intracytoplasmic sperm injection)</ListItem><ListItem>
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro fertilization</GlossaryTermRef> (IVF), which is a procedure where eggs and sperm are placed together in a container,  giving the sperm the chance to enter an egg</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_314"><KeyPoint id="_315">Children of childhood cancer survivors are not affected by the parent's previous treatment for cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_952">The children of childhood cancer survivors do not appear to have an increased risk of birth defects, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> disease, or cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_318"><Title>Respiratory System</Title><SummarySection id="_329"><KeyPoint id="_330">Lung late effects are more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.
</KeyPoint><Para id="_331">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> late effects:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_332" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ cell tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>leukemia</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_323"><KeyPoint id="_324">Certain types of chemotherapy and radiation to the lungs increase the risk of lung late effects.
</KeyPoint><Para id="_327">The risk of health problems that affect the lungs increases after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_328" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery to remove all or part of the lung or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chest wall</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000637625" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bleomycin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045410" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">busulfan</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045976" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carmustine</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lomustine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> or high-dose chemotherapy before a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the chest </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1033">In survivors who had radiation to the chest, the damage to the lungs and chest wall depends on the radiation <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef>, whether all or part of the lungs and chest wall received radiation, whether the radiation was given in small, divided daily doses, and the child's age at treatment.</Para><Para id="_325">The risk of lung late effects is greater in childhood cancer survivors who are treated with a combination of surgery, chemotherapy, and/or radiation therapy. The risk is also increased in survivors who have a history of:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_326" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infections</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">graft-versus-host disease</GlossaryTermRef> after a stem cell transplant</ListItem><ListItem>lung or airway disease, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440101" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">asthma</GlossaryTermRef>, before cancer treatment</ListItem><ListItem>an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> chest wall</ListItem><ListItem>smoking cigarettes or other substances</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_319"><KeyPoint id="_320">Late effects that affect the lungs may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_321">Lung late effects and related health problems include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_322" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflamed</GlossaryTermRef> lung caused by radiation therapy (radiation <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pneumonitis</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>buildup of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000640078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scar tissue</GlossaryTermRef> in the lung (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045852" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pulmonary</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045690" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fibrosis</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>other lung and airway problems, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000524193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</GlossaryTermRef> (COPD), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pneumonia</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pneumothorax</GlossaryTermRef>, cough that does not go away, and asthma</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_748"><KeyPoint id="_749">Possible symptoms of lung late effects include trouble breathing and cough.</KeyPoint><Para id="_750">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by lung late effects or by other problems:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_751" Style="bullet"><ListItem>shortness of breath (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046183" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dyspnea</GlossaryTermRef>), especially when being active</ListItem><ListItem>wheezing</ListItem><ListItem>fever</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic cough</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>congestion (a feeling of fullness in the lungs from extra <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046274" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucus</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>chronic lung infections</ListItem><ListItem>feeling tired</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_785">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by lung late effects is to see a doctor.</Para><Para id="_752">Lung late effects in childhood cancer survivors may occur slowly over time or there may be no symptoms. Sometimes lung damage can be  detected only by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046361" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging</GlossaryTermRef> or pulmonary function  testing. Lung late effects may improve over time.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_753"><KeyPoint id="_754">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the lung.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1014">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_756" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an x-ray of the organs and bones inside the chest.  An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of areas inside the body.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Pulmonary function test (PFT)</Strong> is a test to see how well the lungs are working. It measures how much air the lungs can hold and how quickly air moves into and out of the lungs. It also measures how much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> is used and how much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538147" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carbon dioxide</GlossaryTermRef> is given off during breathing. This is also called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung function test</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CT scan (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_795">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of lung late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_860"><KeyPoint id="_861">Health habits that promote healthy lungs are important for survivors of childhood cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_862">Childhood cancer survivors with lung late effects should take care to protect their health, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_863" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Not smoking. Self-help programs and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counseling</GlossaryTermRef> are available to those who want to quit. Learn more about the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062889" url="/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-pdq">health risks of cigarette smoking and how to quit</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Getting <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045938" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaccines</GlossaryTermRef> for flu and pneumococcus.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_333"><Title>Senses</Title><SummarySection id="_334"><KeyPoint id="_335">Hearing</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_343"><KeyPoint id="_344">Hearing problems are a late effect that is more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_345">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause hearing late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_346" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000434562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ cell tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers that are treated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_338"><KeyPoint id="_339">Radiation therapy to the brain and certain types of chemotherapy increase the risk of hearing loss. </KeyPoint><Para id="_340">The risk of hearing loss is increased in childhood cancer survivors after treatment with: 

</Para><ItemizedList id="_341" Style="bullet"><ListItem>certain types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef> or high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carboplatin</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_342">The risk of hearing loss from radiation therapy is greater in children who are diagnosed with cancer before age 5 years, and the risk increases for children of all ages with higher radiation doses. The risk of hearing loss is also greater in childhood cancer survivors who received radiation therapy to the brain and chemotherapy at the same time.</Para><Para id="_1034">The risk of hearing loss may be lower if children treated with cisplatin were also given a drug called sodium thiosulfate.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_757"><KeyPoint id="_758">Hearing loss is the most common sign of hearing late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_759">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by hearing late effects or by other problems:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_760" Style="bullet"><ListItem>hearing loss</ListItem><ListItem>ringing in the ears</ListItem><ListItem>feeling dizzy</ListItem><ListItem>too much hardened wax in the ear</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1035">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by hearing late effects is to see a doctor.</Para><Para id="_761">Hearing loss may occur during treatment, soon after treatment ends, or  several months or  years after  treatment ends and worsen over time. A young child may have trouble learning, communicating, doing well in school, and interacting with others if they have hearing loss. In adulthood, hearing loss can lead to social isolation, depression, anxiety, and trouble finding stable employment. Talk to a doctor to learn about hearing aids or other ways to cope with hearing loss.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_762"><KeyPoint id="_763">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the ear and hearing problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1015">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_765" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Otoscopic exam</Strong> is an exam of the ear. An otoscope is used to look at the ear canal and the eardrum to check for signs of infection or hearing loss. Sometimes the otoscope has a plastic bulb that is squeezed to release a small puff of air into the ear canal. In a healthy ear, the eardrum will move. If there is fluid behind the eardrum, it will not move.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Hearing test</Strong> can be done in different ways depending on a person's age. The test is done to check if the person can hear soft and loud sounds and low- and high-pitched sounds. Each ear is checked separately.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_796">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of hearing late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_347"><KeyPoint id="_348">Seeing</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_359"><KeyPoint id="_360">Eye and vision problems are a late effect that is more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_361">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause eye and vision late effects:



</Para><ItemizedList id="_362" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute lymphoblastic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (ALL)</ListItem><ListItem>brain tumors</ListItem><ListItem>head and neck cancers 
</ListItem><ListItem>retinoblastoma, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rhabdomyosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, and other tumors of the eye</ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total-body irradiation</GlossaryTermRef> (TBI) before a stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_353"><KeyPoint id="_354">Radiation therapy to the brain or head increases the risk of eye problems or vision loss.</KeyPoint><Para id="_766">The risk of eye problems or vision loss may be increased in childhood cancer survivors after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_767" Style="bullet"><ListItem>radiation therapy to the brain, eye, or eye socket</ListItem><ListItem>surgery to remove the eye or a tumor near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">optic nerve</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>certain types of chemotherapy, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045155" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytarabine</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>TBI, busulfan, and corticosteroids as part of a stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1037">Having a history of chronic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">graft-versus-host disease</GlossaryTermRef> after a stem cell transplant can also increase the risk of eye problems and vision loss.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_349"><KeyPoint id="_350">Late effects that affect the eye may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_351">Eye late effects and related health problems include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_352" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having a small eye socket that affects the shape of the child's face as it grows</ListItem><ListItem>loss of vision</ListItem><ListItem>vision problems, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440102" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cataracts</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000534224" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glaucoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>not being able to make tears</ListItem><ListItem>damage to the optic nerve and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retina</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>eyelid tumors</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_768"><KeyPoint id="_769">Possible signs and symptoms of eye and vision late effects include changes in vision and dry eyes.</KeyPoint><Para id="_770">These and other symptoms may be caused by eye and vision late effects or by other problems:</Para><ItemizedList id="_771" Style="bullet"><ListItem>changes in vision, such as:<ItemizedList id="_772" Style="dash"><ListItem>not being able to see objects that are close</ListItem><ListItem>not being able to see objects that are far away</ListItem><ListItem>double vision</ListItem><ListItem>cloudy or blurred vision</ListItem><ListItem>colors seem faded</ListItem><ListItem>being sensitive to light or trouble seeing at night</ListItem><ListItem>seeing a glare or halo around lights at night</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>dry eyes that may feel like they are itchy, burning, or swollen, or like there is something in the eye</ListItem><ListItem>eye pain</ListItem><ListItem>eye redness</ListItem><ListItem>having a growth on the eyelid</ListItem><ListItem>drooping of the upper eyelid</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_786">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by eye and vision late effects is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_773"><KeyPoint id="_774">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the eye and vision problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1016">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_776" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Eye exam with dilated pupil</Strong> is when the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000546600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pupil</GlossaryTermRef> is dilated (widened) with medicated eye drops to allow the doctor to look through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> and pupil to the retina. The inside of the eye, including the retina and the optic nerve, is checked using an instrument that makes a narrow beam of light. This is sometimes called a slit-lamp exam. If there is a tumor, the doctor may take pictures over time to keep track of changes in the size of the tumor and how fast it is growing.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000534231" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Indirect ophthalmoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an exam of the inside of the back of the eye using a small magnifying lens and a light.
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_797">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of eye and vision late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_363"><Title>Urinary System</Title><SummarySection id="_399"><KeyPoint id="_400">Kidney</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_991"><KeyPoint id="_992">Kidney problems are a late effect that is more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_993">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef> late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_994" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_364"><KeyPoint id="_365">Certain types of chemotherapy increase the risk of kidney late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_366">The risk of health problems that affect the kidney increases after treatment with:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_798" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carboplatin</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ifosfamide</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> or middle of the back</ListItem><ListItem>surgery to remove part or all of a kidney</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_953">The risk of kidney late effects is greater in childhood cancer survivors who were treated with a combination of surgery, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_942">The following may also increase the risk of kidney late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_800" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having cancer in both kidneys</ListItem><ListItem>having a genetic syndrome that increases the risk of kidney problems, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Denys-Drash syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">WAGR syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>being treated with more than one type of treatment</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_801"><KeyPoint id="_802">Late effects that affect the kidney may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_803">Kidney late effects or related health problems include:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_804" Style="bullet"><ListItem>damage to the parts of the kidney that filter and clean the blood or the parts that remove extra water from the blood</ListItem><ListItem>loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044338" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electrolytes</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373087" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">magnesium</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045632" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">calcium</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044344" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">potassium</GlossaryTermRef>, from the body</ListItem><ListItem>high blood pressure (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044038" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypertension</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_805"><KeyPoint id="_806">Possible symptoms of kidney late effects include problems urinating and swelling of the feet or hands.</KeyPoint><Para id="_807">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by kidney late effects or by other problems:</Para><ItemizedList id="_808" Style="bullet"><ListItem>feeling the need to urinate without being able to do so</ListItem><ListItem>frequent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urination</GlossaryTermRef> (especially at night)</ListItem><ListItem>trouble urinating</ListItem><ListItem>feeling very tired</ListItem><ListItem>swelling of the legs, ankles, feet, face, or hands</ListItem><ListItem>itchy skin</ListItem><ListItem>shortness of breath</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>a metal-like taste in the mouth or bad breath</ListItem><ListItem>headache</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_809">Sometimes there are no signs or symptoms in the early stages. Signs or symptoms may appear as damage to the kidney continues over time. The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by kidney late effects is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_810"><KeyPoint id="_811">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the kidney.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1017">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_813" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Blood chemistry study</Strong> uses a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044337" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">creatinine</GlossaryTermRef>, released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance may be a sign of kidney disease.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Urinalysis</Strong> checks the color of urine and its contents, such as sugar, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Ultrasound exam</Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs, such as the kidney, and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_815">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of kidney late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.

</Para><Para id="_1036">If kidney problems are found, treatment options are available, including kidney transplant.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_816"><KeyPoint id="_817">Health habits that promote healthy kidneys are important for survivors of childhood cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_818">Childhood cancer survivors who had all or part of their kidney removed should talk to their doctor about: </Para><ItemizedList id="_819" Style="bullet"><ListItem>whether it is safe to play sports that have a high risk of heavy contact or impact such as football or hockey</ListItem><ListItem>bicycle safety and avoiding handlebar injuries</ListItem><ListItem>wearing a seatbelt around the hips, not the waist</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_402"><KeyPoint id="_403">Bladder</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_995"><KeyPoint id="_996">Bladder problems are a late effect that is more likely to occur after treatment for certain childhood cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_997">Treatment for these and other childhood cancers may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> late effects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_998" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancers treated with a stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_408"><KeyPoint id="_409">Surgery to the pelvic area and certain types of chemotherapy increase the risk of bladder late effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_410">The risk of health problems that affect the bladder increases after treatment with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_411" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery to remove part or all of the bladder</ListItem><ListItem>surgery to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>, or brain</ListItem><ListItem>certain types of chemotherapy, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclophosphamide</GlossaryTermRef> or ifosfamide</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy to areas  near the bladder, pelvis, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinary tract</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>stem cell transplant</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_404"><KeyPoint id="_405">Late effects that affect the bladder may cause certain health problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_406">Bladder late effects and related health problems include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_407" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammation</GlossaryTermRef> of the inside of the bladder wall, which leads to bleeding (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000695987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemorrhagic cystitis</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>thickening of the bladder wall</ListItem><ListItem>decreased urine storage</ListItem><ListItem>trouble emptying the bladder</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incontinence</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>a blockage in the kidney, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef>, bladder, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046640" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urethra</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>urinary tract <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infections</GlossaryTermRef> that last a long time or keep coming back</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_820"><KeyPoint id="_821">Possible symptoms of bladder late effects include changes in urination and swelling of the feet or hands.</KeyPoint><Para id="_822">These and other symptoms may be caused by bladder late effects or by other problems:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_823" Style="bullet"><ListItem>feeling the need to urinate without being able to do so</ListItem><ListItem>frequent urination (especially at night)</ListItem><ListItem>trouble urinating</ListItem><ListItem>feeling like the bladder does not empty completely after urination</ListItem><ListItem>swelling of the legs, ankles, feet, face, or hands</ListItem><ListItem>little or no bladder control</ListItem><ListItem>blood in the urine</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_824">The only way to know if these symptoms are caused by bladder late effects is to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_825"><KeyPoint id="_826">Certain tests and procedures are used to diagnose health problems in the bladder.</KeyPoint><Para id="_1018">In addition to asking the childhood cancer survivor about their personal and family health history and doing a physical exam, the doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_828" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Blood chemistry study</Strong> uses a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as magnesium, calcium, and potassium, released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance may be a sign of bladder problems.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Urinalysis</Strong> checks the color of urine and its contents, such as sugar, protein, red blood cells, and white blood cells.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Urine culture</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> checks for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bacteria</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000770605" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">yeast</GlossaryTermRef>, or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044059" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microorganisms</GlossaryTermRef> in the urine when there are symptoms of infection. Urine cultures can help identify the type of microorganism that is causing an infection. Treatment of the infection depends on the type of microorganism that is causing the infection.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Ultrasound exam</Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs, such as the bladder, and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_831">Talk to the doctor about whether tests and procedures are needed to check for signs of bladder late effects. If tests are needed, find out how often they should be done.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_111"><Title>To Learn More About Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</Title><Para id="_112">For more information about  late effects of treatment for childhood cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_113" Style="bullet">
   
   
   
  <ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.survivorshipguidelines.org/">Long-Term Follow-Up Guidelines for Survivors of Childhood, Adolescent, and Young Adult Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cogmembers.org/public/lateeffects/default.aspx">Late Effects Directory of Services</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_891">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_892" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors and Caregivers</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the late effects of treatment for childhood cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389365]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000343584"/><DateFirstPublished>2005-03-24</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-02-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
