<Summary id="CDR0000378089" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062723"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS) treatment options include supportive care, drug therapy, and chemotherapy with allogeneic stem cell transplant. Learn more about newly diagnosed or recurrent MDS and its treatment in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/myeloproliferative/patient/myelodysplastic-treatment-pdq">Myelodysplastic Syndromes (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/myeloproliferative/hp/myelodysplastic-treatment-pdq">Myelodysplastic Syndromes (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039817">myelodysplastic syndromes</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_275">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of myelodysplastic syndromes. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_276">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>myelodysplastic syndromes</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>refractory anemia</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>refractory cytopenia</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Myelodysplastic Syndromes Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Myelodysplastic Syndromes Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Myelodysplastic Syndromes Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Myelodysplastic Syndromes </Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Myelodysplastic syndromes are a group of cancers in which immature blood cells in the bone marrow do not mature or become healthy blood cells. </KeyPoint><Para id="_120">In a healthy person, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> makes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765906" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> (immature <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>) that become mature <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> cells over time. </Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000755927" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the bone; drawing shows spongy bone, red marrow, and yellow marrow. A cross section of the bone shows compact bone and blood vessels in the bone marrow. Also shown are red blood cells, white blood cells, platelets, and a blood stem cell." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_273"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the bone. The bone is made up of compact bone, spongy bone, and bone marrow. Compact bone makes up the outer layer of the bone. Spongy bone is found mostly at the ends of bones and contains red marrow. Bone marrow is found in the center of most bones and has many blood vessels. There are two types of bone marrow: red and yellow. Red marrow contains blood stem cells that can become red blood cells, white blood cells, or platelets. Yellow marrow is made mostly of fat.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_272">A blood stem cell may become a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046298" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoid</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell</GlossaryTermRef> or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046279" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myeloid</GlossaryTermRef> stem cell.   A lymphoid stem cell becomes a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cell</GlossaryTermRef>. A myeloid stem cell becomes one of three types of mature blood cells:</Para><ItemizedList id="_121" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> that carry <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> and other substances to all <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> of the body.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Platelets</GlossaryTermRef> that form <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clots</GlossaryTermRef> to stop bleeding.
</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Granulocytes</GlossaryTermRef>, which are white blood cells that help fight <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef> and disease.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526219" type="image/jpeg" alt="Blood cell development; drawing shows the steps a blood stem cell goes through to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell. Drawing shows a myeloid stem cell becoming a red blood cell, platelet, or myeloblast, which then becomes a white blood cell. Drawing also shows a lymphoid stem cell becoming a lymphoblast and then one of several different types of white blood cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_208"><Caption language="en">Blood cell development. A blood stem cell goes through several steps to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_122">In a patient with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelodysplastic syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>, the blood stem cells (immature cells) do not become mature red blood cells, white blood cells, or platelets in the bone marrow.  These immature blood cells, called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046503" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blasts</GlossaryTermRef>, do not work the way they should and either die in the bone marrow or soon after they go into the blood.  This leaves less room for healthy white blood cells, red blood cells, and platelets to form in the bone marrow. When there are fewer healthy blood cells, infection, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef>, or easy bleeding may occur. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_268"><KeyPoint id="_269">The different types of myelodysplastic syndromes are diagnosed based on certain changes in the blood cells and bone marrow.</KeyPoint><ItemizedList id="_160" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Refractory anemia</Strong>: There are too few red blood cells in the blood and the patient has anemia. The number of white blood cells and platelets is normal.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Refractory anemia with ring sideroblasts</Strong>:

There are too few red blood cells in the blood and the patient has anemia. The red blood cells have too much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iron</GlossaryTermRef> inside the cell. The number of white blood cells and platelets is normal.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Refractory anemia with excess blasts</Strong>: There are too few red blood cells in the blood and the patient has anemia. Five percent to 19% of the cells in the bone marrow are blasts. There also may be changes to the white blood cells and platelets. Refractory anemia with excess blasts may progress to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (AML). For more information, see  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000257990" url="/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Refractory cytopenia with multilineage dysplasia</Strong>:

There are too few of at least two types of blood cells (red blood cells, platelets, or white blood cells). Less than 5% of the cells in the bone marrow are blasts and less than 1% of the cells in the blood are blasts. If red blood cells are affected, they may have extra iron. Refractory cytopenia may progress to acute myeloid leukemia (AML). </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Refractory cytopenia with unilineage dysplasia</Strong>: There are too few of one type of blood cell (red blood cells, platelets, or white blood cells). There are changes in 10% or more of two other types of blood cells. Less than 5%  of the cells  in the bone marrow are blasts and less than 1% of the cells in the blood are blasts.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Unclassifiable myelodysplastic syndrome</Strong>:

The numbers of blasts in the bone marrow and blood are normal, and the disease is not one of the other myelodysplastic syndromes. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Myelodysplastic syndrome associated with an isolated del(5q) chromosome abnormality</Strong>:  

There are too few red blood cells in the blood and the patient has anemia.  Less than 5% of the cells in the bone marrow and blood are blasts. There is a specific change in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chronic myelomonocytic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (CMML)</Strong>: For more information, see    <SummaryRef href="CDR0000378291" url="/types/myeloproliferative/patient/mds-mpd-treatment-pdq">Myelodysplastic/Myeloproliferative Neoplasms Treatment</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_5">Age and past treatment with chemotherapy or radiation therapy affect the risk of a myelodysplastic syndrome. </KeyPoint><Para id="_150">Anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop myelodysplastic syndromes, and they will develop in people who don't have any known risk factors. Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk. Risk factors for myelodysplastic syndromes include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_151" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Past treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Being exposed to certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemicals</GlossaryTermRef>, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439432" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tobacco</GlossaryTermRef> smoke, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000411385" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pesticides</GlossaryTermRef>, fertilizers, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solvents</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270734" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benzene</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Being exposed to heavy metals, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285976" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mercury</GlossaryTermRef> or lead.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_239">The cause of myelodysplastic syndromes in most patients is not known.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_12">Signs and symptoms of a myelodysplastic syndrome include shortness of breath and feeling tired.</KeyPoint><Para id="_13">Myelodysplastic syndromes often do not cause early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. They may be found during a routine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045107" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood test</GlossaryTermRef>.  Signs and symptoms may be caused by myelodysplastic syndromes or by other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>. Check with your doctor if you have any of the  following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_14" Style="bullet"> 
    <ListItem>Shortness of breath.
</ListItem><ListItem>Weakness or feeling tired.</ListItem><ListItem>Having skin that is paler than usual.</ListItem><ListItem>Easy bruising or bleeding.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046236" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Petechiae</GlossaryTermRef> (flat, pinpoint spots under the skin caused by bleeding). 
</ListItem> 
     
     
     
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_16">Tests that examine the blood and bone marrow are used to diagnose myelodysplastic syndromes.</KeyPoint><Para id="_17">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18" Style="bullet">
    
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000729979" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Complete blood count (CBC) with differential</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a sample of blood is drawn and checked for the following:   
<ItemizedList id="_125" Style="dash"><ListItem>The number of red blood cells and platelets. 
</ListItem><ListItem>The number and type of white blood cells. </ListItem><ListItem>The amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemoglobin</GlossaryTermRef> (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> that carries oxygen) in the red blood cells.</ListItem><ListItem>The portion of the blood sample made up of red blood cells. 
</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526546" type="image/jpeg" alt="Complete blood count (CBC); left panel shows blood being drawn from a vein on the inside of the elbow using a tube attached to a syringe; right panel shows a laboratory test tube with blood cells separated into layers: plasma, white blood cells, platelets, and red blood cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_202"><Caption language="en">Complete blood count (CBC). Blood is collected by inserting a needle into a vein and allowing the blood to flow into a tube. The blood sample is sent to the laboratory and the red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets are counted.  The CBC is used to test for, diagnose, and monitor many different conditions.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390307" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Peripheral blood smear</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a sample of blood is checked for changes in the number, type, shape, and size of blood cells and for too much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iron</GlossaryTermRef> in the red blood cells.  </ListItem>
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cytogenetic analysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> in which the chromosomes of cells in a sample of bone marrow or blood are counted and checked for any changes, such as broken, missing, rearranged, or extra chromosomes. Changes in certain chromosomes may be a sign of cancer. Cytogenetic analysis is used to help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> cancer, plan treatment, or find out how well treatment is working. </ListItem>
    
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin B12</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">folate</GlossaryTermRef>, released into the blood by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organs</GlossaryTermRef> and tissues in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046505" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone marrow aspiration</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046506" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of  bone marrow, blood, and a small piece of bone  by inserting a   hollow needle into the hipbone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000549425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breastbone</GlossaryTermRef>. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views   the bone marrow, blood, and bone under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> to look for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> cells.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000554337" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy; drawing shows a patient lying face down on a table and a bone marrow needle being inserted into the hip bone. An inset shows a close up of the needle being inserted through the skin and hip bone into the bone marrow." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_215"><Caption language="en">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy. After a small area of skin is numbed, a long, hollow needle is inserted through the patient's skin and hip bone into the bone marrow. A sample of bone marrow and a small piece of bone are removed for examination under a microscope.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_270">The following tests may be done on the sample of tissue that is removed:</Para><ItemizedList id="_271" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000755134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunocytochemistry</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient’s bone marrow. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to the antigen in the sample of the patient’s cells, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to tell the difference between myelodysplastic syndromes, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>, and other conditions. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000341450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunophenotyping</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test that uses antibodies to identify cancer cells based on the types of antigens or markers on the surface of the cells. This test is used to help diagnose specific types of leukemia and other blood disorders. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335066" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Flow cytometry</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test that measures the number of cells in a sample, the percentage of live cells in a sample, and certain characteristics of the cells, such as size, shape, and the presence of tumor (or other) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> on the cell surface. The cells from a sample of a patient’s blood, bone marrow, or other tissue are stained with a fluorescent dye, placed in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef>, and then passed one at a time through a beam of light. The test results are based on how the cells that were stained with the fluorescent dye react to the beam of light. This test is used to help diagnose and manage certain types of cancers, such as leukemia and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460228" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FISH</GlossaryTermRef> (fluorescence in situ hybridization)</Strong>: A laboratory test used to look at and count <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> or chromosomes in cells and tissues. Pieces of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> that contain fluorescent dyes are made in the laboratory and added to a sample of a patient’s cells or tissues. When these dyed pieces of DNA attach to certain genes or areas of chromosomes in the sample, they light up when viewed under a fluorescent microscope. The FISH test is used to help diagnose cancer and help plan treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem>
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Certain factors affect prognosis  (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_21">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef>  and treatment options depend on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>The number of blast cells in the bone marrow.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether one or more types of blood cells are affected.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Whether the patient has signs or symptoms of anemia, bleeding, or infection.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the patient has a low or high risk of leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>	Certain changes in the chromosomes.</ListItem>
    
   <ListItem>Whether the myelodysplastic syndrome occurred after chemotherapy or radiation therapy for cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>The patient's age and general health.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_49"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_50"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_51">There are different types of treatment for patients with myelodysplastic syndromes.</KeyPoint><Para id="_52">Different types of treatment are available for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelodysplastic syndromes</GlossaryTermRef>. Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.  A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.      When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the  standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment. Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_132"><KeyPoint id="_133">Treatment for myelodysplastic syndromes   includes supportive care, drug therapy, and stem cell transplant.</KeyPoint><Para id="_263">Patients with a myelodysplastic syndrome who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> caused by low <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood counts</GlossaryTermRef> are given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supportive care</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve symptoms and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Drug therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may be used to slow <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease. Certain patients can be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cured</GlossaryTermRef> with aggressive treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_58"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_59">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_60"><KeyPoint id="_61">
     Supportive care
    </KeyPoint><Para id="_62">Supportive care is given to lessen the problems caused by the disease or its treatment. Supportive care may include the following:</Para><SummarySection id="_179"><ItemizedList id="_180" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Transfusion therapy
</Strong><Para id="_181">Transfusion <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045991" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood transfusion</GlossaryTermRef>) is a method of giving <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef> to replace blood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> destroyed by disease or treatment.   A red blood cell transfusion is given when the red blood cell count is low and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> or symptoms of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef>, such as shortness of breath or feeling very tired, occur. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelet</GlossaryTermRef> transfusion is usually given when the patient is bleeding, is having a procedure that may cause bleeding, or when the platelet count is very low.</Para><Para id="_264">Patients who receive many blood cell transfusions may have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> damage caused by the buildup of extra <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iron</GlossaryTermRef>. These patients may be treated with iron <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000613204" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chelation</GlossaryTermRef>    therapy to remove the extra <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iron</GlossaryTermRef> from the blood. </Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Erythropoiesis-stimulating agents</Strong><Para id="_183"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000747357" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Erythropoiesis-stimulating agents</GlossaryTermRef> (ESAs) may be given to increase the number of mature red blood cells made by the body and to lessen the effects of anemia.  Sometimes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046749" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">granulocyte colony-stimulating factor</GlossaryTermRef> (G-CSF) is given with ESAs to help the treatment work better.

</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Antibiotic therapy</Strong><Para id="_198"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Antibiotics</GlossaryTermRef> may be given to fight <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_241"><KeyPoint id="_242">Drug therapy</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_243"><ItemizedList id="_244" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Lenalidomide</Strong><Para id="_255">Patients with myelodysplastic syndrome associated with an isolated del(5q) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormality</GlossaryTermRef> who need frequent red blood cell transfusions  may be treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000393761" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lenalidomide</GlossaryTermRef>. Lenalidomide is used to lessen the need for red blood cell transfusions.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Immunosuppressive therapy</Strong><Para id="_256"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Antithymocyte globulin</GlossaryTermRef> (ATG) works to suppress or weaken the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>. It is used to lessen the need for red blood cell transfusions.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Azacitidine and decitabine</Strong><Para id="_257"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045177" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Azacitidine</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045208" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">decitabine</GlossaryTermRef> are used to treat myelodysplastic syndromes by killing cells that are dividing rapidly. They also help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> that are involved in cell growth to work the way they should. Treatment with azacitidine and decitabine may slow the progression of myelodysplastic syndromes to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Chemotherapy used in acute myeloid leukemia (AML)</Strong><Para id="_258">Patients with a myelodysplastic syndrome and a high number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046503" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blasts</GlossaryTermRef> in their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> have a high risk of acute leukemia. They may be treated with the same chemotherapy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimen</GlossaryTermRef> used in patients with acute myeloid leukemia.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_84"><KeyPoint id="_85">Chemotherapy with stem cell transplant</KeyPoint><Para id="_86">Chemotherapy is given to kill cancer cells. Healthy cells, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>-forming cells, are also destroyed by the cancer treatment. Stem cell transplant is a treatment to replace the blood-forming cells. Stem cells (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> of the patient or a donor and are frozen and stored. After the patient completes chemotherapy, the stored stem cells are thawed and given back to the patient through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These reinfused stem cells grow into (and restore) the body's blood cells.</Para><Para id="_265">This treatment may not work as well in patients whose myelodysplastic syndrome was caused by past treatment for cancer. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000765030" type="image/jpeg" alt="Donor stem cell transplant; (Panel 1): Drawing of stem cells being collected from a donor's bloodstream using an apheresis machine. Blood is removed from a vein in the donor's arm and flows through the machine where the stem cells are removed. The rest of the blood is then returned to the donor through a vein in their other arm. (Panel 2): Drawing of a health care provider giving a patient an infusion of chemotherapy through a catheter in the patient's chest. The chemotherapy is given to kill cancer cells and prepare the patient's body for the donor stem cells. (Panel 3): Drawing of a patient receiving an infusion of the donor stem cells through a catheter in the chest." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_274"><Caption language="en">Donor stem cell transplant. (Step 1): Four to five days before donor stem cell collection, the donor receives a medicine to increase the number of stem cells circulating through their bloodstream (not shown). The blood-forming stem cells are then collected from the donor through a large vein in their arm. The blood flows through an apheresis machine that removes the stem cells. The rest of the blood is returned to the donor through a vein in their other arm. (Step 2): The patient receives chemotherapy to kill cancer cells and prepare their body for the donor stem cells. The patient may also receive radiation therapy (not shown). (Step 3): The patient receives an infusion of the donor stem cells.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_205"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_206">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_207">Information about clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_277"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_278">Treatment for myelodysplastic syndromes may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_277_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_209"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_210">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_209_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_209_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_209_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_211"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_212">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_211_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_211_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_213"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_214">Follow-up tests may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_213_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_213_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_92"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000743368">adult myelodysplastic syndromes</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of  Myelodysplastic Syndromes</Title><Para id="_279">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000378089#_58" url="/types/myeloproliferative/patient/myelodysplastic-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_281">The treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelodysplastic syndromes</GlossaryTermRef> may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_282" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Supportive care</GlossaryTermRef> with one or more of the following:<ItemizedList id="_260" Style="dash">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Transfusion</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000747357" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Erythropoiesis-stimulating agents</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Antibiotic</GlossaryTermRef> therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Treatments to slow <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression</GlossaryTermRef> to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> (AML):<ItemizedList id="_248" Style="dash">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000393761" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lenalidomide</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045728" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunosuppressive therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045177" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Azacitidine</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045208" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">decitabine</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> used in acute myeloid leukemia.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_283">Patients who were treated in the past with chemotherapy or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may develop <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046279" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myeloid</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neoplasms</GlossaryTermRef> related to that therapy. Treatment options  are the same as for other myelodysplastic syndromes.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_92_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_101"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000743368">adult myelodysplastic syndromes</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Relapsed or Refractory Myelodysplastic Syndromes</Title><Para id="_280">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000378089#_58" url="/types/myeloproliferative/patient/myelodysplastic-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_240">There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapsed</GlossaryTermRef>    <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelodysplastic syndromes</GlossaryTermRef>. Patients whose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>  does not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment or has come back after treatment may want to take part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_101_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_199"><Title>To Learn More About Myelodysplastic Syndromes</Title><Para id="_200">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  myelodysplastic syndromes, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_227" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/stem-cell-transplant">Stem Cell Transplants in Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_199_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_199_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of myelodysplastic syndromes.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Myelodysplastic Syndromes Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/myeloproliferative/patient/myelodysplastic-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/myeloproliferative/patient/myelodysplastic-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389239]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062929"/><DateFirstPublished>2005-02-18</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-04</DateLastModified></Summary>
