<Summary id="CDR0000403689" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062842"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Ewing sarcoma treatment usually begins with chemotherapy and/or radiation followed by surgery to remove any remaining cancer. Treatment options for recurrent sarcoma include targeted therapy and high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell transplant. Learn more in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">Ewing Sarcoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Ewing Sarcoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000546979">Ewing sarcoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000546986">peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_236">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood Ewing sarcoma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_237">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Ewing sarcoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Ewing Sarcoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Ewing Sarcoma Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Ewing Sarcoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Ewing Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Ewing sarcoma is a type of cancer that forms from a certain kind of cell in bone or soft tissue.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046031" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ewing sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> may form in the bones of the legs, arms, feet, hands, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chest</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef>. It may also form in the body's  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissues</GlossaryTermRef>, which connect, support, and surround other body parts and organs.</Para><Para id="_123">Ewing sarcoma is most common in adolescents and young adults (teens through mid-20s).</Para><Para id="_247">Ewing sarcoma has also been called peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor, Askin tumor (Ewing sarcoma of the chest wall),  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476629" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extraosseous</GlossaryTermRef> Ewing sarcoma (Ewing sarcoma in tissue other than bone), and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ewing sarcoma family of tumors</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_279"><KeyPoint id="_271">Undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma may also form in the bone or soft tissue.</KeyPoint><Para id="_272"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Undifferentiated</GlossaryTermRef> small round cell sarcoma usually forms in the bones or the muscles that are attached to bones and that help the body move. Undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma is usually treated the same way as Ewing sarcoma. Types of undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_273" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> rearrangements.</Strong> This type of round cell sarcoma usually forms in the pelvis, arms, or legs and may spread to other parts of the body. It is more common in children younger than 18 years. In this type of round cell sarcoma, the <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is joined to the <GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName> gene or to other genes. To <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> this round cell sarcoma, the tumor cells are checked for these gene changes.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma with <GeneName>CIC::DUX4</GeneName> rearrangements.</Strong> This type of round cell sarcoma usually forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000796908" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trunk</GlossaryTermRef>, arms, or legs. It is most common in males and in young adults. In this type of round cell sarcoma, the <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene is joined to the <GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> gene. To diagnose this round cell sarcoma, the tumor cells are checked for this gene change.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma with <GeneName>CIC::NUTM1</GeneName> rearrangements.</Strong> This type of soft tissue tumor usually forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef>, but it can also form in the trunk. It is most common in children about 6 years of age.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma with <GeneName>ATXN1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM2A</GeneName> or <GeneName>ATXN1L</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM2A</GeneName> fusions.</Strong> This type of soft tissue tumor has been found in three children. All were newborns or infants, and the cancer was in the central nervous system or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma with <GeneName>EWSR1::NFATC2</GeneName> and <GeneName>FUS::NFATC2</GeneName> rearrangements.</Strong> This type of soft tissue tumor may be a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045614" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046461" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyst</GlossaryTermRef> or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> (cancer) tumor. It usually forms in the arms and legs. The malignant tumor is more common in males and in adults.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma with <GeneName>EWSR1::PATZ1</GeneName> fusions.</Strong> This type of soft tissue tumor usually forms in the trunk and is more common in adults.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_334"><KeyPoint id="_335">A genetic condition may increase the risk of Ewing sarcoma and other sarcomas.</KeyPoint><Para id="_342">Ewing sarcoma is caused by certain changes to the way bone cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_336">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with a risk factor will develop Ewing sarcoma or other sarcomas. And they can develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. Children with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fanconi anemia</GlossaryTermRef> may be at increased risk of Ewing sarcoma. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_15">Symptoms of Ewing sarcoma include swelling and pain near the tumor.</KeyPoint><Para id="_16">It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_115" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a lump (which may feel soft and warm) in the arms, legs, chest, or pelvis</ListItem><ListItem>pain and/or swelling near the lump</ListItem><ListItem>fever for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>a bone that breaks for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>a limp when walking </ListItem><ListItem>fatigue</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss</ListItem><ListItem>anemia</ListItem><ListItem>shortness of breath</ListItem><ListItem>back pain, weakness, numbness, or paralysis in the arms or legs</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_343">These <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by problems other than Ewing sarcoma. The only way to know is for your child to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_19">Tests that examine the bone and soft tissue are used to diagnose and stage Ewing sarcoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_224">If your child has symptoms that suggest Ewing sarcoma, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They also will ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with Ewing sarcoma, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_344">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. To plan treatment, it is important to know whether the cancer has spread to other parts of the body. Tests and procedures to detect, diagnose, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> Ewing sarcoma are usually done at the same time.</Para><Para id="_345">The tests used to diagnose and stage Ewing sarcoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet">
    
    
    <ListItem><Strong>MRI (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the area where the tumor formed. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_242"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem>
    <ListItem><Strong>CT scan (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the area where the tumor formed or the chest.  The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs.  A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_243"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem>
    <ListItem><Strong>PET-CT scan</Strong> combines the pictures from a positron emission tomography scan (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef>) and CT scan. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time on the same machine. The pictures from both scans are combined to make a more detailed picture than either test would make by itself. For the PET scan, a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> sugar (radioactive glucose) is injected into a vein. The scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where the sugar is being used in the body. Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more sugar than normal cells do.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775456" type="image/jpeg" alt="Positron emission tomography (PET) scan; drawing shows a child lying on table that slides through the PET scanner." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_244"><Caption language="en">Positron emission tomography (PET) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the PET scanner. The head rest and white strap help the child lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the child's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Bone scan</Strong> checks if there are rapidly dividing cells, such as cancer cells, in the bone.  A very small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> material is injected into a vein and travels through the bloodstream.  The radioactive material collects in the bones with cancer and is detected by a scanner.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775451" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides under the scanner, a technician operating the scanner, and a computer monitor that will show images made during the scan." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_245"><Caption language="en">Bone scan.  A small amount of radioactive material is injected into the child's vein and travels through the blood. The radioactive material collects in the bones. As the child lies on a table that slides under the scanner, the radioactive material is detected and images are made on a computer screen.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046505" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone marrow aspiration</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046506" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> removes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> and a small piece of bone by inserting a hollow needle into the hipbone. Samples are removed from both hipbones. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the bone marrow and bone under a microscope to see if the cancer has spread. This test is only used if other tests have shown that the cancer may have spread from where it first formed.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775458" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy; drawing shows a child lying face down on a table and a bone marrow needle being inserted into the right hip bone. An inset shows the bone marrow needle being inserted through the skin into the bone marrow of the hip bone." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_246"><Caption language="en">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy. After a small area of skin is numbed, a bone marrow needle  is inserted into the child’s hip bone.  Samples of blood, bone, and bone marrow are removed for examination under a microscope.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem>
   <ListItem><Strong>X-ray</Strong> is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest or the area where the tumor formed.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045107" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Complete blood count</GlossaryTermRef> (CBC)</Strong> checks a sample of blood for:<ItemizedList id="_144" Style="dash"><ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the amount of hemoglobin (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> that carries <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef>) in the red blood cells</ListItem><ListItem>the portion of the blood sample made up of red blood cells</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry study</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lactate dehydrogenase</GlossaryTermRef> (LDH), released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Biopsy</Strong> is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the tumor so that a pathologist can view it under a microscope to check for cancer. The following types of biopsies are used to check for Ewing sarcoma:<ItemizedList id="_204" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Incisional biopsy</Strong> removes a sample of tissue through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> in the skin.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Needle biopsy</Strong> uses a needle to remove a sample of tissue.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_210">The child's pathologist, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044306" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgeon</GlossaryTermRef> usually work together to decide the best site to place the needle or biopsy incision. The selection of the biopsy site is important. A biopsy site that is not properly selected may result in more extensive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the tumor or a larger area that is treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_205">If there is a chance that the cancer has spread to nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, one or more lymph nodes may be removed and checked for cancer.</Para><Para id="_147">The following tests may be done on the tissue that is removed:</Para><ItemizedList id="_148" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Cytogenetic analysis</Strong> is a test in which the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosomes</GlossaryTermRef> of cells in a sample of tissue are counted and checked for any changes, such as broken, missing, rearranged, or extra chromosomes. Changes in certain chromosomes may be a sign of cancer. Cytogenetic analysis is used to help diagnose cancer, plan treatment, or find out how well treatment is working.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Immunohistochemistry</Strong> is a test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient's tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Flow cytometry</Strong> measures the number of cells in a sample, the percentage of live cells in a sample, and certain characteristics of the cells, such as size, shape, and the presence of tumor (or other) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> on the cell surface. The cells from a sample of a patient's blood, bone marrow, or other tissue are stained with a fluorescent dye, placed in a fluid, and then passed one at a time through a beam of light. The test results are based on how the cells that were stained with the fluorescent dye react to the beam of light.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Molecular test</Strong> checks for certain genes, proteins, or other molecules in a sample of tissue, blood, or other body fluid. A molecular test may be done with other procedures, such as biopsies, to help diagnose some types of cancer. Molecular tests check for certain gene or chromosome changes that occur in some Ewing sarcomas.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RT–PCR</GlossaryTermRef>) test</Strong> measures the amount of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> substance called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000662001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mRNA</GlossaryTermRef> made by a specific gene. An enzyme called reverse transcriptase is used to convert a specific piece of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046568" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RNA</GlossaryTermRef> into a matching piece of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef>, which can be amplified (made in large numbers) by another enzyme called DNA polymerase. The amplified DNA copies help tell whether a specific mRNA is being made by a gene. RT–PCR can be used to check the activation of certain genes that may indicate the presence of cancer cells. This test may be used to look for certain changes in a gene or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef>, which may help diagnose cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_23">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery).</KeyPoint><Para id="_24">If your child has been diagnosed with Ewing sarcoma, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis. The factors that affect prognosis are different before and after treatment.  </Para><Para id="_152">Before any treatment is given, prognosis depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_128" Style="bullet"><ListItem>whether the tumor has spread to lymph nodes or distant parts of the body</ListItem><ListItem>where in the body the tumor started</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor formed in the bone or in soft tissue</ListItem><ListItem>how large the tumor is when the tumor is diagnosed</ListItem><ListItem>whether the LDH level in the blood is higher than normal</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor has certain gene changes</ListItem><ListItem>whether tumor cells or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> has been found in the blood</ListItem><ListItem>your child's age</ListItem><ListItem>your child's sex</ListItem><ListItem>whether your child has had treatment for a different  cancer</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor has just been diagnosed or has come back</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_149">After treatment is given, prognosis is affected by:</Para><ItemizedList id="_150" Style="bullet"><ListItem>whether the tumor was completely removed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">responded</GlossaryTermRef> to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or radiation therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_226">If the cancer recurs after initial treatment, prognosis depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_227" Style="bullet"><ListItem>whether the cancer came back more than two years after the initial treatment</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer came back where it first formed and in other parts of the body, or whether the cancer came back in only one site</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><Title>Stages of Ewing Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_106"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_107">Ewing sarcoma is described as localized, metastatic, or recurrent.</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_108"><KeyPoint id="_109">Localized Ewing sarcoma</KeyPoint><Para id="_110">The cancer is found in  the bone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue</GlossaryTermRef> where it began and may have  spread to nearby tissue, including nearby lymph nodes.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_111"><KeyPoint id="_112">Metastatic Ewing sarcoma</KeyPoint><Para id="_113"> 
The cancer has spread from the bone or soft tissue where it began to other parts of the body. In Ewing sarcoma of bone, the cancer most often spreads to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, other bones, and bone marrow.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_268"><KeyPoint id="_269">Recurrent Ewing sarcoma</KeyPoint><Para id="_270">The cancer has recurred (come back) after it has been treated. The cancer may come back in the bone or soft tissue where it began or in another part of the body.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_47"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_52"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_53">Children with Ewing sarcoma should have their treatment planned by a team of            health care providers who are experts in treating cancer in children.</KeyPoint><Para id="_54">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of Ewing sarcoma. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with Ewing sarcoma and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_55" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgical oncologist</GlossaryTermRef> or orthopedic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046260" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef> </ListItem>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
   <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_49">There are different types of treatment for children with Ewing sarcoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_346">You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as where the cancer is located, your child's age and overall health, and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_347">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the tumor, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, visit our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_56"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_57">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_65"><KeyPoint id="_66">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_151">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cancer cells or stops them from dividing.</Para><Para id="_348">Chemotherapy for Ewing sarcoma is taken by mouth or injected into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body. Systemic combination chemotherapy is often given to shrink the tumor before <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and to kill any cancer cells that have spread to other parts of the body. It is often the first treatment given and lasts for about 6 to 12 months.</Para><Para id="_349">Chemotherapy drugs used alone or in combination to treat Ewing sarcoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_350" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496383" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/docetaxel">docetaxel</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000542867" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/doxorubicinhydrochloride">doxorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495426" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemcitabinehydrochloride">gemcitabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000686471" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ifosfamide">ifosfamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537382" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecanhydrochloride">irinotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496409" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/temozolomide">temozolomide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495675" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/topotecanhydrochloride">topotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599877" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vincristinesulfate">vincristine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_351">Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_352">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><KeyPoint id="_63">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_64">Radiation therapy uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Ewing sarcoma is treated with external beam radiation therapy. This type of therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para><Para id="_200">Radiation therapy is used when the tumor cannot be removed by surgery or when surgery to remove the tumor will affect important body functions or the way the child will look. It may be used to make the tumor smaller and decrease the amount of tissue that needs to be removed during surgery. It may also be used to treat any tumor that remains after surgery and tumors that have spread to other parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_337">Radiation therapy may also be used as palliative therapy to relieve symptoms caused by the tumor in the bone.</Para><Para id="_353">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_206"><KeyPoint id="_192">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_193">Surgery is usually done to remove cancer that is left after chemotherapy or radiation therapy. When possible, the whole tumor is removed by surgery. Tissue and bone that are removed may be replaced with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046373" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">graft</GlossaryTermRef>, which uses tissue and bone taken from another part of the child's body or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef>. Sometimes an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">implant</GlossaryTermRef>, such as artificial bone, is used.</Para><Para id="_194">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some children may be given chemotherapy or radiation therapy to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after the surgery to lower the risk that the cancer will come back is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_233"><KeyPoint id="_234">Stem cell transplant</KeyPoint><Para id="_235">High <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells. These treatments destroy healthy cells, including blood-forming cells. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment to replace the blood-forming cells. Stem cells (immature blood cells) are removed from the child's blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045263" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> and are frozen and stored. After the child completes chemotherapy, the stored stem cells are thawed and given back to the child through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These reinfused stem cells grow into (and restore) the body's blood cells. Stem cell transplant is used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">localized</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> Ewing sarcoma.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_80"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_81">You may want to think about having your child take part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_80_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_80_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_80_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_255">Treatment for Ewing sarcoma may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_354">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_118_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_120"> 
Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_130" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer), such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myelodysplastic syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> in the areas treated with radiation therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_131">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the effects cancer treatment can have on your child. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_163"><KeyPoint id="_164">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_163_md_55">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_163_md_56">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_355">To learn more about these follow-up tests, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000403689#_19" url="/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">Tests to diagnose Ewing sarcoma</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_280"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043411">localized Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Localized Ewing Sarcoma </Title><Para id="_282">Treatments for newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">localized</GlossaryTermRef> Ewing sarcoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_283" Style="bullet"><ListItem>chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>surgery and/or radiation therapy</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> with the child's own cells</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_356">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000403689#_56" url="/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_280_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_284"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043412">metastatic Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_286">Treatments for newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> Ewing sarcoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_287" Style="bullet"><ListItem>chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>surgery</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_357">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000403689#_56" url="/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_284_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_288"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043413">recurrent Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_290">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> Ewing sarcoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_291" Style="bullet"><ListItem>combination chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>surgery</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy to bone tumors, as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy that may be followed by  surgery to remove tumors that have spread to the lungs</ListItem>
    
    
   <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> with the child's own cells</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_358">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000403689#_56" url="/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_288_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_142"><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone">Bone Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/bone-fact-sheet">Bone Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood Ewing sarcoma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Ewing Sarcoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389350]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062841"/><DateFirstPublished>2007-12-14</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-02-28</DateLastModified></Summary>
