<Summary id="CDR0000415235" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Wilms tumor forms in the kidney in children and, rarely, adults. Learn about the risk factors and symptoms and how Wilms tumor is diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">Wilms Tumor and Other Childhood Kidney Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/hp/wilms-treatment-pdq">Wilms Tumor and Other Childhood Kidney Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000775589">Wilms tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_425">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of Wilms tumor and other childhood kidney tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_426">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Childhood </SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Cystic partially differentiated nephroblastoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Nephroblastomatosis</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Wilms tumor</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Wilms Tumor (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Wilms Tumor</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Wilms Tumor</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_477"><Title>What is Wilms tumor?</Title><Para id="_478">Wilms tumor (also called nephroblastoma) is the most common type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney cancer</GlossaryTermRef> in children younger than 15 years. In the United States, about 650 children are diagnosed with it each year, and  most are between the ages of 2 and 5 years. Wilms tumor can occur in older adolescents and adults, but this is rare.</Para><Para id="_479">The kidneys are bean-shaped organs located on either side of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>, above the waist. Their main job is to remove waste and extra fluids from the body to make urine:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18224" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tiny tubules in the kidneys filter and clean the blood.</ListItem><ListItem>Urine passes from each kidney through a thin tube called a ureter into the bladder.</ListItem><ListItem>The bladder stores the urine until it leaves the body through a tube called the urethra.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000666578" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the urinary system; drawing showing the right and left kidneys, the ureters, the bladder filled with urine, and the urethra. The inside of the left kidney shows the renal pelvis. An inset shows the renal tubules and urine. The spine and adrenal glands are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_279"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the urinary system showing the kidneys, ureters, bladder, and urethra. The inside of the left kidney shows the renal pelvis. An inset shows the renal tubules and urine. Also shown is the spine and adrenal glands. Urine is made in the renal tubules and collects in the renal pelvis of each kidney. The urine flows from the kidneys through the ureters to the bladder. The urine is stored in the bladder until it leaves the body through the urethra.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_480">Wilms tumor can affect one or both kidneys. It may spread to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000801547" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_481">A rare  type of Wilms tumor called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046461" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cystic</GlossaryTermRef> partially <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">differentiated</GlossaryTermRef> nephroblastoma is made of cysts and usually occurs in young children.</Para><Para id="_18217">During fetal development, some kidney cells may not develop normally. These abnormal groups of kidney cells may remain in one or both kidneys after birth, and in some cases, may lead to nephroblastomatosis (also called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000534219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diffuse hyperplastic perilobar nephroblastomatosis</GlossaryTermRef>) or Wilms tumor. In nephroblastomatosis (a non-cancerous kidney condition),  these abnormal groups of cells may grow in many places inside the kidney or make a thick layer around the kidney. These abnormal groups of cells most often occur in both kidneys. Although nephroblastomatosis is not cancer, it can develop into Wilms tumor if left untreated. If a child has one kidney removed because of Wilms tumor and doctors find nephroblastomatosis in the removed kidney, the child has a higher risk of Wilms tumor in the remaining kidney.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_483"><Title>Causes and risk factors for Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_484">Wilms tumor is caused by certain changes to the way the kidney cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. The exact cause of these changes is often unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_485">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with one or more of these risk factors will develop a kidney tumor. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. </Para><Para id="_486">Wilms tumor may be part of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> that affects growth or development. A genetic syndrome is a set of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> or conditions that occur together and is caused by certain changes in the genes. Certain conditions or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000802104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">environmental exposures</GlossaryTermRef> can also increase your child's risk of developing Wilms tumor. The following have been linked to Wilms tumor:</Para><ItemizedList id="_10" Style="bullet"> 
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">WAGR syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (also called WAGR spectrum) includes Wilms tumor, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aniridia</GlossaryTermRef>, abnormal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046381" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genitourinary system</GlossaryTermRef>, and mental developmental delays</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Denys-Drash syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>Frasier syndrome </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304689" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> includes an abnormally large growth of one or more body parts, a  large tongue, an umbilical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000630906" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hernia</GlossaryTermRef> at birth, and an abnormal genitourinary system </ListItem> 
    <ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of Wilms tumor</ListItem><ListItem>aniridia (part or all of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000534221" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iris</GlossaryTermRef>, the colored part of the eye, is missing) </ListItem><ListItem>isolated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemihypertrophy</GlossaryTermRef>, an abnormally large growth of one or more body parts</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinary tract</GlossaryTermRef> problems, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046458" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cryptorchidism</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypospadias</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
     
     
   <ListItem>a mother being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000411385" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pesticides</GlossaryTermRef> while she was <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pregnant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_487">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_488"><Title>Monitoring children at risk of Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_489">Some children have a higher risk of Wilms tumor. Regular testing can help find cancer at an earlier stage and improve your child's chance of survival. If your child has a higher risk of Wilms tumor, they may have an abdominal ultrasound for Wilms tumor every 3 months until they are at least 8 years old. This test can find small Wilms tumors before symptoms occur.</Para><SummarySection id="_18218"><Title>Testing for children with Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome or hemihypertrophy</Title><Para id="_492">Children with Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome or hemihypertrophy are at risk of tumors in the liver, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adrenal</GlossaryTermRef> glands, and kidneys. These children may receive testing to find Wilms tumor before symptoms occur. The testing schedule may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18219" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Until age 4 years, a blood test to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046208" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alpha-fetoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> (AFP) levels and an abdominal ultrasound.</ListItem><ListItem>For ages 4 to 8 years, an ultrasound of the kidneys and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723337" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">geneticist</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric oncologist</GlossaryTermRef> twice a year. Some children with certain gene changes may have a different schedule for an abdominal ultrasound.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18220"><Title>Testing for children with aniridia</Title><Para id="_18221">Children with aniridia and a certain gene change may have an abdominal ultrasound every 3 months until age 8 years to look for Wilms tumor. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18222"><Title>Testing for children at risk of Wilms tumor in the second kidney</Title><Para id="_494">Some children are diagnosed with Wilms tumor in both kidneys at the same time. Wilms tumor may also occur in the second kidney after your child is successfully treated for Wilms tumor in one kidney. If your child is at risk of developing Wilms tumor in the second kidney, they should have an abdominal ultrasound every 3 months for up to 8 years to monitor for any new tumors. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_502"><Title>Symptoms of Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_503">Sometimes Wilms tumor causes symptoms. But sometimes a parent may notice a lump in their child's abdomen or notice that their child's stomach looks bigger than before. In some cases, a doctor finds the tumor during a routine check-up. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_504" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a lump, swelling, or pain in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>blood in the urine</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>fever for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>loss of appetite</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>a cough</ListItem><ListItem>blood in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045883" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sputum</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>chest pain</ListItem><ListItem>pain in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>fever</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_507">These symptoms may also be caused by other problems. The only way to know is for your child to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_508"><Title>Diagnosis of Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_509">If your child has symptoms that suggest Wilms tumor, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. The doctor will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend tests to find out if your child has Wilms tumor, and if so, its extent (stage).</Para><SummarySection id="_510"><Title>Tests to diagnose Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_511">The following tests may be used to diagnose Wilms tumor. The results of these tests will help plan treatment.</Para><SummarySection id="_512"><Title>Lab tests</Title><ItemizedList id="_513" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045107" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Complete blood
			 count</GlossaryTermRef> (CBC)</Strong> checks a sample of blood for:<ItemizedList id="_151" Style="dash"><ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and
				  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
				<ListItem>the amount of hemoglobin (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> that carries <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef>) in
				  the red blood cells</ListItem> 
				<ListItem>the amount of hematocrit (whole blood that is made up of red blood cells)</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry study</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign that the liver and kidneys are not working as they should.</ListItem>
    
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Renal function test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by the kidneys. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign that the kidneys are not working as they should.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Urinalysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> checks the color of urine and its contents, such as sugar, protein, blood, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bacteria</GlossaryTermRef>. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign that the kidneys are not working as they should.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_514"><Title>Imaging tests and procedures</Title><ItemizedList id="_515" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Ultrasound</Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. An ultrasound of the abdomen is done to diagnose a kidney tumor.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775457" type="image/jpeg" alt="Abdominal ultrasound; drawing shows a child lying on an exam table during an abdominal ultrasound procedure. A technician is shown pressing a transducer (a device that makes sound waves that bounce off tissues inside the body) against the skin of the abdomen. A computer screen shows a sonogram (picture)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_427"><Caption language="en">Abdominal ultrasound. An ultrasound transducer connected to a computer is pressed against the skin of the abdomen. The transducer bounces sound waves off internal organs and tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture).</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CT scan (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest, abdomen, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs.  A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_428"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with gadolinium</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the  abdomen or pelvis. A substance called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597153" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gadolinium</GlossaryTermRef> is injected into  a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).
<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_429"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>X-ray</Strong> is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> that can go through the body and make pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest and abdomen.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000742485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET-CT scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> combines the pictures from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046218" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">positron emission tomography (PET) scan</GlossaryTermRef> and a computed tomography (CT) scan. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time on the same machine. The combined scans make more detailed pictures than either test would make by itself. <ItemizedList id="_1695" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For the PET scan, a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> sugar (also called radioactive glucose)  is injected into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes pictures of where sugar is being used in the body. Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more sugar than normal cells do.</ListItem><ListItem>For the CT scan (CAT scan), a series of detailed x-ray pictures are taken from different angles to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of a sample of cells or  tissue from the tumor so that a pathologist can view it under a microscope to check for  cancer. The decision of whether to do a biopsy is based on: <ItemizedList id="_260" Style="dash"><ListItem>The size of the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer. There will not be a biopsy if the tumor can be removed with surgery or is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. The reason for not doing a biopsy is to avoid the spread of tumor cells during the procedure.</ListItem><ListItem>Where in the kidney the tumor is and whether cancer is in one or both kidneys.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether imaging tests clearly show the cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the child is participating in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1696">A biopsy may be done before your child has any treatment, after chemotherapy, or during surgery.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1697"><Title>Tests to stage Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_1698">If your child is diagnosed with a Wilms tumor, you will be referred to a pediatric oncologist. This is a doctor who specializes in childhood cancers. They will recommend tests to determine the extent of the cancer. The cancer may only be in one spot, but sometimes it spreads to other parts of the body. The process of learning the extent of the cancer in the body is called staging. It is important to know the stage of the tumor to plan the best treatment.</Para><Para id="_1699">The following tests and procedures may be used to determine the stage of the Wilms tumor:</Para><SummarySection id="_1700"><Title>Lab tests</Title><ItemizedList id="_1701" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Renal function test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390293" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Liver function test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a blood sample to check how the liver is functioning.  The blood sample is used to check the liver enzymes and to measure the amounts of certain substances (such as bilirubin) that are released into the blood by the liver. A higher-than-normal amount of a substance can be a sign that the liver is not working as it should.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1702"><Title>Imaging tests and procedures</Title><ItemizedList id="_152" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of all or part of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> in the abdomen. A pathologist views the lymph node tissue under a microscope to check for cancer cells. This procedure is also called lymph  node sampling.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">X-ray</GlossaryTermRef> of the chest and bones</Strong>.

</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000742485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET-CT scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> checks if there are rapidly dividing cells, such as cancer cells, in the bone.  A very small amount of radioactive material is injected into a vein and travels through the bloodstream.  The radioactive material collects in the areas of the bones with cancer and is detected by a scanner.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> of the major blood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vessels</GlossaryTermRef> of the heart is done to see if the tumor has started to grow in a blood vessel that returns the blood to the heart.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1703"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_1704">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the genetic testing report, pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's tumor.</Para><Para id="_1705">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_495"><Title>Genetic counseling for children with Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_496">It is not always clear from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> whether a child with Wilms tumor has an inherited condition that increased their risk. Genetic counseling can assess the likelihood that your child's cancer is inherited and whether <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef> is needed. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic counselors</GlossaryTermRef> and other specially trained health professionals can discuss your child's diagnosis and your family's medical history to help you understand the:</Para><ItemizedList id="_497" Style="bullet"><ListItem>options for testing for syndromes that may increase the risk of cancer</ListItem><ListItem>risk of your child developing other types of cancer</ListItem><ListItem>risk of kidney tumors and other cancers for your child's siblings</ListItem><ListItem>risks and benefits of learning genetic information</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_498">Genetic counselors can also help you cope with your child's genetic testing results, including how to discuss the results with family members. They can advise you about whether other members in your family should receive genetic testing.</Para><Para id="_499">Genetic counseling may be done if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_500" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a genetic syndrome or condition that increases the risk of Wilms tumor</ListItem><ListItem>Wilms tumors in both kidneys</ListItem><ListItem>Wilms tumor that is diagnosed before age 2 years</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_501">To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/genetic-testing-fact-sheet">Genetic Testing for Inherited Cancer Risk</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_29"><Title>Stages of Wilms tumor </Title><Para id="_1706">Staging is the process of learning the extent of the cancer in the body. Sometimes cancer is only in the kidney. Or, it may have spread to other parts of the body. </Para><Para id="_1708">Besides stages, Wilms tumors are described by their histology, which refers to how the cells look under a microscope. The histology affects the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and the treatment of Wilms tumor.</Para><Para id="_1709">The histology may be favorable or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> (unfavorable):</Para><ItemizedList id="_18223" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tumors with a favorable histology have a better prognosis and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> better to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> than anaplastic tumors. </ListItem><ListItem>Tumor cells that are anaplastic divide quickly and do not look like the type of cells they came from when viewed under a microscope. Anaplastic tumors are harder to treat with chemotherapy than other Wilms tumors at the same stage.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_37"><Title>Stage I</Title><Para id="_39">In stage I, the tumor was completely removed by surgery and all of the following are true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_158" Style="bullet"><ListItem>cancer was found only in the kidney and did not spread to blood vessels in the renal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sinus</GlossaryTermRef> (the part of the kidney where it joins the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureter</GlossaryTermRef>) or to the lymph nodes</ListItem><ListItem>no cancer cells         were found at the edges of the area where the tumor was removed</ListItem><ListItem> the outer layer of the kidney did not break open</ListItem><ListItem>the tumor did not break open</ListItem><ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> was not done before the tumor was removed</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_40"><Title>Stage II</Title><Para id="_170">In stage II, the tumor was completely removed by surgery and no cancer cells     were found at the edges of the area where the cancer was removed. Cancer has not spread to the lymph nodes. Before the tumor was removed, one of the following was also  true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_171" Style="bullet"><ListItem>cancer had spread  to the renal sinus (the part of the kidney where it joins the ureter)</ListItem><ListItem>cancer had spread to blood vessels outside the area of the kidney where <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef> is made, such as the renal sinus</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><Title>Stage III</Title><Para id="_45">In stage III, cancer remains in the abdomen after surgery and at least one of the  following is true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_146" Style="bullet"><ListItem>cancer has spread to the lymph nodes in the abdomen or pelvis (the part of the body between the hips)</ListItem><ListItem>cancer has spread to or through the surface of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef> (the tissue that lines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef> and covers most organs in the abdomen)</ListItem><ListItem>a biopsy of the tumor was done before it was removed</ListItem><ListItem>the tumor broke open before or during surgery to remove it</ListItem><ListItem>the tumor was removed in more than one piece </ListItem><ListItem>cancer cells are found at the edges of the area where the tumor was removed</ListItem><ListItem>the entire tumor could not be removed because important organs or tissues in the body would be damaged</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_46"><Title>Stage IV</Title><Para id="_48">In stage IV, cancer has spread through the blood to other parts of the body such as the lungs, liver, bone, or brain, or to lymph nodes outside the abdomen and pelvis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_49"><Title>Stage V</Title><Para id="_51">In stage V (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045615" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilateral</GlossaryTermRef>) Wilms tumor, cancer cells are found in both kidneys when the cancer is first diagnosed. The cancer in each kidney is staged separately as stage I, II, III, or IV.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1710"><Title>Recurrent Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_1711">Recurrent Wilms tumor is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. If there are signs that the cancer has returned, your child will have tests to find out where the cancer is in your child's body and if it has spread. </Para><Para id="_1712">The type of treatment that your child will have depends on whether the Wilms tumor came back in the kidney or came back in other places in the body, such as the lungs, abdomen, or liver.</Para><Para id="_1713">Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000415235#_376" url="/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">Treatment of recurrent Wilms tumor</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1714"><Title>Types of treatment for Wilms tumor</Title><SummarySection id="_1715"><Title>Who treats children with Wilms tumor?</Title><Para id="_1716">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of Wilms tumor. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children and specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1694" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18225"><Title>Treatment options</Title><Para id="_1717">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with Wilms tumor. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as: </Para><ItemizedList id="_18214" Style="bullet"><ListItem>your child's overall health</ListItem><ListItem>the stage of your child's tumor</ListItem><ListItem>the histology (favorable or anaplastic)</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of cancer coming back after treatment</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to other areas in the body</ListItem><ListItem>whether both kidneys have cancer</ListItem><ListItem>whether your child has an inherited cancer syndrome</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18215">The goal of treatment is to kill the cancer cells and decrease the risk of late effects from treatment.</Para><Para id="_1718">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, visit our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1719">Types of treatment your child might have include:</Para><SummarySection id="_1720"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_1721">Children with Wilms tumor may have surgery to obtain a biopsy sample or to remove the cancer. There are two types of surgery used to treat Wilms tumors:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1722" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nephrectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is surgery to remove the whole kidney. This is the most common treatment for Wilms tumor. Nearby lymph nodes may also be removed and checked for cancer. If the cancer is in both kidneys and they are not working well, your child may need a kidney <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef>. A transplant is surgery to remove the kidney and replace it with one from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000344353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Partial nephrectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is the removal of the cancer in the kidney and a small amount of normal tissue around it. Your child may have this surgery if cancer is found in both kidneys or if it is likely to spread to both kidneys. The goal of the surgery is to keep as much of the kidney as possible. A partial nephrectomy is also called renal-sparing surgery.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1723">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, your child may have chemotherapy or radiation therapy to kill any cancer cells that are left.</Para><Para id="_1724">Sometimes, the tumor cannot be removed because:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1725" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the tumor is too close to important organs or blood vessels or is growing in important blood vessels (such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044154" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inferior vena cava</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>the tumor is too large to remove</ListItem><ListItem>the cancer is in both kidneys, unless the tumors are very small</ListItem><ListItem>there is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clot</GlossaryTermRef> in the vessels near the liver</ListItem><ListItem>the cancer has spread to the lungs, and your child has trouble breathing</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1726">If the tumor cannot be removed, your child will have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> first. Then, they will receive chemotherapy to reduce the size of the tumor to make surgery possible. The goal of this approach is to save as much healthy kidney tissue as possible and reduce problems after surgery. Chemotherapy given before surgery is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neoadjuvant</GlossaryTermRef> chemotherapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1727"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_1728">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Wilms tumor is treated with external beam radiation therapy. This type of therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation therapy may be given alone or with other treatments, such as chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_1729">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1730"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_1731">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cells or stops them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_1732">For children with Wilms tumor, chemotherapy is injected into a vein. When given this way, chemotherapy enters the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body. </Para><Para id="_18226">Chemotherapy drugs used alone or in combination to treat Wilms tumor include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1733" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000720376" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dactinomycin">dactinomycin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000542867" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/doxorubicinhydrochloride">doxorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000686471" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ifosfamide">ifosfamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537382" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecanhydrochloride">irinotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599877" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vincristinesulfate">vincristine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1734">Other chemotherapy not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_1735">Chemotherapy may be given before or after surgery. Chemotherapy given after surgery to kill any cancer cells that remain is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_1736">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1737"><Title>Stem cell transplant</Title><Para id="_1738"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> (or stem cell rescue) is a procedure to replace the blood-forming stem cells that are destroyed when high doses of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells.  Before high-dose chemotherapy, stem cells (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> of your child and are stored in a freezer. After your child completes chemotherapy, the frozen stem cells are thawed and given back to them through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These stem cells grow into new blood cells. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1739"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_1739_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_1739_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_1739_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1740">Clinical trials have led to  improvements in the treatment of Wilms tumor, including the number of children who are cured.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1741"><Title>Treatment of Wilms tumor by stage and histology</Title><Para id="_1742">To learn more about the treatments listed below, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000415235#_1714" url="/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">Types of treatment for Wilms tumor</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_93"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043735">stage I Wilms tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage I Wilms tumor </Title><Para id="_186">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef> with favorable <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">histology</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_187" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nephrectomy</GlossaryTermRef> with removal of lymph nodes, followed by combination chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes for children younger than 2 years and who have a certain weight</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_188">Treatment of stage I <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> Wilms tumor is nephrectomy with   removal of lymph nodes, followed by combination chemotherapy   and radiation therapy to the flank area (either side of the body between the ribs and hipbone).</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_93_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_97"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043736">stage II Wilms tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage II Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_189">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef> with favorable <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">histology</GlossaryTermRef> is nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes, followed by combination chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_191">Treatment of stage II <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> Wilms tumor is nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes, followed by radiation therapy to the abdomen and combination chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_97_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_101"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043737">stage III Wilms tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage III Wilms tumor </Title><Para id="_215">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046777" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef> with favorable <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">histology</GlossaryTermRef> is nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes, followed by radiation therapy to the abdomen and combination chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_217">Treatment of stage III <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> Wilms tumor may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_218" Style="bullet"><ListItem>nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes, followed by radiation therapy to the abdomen and combination chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>combination chemotherapy, followed by nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes, followed by  radiation therapy to the abdomen</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_101_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_105"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043738">stage IV Wilms tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage IV Wilms tumor </Title><Para id="_207">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046778" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IV Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef> with favorable <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">histology</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_219" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes, followed by combination chemotherapy. Radiation therapy may be given to the area where the tumor was or to other parts of the abdomen.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy to treat cancer that has spread to other parts of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_208">Treatment of  stage IV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> Wilms tumor  may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_244" Style="bullet"><ListItem>nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes, followed by radiation therapy to the abdomen and combination chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy given before  nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes, followed by radiation therapy to the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy to treat cancer that has spread to other parts of the body</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_105_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_109"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043739">stage V Wilms tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage V Wilms tumor and children at high risk of developing bilateral Wilms tumor  </Title><Para id="_110">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046779" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage V Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef> or bilateral Wilms tumor  may be different for each child and may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_252" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Combination chemotherapy to shrink the tumor, followed by repeat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046361" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging</GlossaryTermRef> at 6 to 12 weeks to decide on further treatment. A biopsy may be done or treatment may be given, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000344353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">partial nephrectomy</GlossaryTermRef>, continued chemotherapy, or radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>A biopsy of the kidneys, followed by         combination chemotherapy to shrink the tumor.     Then, surgery is done to remove as much of the cancer as possible. If cancer remains after surgery, your child may have chemotherapy and possibly radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_245">If a kidney <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef> is needed because of kidney problems, it is usually delayed until 1 to 2 years after treatment is completed and there are no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_109_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_361"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of cystic partially differentiated nephroblastoma</Title><Para id="_362">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046461" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cystic</GlossaryTermRef> partially <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">differentiated</GlossaryTermRef> nephroblastoma is surgery that may be followed by chemotherapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_376"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037763">recurrent Wilms tumor and other childhood kidney tumors</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of recurrent Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_460">To learn about the treatments listed below, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000415235#_1714" url="/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">Types of treatment for Wilms tumor</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_377">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> Wilms tumor may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_378" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a combination of chemotherapy, surgery, and radiation therapy</ListItem><ListItem>high-dose chemotherapy followed by a stem cell transplant using your child's own blood stem cells</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_376_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18200"><Title>Prognostic factors for Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_18201">If your child has been diagnosed with Wilms tumor, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_18202">The prognosis for Wilms tumor depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18203" Style="bullet"><ListItem>how different the tumor cells are from normal kidney cells when looked at under a microscope (favorable histology or anaplastic)</ListItem><ListItem>the stage of the cancer</ListItem><ListItem>your child's age</ListItem><ListItem>whether there are certain changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosomes</GlossaryTermRef> or genes</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has come back after treatment</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to the lymph nodes</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18216">Newly diagnosed Wilms tumor with <SummaryRef href="CDR0000415235#_29" url="/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">favorable histology</SummaryRef> can often be cured.</Para><Para id="_18204">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18205"><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_18206">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_18205_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_18207">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18198" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems, such as trouble with exercise, mobility, strength, and flexibility</ListItem><ListItem>chronic health conditions that affect the heart, lungs, kidneys, intestines, and hormone levels</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infertility</GlossaryTermRef> or problems during pregnancy, including high blood pressure, early labor, or the baby being in an unusual position as birth approaches</ListItem><ListItem>neurological symptoms, such as changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer), such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemias</GlossaryTermRef>, thyroid cancer, cancer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal tract</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skin cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18199">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the effects cancer treatment can have on your child. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_468">Children with Wilms tumor and related problems may be monitored for late effects involving the kidneys.</Para><ItemizedList id="_469" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Children with  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">WAGR syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> are monitored throughout their lives because they are at increased risk of
developing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044038" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypertension</GlossaryTermRef> and kidney disease.</ListItem><ListItem> Children with Wilms tumor and an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046381" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genitourinary system</GlossaryTermRef> are monitored  because they are  at increased risk of late <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney failure</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Children with
Wilms tumor and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aniridia</GlossaryTermRef> without an abnormal genitourinary system are at lower
risk but are monitored for  kidney disease or kidney failure.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_91">  Clinical trials are being done to find out if lower doses of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> can be used to lessen the late effects of treatment without changing how well the treatment works.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18208"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_18209">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer or to find out the stage of the cancer may be repeated. Some tests will be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_18210">Some of the tests will continue to be done for years after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed, the health of your child's kidney or other organs, or if the cancer has come back. </Para><Para id="_18211">To learn more about follow-up tests, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000415235#_510" url="/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">Tests to diagnose Wilms tumor</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18212"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_18213">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_227"><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_4500" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney">Kidney Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of Wilms tumor and other childhood kidney tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Wilms Tumor. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389390]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062789"/><DateFirstPublished>2006-05-05</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
