<Summary id="CDR0000419665" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062689"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Vulvar cancer treatment options include various surgical procedures, topical therapy, radiation therapy and/or chemotherapy. Learn more about the treatment options for newly diagnosed and recurrent vulvar cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Vulvar Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Vulvar Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037961">vulvar cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_198">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of vulvar cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_199">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>vulvar cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Vulvar Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Vulvar Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Vulvar Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Vulvar Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_4">Vulvar cancer is a rare cancer that starts in the tissues of the vulva.</KeyPoint><Para id="_6"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vulvar cancer</GlossaryTermRef> forms in a woman's external <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476624" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genitalia</GlossaryTermRef>, called the vulva. It occurs when cells in the vulva start to grow out of control. The vulva includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_189" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the inner and outer lips of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the clitoris (the sensitive tissue  above the lips of the vagina)</ListItem><ListItem>the opening of the vagina and its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glands</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the mons pubis (the rounded area in front of the pubic bones that becomes covered with hair at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">puberty</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000742480" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the vulva; drawing shows the mons pubis, clitoris, urethral opening, inner and outer lips of the vagina, and the vaginal opening. Also shown are the perineum and anus." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_242"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the vulva. The vulva includes the mons pubis, clitoris, inner and outer lips of the vagina, and the openings of the  urethra and vagina.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_141">Vulvar cancer most often affects the outer vaginal lips.      Less often, cancer affects the inner vaginal lips, clitoris, or vaginal glands.</Para><Para id="_142">Vulvar cancer usually forms slowly over many years. Abnormal cells can grow on the surface of the vulvar skin for a long time.  This   condition is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000570425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia</GlossaryTermRef> (VIN). Because it is possible for VIN to become vulvar cancer, it is important to get treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_119">Having vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia or HPV infection can increase the risk of vulvar cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_120">Anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop vulvar cancer, and it will develop in some people who don't have any known risk factors.  Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk.  Risk factors for vulvar cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_121" Style="bullet"> 
    <ListItem>older age</ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000753084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-risk human papillomavirus</GlossaryTermRef> (HPV) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
    <ListItem>having vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia (VIN)</ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476624" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genital</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046652" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">warts</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
     
     
   </ItemizedList><Para id="_180">Other possible risk factors include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_181" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>having many sexual partners</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>having first sexual intercourse at a young age</ListItem><ListItem>having a history of abnormal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045978" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pap tests</GlossaryTermRef> (Pap smears)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_12">Signs of vulvar cancer include bleeding or itching in the vulvar area.</KeyPoint><Para id="_13">Vulvar cancer often does not cause early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. Signs and symptoms may be caused by vulvar cancer or by other conditions.  Check with your doctor if you have any of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_14" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>a lump or growth on the vulva that looks like a wart or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390317" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulcer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>itching in the vulvar area that does not go away</ListItem><ListItem>bleeding not related to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046297" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menstruation</GlossaryTermRef> (periods)</ListItem><ListItem>pain in the vulvar area</ListItem> 
     
     
     
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">Tests that examine the vulva are used to diagnose vulvar cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_18">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet">
    
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pelvic exam</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An exam of the vagina, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>.    A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046588" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">speculum</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted into the vagina and the doctor or nurse looks at the vagina and cervix for signs of disease.  A Pap test of the cervix is usually done.  The doctor or nurse also inserts one or two <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lubricated</GlossaryTermRef>, gloved fingers of one hand into the vagina and places the other hand over the lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> to feel the size, shape, and position of the uterus and ovaries. The doctor or nurse also inserts a lubricated, gloved finger into the rectum to feel for lumps or abnormal areas.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000609924" type="image/jpeg" alt="Pelvic exam; drawing shows a side view of the female reproductive anatomy during a pelvic exam. The uterus, left fallopian tube, left ovary, cervix, vagina, bladder, and rectum are shown. Two gloved fingers of one hand of the doctor or nurse are shown inserted into the vagina, while the other hand is shown pressing on the lower abdomen. The inset shows a woman covered by a drape on an exam table with her legs apart and her feet in stirrups." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_207"><Caption language="en">Pelvic exam. A doctor or nurse inserts one or two lubricated, gloved fingers of one hand into the vagina and presses on the lower abdomen with the other hand. This is done to feel the size, shape, and position of the uterus and ovaries. The vagina, cervix,  fallopian tubes, and rectum are also checked.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Pap test</Strong>: A procedure to collect cells from the surface of the cervix and vagina.  A piece of cotton, a brush, or a small wooden stick is used to gently scrape cells from the cervix and vagina.  The cells are viewed under a microscope to find out if they are abnormal.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000752847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Human papillomavirus (HPV) test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> used to check <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046568" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RNA</GlossaryTermRef> for certain types of HPV infection. Cells are collected from the vulva and DNA or RNA from the cells is checked to find out if an infection is caused by a type of human papillomavirus that is linked to vulvar cancer. This test may be done using the sample of cells removed during a Pap test. This test may also be done if the results of a Pap test show certain abnormal vulvar cells.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of cells or tissues from the vulva so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer.</ListItem>
    
    
    
   <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Colposcopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a colposcope (a lighted, magnifying instrument) is used to check the vagina and cervix for abnormal areas.   Tissue samples may be taken using a curette (spoon-shaped instrument) or a brush and checked under a microscope for signs of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> cells in the body.  A small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> glucose (sugar) is injected into a vein.  The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body.  Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_21">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_22">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_23" Style="bullet">
    
    
    <ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to nearby areas or other parts of the body</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>whether the  cancer has just been <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> or has recurred (come back)</ListItem>
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_24"><Title>Stages of Vulvar Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_25"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_26">After vulvar cancer has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the vulva or to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_27">The process used to find out if cancer has spread within the vulva or to other parts of the body is called staging. The information gathered from the staging process determines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease. It is important to know the stage in order to plan treatment. The following tests and procedures may be used in the staging process:</Para><ItemizedList id="_28" Style="bullet"> 
      <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045988" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cystoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  A procedure to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046640" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urethra</GlossaryTermRef> to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas. A cystoscope is inserted through the urethra into the bladder. A cystoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient"/> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Proctoscopy</Strong>: A procedure to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anus</GlossaryTermRef> to check for abnormal areas, using a proctoscope. A proctoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing the inside of the rectum and anus. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem> 
     
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An x-ray is a type of energy beam that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the body. To stage vulvar cancer, x-rays may be taken of the organs and bones inside the chest.</ListItem><ListItem>                              <Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intravenous pyelogram</GlossaryTermRef> (IVP)</Strong>: A series of x-rays of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureters</GlossaryTermRef>, and bladder to find out if cancer has spread to these organs. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">contrast dye</GlossaryTermRef> is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. As the contrast dye moves through the kidneys, ureters and bladder,    x-rays are taken to see if there are any blockages. This procedure is also called intravenous    urography.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal  of cells or tissues from the bladder or rectum so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer,  if it is suspected that cancer has spread there.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_151"><KeyPoint id="_152">There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_151_md_69">Cancer can spread through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_151_md_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.
</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_194"><KeyPoint id="_195">Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_194_md_66">When cancer spreads to another part of the body, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer cells break away from where they began (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>) and travel through the lymph system or blood.</Para><ItemizedList id="_194_md_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer gets into the lymph system, travels through the lymph vessels, and forms a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer gets into the blood, travels through the blood vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_196">The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if  vulvar cancer spreads to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, the cancer cells in the lung are actually vulvar cancer cells. The disease is metastatic vulvar cancer, not lung cancer.</Para><EmbeddedVideo id="_202" ref="CDR0000787719" hosting="youtube" unique_id="fQwar_-QdiQ" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>metastasis: how cancer spreads</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Many cancer deaths are caused when cancer moves from the original tumor and spreads to other tissues and organs. This is called metastatic cancer. This animation shows how cancer cells travel from the place in the body where they first formed to other parts of the body.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_190"><KeyPoint id="_191">In vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia (VIN), abnormal cells are found on the surface of the vulvar skin.</KeyPoint><Para id="_192">These abnormal cells are not cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000570425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia</GlossaryTermRef> (VIN) may become cancer and spread into nearby tissue. VIN is sometimes called stage 0 or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma in situ</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_243">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging system</GlossaryTermRef> below does not apply to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the vulva, which is staged like melanoma of the skin.  For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062713#_96" url="/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Stage Information for Melanoma</SummaryRef> section in Melanoma Treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_31">The following stages are used for vulvar cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_175"><KeyPoint id="_176">Stage I</KeyPoint><Para id="_177">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046120" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I</GlossaryTermRef>, cancer has formed.  The tumor  is found only in the vulva. Stage I is divided into stages IA and  IB.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_193"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink></Para><ItemizedList id="_178" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In stage IA, the tumor is 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller and has spread 1 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeter</GlossaryTermRef> or less into the tissue of the vulva. Cancer has not spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IB, the tumor is larger than 2 centimeters or has spread more than 1 millimeter into the tissue of the vulva. Cancer has not spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000578121" type="image/jpeg" alt="Millimeters; drawing shows millimeters (mm) using everyday objects. A sharp pencil point shows 1 mm, a new crayon point shows 2 mm, and a new pencil-top eraser shows 5 mm." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_186"><Caption language="en">Millimeters (mm). A sharp pencil point is about 1 mm, a new crayon point is about 2 mm, and a new pencil eraser is about 5 mm.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><KeyPoint id="_39">Stage II</KeyPoint><Para id="_170">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046121" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II</GlossaryTermRef>, the tumor is any size and has spread to  the lower one-third of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046640" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urethra</GlossaryTermRef>, the lower one-third of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>, or the lower one-third of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anus</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer has not spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_41"><KeyPoint id="_42">Stage III</KeyPoint><Para id="_239">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III</GlossaryTermRef>, the tumor is any size and has spread to the upper two-thirds of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046640" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urethra</GlossaryTermRef>, the upper two-thirds of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>, the inner lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>, or to any number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>. Stage III is divided into stages IIIA, IIIB, and IIIC. </Para><ItemizedList id="_238" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In stage IIIA, cancer is found in lymph nodes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef> that are not larger than 5 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeters</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIB, cancer is found in lymph nodes in the groin that are larger than 5 millimeters.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIC, cancer is found in lymph nodes in the groin and has extended through  the outer covering of the lymph nodes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_44"><KeyPoint id="_45">Stage IV</KeyPoint><Para id="_240">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IV</GlossaryTermRef>, the tumor is any size and has become attached to the bone, or cancer has spread to  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> that are not movable  or have become <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulcerated</GlossaryTermRef>, or there is distant spread. Stage IV is divided into stages IVA and IVB.</Para><ItemizedList id="_241" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In stage IVA, the cancer is attached to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045087" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvic</GlossaryTermRef> bone or  has spread to lymph nodes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef> that are not movable or have become ulcerated. </ListItem><ListItem>In stage IVB, the cancer has spread beyond the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> to distant parts of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_235"><KeyPoint id="_236">Vulvar cancer can recur (come back) after it has been treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_237">The cancer may come back in the vulva or in other parts of the body.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_49"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_50"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_51">There are different types of treatment for patients with vulvar cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_52">Different types of treatments are available for patients with vulvar cancer. Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>. A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the  standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment. Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_54"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_55">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_56"><KeyPoint id="_57">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_58">Surgery is the most common treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000570425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia</GlossaryTermRef> (VIN) and vulvar cancer.</Para><Para id="_230">One of the following types of surgery may be done to treat VIN:</Para><ItemizedList id="_59" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Separate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269459" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excision</GlossaryTermRef> of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesion</GlossaryTermRef>: A surgical procedure to remove a lesion of concern.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef>: A surgical procedure to remove the area of skin affected by VIN and some of the normal tissue around it.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Laser surgery</GlossaryTermRef>: A surgical procedure that uses a laser beam (a narrow beam of intense light) as a knife to make bloodless cuts in tissue or to remove a surface lesion such as a tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Ultrasound surgical aspiration: A surgical procedure to break the tumor up into small pieces using very fine vibrations. The small pieces of tumor are washed away and removed by suction. This procedure  causes less damage to nearby tissue.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Skinning vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef>: The top layer of vulvar skin where the VIN is found is removed. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046581" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Skin grafts</GlossaryTermRef> from other parts of the body may be needed to cover the area where the skin was removed.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_231">The goal of surgery for vulvar cancer is to remove all the cancer without any loss of the woman's sexual function. One of the following types of surgery may be done to treat vulvar cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_232" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef>: A surgical procedure to remove  the cancer and some of the normal  tissue around the cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radical local excision</GlossaryTermRef>:  A surgical procedure to remove the cancer and a large amount of normal tissue around it. Nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef> may also be removed.</ListItem><ListItem>Vulvectomy: A surgical procedure to remove  part or all of the vulva:<ItemizedList id="_233" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Modified  radical vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef>: Surgery to remove most of the vulva. Nearby lymph nodes may also be removed.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radical vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef>: Surgery to remove the entire vulva. Nearby lymph nodes are also  removed.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Pelvic exenteration: A surgical procedure to remove the lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef>. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef>, and nearby lymph nodes are also removed.  Artificial openings (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stoma</GlossaryTermRef>) are made for urine and stool to flow from the body into a collection bag.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_60">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some patients may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> after surgery to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after the surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><KeyPoint id="_63">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_64"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward area of the body with cancer.</Para><Para id="_201">External radiation therapy may also be used as
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><KeyPoint id="_66">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_67">Chemotherapy is a cancer treatment that uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping the cells from dividing.   When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>). <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046619" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Topical chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> for vulvar cancer may be applied to the skin in a cream or lotion. The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the type and stage of the cancer being treated.</Para><Para id="_162">See <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vulvar">Drugs Approved to Treat Vulvar Cancer</ExternalRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_182"><KeyPoint id="_183">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_184">Immunotherapy is a treatment that uses the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to fight cancer. Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the body's natural defenses against cancer.

</Para><Para id="_187"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Imiquimod</GlossaryTermRef> is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune response</GlossaryTermRef> modifier  used to treat vulvar <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesions</GlossaryTermRef> and is applied to the skin in a cream.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_80"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_81">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_89"> Information about clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_203"><KeyPoint id="_204">Treatment for vulvar cancer may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_203_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_153"><KeyPoint id="_154">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_153_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_153_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_153_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_155"><KeyPoint id="_156">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_155_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_155_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_157"><KeyPoint id="_158">Follow-up tests may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_157_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_157_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_188">It is important to have regular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> exams to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vulvar cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_208"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Vulvar Intraepithelial Neoplasia (VIN)</Title><Para id="_209">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000419665#_54" url="/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_210">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000570425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia</GlossaryTermRef> (VIN)    may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_211" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery may be one of the following:<ItemizedList id="_234" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>separate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269459" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excision</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesions</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laser surgery</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>ultrasound surgical aspiration</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443586" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skinning vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>  with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045927" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">topical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imiquimod</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_212"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037915">stage I vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037926">stage II vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stages I and II Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_213">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000419665#_54" url="/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_214">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046120" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I vulvar cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046121" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II vulvar cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_215" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radical local excision</GlossaryTermRef> with removal of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef> and upper thigh)</ListItem><ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">modified radical vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radical vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef> with removal of lymph nodes in the groin and upper thigh) followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> in some cases</ListItem><ListItem>surgery (radical local excision and removal of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045876" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node</GlossaryTermRef>) followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> in some cases</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy alone</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_212_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_216"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037930">stage III vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_217">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000419665#_54" url="/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_218">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III vulvar cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_219" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">modified radical vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radical vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef> with removal of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef> and upper thigh) with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and radiation therapy followed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_216_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_220"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000739551">stage IVA vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IVA Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_221">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000419665#_54" url="/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_222">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IVA vulvar cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_223" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radical vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322874" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvic exenteration</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>surgery and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and radiation therapy followed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_220_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_224"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037940">stage IVB vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IVB Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_226">There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>  for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IVB vulvar cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> has been studied and may be used if the patient can tolerate it.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_224_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_111"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037950">recurrent vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_206">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000419665#_54" url="/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_112">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> vulvar cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_113" Style="bullet">
   <ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef>) with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
   <ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443589" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radical vulvectomy</GlossaryTermRef> and  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322874" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvic exenteration</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and radiation therapy with or without surgery</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy and surgery</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative treatment</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
   
   
   
  </ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_111_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_145"><Title>To Learn More About Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_147">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  vulvar cancer, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_163" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar">Vulvar Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery/lasers">Lasers to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vulvar">Drugs Approved to Treat Vulvar Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/infectious-agents/hpv-fact-sheet">HPV and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_145_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_145_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of vulvar cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Vulvar Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389324]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062886"/><DateFirstPublished>2005-09-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-09-18</DateLastModified></Summary>
