<Summary id="CDR0000433282" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Prevention</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Liver (hepatocellular) cancer prevention strategies include avoiding risk factors and vaccinating against hepatitis B. Risk factors include hepatitis B and C infection, cirrhosis, and aflatoxin. Get detailed information about risk factors and preventing liver cancer in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/hp/liver-prevention-pdq">Liver    (Hepatocellular) Cancer (PDQ®): Prevention</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038968">liver and intrahepatic biliary tract cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041588">cancer prevention</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_94">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about liver (hepatocellular) cancer prevention. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_95">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer prevention</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>liver and intrahepatic biliary tract cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Prevention (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Prevention (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage"> Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Prevention</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_23">Note: The Overview section summarizes the published evidence on this topic. The rest of the summary describes the evidence in more detail.</Para><Para id="_360">Other PDQ summaries containing information related to liver (hepatocellular) cancer prevention include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_361" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062840" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-screening-pdq">Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Screening</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062906" url="/types/liver/hp/adult-liver-treatment-pdq">Primary Liver Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062836" url="/types/liver/hp/child-liver-treatment-pdq">Childhood Liver Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">Levels of Evidence for Cancer Screening and Prevention Studies</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_174"><Title>Who Is at Risk?</Title><Para id="_175">The critical etiological agent in at least 80% of hepatocellular cancer (HCC) cases worldwide is chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection or chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Both viruses, either alone or with other risk factors, are responsible for staggering increases in the risk of HCC, relative to the absence of these hepatitis viruses. Men with chronic HBV or HCV infection are more likely to develop HCC than are women with the same chronic infection, with some, but not the entire difference explained by varying prevalence of other risk factors.<Reference refidx="2"/> Cirrhosis, regardless of its etiology, predisposes patients to HCC <Reference refidx="3"/> and is present in 70% to 90% of HCC patients at the time of diagnosis.<Reference refidx="4"/> Heavy alcohol use is a strong etiologic agent for HCC because it can cause cirrhosis and the presence of HBV or HCV increases risk even more.<Reference refidx="5"/> Exposure to aflatoxin B1 strongly increases HCC risk in individuals with chronic HBV infection and may do so, but to a much lesser extent, in individuals without chronic HBV infection.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) increases risk of HCC among patients who have accompanying cirrhosis <Reference refidx="6"/> and may modestly increase risk in patients without cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> Cigarette smoking modestly increases the risk.<Reference refidx="9"/> Untreated hereditary hemochromatosis and certain other rare medical and genetic conditions are responsible for large increases in HCC risk but are responsible for only a small percentage of cases.<Reference refidx="1"/> The future HCC incidence among patients newly diagnosed with  nonalcoholic fatty liver (NAFL) is not known, and because NAFL can progress to NASH, and patients with NAFL can develop cirrhosis, there is reason to believe that patients with NAFL are at elevated risk.<Reference refidx="10"/> A diagnosis of metabolic syndrome (MetS) is associated with an increased risk of HCC,<Reference refidx="11"/> as are obesity and type 2 diabetes, which are common component conditions of MetS.<Reference refidx="11"/> Those three conditions also can occur concurrently with NAFL.<Reference refidx="12"/> The frequent coexistence of these four conditions makes the interpretation of condition-specific risk measures difficult. Decreases in HCC incidence rates have occurred after implementation of HBV vaccination programs,<Reference refidx="13"/> and treatment with nucleos(t)ide analogue therapy reduces but does not eliminate the risk of HCC in patients with chronic HBV infection.<Reference refidx="14"/> Replacement of a food supply that was heavily contaminated with aflatoxin B1 with one that contained much lower levels resulted in a more than 50% reduction in primary liver cancer.<Reference refidx="15"/> HCV treatment with direct-acting antivirals that results in sustained virological response may reduce HCC risk.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_176"><Title>Factors With Adequate Evidence of Increased Risk of Hepatocellular Cancer (HCC)</Title><SummarySection id="_177"><Title>Chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection</Title><Para id="_178">Based on solid evidence, chronic HBV infection causes HCC.</Para><Para id="_179"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Chronic HBV infection is the leading cause of HCC in Asia and Africa.<Reference refidx="17"/> HBV, either alone or in the presence of other risk factors, is responsible for large increases in the risk of developing HCC. Although the degree of increase in risk varies by other factors or characteristics of infection, it is reasonable to assume that, on average, relative risks (RRs) of HBV are at least fivefold.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_180" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Prospective cohort studies; case-control studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_295"><Title>Chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection</Title><Para id="_296">Based on solid evidence, chronic HCV infection causes HCC.</Para><Para id="_297"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: HCV infection is the leading cause of HCC in North America, Europe, and Japan.<Reference refidx="17"/> HCV, either alone or in the presence of other risk factors, is responsible for staggering increases in the risk of developing HCC.  Although degree of increase in risk varies by the presence of other factors or characteristics of infection, it is reasonable to assume that, on average, relative risks of HCV are at least 15-fold.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_298" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Prospective cohort studies; case-control studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_181"><Title>Cirrhosis</Title><Para id="_182">Based on solid evidence, cirrhosis, regardless of its etiology, predisposes patients to HCC.<Reference refidx="3"/>  HCC develops in the presence of a cirrhotic liver in most instances.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_183"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: In autopsy studies, 80% to 90% of individuals who die of HCC have cirrhotic livers.<Reference refidx="3"/> The risk of HCC varies by cause of cirrhosis; patients with HCV-related cirrhosis are at greater risk than those with HBV-related cirrhosis, and those with HBV-related cirrhosis are at greater risk than those with alcohol-related cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/> The 5-year cumulative risk of developing HCC for patients with cirrhosis ranges between 5% and 30%.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_184" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Autopsy studies, prospective cohort studies, case-control studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_185"><Title>Heavy alcohol use</Title><Para id="_186">Based on solid evidence, heavy alcohol use increases HCC risk.<Reference refidx="2"/> Heavy alcohol use causes cirrhosis, and the development of most alcohol-related HCC is thought to occur via that pathway.<Reference refidx="3"/> However, heavy alcohol users who do not develop cirrhosis are also at elevated risk of developing HCC.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_187"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Heavy alcohol consumption increases HCC risk at least twofold; some studies suggest at least a fivefold increase.<Reference refidx="17"/> Among individuals with HBV or HCV infection, the magnitude of the association is about the same.<Reference refidx="19"/> However, heavy alcohol consumption and chronic HCV infection appear to act synergistically on HCC risk, resulting in perhaps a 100-fold increase in risk relative to individuals who are not infected and not heavy consumers of alcohol. The existence of a synergistic effect with HBV is less consistent, although one study observed a 50-fold increase in risk.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_188" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Case-control study, case series, cohort studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_189"><Title>Aflatoxin B1</Title><Para id="_190">Aflatoxin B1 is a mycotoxin that can contaminate corn and peanuts stored in warm, humid environments.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Based on solid evidence, aflatoxin B1 exposure increases HCC risk.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_191"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: In individuals with chronic HBV infection, aflatoxin B1 exposure is estimated to increase risk 60-fold.<Reference refidx="18"/> Because chronic HBV infection is highly prevalent in areas where exposure to aflatoxin B1 is an environmental concern, it is difficult to assess the magnitude of effect in individuals without HBV, although the available limited data suggest that the increase in risk may be fourfold.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_196" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Ecological studies, prospective cohort studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_192"><Title>Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH)</Title><Para id="_193">Based on fair evidence, NASH increases risk of HCC.</Para><Para id="_194"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: In a study of 195 patients with NASH and cirrhosis, 13% were diagnosed with HCC after a median follow-up of 3.2 years.<Reference refidx="6"/> In patients with NASH without cirrhosis, HCC occurs infrequently; however, these patients are thought to have a modestly elevated risk of HCC.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_195" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Prospective cohort studies, medical record abstraction, case series.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_197"><Title>Cigarette smoking</Title><Para id="_198">Based on fair evidence, cigarette smoking increases HCC risk.</Para><Para id="_199"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Cigarette smoking in the absence of viral infection is associated with a modest (up to twofold) increase in HCC risk. Cigarette smoking and presence of chronic HBV or HCV infection results in at least an additive effect on HCC risk.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_200" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Case-control and cohort studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_205"><Title>Certain rare genetic and medical conditions (untreated hereditary hemochromatosis [HH], alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency, glycogen storage disease, porphyria cutanea tarda, and Wilson disease)</Title><Para id="_206">Based on solid evidence, untreated HH, alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency (AAT), glycogen storage disease, porphyria cutanea tarda, and Wilson disease increase the risk of HCC, but account for few cases.<Reference refidx="1"/> In the absence of treatment, HH leads to cirrhosis, although there are reports of HCC developing in patients with noncirrhotic livers.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_207"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Untreated HH confers at least a 20-fold increase in risk,<Reference refidx="17"/> although risk varies according to other factors (including HBV and HCV infection). Treatment to reduce iron stores can greatly reduce risk. AAT deficiency, glycogen storage disease, porphyria cutanea tarda, and Wilson disease confer large but varied increases in risk of HCC.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_208" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Prospective cohort studies (HH), case series (other conditions).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair (HCC), not applicable (N/A; other conditions).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Fair (HCC), good (other conditions).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Fair (HCC), N/A (other conditions).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_209"><Title>Factors With Inadequate Evidence of Increased Risk of HCC</Title><SummarySection id="_210"><Title>Nonalcoholic fatty liver</Title><Para id="_211">Based on limited evidence, some patients with NAFL  will develop NASH or cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="10"/>  Therefore, NAFL is assumed to increase HCC risk.</Para><Para id="_212"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: A small clinical study suggested that between 20% and 50% of NAFL patients may develop NASH.<Reference refidx="10"/> Up to 4% of NAFL patients may develop cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="21"/> The observation that NAFL patients have developed these conditions, which are known to increase HCC risk, leads to the conclusion that NAFL increases HCC risk, even though the future incidence of HCC among patients newly diagnosed with NAFL is not known.</Para><ItemizedList id="_213" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Biopsy studies, case series.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Poor.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: N/A.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: N/A.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_214"><Title>Metabolic syndrome (MetS)</Title><Para id="_215">Based on fair evidence, a diagnosis of MetS is associated with an increased risk of HCC.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_216"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: A meta-analysis of more than 7,000 HCC cases from four studies produced a risk ratio of 1.8 (95% confidence interval [CI], 1.37–2.40) for a diagnosis of MetS. The combined risk ratios were varied (range, 1.2 [95% CI, 0.55–2.53] to 3.7 [95% CI, 1.78–7.58]).<Reference refidx="23"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_217" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Case-control studies and cohort studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_299"><Title>Obesity</Title><Para id="_300">Based on fair evidence, obesity is associated with an increase in HCC risk.</Para><Para id="_301"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Numerous large epidemiological studies suggest about a twofold increase in HCC risk for individuals who are obese.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_302" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Case-control studies, retrospective and prospective cohort studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_303"><Title>Type 2 diabetes</Title><Para id="_304">Based on fair evidence, type 2 diabetes is associated with an increase in HCC risk.</Para><Para id="_305"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Numerous large epidemiological studies suggest a twofold to fourfold increase in HCC risk for individuals with type 2 diabetes.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_306" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Case-control studies, retrospective and prospective cohort studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_218"><Title>Interventions With Adequate Evidence of Decreased Risk of HCC</Title><SummarySection id="_219"><Title>HBV vaccination</Title><Para id="_220">Based on solid evidence, neonatal HBV vaccination or catch-up vaccination at young ages reduces HCC incidence in young adults.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para><Para id="_221"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Reductions in pediatric and young adult HCC risk of at least 50% have been observed in cohorts immunized at birth or during early childhood. It is predicted that universal neonate immunization will ultimately eliminate 70% to 85% of global HCC cases.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_222" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Cluster randomized controlled trial (RCT), historical trends, mathematical modeling.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_307"><Title>Treatment for chronic HBV infection</Title><Para id="_308">Based on solid evidence, chronic HBV treatment with nucleos(t)ide analogue therapy reduces the risk of HCC.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_309"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: About a 50% reduction in incidence.</Para><ItemizedList id="_310" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Meta-analysis of clinical trials (some randomized, some blinded), retrospective cohort studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_311"><Title>Availability of food not contaminated with aflatoxin B1</Title><Para id="_312">Based on solid evidence, replacement of food highly contaminated with aflatoxin B1 with food that harbors much lower levels of aflatoxin B1 leads to a reduction in liver cancer mortality.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_313"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: A more-than-50% reduction in liver cancer mortality.</Para><ItemizedList id="_314" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Historical trends.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: N/A.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: N/A.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_223"><Title>Interventions With Inadequate Evidence of Decreased Risk of HCC</Title><SummarySection id="_224"><Title>HCV treatment with direct-acting antivirals (DAAs)</Title><Para id="_225">Based on fair evidence, HCV treatment with DAAs that results in sustained virological response (SVR) may reduce HCC risk.</Para><Para id="_226"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Patients treated with DAAs who attained SVR had an approximately 75% reduction in HCC risk relative to those who did not attain SVR.<Reference refidx="16"/> Reduction in relative risk with SVR was similar in patients with cirrhosis (hazard ratio [HR], 0.31; 95% CI, 0.23–0.44) and patients without cirrhosis (HR, 0.18; 95% CI, 0.11–0.30). There does not appear to be an increased risk of HCC among individuals, with or without cirrhosis, who received DAAs as opposed to those who received interferon.<Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_227" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Retrospective cohort, case series.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_348"><Title>Statin use among adults with HBV or HCV</Title><Para id="_349">Based on fair evidence, statin use may be associated with a reduced risk of developing HCC in patients with HBV or HCV infection.<Reference refidx="28"/>  Statin use may be associated with a reduced risk of developing HCC in all adults.</Para><Para id="_350"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Relative reductions in HCC risk in adults with HBV or HCV infection of approximately 50% was found in a systematic review of observational studies (kappa statistic, 13). A statistically significant effect was observed with lipophilic statin use (HR, 0.52; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001; kappa statistic, 2) but not with hydrophilic statin use  (RR, 0.89; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .21; kappa statistic, 2) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> for subgroup difference &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="28"/> However, there was moderate heterogeneity in the two studies that reported on hydrophilic statin use, with one study <Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/>   showing a 49% statistically significant relative reduction and the other study <Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/>   showing a nonsignificant 5% relative reduction.</Para><ItemizedList id="_351" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Systematic review and meta-analysis of observational study.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good across patient characteristics, including possibly HBV/HCV status but possibly inconsistent for the type of statin use (lipophilic vs. hydrophilic).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Unclear.  A systematic review and meta-analysis of observational and randomized studies in adults with and without HBV/HCV infection (kappa statistic, 10) reported that statin use was associated with a 37% relative reduction in developing HCC (odds ratio [OR], 0.63; 95% CI, 0.52–0.76). Five studies did not report the baseline prevalence of HBV/HCV in individuals; one study noted that 100% of individuals had HBV infection, another study noted that HBV/HCV was present in 23.9%/25.1% at baseline while another study noted 1.9%/14.7%, respectively. Two other studies reported that HBV/HCV was present in less than 10% of the population. In sensitivity analyses, the association between statin use and HCC was observed in observational studies (kappa statistic, 7; adjusted OR, 0.60; 95% CI, 0.49–0.73) but not in RCTs (kappa statistic, 3; OR, 0.95; 95% CI, 0.62–1.45 [although CIs were wide]).<Reference refidx="33"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">London WT, McGlynn K: Liver cancer. In: Schottenfeld D, Fraumeni JF Jr, eds.: Cancer Epidemiology and Prevention. 3rd ed. Oxford University Press, 2006, pp 763-86.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="24839253">El-Serag HB, Kanwal F: Epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma in the United States: where are we? Where do we go? Hepatology 60 (5): 1767-75, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="15508101">Fattovich G, Stroffolini T, Zagni I, et al.: Hepatocellular carcinoma in cirrhosis: incidence and risk factors. Gastroenterology 127 (5 Suppl 1): S35-50, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28108047">Hartke J, Johnson M, Ghabril M: The diagnosis and treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma. Semin Diagn Pathol 34 (2): 153-159, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="11836196">Donato F, Tagger A, Gelatti U, et al.: Alcohol and hepatocellular carcinoma: the effect of lifetime intake and hepatitis virus infections in men and women. Am J Epidemiol 155 (4): 323-31, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20209604">Ascha MS, Hanouneh IA, Lopez R, et al.: The incidence and risk factors of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. Hepatology 51 (6): 1972-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="23041539">White DL, Kanwal F, El-Serag HB: Association between nonalcoholic fatty liver disease and risk for hepatocellular cancer, based on systematic review. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 10 (12): 1342-1359.e2, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="26250831">Perumpail RB, Wong RJ, Ahmed A, et al.: Hepatocellular Carcinoma in the Setting of Non-cirrhotic Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and the Metabolic Syndrome: US Experience. Dig Dis Sci 60 (10): 3142-8, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="20447919">Chuang SC, Lee YC, Hashibe M, et al.: Interaction between cigarette smoking and hepatitis B and C virus infection on the risk of liver cancer: a meta-analysis. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 19 (5): 1261-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="27213358">Calzadilla Bertot L, Adams LA: The Natural Course of Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease. Int J Mol Sci 17 (5): , 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="25892859">Streba LA, Vere CC, Rogoveanu I, et al.: Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease, metabolic risk factors, and hepatocellular carcinoma: an open question. World J Gastroenterol 21 (14): 4103-10, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="29128053">Kim D, Touros A, Kim WR: Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Metabolic Syndrome. Clin Liver Dis 22 (1): 133-140, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="26651252">Kao JH: Hepatitis B vaccination and prevention of hepatocellular carcinoma. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 29 (6): 907-17, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="23713520">Singal AK, Salameh H, Kuo YF, et al.: Meta-analysis: the impact of oral anti-viral agents on the incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic hepatitis B. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 38 (2): 98-106, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="23963804">Chen JG, Egner PA, Ng D, et al.: Reduced aflatoxin exposure presages decline in liver cancer mortality in an endemic region of China. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 6 (10): 1038-45, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="28642197">Kanwal F, Kramer J, Asch SM, et al.: Risk of Hepatocellular Cancer in HCV Patients Treated With Direct-Acting Antiviral Agents. Gastroenterology 153 (4): 996-1005.e1, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="25444466">Lafaro KJ, Demirjian AN, Pawlik TM: Epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma. Surg Oncol Clin N Am 24 (1): 1-17, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="22537432">El-Serag HB: Epidemiology of viral hepatitis and hepatocellular carcinoma. Gastroenterology 142 (6): 1264-1273.e1, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="23101985">Grewal P, Viswanathen VA: Liver cancer and alcohol. Clin Liver Dis 16 (4): 839-50, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="25260306">Bosetti C, Turati F, La Vecchia C: Hepatocellular carcinoma epidemiology. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 28 (5): 753-70, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="26057287">Rinella ME: Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review. JAMA 313 (22): 2263-73, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="26196445">Mittal S, El-Serag HB, Sada YH, et al.: Hepatocellular Carcinoma in the Absence of Cirrhosis in United States Veterans is Associated With Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 14 (1): 124-31.e1, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="24402120">Jinjuvadia R, Patel S, Liangpunsakul S: The association between metabolic syndrome and hepatocellular carcinoma: systemic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Gastroenterol 48 (2): 172-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="25549238">Qu C, Chen T, Fan C, et al.: Efficacy of neonatal HBV vaccination on liver cancer and other liver diseases over 30-year follow-up of the Qidong hepatitis B intervention study: a cluster randomized controlled trial. PLoS Med 11 (12): e1001774, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="25921660">McGlynn KA, Petrick JL, London WT: Global epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma: an emphasis on demographic and regional variability. Clin Liver Dis 19 (2): 223-38, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="29205416">Li DK, Ren Y, Fierer DS, et al.: The short-term incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma is not increased after hepatitis C treatment with direct-acting antivirals: An ERCHIVES study. Hepatology 67 (6): 2244-2253, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="30765123">Carrat F, Fontaine H, Dorival C, et al.: Clinical outcomes in patients with chronic hepatitis C after direct-acting antiviral treatment: a prospective cohort study. Lancet 393 (10179): 1453-1464, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="32272891">Li X, Sheng L, Liu L, et al.: Statin and the risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with hepatitis B virus or hepatitis C virus infection: a meta-analysis. BMC Gastroenterol 20 (1): 98, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="22271485">Tsan YT, Lee CH, Wang JD, et al.: Statins and the risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with hepatitis B virus infection. J Clin Oncol 30 (6): 623-30, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="23509319">Tsan YT, Lee CH, Ho WC, et al.: Statins and the risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with hepatitis C virus infection. J Clin Oncol 31 (12): 1514-21, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="31426090">Simon TG, Duberg AS, Aleman S, et al.: Lipophilic Statins and Risk for Hepatocellular Carcinoma and Death in Patients With Chronic Viral Hepatitis: Results From a Nationwide Swedish Population. Ann Intern Med 171 (5): 318-327, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="26891205">Simon TG, Bonilla H, Yan P, et al.: Atorvastatin and fluvastatin are associated with dose-dependent reductions in cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma, among patients with hepatitis C virus: Results from ERCHIVES. Hepatology 64 (1): 47-57, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="23063971">Singh S, Singh PP, Singh AG, et al.: Statins are associated with a reduced risk of hepatocellular cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Gastroenterology 144 (2): 323-32, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_151"><Title>Incidence, Mortality, and Survival</Title><Para id="_228">In the United States, liver cancer, regardless of histology, accounts for about 2% of cancer diagnoses and 5% of cancer deaths. Although liver cancer  is not among the top ten diagnosed cancers in the United States,<Reference refidx="1"/> it is the sixth-leading cause of cancer deaths.<Reference refidx="1"/>  About 42,240 new cases of liver cancer and 30,090 deaths are expected to occur in the United States in 2025.<Reference refidx="2"/> Hepatocellular cancer accounts for about 70% of all liver cancers in the United States.<Reference refidx="2"/> In 1975, liver cancer incidence in the United States was 2.64 per 100,000. In 2021, the rate had risen more than threefold to 8.39 per 100,000.<Reference refidx="3"/> Five-year survival rates vary by stage, from a high of 37.3% for localized disease to a low of 3.3% for distant disease.<Reference refidx="1"/> In the United States, rates of liver cancer incidence and liver cancer death are lowest in White individuals and highest in American Indian or Alaska Native individuals. Rates are also higher in Hispanic individuals than in non-Hispanic individuals.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_229">Worldwide, liver cancer is the sixth most common cancer and the third leading cause of cancer-related death.<Reference refidx="4"/> Liver cancer resulted in about 865,269 new cases and 757,948 deaths in 2022;<Reference refidx="4"/> in most countries, the liver annual incidence and mortality rates are nearly identical.<Reference refidx="4"/> It is the fifth most frequently diagnosed cancer in adult men and the ninth most commonly diagnosed cancer in women.<Reference refidx="4"/> The incidence of liver varies widely according to geographic location.<Reference refidx="4"/> High-incidence regions include Northern and Western Africa (Egypt, the Gambia, Guinea) and Eastern and South-Eastern Asia (Mongolia, Cambodia, and Vietnam). Liver incidence is low in North and South America, most of Europe, Australia, and parts of the Middle East.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> In all parts of the world, liver is more common in men than in women.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">National Cancer Institute: SEER Stat Fact Sheets: Liver and Intrahepatic Bile Duct Cancer. Bethesda, Md: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/livibd.html">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 5, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="2">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Surveillance Research Program, National Cancer Institute: SEER*Explorer: An interactive website for SEER cancer statistics. 	Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statistics-network/explorer/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="38572751">Bray F, Laversanne M, Sung H, et al.: Global cancer statistics 2022: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin 74 (3): 229-263, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21296855">Jemal A, Bray F, Center MM, et al.: Global cancer statistics. CA Cancer J Clin 61 (2): 69-90, 2011 Mar-Apr.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_156"><Title>Factors With Adequate Evidence of Increased Risk of HCC</Title><SummarySection id="_160"><Title>Chronic HBV Infection</Title><Para id="_231">Chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection is the leading cause of hepatocellular cancer (HCC) in Asia and Africa.<Reference refidx="1"/> Hepatitis B is transmitted through contact with infected blood, semen, or other body fluids. In areas with high incidence of chronic HBV infection and HCC, about 70% of infections are acquired in the perinatal period or in early childhood.<Reference refidx="2"/> In addition to maternal-to-child transmission, HBV can be spread through sexual contact and contact with infected blood.<Reference refidx="3"/> In the United States, the most common route of transmission is sharing drug-injecting needles.<Reference refidx="4"/> It is estimated that 850,000 to 2.2 million people in the United States have chronic HBV infection <Reference refidx="3"/>  and that the infection is responsible for 10% to 15% of HCC cases.<Reference refidx="5"/>  The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that 240 million people are infected worldwide.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_232">Evidence for a causal relationship between chronic HBV infection and HCC comes from etiological studies, case series, case-control studies, and prospective epidemiological studies.<Reference refidx="2"/> Ecological studies demonstrate a strong positive correlation between the prevalence of chronic HBV and HCC incidence and mortality. HBV is present in liver tissue in nearly all patients who are seropositive for the virus and have HCC,<Reference refidx="2"/> and HBV DNA has been found in 10% to 20% of HCC tumors in patients who are seronegative but are positive for HBV antibodies.<Reference refidx="2"/> Case-control studies and prospective studies have observed odds ratios or relative risks (RRs) of at least 5 for chronic HBV infection.<Reference refidx="2"/> Some prospective studies have observed RRs exceeding 50.<Reference refidx="2"/> The lifetime risk of HCC in individuals chronically infected with HBV is estimated to be between 10% and 25%.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Clinical factors that have been reported to increase risk in individuals with chronic HBV infection include higher levels of HBV replication; certain HBV genotypes; longer duration of infection; and coinfection with hepatitis C virus (HCV), HIV, or hepatitis D virus.<Reference refidx="6"/> The presence of cirrhosis increases risk, although HBV can cause HCC in the absence of cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_315">Coinfection with HCV appears to have an additive effect on risk.<Reference refidx="8"/> In addition, degree of increased risk of chronic HBV varies with the presence of other factors and is discussed in sections of this summary that cover those specific factors.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_135"><Title>Chronic HCV Infection</Title><Para id="_233">Chronic HCV infection is the leading cause of HCC in North America, Europe, and Japan.<Reference refidx="1"/> Chronic HCV infection accounts for about one-third of HCC cases in the United States.<Reference refidx="4"/> HCV is a blood-borne pathogen; before screening of the blood supply or donated human organs (1992), HCV infection often was acquired during blood transfusions or organ transplants. Today, most new infections are caused by the sharing of drug-injecting needles. HCV can be transmitted during sexual contact, although this occurs infrequently. An estimated 2.7 to 3.9 million people in the United States have chronic hepatitis C.<Reference refidx="9"/> In the United States, more cases are attributable to chronic HCV infection than to any other risk factor.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_234">Even though the mechanisms through which HCV increases HCC risk are unclear, chronic HCV infection is accepted as playing a causal role in the development of HCC. Evidence of a strong association comes primarily from cross-sectional and case-control studies, which suggest that individuals with HCV infection have at least a 15-fold increase in HCC risk, relative to individuals without HCV infection.<Reference refidx="6"/>  A prospective study of more than 23,000 residents of Taiwan observed a cumulative lifetime HCC incidence of 24% in men and 17% in women;<Reference refidx="11"/> other prospective studies, including cases series of individuals accidently infected with HCV through blood transfusion, have produced a wide range of incidence estimates.<Reference refidx="2"/> The reason for such variability is likely the variation in prevalence of advanced fibrosis and cirrhosis in the groups being studied. Chronic HCV infection typically leads to liver fibrosis, but HCC is rare in HCV-positive individuals with minimal or no fibrosis.<Reference refidx="6"/>  Once HCV-related cirrhosis develops, HCC develops annually in 1% to 8% of patients.<Reference refidx="6"/> Other clinical factors that have been reported to increase risk in individuals with chronic HCV infection include coinfection with HBV or HIV, HCV genotype 1b, and steatosis.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_316">Coinfection with HBV appears to have an additive effect on risk.<Reference refidx="8"/> In addition, degree of increased risk of chronic HCV varies with the presence of other factors and is discussed in sections of this summary that cover those specific factors.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_235"><Title>Cirrhosis</Title><Para id="_236">The prevalence of cirrhosis in the United States is estimated to be 0.3%, which corresponds to more than 600,000 adults.<Reference refidx="12"/>  Because cirrhosis is present in 70% to 90% of HCC patients at the time of diagnosis,<Reference refidx="13"/> cirrhosis is considered a predisposing factor for HCC.<Reference refidx="14"/> In autopsy studies, 80% to 90% of individuals who die of HCC have cirrhotic livers.<Reference refidx="14"/>  A standardized incidence ratio of 60 was observed in a prospective 16-year study of 11,065 Danish individuals with cirrhosis (more than one-half of cases caused by alcohol consumption).<Reference refidx="2"/>  The 5-year cumulative risk of developing HCC for patients with cirrhosis is 5% to 30%, with risk dependent on cause of cirrhosis and stage of cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_237">With perhaps the exception of aflatoxin B1, all HCC risk factors are also risk factors for cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="1"/>  In patients with established cirrhosis, HCC risk may be modifiable with elimination of the factor responsible for cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="15"/> However, evidence to support that possibility is limited, and reduction in risk is likely to occur only in patients with precirrhotic changes or very early-stage cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_238">Patients with HCV-related cirrhosis are at greater risk of developing HCC than are those with cirrhosis related to HBV and alcohol-related cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="14"/>  Using data from several prospective studies, 5-year cumulative HCC incidence rates for individuals with cirrhosis and specific risk factors were estimated as follows: HCV, 30% in Japan and 17% in Western countries; HBV, 15% in endemic areas and 10% in Western countries; and alcohol, 8%.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_239"><Title>Heavy Alcohol Use</Title><Para id="_240">Heavy alcohol use causes cirrhosis; between 8% and 20% of chronic alcoholics develop the condition.<Reference refidx="1"/> HCC also occurs in heavy alcohol users who do not have cirrhosis. Some data exist to suggest a synergistic effect on HCC risk by heavy alcohol use and tobacco use, fatty liver disease, and metabolic syndrome (MetS) components.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_241">Many epidemiological studies have examined the association of alcohol use and HCC; those that could examine the impact of increasing exposure typically have seen a positive correlation between consumption and risk. The following RRs (95% confidence intervals [CIs]) were generated by using models derived from a meta-analysis: 1.19 (1.12–1.27) for 25 g of alcohol per day; 1.40 (1.25–1.56) for 50 g/d; and 1.81 (1.50–2.19) for 100 g/d.<Reference refidx="1"/> While there is agreement that alcohol consumption, especially heavy consumption, is an important HCC risk factor, the magnitude of the increase in risk varies across studies.<Reference refidx="16"/>  Some studies report a twofold increase in risk with heavy consumption, while others observe a greater increase, at least fivefold. Variability is likely caused by many factors, including choice of control subjects, choice of referent categories, definition of heavy alcohol use, and presence of cofactors. </Para><Para id="_242">Alcoholics with cirrhosis appear to have a roughly tenfold risk of developing HCC, relative to alcoholics without cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="16"/> In a cohort study of alcoholics, the summary incidence rate was 0.2 per 100 person-years in people with cirrhosis, and 0.01 per 100 person-years in those without cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="14"/> The evidence for a twofold to threefold increase in risk with heavy alcohol use is more consistent for individuals with chronic HCV infection than for individuals with chronic HBV infection.<Reference refidx="16"/> An Italian case-control study observed synergistic effects of heavy alcohol use and HBV or HCV infection: heavy alcohol use and HBV infection led to a 50-fold increase in risk, and heavy alcohol use and HCV infection led to a  100-fold increase in risk, relative to absence of heavy alcohol use and HBV or HCV infection.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_243"><Title>Aflatoxin B1</Title><Para id="_244">Aflatoxin B1 is a mycotoxin that can contaminate corn and peanuts stored in warm, humid environments.<Reference refidx="2"/> The highest levels of aflatoxin B1 exposure are found in sub-Saharan Africa, Southeast Asia, and China.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_245">Aflatoxin B1 was deemed a carcinogen by the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC) in 1987.<Reference refidx="2"/> The population-attributable risk of aflatoxin B1 to HCC is estimated to be 20% in the Western Pacific (including China), 27% in southeast Asia, and 40% in Africa.<Reference refidx="19"/> Exposure may be responsible for up to 155,000 HCC cases worldwide.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><Para id="_246">Prospective cohort studies established aflatoxin B1 as an etiologic agent for HCC, and demonstrated that magnitude of risk varies by presence or absence of chronic HBV infection. A nested case-control study comprising about 18,000 men who resided in Shanghai in the 1980s indicated that aflatoxin exposure increases risk 4-fold among individuals without chronic HBV infection, but exposure increases risk 60-fold among individuals with chronic HBV infection.<Reference refidx="20"/> A subsequent cohort study in Taiwan observed a similar multiplicative or more-than-multiplicative increase in risk with the presence of both factors, relative to the presence of neither factor.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_247"><Title>NASH</Title><Para id="_248">Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) is an aggressive yet dynamic condition; it can regress, persist at a relatively constant level of activity, or cause progressive fibrosis that leads to cirrhosis. It is estimated that 6% of the U.S. adult population has NASH and that 2% of U.S. adults will develop NASH-related cirrhosis at some time in their lives.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_249">At least 17 prospective cohort studies have examined HCC risk in patients with either NASH or nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD), but few have examined NASH patients alone.<Reference refidx="22"/> The most frequently referenced study of NASH patients is a prospective study conducted in the United States that examined HCC experience in 195 patients with NASH-related cirrhosis. After a median follow-up of 3.2 years, 13% of the patients had been diagnosed with HCC.<Reference refidx="23"/> Yearly cumulative incidence in this case series was 2.6%. A case series of HCV patients was conducted concurrently; that group experienced higher rates (20% had an HCC diagnosis, and yearly cumulative incidence was 4%). </Para><Para id="_250">HCC has been observed in patients with NASH who do not have cirrhosis. Reliable risk estimates are not available, but most researchers believe that these individuals are at elevated risk, albeit lower than in those with cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_251">MetS, obesity, type 2 diabetes, insulin resistance, hypertension, and hyperlipidemia or dyslipidemia, are suspected risk factors for HCC and are associated with NASH. A study of 8.5 million people from 22 countries reported prevalence estimates for NASH patients with the following diagnoses: overweight or obesity, 80%; hyperlipidemia or dyslipidemia, 72%; type 2 diabetes, 44%; and MetS, 71%.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_252"><Title>Cigarette Smoking</Title><Para id="_253">The relationship between tobacco use and liver cancer has been studied extensively for many years.<Reference refidx="25"/> Early epidemiological studies produced positive associations, but doubt regarding the legitimacy of tobacco use as an independent risk factor existed because of the possibility of residual confounding by HBV status, HCV status, and alcohol consumption. In addition, some studies also suggested that the increase in risk might exist only in subgroups, particularly in patients with chronic HBV infection. In 2004, the IARC reported that tobacco use was causally associated with HCC; that conclusion was on the basis of studies that had consistently shown increased risk with increased duration or intensity of tobacco use after careful consideration of potential confounders.<Reference refidx="25"/>   In 2014, the U.S. Surgeon General concluded a causal relationship on the basis of study results published after 2004.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para><Para id="_254">An extensive meta-analysis published in 2009 examined 38 cohort and 58 case-control studies that evaluated the relationship between cigarette smoking and liver cancer.<Reference refidx="25"/>  Studies varied in their degree of adjustment for possible confounders, though most adjusted for age and about one-third adjusted for alcohol consumption. Relative to never-smokers, the summary RR (SRR) for current smokers was 1.51 (95% CI, 1.37–1.67) and for former smokers, 1.12 (95% CI, 0.78–1.60). The point estimate was similar when restricted to five high-quality studies that adjusted for alcohol use (RR, 1.45; 95% CI, 1.14–1.80); the point estimates were similar but not significant when restricted to three studies that adjusted for chronic HBV infection and three studies that adjusted for chronic HCV infection. A dose-response relationship for the number of cigarettes smoked per day was observed, even though there was substantial statistical heterogeneity in the eight studies that were analyzed together for that analysis. A prospective cohort study published after the meta-analysis observed significant linear increases in risk with increasing number of cigarettes smoked per day, years smoked, and pack-years; analyses were adjusted for grams of alcohol consumed per day, and significant linear increases also were observed when daily drinkers were excluded.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_255">A meta-analysis that examined the relationship of cigarette smoking in the presence and absence of chronic HBV or HCV infection observed the following:<Reference refidx="28"/> in the absence of viral infection, cigarette smoking was associated with an RR of about 1.5 to 2; in the presence of HBV, the increase in risk appeared additive; and in the presence of HCV, the increase in risk appeared to be more than multiplicative. Relative to persons who were negative for HBV and did not smoke cigarettes, the adjusted random effects estimate was 21.7 (11.8–40) for those with HBV who smoked cigarettes. Relative to individuals who were negative for HCV and did not smoke cigarettes, the adjusted random effects estimate was 19.6 (1.55–247) for those with HCV who smoked cigarettes.<Reference refidx="28"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_268"><Title>Certain Rare Medical and Genetic Conditions (Untreated HH, Alpha-1-Antitrypsin Deficiency, Glycogen Storage Disease, Porphyria Cutanea Tarda, and Wilson Disease)</Title><Para id="_269">Untreated hereditary hemochromatosis (HH), alpha-1-antitrypsin (AAT) deficiency, glycogen storage disease, porphyria cutanea tarda (PCT), and Wilson disease are known to increase the risk of developing HCC. While increases in risk are known or believed to be large, these conditions contribute little to the burden of HCC.</Para><Para id="_317">Hemochromatosis is an autosomal recessive disorder that leads to excessive absorption of dietary iron and subsequent iron loading in certain organs, including the liver.<Reference refidx="2"/> Between 1 in 200 and 1 in 400 individuals of northern European descent carry the most common genetic mutation, although many of these individuals do not develop progressive iron overload.<Reference refidx="29"/> Patients with untreated hemochromatosis may develop cirrhosis. The annual incidence of HCC in patients with hemochromatosis is 4% once cirrhosis has been established.<Reference refidx="30"/> In cohorts of patients with untreated hemochromatosis and cirrhosis, the observed number of HCC cases is at least 20-fold higher than expected.<Reference refidx="29"/> HCC is seen, albeit rarely, in hemochromatosis patients who do not have cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="29"/> Between 25% and 45% of premature deaths in hemochromatosis patients are caused by HCC.<Reference refidx="29"/> Hemochromatosis can be treated successfully through phlebotomy, repeated at necessary intervals.<Reference refidx="30"/> Treatment before the development of cirrhosis appears to greatly reduce the risk of HCC.<Reference refidx="30"/> It is hypothesized that the presence of other HCC risk factors, particularly chronic HBV infection, chronic HCV infection, and heavy alcohol use, could increase risk among patients with untreated hemochromatosis in a more-than-additive manner,<Reference refidx="29"/> but appropriate data in which to explore this possibility are not available.</Para><Para id="_318">AAT deficiency is an inherited disorder affecting the lungs, liver, and rarely, the skin. It is estimated that about 100,000 individuals in the United States have AAT deficiency.<Reference refidx="31"/> Liver disease results from the accumulation within hepatocytes of unsecreted variant AAT proteins.<Reference refidx="32"/> Individuals with certain AAT deficiency genotypes are at high risk of developing HCC.<Reference refidx="33"/></Para><Para id="_319">Glucose-6-phosphatase deficiency (G6PD) is an autosomal-recessive disorder. It also is known as von Gierke disease and is more commonly known as glycogen storage disease, or GSD1. The defective enzymes involved are mainly active in the liver and kidneys. The incidence of GSD1 is 1 per 100,000 live births. HCC is recognized as a late complication of GSD1.<Reference refidx="34"/> No estimates of increase in HCC risk are available.</Para><Para id="_320">PCT is the result of deficient activity of hepatic uroporphyrinogen; acute intermittent porphyria (AIP, also known as Swedish porphyria) is characterized by deficient activity of porphobilinogen. The prevalence of PCT in the United States is 1 in 25,000.<Reference refidx="35"/> PCT and AIP are associated with increases in HCC risk.<Reference refidx="2"/> A prospective study in Sweden of individuals with porphyria observed a standardized incidence ratio of 21 for PCT and 70 for AIP.<Reference refidx="36"/></Para><Para id="_321">Wilson disease (hepatolenticular degeneration) is caused by a genetic abnormality inherited in an autosomal recessive manner that leads to impairment of cellular copper transport. Worldwide prevalence is approximately 1 in 30,000 live births.<Reference refidx="37"/> Wilson disease causes progressive liver damage, including cirrhosis. The association between Wilson disease and HCC is uncertain but suspected given that tumors of the liver, including HCC, are observed in Wilson disease patients.<Reference refidx="38"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25444466">Lafaro KJ, Demirjian AN, Pawlik TM: Epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma. Surg Oncol Clin N Am 24 (1): 1-17, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2">London WT, McGlynn K: Liver cancer. In: Schottenfeld D, Fraumeni JF Jr, eds.: Cancer Epidemiology and Prevention. 3rd ed. Oxford University Press, 2006, pp 763-86.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention: Hepatitis B FAQs for the Public. Atlanta, GA: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Division of Viral Hepatitis, 2016. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis-b/about/?CDC_AAref_Val=https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/hbv/bfaq.htm">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 5, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="4">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: Hepatitis B Basic Information. Washington, DC: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 2017. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.hhs.gov/hepatitis/learn-about-viral-hepatitis/hepatitis-b-basics/index.html">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 5, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="23632345">Mittal S, El-Serag HB: Epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma: consider the population. J Clin Gastroenterol 47 (Suppl): S2-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="22537432">El-Serag HB: Epidemiology of viral hepatitis and hepatocellular carcinoma. Gastroenterology 142 (6): 1264-1273.e1, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="25220842">Ferlay J, Soerjomataram I, Dikshit R, et al.: Cancer incidence and mortality worldwide: sources, methods and major patterns in GLOBOCAN 2012. Int J Cancer 136 (5): E359-86, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="24839253">El-Serag HB, Kanwal F: Epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma in the United States: where are we? Where do we go? Hepatology 60 (5): 1767-75, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention: Hepatitis C FAQs for Health Professionals. Atlanta, GA: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Division of Viral Hepatitis, 2017. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis-c/hcp/resources/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 5, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="28694740">Ghouri YA, Mian I, Rowe JH: Review of hepatocellular carcinoma: Epidemiology, etiology, and carcinogenesis. J Carcinog 16: 1, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="21859997">Huang YT, Jen CL, Yang HI, et al.: Lifetime risk and sex difference of hepatocellular carcinoma among patients with chronic hepatitis B and C. J Clin Oncol 29 (27): 3643-50, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="25291348">Scaglione S, Kliethermes S, Cao G, et al.: The Epidemiology of Cirrhosis in the United States: A Population-based Study. J Clin Gastroenterol 49 (8): 690-6, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="28108047">Hartke J, Johnson M, Ghabril M: The diagnosis and treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma. Semin Diagn Pathol 34 (2): 153-159, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="15508101">Fattovich G, Stroffolini T, Zagni I, et al.: Hepatocellular carcinoma in cirrhosis: incidence and risk factors. Gastroenterology 127 (5 Suppl 1): S35-50, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="27170391">Saffioti F, Pinzani M: Development and Regression of Cirrhosis. Dig Dis 34 (4): 374-81, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="23101985">Grewal P, Viswanathen VA: Liver cancer and alcohol. Clin Liver Dis 16 (4): 839-50, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="11836196">Donato F, Tagger A, Gelatti U, et al.: Alcohol and hepatocellular carcinoma: the effect of lifetime intake and hepatitis virus infections in men and women. Am J Epidemiol 155 (4): 323-31, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="25921660">McGlynn KA, Petrick JL, London WT: Global epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma: an emphasis on demographic and regional variability. Clin Liver Dis 19 (2): 223-38, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="20172840">Liu Y, Wu F: Global burden of aflatoxin-induced hepatocellular carcinoma: a risk assessment. Environ Health Perspect 118 (6): 818-24, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="23963804">Chen JG, Egner PA, Ng D, et al.: Reduced aflatoxin exposure presages decline in liver cancer mortality in an endemic region of China. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 6 (10): 1038-45, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="29166236">Diehl AM, Day C: Cause, Pathogenesis, and Treatment of Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis. N Engl J Med 377 (21): 2063-2072, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="23041539">White DL, Kanwal F, El-Serag HB: Association between nonalcoholic fatty liver disease and risk for hepatocellular cancer, based on systematic review. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 10 (12): 1342-1359.e2, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="20209604">Ascha MS, Hanouneh IA, Lopez R, et al.: The incidence and risk factors of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. Hepatology 51 (6): 1972-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="26707365">Younossi ZM, Koenig AB, Abdelatif D, et al.: Global epidemiology of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease-Meta-analytic assessment of prevalence, incidence, and outcomes. Hepatology 64 (1): 73-84, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="19720726">Lee YC, Cohet C, Yang YC, et al.: Meta-analysis of epidemiologic studies on cigarette smoking and liver cancer. Int J Epidemiol 38 (6): 1497-511, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="26">Cancer. In: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: The Health Consequences of Smoking—50 Years of Progress: A Report of the Surgeon General. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, CDC, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health, 2014, pp 139-351. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK294309/">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 5, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="21915129">Koh WP, Robien K, Wang R, et al.: Smoking as an independent risk factor for hepatocellular carcinoma: the Singapore Chinese Health Study. Br J Cancer 105 (9): 1430-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="20447919">Chuang SC, Lee YC, Hashibe M, et al.: Interaction between cigarette smoking and hepatitis B and C virus infection on the risk of liver cancer: a meta-analysis. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 19 (5): 1261-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="15656932">Harrison SA, Bacon BR: Relation of hemochromatosis with hepatocellular carcinoma: epidemiology, natural history, pathophysiology, screening, treatment, and prevention. Med Clin North Am 89 (2): 391-409, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="20955973">Villanueva A, Newell P, Hoshida Y: Inherited hepatocellular carcinoma. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 24 (5): 725-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="16162704">Campos MA, Wanner A, Zhang G, et al.: Trends in the diagnosis of symptomatic patients with alpha1-antitrypsin deficiency between 1968 and 2003. Chest 128 (3): 1179-86, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="1608473">Lomas DA, Evans DL, Finch JT, et al.: The mechanism of Z alpha 1-antitrypsin accumulation in the liver. Nature 357 (6379): 605-7, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="22200689">Nelson DR, Teckman J, Di Bisceglie AM, et al.: Diagnosis and management of patients with α1-antitrypsin (A1AT) deficiency. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 10 (6): 575-80, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="2453430">Limmer J, Fleig WE, Leupold D, et al.: Hepatocellular carcinoma in type I glycogen storage disease. Hepatology 8 (3): 531-7, 1988 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="35">Harber LC, Bickers DR: Photosensitivity Diseases: Principles of Diagnosis and Treatment. Saunders, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="10355376">Linet MS, Gridley G, Nyrén O, et al.: Primary liver cancer, other malignancies, and mortality risks following porphyria: a cohort study in Denmark and Sweden. Am J Epidemiol 149 (11): 1010-5, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="20955957">Huster D: Wilson disease. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 24 (5): 531-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="25369181">Pfeiffenberger J, Mogler C, Gotthardt DN, et al.: Hepatobiliary malignancies in Wilson disease. Liver Int 35 (5): 1615-22, 2015.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_278"><Title>Factors With Inadequate Evidence of Increased Risk of HCC</Title><SummarySection id="_279"><Title>NAFL</Title><Para id="_280">Nonalcoholic fatty liver (NAFL) is diagnosed when hepatic steatosis cannot be explained by alcohol use or viral infection.<Reference refidx="1"/> It generally is an asymptomatic, benign condition and is often detected incidentally.<Reference refidx="2"/> NAFL can progress to cirrhosis or nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH). Up to 4% of NAFL patients may develop cirrhosis,<Reference refidx="3"/> and a small clinical study suggested that between 20% and 50% of NAFL patients may develop NASH.<Reference refidx="4"/> The observation that NAFL patients have developed these conditions, which are known to increase hepatocellular cancer (HCC) risk, leads to the conclusion that NAFL increases HCC risk. </Para><Para id="_322">Even though NAFL and NASH have different clinical relevance, they often are combined into one clinical entity known as NAFLD (nonalcoholic fatty liver disease). While prevalence estimates and measures of relative risk (RR) are available for NAFLD and NASH, they are unavailable for NAFL. NAFLD estimates can provide an upper bound for NAFL, however.</Para><Para id="_282">In the United States, NAFLD prevalence is estimated at 25%.<Reference refidx="5"/>  NAFLD prevalence has more than doubled in the last 30 years <Reference refidx="1"/> and is now the most common liver disorder in the United States.<Reference refidx="1"/> NAFLD is sometimes referred to as the hepatic presentation of metabolic syndrome (MetS);<Reference refidx="5"/> increases in NAFLD rates parallel those of MetS, including obesity and type 2 diabetes.<Reference refidx="1"/> MetS, obesity, and type 2 diabetes are frequent NAFLD comorbidities. Estimates of global prevalence of MetS, obesity, and type 2 diabetes in individuals with NAFLD are as follows: MetS, 43%; obesity, 51%; and type 2 diabetes, 23%.<Reference refidx="1"/> A meta-analysis that considered data from countries around the world reported that the HCC incidence rate ratio for NAFLD versus non-NAFLD patients was 1.94 (95% confidence interval [CI], 1.28–2.92).<Reference refidx="1"/> HCC has been diagnosed in patients with both cirrhotic and noncirrhotic NAFLD.<Reference refidx="6"/> A study of 1,500 U.S. Veterans' Administration patients with NAFLD, 107 patients developed HCC. Of the 107 patients, 6 patients had level 1 evidence (histological) of no cirrhosis, and 31 patients had level 2 evidence (imaging or biospecimen) of no cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="7"/> Furthermore, the percentage of noncirrhotic HCC patients among those with NAFLD was greater than was observed for other known HCC risk factors.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_284"><Title>MetS</Title><Para id="_285">MetS is diagnosed when at least three of five metabolic risk factors (central adiposity, high triglyceride levels, low levels of high-density lipoprotein, high fasting glucose levels, and hypertension) are present.<Reference refidx="8"/> The prevalence of MetS has been rising for at least the last 30 years, and by 2012, more than one-third of U.S. adults met the criteria for MetS.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_323">A meta-analysis of more than 7,000 HCC cases from five studies produced a risk ratio of 1.8 (95% CI, 1.37–2.40) for a diagnosis of MetS.<Reference refidx="10"/> The combined risk ratios were varied (range, 1.2 [95% CI, 0.55–2.53] to 3.7 [96% CI, 1.78–7.58]).</Para><Para id="_286">MetS and NAFLD are frequently comorbid conditions. The prevalence of MetS among patients with NAFLD was estimated to be 42.5% in a meta-analysis that included studies from around the world.<Reference refidx="1"/> Given that obesity and type 2 diabetes, two suspected HCC risk factors, are component causes of MetS and also prevalent in patients with NAFLD, attempts to disentangle the independent impact on HCC risk of MetS using epidemiological data is not warranted. Observed associations should not be interpreted as causal relationships.</Para><Para id="_324">Only a few studies have examined insulin resistance, hypertension, and dyslipidemia, yet there is a suggestion that the first two are associated with an increase in HCC risk.<Reference refidx="11"/> These factors will not be discussed further.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_289"><Title>Obesity</Title><Para id="_325">Obesity has been considered extensively as a risk factor for HCC, and in most instances, a positive association has been observed. A European multicenter prospective cohort study with 177 HCC cases examined central obesity, as measured by waste-to-hip ratio, and observed a more-than-threefold increase in HCC risk for the highest tertile (males, ≥ 27.81; females, ≥ 26.65), relative to the lowest (RR, 3.51; 95% CI, 2.09–5.87), after adjustment for several potential confounders, including alcohol consumption.<Reference refidx="12"/> A meta-analysis of 26 prospective studies (25,337 HCC cases) reported that obesity (BMI ≥ 30 kg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) was associated with an increased risk of primary liver cancer (SRR, 1.83; 95% CI, 1.59–2.11). Of note is that the included studies varied in their control for confounding, with 11 not controlling for alcohol consumption and 15 not controlling for history of diabetes; furthermore, not all studies were population based. Nevertheless, point estimates were somewhat consistently suggestive of a modest increase in risk, and associations of a similar magnitude have been seen in Japanese and U.S. populations.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_326">NAFLD is estimated to be present in up to 90% of individuals with obesity.<Reference refidx="15"/> Obesity is a component cause of MetS, another suspected HCC risk factor; obesity also is a frequent comorbidity to type 2 diabetes, yet another suspected HCC risk factor. Attempts to disentangle the independent impact on HCC risk of obesity using epidemiological data is not warranted. Observed associations should not be interpreted as causal relationships. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_292"><Title>Type 2 Diabetes</Title><Para id="_294">Type 2 diabetes has been considered extensively as a risk factor for HCC, and in most instances, positive associations have been observed. The most recent meta-analysis of diabetes and HCC was published in 2012.<Reference refidx="16"/> Seventeen case-control studies and 32 cohort studies were included, and a summary RR of 2.31 (95% CI, 1.87–2.84) for either type 1 or type 2 diabetes was observed. Of the 49 studies used to produce the summary RR, only 19 adjusted for alcohol use and 13 for obesity, and not all were population based. The summary risk estimate for type 2 diabetes alone, based on data from 13 studies, was 2.18 (95% CI, 1.58–3.01).  Studies published since the meta-analysis produced estimates similar to those of the summary measure.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_327">NAFLD is estimated to be present in up to 70% of individuals with type 2 diabetes.<Reference refidx="15"/> Type 2 diabetes is a component cause of MetS, another suspected HCC risk factor; type 2 diabetes is a frequent comorbidity to obesity, yet another suspected HCC risk factor. An additional complexity is that diabetes can be caused by cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="18"/> With the exception of cirrhosis, attempts to disentangle the independent impact on HCC risk of type 2 diabetes using epidemiological data is not warranted. Observed associations should not be interpreted as causal relationships.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21440669">Younossi ZM, Stepanova M, Afendy M, et al.: Changes in the prevalence of the most common causes of chronic liver diseases in the United States from 1988 to 2008. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 9 (6): 524-530.e1; quiz e60, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25018867">Dyson JK, Anstee QM, McPherson S: Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: a practical approach to diagnosis and staging. Frontline Gastroenterol 5 (3): 211-218, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="26057287">Rinella ME: Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review. JAMA 313 (22): 2263-73, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27213358">Calzadilla Bertot L, Adams LA: The Natural Course of Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease. Int J Mol Sci 17 (5): , 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="26707365">Younossi ZM, Koenig AB, Abdelatif D, et al.: Global epidemiology of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease-Meta-analytic assessment of prevalence, incidence, and outcomes. Hepatology 64 (1): 73-84, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="22326465">Baffy G, Brunt EM, Caldwell SH: Hepatocellular carcinoma in non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: an emerging menace. J Hepatol 56 (6): 1384-91, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26196445">Mittal S, El-Serag HB, Sada YH, et al.: Hepatocellular Carcinoma in the Absence of Cirrhosis in United States Veterans is Associated With Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 14 (1): 124-31.e1, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="29128053">Kim D, Touros A, Kim WR: Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Metabolic Syndrome. Clin Liver Dis 22 (1): 133-140, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="25988468">Aguilar M, Bhuket T, Torres S, et al.: Prevalence of the metabolic syndrome in the United States, 2003-2012. JAMA 313 (19): 1973-4, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="24402120">Jinjuvadia R, Patel S, Liangpunsakul S: The association between metabolic syndrome and hepatocellular carcinoma: systemic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Gastroenterol 48 (2): 172-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="24069511">Rahman R, Hammoud GM, Almashhrawi AA, et al.: Primary hepatocellular carcinoma and metabolic syndrome: An update. World J Gastrointest Oncol 5 (9): 186-94, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="22618881">Schlesinger S, Aleksandrova K, Pischon T, et al.: Abdominal obesity, weight gain during adulthood and risk of liver and biliary tract cancer in a European cohort. Int J Cancer 132 (3): 645-57, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="21538440">Welzel TM, Graubard BI, Zeuzem S, et al.: Metabolic syndrome increases the risk of primary liver cancer in the United States: a study in the SEER-Medicare database. Hepatology 54 (2): 463-71, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="22446023">Chen Y, Wang X, Wang J, et al.: Excess body weight and the risk of primary liver cancer: an updated meta-analysis of prospective studies. Eur J Cancer 48 (14): 2137-45, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="25892859">Streba LA, Vere CC, Rogoveanu I, et al.: Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease, metabolic risk factors, and hepatocellular carcinoma: an open question. World J Gastroenterol 21 (14): 4103-10, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="21898753">Wang P, Kang D, Cao W, et al.: Diabetes mellitus and risk of hepatocellular carcinoma: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Diabetes Metab Res Rev 28 (2): 109-22, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="28290049">Wainwright P, Scorletti E, Byrne CD: Type 2 Diabetes and Hepatocellular Carcinoma: Risk Factors and Pathogenesis. Curr Diab Rep 17 (4): 20, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="25220842">Ferlay J, Soerjomataram I, Dikshit R, et al.: Cancer incidence and mortality worldwide: sources, methods and major patterns in GLOBOCAN 2012. Int J Cancer 136 (5): E359-86, 2015.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_328"><Title>Interventions With Adequate Evidence of Decreased Risk of HCC</Title><SummarySection id="_329"><Title>HBV Vaccination</Title><Para id="_330">Hepatitis B virus (HBV) vaccines became available for the prevention of HBV infection in the early 1980s.<Reference refidx="1"/> The World Health Organization recommends that all infants receive the hepatitis B vaccine as soon as possible after birth, preferably within 24 hours.<Reference refidx="2"/> By 2011, 180 countries had introduced infant HBV vaccination, and the global HBV vaccination coverage rate for the final dose was estimated to be about 78%.<Reference refidx="1"/> It is estimated that in 2015, the worldwide prevalence of HBV infection in children younger than 5 years was about 1.3%, compared with about 4.7% in the prevaccination era.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_331">Epidemiological evidence regarding the ability of hepatitis B vaccination to reduce hepatocellular cancer (HCC) comes from follow-up studies of children and risk of childhood liver cancer. In a cluster randomized controlled trial of HBV immunization of 75,000 newborns in Qidong, China (an area where HBV is endemic), the incidence ratio of primary liver cancer in the vaccination-at-birth group compared with the control group (68% of whom received catch-up vaccinations at ages 10–14 years) was 0.16 (95% confidence interval [CI], 0.03–0.77).<Reference refidx="3"/> A registry study conducted in Taiwan identified 1,509 patients aged 6 to 26 years with HCC, and observed that HCC incidence per 100,000 person-years was 0.92 in the unvaccinated cohort and 0.23 in the vaccinated birth cohorts.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_332">It is too soon to know if neonate vaccination also will reduce HCC risk in later adulthood, and no data have been published on the impact of vaccination in adulthood. Nevertheless, vaccination at any age before infection should reduce HCC risk. Mathematical modeling suggests that neonatal HBV vaccination ultimately will lead to the elimination of 70% to 85% of HBV-related HCC cases worldwide.<Reference refidx="5"/> Booster immunizations currently are not recommended for those who are not immunocompromised.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_333"><Title>Treatment for Chronic HBV Infection</Title><Para id="_334">The presence of hepatitis B surface antigen for more than 6 months identifies patients with chronic HBV infection. Expanded and sustained HBV vaccination ultimately will decrease the prevalence of individuals with chronic HBV infection, but the need to minimize downstream consequences of chronic infection, including the risk of HCC, exists for the foreseeable future. Anti-HBV treatment options for chronic HBV carriers are interferon and nucleos(t)ide analogues    (NAs). Interferon is used in young patients who want a short course of therapy and have well-compensated liver disease,<Reference refidx="7"/> although it is not consistently associated with a reduction in HCC incidence. There are several NAs that are preferred because of their low risk of viral resistance (e.g., entecavir, tenofovir disoproxil fumarate, and tenofovir alafenamide). Other NAs (e.g., lamivudine, adefovir, and telbivudine) are available, although they are less preferred because of the emergence of viral resistance, which may lead to hepatic decompensation.<Reference refidx="8"/> Reductions in HCC risk, when observed for interferon therapy, have typically been among treatment responders with preexisting liver cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="9"/> A reduction in HCC risk has been consistently observed for patients treated with NA therapy, regardless of cirrhosis status.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_369">The decision to initiate anti-HBV therapy depends on several factors, including the presence or absence of hepatitis B e antigen (HBeAg), a relative increase of alanine transaminase (ALT) compared with the upper limit of normal (ULN), HBV DNA level, degree of fibrosis, and age. It has been recommended that patients in the immune-active phase of chronic HBV be treated with anti-HBV therapy. Patients are considered to be in the immune-active phase if they have evidence of liver inflammation and are either: (1) HBeAg-positive with an HBV DNA  level of more than 20,000 IU/mL and an ALT  level more than two times the ULN, or (2) HBeAg-negative with an HBV DNA  level of more than 2,000 IU/mL and an ALT level more than two times the ULN.<Reference refidx="8"/> Patients with inactive HBV, in general, have normal ALT levels and HBV DNA levels of more than 2,000 IU/mL.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_370">Antiviral therapy has not been routinely recommended for patients who are not in the immune-active phase. Patients who are neither in the immune-active phase nor in one of the other standard phases of chronic HBV (immune-tolerant phase or inactive phase) are considered to be in an indeterminate phase, representing approximately 40% of patients with chronic HBV.<Reference refidx="10"/> The 10-year cumulative incidence of HCC was higher among patients in the indeterminate phase of chronic HBV (4.6%; 95% CI, 3.0%–7.2%) compared with patients in the inactive phase (0.5%; 95% CI, 0.2%–1.3%).<Reference refidx="10"/> However, their risk may be reduced if anti-HBV therapy is initiated.</Para><Para id="_371">In a multicenter, international, retrospective cohort study of 819 patients with chronic HBV who had no fibrosis or liver cirrhosis in the indeterminate phase, anti-HBV therapy was associated with a 70% reduction in HCC risk (hazard ratio [HR], 0.30; 95% CI, 0.10–0.60).<Reference refidx="10"/> The cumulative incidence of HCC was significantly lower in those treated with anti-HBV therapy compared with those who were not, with proportions as follows:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_377" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>At 10 years, 3.9% (95% CI, 1.9%–7.8%) versus 14.7% (95% CI, 9.6%–22.0%).</ListItem><ListItem>At 15 years, 9.4% (95% CI 4.5%–19.3%) versus 19.1% (95% CI, 12.9%–27.6%).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_372">While these findings suggest a significant benefit of anti-HBV therapy in reducing HCC incidence, several limitations should be noted. Firstly, the study did not specify details on HCC surveillance or the HCC diagnostic criteria used, although it was reported that diagnoses were made according to the American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases (AASLD) guidelines, using either pathology or noninvasive imaging. Additionally, the study did not provide information about the specific types or doses of anti-HBV therapy administered, although it was noted that patients in the treatment group remained on therapy throughout follow-up.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><Para id="_335">The degree of HCC risk reduction with NA therapy has been nearly consistent across studies, with treated patients experiencing about half the risk of those who are not treated with NA therapy.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Most studies have been conducted in countries outside North America, yet the two studies conducted in North America observed similarly-sized, statistically significant reductions. A Canadian cohort of 322 patients with chronic HBV infection experienced lower than expected rates of HCC with a standardized incidence ratio of 0.46 (95% CI, 0.23–0.82) for patients treated with NA therapy, relative to those who were not.<Reference refidx="13"/> A U.S. cohort of more than 2,000 patients with chronic HBV infection observed an HR of 0.39 (95% CI, 0.27–0.56) with treatment, although the cohort included patients treated with interferon.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><SummarySection id="_365"><Title>Potential harms of treatment for chronic HBV infection</Title><Para id="_366">NA-based therapy is generally considered safe with limited side effects. Lactic acidosis has been reported along with renal toxicity and osteomalacia. In patients with chronic HBV infection and known renal or bone disease, tenofovir alafenamide may be considered as it has been found to be more stable in the plasma and delivers active metabolite to hepatocytes efficiently, allowing a lower dose and less risk of bone and renal toxicity. Interferon-based therapy has been associated with flu-like symptoms, fatigue, mood disturbances, cytopenias, and autoimmune disorders.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_337"><Title>Availability of Food Not Contaminated With Aflatoxin B1</Title><Para id="_338">Qidong, China, historically has had exceptionally high rates of primary liver cancer due to endemic chronic HBV infection and a food supply (predominately corn) with high levels of aflatoxin B1 contamination. Agricultural reforms in the 1980s led to greater availability of rice, which typically harbors much lower levels of aflatoxin B1. A population-based cancer registry was used to examine primary liver cancer mortality in Qidong residents born before 2002, the year that universal HBV vaccination of newborns was achieved. For that group, a higher-than-50% reduction in mortality from primary liver cancer was observed following the availability of rice. About 80% of the benefit was estimated to be among those infected with HBV.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26651252">Kao JH: Hepatitis B vaccination and prevention of hepatocellular carcinoma. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 29 (6): 907-17, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2">World Health Organization: Hepatitis B Fact Sheet. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization, 2017. <ExternalRef xref="http://www.who.int/en/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/hepatitis-b">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 5, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25549238">Qu C, Chen T, Fan C, et al.: Efficacy of neonatal HBV vaccination on liver cancer and other liver diseases over 30-year follow-up of the Qidong hepatitis B intervention study: a cluster randomized controlled trial. PLoS Med 11 (12): e1001774, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27269245">Chang MH, You SL, Chen CJ, et al.: Long-term Effects of Hepatitis B Immunization of Infants in Preventing Liver Cancer. Gastroenterology 151 (3): 472-480.e1, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="25921660">McGlynn KA, Petrick JL, London WT: Global epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma: an emphasis on demographic and regional variability. Clin Liver Dis 19 (2): 223-38, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="21653306">Leuridan E, Van Damme P: Hepatitis B and the need for a booster dose. Clin Infect Dis 53 (1): 68-75, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="19399806">Perrillo R: Benefits and risks of interferon therapy for hepatitis B. Hepatology 49 (5 Suppl): S103-11, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="29405329">Terrault NA, Lok ASF, McMahon BJ, et al.: Update on prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of chronic hepatitis B: AASLD 2018 hepatitis B guidance. Hepatology 67 (4): 1560-1599, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="22806323">Lai CL, Yuen MF: Prevention of hepatitis B virus-related hepatocellular carcinoma with antiviral therapy. Hepatology 57 (1): 399-408, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="33465482">Huang DQ, Li X, Le MH, et al.: Natural History and Hepatocellular Carcinoma Risk in Untreated Chronic Hepatitis B Patients With Indeterminate Phase. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 20 (8): 1803-1812.e5, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="37184202">Huang DQ, Tran A, Yeh ML, et al.: Antiviral therapy substantially reduces HCC risk in patients with chronic hepatitis B infection in the indeterminate phase. Hepatology 78 (5): 1558-1568, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="23713520">Singal AK, Salameh H, Kuo YF, et al.: Meta-analysis: the impact of oral anti-viral agents on the incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic hepatitis B. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 38 (2): 98-106, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="25312649">Coffin CS, Rezaeeaval M, Pang JX, et al.: The incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma is reduced in patients with chronic hepatitis B on long-term nucleos(t)ide analogue therapy. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 40 (11-12): 1262-9, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="24107395">Gordon SC, Lamerato LE, Rupp LB, et al.: Antiviral therapy for chronic hepatitis B virus infection and development of hepatocellular carcinoma in a US population. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 12 (5): 885-93, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="23963804">Chen JG, Egner PA, Ng D, et al.: Reduced aflatoxin exposure presages decline in liver cancer mortality in an endemic region of China. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 6 (10): 1038-45, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_263"><Title>Interventions with Inadequate Evidence of Decreased Risk of HCC</Title><SummarySection id="_264"><Title>HCV Treatment With DAAs</Title><Para id="_265">Treatment with direct-acting antivirals (DAAs) leads to elimination of hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection in almost all patients.<Reference refidx="1"/> The goal of therapy is to eradicate HCV RNA and attain a sustained virologic response (SVR), which is defined as an undetectable RNA level 12 weeks after the completion of therapy. Attainment of an SVR is associated with a 97% to 100% chance of being HCV RNA negative during 5-year follow-up, and patients can therefore be considered cured of the HCV infection.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_266">Results from studies of hepatocellular cancer (HCC) risk after attaining SVR have produced conflicting results; some have observed increases in risk after treatment.<Reference refidx="2"/> Most studies have included small numbers of patients, and some had insufficient follow-up time.<Reference refidx="2"/> Some studies did not consider that the presence or absence of cirrhosis could affect the impact of DAAs on HCC risk.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_267">The strongest evidence to date regarding DAA treatment and HCC risk comes from a cohort study of more than 22,000 U.S. veterans receiving DAA treatment for HCV infection.<Reference refidx="2"/> In that cohort, 271 HCC diagnoses occurred.  Patients treated with DAAs who attained an SVR had an approximately 75% reduction in the HCC risk,  relative to those who did not attain an SVR. Reduction relative risk with SVR was similar in patients with cirrhosis (hazard ratio [HR], 0.31;  95% CI, 0.23–0.44) and patients without cirrhosis (HR, 0.18; 95% CI, 0.11–0.30). Nevertheless, among patients who achieved an SVR, those with cirrhosis had an almost fivefold increase in HCC risk, relative to those without cirrhosis (HR, 4.73; 95% CI, 3.34–6.68).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_352"><Title>Statin Use Among Adults With HBV or HCV</Title><Para id="_353">Statins, also known as 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl CoA (HMG-CoA) reductase inhibitors, are cholesterol-lowering medications. Statins have been implicated in the regulation of cell proliferation, apoptosis, and tumor progression in cancer patients, and statin use at the time of cancer diagnosis has been reported to be associated with reduced cancer risk and improved survival. A systematic review and meta-analysis noted that statin use was associated with lower cancer mortality and progression overall and in patients who initiated statin use after cancer diagnosis.<Reference refidx="4"/> Another meta-analysis indicated that statin use may be associated with a 37% reduced risk of HCC (odds ratio [OR], 0.63; 95% CI, 0.52– 0.76).<Reference refidx="5"/> However, this meta-analysis included a patient population with and without HBV/HCV infection, making the results difficult to interpret for HBV- or HCV-infected  individuals.<Reference refidx="6"/> In a U.K. study of 3,719 liver cancer cases and 14,876 controls, the authors observed a 35% lower risk (OR, 0.65; 95% CI, 0.58–0.74) of liver cancer among patients who received one or more statin prescriptions before a liver cancer diagnosis date for cases and corresponding date for matched controls     after adjusting for factors including HBV infection, HCV infection, alcohol-related disorders, and diabetes mellitus.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_367"><Title>Nonstatin Cholesterol-Lowering Medication Use Among Adults</Title><Para id="_368">Although several studies have shown that statin use lowers liver cancer risk, many patients are not able to tolerate statin therapy because of its side effects. It is unclear whether other cholesterol-lowering medications reduce the risk of liver cancer. Cholesterol-absorption inhibitors work in the small intestine to prevent cholesterol reabsorption and reduce the level of circulating cholesterol, which may regulate key signaling factors   for angiogenesis and liver tumor growth. In the U.K.-based, nested case-control study, receiving one or more prescriptions for cholesterol-absorption inhibitors     was associated with a lower risk of liver cancer overall (OR, 0.69; 95% CI, 0.50–0.95) and among patients with liver disease (OR, 0.53; 95% CI, 0.30–0.96).<Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26787172">Simmons B, Saleem J, Hill A, et al.: Risk of Late Relapse or Reinfection With Hepatitis C Virus After Achieving a Sustained Virological Response: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. Clin Infect Dis 62 (6): 683-694, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="28642197">Kanwal F, Kramer J, Asch SM, et al.: Risk of Hepatocellular Cancer in HCV Patients Treated With Direct-Acting Antiviral Agents. Gastroenterology 153 (4): 996-1005.e1, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="29264439">Buonomo AR, Gentile I, Borgia G: Direct acting antiviral agents and hepatocellular carcinoma development: don't take it for granted. Transl Gastroenterol Hepatol 2: 101, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27859151">Mei Z, Liang M, Li L, et al.: Effects of statins on cancer mortality and progression: A systematic review and meta-analysis of 95 cohorts including 1,111,407 individuals. Int J Cancer 140 (5): 1068-1081, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="23063971">Singh S, Singh PP, Singh AG, et al.: Statins are associated with a reduced risk of hepatocellular cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Gastroenterology 144 (2): 323-32, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="32272891">Li X, Sheng L, Liu L, et al.: Statin and the risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with hepatitis B virus or hepatitis C virus infection: a meta-analysis. BMC Gastroenterol 20 (1): 98, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="39072717">Zamani SA, Graubard BI, Hyer M, et al.: Use of cholesterol-lowering medications in relation to risk of primary liver cancer in the Clinical Practice Research Datalink. Cancer 130 (20): 3506-3518, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (04/30/2025)</Title><Para id="_19">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_363"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000433282#_151" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-prevention-pdq">Incidence, Mortality, and Survival</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_381">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000433282#_228" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-prevention-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cases and deaths for 2025 (cited American Cancer Society as reference 2).</Para><Para id="_382">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000433282#_229" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-prevention-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cases and deaths worldwide in 2022 (cited Bray et al. as reference 4).</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000433282#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-prevention-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about liver (hepatocellular) cancer prevention. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Prevention. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/hp/liver-prevention-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/hp/liver-prevention-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389403]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2005-05-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-04-30</DateLastModified></Summary>
