<Summary id="CDR0000441069"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Aromatherapy with the use of essential oils has been studied in cancer patients to help with symptom relief. Read about how aromatherapy massage or inhalation of essential oils have reduced symptoms in cancer patients in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/aromatherapy-pdq">Aromatherapy With Essential Oils (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/aromatherapy-pdq">Aromatherapy With Essential Oils (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000441095">aromatherapy and essential oils</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_134">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of aromatherapy with essential oils in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_135">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>aromatherapy with essential oils</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Aromatherapy With Essential Oils (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Aromatherapy With Essential Oils (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Aromatherapy With Essential Oils</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_2">This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summary provides an overview of the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">essential oils</GlossaryTermRef> primarily to improve the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer patients.  This summary includes a brief history of aromatherapy, a review of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory studies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, and possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> associated with aromatherapy use. </Para><Para id="_3">This summary contains the following key information:
</Para><ItemizedList id="_7" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Aromatherapy is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> use of essential oils (also known as volatile oils) from plants (flowers, herbs, or trees) for the improvement of physical, emotional, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef> well-being.</ListItem><ListItem>Aromatherapy is used by patients with cancer primarily as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supportive care</GlossaryTermRef>  for general well-being.</ListItem><ListItem>Aromatherapy is commonly used with other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044951" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary treatments</GlossaryTermRef> (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454761" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">massage</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acupuncture</GlossaryTermRef>) as well as with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatments</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269453" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptom management</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Essential oils are volatile liquid substances <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracted</GlossaryTermRef> from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatic</GlossaryTermRef> plant material by steam distillation or mechanical expression; oils produced with the aid of chemical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solvents</GlossaryTermRef> are not considered true essential oils.</ListItem><ListItem>As essential oils age, the  chemical composition changes. Many essential oils do not have an expiration date.</ListItem><ListItem>	Essential oils are available in the United States for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhalation</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045927" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">topical</GlossaryTermRef> treatment. Topical treatments are generally used in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462674" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diluted</GlossaryTermRef> forms.</ListItem><ListItem>Aromatherapy is not widely administered via <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ingestion</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The effects of aromatherapy are theorized to result from the binding of chemical components in the essential oil to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">receptors</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000698420" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">olfactory bulb</GlossaryTermRef>, impacting the brain’s emotional center, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">limbic system</GlossaryTermRef>.  Topical application of aromatic oils may exert <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibacterial</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anti-inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analgesic</GlossaryTermRef> effects.</ListItem><ListItem>Studies in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animals</GlossaryTermRef> show <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450118" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sedative</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450121" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stimulant</GlossaryTermRef> effects of specific essential oils as well as positive effects on behavior and the immune system.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Functional imaging</GlossaryTermRef> studies in humans support the influence of odors on the limbic system and its emotional pathways.</ListItem><ListItem>Human clinical trials have investigated aromatherapy primarily in the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with critical illnesses or in other hospitalized patients.  Several clinical trials involving patients with cancer have been published.</ListItem><ListItem>Aromatherapy has a relatively low <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> profile when administered by inhalation or diluted topical application.</ListItem><ListItem>Aromatherapy products are not subject to approval by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef>  unless there is a claim for treatment of specific diseases.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_20">Many of the medical and scientific terms used in the summary are hypertext linked (at first use in each section) to the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>, which is oriented toward nonexperts.  When a linked term is clicked, a definition will appear in a separate window.</Para><Para id="_21">Reference citations in some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef>  cancer information summaries may include links to external websites that are operated by individuals or organizations for the purpose of marketing or advocating the use of specific treatments or products. These reference citations are included for informational purposes only. Their inclusion should not be viewed as an endorsement of the content of the websites, or of any treatment or product, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_6"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Aromatherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">derivative</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbal medicine</GlossaryTermRef>, which is itself a subset of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biological</GlossaryTermRef> or nature-based <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef>.  Aromatherapy has been defined as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">essential oils</GlossaryTermRef> from   plants for the improvement of physical, emotional, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef> well-being.  </Para><Para id="_22">Essential oils are volatile liquid substances <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracted</GlossaryTermRef> from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatic</GlossaryTermRef> plant material by steam distillation or mechanical expression.  Essential oils produced with the aid of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solvents</GlossaryTermRef> are not considered true essential oils because the solvent residues can alter the quality of the essential oils and lead to adulteration of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462679" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fragrance</GlossaryTermRef> or to skin irritation.</Para><Para id="_23">Essential oils are made up of a large array of chemical components that consist of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolites</GlossaryTermRef> found in various plant materials.  The major chemical components of essential oils include monoterpenes, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esters</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463111" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aldehydes</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ketones</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohols</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463152" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phenols</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463160" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxides</GlossaryTermRef>,  which are volatile and may produce characteristic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462689" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">odors</GlossaryTermRef>.  Different types of essential oils contain varying amounts of each of these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef>, which are said to give each essential oil its particular fragrance and therapeutic characteristics.  Plant species may have different chemovarieties (variations of subspecies that produce essential oils with different chemical compositions, as a result of genetic variation and growth conditions).<Reference refidx="1"/> Thus, their essential oils can occur as several chemotypes that differ in chemical composition and may produce different <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> effects. It should be noted that essential oils are distinctly different chemically from (fatty) oils, such as those used as food. As essential oils age, the  chemical composition changes. Many essential oils do not have an expiration date.</Para><Para id="_24"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Synthetic</GlossaryTermRef> odors are often made up of many of the same compounds that are components of the essential oils. These compounds are synthesized and typically  combined with other odor-producing chemicals.  However, synthetic fragrances frequently contain irritants, such as solvents and propellants, that can <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454808" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trigger</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322883" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sensitivities</GlossaryTermRef> in some people.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Most aromatherapists believe that synthetic fragrances are inferior to essential oils because they lack natural or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046649" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vital</GlossaryTermRef> energy; however, this has been contested by odor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologists</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462667" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biochemists</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_25">Aromatherapy is used or claimed to be useful for a vast array of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>.   Published studies regarding the uses of aromatherapy have generally focused on its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef> effects as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef> reliever or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiolytic</GlossaryTermRef> agent or its use as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045927" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">topical</GlossaryTermRef> treatment for skin-related conditions.</Para><Para id="_26">A large body of literature has been published on the effects of odors on the human brain and emotions.  Some studies  have tested the effects of essential oils on mood, alertness, and mental stress in healthy participants.  Other studies investigated the effects of various (usually synthetic) odors on task performance, reaction time, and autonomic parameters or evaluated the direct effects of odors on the brain via <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462676" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electroencephalogram</GlossaryTermRef> patterns and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">functional imaging</GlossaryTermRef> studies.<Reference refidx="6"/>   Such studies have consistently shown that odors can produce specific effects on human neuropsychological and autonomic function and that odors can influence mood, perceived health, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463165" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">arousal</GlossaryTermRef>.  These studies suggest that odors may have therapeutic applications  in the context of stressful and adverse psychological conditions.</Para><Para id="_27"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Practitioners</GlossaryTermRef> of aromatherapy apply essential oils using several different  methods, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_194" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Indirect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhalation</GlossaryTermRef> via a  room diffuser or drops of oil placed near the patient (e.g., on a tissue), or inside a  vial  with saturated cotton.</ListItem><ListItem>Direct inhalation used in an individual inhaler      (e.g.,       a few drops of essential oil floated on top of hot water to aid a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sinus</GlossaryTermRef> headache).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462663" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Aromatherapy massage</GlossaryTermRef>, which is the application to the body of essential oils diluted in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carrier oil</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_195"> Other direct and indirect applications include mixing essential oils in bath salts and lotions or applying them to dressings.</Para><Para id="_142">Different aromatherapy practitioners  may have different recipes for treating specific  conditions, involving various combinations of essential oils and methods of application.  Differences seem to be  practitioner dependent, with some common uses more accepted throughout the aromatherapy community.  Training and certification in aromatherapy for lay practitioners is available at several schools throughout the United States and United Kingdom;     however,  there is no professional standardization   in the United States  and no license is required to practice in either country.  Thus, there is little consistency among practitioners in the specific 
treatments used  for specific illnesses.  This lack of standardization has led to variability in therapeutic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protocols</GlossaryTermRef> used in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research</GlossaryTermRef> on the effects of aromatherapy. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Anecdotal</GlossaryTermRef> evidence alone or previous experience has driven the choice of essential oils and different researchers  choose different essential oils when studying the same applications.  However, now there are  specific courses for licensed health professionals that give nursing or continuing medical education credit hours, including a small research component and  information about evaluating and measuring outcomes.</Para><Para id="_96"> The National Association for Holistic Aromatherapy (NAHA) (<ExternalRef xref="http://www.naha.org/">www.naha.org/</ExternalRef>) and the Alliance of International Aromatherapists    (<ExternalRef xref="http://www.alliance-aromatherapists.org/">www.alliance-aromatherapists.org</ExternalRef>) are the two governing bodies for national educational standards for aromatherapists.  NAHA is taking steps toward standardizing aromatherapy certification in the United States.  Many schools offer certificate programs approved by NAHA.            A list of these schools can be found on the NAHA website  (<ExternalRef xref="https://naha.org/index.php/education/approved-schools/">https://naha.org/index.php/education/approved-schools/</ExternalRef>). National <ExternalRef xref="http://www.aromatherapycouncil.org/">examinations</ExternalRef> in aromatherapy are held twice per year.</Para><Para id="_86">The Canadian Federation of Aromatherapists has established standards for aromatherapy certification in Canada (<ExternalRef xref="http://www.cfacanada.com/">www.cfacanada.com/</ExternalRef>).  They also have standards for safety and professional conduct and a public directory of certified aromatherapists.  Other countries may  have similar organizations.</Para><Para id="_28">Although essential oils are given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">orally</GlossaryTermRef> or internally by aromatherapists in France and Germany,  their use is generally limited to inhalation or topical application in the United Kingdom and United States.    Nonmedical use of essential oils is common in the flavoring and fragrance industries. Most essential oils have been classified as GRAS (generally recognized as safe), at specified <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentration</GlossaryTermRef> limits, by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA).  For a list of international aromatherapy programs, see the International  Federation of Aromatherapists  website (<ExternalRef xref="https://ifaroma.org/en_GB/home">www.ifaroma.org/</ExternalRef>).</Para><Para id="_29">Aromatherapy products do not need approval by the FDA.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Wildwood C: The Encyclopedia of Aromatherapy. Healing Arts Press, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="23832131">Silva-Néto RP, Peres MF, Valença MM: Odorant substances that trigger headaches in migraine patients. Cephalalgia 34 (1): 14-21, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23829679">Vethanayagam D, Vliagoftis H, Mah D, et al.: Fragrance materials in asthma: a pilot study using a surrogate aerosol product. J Asthma 50 (9): 975-82, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="24767833">Celeiro M, Guerra E, Lamas JP, et al.: Development of a multianalyte method based on micro-matrix-solid-phase dispersion for the analysis of fragrance allergens and preservatives in personal care products. J Chromatogr A 1344: 1-14, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Dodd GH: The molecular dimension in perfumery. In: Van Toller S, Dodd GH, eds.: Perfumery: The Psychology and Biology of Fragrance. Chapman and Hall, 1988, pp 19-46.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="8331544">Buchbauer G, Jirovetz L, Jäger W, et al.: Fragrance compounds and essential oils with sedative effects upon inhalation. J Pharm Sci 82 (6): 660-4, 1993.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><Title>History</Title><Para id="_9">Proponents of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatherapy</GlossaryTermRef> report that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatic</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">essential oils</GlossaryTermRef> have been used for thousands of years as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450121" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stimulants</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450118" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sedatives</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446114" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> and as treatments for a wide range of other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disorders</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/>  They link it historically to the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infused</GlossaryTermRef> oils and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">unguents</GlossaryTermRef> in the Bible and ancient Egypt,<Reference refidx="1"/> remedies used throughout the Middle Ages and the Renaissance,<Reference refidx="2"/> and the burning of aromatic plants in various religious rites.   The current applications of aromatherapy did not come about until the early 20th century when the French chemist and perfumer Rene Gattefosse coined the term <Emphasis>aromatherapy</Emphasis> and published a book of that name in 1937.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Gattefosse proposed the use of aromatherapy to treat diseases in virtually every <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> system, citing mostly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anecdotal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case-based evidence</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_30">Although Gattefosse and his colleagues in France, Italy, and Germany studied the effects of aromatherapy for some 30 years, its use went out of fashion midcentury and was rediscovered by another Frenchman, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physician</GlossaryTermRef>, Jean Valnet, in the latter part of the century.  Valnet published his book <Emphasis>The Practice of Aromatherapy</Emphasis> in 1982,<Reference refidx="3"/>  at which time the practice became more well-known in Britain and the United States.  Through the 1980s and 1990s, as patients in Western countries became increasingly interested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)</GlossaryTermRef> treatments, aromatherapy developed a following that continues to grow to this day.  In addition to the use of essential oils by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nurses</GlossaryTermRef> and aromatherapy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">practitioners</GlossaryTermRef> for specific medical issues, the popularity of aromatherapy has also been exploited by cosmetics companies that have created lines of essential oil-based (although often with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">synthetic</GlossaryTermRef> component) cosmetics and toiletries, claiming to improve mood and well-being in their users.</Para><Para id="_31">Despite the growing popularity of aromatherapy in the latter part of the 20th century (especially in the United Kingdom), little <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research</GlossaryTermRef> on aromatherapy was available in the English-language medical literature until the early or mid-1990s.  The research that began to appear in the 1990s was most often conducted by nurses, who tended to be the primary practitioners of aromatherapy in the United States and United Kingdom (although it is dispensed by medical doctors in France and Germany).  Aromatherapists now publish their own journal, the <Emphasis>International Journal of Essential Oil Therapeutics</Emphasis>.      Also, many studies regarding the effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462689" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">odor</GlossaryTermRef> on the brain and other systems in animals and healthy humans have been published in the context of odor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730431" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychology</GlossaryTermRef> and neurobiology (and in the absence of the specific term aromatherapy).</Para><Para id="_32">In addition to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045927" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">topical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462661" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antimicrobial</GlossaryTermRef> uses,<Reference refidx="4"/> aromatherapy has also been proposed for use in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wound</GlossaryTermRef> care <Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  and to treat a variety of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">localized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and illnesses such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alopecia</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462675" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">eczema</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446534" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pruritus</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> Aromatherapy has also been studied via <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhalation</GlossaryTermRef> for airway reactivity.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_33">Studies on aromatherapy have examined a variety of other conditions, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_196" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>  Sedation and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463165" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">arousal</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem>Startle reflex and reaction time.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Psychological</GlossaryTermRef> states such as mood, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef>, and general sense of well-being.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/></ListItem><ListItem>    Psychiatric disorders.<Reference refidx="30"/></ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Neurologic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">impairment</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="23"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chronic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462925" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal failure</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="24"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462659" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Agitation</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462672" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dementia</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/></ListItem><ListItem>   Smoking withdrawal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/></ListItem><ListItem>Motion sickness.<Reference refidx="38"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043980" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Postoperative</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/></ListItem><ListItem>   Nausea and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">emesis</GlossaryTermRef> in combination with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, pain, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> in patients in labor.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="41"/></ListItem><ListItem>Pain alone.<Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/></ListItem><ListItem>  Pain in combination with other symptoms.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_34">Published articles have described the use of aromatherapy in specific hospital settings such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> wards, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hospices</GlossaryTermRef>, and other areas where patients are critically ill and require <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative care</GlossaryTermRef> for the following symptoms: </Para><ItemizedList id="_197" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Nausea.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045359" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymphedema</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="47"/></ListItem><ListItem>          Generalized <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef>.  </ListItem><ListItem>Anxiety.<Reference refidx="48"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Depression</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="49"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_198">  In addition, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000286105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">observational studies</GlossaryTermRef> provide examples of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> uses of aromatherapy (and other CAM <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270868" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">modalities</GlossaryTermRef>), although they are generally not evidence based.  Participants have included homebound patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044178" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">terminal disease</GlossaryTermRef>,<Reference refidx="50"/> and  hospitalized patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="51"/> Aromatherapy has also been used to reduce malodor of necrotic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulcers</GlossaryTermRef> in cancer patients.<Reference refidx="52"/>     

</Para><Para id="_97">Studies of aromatherapy use with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mental health</GlossaryTermRef> patients have also been conducted.<Reference refidx="53"/>     Most of the resulting  articles describe successful incorporation of aromatherapy into the treatment of these patients, although outcomes are clearly subjective.</Para><Para id="_49">Theories about the mechanism of action of aromatherapy with essential oils differ, depending on the community studying them.  Proponents of aromatherapy often cite the connection between <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">olfaction</GlossaryTermRef> and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">limbic system</GlossaryTermRef> in the brain as the basis for the effects of aromatherapy on mood and emotions; less is said about proposed mechanisms for its effects on other parts of the body.  Most of the aromatherapy literature, however, lacks in-depth neurophysiological studies on the nature of olfaction and its link to the limbic system, and it generally does not cite research that shows these links.  Proponents of aromatherapy also believe that the effects of the treatments are based on the special nature of the essential oils used and that essential oils produce effects on the body that are greater than the sum of the individual <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef> components of the scents.  
</Para><Para id="_35">These assertions have been contested by the biochemistry and psychology communities, which take a different view of the possible mechanism of action of odors on the human brain (most do not differentiate the odors produced by essential oils from those of synthetic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462679" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fragrances</GlossaryTermRef>).<Reference refidx="30"/>                                     This neurobiological view, which focuses mostly on the emotional and psychological effects of fragrances (as opposed to the other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptomatic</GlossaryTermRef> effects claimed by aromatherapists), takes into account what is known about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462728" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">olfactory transduction</GlossaryTermRef>  and the connection of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">olfactory system</GlossaryTermRef> to other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> functions, including memory; however, it is primarily theoretical because of the  lack of significant research addressing this topic.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Tisserand R: Essential oils as psychotherapeutic agents. In: Van Toller S, Dodd GH, eds.: Perfumery: The Psychology and Biology of Fragrance. Chapman and Hall, 1988, pp 167-80.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Gattefosse RM: Gattefosse's Aromatherapy. CW Daniel, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Valnet J: The Practice of Aromatherapy: A Classic Compendium of Plant Medicines &amp; Their Healing Properties. Healing Arts Press, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12360766">Hartman D, Coetzee JC: Two US practitioners' experience of using essential oils for wound care. J Wound Care 11 (8): 317-20, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10776219">Asquith S: The use of aromatherapy in wound care. J Wound Care 8 (6): 318-20, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15555788">Edwards-Jones V, Buck R, Shawcross SG, et al.: The effect of essential oils on methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus using a dressing model. Burns 30 (8): 772-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9828867">Hay IC, Jamieson M, Ormerod AD: Randomized trial of aromatherapy. Successful treatment for alopecia areata. Arch Dermatol 134 (11): 1349-52, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="10960901">Anderson C, Lis-Balchin M, Kirk-Smith M: Evaluation of massage with essential oils on childhood atopic eczema. Phytother Res 14 (6): 452-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12240499">Ro YJ, Ha HC, Kim CG, et al.: The effects of aromatherapy on pruritus in patients undergoing hemodialysis. Dermatol Nurs 14 (4): 231-4, 237-8, 256; quiz 239, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="7111875">Cohen BM, Dressler WE: Acute aromatics inhalation modifies the airways. Effects of the common cold. Respiration 43 (4): 285-93, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="10069621">Diego MA, Jones NA, Field T, et al.: Aromatherapy positively affects mood, EEG patterns of alertness and math computations. Int J Neurosci 96 (3-4): 217-24, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11806592">Motomura N, Sakurai A, Yotsuya Y: Reduction of mental stress with lavender odorant. Percept Mot Skills 93 (3): 713-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="8146248">Miltner W, Matjak M, Braun C, et al.: Emotional qualities of odors and their influence on the startle reflex in humans. Psychophysiology 31 (1): 107-10, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="11958848">Millot JL, Brand G, Morand N: Effects of ambient odors on reaction time in humans. Neurosci Lett 322 (2): 79-82, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="1491983">Stevenson C: Measuring the effects of aromatherapy. Nurs Times 88 (41): 62-3, 1992 Oct 7-13.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="7897075">Dunn C, Sleep J, Collett D: Sensing an improvement: an experimental study to evaluate the use of aromatherapy, massage and periods of rest in an intensive care unit. J Adv Nurs 21 (1): 34-40, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="8321672">Buckle J: Aromatherapy. Nurs Times 89 (20): 32-5, 1993 May 19-25.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="12066022">Hadfield N: The role of aromatherapy massage in reducing anxiety in patients with malignant brain tumours. Int J Palliat Nurs 7 (6): 279-85, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="19">Wilkinson S: Aromatherapy and massage in palliative care. Int J Palliat Nurs  1 (1): 21-30, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="10659113">Wilkinson S, Aldridge J, Salmon I, et al.: An evaluation of aromatherapy massage in palliative care. Palliat Med 13 (5): 409-17, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="21">Corner J, Cawler N, Hildebrand S: An evaluation of the use of massage and essential oils on the wellbeing of cancer patients. Int J Palliat Nurs  1 (2): 67-73, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="12442972">Louis M, Kowalski SD: Use of aromatherapy with hospice patients to decrease pain, anxiety, and depression and to promote an increased sense of well-being. Am J Hosp Palliat Care 19 (6): 381-6, 2002 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="10427231">Walsh E, Wilson C: Complementary therapies in long-stay neurology in-patient settings. Nurs Stand 13 (32): 32-5, 1999 Apr 28-May 4.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="10997854">Itai T, Amayasu H, Kuribayashi M, et al.: Psychological effects of aromatherapy on chronic hemodialysis patients. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci 54 (4): 393-7, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="8152975">Burns E, Blamey C: Complementary medicine. Using aromatherapy in childbirth. Nurs Times 90 (9): 54-60, 1994 Mar 2-8.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="10784271">Burns EE, Blamey C, Ersser SJ, et al.: An investigation into the use of aromatherapy in intrapartum midwifery practice. J Altern Complement Med 6 (2): 141-7, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="9743836">Kite SM, Maher EJ, Anderson K, et al.: Development of an aromatherapy service at a Cancer Centre. Palliat Med 12 (3): 171-80, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="8646568">Komori T, Fujiwara R, Tanida M, et al.: Effects of citrus fragrance on immune function and depressive states. Neuroimmunomodulation 2 (3): 174-80, 1995 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="11183431">Wiebe E: A randomized trial of aromatherapy to reduce anxiety before abortion. Eff Clin Pract 3 (4): 166-9, 2000 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="16599645">Perry N, Perry E: Aromatherapy in the management of psychiatric disorders: clinical and neuropharmacological perspectives. CNS Drugs 20 (4): 257-80, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="12143909">Ballard CG, O'Brien JT, Reichelt K, et al.: Aromatherapy as a safe and effective treatment for the management of agitation in severe dementia: the results of a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial with Melissa. J Clin Psychiatry 63 (7): 553-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="11607948">Smallwood J, Brown R, Coulter F, et al.: Aromatherapy and behaviour disturbances in dementia: a randomized controlled trial. Int J Geriatr Psychiatry 16 (10): 1010-3, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="11994882">Holmes C, Hopkins V, Hensford C, et al.: Lavender oil as a treatment for agitated behaviour in severe dementia: a placebo controlled study. Int J Geriatr Psychiatry 17 (4): 305-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="12083347">Gray SG, Clair AA: Influence of aromatherapy on medication administration to residential-care residents with dementia and behavioral challenges. Am J Alzheimers Dis Other Demen 17 (3): 169-74, 2002 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="15253846">Snow LA, Hovanec L, Brandt J: A controlled trial of aromatherapy for agitation in nursing home patients with dementia. J Altern Complement Med 10 (3): 431-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="8033760">Rose JE, Behm FM: Inhalation of vapor from black pepper extract reduces smoking withdrawal symptoms. Drug Alcohol Depend 34 (3): 225-9, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="10340155">Sayette MA, Parrott DJ: Effects of olfactory stimuli on urge reduction in smokers. Exp Clin Psychopharmacol 7 (2): 151-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="38">Post-White N, Nichols W: Randomized trial testing of QueaseEase™ essential oil for motion sickness. International Journal of Essential Oil Therapeutics  1 (4): 158-66, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="9378876">Tate S: Peppermint oil: a treatment for postoperative nausea. J Adv Nurs 26 (3): 543-9, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="22513952">Hines S, Steels E, Chang A, et al.: Aromatherapy for treatment of postoperative nausea and vomiting. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 4: CD007598, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="10984871">Oyama H, Kaneda M, Katsumata N, et al.: Using the bedside wellness system during chemotherapy decreases fatigue and emesis in cancer patients. J Med Syst 24 (3): 173-82, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="8138636">Dale A, Cornwell S: The role of lavender oil in relieving perineal discomfort following childbirth: a blind randomized clinical trial. J Adv Nurs 19 (1): 89-96, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="7954745">Göbel H, Schmidt G, Soyka D: Effect of peppermint and eucalyptus oil preparations on neurophysiological and experimental algesimetric headache parameters. Cephalalgia 14 (3): 228-34; discussion 182, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="12044597">Marchand S, Arsenault P: Odors modulate pain perception: a gender-specific effect. Physiol Behav 76 (2): 251-6, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="17129308">Kim JT, Wajda M, Cuff G, et al.: Evaluation of aromatherapy in treating postoperative pain: pilot study. Pain Pract 6 (4): 273-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="16563861">Barclay J, Vestey J, Lambert A, et al.: Reducing the symptoms of lymphoedema: is there a role for aromatherapy? Eur J Oncol Nurs 10 (2): 140-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="15684846">Kohara H, Miyauchi T, Suehiro Y, et al.: Combined modality treatment of aromatherapy, footsoak, and reflexology relieves fatigue in patients with cancer. J Palliat Med 7 (6): 791-6, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="48">Buckle  J: Clinical Aromatherapy: Essential Oils in Practice. 2nd ed. Churchill Livingston, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="17290062">Wilkinson SM, Love SB, Westcombe AM, et al.: Effectiveness of aromatherapy massage in the management of anxiety and depression in patients with cancer: a multicenter randomized controlled trial. J Clin Oncol 25 (5): 532-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="9526345">Rimmer L: The clinical use of aromatherapy in the reduction of stress. Home Healthc Nurse 16 (2): 123-6, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="10844744">Stringer J: Massage and aromatherapy on a leukaemia unit. Complement Ther Nurs Midwifery 6 (2): 72-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="16785038">Warnke PH, Sherry E, Russo PA, et al.: Antibacterial essential oils in malodorous cancer patients: clinical observations in 30 patients. Phytomedicine 13 (7): 463-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="9807369">Hicks G: Aromatherapy as an adjunct to care in a mental health day hospital. J Psychiatr Ment Health Nurs 5 (4): 317, 1998.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><Para id="_11">Numerous studies on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045927" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">topical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibacterial </GlossaryTermRef>effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">essential oils</GlossaryTermRef> have been published; most have found the essential oils to have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">significant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462661" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antimicrobial</GlossaryTermRef> activity.<Reference refidx="1"/> Some essential oils are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antiviral</GlossaryTermRef> and inhibit replication of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000644314" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herpes simplex virus</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/> Other essential oils are fungistatic and fungicidal against both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044308" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaginal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharyngeal</GlossaryTermRef> <ScientificName>Candida albicans</ScientificName>.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para><Para id="_36">Studies on rats in Europe and Japan have shown that exposure to various <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462689" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">odors</GlossaryTermRef> can result in stimulation or sedation, as well as changes in behavioral responses to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef> and pain.  A study <Reference refidx="4"/> on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450118" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sedative</GlossaryTermRef> effects of essential oils and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462679" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fragrance</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef> (mostly individual <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef> components of the essential oils) on rat motility  showed that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lavender </GlossaryTermRef> oil <ScientificName>(Lavandula angustifolia </ScientificName>Miller [synonyms: <ScientificName>Lavandula spicata</ScientificName> L.; <ScientificName>Lavandula vera </ScientificName>DC.])  in particular had a significant sedative effect, and several single-oil constituents (as opposed to whole essential oils) had similarly strong effects.  The authors do not comment on the presumed mechanism for this effect.           The differences in bioavailability are ascribed to different levels of lipophilicity, with the more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lipophilic</GlossaryTermRef> oils producing the most sedative effects.  The researchers also found significant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> levels of the fragrance compounds after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhalation</GlossaryTermRef>, suggesting that the effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatherapy</GlossaryTermRef> result from a direct pharmacological interaction rather than an indirect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> relay.</Para><Para id="_37">Other studies have investigated the effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatherapy</GlossaryTermRef> on rats’ behavioral and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunological responses</GlossaryTermRef> to painful, stressful, or startling stimuli.  In two European studies, rats exposed to pleasant odors during painful stimuli exhibited decreased pain-related behaviors, with some variation in response between the sexes.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  Two studies from Japan showed an improvement in immunological and behavioral markers in rats exposed to fragrances while under stressful conditions.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12510839">Aridoğan BC, Baydar H, Kaya S, et al.: Antimicrobial activity and chemical composition of some essential oils. Arch Pharm Res 25 (6): 860-4, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="14584615">Minami M, Kita M, Nakaya T, et al.: The inhibitory effect of essential oils on herpes simplex virus type-1 replication in vitro. Microbiol Immunol 47 (9): 681-4, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="16178366">D'Auria FD, Tecca M, Strippoli V, et al.: Antifungal activity of Lavandula angustifolia essential oil against Candida albicans yeast and mycelial form. Med Mycol 43 (5): 391-6, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="8331544">Buchbauer G, Jirovetz L, Jäger W, et al.: Fragrance compounds and essential oils with sedative effects upon inhalation. J Pharm Sci 82 (6): 660-4, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="12385797">Aloisi AM, Ceccarelli I, Masi F, et al.: Effects of the essential oil from citrus lemon in male and female rats exposed to a persistent painful stimulation. Behav Brain Res 136 (1): 127-35, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="9251980">Jahangeer AC, Mellier D, Caston J: Influence of olfactory stimulation on nociceptive behavior in mice. Physiol Behav 62 (2): 359-66, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="1938152">Shibata H, Fujiwara R, Iwamoto M, et al.: Immunological and behavioral effects of fragrance in mice. Int J Neurosci 57 (1-2): 151-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9762013">Fujiwara R, Komori T, Noda Y, et al.: Effects of a long-term inhalation of fragrances on the stress-induced immunosuppression in mice. Neuroimmunomodulation 5 (6): 318-22, 1998 Nov-Dec.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><Title>Human/Clinical Studies</Title><Para id="_13">No studies in the published <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561727" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed</GlossaryTermRef> literature discuss <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatherapy</GlossaryTermRef> as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> specifically.     The studies discussed below, most of which were conducted in patients with cancer, primarily focus on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_199" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Other health-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Procedure-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Infection</GlossaryTermRef> control.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Quality-of-life</GlossaryTermRef> (QOL) measures such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> levels.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_200">These studies purport to test the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of aromatherapy, implying that the products used contain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">essential oils</GlossaryTermRef>; however, only an occasional reference article includes significant descriptive information about the product(s) used (e.g., composition, source) thereby greatly limiting the ability of interested <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000543931" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinicians</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561326" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">researchers</GlossaryTermRef> to compare or duplicate studies or produce meaningful <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meta-analyses</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research</GlossaryTermRef> results.</Para><SummarySection id="_151"><Title>Anxiety and Depression</Title><Para id="_152">A major review published in 2000 <Reference refidx="1"/> focused on six studies investigating treatment or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> of anxiety with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462663" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatherapy massage</GlossaryTermRef>.  Although the studies suggested that aromatherapy massage had a mild transient <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiolytic</GlossaryTermRef> effect, the authors concluded that the research done at that time was not sufficiently rigorous or consistent to prove the effectiveness of aromatherapy in treating anxiety.  This review excluded <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trials</GlossaryTermRef> related to other effects of aromatherapy (such as pain control) and did not include any studies looking at the effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462689" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">odors</GlossaryTermRef> that were not specifically labeled as aromatherapy.</Para><Para id="_153">Another <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled trial</GlossaryTermRef> investigated the effects of massage or aromatherapy massage in 103 cancer patients who were randomly assigned to receive massage using a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carrier oil</GlossaryTermRef> (massage group) or massage using a carrier oil plus the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Roman chamomile</GlossaryTermRef> essential oil (<ScientificName>Chamaemelum nobile</ScientificName> [L.] All. [synonym: <ScientificName>Anthemis nobilis </ScientificName>L.])
(aromatherapy massage group).<Reference refidx="2"/>  Two weeks after the massage,  a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef> reduction was found in anxiety in the aromatherapy massage group (as measured by the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory) and improvement in symptoms (as measured by the Rotterdam Symptom Checklist [RSCL]). The subscales with improved scores were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef>, QOL, severe physical, and severe psychological.  The  massage-only group showed improvement on four RSCL subscales; however, these improvements did not reach statistical significance.</Para><Para id="_154">A study that evaluated an aromatherapy service following changes made after an initial pilot at a U.K. cancer center, also reported on the experiences of patients referred to the service.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Of the 89 patients originally  referred, 58 patients completed six aromatherapy sessions.  Significant improvements in anxiety and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>  (as measured by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale [HADS]) were reported at study completion in comparison with measurements taken before the six sessions.</Para><Para id="_177">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045673" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">double-blind</GlossaryTermRef>, randomized trial conducted in Australia investigated the effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhalation</GlossaryTermRef> aromatherapy on anxiety during radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="4"/>  A total of 313 patients who received radiation therapy were randomly assigned to one of three groups (carrier oil with essential oils, carrier oil only, or pure essential oils of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lavender</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462666" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bergamot</GlossaryTermRef> (<ScientificName>Citrus aurantium</ScientificName>  L. ssp. <ScientificName>bergamia</ScientificName> [Risso] Wright &amp; Arn. [Rutaceae]; 
[synonym: <ScientificName>Citrus bergamia</ScientificName> Risso]), and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462670" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cedarwood</GlossaryTermRef> (<ScientificName>Cedrus atlantica </ScientificName>[Endl.] Manetti ex Carriere 
[Pinaceae])).  All three groups received the oils by inhalation during radiation therapy.  There were no significant differences reported in depression (as measured by HADS) or psychological effects (as measured by the Somatic and Psychological Health Report) between the groups.  The group that received  carrier oil only showed a statistically significant decrease in anxiety (as measured by HADS) compared with the other two groups.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_155"><Title>Health-Related Quality of Life</Title><Para id="_156">A randomized, controlled, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045838" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pilot study</GlossaryTermRef> examined the effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044144" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjunctive</GlossaryTermRef> aromatherapy massage on mood, QOL, and physical symptoms in patients with cancer.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Forty-six patients were randomly assigned to either conventional day care alone or day care plus weekly aromatherapy massage using a standardized blend of essential oils (1% lavender and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chamomile</GlossaryTermRef> in
sweet almond carrier oil) for 4 weeks.  Patients self-rated their mood, QOL, and the intensity of the two symptoms that were the most concerning to them at the beginning of the study and at weekly intervals thereafter.  Of the 46 patients, only 11 of 23 patients (48%) in the aromatherapy group and 18 of 23 patients (78%) in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control group</GlossaryTermRef> completed all 4 weeks.  Patient-reported mood, symptoms, and QOL improved in both groups, and there were no statistically significant differences between the two groups in any of these measures.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_182"><Title>Sleep</Title><Para id="_183">A placebo-controlled, double-blind, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797424" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">crossover</GlossaryTermRef>, randomized trial compared an essential oil (choice of lavender, peppermint, or chamomile) with a pleasant-smelling placebo (rose water) administered by diffuser overnight for 3 weeks in 50 adult patients with newly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> who were hospitalized for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> of intensive chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="6"/>
 Most patients reported poor quality sleep on the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">baseline</GlossaryTermRef>, with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean</GlossaryTermRef> score of 12.7. During the aromatherapy week, the mean PSQI score decreased to 9.7, but returned to a near-baseline score of 12.4 during the washout week. The difference in mean PSQI score and mean placebo score was statistically significant (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0001). Aromatherapy also reduced the weekly average Edmonton Symptom Assessment Scale–Revised (ESASr) score by 6.06 points, which was statistically significant (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0006). All subscales demonstrated a reduction in ESASr score with six symptom score changes showing a statistically significant benefit from aromatherapy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_201" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Tiredness (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).</ListItem><ListItem>Drowsiness (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03).</ListItem><ListItem>Lack of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef> (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).</ListItem><ListItem>Depression (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> =
.003).</ListItem><ListItem>Anxiety (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03).</ListItem><ListItem>Well-being (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .05).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_184">Another randomized controlled trial examined the effects of aromatherapy massage and massage alone in 42 patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef> over a 4-week period.<Reference refidx="7"/>  Patients were randomly assigned to one of the following groups:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_202" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Aromatherapy group: received massages with lavender essential oil (<ScientificName>Lavandula angustifolia</ScientificName> Miller [synonyms: <ScientificName>Lavandula spicata</ScientificName> L.; <ScientificName>Lavandula vera</ScientificName> DC.])  and an inert carrier oil.</ListItem><ListItem>Massage-only group: received massages with an inert oil only.</ListItem><ListItem>Control group: no massage.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_203">No significant long-term benefits of aromatherapy or massage in pain control, QOL, or anxiety were reported, but sleep scores (as measured by the Verran and Snyder-Halpern sleep scale) improved significantly in both groups.  A statistically significant reduction in depression scores was also reported (as measured by the HADS) in the massage-only group.
</Para><Para id="_185">A randomized controlled trial of lavender, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tea tree</GlossaryTermRef> oil, or no-treatment control in adult patients who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044520" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outpatient</GlossaryTermRef> chemotherapy with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045258" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paclitaxel</GlossaryTermRef> reported that trait anxiety and sleep quality improved with lavender, and that tea tree oil led to the highest change in sleep quality. However, changes in anxiety were observed only on the trait anxiety scores, not on the state anxiety scores, which may reflect short term changes associated with an aromatherapy intervention. In addition, there were no significant differences in sleep scores between the two aromatherapy groups and the controls, which the study was designed to detect.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_186"><Title>Xerostomia</Title><Para id="_187"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045855" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radioactive iodine</GlossaryTermRef> damage to normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">salivary glands</GlossaryTermRef> may be minimized by increased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257526" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">saliva</GlossaryTermRef> production during the period of treatment. Inhalation aromatherapy was evaluated for its ability to increase saliva production during this administration period. An aromatherapy intervention consisting of a 2:1 mixture of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537557" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lemon</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ginger</GlossaryTermRef> essential oils versus a distilled water (no smell) control inhaled for 10 min/d during a 2-week hospitalization for administration of radioactive iodine therapy for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">differentiated</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid cancer</GlossaryTermRef> was investigated in a randomized controlled trial of 71 patients. Salivary gland function was assessed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000580343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scintigraphy</GlossaryTermRef>. Compared with placebo, those in the aromatherapy group showed a significantly higher rate of change of the maximum accumulation ratio in the parotid and submandibular glands (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05) and a significantly increased rate of change of the washout ratio before and after therapy in the bilateral parotid glands (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05). Although an increasing trend was observed for the submandibular glands in subjects receiving aromatherapy, no significant differences were noted between the groups.<Reference refidx="9"/> These results suggest that by increasing saliva production during radioactive iodine treatment with inhalation aromatherapy with a lemon and ginger combination, increased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044548" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iodine</GlossaryTermRef> clearance in salivary glands may lead to reductions in long-term damage to saliva production.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_188"><Title>Nausea and Vomiting</Title><Para id="_189">A randomized, controlled, crossover  trial investigated the effects of inhaled ginger essential oil on alleviating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>-induced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef> in Asian women with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="10"/>
 Aromatherapy administered as inhaled ginger essential oil for 5 days was associated with small statistically significant, but not clinically significant, reductions in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute</GlossaryTermRef> nausea and  had limited effects on reducing vomiting or delaying nausea in 60 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044029" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">evaluable patients</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_191">Another study evaluated the efficacy of an aromatherapy intervention for reduction of symptom intensity of nausea, retching, and/or coughing among adult patients who received stem cells preserved in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dimethyl sulfoxide</GlossaryTermRef>. The study found that an intervention of tasting or sniffing sliced oranges was more effective at reducing symptom intensity compared with orange essential oil inhalation aromatherapy.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_159"><Title>Procedure-Related Symptoms</Title><Para id="_161">In a randomized placebo-controlled study of two different types of external aromatherapy tabs (lavender-sandalwood and orange-peppermint) compared with a matched placebo-controlled delivery system in 87 women undergoing breast <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsies</GlossaryTermRef>, there was a statistically significant reduction in self-reported anxiety with the use of the lavender-sandalwood aromatherapy tab compared with the placebo group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .032).<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_162">In a three-arm randomized trial of 123 patients that compared lavender, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">eucalyptus</GlossaryTermRef>, and no essential oil administered via inhalation, procedural pain after needle insertion into an implantable central venous <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">port</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> was significantly decreased in the lavender oil inhalation aromatherapy group compared with the control group. Inhalation of eucalyptus oil did not reduce procedural pain levels during needle insertion.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_205">A four-arm randomized trial compared aromatherapy, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000640061" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">music therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, a combination of the two, and a placebo in breast cancer patients before and after a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045777" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mastectomy</GlossaryTermRef>. The aromatherapy arm utilized a mixture of lavender, bergamot, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462680" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">geranium</GlossaryTermRef> essential oils, while the music arm offered a choice of music styles. Measured <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef> included pain intensity and anxiety. The combination of treatments was superior to either single treatment with all endpoints.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para></SummarySection><Table id="_168"><Title>Table 1.  Use of Aromatherapy as a Supportive Care Agent in Cancer and Palliative Care for Anxiety and Depression: Table of Clinical Studies</Title><TGroup Cols="8"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="9.36%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="15.16%"/><ColSpec ColName="col03" ColNum="3" ColWidth="21.62%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="11.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="6.59%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="6" ColWidth="13.11%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="7" ColWidth="10.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="8" ColWidth="12.52%"/><THead><Row><entry>Reference </entry><entry>Trial Design</entry><entry>Essential Oil/Route of Administration</entry><entry>Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Placebo</GlossaryTermRef> or No Treatment Control)</entry><entry>Condition or Cancer Type</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Concurrent Therapy</GlossaryTermRef> Used</entry><entry>Results</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Level of Evidence</GlossaryTermRef> Score<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1">QOL = quality of life.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Patients with malignant brain tumors.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>Double-blind, randomized, controlled trial</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lavender</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462666" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bergamot </GlossaryTermRef>(<ScientificName>Citrus aurantium</ScientificName>  L. ssp. <ScientificName>bergamia </ScientificName>[Risso] Wright &amp; Arn. [Rutaceae]; 
[synonym: <ScientificName>Citrus bergamia </ScientificName>Risso]), and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462670" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cedarwood</GlossaryTermRef>  (<ScientificName>Cedrus atlantica </ScientificName>[Endl.] Manetti ex Carriere 
[Pinaceae])/inhalation</entry><entry>313; 100 (pure essential oils), 100 (carrier oil with fractionated low-grade essential oils), 100 (carrier oil only, no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462679" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fragrance</GlossaryTermRef>)</entry><entry>Anxiety</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef>: no effect on  anxiety; secondary outcome: no effect on depression or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="2"/></entry><entry>Randomized nonblinded trial</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chamomile</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454761" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">massage</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>103; 43; 44</entry><entry>Physical and psychological symptoms, QOL</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcomes: reduction in anxiety and in physical and psychological symptoms; improved QOL</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef> </entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="15"/></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Consecutive case series</GlossaryTermRef><Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>Lavender or chamomile/massage</entry><entry>12; 8; none</entry><entry>Anxiety, depression</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: no reduction in anxiety or depression; secondary outcome: reduction in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pulse</GlossaryTermRef>, and respiration </entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335146" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iiC</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_169"><Title>Table 2.  Use of Aromatherapy as a Supportive Care Agent in Cancer and Palliative Care for Health-Related Quality of Life Symptoms: Table of Clinical Studies</Title><TGroup Cols="8"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="9.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="14.67%"/><ColSpec ColName="col03" ColNum="3" ColWidth="17.89%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="11.95%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="10.17%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="6" ColWidth="10.85%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="7" ColWidth="8.48%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="8" ColWidth="16.28%"/><THead><Row><entry>Reference </entry><entry>Trial Design</entry><entry>Essential Oil/Route of Administration</entry><entry>Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)</entry><entry>Condition or Cancer Type</entry><entry>Concurrent Therapy Used</entry><entry>Results</entry><entry>Level of Evidence Score<Superscript>d</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1">EORTC QLQ-C30 = European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire; HRQOL = health-related quality of life; QOL = quality of life.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Lavender (43%), rosewood (29%), rose (7%), and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367414" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">valerian</GlossaryTermRef> (4%).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Patients with breast cancer undergoing chemotherapy.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Patients with breast cancer undergoing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045263" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow transplantation</GlossaryTermRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>d</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="6"/></entry><entry>Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</entry><entry>Lavender, peppermint, or chamomile/inhalation</entry><entry>53; 25; 28</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Insomnia</GlossaryTermRef>, shortness of breath, tiredness, drowsiness, pain, nausea, appetite, depression, anxiety, well-being</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: improvements in tiredness, drowsiness,
lack of appetite, depression, anxiety, and well-being</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry>Randomized controlled trial</entry><entry>Lemon and ginger/inhalation</entry><entry>71; 35; 36</entry><entry>Salivary gland damage</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: compared with control group, the rate of change of the
accumulation rate (marker of saliva production)  was significantly higher in the parotid glands and submandibular glands of the aromatherapy group</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="5"/></entry><entry>Randomized nonblinded trial</entry><entry>Lavender (<ScientificName>Lavandula angustifolia</ScientificName> Miller [synonyms: <ScientificName>Lavandula  spicata</ScientificName> L.; <ScientificName>Lavandula  vera</ScientificName> DC.]) and  chamomile blend/massage</entry><entry>46; 11; 18</entry><entry>Mood, QOL, physical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: no effect on mood, QOL, or physical symptoms</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="7"/></entry><entry>Randomized nonblinded trial</entry><entry>Lavender/massage</entry><entry>42; 29; 13</entry><entry>Pain</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: no effect on pain; secondary outcome: improved sleep in both groups;  reduced depression (in massage group); no effect on QOL</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="8"/></entry><entry>Randomized controlled trial</entry><entry>Lavender, tea tree, or no oil/inhalation</entry><entry>70; 30 (lavender),  20 (tea tree); 20</entry><entry>Anxiety and sleep quality</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcomes: no improvement in state anxiety scores; no differences in changes in sleep quality between groups; secondary outcome: lower trait anxiety scores and higher sleep-quality scores observed with lavender oil </entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="16"/></entry><entry>Randomized nonblinded trial</entry><entry>Chamomile/massage</entry><entry>52; 26; 25</entry><entry>QOL, physical symptoms, anxiety</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: improved QOL, fewer physical symptoms, reduced anxiety</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="17"/></entry><entry>Randomized nonblinded trial</entry><entry>Aromatherapy blend<Superscript>a</Superscript>/massage</entry><entry>52; 34; 18</entry><entry>Anxiety, mobility</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcomes: decreased anxiety, pain; improved mobility</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="10"/></entry><entry>Randomized, controlled, single-blind, crossover trial<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ginger</GlossaryTermRef> essential oil/inhalation</entry><entry>75; 30; 30</entry><entry>Nausea, vomiting, HRQOL (EORTC QLQ-C30)</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>Primary outcomes: small reduction in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute</GlossaryTermRef> nausea; no reduction in delayed nausea or  vomiting episodes; secondary outcome: improved HRQOL</entry><entry>1C</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="11"/></entry><entry>Randomized, controlled<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient"/>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044727" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">single-blind</GlossaryTermRef> trial</entry><entry>Sweet orange/inhalation</entry><entry>60; 23 (orange sniffing),  19 (orange tasting); 18 </entry><entry>Symptom intensity (nausea, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476298" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retching</GlossaryTermRef>, cough)</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>Primary outcome: greatest reduction in symptom intensity with orange tasting/sniffing</entry><entry>1C</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="18"/></entry><entry>Randomized controlled pilot trial</entry><entry>Peppermint (<ScientificName>Mentha piperita</ScientificName>; 2%), bergamot (<ScientificName>Citrus bergamia</ScientificName>; 1%), and cardamom (<ScientificName>Elettaria cardamomum</ScientificName>; 1%) in 100 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mL</GlossaryTermRef> of sweet almond carrier oil/inhalation or massage or no-treatment control </entry><entry>75;  25 (massage),  25 (inhalation); 25</entry><entry>Nausea and vomiting</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>Primary outcomes: nausea/retching improved with massage; nausea severity better with inhalation</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="19"/></entry><entry>Randomized single-blind trial</entry><entry>Choice of 20 essential oils/massage</entry><entry>39; 20; 19</entry><entry>Feasibility; mood</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: improvements in mood in both groups (aromatherapy massage and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cognitive behavioral therapy</GlossaryTermRef>); secondary outcome: preference for aromatherapy over cognitive behavioral therapy</entry><entry>1C</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="20"/></entry><entry>Randomized single-blind trial</entry><entry>Choice of bitter orange, black pepper, rosemary, marjoram, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462746" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">patchouli</GlossaryTermRef>/massage</entry><entry>45; 15 (aromatherapy massage), 15 (plain massage); 15 </entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Constipation</GlossaryTermRef>; QOL</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>Primary outcome: improvement with aromatherapy massage; secondary outcome: improved QOL</entry><entry>1C</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="21"/></entry><entry>Nonrandomized controlled <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef><Superscript>c</Superscript></entry><entry>Geranium (<ScientificName>Pelargonium</ScientificName> species), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">German chamomile </GlossaryTermRef>(<ScientificName>Matricaria recutita</ScientificName> L. [synonyms: <ScientificName>Matricaria chamomilla</ScientificName> L., <ScientificName>Chamomilla 
recutita</ScientificName> (L.) Rausch.]),   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462746" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">patchouli</GlossaryTermRef> (<ScientificName>Pogostemon cablin</ScientificName> [Blanco] Benth. [Lamiaceae] [synonyms: <ScientificName>Mentha cablin</ScientificName> 
Blanco, <ScientificName>Pogostemon patchouly</ScientificName> Letettier]), and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463059" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phytol</GlossaryTermRef>/oral application</entry><entry>48; 24; 24</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> symptoms</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: no effect on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> symptoms</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="22"/></entry><entry>Consecutive case</entry><entry>Various oils/massage</entry><entry>69</entry><entry>General symptoms</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: general improvement in symptoms reported by patients; no statistical analysis completed           </entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335146" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iiC</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_170"><Title>Table 3.  Use of Aromatherapy as a Supportive Care Agent in Cancer and Palliative Care for Procedure-Related Symptoms: Table of Clinical Studies</Title><TGroup Cols="8"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="12.81%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="15.21%"/><ColSpec ColName="col03" ColNum="3" ColWidth="8.89%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="10.85%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="14.50%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="6" ColWidth="14.05%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="7" ColWidth="9.96%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="8" ColWidth="13.70%"/><THead><Row><entry>Reference </entry><entry>Trial Design</entry><entry>Essential Oil/Route of Administration</entry><entry>Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)</entry><entry>Condition or Cancer Type</entry><entry>Concurrent Therapy Used</entry><entry>Results</entry><entry>Level of Evidence Score<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="12"/></entry><entry>Randomized controlled trial</entry><entry>Lavender-sandalwood, orange-peppermint, or placebo/inhalation</entry><entry>87; 30 (lavender),  30 (orange); 27</entry><entry>Anxiety</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcome: reduction in anxiety with the use of lavender-sandalwood aromatherapy tab</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>Quasi-randomized controlled pilot study</entry><entry>Lavender (<ScientificName>Lavandula officinalis</ScientificName>) and eucalyptus (<ScientificName>Eucalyptus globulus</ScientificName>)/inhalation</entry><entry>123; 41(lavender),  41 (eucalyptus); 41</entry><entry>Pain, anxiety</entry><entry>No</entry><entry>Primary outcome: decreased  procedural pain in the lavender oil group</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry><entry>Randomized controlled trial </entry><entry>Lavender, bergamot, geranium/inhalation</entry><entry>160; 40 (essential oil), 40 (music), 40 (combination),  40 (usual care)</entry><entry>Breast cancer; mastectomy pain and anxiety</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>Combination of music and aromatherapy superior to individual treatments</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_208"><Title>Pediatric Population and Aromatherapy</Title><Para id="_209">Aromatherapy is used or claimed to be useful for a variety of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>.  A book about aromatherapy in children suggests aromatherapy remedies for everything from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044183" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acne</GlossaryTermRef> to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463089" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">whooping cough</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="23"/> When used safely, aromatherapy can help children feel calmer and sleep better.</Para><Para id="_210">A placebo-controlled, double-blind, randomized trial compared bergamot inhalation aromatherapy with a pleasant-smelling shampoo that did not contain essential oils in 37 children and adolescents who were undergoing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusions</GlossaryTermRef>. The study found that aromatherapy was not beneficial in reducing nausea, anxiety, or pain.<Reference refidx="24"/> As administered in this study, bergamot inhalation aromatherapy may have contributed to persistent anxiety after the infusion of stem cells. Although no more effective than placebo, parents who received aromatherapy showed a significant decrease in their transitory anxiety during the period between the completion of their child’s infusion and 1 hour after infusion. Nausea and pain subsided over the course of the intervention for all children, although nausea remained significantly greater in patients who received aromatherapy. These findings suggest that the diffusion of bergamot essential oil may not provide suitable anxiolytic and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antiemetic</GlossaryTermRef> effects among children and adolescents undergoing stem cell transplantation. These results may be explained by the  double-blind methodology of the trial, because <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044727" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">single-blinded</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044066" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nonblinded</GlossaryTermRef> trials generally supported the aromatherapy intervention.</Para><Table id="_212"><Title>Table 4.  Use of Aromatherapy as a Supportive Care Agent in Children with Cancer</Title><TGroup Cols="8"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="12.39%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="12.39%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="12.50%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="12.50%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="12.60%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="11.49%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="7" ColWidth="10.08%"/><ColSpec ColName="col8" ColNum="8" ColWidth="16.02%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design</entry><entry Align="Center">Essential Oil/Route of Administration</entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)</entry><entry Align="Center">Condition or Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Concurrent Therapy Used</entry><entry Align="Center">Results</entry><entry Align="Center">Level of Evidence Score<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col8" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="24"/></entry><entry>Randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind trial</entry><entry>Bergamot/inhalation</entry><entry>37; 17; 20</entry><entry>Anxiety, nausea, pain in children undergoing stem cell transplant</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>Primary outcomes: increased anxiety and nausea in children 1 hour after stem cell infusion in aromatherapy group; no effect on pain; secondary outcome: parental anxiety declined in both groups</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_12_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_12_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10962794">Cooke B, Ernst E: Aromatherapy: a systematic review. Br J Gen Pract 50 (455): 493-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10659113">Wilkinson S, Aldridge J, Salmon I, et al.: An evaluation of aromatherapy massage in palliative care. Palliat Med 13 (5): 409-17, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9743836">Kite SM, Maher EJ, Anderson K, et al.: Development of an aromatherapy service at a Cancer Centre. Palliat Med 12 (3): 171-80, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12805340">Graham PH, Browne L, Cox H, et al.: Inhalation aromatherapy during radiotherapy: results of a placebo-controlled double-blind randomized trial. J Clin Oncol 21 (12): 2372-6, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15198118">Wilcock A, Manderson C, Weller R, et al.: Does aromatherapy massage benefit patients with cancer attending a specialist palliative care day centre? Palliat Med 18 (4): 287-90, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="28640576">Blackburn L, Achor S, Allen B, et al.: The Effect of Aromatherapy on Insomnia and Other Common Symptoms Among Patients With Acute Leukemia. Oncol Nurs Forum 44 (4): E185-E193, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="15046404">Soden K, Vincent K, Craske S, et al.: A randomized controlled trial of aromatherapy massage in a hospice setting. Palliat Med 18 (2): 87-92, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="29547610">Ozkaraman A, Dügüm Ö, Özen Yılmaz H, et al.: Aromatherapy: The Effect of Lavender on Anxiety and Sleep Quality in Patients Treated With Chemotherapy Clin J Oncol Nurs 22 (2): 203-210, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="28042578">Nakayama M, Okizaki A, Takahashi K: A Randomized Controlled Trial for the Effectiveness of Aromatherapy in Decreasing Salivary Gland Damage following Radioactive Iodine Therapy for Differentiated Thyroid Cancer. Biomed Res Int 2016: 9509810, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="26051575">Lua PL, Salihah N, Mazlan N: Effects of inhaled ginger aromatherapy on chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting and health-related quality of life in women with breast cancer. Complement Ther Med 23 (3): 396-404, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="21372706">Potter P, Eisenberg S, Cain KC, et al.: Orange interventions for symptoms associated with dimethyl sulfoxide during stem cell reinfusions: a feasibility study. Cancer Nurs 34 (5): 361-8, 2011 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="28395396">Trambert R, Kowalski MO, Wu B, et al.: A Randomized Controlled Trial Provides Evidence to Support Aromatherapy to Minimize Anxiety in Women Undergoing Breast Biopsy. Worldviews Evid Based Nurs 14 (5): 394-402, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29199999">Yayla EM, Ozdemir L: Effect of Inhalation Aromatherapy on Procedural Pain and Anxiety After Needle Insertion Into an Implantable Central Venous Port Catheter: A Quasi-Randomized Controlled Pilot Study. Cancer Nurs 42 (1): 35-41, 2019 Jan/Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="34134947">Deng C, Xie Y, Liu Y, et al.: Aromatherapy Plus Music Therapy Improve Pain Intensity and Anxiety Scores in Patients With Breast Cancer During Perioperative Periods: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Clin Breast Cancer 22 (2): 115-120, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="12066022">Hadfield N: The role of aromatherapy massage in reducing anxiety in patients with malignant brain tumours. Int J Palliat Nurs 7 (6): 279-85, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="16">Wilkinson S: Aromatherapy and massage in palliative care. Int J Palliat Nurs  1 (1): 21-30, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="17">Corner J, Cawler N, Hildebrand S: An evaluation of the use of massage and essential oils on the wellbeing of cancer patients. Int J Palliat Nurs  1 (2): 67-73, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="28426542">Zorba P, Ozdemir L: The Preliminary Effects of Massage and Inhalation Aromatherapy on Chemotherapy-Induced Acute Nausea and Vomiting: A Quasi-Randomized Controlled Pilot Trial. Cancer Nurs 41 (5): 359-366, 2018 Sep/Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="21370309">Serfaty M, Wilkinson S, Freeman C, et al.: The ToT study: helping with Touch or Talk (ToT): a pilot randomised controlled trial to examine the clinical effectiveness of aromatherapy massage versus cognitive behaviour therapy for emotional distress in patients in cancer/palliative care. Psychooncology 21 (5): 563-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="21168113">Lai TK, Cheung MC, Lo CK, et al.: Effectiveness of aroma massage on advanced cancer patients with constipation: a pilot study. Complement Ther Clin Pract 17 (1): 37-43, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="21">Gravett P: Treatment of gastrointestinal upset following high-dose chemotherapy. International Journal of Aromatherapy  11 (2): 84-6, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="22">Evans B: An audit into the effects of aromatherapy massage and the cancer patient in palliative and terminal care. Complement Ther Med  3 (4): 239-41, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="23">Worwood VA: Aromatherapy for the Healthy Child: More Than 300 Natural, Non-Toxic, and Fragrant Essential Oil Blends. New World Library, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="22383266">Ndao DH, Ladas EJ, Cheng B, et al.: Inhalation aromatherapy in children and adolescents undergoing stem cell infusion: results of a placebo-controlled double-blind trial. Psychooncology 21 (3): 247-54, 2012.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><Title>Adverse Effects</Title><Para id="_15">Safety testing on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">essential oils</GlossaryTermRef> has shown minimal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef>.  Several essential oils have been approved for use as food additives and are classified as GRAS (generally recognized as safe)  by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef>;  however, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ingestion</GlossaryTermRef> of large amounts of essential oils is not recommended.  In addition, a few cases of contact <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045667" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dermatitis</GlossaryTermRef> have been reported, mostly in aromatherapists who have had prolonged skin contact with essential oils in the context of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462663" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatherapy massage</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/> Some essential oils (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">camphor</GlossaryTermRef> oil) can cause local irritation; therefore, care should be taken when applying them.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462755" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Phototoxicity</GlossaryTermRef> has occurred when essential oils (particularly citrus oils) are applied directly to the skin before sun exposure.  One <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case report</GlossaryTermRef> also showed airborne contact dermatitis in the context of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhaled</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatherapy</GlossaryTermRef> without massage.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Often, aromatherapy uses undefined mixtures of essential oils without specifying the plant sources. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Allergic reactions</GlossaryTermRef> are sometimes reported, especially after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045927" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">topical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef>.  Individual <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef> associations with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462689" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">odors</GlossaryTermRef> may result in adverse <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">responses</GlossaryTermRef>.                         Repeated exposure to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lavender</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tea tree</GlossaryTermRef> oils by topical administration was shown in one study to be associated with reversible prepubertal gynecomastia.<Reference refidx="3"/> The effects appear to have been caused by the purported weak estrogenic and antiandrogenic activities of lavender and tea tree oils.  Therefore,  avoiding these two essential oils is recommended in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046076" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estrogen</GlossaryTermRef>-dependant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>. However, this is the first published report of this type of adverse effect when using      products containing tea tree or lavender oils. </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2401143">Bilsland D, Strong A: Allergic contact dermatitis from the essential oil of French marigold (Tagetes patula) in an aromatherapist. Contact Dermatitis 23 (1): 55-6, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="8565250">Schaller M, Korting HC: Allergic airborne contact dermatitis from essential oils used in aromatherapy. Clin Exp Dermatol 20 (2): 143-5, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="17267908">Henley DV, Lipson N, Korach KS, et al.: Prepubertal gynecomastia linked to lavender and tea tree oils. N Engl J Med 356 (5): 479-85, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Aromatherapy With Essential Oils</Title><Para id="_17">To assist readers in evaluating the results of human studies of integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies for people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever possible. To qualify for a level of evidence <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef>, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Be published in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed scientific journal</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem>Report on a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem>Describe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> findings in enough detail that a meaningful evaluation can be made. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_46">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score, with a score of  1 being the strongest evidence and a score of 4 being the weakest design (or sometime similar).  For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis for people with cancer, see  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (10/31/2024)</Title><Para id="_19">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_214">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000441069#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/aromatherapy-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of aromatherapy with essential oils in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Aromatherapy With Essential Oils. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/aromatherapy-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/aromatherapy-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389313]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2005-10-24</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-31</DateLastModified></Summary>
