<Summary id="CDR0000441548" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062885"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Merkel cell carcinoma is a rare type of skin cancer that usually starts in areas of skin exposed to the sun. Sun exposure and having a weak immune system can affect the risk of Merkel cell  carcinoma.  Merkel cell carcinoma usually appears as a single painless lump on sun-exposed skin. Find out more about risk factors, symptoms, tests to diagnose, prognosis, staging, and treatment for Merkel cell carcinoma.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/patient/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq">Merkel Cell Carcinoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/hp/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq">Merkel Cell Carcinoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038240">Merkel cell carcinoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_198">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of Merkel cell carcinoma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_199">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>neuroendocrine carcinoma of the skin</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Merkel Cell Carcinoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Merkel Cell Carcinoma Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Merkel Cell Carcinoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Merkel Cell Carcinoma</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Merkel cell carcinoma  is a very rare type of cancer that forms in the skin.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000674683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Merkel cells</GlossaryTermRef> are  found in the top layer of the skin. These cells are very close to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve</GlossaryTermRef> endings that receive the sensation of touch. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Merkel cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>, also called neuroendocrine carcinoma of the skin or trabecular cancer, is a very rare type  of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skin cancer</GlossaryTermRef> that  forms when Merkel cells grow out of control. Merkel cell carcinoma starts most often in areas of skin exposed to the sun, especially the head and neck, as well as the arms, legs, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000796908" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trunk</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000579043" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the skin with Merkel cells; drawing shows normal skin anatomy, including the epidermis, dermis, hair follicles, sweat glands, hair shafts, veins, arteries, fatty tissue, nerves, lymph vessels, oil glands, and subcutaneous tissue. The pullout shows a close-up of the epidermis with Merkel cells above the dermis with a vein and artery. Nerves are connected to Merkel cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_152"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the skin showing the epidermis, dermis, and subcutaneous tissue. Merkel cells are in the layer of basal cells at the deepest part of the epidermis and are connected to nerves.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_121">Merkel cell carcinoma tends to grow quickly and to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046283" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasize</GlossaryTermRef> (spread) at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. It   usually spreads first to nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> and then may spread to lymph nodes or skin in distant parts of the body,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>, brain, bones, or other    organs.</Para><Para id="_230">Merkel cell carcinoma is the second most common cause of skin cancer death after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_6">Sun exposure and having a weak immune system affects the risk of developing Merkel cell carcinoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_7">Anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease is called 
         a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>.  Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop Merkel cell carcinoma, and it can develop in people who don't have any known risk factors. Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_244">Risk factors for Merkel cell carcinoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_8" Style="bullet"> 
    <ListItem>being exposed to a lot of natural sunlight</ListItem> 
    <ListItem>being exposed to artificial sunlight, such as from tanning beds or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439424" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psoralen and ultraviolet A (PUVA) therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psoriasis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>  having an  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> weakened by disease, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044846" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic lymphocytic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HIV</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
    <ListItem>taking medicine that  makes the immune system less active,  such as after an organ <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem> having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">history</GlossaryTermRef> of other types of cancer</ListItem><ListItem>being older than 50 years, male, or White</ListItem> 
     
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_13">Merkel cell carcinoma usually appears as a single painless lump on sun-exposed skin.</KeyPoint><Para id="_14">This and other changes in the skin may be caused by Merkel cell carcinoma or by other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>. Check with your doctor if you see changes in your skin.</Para><Para id="_122">Merkel cell carcinoma usually appears  on sun-exposed skin as a single lump that  is:</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>fast-growing</ListItem> 
    <ListItem>painless</ListItem><ListItem>firm and dome-shaped or raised</ListItem> 
    <ListItem>red or violet in color</ListItem> 
     
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">Tests that examine the skin  are used to diagnose Merkel cell carcinoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_18">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem><Strong>Full-body skin exam</Strong> is an exam of the skin. A doctor or nurse checks the skin for bumps or spots that look abnormal in color, size, shape, or texture. The size, shape, and texture of the lymph nodes will also be checked.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Skin <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of skin cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer.</ListItem>
    
    
    
    
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_28">After Merkel cell carcinoma has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread  to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_29">The process used to find out if cancer has spread  to other parts of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. The information gathered from the staging process determines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease. It is important to know the stage in order to plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_197">The following tests and procedures may be used in the staging process:</Para><ItemizedList id="_30" Style="bullet"> 
     
     
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest, abdomen, head, and neck. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong> uses a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> sugar (also called radioactive glucose) that is injected into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes pictures of where sugar is being used by the body. Cancer cells show up brighter in the pictures because they are more active and take up more sugar than normal cells do.</ListItem> 
   <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of all or part of a lymph node. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the lymph node tissue under a microscope to check for cancer cells. This procedure is also called lymph node sampling. There are several types of lymph node biopsy used to stage Merkel cell carcinoma.<ItemizedList id="_192" Style="dash"><ListItem><Strong>Sentinel lymph node biopsy</Strong> removes the sentinel lymph node during surgery. The sentinel lymph node is the first lymph node in a group of lymph nodes to receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic drainage</GlossaryTermRef> from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. It is therefore the first lymph node the cancer is likely to spread to from the primary tumor.  To identify the sentinel lymph node, a radioactive substance, blue dye, or both is injected near the tumor.  The substance or dye flows through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046441" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ducts</GlossaryTermRef> to the lymph nodes.  The first lymph node to receive the substance or dye is removed.   A pathologist views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells.  If cancer cells are found, more lymph nodes will be removed through a separate incision (cut). This is called a lymph node dissection. Sometimes, a sentinel lymph node is found in more than one group of nodes.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000592566" type="image/jpeg" alt="Sentinel lymph node biopsy of the skin. The first of three panels shows a radioactive substance and/or blue dye injected near the tumor; the middle panel shows that the injected material is followed visually and/or with a probe that detects radioactivity to find the sentinel nodes (the first lymph nodes to take up the material); the third panel shows the removal of the tumor and the sentinel nodes to check for cancer cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_191"><Caption language="en">Sentinel lymph node biopsy of the skin. A radioactive substance and/or blue dye is injected near the tumor (first panel). The injected material is detected visually and/or with a probe that detects radioactivity (middle panel). The sentinel nodes (the first lymph nodes to take up the material) are removed and checked for cancer cells (last panel).</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Lymph node dissection</Strong> is a surgical procedure in which the lymph nodes are removed and a sample of tissue is checked under a microscope for signs of cancer. For a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044620" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef>, some of the lymph nodes in the tumor area are removed. For a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radical lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef>, most or all of the lymph nodes in the tumor area are removed. This procedure is also called lymphadenectomy.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Core needle biopsy</Strong> is a procedure to remove a sample of tissue using a wide needle.  A pathologist views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Fine-needle aspiration biopsy</Strong> is a procedure to remove a sample of tissue using a thin needle. A pathologist views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000653117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunohistochemistry</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>  uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient’s cells or tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and help tell one type of cancer from another type.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_645"><KeyPoint id="_646">Some people decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_647">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your Merkel cell carcinoma diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_648">Learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI’s Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_21">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_22">The prognosis and treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_23" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>the stage of the cancer (the size of the tumor and whether it has spread to the lymph nodes or other parts of the body)</ListItem><ListItem>where the cancer is in the body</ListItem>
    <ListItem>whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back)</ListItem>
    <ListItem>the person's age and general health</ListItem>
   </ItemizedList><Para id="_135">Prognosis also depends on  how deeply  the tumor has grown into the skin.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Stages of Merkel Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_643">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of Merkel cell cancer to plan the best treatment.</Para><Para id="_644">There are several staging systems for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. Merkel cell carcinoma staging usually uses the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. The cancer may be described by this staging system in your pathology report. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to your cancer. When talking to you about your diagnosis, your doctor may describe the cancer as one of these stages.</Para><Para id="_642">Learn about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000441548#_27" url="/types/skin/patient/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq">tests to stage Merkel cell carcinoma</SummaryRef>. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_31"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_32">The following stages are used for Merkel cell carcinoma:</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_137"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink><SummarySection id="_161"><KeyPoint id="_162">Stage 0 (carcinoma in situ)</KeyPoint><Para id="_207">In stage 0, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000674683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Merkel cells</GlossaryTermRef> are found in the top layer of skin. These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_208"><KeyPoint id="_209">Stage I (also called Stage 1) Merkel cell carcinoma</KeyPoint><Para id="_210">In stage I, the tumor is 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_211"><KeyPoint id="_212">Stage II (also called Stage 2) Merkel cell carcinoma</KeyPoint><Para id="_213">Stage II Merkel cell carcinoma is divided into stages IIA and IIB.</Para><ItemizedList id="_214" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem>In stage IIA, the tumor is larger than 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIB, the tumor has spread to nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, muscle, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044190" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cartilage</GlossaryTermRef>, or bone.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_215"><KeyPoint id="_216">Stage III (also called Stage 3) Merkel cell carcinoma</KeyPoint><Para id="_217">Stage III Merkel cell carcinoma is divided into stages IIIA and IIIB.</Para><Para id="_219">In stage IIIA, either of the following is found:</Para><ItemizedList id="_218" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the tumor may be any size and may have spread to nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, muscle, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044190" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cartilage</GlossaryTermRef>, or bone. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> cannot be felt during a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> but cancer is found in the lymph node by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> or after the lymph node is removed and checked under a microscope for signs of cancer; or</ListItem><ListItem>a swollen lymph node is felt during a physical exam and/or seen on an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging test</GlossaryTermRef>. When the lymph node is removed and checked under a microscope for signs of cancer, cancer is found in the lymph node. The place where the cancer began is not known.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_220"> In stage IIIB, the tumor may be any size and:</Para><ItemizedList id="_222" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>may have spread to nearby connective tissue, muscle, cartilage, or bone. A swollen lymph node is felt during a physical exam and/or seen on an imaging test. When the lymph node is removed and checked under a microscope for signs of cancer, cancer is found in the lymph node; or</ListItem><ListItem>cancer is in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessel</GlossaryTermRef> between the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> and lymph nodes that are near or far away. Cancer may have spread to lymph nodes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_185"><KeyPoint id="_186">Stage IV (also called Stage 4) Merkel cell carcinoma</KeyPoint><Para id="_221">In stage IV, the tumor has spread to skin  that is not close to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> or to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, bone, or brain.</Para><Para id="_255">Stage IV Merkel cell carcinoma is also called metastatic Merkel cell carcinoma. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if Merkel cell carcinoma spreads to the liver, the cancer cells in the liver are actually Merkel cell carcinoma cells. The disease is called metastatic Merkel cell carcinoma, not liver cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_243"><KeyPoint id="_238">It is common for Merkel cell carcinoma to recur (come back) after it has been treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_256">Recurrent Merkel cell carcinoma is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. If Merkel cell carcinoma comes back, it may come back in the skin, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, or other parts of the body. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned. The type of treatment for recurrent Merkel cell carcinoma will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_257">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_51"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_52">There are different types of treatment for people with Merkel cell carcinoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_258">Different types of treatments are available for Merkel cell carcinoma. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the stage of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment.</Para><Para id="_259">Talking with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You’ll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you’ll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_60">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_61"><KeyPoint id="_62">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_63">One or more of the following surgical procedures may be used to treat Merkel cell carcinoma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_131" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef>: The cancer is cut from the skin along with  some of the  tissue around it. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> may be done during the wide local excision procedure. If there is cancer in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef> also may be done.</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph node dissection: A surgical procedure in which the lymph nodes are removed and  a sample of tissue is checked under a microscope for signs of cancer. For a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044620" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef>, some of the lymph nodes in the tumor area are removed; for a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radical lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef>, most or all of the lymph nodes in the tumor area are removed. This procedure is also called lymphadenectomy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_64">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some patients may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> after surgery to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after the surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called adjuvant therapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><KeyPoint id="_66">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_67">Radiation therapy uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. It is used to treat Merkel cell carcinoma and may also be used as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_249">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy">Radiation Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_68"><KeyPoint id="_69">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_70">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping the cells from dividing.   When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para><Para id="_250">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_223"><KeyPoint id="_224">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_225">Immunotherapy helps a person's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> fight cancer.</Para><Para id="_260">Immunotherapy drugs used to treat Merkel cell carcinoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_261" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000787910" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/avelumab">avelumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000812014" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/retifanlimab-dlwr">retifanlimab</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_263">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_83"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_84">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_91"><Para id="_91_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_91_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_91_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_203"><KeyPoint id="_204">Treatment for Merkel cell carcinoma may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_203_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_150"><KeyPoint id="_151">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_150_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_150_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_98"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038241">stage I Merkel cell carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038242">stage II Merkel cell carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage I and Stage II Merkel Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="CDR0000512918">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000512918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000512921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II</GlossaryTermRef> Merkel cell carcinoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_132" Style="bullet"><ListItem> surgery to remove the tumor, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> after surgery</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_251">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000441548#_59" url="/types/skin/patient/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_98_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038244">stage III Merkel cell carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III Merkel Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_107">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000512926" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III</GlossaryTermRef> Merkel cell carcinoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_157" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000772606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune checkpoint inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef>), for tumors that cannot be removed by surgery</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_252">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000441548#_59" url="/types/skin/patient/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_106_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_160"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000663349">stage IV Merkel cell carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IV Merkel Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_158">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000668176" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IV</GlossaryTermRef> Merkel cell carcinoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_229" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000772606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune checkpoint inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000787910" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/avelumab">avelumab</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef>, or <DrugRef href="CDR0000812014" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/retifanlimab-dlwr">retifanlimab</DrugRef>)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, surgery, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative treatment</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_253">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000441548#_59" url="/types/skin/patient/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_160_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_114"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038245">recurrent Merkel cell carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Merkel Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_115">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> Merkel cell carcinoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_116" Style="bullet">
   
   <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef> to remove a larger area of tissue than was removed in earlier surgery with or without  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
   
   <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> after surgery</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
   
  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000772606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune checkpoint inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000787910" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/avelumab">avelumab</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef>, or <DrugRef href="CDR0000812014" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/retifanlimab-dlwr">retifanlimab</DrugRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy and/or surgery as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative treatment</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_254">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000441548#_59" url="/types/skin/patient/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_114_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>To Learn More About Merkel Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_139">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Merkel cell  carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>,     visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_141" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin">Skin Cancer (Including Melanoma) Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062802" url="/types/skin/patient/skin-prevention-pdq">Skin Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258037" url="/types/skin/patient/skin-screening-pdq">Skin Cancer Screening</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging/sentinel-node-biopsy-fact-sheet">Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_138_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_138_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of merkel cell carcinoma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Merkel Cell Carcinoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/patient/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/patient/merkel-cell-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389202]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062884"/><DateFirstPublished>2006-02-21</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
