<Summary id="CDR0000446580"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>714-X is made by mixing chemicals with camphor, a natural substance that comes from the wood and bark of the camphor tree. 714-X is reported to help the body fight cancer cells. Read about the theory behind using 714-X and its current use in cancer patients.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">714-X  (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/714-x-pdq">714-X  (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000257609">714-X</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_32">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of 714-X in the treatment of people with cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_33">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>714-X</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>714-X (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">714-X - CAM</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">714-X - CAM</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_31"><Strong>NOTE: There is either no new research on this topic or the recent published research is weak and not appropriate for inclusion in the summary. Therefore, the information in this summary is no longer being updated and is provided for reference purposes only.</Strong></Para><ItemizedList id="_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The main ingredient of 714-X is  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">camphor</GlossaryTermRef>, which comes from the wood and bark of the camphor tree (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000446580#_20" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">Question 1</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>It is claimed that 714-X helps the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> fight <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000446580#_22" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">Question 3</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>No study of 714-X has been published in a peer-reviewed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> journal to show it is safe or effective in treating cancer (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000446580#_25" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">Question 6</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>714-X is not approved by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">US Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef>  for use in the United States (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000446580#_27" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">Question 8</SummaryRef>).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2"><Title>Questions and Answers About 714-X</Title><QandASet id="_7"><QandAEntry id="_20"><Question>What is 714-X?</Question><Answer><Para id="_8">The main ingredient in 714-X is made by combining <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemicals</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">camphor</GlossaryTermRef>, a natural substance that comes from the wood and bark of the camphor tree.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691409" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ammonia</GlossaryTermRef> and salt are added to camphor to make 714-X.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_21"><Question>What is the history of the discovery and use of 714-X as a complementary and alternative treatment for cancer?</Question><Answer><Para id="_9">714-X was developed in the 1960s in  Canada, where it is still being made. Patients in Canada can get 714-X only from a doctor, for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046526" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compassionate use</GlossaryTermRef> (giving a treatment to patients before it is approved, because they have a life-threatening disease and there is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef> or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to treat the disease).   714-X is used in Mexico and some western European countries. It is not approved by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">US Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) for use in the United States (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000446580#_27" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">Question 8</SummaryRef>). </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_22"><Question>What is the theory behind the claim that 714-X is useful in treating cancer?</Question><Answer><Para id="_10">The development of 714-X was based on the theory that there are tiny living things in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> called somatids. According to this theory, some types of somatids are found only in the blood of people who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or other serious diseases. These types of somatids are said to make growth <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef> that cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> to grow without control. The makers of 714-X state that by looking at the number and type of somatids in the blood, doctors can see if cancer is starting to form or can <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> cancer and predict where the cancer will spread. </Para><Para id="_28">The theory states that cancer cells trap nitrogen needed by normal cells and make a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxic</GlossaryTermRef> substance that weakens the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>. 714-X is reported to help the body fight cancer cells in these ways: </Para><ItemizedList id="_29" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The camphor in 714-X is said to prevent cancer cells from taking nitrogen from the body's normal cells. </ListItem><ListItem>714-X is also said to   help the immune system by increasing the flow of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph</GlossaryTermRef>, the colorless <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef> that travels through the body carrying <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef> that help fight <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef> and disease. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_12">Some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research studies</GlossaryTermRef> are published in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> journals. Most scientific journals have experts who review research reports before they are published, to make sure that the evidence and conclusions are sound. This is called peer review. Studies published in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed scientific journals</GlossaryTermRef> are considered to be better evidence. No studies have been published in peer-reviewed scientific journals to support the theory of somatids in the development of cancer. Research  on the use of 714-X as a cancer treatment is discussed in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000446580#_24" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">Question 5</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000446580#_25" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">Question 6</SummaryRef>.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_23"><Question>How is 714-X administered?</Question><Answer><Para id="_13">714-X is usually given by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef>.  In some patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, 714-X can be sprayed into the nose using a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nebulizer</GlossaryTermRef> (a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635288" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">device</GlossaryTermRef> that turns liquid into a fine spray).  The makers of 714-X do not recommend injecting it into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenously</GlossaryTermRef>) or taking it by mouth.  </Para><Para id="_14">The makers of 714-X suggest the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet"><ListItem>714-X is more effective if given early in the disease, before <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is begun.</ListItem><ListItem>714-X can be used along with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conventional treatments</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin B</GlossaryTermRef><Subscript>12</Subscript> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplements,</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin E</GlossaryTermRef> supplements, shark <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044190" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cartilage</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef> should not be used during treatment with 714-X.</ListItem></ItemizedList></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_24"><Question>Have any preclinical (laboratory or animal) studies been conducted using 714-X?</Question><Answer><Para id="_30">Research in a laboratory or using animals is done to find out if a drug, procedure, or treatment is likely to be useful in humans. Animal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor models</GlossaryTermRef> are used to learn how a cancer may <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progress</GlossaryTermRef> and to test new treatments. These <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">preclinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> are done before any testing in humans is begun. </Para><Para id="_16">No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory studies</GlossaryTermRef> of the safety and/or effectiveness of 714-X have been published in a peer-reviewed scientific journal.  A few animal experiments have been done, but the results of these experiments have not been reported in scientific journals.  The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> used a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> tumor model in rats and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> tumor models in dogs and cows.  714-X was not found to be effective against cancer in these studies. </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_25"><Question>Have any clinical trials (research studies with people) of 714-X been conducted?</Question><Answer><Para id="_17">No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> or other studies with cancer patients have been published in 
peer-reviewed scientific journals to support the safety or effectiveness of 714-X.  A number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anecdotal reports</GlossaryTermRef> (incomplete descriptions of the medical and treatment history of one or more patients) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testimonials</GlossaryTermRef> (personal reports from people who claim to have been helped or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cured</GlossaryTermRef> by the product) have been published in newspapers and other nonmedical literature.
The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> (NCI) reviewed the records of some cancer patients who used 714-X. This review was done to decide if NCI should begin a clinical trial of the product. Not enough information was available to support recommending a trial. </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_26"><Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from 714-X?</Question><Answer><Para id="_18">The makers of 714-X claim that it is not harmful to humans.  The reported <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of treatment with 714-X are redness, tenderness, and swelling at the injection site.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_27"><Question>Is  714-X approved by the FDA as a cancer treatment in the United States?</Question><Answer><Para id="_19">The FDA has not approved 714-X for use in the United States.  </Para></Answer></QandAEntry></QandASet></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of 714-X in the treatment of people with cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ 714-X. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/714-x-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389214]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_2"><Title>General CAM Information</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_3">Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)—also called integrative medicine—includes a broad range of healing philosophies, approaches, and therapies. A therapy is generally called complementary when it is used in addition to conventional treatments; it is often called alternative when it is used instead of conventional treatment. (Conventional treatments are those that are widely accepted and practiced by the mainstream medical community.) Depending on how they are used, some therapies can be considered either complementary or alternative. Complementary and alternative therapies are used in an effort to prevent illness, reduce stress, prevent or reduce side effects and symptoms, or control or cure disease. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_4">Unlike conventional treatments for cancer, complementary and alternative therapies are often not covered by insurance companies. Patients should check with their insurance provider to find out about coverage for complementary and alternative therapies. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_5">Cancer patients considering complementary and alternative therapies should discuss this decision with their doctor, nurse, or pharmacist as they would any type of treatment. Some complementary and alternative therapies may affect their standard treatment or may be harmful when used with conventional treatment. </Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_6"><Title>Evaluation of CAM Therapies</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_7">It is important that the same scientific methods used to test conventional therapies are used to test CAM therapies. The National Cancer Institute  and the National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) are sponsoring a number of clinical trials (research studies) at medical centers to test CAM therapies for use in cancer. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_8">Conventional approaches to cancer treatment have generally been studied for safety and effectiveness through a scientific process that includes clinical trials with large numbers of patients. Less is known about the safety and effectiveness of complementary and alternative methods. Few CAM therapies have been tested using demanding scientific methods. A small number of CAM therapies that were thought to be purely alternative approaches are now being used in cancer treatment—not as cures, but as complementary therapies that may help patients feel better and recover faster. One example is acupuncture. According to a panel of experts at a National Institutes of Health (NIH) meeting  in November 1997, acupuncture has been found to help control nausea and vomiting caused by chemotherapy and pain related to surgery. However, some approaches, such as the use of laetrile, have been studied and found not to work and to possibly cause harm.</Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_9"><ExternalRef xref="https://cam.cancer.gov/indentifying_novel_cam_therapies/best_case_series_program.htm">The NCI Best Case Series Program</ExternalRef>   which was started  in 1991, is one way CAM approaches that are being used in practice are being studied. The program is overseen by the NCI’s Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM). Health care professionals who offer alternative cancer therapies submit their patients’ medical records and related materials to OCCAM. OCCAM carefully reviews these materials to see if any seem worth further research.</Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_QandA_2"><Title>Questions to Ask Your Health Care Provider About CAM</Title><Para id="_QandA_3">When considering complementary and alternative therapies, patients should ask their health care provider the following questions: </Para><ItemizedList id="_QandA_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>What side effects can be expected?</ListItem><ListItem>What are the risks related to this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>What benefits can be expected from this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>Do the known benefits outweigh the risks?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy affect conventional treatment?</ListItem><ListItem>Is this therapy part of a clinical trial?</ListItem><ListItem>If so, who is the sponsor of the trial?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy be covered by health insurance?</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
   
  <SummarySection id="_ToLearnMore_2"><Title>To Learn More About CAM</Title><Para id="_ToLearnMore_3"><Strong><Emphasis>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_4">The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) facilitates research and evaluation of complementary and alternative practices, and provides information about a variety of approaches to health professionals and the public.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_5" Style="simple"><ListItem>NCCIH Clearinghouse</ListItem><ListItem>Post Office Box 7923 Gaithersburg, MD 20898–7923</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-644-6226 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and hard of hearing callers): 1-866-464-3615</ListItem><ListItem>E-mail: info@nccih.nih.gov</ListItem><ListItem>Website:  <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/">https://nccih.nih.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_15"><Strong><Emphasis>CAM on PubMed</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_16">NCCIH and the NIH National Library of Medicine (NLM) jointly developed <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/research/camonpubmed">CAM on PubMed</ExternalRef>, a free and easy-to-use search tool for finding CAM-related journal citations. As a subset of the NLM's PubMed bibliographic database, CAM on PubMed features more than 230,000 references and abstracts for CAM-related articles from scientific journals. This database also provides links to the websites of over 1,800 journals, allowing users to view full-text articles. (A subscription or other fee may be required to access full-text articles.) </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_17"><Strong><Emphasis>Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_18">The NCI Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM) coordinates the activities of the NCI in the area of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM). OCCAM supports CAM cancer research and provides information about cancer-related CAM to health providers and the general public via the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/">NCI website</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_19"><Strong><Emphasis>National Cancer Institute (NCI) Cancer Information Service</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_20">U.S. residents may call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, toll free at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237) Monday through Friday from 9:00 am to 9:00 pm. A trained Cancer Information Specialist is available to answer your questions.</Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_8"><Strong><Emphasis>Food and Drug Administration </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_9">The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulates drugs and medical devices to ensure that they are safe and effective.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_10" Style="simple"><ListItem>Food and Drug Administration </ListItem><ListItem>10903 New Hampshire Avenue</ListItem><ListItem>Silver Spring, MD 20993</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-463-6332 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/">http://www.fda.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_11"><Strong><Emphasis>Federal Trade Commission </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_12">The Federal Trade Commission (FTC) enforces consumer protection laws. Publications available from the FTC include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_13" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Emphasis>Who Cares: Sources of Information About Health Care Products and Services </Emphasis></ListItem><ListItem><Emphasis>Fraudulent Health Claims: Don’t Be Fooled </Emphasis></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_14" Style="simple"><ListItem>Consumer Response Center</ListItem><ListItem>Federal Trade Commission</ListItem><ListItem>600 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW</ListItem><ListItem>Washington, DC 20580</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-877-FTC-HELP (1-877-382-4357) (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and  hard of hearing callers): 202-326-2502</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ftc.gov/">http://www.ftc.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
  <PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062972"/><DateFirstPublished>2005-09-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2017-04-28</DateLastModified></Summary>
