<Summary id="CDR0000453628"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Gerson therapy is a complex regimen that has been used to treat people with cancer and other diseases. It includes a strict diet, dietary supplements, and enemas. No results of laboratory or animal studies have been published in scientific journals. Learn more in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Gerson Therapy (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/gerson-pdq">Gerson Therapy (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000453793">Gerson therapy</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_39">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of Gerson therapy in the treatment of people with cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_40">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Gerson therapy</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Gerson Therapy (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Gerson Therapy</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Gerson Therapy</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_38"><Strong>NOTE: There is either no new research on this topic or the recent published research is weak and not appropriate for inclusion in the summary. Therefore, the information in this summary is no longer being updated and is provided for reference purposes only.</Strong></Para><ItemizedList id="_7" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446537" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gerson therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a complex <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimen</GlossaryTermRef> that has been used to treat people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and other diseases (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453628#_9" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Question 1</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>The key parts of the Gerson therapy are a strict <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044204" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enemas</GlossaryTermRef> (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453628#_9" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Question 1</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>The theory is that disease can be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cured</GlossaryTermRef> by removing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxins</GlossaryTermRef> from the body,  boosting the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>, and replacing excess salt in the body's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044344" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">potassium</GlossaryTermRef> (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453628#_24" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Question 3</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>The Gerson therapy requires that the many details of its treatment plan be followed exactly (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453628#_12" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Question 4</SummaryRef>).

</ListItem><ListItem>Few <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> of the Gerson therapy have been published (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453628#_14" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Question 6</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>Taking too many enemas of any kind can be harmful (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453628#_28" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Question 7</SummaryRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">US Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> has not approved the Gerson therapy for the treatment of cancer or other diseases (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453628#_16" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Question 8</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer patients should talk with their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care providers</GlossaryTermRef> about an appropriate diet to follow (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000453628#_16" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">Question 8</SummaryRef>).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>Questions and Answers About the Gerson Therapy</Title><QandASet id="_8"><QandAEntry id="_9"><Question>What is the Gerson therapy?</Question><Answer><Para id="_6">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446537" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gerson therapy</GlossaryTermRef> has been used by some people to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and other diseases.  It is based on the role of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef>, and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary</GlossaryTermRef> factors. 

There are 3 key parts  to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Diet: <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000531137" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Organic</GlossaryTermRef> fruits, vegetables, and whole grains to give the body plenty of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, minerals, enzymes, and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef>. The fruits and vegetables are low in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044731" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sodium</GlossaryTermRef> (salt) and high in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044344" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">potassium</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Supplementation</GlossaryTermRef>: The addition of certain substances to the diet  to help correct <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> (the chemical changes that take place in a cell to make energy and basic materials needed for the body's life processes).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Detoxification</GlossaryTermRef>: Treatments, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044204" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enemas</GlossaryTermRef>, to remove <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxic</GlossaryTermRef> (harmful) substances from the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_10"><Question>What is the history of the discovery and use of the Gerson therapy as a complementary or alternative treatment for cancer?</Question><Answer><Para id="_11">The Gerson therapy was named after Dr. Max B. Gerson (1881-1959), who first used it to treat his migraine headaches.  In the 1930's, Dr. Gerson’s therapy became known to the public as a treatment for a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tuberculosis</GlossaryTermRef> (TB).  The Gerson therapy was later used to treat other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions,</GlossaryTermRef> including cancer.  </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_24"><Question>What is the theory behind the claim that the Gerson therapy is useful in treating cancer?</Question><Answer><Para id="_25">The Gerson therapy is based on the idea that cancer develops when there are changes in cell metabolism because of the buildup  of toxic substances  in the body. Dr. Gerson  said the disease process makes more toxins and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> becomes overworked.   According to Dr. Gerson, people with cancer also have too much sodium and too little potassium in the cells in their bodies, which causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> damage and weakened <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organs</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_32">The goal of the Gerson therapy is to restore the body to health by repairing the liver and returning the metabolism to its normal state. According to Dr. Gerson, this can be done by removing toxins from the body and  building up the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> with diet and supplements. The enemas are said to  widen the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile ducts</GlossaryTermRef> of the liver so  toxins can be released. According to Dr. Gerson, the liver is further overworked as the treatment <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimen</GlossaryTermRef> breaks down cancer cells and rids the body of toxins.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046704" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pancreatic enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> are given to decrease the demands on the weakened liver and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef> to make enzymes for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463707" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestion</GlossaryTermRef>. An organic diet and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutritional supplements</GlossaryTermRef> are used to boost the immune system and support the body as the regimen cleans the body of toxins. Foods low in sodium and high in potassium are said to help correct the tissue damage caused by having too much sodium in the cells.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_12"><Question>How is the Gerson therapy administered?</Question><Answer><Para id="_22">The Gerson therapy requires that the many details of its treatment plan be followed exactly.

Some key parts of the regimen include the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_23" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Drinking 13 glasses of juice a day. The juice must be freshly made from organic fruits and vegetables and be taken once every hour. </ListItem><ListItem>Eating vegetarian meals of organically grown fruits, vegetables, and whole grains. </ListItem><ListItem>Taking a number of supplements, including:<ItemizedList id="_31" Style="dash"><ListItem>Potassium.</ListItem><ListItem>Lugol's Solution (potassium iodide, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044548" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iodine</GlossaryTermRef>, and water).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Coenzyme Q10</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin B12</GlossaryTermRef>. (The original regimen used crude liver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef> instead of coenzyme Q10.)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamins A</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">C</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000629155" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">B3</GlossaryTermRef> (niacin).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285920" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Flaxseed</GlossaryTermRef> oil.</ListItem><ListItem>Pancreatic enzymes.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689977" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pepsin</GlossaryTermRef> (a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> enzyme). </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446111" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coffee</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chamomile</GlossaryTermRef> enemas regularly to remove toxins from the body. </ListItem><ListItem>Preparing food without salt, spices, or oils, and without using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639941" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aluminum</GlossaryTermRef> cookware or utensils.</ListItem></ItemizedList></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_26"><Question>Have any preclinical (laboratory or animal) studies  been conducted using the Gerson therapy?</Question><Answer><Para id="_27">No results of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> have been published in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> journals. </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_14"><Question>Have any  clinical trials (research studies with people) of the Gerson therapy been conducted?</Question><Answer><Para id="_33">Most of the published information on the use of  the Gerson therapy reports on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044956" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retrospective studies</GlossaryTermRef> (reviews of past cases). Dr. Gerson published <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case histories</GlossaryTermRef> (detailed reports of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>, treatment, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> of individual patients) of 50 of his patients. He treated several different types of cancer in his practice.  The reports include Dr. Gerson's notes, with some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">X-rays</GlossaryTermRef> of the patients over time.  The follow-up was contact with patients by mail or phone and included <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anecdotal reports</GlossaryTermRef> (incomplete descriptions of the medical and treatment histories of one or more patients).</Para><Para id="_37">In 1947 and 1959, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> (NCI) reviewed 
the cases of a total of 60 patients treated by Dr. Gerson. The NCI found that the available information did not prove the regimen had benefit.</Para><Para id="_35">The following studies of the Gerson therapy were published:</Para><ItemizedList id="_34" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In 1983-1984, a retrospective study of 38 patients treated with the Gerson therapy was done. Medical records were not available to the  authors of the study; information came from patient interviews.  These case reviews did not provide information that supports the usefulness of  the Gerson therapy for treating cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>    In 1990, a study of a diet regimen similar to the Gerson therapy was done in Austria. The patients received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> along with the special diet. The authors of the study reported that the diet appeared to help patients live longer than usual and have fewer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>. The authors said it needed further study.</ListItem><ListItem>In 1995, the Gerson Research Organization did a retrospective study of their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef> patients  who were treated with the Gerson therapy.  The study reported that patients who had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045138" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045139" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage  IV melanoma</GlossaryTermRef> lived longer than usual for patients with these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stages</GlossaryTermRef> of melanoma. There have been no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> that support the findings of this retrospective study. </ListItem><ListItem>A case review of 6 patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic cancer</GlossaryTermRef> who used the Gerson therapy reported that  the regimen helped patients in some ways,  both physically and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologically</GlossaryTermRef>.  Based on these results, the reviewers recommended that  clinical trials of the Gerson therapy be conducted.</ListItem></ItemizedList></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_28"><Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from use of the Gerson therapy?</Question><Answer><Para id="_29">Reports of three deaths that may be related to coffee enemas have been published.  Taking too many enemas of any kind can cause changes in normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> chemistry, chemicals that occur naturally in the body and keep the muscles, heart, and other organs working properly.
</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_16"><Question>Is the Gerson therapy approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for use as a cancer treatment in the United States?</Question><Answer><Para id="_30">The Gerson therapy has not been approved by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454786" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FDA</GlossaryTermRef> for use as a treatment for cancer or any other disease.</Para><Para id="_17">For most cancer patients, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrition</GlossaryTermRef>  guidelines include eating a well-balanced diet with plenty of fruits, vegetables, and whole-grain products.  However, general guidelines such as these may have to be changed to meet the specific needs of an individual patient.  Patients should talk with their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care providers</GlossaryTermRef> about an appropriate diet to follow.  Information about diet during cancer treatment is also available from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer Information Service</GlossaryTermRef> (1-800-4-CANCER) and in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nutrition">Nutrition During Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry></QandASet></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of Gerson therapy in the treatment of people with cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Gerson Therapy. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/gerson-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389408]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_2"><Title>General CAM Information</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_3">Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)—also called integrative medicine—includes a broad range of healing philosophies, approaches, and therapies. A therapy is generally called complementary when it is used in addition to conventional treatments; it is often called alternative when it is used instead of conventional treatment. (Conventional treatments are those that are widely accepted and practiced by the mainstream medical community.) Depending on how they are used, some therapies can be considered either complementary or alternative. Complementary and alternative therapies are used in an effort to prevent illness, reduce stress, prevent or reduce side effects and symptoms, or control or cure disease. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_4">Unlike conventional treatments for cancer, complementary and alternative therapies are often not covered by insurance companies. Patients should check with their insurance provider to find out about coverage for complementary and alternative therapies. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_5">Cancer patients considering complementary and alternative therapies should discuss this decision with their doctor, nurse, or pharmacist as they would any type of treatment. Some complementary and alternative therapies may affect their standard treatment or may be harmful when used with conventional treatment. </Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_6"><Title>Evaluation of CAM Therapies</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_7">It is important that the same scientific methods used to test conventional therapies are used to test CAM therapies. The National Cancer Institute  and the National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) are sponsoring a number of clinical trials (research studies) at medical centers to test CAM therapies for use in cancer. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_8">Conventional approaches to cancer treatment have generally been studied for safety and effectiveness through a scientific process that includes clinical trials with large numbers of patients. Less is known about the safety and effectiveness of complementary and alternative methods. Few CAM therapies have been tested using demanding scientific methods. A small number of CAM therapies that were thought to be purely alternative approaches are now being used in cancer treatment—not as cures, but as complementary therapies that may help patients feel better and recover faster. One example is acupuncture. According to a panel of experts at a National Institutes of Health (NIH) meeting  in November 1997, acupuncture has been found to help control nausea and vomiting caused by chemotherapy and pain related to surgery. However, some approaches, such as the use of laetrile, have been studied and found not to work and to possibly cause harm.</Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_9"><ExternalRef xref="https://cam.cancer.gov/indentifying_novel_cam_therapies/best_case_series_program.htm">The NCI Best Case Series Program</ExternalRef>   which was started  in 1991, is one way CAM approaches that are being used in practice are being studied. The program is overseen by the NCI’s Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM). Health care professionals who offer alternative cancer therapies submit their patients’ medical records and related materials to OCCAM. OCCAM carefully reviews these materials to see if any seem worth further research.</Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_QandA_2"><Title>Questions to Ask Your Health Care Provider About CAM</Title><Para id="_QandA_3">When considering complementary and alternative therapies, patients should ask their health care provider the following questions: </Para><ItemizedList id="_QandA_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>What side effects can be expected?</ListItem><ListItem>What are the risks related to this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>What benefits can be expected from this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>Do the known benefits outweigh the risks?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy affect conventional treatment?</ListItem><ListItem>Is this therapy part of a clinical trial?</ListItem><ListItem>If so, who is the sponsor of the trial?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy be covered by health insurance?</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
   
  <SummarySection id="_ToLearnMore_2"><Title>To Learn More About CAM</Title><Para id="_ToLearnMore_3"><Strong><Emphasis>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_4">The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) facilitates research and evaluation of complementary and alternative practices, and provides information about a variety of approaches to health professionals and the public.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_5" Style="simple"><ListItem>NCCIH Clearinghouse</ListItem><ListItem>Post Office Box 7923 Gaithersburg, MD 20898–7923</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-644-6226 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and hard of hearing callers): 1-866-464-3615</ListItem><ListItem>E-mail: info@nccih.nih.gov</ListItem><ListItem>Website:  <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/">https://nccih.nih.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_15"><Strong><Emphasis>CAM on PubMed</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_16">NCCIH and the NIH National Library of Medicine (NLM) jointly developed <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/research/camonpubmed">CAM on PubMed</ExternalRef>, a free and easy-to-use search tool for finding CAM-related journal citations. As a subset of the NLM's PubMed bibliographic database, CAM on PubMed features more than 230,000 references and abstracts for CAM-related articles from scientific journals. This database also provides links to the websites of over 1,800 journals, allowing users to view full-text articles. (A subscription or other fee may be required to access full-text articles.) </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_17"><Strong><Emphasis>Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_18">The NCI Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM) coordinates the activities of the NCI in the area of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM). OCCAM supports CAM cancer research and provides information about cancer-related CAM to health providers and the general public via the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/">NCI website</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_19"><Strong><Emphasis>National Cancer Institute (NCI) Cancer Information Service</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_20">U.S. residents may call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, toll free at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237) Monday through Friday from 9:00 am to 9:00 pm. A trained Cancer Information Specialist is available to answer your questions.</Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_8"><Strong><Emphasis>Food and Drug Administration </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_9">The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulates drugs and medical devices to ensure that they are safe and effective.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_10" Style="simple"><ListItem>Food and Drug Administration </ListItem><ListItem>10903 New Hampshire Avenue</ListItem><ListItem>Silver Spring, MD 20993</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-463-6332 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/">http://www.fda.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_11"><Strong><Emphasis>Federal Trade Commission </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_12">The Federal Trade Commission (FTC) enforces consumer protection laws. Publications available from the FTC include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_13" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Emphasis>Who Cares: Sources of Information About Health Care Products and Services </Emphasis></ListItem><ListItem><Emphasis>Fraudulent Health Claims: Don’t Be Fooled </Emphasis></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_14" Style="simple"><ListItem>Consumer Response Center</ListItem><ListItem>Federal Trade Commission</ListItem><ListItem>600 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW</ListItem><ListItem>Washington, DC 20580</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-877-FTC-HELP (1-877-382-4357) (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and  hard of hearing callers): 202-326-2502</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ftc.gov/">http://www.ftc.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
  <PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000538268"/><DateFirstPublished>2005-10-24</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2015-01-07</DateLastModified></Summary>
