<Summary id="CDR0000458088"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Acupuncture is a complementary therapy used by cancer patients to manage symptoms related to cancer and its treatment. Learn more about acupuncture and its use as a complementary therapy in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/acupuncture-pdq">Acupuncture (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/acupuncture-pdq">Acupuncture (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000372888">acupuncture therapy</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_121">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of acupuncture in the treatment of people with cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_122">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the  version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>acupuncture therapy</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Acupuncture (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Acupuncture</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Acupuncture</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><ItemizedList id="_9" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Acupuncture</GlossaryTermRef> applies needles, heat, pressure, and other treatments to one or more places on the skin known as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449727" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acupuncture points</GlossaryTermRef> (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000458088#_45" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/acupuncture-pdq">Question 1</SummaryRef>). </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> report that acupuncture relieves <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef> from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639945" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anticancer therapies</GlossaryTermRef> (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000458088#_57" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/acupuncture-pdq">Question 5</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>Other trials have studied the use of acupuncture in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> treatment to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, dry mouth, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256567" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hot flashes</GlossaryTermRef> (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000458088#_57" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/acupuncture-pdq">Question 5</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>A strict clean needle method must be used when acupuncture treatment is given to people with cancer  (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000458088#_59" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/acupuncture-pdq">Question 6</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000458088#_60" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/acupuncture-pdq">Question 7</SummaryRef>).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Questions and Answers About Acupuncture</Title><QandASet id="_24"><QandAEntry id="_45"><Question> What is acupuncture?  </Question><Answer><Para id="_17"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Acupuncture</GlossaryTermRef> applies needles, heat, pressure, and other treatments to places on the skin, called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449727" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acupuncture points</GlossaryTermRef>  (or acupoints), to control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> such as pain or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef>. Acupuncture is part of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">traditional Chinese medicine</GlossaryTermRef> (TCM). </Para><Para id="_4">Acupuncture is based on the belief that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454782" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">qi</GlossaryTermRef> (vital energy) flows through the body along paths, called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meridians</GlossaryTermRef>. Qi is said to affect a person's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef>, emotional, mental, and physical health. </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_55"><Question>How is acupuncture given?</Question><Answer><Para id="_28">Most acupuncture methods use needles. Disposable, stainless steel needles that are slightly thicker than a human hair are inserted into the skin at acupoints. The acupuncture <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">practitioner</GlossaryTermRef> chooses the correct acupoints for the problem being treated. The inserted needles may be twirled, moved up and down at different speeds and depths, heated, or charged with a weak electric current.</Para><Para id="_70">Acupuncture methods include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_20" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793175" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Auricular acupuncture</GlossaryTermRef>: Acupuncture needles are placed at acupoints on the outer ear that match up with  certain parts of the body. Other parts of the body used in acupuncture include scalp, face, nose, hand, wrist-ankle, and foot.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269415" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Electroacupuncture</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449745" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Trigger point acupuncture</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Laser acupuncture</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Acupuncture point injection</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Microwave acupuncture</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046723" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Acupressure</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Moxibustion</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449725" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cupping</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_85"><Question>What do people feel during acupuncture?</Question><Answer><Para id="_86">People may have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449723" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">needling</GlossaryTermRef> feeling during acupuncture, known as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467835" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">de qi sensation</GlossaryTermRef>, making them feel heaviness, numbness, or tingling.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_56"><Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies  been done using    
	acupuncture?
</Question><Answer><Para id="_31">	In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory studies</GlossaryTermRef>, a treatment is tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> samples to find out if it has any anticancer effects. In animal studies, a drug, procedure, or treatment is tested in mice or other animals to see if it is safe and effective. Laboratory and animal studies are done before a treatment is tested in people. </Para><Para id="_123">Laboratory and animal studies have tested the effects of acupuncture. For information on laboratory and animal studies, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000445441#_25" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/acupuncture-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Acupuncture. </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_57"><Question>Have any  studies been done in people?</Question><Answer><Para id="_22"> In 1997, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044268" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Institutes of Health</GlossaryTermRef> (NIH) began looking at how well acupuncture worked as a complementary therapy for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>-related symptoms and side effects of cancer treatments. Studies of acupuncture in cancer care also have been done in China and other countries.</Para><ItemizedList id="_63" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Nausea and vomiting caused by chemotherapy, surgery, and radiation therapy</Strong><Para id="_124">The strongest evidence for acupuncture has come from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> on the use of acupuncture to relieve nausea and vomiting.</Para><ItemizedList id="_125" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>A 2013 review that included 41 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled trials</GlossaryTermRef> found that acupuncture helped treat  nausea and vomiting caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Another review from 11 randomized clinical trials found that people receiving chemotherapy who also received acupuncture were less likely to experience <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute</GlossaryTermRef> vomiting compared to people who did not receive acupuncture.</ListItem><ListItem>A comparison of studies suggests that using specific acupuncture points may make a difference in how well acupuncture works to relieve nausea caused by chemotherapy.  </ListItem><ListItem>People who received either true acupuncture or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sham</GlossaryTermRef> acupuncture were compared to people who received only <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689630" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard care</GlossaryTermRef> to prevent nausea and vomiting from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. The study found that people in both the true and sham acupuncture groups had less nausea and vomiting than those in the standard care group.</ListItem><ListItem>In a 2016  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of auricular acupressure  that included 48 people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> treated with chemotherapy, people who received auricular acupressure had  less intense and less frequent nausea and vomiting compared with those who did not have auricular acupressure. These findings are  limited because the study  had a small number of participants and no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> group. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Pain</Strong><Para id="_136">Acupuncture has been studied to help relieve pain in people with cancer. The results are mixed due to small sample sizes and design problems.</Para><ItemizedList id="_137" Style="bullet" Compact="No">
     <ListItem><Strong>Cancer pain</Strong><Para id="_154">Most <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of acupuncture  for cancer pain use conventional acupuncture methods with needles in different parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_138">In one review of several small studies, acupuncture reduced cancer pain in some people with various cancers. Another review concluded acupuncture with pain medicine worked better than the pain medicine alone. This review was limited by poor quality of clinical trials.</Para><Para id="_155">A 2020 clinical trial to treat cancer pain showed that the combination of wrist-ankle acupuncture and auricular acupuncture was effective in reducing pain and use of pain medication. The study was limited by small size, lack of a placebo group, and short follow up.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Postoperative pain</Strong><Para id="_139">In several randomized clinical trials on pain after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>, acupuncture reduced pain, but sample sizes were small and additional treatments were unknown. Some studies reported that pain decreased even more when acupuncture was used with standard care.</Para><Para id="_144">In two randomized clinical trials in people who had a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000669655" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow aspiration and biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>, acupressure was found to relieve pain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> compared to sham acupressure.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Muscle and joint pain from aromatase inhibitors</Strong><Para id="_140"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044232" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Aromatase inhibitors</GlossaryTermRef>, a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmenopausal</GlossaryTermRef> women who have hormone-dependent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, may cause muscle and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">joint</GlossaryTermRef> pain. </Para><ItemizedList id="_141" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Five randomized controlled trials compared the effects of real and sham acupuncture in reducing pain. All five trials showed no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> from either real acupuncture or sham acupuncture. Two trials showed real acupuncture was better than sham acupuncture in relieving joint and muscle pain, but the other three trials did not.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000286105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Observational studies</GlossaryTermRef> have also reported both real acupuncture and sham acupuncture may relieve pain more than standard care.</ListItem><ListItem>A review of 17,922 people with cancer reported that real acupuncture relieved pain better than sham acupuncture.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Muscle and joint pain in cancer survivors</Strong><Para id="_156">In  a 2021 randomized clinical trial that included 360 cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> with muscle and joint pain, people reported better pain relief from  acupuncture compared to standard care.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy</Strong><Para id="_150"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044705" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Peripheral neuropathy</GlossaryTermRef> is a common side effect of chemotherapy that   can cause  pain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044118" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paresthesia</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044121" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sensory</GlossaryTermRef> loss, and muscle weakness.   These symptoms can cause a person to  delay or end treatment. Chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy (CIPN)  can affect  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>  and may last long after chemotherapy has ended. </Para><Para id="_151"> The current <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard of care</GlossaryTermRef> for CIPN is  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269453" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptom management</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">narcotics</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antidepressants</GlossaryTermRef>. However,  treatment may not relieve all of the pain,  and  it can cause dizziness, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sedation</GlossaryTermRef>, dry mouth, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_152">Some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of acupuncture have shown promise in treating CIPN.  More evidence is needed to explore how  acupuncture may relieve symptoms  of CIPN and to find out which people  may benefit most from acupuncture. For more information about these studies, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000445441#_367" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/acupuncture-pdq">Acupuncture to treat persistent CIPN from taxane or platinum-based chemotherapy</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Acupuncture.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Hot flashes</Strong><Para id="_76">  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256567" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hot flashes</GlossaryTermRef> in women with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and men with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Studies of the use of acupuncture to relieve hot flashes have shown mixed results.</Para><ItemizedList id="_116" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Six randomized clinical trials studied the use of   acupuncture to prevent hot flashes in breast cancer survivors. These trials found that acupuncture was safe and decreased hot flashes. It was not clear whether real acupuncture worked better than sham acupuncture.</ListItem><ListItem>A 2015 randomized  trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269415" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electroacupuncture</GlossaryTermRef> in breast cancer survivors with hot flashes had four groups for treatment: electroacupuncture, sham acupuncture,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045039" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gabapentin</GlossaryTermRef>, and placebo. The trial looked at how well sham acupuncture worked compared to the placebo and compared hot flash relief in all groups. The study found that sham acupuncture worked better than gabapentin or the placebo, and both electroacupuncture and sham acupuncture gave better relief than gabapentin. </ListItem><ListItem>A 2016 randomized trial compared acupuncture plus self-care (as described in an information booklet provided to all patients) to self-care alone in breast cancer survivors.  The study found that adding acupuncture reduced hot flashes after 12 weeks of treatment and at the 3- and 6-month <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> visits.  The study also found that acupuncture improved the participants' <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A 2016 review of 12 randomized trials in breast cancer survivors with hot flashes included six studies that compared real  acupuncture with sham acupuncture. Of these, only two studies found that real acupuncture had a benefit compared with  the sham treatment. The other studies found that acupuncture was no better than hormone therapy, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">venlafaxine</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689628" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relaxation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> in relieving hot flashes.</ListItem><ListItem>Some studies have reported that acupuncture may relieve hot flashes in people with prostate cancer who are on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">androgen-deprivation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Fatigue</Strong><Para id="_104"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fatigue</GlossaryTermRef> is a common symptom in people with cancer and a frequent side effect of chemotherapy and radiation therapy. </Para><ItemizedList id="_117" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Several randomized clinical trials have studied the use of   acupuncture in reducing cancer-related fatigue. These trials found that acupuncture improved fatigue when compared to standard care alone. It is not clear whether real acupuncture works better than sham acupuncture.</ListItem><ListItem>A 2016 randomized clinical trial of 78 cancer survivors with cancer-related fatigue showed that infrared <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laser acupuncture</GlossaryTermRef> used on certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454748" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acupoints</GlossaryTermRef> was safe. People who received infrared laser acupuncture three times per week for 4 weeks had less fatigue than those who received sham treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>A 2016 randomized clinical trial of 288 breast cancer survivors with  fatigue that wouldn't go away showed that two types of acupressure (relaxing and stimulating) significantly reduced cancer-related fatigue.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Dry mouth (xerostomia)  </Strong><Para id="_92">Several clinical trials have studied the effect of acupuncture in the treatment and prevention of dry mouth caused by radiation therapy in people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharyngeal carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><ItemizedList id="_106" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In studies that compared acupuncture with standard care for preventing dry mouth in people receiving radiation therapy, people receiving acupuncture had fewer dry mouth symptoms and better <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257526" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">saliva</GlossaryTermRef> flow.</ListItem><ListItem>Two randomized controlled trials compared real and sham acupuncture for the prevention and treatment of dry mouth. These trials found that both real and sham acupuncture increased the flow of saliva.</ListItem><ListItem>A study on the long-term effects of acupuncture on dry mouth found that people had better saliva flow 6 months after receiving acupuncture treatment than  before they began acupuncture treatment. People who received additional acupuncture had more saliva flow at 3 years compared to people who did not continue acupuncture treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_153">One <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045833" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase III clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> with sites in the United States and China studied 339 people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef> who received true acupuncture, sham acupuncture, or standard care while receiving radiation therapy. Acupuncture was given three times per week during a 6- to 7-week course of radiation therapy. The dry mouth  score reduction at 1 year was greater  in the true acupuncture group than in the standard care group, but only slightly different  from  the sham acupuncture group. An additional phase III clinical trial is in progress to study the role  of acupuncture for the  treatment of  dry mouth in people with head and neck cancer. </Para><Para id="_118"> Other trials are ongoing. </Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Lymphedema</Strong><Para id="_113">There have been a number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case reports</GlossaryTermRef> and studies that show acupuncture is safe and may decrease swelling and relieve symptoms in people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045359" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphedema</GlossaryTermRef> in the arms and legs.</Para><ItemizedList id="_147" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In one randomized clinical trial, acupuncture may have kept lymphedema from getting worse but did not decrease swelling or symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem>  In a  2016 study, acupuncture along with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">moxibustion</GlossaryTermRef> treatments were shown to increase energy levels and decrease pain in 23 people with breast or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and lymphedema.</ListItem><ListItem>In a 2016 randomized clinical trial that included 30 people with breast cancer and lymphedema, warm acupuncture (acupuncture and moxibustion) improved lymphedema symptoms for some participants. However, a small portion of people who did not receive warm acupuncture also had improved symptoms.  People who received warm acupuncture also had improved shoulder <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">joint</GlossaryTermRef> range of motion and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> compared to those who did not receive warm acupuncture.</ListItem><ListItem>A randomized clinical trial that included 82 people with breast cancer and lymphedema found that those who received acupuncture had no change in lymphedema symptoms compared to those who did not receive acupuncture.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Ileus </Strong><Para id="_107">After cancer surgery, some people develop <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000558995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ileus</GlossaryTermRef>. Randomized clinical trials  that studied acupuncture for ileus had mixed results.</Para><Para id="_163">A 2023  randomized clinical trial of 249 patients  in China compared electroacupuncture with sham acupuncture  in people who underwent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000637280" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laparoscopic surgery</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The study reported that the average time to recover <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446980" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel function</GlossaryTermRef> was shorter in the electroacupuncture  group compared with the sham acupuncture group. Electroacupuncture after laparoscopic colon cancer surgery was  reported to be safe and effective in reducing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043980" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postoperative</GlossaryTermRef> ileus.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Anxiety</Strong><Para id="_157">A randomized clinical trial that included 141 people studied the effect of acupuncture on relieving anxiety in people undergoing surgery. Participants received either standard care for relieving anxiety or acupuncture before surgery,  during surgery,  or both combined. Acupuncture before  surgery relieved anxiety for people waiting for their surgery to begin. Acupuncture before and during surgery combined were most effective in  improving quality of life after surgery. Because there was no group that received sham acupuncture as a placebo, future studies are needed to find out  if acupuncture is useful for anxiety.</Para><Para id="_158"> A randomized clinical trial  published in 2013 studied  cancer-related fatigue in 246 patients. Participants reported that acupuncture reduced fatigue, anxiety, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>, and improved quality of life when compared with standard care.</Para><Para id="_159">An analysis of a larger study showed that acupressure was linked to decreased anxiety and pain and fewer symptoms of depression when compared with standard care.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Sleep problems</Strong><Para id="_148">Studies have shown that acupuncture may help relieve sleep problems.</Para><ItemizedList id="_149" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A 2019 randomized controlled trial of cancer survivors found that acupuncture reduced the severity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">insomnia</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A 2014 study found that acupuncture improved sleep slightly more than standard care.</ListItem><ListItem>A 2011 study that compared    acupuncture with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluoxetine</GlossaryTermRef>  found that acupuncture worked better in relieving <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef> and improving sleep.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>The immune system</Strong><Para id="_126">Studies that suggest acupuncture may improve the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> are limited.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Other symptoms of cancer  and side effects of cancer treatment</Strong><Para id="_62"> Other clinical trials in people with cancer have studied the effects of acupuncture on  cancer symptoms and side effects  caused by cancer treatment, including weight loss, cough, coughing up blood, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef>, depression,   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454770" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proctitis</GlossaryTermRef>, speech problems, blocked        <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>, chemotherapy-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cognitive</GlossaryTermRef> problems, and hiccups. A randomized study of acupressure  in managing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045054" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">opioid</GlossaryTermRef>-induced constipation suggested that it helped to  improve quality of life and reduce symptoms. Studies have shown that treatment with  acupuncture either relieves symptoms or keeps them from getting worse.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Acupuncture in children with cancer</Strong><Para id="_160">Few studies have examined the effects of acupuncture in children with cancer. In a  study of 80 participants, the acceptance rate for acupuncture was 82% in children, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adolescents</GlossaryTermRef>, and young adults who were having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hematopoietic stem cell</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_162"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> of acupuncture in children appear to be rare and similar to the same effects found in adults. One study in children who received acupuncture showed that there was no higher rate of adverse effects in those with cancer-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045365" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thrombocytopenia</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045361" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neutropenia</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_59"><Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from acupuncture?</Question><Answer><Para id="_29">There have been few <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complications</GlossaryTermRef> reported. Problems may arise from  using needles that are not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sterile</GlossaryTermRef>, placing the needle in the wrong place, movement of the person receiving acupuncture, or a defect in the needle.  </Para><Para id="_133">Side effects include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_134" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Soreness and pain during treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling tired, lightheaded, or sleepy.</ListItem><ListItem>Getting an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_135">A strict clean needle method must be used when acupuncture treatment is given to people with cancer, because chemotherapy and radiation therapy weaken the body's immune system.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_60"><Question>Is acupuncture approved by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA)?</Question><Answer><Para id="_30">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454786" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FDA</GlossaryTermRef> approved acupuncture needles for use by licensed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">practitioners</GlossaryTermRef> in 1996. The FDA requires that sterile needles be used and labeled for single use by qualified practitioners only.</Para><Para id="_71">More than 40 states and the District of Columbia have laws about acupuncture practice.   The National Certification Commission for Acupuncture and Oriental Medicine (<ExternalRef xref="http://www.nccaom.org/">www.nccaom.org</ExternalRef>) certifies practitioners of acupuncture and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">traditional Chinese medicine</GlossaryTermRef> (TCM). Most states require this certification.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry></QandASet></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_80"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_80_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of acupuncture in the treatment of people with cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Acupuncture. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/acupuncture-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/acupuncture-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389264]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_2"><Title>General CAM Information</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_3">Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)—also called integrative medicine—includes a broad range of healing philosophies, approaches, and therapies. A therapy is generally called complementary when it is used in addition to conventional treatments; it is often called alternative when it is used instead of conventional treatment. (Conventional treatments are those that are widely accepted and practiced by the mainstream medical community.) Depending on how they are used, some therapies can be considered either complementary or alternative. Complementary and alternative therapies are used in an effort to prevent illness, reduce stress, prevent or reduce side effects and symptoms, or control or cure disease. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_4">Unlike conventional treatments for cancer, complementary and alternative therapies are often not covered by insurance companies. Patients should check with their insurance provider to find out about coverage for complementary and alternative therapies. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_5">Cancer patients considering complementary and alternative therapies should discuss this decision with their doctor, nurse, or pharmacist as they would any type of treatment. Some complementary and alternative therapies may affect their standard treatment or may be harmful when used with conventional treatment. </Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_6"><Title>Evaluation of CAM Therapies</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_7">It is important that the same scientific methods used to test conventional therapies are used to test CAM therapies. The National Cancer Institute  and the National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) are sponsoring a number of clinical trials (research studies) at medical centers to test CAM therapies for use in cancer. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_8">Conventional approaches to cancer treatment have generally been studied for safety and effectiveness through a scientific process that includes clinical trials with large numbers of patients. Less is known about the safety and effectiveness of complementary and alternative methods. Few CAM therapies have been tested using demanding scientific methods. A small number of CAM therapies that were thought to be purely alternative approaches are now being used in cancer treatment—not as cures, but as complementary therapies that may help patients feel better and recover faster. One example is acupuncture. According to a panel of experts at a National Institutes of Health (NIH) meeting  in November 1997, acupuncture has been found to help control nausea and vomiting caused by chemotherapy and pain related to surgery. However, some approaches, such as the use of laetrile, have been studied and found not to work and to possibly cause harm.</Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_9"><ExternalRef xref="https://cam.cancer.gov/indentifying_novel_cam_therapies/best_case_series_program.htm">The NCI Best Case Series Program</ExternalRef>   which was started  in 1991, is one way CAM approaches that are being used in practice are being studied. The program is overseen by the NCI’s Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM). Health care professionals who offer alternative cancer therapies submit their patients’ medical records and related materials to OCCAM. OCCAM carefully reviews these materials to see if any seem worth further research.</Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_QandA_2"><Title>Questions to Ask Your Health Care Provider About CAM</Title><Para id="_QandA_3">When considering complementary and alternative therapies, patients should ask their health care provider the following questions: </Para><ItemizedList id="_QandA_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>What side effects can be expected?</ListItem><ListItem>What are the risks related to this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>What benefits can be expected from this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>Do the known benefits outweigh the risks?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy affect conventional treatment?</ListItem><ListItem>Is this therapy part of a clinical trial?</ListItem><ListItem>If so, who is the sponsor of the trial?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy be covered by health insurance?</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
   
  <SummarySection id="_ToLearnMore_2"><Title>To Learn More About CAM</Title><Para id="_ToLearnMore_3"><Strong><Emphasis>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_4">The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) facilitates research and evaluation of complementary and alternative practices, and provides information about a variety of approaches to health professionals and the public.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_5" Style="simple"><ListItem>NCCIH Clearinghouse</ListItem><ListItem>Post Office Box 7923 Gaithersburg, MD 20898–7923</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-644-6226 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and hard of hearing callers): 1-866-464-3615</ListItem><ListItem>E-mail: info@nccih.nih.gov</ListItem><ListItem>Website:  <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/">https://nccih.nih.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_15"><Strong><Emphasis>CAM on PubMed</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_16">NCCIH and the NIH National Library of Medicine (NLM) jointly developed <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/research/camonpubmed">CAM on PubMed</ExternalRef>, a free and easy-to-use search tool for finding CAM-related journal citations. As a subset of the NLM's PubMed bibliographic database, CAM on PubMed features more than 230,000 references and abstracts for CAM-related articles from scientific journals. This database also provides links to the websites of over 1,800 journals, allowing users to view full-text articles. (A subscription or other fee may be required to access full-text articles.) </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_17"><Strong><Emphasis>Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_18">The NCI Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM) coordinates the activities of the NCI in the area of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM). OCCAM supports CAM cancer research and provides information about cancer-related CAM to health providers and the general public via the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/">NCI website</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_19"><Strong><Emphasis>National Cancer Institute (NCI) Cancer Information Service</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_20">U.S. residents may call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, toll free at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237) Monday through Friday from 9:00 am to 9:00 pm. A trained Cancer Information Specialist is available to answer your questions.</Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_8"><Strong><Emphasis>Food and Drug Administration </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_9">The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulates drugs and medical devices to ensure that they are safe and effective.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_10" Style="simple"><ListItem>Food and Drug Administration </ListItem><ListItem>10903 New Hampshire Avenue</ListItem><ListItem>Silver Spring, MD 20993</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-463-6332 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/">http://www.fda.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_11"><Strong><Emphasis>Federal Trade Commission </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_12">The Federal Trade Commission (FTC) enforces consumer protection laws. Publications available from the FTC include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_13" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Emphasis>Who Cares: Sources of Information About Health Care Products and Services </Emphasis></ListItem><ListItem><Emphasis>Fraudulent Health Claims: Don’t Be Fooled </Emphasis></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_14" Style="simple"><ListItem>Consumer Response Center</ListItem><ListItem>Federal Trade Commission</ListItem><ListItem>600 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW</ListItem><ListItem>Washington, DC 20580</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-877-FTC-HELP (1-877-382-4357) (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and  hard of hearing callers): 202-326-2502</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ftc.gov/">http://www.ftc.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
  <PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000445441"/><DateFirstPublished>2006-05-11</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-04-09</DateLastModified></Summary>
