<Summary id="CDR0000548358" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatment options for children with medulloblastoma and other central nervous system embryonal tumors   include surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy, stem cell rescue, and targeted therapy. Get detailed treatment information for untreated and recurrent medulloblastoma and CNS embryonal tumors in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors  (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors  (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041539">childhood brain tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041638">childhood medulloblastoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000612114">childhood medulloepithelioma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000562070">childhood pineoblastoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_714">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood medulloblastoma and other central nervous system embryonal tumors. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_715">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood brain tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood medulloblastoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood medulloepithelioma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood nonmedulloblastoma tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood pineoblastoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other CNS Embryonal Tumors (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other CNS Embryonal Tumors</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041638">childhood medulloblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System (CNS) Embryonal Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_607"><Title>World Health Organization (WHO) Classification for CNS Embryonal Tumors and Pineoblastoma</Title><Para id="_608">  Embryonal tumors are a collection of biologically heterogeneous lesions that share the tendency to disseminate throughout  the nervous system via cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) pathways. Although there is significant variability, histologically these tumors are grouped together because they are at least partially composed of hyperchromatic cells (blue cell tumors on standard staining) with little cytoplasm, which are densely packed and demonstrate a high degree of mitotic activity.  Other histological and immunohistochemical features, such as the degree of apparent cellular transformation along identifiable cell lineages (e.g., ependymal or glial), can be used to separate these tumors to some degree.  However, a convention, which has been accepted by the WHO, also separates these tumors based on presumed location of origin within the CNS. Molecular studies have substantiated the differences between tumors arising in different areas of the brain and give partial credence to this classification approach.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_1796">In 2016, the WHO proposed an integrated phenotypic and genotypic classification system for CNS tumors in which diagnoses are layered with WHO grade, histological classification, and molecular classification.<Reference refidx="2"/> The term primitive neuroectodermal tumor (PNET) has been removed from the WHO diagnostic lexicon, although some rare entities (e.g., medulloepithelioma) have remained. A molecularly distinct entity, embryonal tumor with multilayered rosettes (ETMR), <GeneName>C19MC</GeneName>-altered, was added, encompassing embryonal tumor with abundant neuropil and true rosettes (ETANTR), ependymoblastoma, and medulloepithelioma. The WHO classification will be updated as other molecularly distinct entities are defined.</Para><Para id="_614">The pathological diagnosis of embryonal tumors is based primarily on histological and immunohistological microscopic features. However,  molecular genetic studies are employed increasingly to subclassify embryonal tumors.  These molecular genetic findings are also being used for risk stratification and treatment planning.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_609">The 2021 WHO classification of embryonal tumors is as follows:<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_2100" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1896" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Medulloblastoma</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_2101" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Medulloblastomas, molecularly defined.<ItemizedList id="_2102" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, WNT-activated.</ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, SHH-activated and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>-wild type.</ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, SHH-activated and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>-altered.</ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, non-WNT/non-SHH.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastomas, histologically defined.<ItemizedList id="_2117" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Desmoplastic nodular medulloblastoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity.</ListItem><ListItem>Large cell medulloblastoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Anaplastic medulloblastoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Other CNS embryonal tumors.<ItemizedList id="_2103" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Cribriform neuroepithelial tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Embryonal tumor with multilayered rosettes.</ListItem><ListItem>CNS neuroblastoma, <GeneName>FOXR2</GeneName>-activated.</ListItem><ListItem>CNS tumor with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> internal tandem duplication.</ListItem><ListItem>CNS embryonal tumor NEC/NOS.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_615">Pineoblastoma was previously conventionally grouped with embryonal tumors. However, it is now categorized by the WHO as a pineal parenchymal tumor.  The 2021 WHO classification of these tumors is as follows:<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_2104" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Pineocytoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Pineal parenchymal tumor of intermediate differentiation.</ListItem><ListItem>Pineoblastoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Papillary tumor of the pineal region.</ListItem><ListItem>Desmoplastic myxoid tumor of the pineal region, <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName>-altered.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2105">Given that therapies for pineoblastomas are quite similar to those for embryonal tumors, pineoblastomas are discussed in this summary.  A somewhat closely aligned tumor, pineal parenchymal tumor of intermediate differentiation (PPTID), has been identified but is not considered an embryonal tumor and primarily arises in adults.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1984"><Title>Anatomy</Title><Para id="_548"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000748659" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of the inside of the brain showing the supratentorial area (the upper part of the brain) and the posterior fossa/infratentorial area (the lower back part of the brain). The supratentorial area contains the cerebrum, lateral ventricle, third ventricle, choroid plexus, hypothalamus, pineal gland, pituitary gland, and optic nerve. The posterior fossa/infratentorial area contains the cerebellum, tectum, fourth ventricle, and brain stem (pons and medulla). The tentorium and spinal cord are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_549"><Caption language="en">Figure 1.  Anatomy of the inside of the brain, showing the pineal and pituitary glands, optic nerve, ventricles (with cerebrospinal fluid shown in blue), and other parts of the brain. The posterior fossa is the region below the tentorium, which separates the cortex from the cerebellum and essentially denotes the region containing the brain stem, cerebellum, and fourth ventricle.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_541"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_542">Embryonal tumors account for approximately 20% of primary CNS tumors (malignant CNS neoplasms and pilocytic astrocytomas) arising in children. These tumors occur along the pediatric age spectrum but tend to cluster early in life. The incidence of embryonal tumors in children aged 1 to 9 years  is fivefold to tenfold higher than in adults (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_662" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> </Para><Table id="_662"><Title>Table 1.  Annual Incidence Rates for Childhood Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors According to Age<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Age Group (y)	</entry><entry>Annual Incidence Rate (Cases per 1 Million)</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Source: National Childhood Cancer Registry.<Reference refidx="9"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>&lt;5</entry><entry>10</entry></Row><Row><entry>5–9</entry><entry>7</entry></Row><Row><entry>10–19</entry><entry>2–3</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_632">Medulloblastomas comprise the vast majority of pediatric embryonal tumors. By definition, they arise in the posterior fossa (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_549" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Figure 1</SummaryRef>), where they constitute approximately 40% of all posterior fossa tumors.  Other forms of embryonal tumors each make up 2% or less of all childhood brain tumors.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_307"><Title>Diagnostic and Staging Evaluation</Title><Para id="_1985">Imaging studies and CSF analysis are included in the diagnostic and staging evaluation.</Para><SummarySection id="_1986"><Title>Imaging studies</Title><Para id="_1987">Diagnosis is usually made by either magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) scan.  MRI is preferable because the anatomical relationship between the tumor and surrounding brain and tumor dissemination is better visualized with this method.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_635">After diagnosis, evaluation of embryonal tumors is quite similar, essentially independent of the histological subtype and the location of the tumor.  Given the tendency of these tumors to disseminate throughout  the CNS early in the course of illness, imaging evaluation of the neuraxis by MRI of the entire brain and spine is indicated.  Preferably, this is done before surgery to avoid postoperative artifacts, especially blood.  Such imaging can be difficult to interpret and must be performed in at least two planes, with and without the use of contrast enhancement (gadolinium).<Reference refidx="13"/> A study of the significance of equivocal findings on spinal MRIs in children with medulloblastoma identified equivocal findings in 48 of 100 patients (48%). The study reported the following results:<Reference refidx="14"/>   </Para><ItemizedList id="_1988" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Analysis by subgroup identified a higher proportion of equivocal findings in the SHH subgroup (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .007). </ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year overall survival (OS) rate in children with equivocal MRI findings (80%) was not different from the 5-year OS in patients who had normal MRI findings (84.8%), while OS in patients with M3 metastases was worse (54.7%) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1989">In contrast, a Children's Oncology Group (COG) prospective study treated over 400 children without metastatic disease with a reduced dose (23.4 Gy) of craniospinal radiation therapy. Nearly 20% of patients with central neuroradiographic review were found to have either evidence of possible excessive residual disease and/or metastatic disease or were considered to have imaging inadequate to fully evaluate the neuroaxis. For patients with centrally reviewed imaging, children considered to have metastatic disease had poor OS compared with those with nondisseminated disease. The subgroup found to have inadequate imaging by central review had an intermediate survival rate between the children with adequate imaging and those who had metastatic disease.<Reference refidx="13"/> In a subsequent prospective COG study that treated over 500 children with reduced-dose craniospinal radiation therapy (23.4 Gy or 18 Gy), patients with inadequate imaging had poorer survival.<Reference refidx="15"/> Consensus guidelines for timing and neuroimaging techniques have been recommended and include details that outline standards for preoperative assessment of the entire neuroaxis and postoperative assessment of the amount of residual disease.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_1990">After surgery, imaging of the primary tumor site is indicated to determine the extent of residual disease.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1991"><Title>CSF analysis</Title><Para id="_569">After surgery, lumbar CSF analysis is performed, if deemed safe.  Neuroimaging and CSF evaluation are considered complementary because as many as 10% of patients have evidence of free-floating tumor cells in the CSF without clear evidence of leptomeningeal disease on MRI scan.<Reference refidx="17"/>    </Para><Para id="_1992">CSF analysis is conventionally done 14 to 21 days after surgery.  If CSF is obtained within 14 days of the operation, detection of tumor cells within the spinal fluid is possibly related to the surgical procedure.  In most staging systems, if fluid is obtained in the first few days after surgery and found to be positive for tumor cells, the positivity must be confirmed by a subsequent spinal tap to be considered diagnostically significant.  In contrast, if CSF is negative for tumor cells at that time, then no confirmation is needed. When obtaining fluid by lumbar spinal tap is deemed unsafe, ventricular fluid can be obtained. However, this method may not be as sensitive as lumbar fluid assessment.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_627">Because embryonal tumors are very rarely metastatic to the bone, bone marrow, or other body sites at the time of diagnosis, studies such as bone marrow aspirates, chest x-rays, or bone scans are not indicated, unless there are symptoms or signs suggesting organ involvement.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_309"><Title>Prognostic Factors</Title><Para id="_391">Various clinical and biological parameters have been associated with the likelihood of disease control of embryonal tumors after treatment.<Reference refidx="4"/> Many of these factors have been shown to be predictive for medulloblastomas, although some are used to assign risk, to some degree, for other embryonal tumors. Parameters that are most frequently used to predict outcome include the following:<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_414" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_416" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Extent of CNS disease at diagnosis</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_419" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Age at diagnosis</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_576" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Amount of residual disease after definitive surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_421" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Tumor histopathology</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_423" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Biological/molecular tumor cell characteristics</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_621">It has become increasingly clear, especially for medulloblastomas, that outcome is also related to the molecular characteristics of the tumor, but this has not been definitively shown for other embryonal tumors.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/>  OS rates range from 30%   to 90%, depending on the molecular subtype of the medulloblastoma, extent of dissemination at time of diagnosis, and possibly other factors, such as the degree of resection. Children with medulloblastoma who survive for 5 years are considered cured of their tumor.  Survival rates for other embryonal tumors are generally poorer, ranging from less than 5% to 50%. Specific survival rates are discussed within each subgroup in the summary.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_574">In older studies, the presence of brain stem involvement in children with medulloblastoma was found to be a prognostic factor. It  has not been found to be of predictive value in subsequent studies that treated patients with both radiation and chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_1832">An accurate diagnosis is critical for patients with embryonal tumors.  For example, in the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00392327">ACNS0332 (NCT00392327)</ProtocolRef> trial that enrolled 80 patients with high-risk medulloblastoma, supratentorial CNS-PNET tumors, and pineoblastoma, 60 patients had sufficient tissue for evaluation. Thirty-one tumors were nonpineal in location, 22  (71%)  of which represented tumors that were not intended for trial inclusion, including 18 high-grade gliomas, 2 atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors, and 2 ependymomas. Outcomes across tumor types were strikingly different. Patients with supratentorial embryonal tumors/pineoblastomas exhibited a 5-year event-free survival (EFS) rate of 62.8% (95% confidence interval [CI], 43.4%–82.2%) and an OS rate of 78.5% (95% CI, 62.2%–94.8%), whereas patients with molecularly classified high-grade gliomas had a 5-year EFS rate of 5.6% (95% CI, 0%–13%) and an OS rate of 12% (95% CI, 0%–24.7%). Survival rates for patients with high-grade gliomas were similar to those of patients who were enrolled in historical studies that avoided craniospinal irradiation and intensive chemotherapy.  Thus, for patients with CNS-PNET/pineoblastoma, prognosis is considerably better than previously assumed when molecularly confirmed high-grade gliomas are removed.<Reference refidx="28"/></Para><Para id="_512">Prognosis is poor for patients with medulloepithelioma and ETMR, with 5-year survival rates ranging between 0% and 30%.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/> In a retrospective multivariate analysis of 38 patients, total or near-total resection, the use of radiation therapy, and the use of high-dose chemotherapy were associated with an improved prognosis.<Reference refidx="32"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] Another retrospective analysis included 159 patients with confirmed molecular diagnoses of primary ETMRs from the Rare Brain Tumor Registry (median age at diagnosis, 26 months; IQR, 18–36 months). The study revealed an EFS rate of 57% (95% CI, 47%–68%) at 6 months and 31% (95% CI, 21%–42%) at 2 years. The OS rate was 29% (95% CI, 20%–38%) at 2 years and 27% (95% CI, 18%–37%) at 4 years. OS was associated with nonmetastatic disease (hazard ratio [HR], 0.48; 95% CI, 0.28–0.80; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0057) and nonbrainstem location (HR, 0.42; 95% CI, 0.22–0.81; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .013) on univariate analysis, as well as with gross-total resection (HR, 0.30; 95% CI, 0.16–0.58; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0014), use of high-dose chemotherapy (HR, 0.35; 95% CI, 0.19–0.67; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0020), and use of radiation therapy (HR, 0.21; 95% CI, 0.10–0.41; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) on multivariable analysis.<Reference refidx="33"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><SummarySection id="_416"><Title>Extent of CNS disease at diagnosis</Title><Para id="_417">Patients with disseminated CNS disease at diagnosis are at highest risk of disease relapse.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/> Ten percent to 40% of patients with medulloblastoma have CNS dissemination at diagnosis. Infants have the highest incidence and adolescents and adults have the lowest incidence of CNS dissemination.</Para><Para id="_418">Nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors and pineoblastomas may also be disseminated at the time of diagnosis, although the incidence may be somewhat less than for medulloblastomas, with dissemination at diagnosis in approximately 10% to 20% of patients.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/>    Patients with nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors and pineoblastomas who have disseminated disease at the time of diagnosis have a poor OS, with reported survival rates at 5 years ranging from 10% to 30%.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="34"/>  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_419"><Title>Age at diagnosis</Title><Para id="_575">Age younger than 3 years at diagnosis portends an unfavorable outcome for those with medulloblastoma and, possibly, other embryonal tumors.<Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/>  The exception is for those diagnosed with desmoplastic medulloblastoma/medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity (MBEN).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_576"><Title>Amount of residual disease after definitive surgery</Title><Para id="_636">As a predictor of outcome, postoperative MRI measurement of the amount of residual disease after definitive surgery has been supplanted by extent of resection after surgery.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_577">In older studies, the extent of resection for medulloblastomas was found to be related to survival.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/>  A Hirntumor and International Society of Paediatric Oncology study of 340 children reported that residual disease (&gt;1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript>) connoted a poorer 5-year EFS rate.<Reference refidx="43"/> Extent of resection after surgery is still used to separate patients into risk groups, with patients having more than 1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of residual disease stratified into high-risk groups, with intensification of craniospinal irradiation to 36 Gy. </Para><Para id="_1994">An international, retrospective, collaborative study included 787 patients of all ages with medulloblastoma who were treated in a variety of ways. The study incorporated molecular subgrouping and clinical factors in the analysis. The multivariate analysis found that subtotal resection (&gt;1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> residual), but not near-total resection (&lt;1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> residual), was associated with inferior progression-free survival compared with gross-total resection. This study suggested that attempts to completely remove the tumor, especially when the likelihood of neurological morbidity is high, are not warranted because there appears to be little or no benefit to gross-total resection when compared with near-total resection.  It gives some credence to the present approach, in which patients with more than 1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of disease are considered higher-risk patients.<Reference refidx="44"/> In a retrospective analysis of 1,100 patients with molecularly characterized medulloblastoma, subtotal resection was associated with worse survival in univariable analysis (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001). However, subtotal resection was not independently prognostic in multivariable analyses and not prognostic in patients who did not have metastatic disease and received up-front craniospinal irradiation.<Reference refidx="45"/> Prospective studies are needed to better define the impact of extent of resection on outcome within molecularly defined subgroups.</Para><Para id="_578">In patients with other forms of embryonal tumors, the extent of resection has not been definitively shown to impact survival.<Reference refidx="26"/> However, in a COG study of 66 children with supratentorial embryonal tumors, extent of resection was found to be prognostic for those with localized disease at the time of diagnosis.<Reference refidx="46"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_421"><Title>Tumor histopathology</Title><Para id="_422"><Strong>For medulloblastomas</Strong>, histopathological  features such as large cell variant, anaplasia, and desmoplasia have been shown in retrospective analyses to correlate with outcome.<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/>  In prospective studies, immunohistochemical and histopathological findings have not predicted outcome in children older than 3 years at diagnosis, with the exception of the large cell/anaplastic variant, which has been associated with poorer prognosis.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="49"/> Several studies have observed that the histological finding of desmoplasia, seen in patients aged 3 years and younger with desmoplastic medulloblastoma, especially MBEN,  connotes a significantly better prognosis compared with outcomes for infants and young children with classic or large cell/anaplastic medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="50"/>; <Reference refidx="38"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]  Within the SHH group with <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants, both somatic and constitutional (called Li-Fraumeni syndrome) <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants may occur. Both of these variants connote a poor prognosis, compared with other SHH pathway–activated tumors.<Reference refidx="23"/></Para><Para id="_628"><Strong>For other embryonal tumors</Strong>, histological variations have not been associated with differing outcomes.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_423"><Title>Biological/molecular tumor cell characteristics</Title><SummarySection id="_2118"><Title>Measure of minimal residual disease</Title><Para id="_2119">In one study, CSF copy number variations, similar to those found in the primary tumors, were prognostic of relapse when present after radiation therapy or during or after chemotherapy. If this finding is replicated in prospective clinical trials and the technique becomes available, it will be an important measure of minimal residual disease and likely will become part of the baseline evaluation, as well as part of surveillance testing.<Reference refidx="51"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2120"><Title>Genomic analyses</Title><Para id="_617"><Strong>For medulloblastoma</Strong>, genomic analyses (including RNA gene expression and DNA methylation profiles, as well as DNA sequencing to identify variants) on both fresh-frozen and formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded sections, have identified molecular subtypes.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/><Reference refidx="55"/><Reference refidx="56"/><Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="59"/> These subtypes include those characterized by WNT pathway activation and SHH pathway activation, as well as additional subgroups characterized by <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> or <GeneName>MYCN</GeneName> alterations and other genomic alterations.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/><Reference refidx="55"/><Reference refidx="56"/><Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="58"/> Children with medulloblastoma whose tumors show WNT pathway activation usually have an excellent prognosis. Within the non-WNT, non-SHH medulloblastoma group, there are subsets of patients with differing prognoses. For example, patients  with chromosome 11 loss have an excellent prognosis, similar to  those with WNT tumors.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="60"/><Reference refidx="61"/> Patients with SHH pathway–activated tumors have a prognosis that is influenced by the presence or absence of <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants (favorable vs. unfavorable prognosis, respectively).<Reference refidx="61"/>  The outcome for the remaining patients is less favorable than for patients with WNT  pathway activation. Variants in medulloblastoma are observed in a subtype-specific manner. <GeneName>CTNNB1</GeneName> variants are observed in most WNT-subtype tumors. <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>SMO</GeneName>, and <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName> variants are observed in the SHH-subtype tumors.  The prognostic significance of recurring variants is closely aligned with that of the molecular subtype with which they are associated.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="62"/> At recurrence, the subtype remains unchanged from the original molecular subtype at diagnosis.<Reference refidx="63"/></Para><Para id="_630"><Strong>For nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors</Strong>, integrative genomic analysis has also identified molecular subtypes with different outcomes.  For more detailed information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1950" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Subtypes of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_572"><Title>Follow-Up After Treatment</Title><Para id="_580">Relapse in children with embryonal tumors is most likely to occur within the first 18 months of diagnosis.<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="64"/>  Surveillance imaging of the brain and spine is usually undertaken at routine intervals during and after treatment (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_631" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>). The frequency of such imaging, designed to detect recurrent disease at an early, asymptomatic state, has been arbitrarily determined and has not been shown to clearly influence survival.<Reference refidx="65"/><Reference refidx="66"/><Reference refidx="67"/><Reference refidx="68"/> Growth hormone replacement therapy has not been shown to increase the likelihood of disease relapse and should not impact the frequency of surveillance testing.<Reference refidx="37"/></Para><Table id="_631"><Title>Table 2.  Surveillance Testing During and After Treatment for Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Surveillance Period	</entry><entry>Frequency of Visits During Surveillance Period</entry><entry>Testing</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">MRI = magnetic resonance imaging.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For pineoblastoma, continue spinal evaluations every 6 months until 5 years from diagnosis. Although these suggestions are based on a small sample size, there is evidence for continuing surveillance testing of the spine until 5 years after diagnosis.<Reference refidx="69"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="3">First 3 years after diagnosis	</entry><entry MoreRows="3">Every 3 months	</entry><entry>Physical examination
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Imaging of the brain every 3 months for the first 3 years, then every 6 months for the ensuing 2 years, and then as per preference of the treating physician or per protocol; MRI of the spine every 3 months for the first 2 years, then every 6 months for 1 year, and then as per  preference of the treating physician or per protocol<Superscript>a</Superscript>

</entry></Row><Row><entry>Endocrinology evaluation once a year
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Neuropsychological testing every 1–2 years</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">3–5 years after diagnosis	</entry><entry MoreRows="3">Every 6 months	</entry><entry>Physical examination
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Imaging of the brain and spine once a year

</entry></Row><Row><entry>Endocrinology evaluation once a year </entry></Row><Row><entry>Neuropsychological testing every 1–2 years</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">More than 5 years after diagnosis	</entry><entry MoreRows="3">Once a year	</entry><entry>Physical examination
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Imaging of the brain once a year
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Endocrinology evaluation once a year
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Neuropsychological testing every 1–2 years (optional)
</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_2121">The development of surveillance strategies other than imaging for patients with medulloblastoma is the subject of ongoing research. In one study of 134 children with newly diagnosed medulloblastoma, copy number variants were detected at baseline in 123 patients (92%) by primary tumor testing and in 65 patients (49%) by CSF testing. Copy number variants were detected more frequently in the CSF of patients with disseminated disease and in those with subsequent progression. Prospective studies will be necessary to evaluate the potential for CSF copy number analysis to become a component of surveillance testing, as a measure of medulloblastoma minimal residual disease and early relapse.<Reference refidx="51"/></Para><Para id="_1993">Childhood and adolescent cancer survivors require close monitoring because cancer therapy side effects may persist or develop months or years after treatment. For specific information about the incidence, type, and monitoring of late effects in childhood and adolescent cancer survivors, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343584" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-hp-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11807556" MedlineID="21666525">Pomeroy SL, Tamayo P, Gaasenbeek M, et al.: Prediction of central nervous system embryonal tumour outcome based on gene expression. Nature 415 (6870): 436-42, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="27157931">Louis DN, Perry A, Reifenberger G, et al.: The 2016 World Health Organization Classification of Tumors of the Central Nervous System: a summary. Acta Neuropathol 131 (6): 803-20, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19255330">Pfister S, Remke M, Benner A, et al.: Outcome prediction in pediatric medulloblastoma based on DNA copy-number aberrations of chromosomes 6q and 17q and the MYC and MYCN loci. J Clin Oncol 27 (10): 1627-36, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="22134537">Taylor MD, Northcott PA, Korshunov A, et al.: Molecular subgroups of medulloblastoma: the current consensus. Acta Neuropathol 123 (4): 465-72, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18769486">Kool M, Koster J, Bunt J, et al.: Integrated genomics identifies five medulloblastoma subtypes with distinct genetic profiles, pathway signatures and clinicopathological features. PLoS One 3 (8): e3088, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16258095">Ellison DW, Onilude OE, Lindsey JC, et al.: beta-Catenin status predicts a favorable outcome in childhood medulloblastoma: the United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group Brain Tumour Committee. J Clin Oncol 23 (31): 7951-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="7">WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board, ed.: WHO Classification of Tumours: Central Nervous System Tumours. Vol. 6. 5th ed. IARC Press; 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="34185076">Louis DN, Perry A, Wesseling P, et al.: The 2021 WHO Classification of Tumors of the Central Nervous System: a summary. Neuro Oncol 23 (8): 1231-1251, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="9">National Cancer Institute: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://NCCRExplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Surveillance Research Program, National Cancer Institute: SEER*Explorer: An interactive website for SEER cancer statistics. 	Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statistics-network/explorer/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="11">Chintagumpala MM, Paulino A, Panigrahy A, et al.: Embryonal and pineal region tumors. In: Pizzo PA, Poplack DG, eds.: Principles and Practice of Pediatric Oncology. 7th ed. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2015, pp 671-99.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="36519599">Jaju A, Li Y, Dahmoush H, et al.: Imaging of pediatric brain tumors: A COG Diagnostic Imaging Committee/SPR Oncology Committee/ASPNR White Paper. Pediatr Blood Cancer 70 Suppl 4 (Suppl 4): e30147, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16943538">Packer RJ, Gajjar A, Vezina G, et al.: Phase III study of craniospinal radiation therapy followed by adjuvant chemotherapy for newly diagnosed average-risk medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 24 (25): 4202-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="28205381">Bennett J, Ashmawy R, Ramaswamy V, et al.: The clinical significance of equivocal findings on spinal MRI in children with medulloblastoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 64 (8): , 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="34110925">Michalski JM, Janss AJ, Vezina LG, et al.: Children's Oncology Group Phase III Trial of Reduced-Dose and Reduced-Volume Radiotherapy With Chemotherapy for Newly Diagnosed Average-Risk Medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 39 (24): 2685-2697, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="28449033">Warren KE, Vezina G, Poussaint TY, et al.: Response assessment in medulloblastoma and leptomeningeal seeding tumors: recommendations from the Response Assessment in Pediatric Neuro-Oncology committee. Neuro Oncol 20 (1): 13-23, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="10506624" MedlineID="99438194">Fouladi M, Gajjar A, Boyett JM, et al.: Comparison of CSF cytology and spinal magnetic resonance imaging in the detection of leptomeningeal disease in pediatric medulloblastoma or primitive neuroectodermal tumor. J Clin Oncol 17 (10): 3234-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="10071274">Zeltzer PM, Boyett JM, Finlay JL, et al.: Metastasis stage, adjuvant treatment, and residual tumor are prognostic factors for medulloblastoma in children: conclusions from the Children's Cancer Group 921 randomized phase III study. J Clin Oncol 17 (3): 832-45, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="9231668" MedlineID="97375351">Yao MS, Mehta MP, Boyett JM, et al.: The effect of M-stage on patterns of failure in posterior fossa primitive neuroectodermal tumors treated on CCG-921: a phase III study in a high-risk patient population. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 38 (3): 469-76, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="16567768">Thompson MC, Fuller C, Hogg TL, et al.: Genomics identifies medulloblastoma subgroups that are enriched for specific genetic alterations. J Clin Oncol 24 (12): 1924-31, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="20823417">Northcott PA, Korshunov A, Witt H, et al.: Medulloblastoma comprises four distinct molecular variants. J Clin Oncol 29 (11): 1408-14, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="20940197">Rutkowski S, von Hoff K, Emser A, et al.: Survival and prognostic factors of early childhood medulloblastoma: an international meta-analysis. J Clin Oncol 28 (33): 4961-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="37379234">Kolodziejczak AS, Guerrini-Rousseau L, Planchon JM, et al.: Clinical outcome of pediatric medulloblastoma patients with Li-Fraumeni syndrome. Neuro Oncol 25 (12): 2273-2286, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="7602359" MedlineID="95325887">Cohen BH, Zeltzer PM, Boyett JM, et al.: Prognostic factors and treatment results for supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors in children using radiation and chemotherapy: a Childrens Cancer Group randomized trial. J Clin Oncol 13 (7): 1687-96, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="10813733" MedlineID="20273504">Reddy AT, Janss AJ, Phillips PC, et al.: Outcome for children with supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors treated with surgery, radiation, and chemotherapy. Cancer 88 (9): 2189-93, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="11821469" MedlineID="21679506">Timmermann B, Kortmann RD, Kühl J, et al.: Role of radiotherapy in the treatment of supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors in childhood: results of the prospective German brain tumor trials HIT 88/89 and 91. J Clin Oncol 20 (3): 842-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="7751882" MedlineID="95271259">Jakacki RI, Zeltzer PM, Boyett JM, et al.: Survival and prognostic factors following radiation and/or chemotherapy for primitive neuroectodermal tumors of the pineal region in infants and children: a report of the Childrens Cancer Group. J Clin Oncol 13 (6): 1377-83, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="30332335">Hwang EI, Kool M, Burger PC, et al.: Extensive Molecular and Clinical Heterogeneity in Patients With Histologically Diagnosed CNS-PNET Treated as a Single Entity: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group Randomized ACNS0332 Trial. J Clin Oncol : JCO2017764720, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="17618441">Louis DN, Ohgaki H, Wiestler OD, et al.: The 2007 WHO classification of tumours of the central nervous system. Acta Neuropathol 114 (2): 97-109, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="9548346">Sharma MC, Mahapatra AK, Gaikwad S, et al.: Pigmented medulloepithelioma: report of a case and review of the literature. Childs Nerv Syst 14 (1-2): 74-8, 1998 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="22037651">Müller K, Zwiener I, Welker H, et al.: Curative treatment for central nervous system medulloepithelioma despite residual disease after resection. Report of two cases treated according to the GPHO Protocol HIT 2000 and review of the literature. Strahlenther Onkol 187 (11): 757-62, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="26438544">Horwitz M, Dufour C, Leblond P, et al.: Embryonal tumors with multilayered rosettes in children: the SFCE experience. Childs Nerv Syst 32 (2): 299-305, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="34599879">Khan S, Solano-Paez P, Suwal T, et al.: Clinical phenotypes and prognostic features of embryonal tumours with multi-layered rosettes: a Rare Brain Tumor Registry study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health 5 (11): 800-813, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="35664557">Hansford JR, Huang J, Endersby R, et al.: Pediatric pineoblastoma: A pooled outcome study of North American and Australian therapeutic data. Neurooncol Adv 4 (1): vdac056, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="21246528">Leary SE, Zhou T, Holmes E, et al.: Histology predicts a favorable outcome in young children with desmoplastic medulloblastoma: a report from the children's oncology group. Cancer 117 (14): 3262-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="10584843">Giangaspero F, Perilongo G, Fondelli MP, et al.: Medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity: a variant with favorable prognosis. J Neurosurg 91 (6): 971-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="21636711">von Bueren AO, von Hoff K, Pietsch T, et al.: Treatment of young children with localized medulloblastoma by chemotherapy alone: results of the prospective, multicenter trial HIT 2000 confirming the prognostic impact of histology. Neuro Oncol 13 (6): 669-79, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="18818397">Rutkowski S, Gerber NU, von Hoff K, et al.: Treatment of early childhood medulloblastoma by postoperative chemotherapy and deferred radiotherapy. Neuro Oncol 11 (2): 201-10, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="15758008">Rutkowski S, Bode U, Deinlein F, et al.: Treatment of early childhood medulloblastoma by postoperative chemotherapy alone. N Engl J Med 352 (10): 978-86, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="28011926">Mynarek M, Pizer B, Dufour C, et al.: Evaluation of age-dependent treatment strategies for children and young adults with pineoblastoma: analysis of pooled European Society for Paediatric Oncology (SIOP-E) and US Head Start data. Neuro Oncol 19 (4): 576-585, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="8869053" MedlineID="97022693">Albright AL, Wisoff JH, Zeltzer PM, et al.: Effects of medulloblastoma resections on outcome in children: a report from the Children's Cancer Group. Neurosurgery 38 (2): 265-71, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="12697884">Taylor RE, Bailey CC, Robinson K, et al.: Results of a randomized study of preradiation chemotherapy versus radiotherapy alone for nonmetastatic medulloblastoma: The International Society of Paediatric Oncology/United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group PNET-3 Study. J Clin Oncol 21 (8): 1581-91, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="22851561">Lannering B, Rutkowski S, Doz F, et al.: Hyperfractionated versus conventional radiotherapy followed by chemotherapy in standard-risk medulloblastoma: results from the randomized multicenter HIT-SIOP PNET 4 trial. J Clin Oncol 30 (26): 3187-93, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="26976201">Thompson EM, Hielscher T, Bouffet E, et al.: Prognostic value of medulloblastoma extent of resection after accounting for molecular subgroup: a retrospective integrated clinical and molecular analysis. Lancet Oncol 17 (4): 484-95, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="38374970">Keeling C, Davies S, Goddard J, et al.: The clinical significance of sub-total surgical resection in childhood medulloblastoma: a multi-cohort analysis of 1100 patients. EClinicalMedicine 69: 102469, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="25704363">Jakacki RI, Burger PC, Kocak M, et al.: Outcome and prognostic factors for children with supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors treated with carboplatin during radiotherapy: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (5): 776-83, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="12834107">McManamy CS, Lamont JM, Taylor RE, et al.: Morphophenotypic variation predicts clinical behavior in childhood non-desmoplastic medulloblastomas. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 62 (6): 627-32, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="22693015">Massimino M, Antonelli M, Gandola L, et al.: Histological variants of medulloblastoma are the most powerful clinical prognostic indicators. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (2): 210-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="15198123">Eberhart CG, Kratz J, Wang Y, et al.: Histopathological and molecular prognostic markers in medulloblastoma: c-myc, N-myc, TrkC, and anaplasia. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 63 (5): 441-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="19276247">Garrè ML, Cama A, Bagnasco F, et al.: Medulloblastoma variants: age-dependent occurrence and relation to Gorlin syndrome--a new clinical perspective. Clin Cancer Res 15 (7): 2463-71, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="34678152">Liu APY, Smith KS, Kumar R, et al.: Serial assessment of measurable residual disease in medulloblastoma liquid biopsies. Cancer Cell 39 (11): 1519-1530.e4, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="20142599">Tabori U, Baskin B, Shago M, et al.: Universal poor survival in children with medulloblastoma harboring somatic TP53 mutations. J Clin Oncol 28 (8): 1345-50, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="20420498">Onvani S, Etame AB, Smith CA, et al.: Genetics of medulloblastoma: clues for novel therapies. Expert Rev Neurother 10 (5): 811-23, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="20425037">Dubuc AM, Northcott PA, Mack S, et al.: The genetics of pediatric brain tumors. Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep 10 (3): 215-23, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="16685513">Giangaspero F, Wellek S, Masuoka J, et al.: Stratification of medulloblastoma on the basis of histopathological grading. Acta Neuropathol 112 (1): 5-12, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="22832583">Jones DT, Jäger N, Kool M, et al.: Dissecting the genomic complexity underlying medulloblastoma. Nature 488 (7409): 100-5, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="22147459">Peyrl A, Chocholous M, Kieran MW, et al.: Antiangiogenic metronomic therapy for children with recurrent embryonal brain tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 59 (3): 511-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="22358457">Kool M, Korshunov A, Remke M, et al.: Molecular subgroups of medulloblastoma: an international meta-analysis of transcriptome, genetic aberrations, and clinical data of WNT, SHH, Group 3, and Group 4 medulloblastomas. Acta Neuropathol 123 (4): 473-84, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="23291781">Schwalbe EC, Williamson D, Lindsey JC, et al.: DNA methylation profiling of medulloblastoma allows robust subclassification and improved outcome prediction using formalin-fixed biopsies. Acta Neuropathol 125 (3): 359-71, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="24493713">Shih DJ, Northcott PA, Remke M, et al.: Cytogenetic prognostication within medulloblastoma subgroups. J Clin Oncol 32 (9): 886-96, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="30392813">Goschzik T, Schwalbe EC, Hicks D, et al.: Prognostic effect of whole chromosomal aberration signatures in standard-risk, non-WNT/non-SHH medulloblastoma: a retrospective, molecular analysis of the HIT-SIOP PNET 4 trial. Lancet Oncol 19 (12): 1602-1616, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="17464337">Polkinghorn WR, Tarbell NJ: Medulloblastoma: tumorigenesis, current clinical paradigm, and efforts to improve risk stratification. Nat Clin Pract Oncol 4 (5): 295-304, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="24140199">Ramaswamy V, Remke M, Bouffet E, et al.: Recurrence patterns across medulloblastoma subgroups: an integrated clinical and molecular analysis. Lancet Oncol 14 (12): 1200-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="23099653">Packer RJ, Zhou T, Holmes E, et al.: Survival and secondary tumors in children with medulloblastoma receiving radiotherapy and adjuvant chemotherapy: results of Children's Oncology Group trial A9961. Neuro Oncol 15 (1): 97-103, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="9164189">Shaw DW, Geyer JR, Berger MS, et al.: Asymptomatic recurrence detection with surveillance scanning in children with medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 15 (5): 1811-3, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="8114859" MedlineID="94159012">Torres CF, Rebsamen S, Silber JH, et al.: Surveillance scanning of children with medulloblastoma. N Engl J Med 330 (13): 892-5, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="8043464" MedlineID="94318502">Kramer ED, Vezina LG, Packer RJ, et al.: Staging and surveillance of children with central nervous system neoplasms: recommendations of the Neurology and Tumor Imaging Committees of the Children's Cancer Group. Pediatr Neurosurg 20 (4): 254-62; discussion 262-3, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="27423645">Sabel M, Fleischhack G, Tippelt S, et al.: Relapse patterns and outcome after relapse in standard risk medulloblastoma: a report from the HIT-SIOP-PNET4 study. J Neurooncol 129 (3): 515-524, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="24401959">Perreault S, Lober RM, Carret AS, et al.: Surveillance imaging in children with malignant CNS tumors: low yield of spine MRI. J Neurooncol 116 (3): 617-23, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1867"><Title>Childhood Medulloblastoma</Title><SummarySection id="_1876"><Title>Hereditary Cancer Predisposition Syndromes Associated With Medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_2045">Increasingly, subsets of children with brain tumors, including medulloblastoma, have been found to have germline pathogenic or likely pathogenic variants, predisposing them to the development of medulloblastoma and other cancers.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> These variants have obvious implications for the affected child, siblings, parents, and, potentially, other family members in regard to cancer surveillance, prevention, diagnosis, and management. The variants may also affect specific tumor treatment.</Para><Para id="_1877">Medulloblastoma can arise in the setting of hereditary cancer predisposition syndromes in approximately 5% of patients.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> A large study of over 1,000 patients demonstrated germline pathogenic variants in approximately 5% of all patients diagnosed with medulloblastoma. Germline pathogenic variants were identified in <GeneName>APC</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName>, and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_1878"> Syndromes known to be associated with medulloblastoma include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1879" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Turcot syndrome (related to germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>APC</GeneName>),<Reference refidx="3"/> exclusive to the WNT-activated subtype.<Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem>Rubinstein-Taybi syndrome (related to germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>CREBBP</GeneName>).<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem>Gorlin syndrome (also known as basal cell nevus syndrome or nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome, associated with germline <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> and <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName> pathogenic variants).<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> The risk of developing medulloblastoma in patients with Gorlin syndrome appears to be higher in those with germline <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName> variants than in those with <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> pathogenic  variants. In one study, 2 of 115 individuals (1.7%) with Gorlin syndrome and a <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> variant developed a pathology-proven medulloblastoma, compared with 3 of 9 individuals (33%) from three families with <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName>-related Gorlin syndrome. Each of the <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName>-related patients developed medulloblastoma before age 3 years.<Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem><ListItem>Li-Fraumeni syndrome is related to germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> Germline <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> pathogenic variants are restricted to the sonic hedgehog (SHH)–activated subtype.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem>Fanconi anemia (related to <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> variants).<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2046">Heterozygous deleterious germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName> were identified in approximately 3% of cases of SHH medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="19"/> <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName> is an inhibitor of SHH signaling. The median age at diagnosis for patients with <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName> variants was 1.5 years. Loss of heterozygosity (LOH) at the GPR161 locus was noted in all tumors, with tumors from five of six patients showing copy-neutral LOH of chromosome 1q (on which <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName> resides). The risk of nonmedulloblastoma cancers in patients with deleterious <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName> variants is not defined.</Para><Para id="_2092">Novel germline loss-of-function pathogenic variants in the largest subunit of the evolutionarily conserved Elongator complex, <GeneName>ELP1</GeneName>, were identified in 14% of pediatric patients with SHH medulloblastoma. <GeneName>ELP1</GeneName> was the most common medulloblastoma predisposition gene, and it increased the prevalence of genetic predisposition to 40% among pediatric patients with SHH medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_1880">Sometimes medulloblastoma may be the initial manifestation of germline pathogenic variants in these predisposition genes.  Germline testing should be considered in the following circumstances:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1881" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GeneName>APC</GeneName> variant testing in patients with WNT-activated medulloblastoma in the absence of a somatic <GeneName>CTNNB1</GeneName> variant.</ListItem><ListItem><GeneName>SUFU</GeneName>, <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> variant testing in patients with SHH-activated medulloblastoma. Patients with desmoplastic tumors with extensive nodularity should be carefully evaluated for stigmata of Gorlin syndrome.<Reference refidx="7"/>  One report observed that medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity (MBEN) was associated with Gorlin syndrome in 5 of 12 cases.<Reference refidx="7"/> Gorlin syndrome is an autosomal dominant disorder in which those affected are predisposed to develop basal cell carcinomas later in life, especially in skin in the radiation portal. The syndrome can be diagnosed early in life by detection of characteristic dermatological and skeletal features such as keratocysts of the jaw, bifid or fused ribs, macrocephaly, and calcifications of the falx.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem><ListItem><GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> variant testing in patients with a family history of <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName>-associated cancers or homologous recombination repair deficiency.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2204">Given the high frequency of underlying germline pathogenic or likely pathogenic variants associated with SHH medulloblastoma, all patients with this disease should be referred for genetic counseling.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1868"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_1869">By definition, medulloblastomas arise in the posterior fossa.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/>  In approximately 80% of children, medulloblastomas arise in the region of the fourth ventricle. Most of the early symptomatology is related to blockage of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and resultant accumulation of CSF in the brain, termed hydrocephalus. Children with medulloblastoma are usually diagnosed within 2 to 3 months of the onset of symptoms. Medulloblastoma commonly presents with the following signs and symptoms:<Reference refidx="23"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_1870" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Relatively abrupt onset of headaches, especially in the morning on waking.</ListItem><ListItem>Nausea and/or vomiting.</ListItem><ListItem>Lethargy.</ListItem><ListItem>Ataxia, including truncal unsteadiness.</ListItem><ListItem>Some degree of nystagmus.</ListItem><ListItem>Papilledema.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1871">Twenty percent of patients with medulloblastoma will not have hydrocephalus at the time of diagnosis and are more likely to present initially with cerebellar deficits.  For example, more laterally positioned medulloblastomas of the cerebellum may not result in hydrocephalus and, because of their location, are more likely to result in lateralizing cerebellar dysfunction (appendicular ataxia) manifested by unilateral dysmetria, unsteadiness,  and weakness of the sixth and seventh nerves on the same side as the tumor.  Later, as the tumor grows toward the midline and blocks CSF, the more classical symptoms associated with hydrocephalus become evident.</Para><Para id="_1872">Cranial nerve findings are less common, except for unilateral or bilateral sixth nerve palsies, which are usually related to hydrocephalus.<Reference refidx="23"/>  At times, medulloblastomas will present explosively, with the acute onset of lethargy and unconsciousness resulting from hemorrhage within the tumor.</Para><Para id="_1873">In infants, the presentation of medulloblastoma is more variable and may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1874" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Nonspecific lethargy.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychomotor delays.</ListItem><ListItem>Loss of developmental milestones.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeding difficulties.</ListItem><ListItem>Increase in head circumference.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1875">On examination, there may be bulging of the anterior fontanel due to increased intracranial pressure and abnormal eye movements, including eyes that are deviated downward (the so-called sun setting sign) because of loss of upgaze secondary to compression of the tectum of the midbrain.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1891"><Title>Cellular and Molecular Classification</Title><Para id="_2106">In the 2021 World Health Organization (WHO) classification,  medulloblastoma is classified based on both histological and molecular features. The tumor is classified as medulloblastoma, histologically defined if no molecular testing has been performed.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="24"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_2107" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Medulloblastoma.<ItemizedList id="_2108" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, molecularly defined.<ItemizedList id="_2109" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, WNT-activated.</ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, SHH-activated and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>-wild type.</ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, SHH-activated and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>-altered.</ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, non-WNT/non-SHH.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma, histologically defined.<ItemizedList id="_2122" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Desmoplastic nodular medulloblastoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity.</ListItem><ListItem>Large cell medulloblastoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Anaplastic medulloblastoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1894">Significant attention has been focused on medulloblastomas that display anaplastic features, including increased nuclear size, marked cytological pleomorphism, numerous mitoses, and apoptotic bodies.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/>    Using the criteria of anaplasia is subjective because most medulloblastomas have some degree of anaplasia. Foci of anaplasia may appear in tumors with histological features of both classic and large cell medulloblastomas, and there is significant overlap between the anaplastic and large cell variants, which are frequently termed large cell/anaplastic medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/> One convention is to consider medulloblastomas as anaplastic when  anaplasia is diffuse (variably defined as anaplasia occurring in 50% to 80% of the tumor).</Para><Para id="_1895">The incidence of medulloblastoma with the desmoplastic/nodular histological variant, which most commonly arises in a cerebellar hemisphere, is higher in infants, is less common in children, and increases again in adolescents and adults. The desmoplastic/nodular histological variant is different from MBEN. The nodular variant has an expanded lobular architecture. The MBEN subtype occurs almost exclusively in infants and generally carries an excellent prognosis.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/> However, a recent report used transcriptome sequencing to identify a subset of patients with MBENs that had a high frequency of germline pathogenic alterations in <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> or <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName>. These patients had less favorable outcomes.<Reference refidx="29"/></Para><SummarySection id="_1896"><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000779394_1"><Title>Molecular subtypes of medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_460">Multiple medulloblastoma subtypes have been identified by integrative molecular analysis.<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/> Since 2012, the general consensus is that medulloblastoma can be molecularly separated into at least four core subtypes, including WNT-activated, sonic hedgehog (SHH)–activated, group 3, and group 4. In the 2021 World Health Organization (WHO) classification, the SHH subgroup has been divided into two groups based on <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> status. Group 3 and group 4, which require methylation analysis for reliable separation, have been combined into medulloblastoma, non-WNT/non-SHH. Because the group 3 and group 4 terminology has been used extensively in completed studies and is still in use in ongoing and planned studies, this nomenclature will be maintained throughout the clinical discussion in this summary.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="24"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_778">Different regions of the same tumor are likely to have other disparate genetic variants, adding to the complexity of devising effective molecularly targeted therapy.<Reference refidx="48"/> However, the major subtypes noted above remain stable across primary and metastatic components.<Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="52"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_763">Further subclassification within these subgroups is possible, which will provide even more prognostic information.<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/><Reference refidx="52"/></Para><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000779394_742"><Title>Medulloblastoma, WNT-activated</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_743"> WNT tumors are medulloblastomas with aberrations in the WNT signaling pathway and represent approximately 10% of all medulloblastomas.<Reference refidx="50"/> WNT medulloblastomas show a WNT signaling gene expression signature and  beta-catenin nuclear staining by immunohistochemistry.<Reference refidx="54"/> They are usually histologically classified as classic medulloblastoma tumors and rarely have a large cell/anaplastic appearance. WNT medulloblastomas generally occur in older patients (median age, 10 years) and are infrequently metastasized at diagnosis. Recent studies have demonstrated the value of methylation profiling in identifying WNT-activated medulloblastomas. These studies included cases that would not be detected using other current testing methods (e.g., beta-catenin immunohistochemistry, <GeneName>CTNNB1</GeneName> variant analysis, and evaluation for monosomy 6).<Reference refidx="55"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_744"><GeneName>CTNNB1</GeneName> variants are observed in 85% to 90% of WNT medulloblastoma cases, with <GeneName>APC</GeneName> variants detected in many of the cases that lack <GeneName>CTNNB1</GeneName> variants. Patients with WNT medulloblastoma whose tumors have <GeneName>APC</GeneName> variants often have Turcot syndrome (i.e., germline <GeneName>APC</GeneName> pathogenic variants).<Reference refidx="51"/> In addition to <GeneName>CTNNB1</GeneName> variants, WNT medulloblastoma tumors show 6q loss (monosomy 6) in 80% to 90% of cases. While monosomy 6 is observed in most medulloblastoma  patients younger than 18 years  at diagnosis, it appears to be much less common (approximately 25% of cases) in patients older than 18 years.<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="54"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_745">The WNT subset is primarily observed in older children, adolescents, and adults and does not show a male predominance. The subset is believed to have brain stem origin, from the embryonal rhombic lip region.<Reference refidx="56"/>   WNT medulloblastomas are associated with a very good outcome in children, especially in individuals whose tumors have beta-catenin nuclear staining and proven 6q loss and/or <GeneName>CTNNB1</GeneName> variants.<Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="59"/> Retrospective studies have suggested that additional <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants and <GeneName>OTX2</GeneName> copy number gains may be associated with a worse prognosis for patients with WNT medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="60"/> These latter associations need to be verified in prospective studies.<Reference refidx="61"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000779394_746"><Title>Medulloblastoma, SHH-activated and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>-altered and medulloblastoma, SHH-activated and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>-wild type </Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_747"> SHH tumors are medulloblastomas with aberrations in the SHH pathway and represent approximately 25% of medulloblastoma cases.<Reference refidx="50"/> SHH medulloblastomas are characterized by chromosome 9q deletions; desmoplastic/nodular histology; and variants in SHH pathway genes, including <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>PTCH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>SMO</GeneName>, <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName>, and <GeneName>GLI2</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="54"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_767">Heterozygous deleterious germline pathogenic variants in the <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName> gene were identified in approximately 3% of cases of SHH medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="19"/> <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName> is an inhibitor of SHH signaling. Median age at diagnosis for <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName>-altered cases was 1.5 years. Loss of heterozygosity (LOH) at the GPR161 locus was noted in all tumors, with tumors from five of six patients showing copy-neutral LOH of chromosome 1q (on which <GeneName>GPR161</GeneName> resides).</Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_768">Variants in the third nucleotide (r.3A&gt;G) of the U1 spliceosomal small nuclear RNAs (snRNAs) are highly specific for SHH medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="62"/><Reference refidx="63"/> U1 snRNA r.3A&gt;G variants are observed in virtually all cases of SHH medulloblastoma in adults, in approximately one-third of cases in children and adolescents, and are absent in cases in infants.<Reference refidx="63"/> U1 snRNA variants disrupt RNA splicing, leading to inactivation of tumor-suppressor genes (e.g., <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName>) and activation of oncogenes (e.g., <GeneName>GLI2</GeneName>). The significance of U1 snRNA r.3A&gt;G variants in specific SHH medulloblastoma subtypes is described below.</Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_748">SHH medulloblastomas show a bimodal age distribution and are observed primarily in children younger than 3 years  and in older adolescence/adulthood. The tumors are believed to emanate from the external granular layer of the cerebellum. The heterogeneity in age at presentation maps to distinctive subsets identified by further molecular characterization, as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000779394_749" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The subset of medulloblastoma most common in <Strong>children aged 3 to 16 years</Strong>, termed SHH-alpha (a provisional subgroup in the 2021 medulloblastoma classification), is <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> altered and is enriched for <GeneName>MYCN</GeneName> and <GeneName>GLI2</GeneName> amplifications.<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="52"/> Amplifications of <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> and <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName> may occur in this subtype and are mutually exclusive with <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants (often germline), while the <GeneName>SMO</GeneName> variant is rare.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="64"/> U1 snRNA variants occur in approximately 25% of SHH-alpha medulloblastoma cases and are associated with a very poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="63"/></ListItem><ListItem>Two SHH subtypes that occur primarily in <Strong>children younger than 3 years</Strong> have been described.<Reference refidx="50"/> One of these subtypes, termed SHH-1 (SHH-beta), is more commonly metastatic, with more frequent focal amplifications.<Reference refidx="65"/> The second of these subtypes, termed SHH-2 (SHH-gamma), is enriched for the medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity (MBEN) histology. SHH pathway variants in children younger than 3 years with medulloblastoma include <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> and <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName> variants.<Reference refidx="52"/> <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName> variants are rarely observed in older children and adults, and they are commonly germline events.<Reference refidx="64"/><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_738">Reports that used DNA methylation arrays have also identified two subtypes of SHH medulloblastoma in young children.<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="65"/> One of the subtypes contained all of the cases with <GeneName>SMO</GeneName> variants, and it was associated with a favorable prognosis. The other subtype had most of the <GeneName>SUFU</GeneName> variants, and it was associated with a much lower progression-free survival (PFS) rate. <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> variants were present in both subtypes.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>A fourth SHH subtype, termed SHH-delta, includes most of the <Strong>adult</Strong> cases of SHH medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="50"/> Virtually all cases of SHH-delta medulloblastoma have the U1 snRNA r.A&gt;3 variant,<Reference refidx="63"/> and approximately 90% of cases have <GeneName>TERT</GeneName> promoter variants.<Reference refidx="50"/> <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> and <GeneName>SMO</GeneName> variants are also observed in adults with SHH medulloblastoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_750">The outcome for patients with nonmetastatic SHH medulloblastoma is relatively favorable for children younger than 3 years and for adults.<Reference refidx="50"/> Young children with the MBEN histology have a particularly favorable prognosis.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="66"/><Reference refidx="67"/><Reference refidx="68"/> Patients with SHH medulloblastoma at greatest risk of treatment failure are children older than 3 years whose tumors have <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants, often with co-occurring <GeneName>GLI2</GeneName> or <GeneName>MYCN</GeneName> amplification and large cell/anaplastic histology.<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="64"/><Reference refidx="69"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_751">Patients with unfavorable molecular findings have an unfavorable prognosis, with fewer than 50% of patients surviving after conventional treatment.<Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="64"/><Reference refidx="69"/><Reference refidx="70"/><Reference refidx="71"/><Reference refidx="72"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_752">The 2021 WHO classification identifies SHH medulloblastoma with a <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variant as a distinctive entity (medulloblastoma, SHH-activated and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>-altered).<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="24"/>  Approximately 25% of SHH-activated medulloblastoma cases have <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants, with a high percentage of these cases also showing a <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> germline pathogenic variant (9 of 20 in one study). These patients are commonly between the  ages of 5 years and 18 years and have a worse outcome (5-year overall survival rate, &lt;30%).<Reference refidx="71"/> The tumors often show large cell anaplastic histology.<Reference refidx="71"/> A larger retrospective study has confirmed the poor prognosis of these patients.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000779394_753"><Title>Medulloblastoma, non–WNT/non–SHH-activated</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_754"> The WHO classification combines group 3 and group 4 medulloblastoma cases into a single entity, partly based on the absence of immediate clinical impact for this distinction. Group 3 represents approximately 25% of medulloblastoma cases, while group 4 represents approximately 40% of medulloblastoma cases.<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="54"/> Both group 3 and group 4 medulloblastoma patients are predominantly male.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="52"/> Group 3 and group 4 medulloblastomas can be further subdivided based on characteristics such as gene expression and DNA methylation profiles, but the optimal approach to their subdivision is not established.<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_755">Various genomic alterations are observed in group 3 and group 4 medulloblastomas. However, no single alteration occurs in more than 10% to 20% of cases. Genomic alterations include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000779394_756" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GeneName>MYC</GeneName> amplification was the most common distinctive alteration reported for group 3 medulloblastoma, occurring in approximately 15% of cases.<Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="51"/></ListItem><ListItem>The most common distinctive genomic alteration described for group 4 medulloblastoma (observed in approximately 15% of cases) was activation of <GeneName>PRDM6</GeneName> by enhancer hijacking, resulting from the tandem duplication of the adjacent  <GeneName>SNCAIP</GeneName> gene.<Reference refidx="51"/></ListItem><ListItem>Other genomic alterations were observed in both group 3 and group 4 cases, including <GeneName>MYCN</GeneName> amplification and structural variants leading to <GeneName>GFI1</GeneName> or <GeneName>GFI1B</GeneName> overexpression through enhancer hijacking.</ListItem><ListItem>Isochromosome 17q (i17q) is the most common cytogenetic abnormality and is observed in a high percentage of group 4 cases, as well as in group 3 cases, but it is rarely observed in WNT and SHH medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="51"/> Prognosis for group 3 and group 4 patients does not appear to be affected by the presence of i17q.<Reference refidx="73"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_757">Group 3 patients with <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> amplification or <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> overexpression have a poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="52"/> Fewer than 50% of these patients survive  5 years after diagnosis.<Reference refidx="50"/> This poor prognosis is especially true in children younger than 4 years  at diagnosis.<Reference refidx="46"/> However, patients with group 3 medulloblastoma without <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> amplification who are older than 3 years  have a prognosis similar to that of most patients with non-WNT medulloblastoma, with a 5-year PFS rate higher than 70%.<Reference refidx="70"/><Reference refidx="73"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_758">Group 4 medulloblastomas occur throughout infancy and childhood and into adulthood. The prognosis for group 4 medulloblastoma patients is similar to that for patients with other non-WNT medulloblastomas. Prognosis may be affected by additional factors such as the presence of metastatic disease, chromosome 11q loss, and chromosome 17p loss.<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="69"/> One study found that group 4 patients with either chromosome 11 loss or gain of chromosome 17 were low risk, regardless of metastases. In cases lacking both of these cytogenetic features, metastasis at presentation differentiated between high and intermediate risk.<Reference refidx="69"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_764">For group 3 and group 4 standard-risk patients (i.e., without <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> amplification or metastatic disease), the gain or loss of whole chromosomes appears to connote a favorable prognosis. This finding was derived from the data of 91 patients with non-WNT/non-SHH medulloblastoma enrolled in the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01351870">SIOP-PNET-4 (NCT01351870)</ProtocolRef> clinical trial and was confirmed in an independent group of 70 children with non-WNT/non-SHH medulloblastoma treated between 1990 and 2014.<Reference refidx="73"/> Chromosomal abnormalities include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000779394_762" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The gain/loss of one or more whole chromosomes was associated with a 5-year event-free survival (EFS) rate of 93%, compared with 64% for no whole chromosome gains/losses.</ListItem><ListItem>The most common whole chromosomal gains/losses are gain of chromosome 7 and loss of chromosomes 8 and 11.</ListItem><ListItem>The optimally performing prognosis discriminator was determined to be the occurrence of two or more of the following aberrations: chromosome 7 gain, chromosome 8 loss, and chromosome 11 loss. Approximately 40% of group 3 and group 4 standard-risk patients had two or more of these chromosomal aberrations and had a 5-year EFS rate of 100%, compared with 68% for patients with fewer than two aberrations.</ListItem><ListItem>In an independent cohort, the prognostic significance of two or more gains/losses versus zero or one gain/loss of chromosomes 7, 8, and 11 was confirmed (5-year EFS rate, 95% for patients with two or more vs. 59% for patients with one or fewer).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_759">The classification of medulloblastoma into the four major subtypes will likely be altered in the future.<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/><Reference refidx="72"/><Reference refidx="74"/><Reference refidx="75"/> Further subdivision within subgroups based on molecular characteristics is likely because each of the subgroups is further molecularly dissected, although the studies are nearing consensus as data from multiple independent studies are merged. As an example, using complementary bioinformatics approaches, concordance was analyzed among multiple large, published cohorts, and a more unified subgrouping was described. For children with group 3 and group 4 medulloblastomas, eight distinct subgroups were determined by DNA methylation clustering. Specific subgroups had different prognoses.<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="54"/><Reference refidx="64"/><Reference refidx="76"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779394_760">It  is unknown whether the classification for adults with medulloblastoma has a predictive ability similar to that for children.<Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="46"/>  In one study of adult patients with medulloblastoma, <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> oncogene amplifications were rarely observed, and tumors with 6q deletion and WNT activation (as identified by nuclear beta-catenin staining) did not share the excellent prognosis seen in pediatric medulloblastomas. However, another study did confirm an excellent prognosis for WNT-activated tumors in adults.<Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="46"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1882"><Title>Staging Evaluation</Title><Para id="_1883">Historically, staging was based on an intraoperative evaluation of both the size and extent of the tumor, coupled with postoperative neuroimaging of the brain and spine and cytological evaluation of CSF (the Chang system). Intraoperative evaluation of the extent of the tumor has been supplanted by neuraxis imaging before diagnosis and postoperative imaging to determine the amount of primary site residual disease.  The following tests and procedures are now used for staging: </Para><ItemizedList id="_1884" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain and spine (often done preoperatively).</ListItem><ListItem>Postoperative MRI of the brain to determine the amount of residual disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Lumbar CSF analysis.<Reference refidx="77"/><Reference refidx="78"/><Reference refidx="79"/>  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1885">The tumor extent is defined as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1886" Style="bullet"><ListItem>M<Subscript>0</Subscript>: No dissemination.</ListItem><ListItem>M<Subscript>1</Subscript>: CSF-positive cytology only.</ListItem><ListItem>M<Subscript>2</Subscript>: Gross nodular seeding in cerebellar-cerebral subarachnoid space and/or lateral or third ventricle.</ListItem><ListItem>M<Subscript>3</Subscript>: Gross nodular seeding in spinal subarachnoid space.</ListItem><ListItem>M<Subscript>4</Subscript>: Extraneural metastasis.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1887">Postoperative degree of residual disease is designated as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1888" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Gross-total resection/near-total resection: No or minimal (≤1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript>) evidence of residual disease after resection.</ListItem><ListItem>Subtotal resection: Residual disease after diagnosis (&gt;1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of measurable residual disease).</ListItem><ListItem>Biopsy: No tumor resection; only a sample of tumor tissue is removed.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1889">Since the 1990s, prospective studies have been performed using this staging system to separate patients into average-risk and high-risk medulloblastoma subgroups.<Reference refidx="78"/><Reference refidx="79"/><Reference refidx="80"/></Para><Para id="_1890">The presence of diffuse (&gt;50% of the pathological specimen) histological anaplasia has been added to  staging systems. If diffuse anaplasia is found, patients with otherwise average-risk disease are upstaged to high-risk disease.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1897"><Title>Risk Stratification</Title><Para id="_1898">Risk stratification is based on neuroradiographic evaluation for disseminated disease, CSF cytological examination, postoperative neuroimaging evaluation for the amount of residual disease, and patient age. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1882" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Staging Evaluation</SummaryRef> section. Patients older than 3 years with medulloblastoma have been stratified into the following two risk groups:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1899" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Average risk:</Strong>  Children older than 3 years with tumors that are totally resected or near-totally resected (≤1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of residual disease) and who have no metastatic disease.<Reference refidx="78"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>High risk:</Strong> Children older than 3 years with metastatic disease     and/or subtotal resection (&gt;1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of residual disease).<Reference refidx="78"/> Metastatic disease includes neuroradiographic evidence of disseminated disease, positive cytology in lumbar or ventricular CSF obtained more than 14 days after surgery, or extraneural disease.<Reference refidx="78"/> Children with tumors showing diffuse anaplasia and who otherwise would be considered average risk are assigned to the high-risk group.<Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="38"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1900">For younger children (younger than 3 years in some studies and younger than 4 or 5 years in others), similar separation into average-risk (no dissemination and ≤1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of residual disease) or high-risk (disseminated disease and/or &gt;1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of residual disease) groups has been used.  Histological findings of desmoplasia have also been used to connote a more favorable risk subgrouping, especially for the MBEN subgroup.<Reference refidx="81"/><Reference refidx="82"/></Para><Para id="_1901"> Assigning a risk group based on the extent of resection and disease at diagnosis may not predict treatment outcome. Molecular genetics and histological factors may be more informative, although they must be evaluated in the context of patient age, the extent of disease at the time of diagnosis, and treatment received.<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="72"/><Reference refidx="83"/> The risk characterizations of molecular subdivisions are changing and are becoming  integrated into risk stratification schema to assign treatment in North American prospective studies (e.g., <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01878617">NCT01878617</ProtocolRef> and <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02724579">NCT02724579</ProtocolRef>).<Reference refidx="74"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1902"><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Childhood Medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_1979"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2029" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Table 3</SummaryRef> describes the standard treatment options for newly diagnosed and recurrent childhood medulloblastoma.</Para><Table id="_2029"><Title>Table 3.  Standard Treatment Options for Childhood Medulloblastoma</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">Treatment Group</entry><entry>Standard Treatment Options</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="7"> <Strong>Newly diagnosed </Strong>childhood medulloblastoma</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Younger children with medulloblastoma</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1917" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1995" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Children older than 3 years with average-risk medulloblastoma</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1930" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1936" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1941" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Children older than 3 years with high-risk medulloblastoma</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_39" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_482" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_649" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong>Recurrent</Strong> childhood medulloblastoma</entry><entry/><entry>There are no standard treatment options. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_71" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Recurrent Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other CNS Embryonal Tumors</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_1903"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_1904">Surgery is considered a standard part of treatment for histological confirmation of tumor type and as a means to improve outcome.  Total or near-total resections are considered optimal if they can be performed safely.<Reference refidx="84"/><Reference refidx="85"/></Para><Para id="_1905">Postoperatively, children may have significant neurological deficits caused by preoperative tumor-related brain injury, hydrocephalus, or surgery-related brain injury.<Reference refidx="86"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] A significant number of patients with medulloblastoma develop cerebellar mutism syndrome (also known as posterior fossa syndrome). Symptoms of cerebellar mutism syndrome, which usually appear within 1 or 2 days after surgery, include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1906" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Loss of speech.</ListItem><ListItem>Suprabulbar palsies.</ListItem><ListItem>Ataxia.</ListItem><ListItem>Hypotonia.</ListItem><ListItem>Emotional lability.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1907">The etiology of cerebellar mutism syndrome remains unclear, although cerebellar vermian damage and/or disruption of cerebellar-cortical tracts has been postulated as the possible cause of the mutism.<Reference refidx="87"/><Reference refidx="88"/>; <Reference refidx="89"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]   In two Children’s Cancer Group studies that evaluated children with both average-risk and high-risk medulloblastoma, the syndrome was identified in nearly 25% of patients.<Reference refidx="88"/><Reference refidx="89"/><Reference refidx="90"/>; <Reference refidx="91"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] A retrospective analysis of 370  patients with medulloblastoma identified younger age, larger tumor size, and midline tumor location as risk factors for developing mutism. This finding is consistent with previous observations. Investigators also observed a correlation between medulloblastoma subtype and risk of mutism. Mutism was more common in patients with group 3 and group 4 medulloblastomas (30%–35% of patients) and less frequent in children with SHH-activated tumors (7% of patients).<Reference refidx="92"/> A prospective study that included longitudinal neurological examination of 178 patients with medulloblastoma identified similar risk factors for mutism (higher risk with younger age; lower risk with SHH subtype), most likely because SHH-activated tumors tend to be located in the hemispheres and not in the midline. The study also reported a higher risk of developing mutism in patients who undergo tumor resections at low-volume surgery centers.<Reference refidx="93"/> Approximately 50% of patients with this syndrome manifest long-term, permanent neurological and neurocognitive sequelae.<Reference refidx="89"/><Reference refidx="91"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1908"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_1909">Radiation therapy to the primary tumor site is usually in the range of 54 Gy to 55.8 Gy.<Reference refidx="94"/> In most instances, this therapy is given with a margin of 1 cm to 2 cm around the primary tumor site, preferably by conformal techniques.<Reference refidx="94"/>  Reducing  boost volumes for the whole posterior fossa and to the tumor bed plus margins did not compromise outcomes in average-risk patients in the Children's Oncology Group (COG) <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00085735">ACNS0331 (NCT00085735)</ProtocolRef> study.<Reference refidx="59"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] For all medulloblastomas in children older than 3 or 4 years  at diagnosis, craniospinal radiation therapy is given at doses ranging between 23.4 Gy and 36 Gy, depending on risk factors such as extent of disease at diagnosis. A prospective phase II toxicity study of proton radiation therapy <Reference refidx="95"/> and a retrospective  efficacy report  of protons versus photons for medulloblastoma <Reference refidx="96"/> demonstrated equivalent outcomes for PFS, overall survival (OS), patterns of relapse, and delayed toxic effects.   A retrospective study of 84 children who received either proton (n = 38) or photon (n = 46) radiation therapy demonstrated similar rates of grade 3 and grade 4 ototoxicity despite low mean cochlear doses in children who received proton radiation therapy, suggesting that other factors (e.g. cisplatin, initial tumor location in relationship to the vestibulocochlear nerve [eighth cranial nerve]) contribute to ototoxicity.<Reference refidx="97"/> The comparative outcomes of these treatment technologies are under investigation.</Para><Para id="_1910">Chemotherapy is usually administered during and after radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_1911">For children younger than 3 years,  efforts are made to omit or delay radiation therapy, given the profound impact of radiation at this age. Children of all ages are susceptible to the adverse effects of radiation on brain development.  Debilitating effects on neurocognitive development, growth, and endocrine function have been frequently observed, especially in younger children.<Reference refidx="98"/><Reference refidx="99"/><Reference refidx="100"/><Reference refidx="101"/><Reference refidx="102"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1912"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_1913">Chemotherapy, usually given during and after radiation therapy, is a standard component of treatment for older children with medulloblastoma and other embryonal tumors.  Chemotherapy can be used to delay and sometimes obviate the need for radiation therapy in 20% to 40% of children younger than 3 to 4 years  with nondisseminated medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="103"/><Reference refidx="104"/>; <Reference refidx="102"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1914"><Title>Treatment of Childhood Medulloblastoma</Title><SummarySection id="_1916"><Title>Treatment of younger children with medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_1918">The 5-year event-free survival (EFS) rates for young children with medulloblastoma, arbitrarily described in the past as aged 3 years and younger at diagnosis, have ranged between 30% and 70%. There is no consensus as to what age constitutes a younger population of children with medulloblastoma who are best treated with immediate postsurgery chemotherapy and delayed or no radiation therapy. Most studies agree that in patients aged 3 years and younger, initial chemotherapy should be strongly considered. In patients between the ages of 3 and 4 years,  and possibly as old as age 5 years, some investigators have recommended that radiation therapy be delayed or omitted entirely. Such decisions are based on multiple factors, including histological subtype, molecular subtype, extent of disease at diagnosis, preexisting neurological and neurodevelopmental status, and family preferences. Most long-term survivors who have been successfully treated with chemotherapy alone have had nondisseminated completely resected tumors.<Reference refidx="81"/><Reference refidx="103"/><Reference refidx="105"/>; <Reference refidx="106"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] Several studies that have used chemotherapy alone for younger patients  have observed that the finding of desmoplasia (seen in patients with desmoplastic medulloblastoma or MBEN) and/or molecular evidence of SHH signaling suggests a significantly better prognosis than the finding of  classic or large cell/anaplastic medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="66"/><Reference refidx="67"/><Reference refidx="68"/>; <Reference refidx="82"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_1919">The treatment of younger children with newly diagnosed medulloblastoma continues to evolve.  Results have been variable, and comparison across studies has been difficult because of differences in the drug regimens used and the utilization of craniospinal and local boost radiation therapy at the end of chemotherapy or when children reached age 3 years in some studies.</Para><Para id="_1920">Standard treatment options for younger children  with newly diagnosed medulloblastoma include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_1929" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1917" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1995" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_1917"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_1923">If feasible, complete surgical resection of the tumor is the optimal treatment. Surgical resectability is associated with histology, as patients with desmoplastic/nodular medulloblastoma or MBEN have a higher rate of complete resection than patients with classic medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="67"/><Reference refidx="68"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1995"><Title>Adjuvant chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_1996">Therapies for younger children with medulloblastoma have included the use of multiagent chemotherapeutic approaches, including drugs such as cyclophosphamide, etoposide, cisplatin, and vincristine, with or without concomitant high-dose intravenous and/or intraventricular methotrexate.<Reference refidx="68"/><Reference refidx="81"/><Reference refidx="103"/><Reference refidx="105"/><Reference refidx="107"/><Reference refidx="108"/>; <Reference refidx="109"/><Reference refidx="110"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] The efficacy of chemotherapy has varied, depending on the histology and/or molecular subtype of the tumor.</Para><SummarySection id="_2059"><Title>Desmoplastic/MBEN medulloblastoma and/or tumors with SHH signaling</Title><Para id="_2060">A series of studies have demonstrated that intensive chemotherapy, including either high-dose systemic and intraventricular methotrexate or high-dose chemotherapy supported by stem cell rescue, without radiation therapy, is an effective treatment for most infants and very young children with medulloblastoma.</Para><Para id="_2061">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_2062" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In the German Hirntumor (HIT) 2000 multicenter trial, a multiagent chemotherapy regimen that included high-dose intravenous and intraventricular methotrexate was used. This drug regimen did not include high-dose chemotherapy supported by bone marrow or peripheral stem cell rescue.<Reference refidx="81"/> <ItemizedList id="_2067" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Nineteen patients with desmoplastic medulloblastoma or MBEN had a 5-year EFS rate of 90% (±7%) and an OS rate of 100% (±0%). </ListItem><ListItem>All patients were treated with postoperative chemotherapy alone, and no radiation was given before progression.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>An expanded cohort of the German HIT 2000 trial included an additional 23 children with nodular desmoplasia or MBEN who were treated with the same regimen. The following results  were reported:<Reference refidx="111"/><ItemizedList id="_2068" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Combined results confirmed the excellent survival, with  a 5-year EFS rate of greater than 90%. </ListItem><ListItem>In this expanded cohort, molecular characterization was performed and a subset of tumors with SHH signaling were identified. These patients with tumors demonstrating SHH signaling had a similar excellent prognosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Further characterization of the SHH signaling molecular subtype by chromosomal aberrations did not identify any differences in EFS or OS.</ListItem><ListItem>Other studies have suggested that further subdivision by chromosomal aberrations in young children with SHH-driven medulloblastoma was predictive of outcome.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A COG clinical trial (CCG-9921) also had a favorable outcome for children with desmoplastic medulloblastoma (including MBEN). In this study, patients with desmoplastic tumors did not receive radiation therapy before progression.<Reference refidx="103"/>  <ItemizedList id="_2069" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Patients in the desmoplastic group achieved an EFS rate  of 77% (±9%) and an OS rate  of 85% (±8%), compared with an EFS rate of 17% (±5%) and an OS  rate of 29% (±6%) for patients in the nondesmoplastic group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001 for both EFS and OS comparisons).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02017964">COG-ACNS1221 (NCT02017964)</ProtocolRef> study tested systemic chemotherapy that was identical to the chemotherapy used in the German HIT 2000 trial, except for the omission of intraventricular methotrexate.<Reference refidx="28"/><ItemizedList id="_2070" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The study was closed early because of a higher-than-expected rate of relapse, with a 2-year PFS rate of 52% in the 25 patients who were studied.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Another treatment option for children younger than 3 years at diagnosis is high-dose chemotherapy. Results of trials using higher-dose, marrow-ablative chemotherapeutic regimens supported by stem cell rescue have also demonstrated that a subgroup of patients with medulloblastoma who are younger than 3 years  and, in some studies, younger than 5 years  at the time of diagnosis can be successfully treated with chemotherapy alone.<Reference refidx="104"/><Reference refidx="106"/><Reference refidx="112"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="113"/> <OrderedList id="_2071" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>The best survival rates using this higher-dose chemotherapy approach have been seen in patients with desmoplastic medulloblastoma and MBEN.<Reference refidx="113"/><ItemizedList id="_2072" Style="bullet"><ListItem>After treatment with chemotherapy without concomitant radiation therapy, patients with nondisseminated disease have achieved survival rates of nearly 90%, and patients with disseminated disease have achieved survival rates of 80%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem><ListItem>One study reported the outcomes of infants and young children with relapsed medulloblastoma who were  initially treated without craniospinal irradiation (CSI).<Reference refidx="114"/> <ItemizedList id="_2130" Style="bullet"><ListItem> A substantial portion of these children were treated with CSI-based regimens and their disease was successfully salvaged. </ListItem><ListItem>The 3-year postrelapse survival rate was 52.4% for patients treated with curative intent. </ListItem><ListItem>The report found that older age at diagnosis, local relapse, and the SHH infant medulloblastoma subtype were associated with better postrelapse survival. </ListItem><ListItem>The addition of chemotherapy to CSI did not improve outcomes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2063"><Title>Nondesmoplastic, non-MBEN, and non-SHH signaling–driven medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_2066">Compared with children with desmoplastic medulloblastoma or MBEN treated with current intensive chemotherapy regimens, children with other histological and/or molecular subtypes fare less well. One study suggested that patients with molecularly identified group 4 tumors did well with chemotherapy alone.<Reference refidx="111"/></Para><Para id="_2064">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_2065" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In children with nondesmoplastic, non-MBEN, and/or non-SHH–signaling tumors, the EFS rates are less than 40% despite the use of intensive chemotherapy supplemented with methotrexate (intravenous and intraventricular) or the use of high-dose chemotherapy regimens supported with stem cell rescue.<Reference refidx="68"/><Reference refidx="103"/><Reference refidx="111"/><Reference refidx="113"/><Reference refidx="115"/> <ItemizedList id="_2073" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Outcome is particularly poor when these patients have disseminated disease. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In some studies, radiation therapy to the primary tumor site and/or craniospinal axis has been added after chemotherapy, which makes the assessment of the efficacy of chemotherapy more difficult.<Reference refidx="111"/><Reference refidx="113"/><Reference refidx="115"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_2129">There is no consensus on how much radiation therapy (dose and extent) should be given and at what age radiation therapy should be instituted in young patients with localized or disseminated disease. </Para><ItemizedList id="_2074" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In the expanded HIT 2000 study, the addition of focal radiation therapy to the primary tumor site in patients with localized disease after chemotherapy did not improve EFS or OS.<Reference refidx="111"/></ListItem><ListItem>In the St. Jude Children's Research Hospital (SJCRH) <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00602667">SJYC07 (NCT00602667)</ProtocolRef> study, focal radiation therapy also did not improve EFS in infants with medulloblastoma denoted as intermediate risk  (5-year EFS rate, 25% ± 12%).<Reference refidx="65"/></ListItem><ListItem>The COG <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00006461">P9934 (NCT00006461)</ProtocolRef> study, which also employed focal radiation therapy, had a similar EFS (4-year EFS rate, 23% ± 12%) for patients with nondesmoplastic medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="116"/></ListItem><ListItem>In the SJCRH SJYC07 study, 29 of the 54 infants with medulloblastoma whose disease progressed received CSI (median dose, 36 Gy). Of the 29 patients, 18 (62%) survived, compared with 6 of 25 patients (24%) who did not receive CSI.<Reference refidx="65"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1928"><Title>Treatment of children older than 3 years with average-risk medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_1931">Standard treatment options for children older than 3 years with newly diagnosed average-risk medulloblastoma include  the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_1932" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1930" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1936" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1941" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_1930"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_1935">If feasible, total or near-total removal of the tumor is considered optimal.<Reference refidx="84"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1936"><Title>Adjuvant radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_1937">Radiation therapy is usually initiated after surgery with or without concurrent chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="117"/><Reference refidx="118"/><Reference refidx="119"/> The best survival results for children with medulloblastoma have been obtained when radiation therapy is initiated within 4 to 6 weeks postsurgery.<Reference refidx="118"/><Reference refidx="119"/><Reference refidx="120"/>; <Reference refidx="94"/><Reference refidx="121"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] A pilot study in children with WNT-activated medulloblastoma attempted to omit craniospinal radiation therapy (and treat patients with postsurgical chemotherapy alone). The study was aborted after the first two patients had early tumor recurrences.<Reference refidx="122"/></Para><Para id="_2028">The radiation dose for patients with average-risk medulloblastoma is 54 Gy to the posterior fossa or local tumor bed and 23.4 Gy to the entire neuraxis (i.e., the whole brain and spine), termed CSI.<Reference refidx="117"/><Reference refidx="118"/><Reference refidx="119"/><Reference refidx="123"/></Para><Para id="_1999">Evidence (adjuvant radiation therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_2000" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>With radiation therapy alone, using a craniospinal radiation dose of 35 Gy with a boost to the posterior fossa of 55 Gy, 5-year EFS rates range between 50% and  65% in patients with nondisseminated disease.<Reference refidx="80"/><Reference refidx="118"/></ListItem><ListItem>The minimal dose of craniospinal radiation needed for disease control  is unknown.  Attempts to lower the dose of craniospinal radiation therapy to 23.4 Gy without chemotherapy have resulted in an increased incidence of isolated leptomeningeal relapse.<Reference refidx="123"/> One series  attempted to treat children with WNT-activated tumors using focal radiation therapy alone, without CSI. The study showed an unacceptable incidence of neuroaxial failure  with the omission of up-front CSI.<Reference refidx="124"/><Para id="_2001">Lower doses  and boost volume of craniospinal radiation were evaluated in a COG study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00085735">NCT00085735</ProtocolRef>). Children aged 3 to 7 years were randomly assigned to receive a craniospinal radiation dose of either 18 Gy or 23.4 Gy, as well as whole posterior fossa versus limited target volume boost to the tumor bed.<Reference refidx="59"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_2002" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Results revealed that 18 Gy of CSI was inferior to 23.4 Gy of CSI (5-year EFS rate of 82.6% ± 4.2% and OS rate of 85.8% for patients who received 23.4 Gy vs. EFS rate of 71.9% ± 4.9% and  OS rate of 77.9% ± 4.9% for patients who received 18 Gy).</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year EFS rate  was 82.5% for patients who received radiation therapy targeting the tumor bed, compared with 80.5% for patients who received posterior fossa radiation therapy. Therefore, radiation therapy targeting the tumor bed was not inferior to posterior fossa radiation therapy (hazard ratio, 0.97; 94% upper confidence interval, 1.32). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2003">Analysis according to molecular subgroups demonstrated that children with group 4 medulloblastoma who received 18 Gy of craniospinal radiation therapy had poorer EFS than those who received 23.4 Gy. This was not demonstrated in the other molecular subgroups, although the study was not sized for molecular subgroup analysis.<Reference refidx="59"/> Craniospinal radiation dose reduction to 18 Gy is currently being investigated in WNT medulloblastoma patients (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02724579">NCT02724579</ProtocolRef>), the molecular subgroup with the best prognosis.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>The <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01351870">SIOP-PNET-4 (NCT01351870)</ProtocolRef> study compared daily radiation therapy (1.8 Gy fractions with 23.4 Gy to the neuraxis and a 30 Gy boost to the posterior fossa) with twice-per-day radiation (1 Gy fractions with 36 Gy and a 24-Gy boost to the posterior fossa).<Reference refidx="125"/><ItemizedList id="_2004" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 7.8 years, the 10-year OS was not significantly different between the two radiation groups.</ListItem><ListItem>Long-term side effects were not reported in this study.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>If chemotherapy is added after radiation therapy, 23.4 Gy of craniospinal radiation therapy has been shown to be an effective dose.<Reference refidx="94"/><Reference refidx="125"/><Reference refidx="126"/><Reference refidx="127"/> Lower doses are being evaluated.</ListItem><ListItem>Although the standard boost in medulloblastoma is to the entire posterior fossa, failure data patterns reveal that radiation therapy to the tumor bed instead of the entire posterior fossa is equally effective and may be associated with reduced toxicity.<Reference refidx="128"/><Reference refidx="129"/>; <Reference refidx="59"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1941"><Title>Adjuvant chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_1942">Chemotherapy is now a standard component of the treatment of children with average-risk medulloblastoma.</Para><Para id="_2005">Evidence (adjuvant chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_1943" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Prospective randomized trials and single-arm trials suggest that adjuvant chemotherapy given during and after radiation therapy improves OS for children with average-risk medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="91"/><Reference refidx="117"/><Reference refidx="118"/><Reference refidx="119"/><Reference refidx="120"/><Reference refidx="121"/><ItemizedList id="_1944" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Radiation therapy and chemotherapy given during and after surgery has demonstrated 5-year EFS rates of 70% to 85%.<Reference refidx="117"/><Reference refidx="118"/><Reference refidx="119"/>; <Reference refidx="130"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A lower radiation dose of 23.4 Gy to the neuraxis when coupled with chemotherapy has been shown to result in disease control in up to 85% of patients and may decrease the severity of long-term neurocognitive sequelae.<Reference refidx="94"/><Reference refidx="126"/><Reference refidx="127"/><Reference refidx="131"/></ListItem><ListItem>A  variety of chemotherapeutic regimens have been successfully used, including the combination of cisplatin, lomustine, and vincristine or the combination of cisplatin, cyclophosphamide, and vincristine.<Reference refidx="117"/><Reference refidx="118"/><Reference refidx="131"/><Reference refidx="132"/> <ItemizedList id="_2125" Style="bullet"><ListItem> These therapies have increased 5-year and 10-year EFS and OS rates and have likely decreased the incidence of late relapse. </ListItem><ListItem>However, long-term survivors treated with multimodality therapy are at a high risk of late effects such as hearing loss, cardiac complications, and secondary neoplasms.<Reference refidx="133"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2006"> In addition, postradiation high-dose cyclophosphamide supported by peripheral stem cell rescue, but with reduced cumulative doses of vincristine and cisplatin, has resulted in similar survival rates.<Reference refidx="58"/></Para></ListItem><ListItem>Although medulloblastoma is often sensitive to chemotherapy, preradiation chemotherapy has not been shown to improve survival in patients with average-risk medulloblastoma, compared with radiation therapy and subsequent chemotherapy.  In some prospective studies, preradiation chemotherapy has been related to a poorer rate of survival.<Reference refidx="118"/><Reference refidx="119"/><Reference refidx="120"/><Reference refidx="121"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><Title>Treatment of children older than 3 years with high-risk medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_478">Standard treatment options for children older than 3 years who are newly diagnosed with medulloblastoma and have metastatic disease or have had a subtotal resection  include  the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_479" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_39" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_482" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_649" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_2007">In high-risk patients, numerous studies have demonstrated that multimodality therapy improves the duration of disease control and overall disease-free survival.<Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="134"/> Studies show that 50% to 70% of patients with high-risk disease, including those with metastatic disease, will experience long-term disease control.<Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="117"/><Reference refidx="134"/><Reference refidx="135"/><Reference refidx="136"/><Reference refidx="137"/><Reference refidx="138"/>; <Reference refidx="139"/><Reference refidx="140"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="141"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] A completed COG study demonstrated that children with group 3 <GeneName>MYC</GeneName>-amplified tumors who were randomly assigned to receive carboplatin during radiation therapy had improved 5-year EFS and OS rates, compared with those who did not receive carboplatin concurrently with radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="135"/> The optimal treatment for children with SHH-activated, <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>-altered medulloblastoma has not been determined, as less than 30% of patients are expected to survive 5 years from diagnosis after treatment with current therapy.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><SummarySection id="_39"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_481">Treatment of high-risk patients is the same as for average-risk patients. An attempt at gross-total resection  is considered  optimal, if feasible.<Reference refidx="80"/><Reference refidx="84"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_482"><Title>Adjuvant radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_2008">In contrast to standard-risk treatment, the craniospinal radiation dose is generally 36 Gy.   </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_649"><Title>Adjuvant chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_2009">Evidence (adjuvant chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_487" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The drugs that are useful in children with average-risk disease are the same drugs that have been used extensively in children with high-risk disease, including cisplatin, lomustine, cyclophosphamide, etoposide, and vincristine.<Reference refidx="139"/><ItemizedList id="_2126" Style="bullet"><ListItem> These therapies have increased 5-year and 10-year EFS and OS rates and have likely decreased the incidence of late relapse. </ListItem><ListItem>However, long-term survivors treated with multimodality therapy are at a high risk of late effects such as hearing loss, cardiac complications, and secondary neoplasms.<Reference refidx="133"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Postradiation high-dose nonmyeloablative chemotherapy supported by peripheral stem cell rescue, but with reduced cumulative doses of vincristine and cisplatin, has also been used and has resulted in 5-year PFS rates of approximately 60%.<Reference refidx="58"/></ListItem><ListItem>The COG <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00392327">ACNS0332 (NCT00392327)</ProtocolRef> study randomly assigned patients to receive daily carboplatin compared with weekly vincristine during radiation therapy (36 Gy craniospinal plus a posterior fossa boost) followed by six cycles of adjuvant treatment with cisplatin, cyclophosphamide, and vincristine.<Reference refidx="135"/><ItemizedList id="_2099" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Of the 261 evaluable patients, the 5-year EFS rate was 62.9%, and the OS rate was 73.4%.</ListItem><ListItem>For the entire cohort, there was no difference in EFS rate between patients who were treated with carboplatin (66.4%) and patients who were not treated with carboplatin (59.2%).</ListItem><ListItem>In a subset analysis based on molecular subgrouping, patients with group 3 medulloblastoma appeared to benefit from the use of daily carboplatin during radiation therapy, with a 5-year EFS rate of 73.2% for patients who  received carboplatin, compared with 53.7% for those who did not.</ListItem><ListItem>A second randomization testing the utility of isotretinoin maintenance therapy was closed at the time of a planned interim analysis for futility.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a trial of 51 patients with newly diagnosed high-risk disease, patients were treated with postoperative induction chemotherapy (etoposide and carboplatin), followed by two high-dose thiotepa courses with peripheral stem cell rescue and risk-adapted craniospinal radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="136"/><ItemizedList id="_2127" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year PFS and OS rates were 76%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><Title>Treatment options under clinical evaluation for childhood medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_272">Early-phase therapeutic trials may be available for selected patients. These trials may be available via the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.childrensoncologygroup.org/">COG</ExternalRef>, the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.pbtc.org/">Pediatric Brain Tumor Consortium</ExternalRef>, or other entities.  Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26580448">Zhang J, Walsh MF, Wu G, et al.: Germline Mutations in Predisposition Genes in Pediatric Cancer. N Engl J Med 373 (24): 2336-46, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="29753700">Waszak SM, Northcott PA, Buchhalter I, et al.: Spectrum and prevalence of genetic predisposition in medulloblastoma: a retrospective genetic study and prospective validation in a clinical trial cohort. Lancet Oncol 19 (6): 785-798, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="7661930" MedlineID="95174843">Hamilton SR, Liu B, Parsons RE, et al.: The molecular basis of Turcot's syndrome. N Engl J Med 332 (13): 839-47, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11741116">Taylor MD, Mainprize TG, Rutka JT, et al.: Medulloblastoma in a child with Rubenstein-Taybi Syndrome: case report and review of the literature. Pediatr Neurosurg 35 (5): 235-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7747773">Miller RW, Rubinstein JH: Tumors in Rubinstein-Taybi syndrome. Am J Med Genet 56 (1): 112-5, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24115570">Bourdeaut F, Miquel C, Richer W, et al.: Rubinstein-Taybi syndrome predisposing to non-WNT, non-SHH, group 3 medulloblastoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (2): 383-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="19276247">Garrè ML, Cama A, Bagnasco F, et al.: Medulloblastoma variants: age-dependent occurrence and relation to Gorlin syndrome--a new clinical perspective. Clin Cancer Res 15 (7): 2463-71, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="19533801">Pastorino L, Ghiorzo P, Nasti S, et al.: Identification of a SUFU germline mutation in a family with Gorlin syndrome. Am J Med Genet A 149A (7): 1539-43, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="22508808">Brugières L, Remenieras A, Pierron G, et al.: High frequency of germline SUFU mutations in children with desmoplastic/nodular medulloblastoma younger than 3 years of age. J Clin Oncol 30 (17): 2087-93, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="1931625">Evans DG, Farndon PA, Burnell LD, et al.: The incidence of Gorlin syndrome in 173 consecutive cases of medulloblastoma. Br J Cancer 64 (5): 959-61, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="25403219">Smith MJ, Beetz C, Williams SG, et al.: Germline mutations in SUFU cause Gorlin syndrome-associated childhood medulloblastoma and redefine the risk associated with PTCH1 mutations. J Clin Oncol 32 (36): 4155-61, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="5396222" MedlineID="71004345">Li FP, Fraumeni JF: Rhabdomyosarcoma in children: epidemiologic study and identification of a familial cancer syndrome. J Natl Cancer Inst 43 (6): 1365-73, 1969.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="6958872">Pearson AD, Craft AW, Ratcliffe JM, et al.: Two families with the Li-Fraumeni cancer family syndrome. J Med Genet 19 (5): 362-5, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="37379234">Kolodziejczak AS, Guerrini-Rousseau L, Planchon JM, et al.: Clinical outcome of pediatric medulloblastoma patients with Li-Fraumeni syndrome. Neuro Oncol 25 (12): 2273-2286, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="14559878">Offit K, Levran O, Mullaney B, et al.: Shared genetic susceptibility to breast cancer, brain tumors, and Fanconi anemia. J Natl Cancer Inst 95 (20): 1548-51, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="19530235">Dewire MD, Ellison DW, Patay Z, et al.: Fanconi anemia and biallelic BRCA2 mutation diagnosed in a young child with an embryonal CNS tumor. Pediatr Blood Cancer 53 (6): 1140-2, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="15689453">Reid S, Renwick A, Seal S, et al.: Biallelic BRCA2 mutations are associated with multiple malignancies in childhood including familial Wilms tumour. J Med Genet 42 (2): 147-51, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="38919026">Sönksen M, Obrecht-Sturm D, Hernáiz Driever P, et al.: Medulloblastoma in children with Fanconi anemia: Association with FA-D1/FA-N, SHH type and poor survival independent of treatment strategies. Neuro Oncol 26 (11): 2125-2139, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="31609649">Begemann M, Waszak SM, Robinson GW, et al.: Germline GPR161 Mutations Predispose to Pediatric Medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 38 (1): 43-50, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="32296180">Waszak SM, Robinson GW, Gudenas BL, et al.: Germline Elongator mutations in Sonic Hedgehog medulloblastoma. Nature 580 (7803): 396-401, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="6296325" MedlineID="83111061">Rorke LB: The cerebellar medulloblastoma and its relationship to primitive neuroectodermal tumors. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 42 (1): 1-15, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="34185076">Louis DN, Perry A, Wesseling P, et al.: The 2021 WHO Classification of Tumors of the Central Nervous System: a summary. Neuro Oncol 23 (8): 1231-1251, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="24616042">Ramaswamy V, Remke M, Shih D, et al.: Duration of the pre-diagnostic interval in medulloblastoma is subgroup dependent. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (7): 1190-4, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="24">WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board, ed.: WHO Classification of Tumours: Central Nervous System Tumours. Vol. 6. 5th ed. IARC Press; 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="12834107">McManamy CS, Lamont JM, Taylor RE, et al.: Morphophenotypic variation predicts clinical behavior in childhood non-desmoplastic medulloblastomas. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 62 (6): 627-32, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="15198123">Eberhart CG, Kratz J, Wang Y, et al.: Histopathological and molecular prognostic markers in medulloblastoma: c-myc, N-myc, TrkC, and anaplasia. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 63 (5): 441-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="10584843">Giangaspero F, Perilongo G, Fondelli MP, et al.: Medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity: a variant with favorable prognosis. J Neurosurg 91 (6): 971-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="31774708">Lafay-Cousin L, Bouffet E, Strother D, et al.: Phase II Study of Nonmetastatic Desmoplastic Medulloblastoma in Children Younger Than 4 Years of Age: A Report of the Children's Oncology Group (ACNS1221). J Clin Oncol 38 (3): 223-231, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="31781912">Korshunov A, Okonechnikov K, Sahm F, et al.: Transcriptional profiling of medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity (MBEN) reveals two clinically relevant tumor subsets with VSNL1 as potent prognostic marker. Acta Neuropathol 139 (3): 583-596, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="20420498">Onvani S, Etame AB, Smith CA, et al.: Genetics of medulloblastoma: clues for novel therapies. Expert Rev Neurother 10 (5): 811-23, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="20425037">Dubuc AM, Northcott PA, Mack S, et al.: The genetics of pediatric brain tumors. Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep 10 (3): 215-23, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="16567768">Thompson MC, Fuller C, Hogg TL, et al.: Genomics identifies medulloblastoma subgroups that are enriched for specific genetic alterations. J Clin Oncol 24 (12): 1924-31, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="18769486">Kool M, Koster J, Bunt J, et al.: Integrated genomics identifies five medulloblastoma subtypes with distinct genetic profiles, pathway signatures and clinicopathological features. PLoS One 3 (8): e3088, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="20142599">Tabori U, Baskin B, Shago M, et al.: Universal poor survival in children with medulloblastoma harboring somatic TP53 mutations. J Clin Oncol 28 (8): 1345-50, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="19255330">Pfister S, Remke M, Benner A, et al.: Outcome prediction in pediatric medulloblastoma based on DNA copy-number aberrations of chromosomes 6q and 17q and the MYC and MYCN loci. J Clin Oncol 27 (10): 1627-36, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="16258095">Ellison DW, Onilude OE, Lindsey JC, et al.: beta-Catenin status predicts a favorable outcome in childhood medulloblastoma: the United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group Brain Tumour Committee. J Clin Oncol 23 (31): 7951-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="17464337">Polkinghorn WR, Tarbell NJ: Medulloblastoma: tumorigenesis, current clinical paradigm, and efforts to improve risk stratification. Nat Clin Pract Oncol 4 (5): 295-304, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="16685513">Giangaspero F, Wellek S, Masuoka J, et al.: Stratification of medulloblastoma on the basis of histopathological grading. Acta Neuropathol 112 (1): 5-12, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="20823417">Northcott PA, Korshunov A, Witt H, et al.: Medulloblastoma comprises four distinct molecular variants. J Clin Oncol 29 (11): 1408-14, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="11807556" MedlineID="21666525">Pomeroy SL, Tamayo P, Gaasenbeek M, et al.: Prediction of central nervous system embryonal tumour outcome based on gene expression. Nature 415 (6870): 436-42, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="22832583">Jones DT, Jäger N, Kool M, et al.: Dissecting the genomic complexity underlying medulloblastoma. Nature 488 (7409): 100-5, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="22147459">Peyrl A, Chocholous M, Kieran MW, et al.: Antiangiogenic metronomic therapy for children with recurrent embryonal brain tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 59 (3): 511-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="22134537">Taylor MD, Northcott PA, Korshunov A, et al.: Molecular subgroups of medulloblastoma: the current consensus. Acta Neuropathol 123 (4): 465-72, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="22358457">Kool M, Korshunov A, Remke M, et al.: Molecular subgroups of medulloblastoma: an international meta-analysis of transcriptome, genetic aberrations, and clinical data of WNT, SHH, Group 3, and Group 4 medulloblastomas. Acta Neuropathol 123 (4): 473-84, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="24791927">Pietsch T, Schmidt R, Remke M, et al.: Prognostic significance of clinical, histopathological, and molecular characteristics of medulloblastomas in the prospective HIT2000 multicenter clinical trial cohort. Acta Neuropathol 128 (1): 137-49, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="21098324">Cho YJ, Tsherniak A, Tamayo P, et al.: Integrative genomic analysis of medulloblastoma identifies a molecular subgroup that drives poor clinical outcome. J Clin Oncol 29 (11): 1424-30, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="26304884">Gajjar A, Bowers DC, Karajannis MA, et al.: Pediatric Brain Tumors: Innovative Genomic Information Is Transforming the Diagnostic and Clinical Landscape. J Clin Oncol 33 (27): 2986-98, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="28394352">Morrissy AS, Cavalli FMG, Remke M, et al.: Spatial heterogeneity in medulloblastoma. Nat Genet 49 (5): 780-788, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="25689980">Wang X, Dubuc AM, Ramaswamy V, et al.: Medulloblastoma subgroups remain stable across primary and metastatic compartments. Acta Neuropathol 129 (3): 449-57, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="28609654">Cavalli FMG, Remke M, Rampasek L, et al.: Intertumoral Heterogeneity within Medulloblastoma Subgroups. Cancer Cell 31 (6): 737-754.e6, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="28726821">Northcott PA, Buchhalter I, Morrissy AS, et al.: The whole-genome landscape of medulloblastoma subtypes. Nature 547 (7663): 311-317, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="28545823">Schwalbe EC, Lindsey JC, Nakjang S, et al.: Novel molecular subgroups for clinical classification and outcome prediction in childhood medulloblastoma: a cohort study. Lancet Oncol 18 (7): 958-971, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="32779246">Hicks D, Rafiee G, Schwalbe EC, et al.: The molecular landscape and associated clinical experience in infant medulloblastoma: prognostic significance of second-generation subtypes. Neuropathol Appl Neurobiol 47 (2): 236-250, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="23175120">Northcott PA, Jones DT, Kool M, et al.: Medulloblastomics: the end of the beginning. Nat Rev Cancer 12 (12): 818-34, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="30252101">Korshunov A, Sahm F, Zheludkova O, et al.: DNA methylation profiling is a method of choice for molecular verification of pediatric WNT-activated medulloblastomas. Neuro Oncol 21 (2): 214-221, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="21150899">Gibson P, Tong Y, Robinson G, et al.: Subtypes of medulloblastoma have distinct developmental origins. Nature 468 (7327): 1095-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="21267586">Ellison DW, Dalton J, Kocak M, et al.: Medulloblastoma: clinicopathological correlates of SHH, WNT, and non-SHH/WNT molecular subgroups. Acta Neuropathol 121 (3): 381-96, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="17012043">Gajjar A, Chintagumpala M, Ashley D, et al.: Risk-adapted craniospinal radiotherapy followed by high-dose chemotherapy and stem-cell rescue in children with newly diagnosed medulloblastoma (St Jude Medulloblastoma-96): long-term results from a prospective, multicentre trial. Lancet Oncol 7 (10): 813-20, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="34110925">Michalski JM, Janss AJ, Vezina LG, et al.: Children's Oncology Group Phase III Trial of Reduced-Dose and Reduced-Volume Radiotherapy With Chemotherapy for Newly Diagnosed Average-Risk Medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 39 (24): 2685-2697, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="36181537">Goschzik T, Mynarek M, Doerner E, et al.: Genetic alterations of TP53 and OTX2 indicate increased risk of relapse in WNT medulloblastomas. Acta Neuropathol 144 (6): 1143-1156, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="36403175">Gottardo NG: Genetic alterations of TP53 and OTX2 indicate increased risk of relapse in WNT medulloblastomas: "it's a numbers game"-implications for WNT medulloblastoma dose-reduction clinical trials. Acta Neuropathol 145 (1): 145-147, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="31597163">Shuai S, Suzuki H, Diaz-Navarro A, et al.: The U1 spliceosomal RNA is recurrently mutated in multiple cancers. Nature 574 (7780): 712-716, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="31664194">Suzuki H, Kumar SA, Shuai S, et al.: Recurrent noncoding U1 snRNA mutations drive cryptic splicing in SHH medulloblastoma. Nature 574 (7780): 707-711, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="24651015">Kool M, Jones DT, Jäger N, et al.: Genome sequencing of SHH medulloblastoma predicts genotype-related response to smoothened inhibition. Cancer Cell 25 (3): 393-405, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="29778738">Robinson GW, Rudneva VA, Buchhalter I, et al.: Risk-adapted therapy for young children with medulloblastoma (SJYC07): therapeutic and molecular outcomes from a multicentre, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 19 (6): 768-784, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="21246528">Leary SE, Zhou T, Holmes E, et al.: Histology predicts a favorable outcome in young children with desmoplastic medulloblastoma: a report from the children's oncology group. Cancer 117 (14): 3262-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="20940197">Rutkowski S, von Hoff K, Emser A, et al.: Survival and prognostic factors of early childhood medulloblastoma: an international meta-analysis. J Clin Oncol 28 (33): 4961-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="21636711">von Bueren AO, von Hoff K, Pietsch T, et al.: Treatment of young children with localized medulloblastoma by chemotherapy alone: results of the prospective, multicenter trial HIT 2000 confirming the prognostic impact of histology. Neuro Oncol 13 (6): 669-79, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="24493713">Shih DJ, Northcott PA, Remke M, et al.: Cytogenetic prognostication within medulloblastoma subgroups. J Clin Oncol 32 (9): 886-96, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="23291781">Schwalbe EC, Williamson D, Lindsey JC, et al.: DNA methylation profiling of medulloblastoma allows robust subclassification and improved outcome prediction using formalin-fixed biopsies. Acta Neuropathol 125 (3): 359-71, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="23835706">Zhukova N, Ramaswamy V, Remke M, et al.: Subgroup-specific prognostic implications of TP53 mutation in medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 31 (23): 2927-35, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="33405951">Gajjar A, Robinson GW, Smith KS, et al.: Outcomes by Clinical and Molecular Features in Children With Medulloblastoma Treated With Risk-Adapted Therapy: Results of an International Phase III Trial (SJMB03). J Clin Oncol 39 (7): 822-835, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="30392813">Goschzik T, Schwalbe EC, Hicks D, et al.: Prognostic effect of whole chromosomal aberration signatures in standard-risk, non-WNT/non-SHH medulloblastoma: a retrospective, molecular analysis of the HIT-SIOP PNET 4 trial. Lancet Oncol 19 (12): 1602-1616, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="24264598">Gottardo NG, Hansford JR, McGlade JP, et al.: Medulloblastoma Down Under 2013: a report from the third annual meeting of the International Medulloblastoma Working Group. Acta Neuropathol 127 (2): 189-201, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="75" PMID="24990071">Louis DN, Perry A, Burger P, et al.: International Society Of Neuropathology--Haarlem consensus guidelines for nervous system tumor classification and grading. Brain Pathol 24 (5): 429-35, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="31076851">Sharma T, Schwalbe EC, Williamson D, et al.: Second-generation molecular subgrouping of medulloblastoma: an international meta-analysis of Group 3 and Group 4 subtypes. Acta Neuropathol 138 (2): 309-326, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="10506624" MedlineID="99438194">Fouladi M, Gajjar A, Boyett JM, et al.: Comparison of CSF cytology and spinal magnetic resonance imaging in the detection of leptomeningeal disease in pediatric medulloblastoma or primitive neuroectodermal tumor. J Clin Oncol 17 (10): 3234-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="10071274">Zeltzer PM, Boyett JM, Finlay JL, et al.: Metastasis stage, adjuvant treatment, and residual tumor are prognostic factors for medulloblastoma in children: conclusions from the Children's Cancer Group 921 randomized phase III study. J Clin Oncol 17 (3): 832-45, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="79" PMID="9231668" MedlineID="97375351">Yao MS, Mehta MP, Boyett JM, et al.: The effect of M-stage on patterns of failure in posterior fossa primitive neuroectodermal tumors treated on CCG-921: a phase III study in a high-risk patient population. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 38 (3): 469-76, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="80" PMID="12697884">Taylor RE, Bailey CC, Robinson K, et al.: Results of a randomized study of preradiation chemotherapy versus radiotherapy alone for nonmetastatic medulloblastoma: The International Society of Paediatric Oncology/United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group PNET-3 Study. J Clin Oncol 21 (8): 1581-91, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="81" PMID="15758008">Rutkowski S, Bode U, Deinlein F, et al.: Treatment of early childhood medulloblastoma by postoperative chemotherapy alone. N Engl J Med 352 (10): 978-86, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="82" PMID="18818397">Rutkowski S, Gerber NU, von Hoff K, et al.: Treatment of early childhood medulloblastoma by postoperative chemotherapy and deferred radiotherapy. Neuro Oncol 11 (2): 201-10, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="83" PMID="25605817">Ramaswamy V, Remke M, Adamski J, et al.: Medulloblastoma subgroup-specific outcomes in irradiated children: who are the true high-risk patients? Neuro Oncol 18 (2): 291-7, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="84" PMID="8869053" MedlineID="97022693">Albright AL, Wisoff JH, Zeltzer PM, et al.: Effects of medulloblastoma resections on outcome in children: a report from the Children's Cancer Group. Neurosurgery 38 (2): 265-71, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="85" PMID="26976201">Thompson EM, Hielscher T, Bouffet E, et al.: Prognostic value of medulloblastoma extent of resection after accounting for molecular subgroup: a retrospective integrated clinical and molecular analysis. Lancet Oncol 17 (4): 484-95, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="86" PMID="17931127">Stargatt R, Rosenfeld JV, Maixner W, et al.: Multiple factors contribute to neuropsychological outcome in children with posterior fossa tumors. Dev Neuropsychol 32 (2): 729-48, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="87" PMID="8559336">Pollack IF, Polinko P, Albright AL, et al.: Mutism and pseudobulbar symptoms after resection of posterior fossa tumors in children: incidence and pathophysiology. Neurosurgery 37 (5): 885-93, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="88" PMID="17184075">Robertson PL, Muraszko KM, Holmes EJ, et al.: Incidence and severity of postoperative cerebellar mutism syndrome in children with medulloblastoma: a prospective study by the Children's Oncology Group. J Neurosurg 105 (6): 444-51, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="89" PMID="20367335">Wells EM, Khademian ZP, Walsh KS, et al.: Postoperative cerebellar mutism syndrome following treatment of medulloblastoma: neuroradiographic features and origin. J Neurosurg Pediatr 5 (4): 329-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="90" PMID="21061011">Gudrunardottir T, Sehested A, Juhler M, et al.: Cerebellar mutism: review of the literature. Childs Nerv Syst 27 (3): 355-63, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="91" PMID="17066468">Wolfe-Christensen C, Mullins LL, Scott JG, et al.: Persistent psychosocial problems in children who develop posterior fossa syndrome after medulloblastoma resection. Pediatr Blood Cancer 49 (5): 723-6, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="92" PMID="31504816">Jabarkheel R, Amayiri N, Yecies D, et al.: Molecular correlates of cerebellar mutism syndrome in medulloblastoma. Neuro Oncol 22 (2): 290-297, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="93" PMID="33823018">Khan RB, Patay Z, Klimo P, et al.: Clinical features, neurologic recovery, and risk factors of postoperative posterior fossa syndrome and delayed recovery: a prospective study. Neuro Oncol 23 (9): 1586-1596, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="94" PMID="16943538">Packer RJ, Gajjar A, Vezina G, et al.: Phase III study of craniospinal radiation therapy followed by adjuvant chemotherapy for newly diagnosed average-risk medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 24 (25): 4202-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="95" PMID="26830377">Yock TI, Yeap BY, Ebb DH, et al.: Long-term toxic effects of proton radiotherapy for paediatric medulloblastoma: a phase 2 single-arm study. Lancet Oncol 17 (3): 287-98, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="96" PMID="26700707">Eaton BR, Esiashvili N, Kim S, et al.: Clinical Outcomes Among Children With Standard-Risk Medulloblastoma Treated With Proton and Photon Radiation Therapy: A Comparison of Disease Control and Overall Survival. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 94 (1): 133-8, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="97" PMID="29373195">Paulino AC, Mahajan A, Ye R, et al.: Ototoxicity and cochlear sparing in children with medulloblastoma: Proton vs. photon radiotherapy. Radiother Oncol 128 (1): 128-132, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="98" PMID="11481352" MedlineID="21374153">Ris MD, Packer R, Goldwein J, et al.: Intellectual outcome after reduced-dose radiation therapy plus adjuvant chemotherapy for medulloblastoma: a Children's Cancer Group study. J Clin Oncol 19 (15): 3470-6, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="99" PMID="2709111" MedlineID="89215996">Packer RJ, Sutton LN, Atkins TE, et al.: A prospective study of cognitive function in children receiving whole-brain radiotherapy and chemotherapy: 2-year results. J Neurosurg 70 (5): 707-13, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="100" PMID="8189255" MedlineID="94246439">Johnson DL, McCabe MA, Nicholson HS, et al.: Quality of long-term survival in young children with medulloblastoma. J Neurosurg 80 (6): 1004-10, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="101" PMID="10577843">Walter AW, Mulhern RK, Gajjar A, et al.: Survival and neurodevelopmental outcome of young children with medulloblastoma at St Jude Children's Research Hospital. J Clin Oncol 17 (12): 3720-8, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="102" PMID="18309946">Laughton SJ, Merchant TE, Sklar CA, et al.: Endocrine outcomes for children with embryonal brain tumors after risk-adapted craniospinal and conformal primary-site irradiation and high-dose chemotherapy with stem-cell rescue on the SJMB-96 trial. J Clin Oncol 26 (7): 1112-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="103" PMID="16234523">Geyer JR, Sposto R, Jennings M, et al.: Multiagent chemotherapy and deferred radiotherapy in infants with malignant brain tumors: a report from the Children's Cancer Group. J Clin Oncol 23 (30): 7621-31, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="104" PMID="15611503">Chi SN, Gardner SL, Levy AS, et al.: Feasibility and response to induction chemotherapy intensified with high-dose methotrexate for young children with newly diagnosed high-risk disseminated medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 22 (24): 4881-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="105" PMID="16054568">Grill J, Sainte-Rose C, Jouvet A, et al.: Treatment of medulloblastoma with postoperative chemotherapy alone: an SFOP prospective trial in young children. Lancet Oncol 6 (8): 573-80, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="106" PMID="26092413">Cohen BH, Geyer JR, Miller DC, et al.: Pilot Study of Intensive Chemotherapy With Peripheral Hematopoietic Cell Support for Children Less Than 3 Years of Age With Malignant Brain Tumors, the CCG-99703 Phase I/II Study. A Report From the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Neurol 53 (1): 31-46, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="107" PMID="8388548" MedlineID="93268341">Duffner PK, Horowitz ME, Krischer JP, et al.: Postoperative chemotherapy and delayed radiation in children less than three years of age with malignant brain tumors. N Engl J Med 328 (24): 1725-31, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="108" PMID="9049886" MedlineID="97202359">Ater JL, van Eys J, Woo SY, et al.: MOPP chemotherapy without irradiation as primary postsurgical therapy for brain tumors in infants and young children. J Neurooncol 32 (3): 243-52, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="109" PMID="19818598">Grundy RG, Wilne SH, Robinson KJ, et al.: Primary postoperative chemotherapy without radiotherapy for treatment of brain tumours other than ependymoma in children under 3 years: results of the first UKCCSG/SIOP CNS 9204 trial. Eur J Cancer 46 (1): 120-33, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="110" PMID="22790443">Blaney SM, Kocak M, Gajjar A, et al.: Pilot study of systemic and intrathecal mafosfamide followed by conformal radiation for infants with intracranial central nervous system tumors: a pediatric brain tumor consortium study (PBTC-001). J Neurooncol 109 (3): 565-71, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="111" PMID="32330099">Mynarek M, von Hoff K, Pietsch T, et al.: Nonmetastatic Medulloblastoma of Early Childhood: Results From the Prospective Clinical Trial HIT-2000 and An Extended Validation Cohort. J Clin Oncol 38 (18): 2028-2040, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="112" PMID="18293379">Dhall G, Grodman H, Ji L, et al.: Outcome of children less than three years old at diagnosis with non-metastatic medulloblastoma treated with chemotherapy on the "Head Start" I and II protocols. Pediatr Blood Cancer 50 (6): 1169-75, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="113" PMID="32304218">Dhall G, O'Neil SH, Ji L, et al.: Excellent outcome of young children with nodular desmoplastic medulloblastoma treated on "Head Start" III: a multi-institutional, prospective clinical trial. Neuro Oncol 22 (12): 1862-1872, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="114" PMID="36548930">Erker C, Mynarek M, Bailey S, et al.: Outcomes of Infants and Young Children With Relapsed Medulloblastoma After Initial Craniospinal Irradiation-Sparing Approaches: An International Cohort Study. J Clin Oncol 41 (10): 1921-1932, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="115" PMID="27145464">Lafay-Cousin L, Smith A, Chi SN, et al.: Clinical, Pathological, and Molecular Characterization of Infant Medulloblastomas Treated with Sequential High-Dose Chemotherapy. Pediatr Blood Cancer 63 (9): 1527-34, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="116" PMID="22851568">Ashley DM, Merchant TE, Strother D, et al.: Induction chemotherapy and conformal radiation therapy for very young children with nonmetastatic medulloblastoma: Children's Oncology Group study P9934. J Clin Oncol 30 (26): 3181-6, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="117" PMID="7931615" MedlineID="95017044">Packer RJ, Sutton LN, Elterman R, et al.: Outcome for children with medulloblastoma treated with radiation and cisplatin, CCNU, and vincristine chemotherapy. J Neurosurg 81 (5): 690-8, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="118" PMID="7623725" MedlineID="95349456">Bailey CC, Gnekow A, Wellek S, et al.: Prospective randomised trial of chemotherapy given before radiotherapy in childhood medulloblastoma. International Society of Paediatric Oncology (SIOP) and the (German) Society of Paediatric Oncology (GPO): SIOP II. Med Pediatr Oncol 25 (3): 166-78, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="119" PMID="10661332">Kortmann RD, Kühl J, Timmermann B, et al.: Postoperative neoadjuvant chemotherapy before radiotherapy as compared to immediate radiotherapy followed by maintenance chemotherapy in the treatment of medulloblastoma in childhood: results of the German prospective randomized trial HIT '91. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 46 (2): 269-79, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="120" PMID="15001263">Taylor RE, Bailey CC, Robinson KJ, et al.: Impact of radiotherapy parameters on outcome in the International Society of Paediatric Oncology/United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group PNET-3 study of preradiotherapy chemotherapy for M0-M1 medulloblastoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 58 (4): 1184-93, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="121" PMID="19250820">von Hoff K, Hinkes B, Gerber NU, et al.: Long-term outcome and clinical prognostic factors in children with medulloblastoma treated in the prospective randomised multicentre trial HIT'91. Eur J Cancer 45 (7): 1209-17, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="122" PMID="37498309">Cohen KJ, Munjapara V, Aguilera D, et al.: A Pilot Study Omitting Radiation in the Treatment of Children with Newly Diagnosed Wnt-Activated Medulloblastoma. Clin Cancer Res 29 (24): 5031-5037, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="123" PMID="10944134" MedlineID="20402475">Thomas PR, Deutsch M, Kepner JL, et al.: Low-stage medulloblastoma: final analysis of trial comparing standard-dose with reduced-dose neuraxis irradiation. J Clin Oncol 18 (16): 3004-11, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="124" PMID="35653134">Gupta T, Pervez S, Dasgupta A, et al.: Omission of Upfront Craniospinal Irradiation in Patients with Low-Risk WNT-Pathway Medulloblastoma Is Associated with Unacceptably High Risk of Neuraxial Failure. Clin Cancer Res 28 (19): 4180-4185, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="125" PMID="27423645">Sabel M, Fleischhack G, Tippelt S, et al.: Relapse patterns and outcome after relapse in standard risk medulloblastoma: a report from the HIT-SIOP-PNET4 study. J Neurooncol 129 (3): 515-524, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="126" PMID="16034048">Oyharcabal-Bourden V, Kalifa C, Gentet JC, et al.: Standard-risk medulloblastoma treated by adjuvant chemotherapy followed by reduced-dose craniospinal radiation therapy: a French Society of Pediatric Oncology Study. J Clin Oncol 23 (21): 4726-34, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="127" PMID="17892918">Merchant TE, Kun LE, Krasin MJ, et al.: Multi-institution prospective trial of reduced-dose craniospinal irradiation (23.4 Gy) followed by conformal posterior fossa (36 Gy) and primary site irradiation (55.8 Gy) and dose-intensive chemotherapy for average-risk medulloblastoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 70 (3): 782-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="128" PMID="9588920" MedlineID="98248334">Fukunaga-Johnson N, Sandler HM, Marsh R, et al.: The use of 3D conformal radiotherapy (3D CRT) to spare the cochlea in patients with medulloblastoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 41 (1): 77-82, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="129" PMID="11849779" MedlineID="21838864">Huang E, Teh BS, Strother DR, et al.: Intensity-modulated radiation therapy for pediatric medulloblastoma: early report on the reduction of ototoxicity. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 52 (3): 599-605, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="130" PMID="19273707">Carrie C, Grill J, Figarella-Branger D, et al.: Online quality control, hyperfractionated radiotherapy alone and reduced boost volume for standard risk medulloblastoma: long-term results of MSFOP 98. J Clin Oncol 27 (11): 1879-83, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="131" PMID="10561268" MedlineID="20029997">Packer RJ, Goldwein J, Nicholson HS, et al.: Treatment of children with medulloblastomas with reduced-dose craniospinal radiation therapy and adjuvant chemotherapy: A Children's Cancer Group Study. J Clin Oncol 17 (7): 2127-36, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="132" PMID="23956184">Nageswara Rao AA, Wallace DJ, Billups C, et al.: Cumulative cisplatin dose is not associated with event-free or overall survival in children with newly diagnosed average-risk medulloblastoma treated with cisplatin based adjuvant chemotherapy: report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (1): 102-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="133" PMID="30730781">Salloum R, Chen Y, Yasui Y, et al.: Late Morbidity and Mortality Among Medulloblastoma Survivors Diagnosed Across Three Decades: A Report From the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study. J Clin Oncol 37 (9): 731-740, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="134" PMID="16956759">Verlooy J, Mosseri V, Bracard S, et al.: Treatment of high risk medulloblastomas in children above the age of 3 years: a SFOP study. Eur J Cancer 42 (17): 3004-14, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="135" PMID="34292305">Leary SES, Packer RJ, Li Y, et al.: Efficacy of Carboplatin and Isotretinoin in Children With High-risk Medulloblastoma: A Randomized Clinical Trial From the Children's Oncology Group. JAMA Oncol 7 (9): 1313-1321, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="136" PMID="33377141">Dufour C, Foulon S, Geoffray A, et al.: Prognostic relevance of clinical and molecular risk factors in children with high-risk medulloblastoma treated in the phase II trial PNET HR+5. Neuro Oncol 23 (7): 1163-1172, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="137" PMID="19075266">Gandola L, Massimino M, Cefalo G, et al.: Hyperfractionated accelerated radiotherapy in the Milan strategy for metastatic medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 27 (4): 566-71, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="138" PMID="2319316" MedlineID="90204019">Evans AE, Jenkin RD, Sposto R, et al.: The treatment of medulloblastoma. Results of a prospective randomized trial of radiation therapy with and without CCNU, vincristine, and prednisone. J Neurosurg 72 (4): 572-82, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="139" PMID="22665539">Jakacki RI, Burger PC, Zhou T, et al.: Outcome of children with metastatic medulloblastoma treated with carboplatin during craniospinal radiotherapy: a Children's Oncology Group Phase I/II study. J Clin Oncol 30 (21): 2648-53, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="140" PMID="23857975">Tarbell NJ, Friedman H, Polkinghorn WR, et al.: High-risk medulloblastoma: a pediatric oncology group randomized trial of chemotherapy before or after radiation therapy (POG 9031). J Clin Oncol 31 (23): 2936-41, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="141" PMID="27863192">von Bueren AO, Kortmann RD, von Hoff K, et al.: Treatment of Children and Adolescents With Metastatic Medulloblastoma and Prognostic Relevance of Clinical and Biologic Parameters. J Clin Oncol 34 (34): 4151-4160, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1945"><Title>Childhood Nonmedulloblastoma Embryonal Tumors</Title><Para id="_2034">The 2021 World Health Organization (WHO) Classification of Tumors of the Central Nervous System (CNS) is listed below in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1949" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Cellular and Molecular Classification</SummaryRef> section. All nonmedulloblastoma tumors of neuroectodermal origin that lack the specific histopathological features or molecular alterations that define other CNS tumors are classified as CNS embryonal tumors.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> These tumors will be discussed in this section, with the exception of atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (AT/RTs). For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000587224" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment</SummaryRef>. Pineoblastoma will also be discussed in this summary because it shares histological features with the embryonal tumors and is conventionally treated in the same fashion. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1963" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Pineoblastoma</SummaryRef> section.</Para><SummarySection id="_1946"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_1947">For nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, presentation is also relatively rapid and depends on the location of the tumor in the nervous system.  Embryonal tumors tend to grow fast and are usually diagnosed within 3 months of initial onset of symptoms. </Para><Para id="_2010">Nonmedulloblastoma  embryonal tumors may occur anywhere in the CNS, and presentation is variable.  Usually there is significant neurological dysfunction associated with lethargy and vomiting. Supratentorial embryonal tumors (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_549" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Figure 1</SummaryRef>) result in focal neurological deficits such as hemiparesis and visual field loss, depending on which portion of the cerebral cortex is involved.  They may also result in seizures and obtundation.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1949"><Title>Cellular and Molecular Classification</Title><Para id="_748">The 2021 WHO Classification of Tumors of the CNS organizes nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors primarily by histological and immunohistological features and, in some cases, by molecular findings. The classification includes the following:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_2110" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT).</ListItem><ListItem>Cribriform neuroepithelial tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Embryonal tumor with multilayered rosettes (ETMR).</ListItem><ListItem>CNS neuroblastoma, <GeneName>FOXR2</GeneName>-activated.</ListItem><ListItem>CNS tumor with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> internal tandem duplication.</ListItem><ListItem>CNS embryonal tumor, not elsewhere classified (NEC)/not otherwise specified (NOS).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2111">NEC is defined as a tumor not elsewhere classified. The NOS nomenclature is used for tumors that cannot be further classified. For many lesions, there are overlapping histological features, and methylation-based clustering is critical for specific diagnosis.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> The contribution of DNA methylation profiling to correctly diagnose supratentorial embryonal tumors was demonstrated in a clinical trial of patients with supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors of the CNS (CNS-PNET) and pineoblastoma.<Reference refidx="3"/> For the pineoblastoma cases, there was high concordance between the diagnosis made by methylation profiling and the diagnosis made by central pathology review diagnosis (26 of 29). However, for the remaining 31 patients without pineoblastoma in the study, the diagnosis made by methylation profiling was high-grade glioma in 18 patients, AT/RT in 2 patients, and <GeneName>RELA</GeneName> fusion–positive ependymoma in 2 patients. Adjudication of discrepancies between the diagnosis made by central review pathology and the diagnosis made by methylation profiling was in favor of methylation profiling in the ten cases that were re-examined.</Para><SummarySection id="_1950"><Title>Subtypes of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000779395_6"><Title>Molecular subtypes of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779395_558">Studies applying unsupervised clustering of DNA methylation patterns for nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors found that approximately one-half of these tumors diagnosed as nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors showed molecular profiles characteristic of other known pediatric brain tumors (e.g., high-grade gliomas).<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> These observations highlight the utility of molecular characterization to assign this class of tumors to their appropriate biology-based diagnosis.</Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779395_559">Among the tumors diagnosed as nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, molecular characterization identified genomically and biologically distinctive subtypes, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000779395_560" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Cribriform neuroepithelial tumor:</Strong> Representing less than 50% of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, this subtype is a nonrhabdoid tumor that arises in the vicinity of the third, fourth, or lateral ventricles. This tumor is characterized by cribriform strands and ribbons and demonstrates loss of nuclear SMARCB1 expression. The median age at diagnosis is 20 months. This tumor occurs more often in males, with a male-to-female ratio of 1.5 to 1.<Reference refidx="6"/><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779395_587">Genomic characterization of ten cases of cribriform neuroepithelial tumors showed large heterozygous 22q deletions in nine of ten cases with <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> variants on the alternative allele.<Reference refidx="6"/> Cribriform neuroepithelial tumor showed DNA methylation profiles that matched those of the TYR subtype of atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT), a tumor that also arises in young children and shows loss of SMARCB1 expression. Patients with cribriform neuroepithelial tumors appear to have relatively favorable outcomes, in contrast to those of patients with AT/RT-TYR.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Embryonal tumor with multilayered rosettes (ETMR):</Strong> Representing up to 20% of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, this subtype combines embryonal, rosette-forming, neuroepithelial brain tumors that were previously categorized as either embryonal tumor with abundant neuropil and true rosettes (ETANTR), ependymoblastoma, or medulloepithelioma.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="7"/> ETMRs arise most commonly in young children (median age at diagnosis, 2–3 years) but may occur in older children.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> <Para id="_sm_CDR0000779395_561">ETMRs are defined at the molecular level by high-level amplification of the microRNA cluster C19MC and by a gene fusion between <GeneName>TTYH1</GeneName> and <GeneName>C19MC</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> This gene fusion puts expression of C19MC under control of the <GeneName>TTYH1</GeneName> promoter, leading to high-level aberrant expression of the microRNAs within the cluster. The World Health Organization (WHO) allows histologically similar tumors without <GeneName>C19MC</GeneName> alteration to be classified as ETMR, not otherwise specified (NOS). This subclass of tumors without <GeneName>C19MC</GeneName> alterations may harbor biallelic <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> variants.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Central nervous system (CNS) neuroblastoma with FOXR2 activation (CNS NB-FOXR2):</Strong> Representing 10% to 15% of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, this tumor may occur in children younger than 3 years, but it more frequently occurs in older children. This subtype is characterized by genomic alterations that lead to increased expression of the transcription factor FOXR2.<Reference refidx="4"/> CNS NB-FOXR2 is primarily observed in children younger than 10 years, and the histology of these tumors is typically that of CNS neuroblastoma or CNS ganglioneuroblastoma.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="14"/> There is no single genomic alteration among CNS NB-FOXR2 tumors leading to FOXR2 overexpression, with gene fusions involving multiple <GeneName>FOXR2</GeneName> partners identified.<Reference refidx="4"/> Protein expression of SOX10 and ANKRD55 detected by immunohistochemistry has been proposed as a potential biomarker to differentiate CNS NB-FOXR2 tumors from related tumor types.<Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS high-grade neuroepithelial tumor with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> alteration (CNS HGNET-BCOR):</Strong> Representing up to 3% of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, this subtype is characterized by internal tandem duplications of <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>,<Reference refidx="4"/> a genomic alteration that is also found in clear cell sarcoma of the kidney.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/> While the median age at diagnosis is younger than 10 years, cases arising in the second decade of life and beyond do occur.<Reference refidx="4"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000779395_582">Although not listed as separate entities in the 2021 WHO Classification of Tumors of the CNS, other nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors have also been described as separate entities, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000779395_583" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>CNS Ewing sarcoma family tumor with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> alteration (CNS EFT-CIC):</Strong> Representing 2% to 4% of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, this subtype is characterized by genomic alterations affecting <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> (located on chromosome 19q13.2), with fusion to <GeneName>NUTM1</GeneName> being identified in several cases tested.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene fusions are also identified in extra-CNS Ewing-like sarcomas, and the gene expression signature of CNS EFT-CIC tumors is similar to that of these sarcomas.<Reference refidx="4"/> CNS EFT-CIC tumors generally occur in children younger than 10 years and are characterized by a small cell phenotype but with variable histology.<Reference refidx="4"/> </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS high-grade neuroepithelial tumor with <GeneName>MN1</GeneName> alteration (CNS HGNET-MN1):</Strong> Representing 1% to 3% of nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, this subtype is characterized by gene fusions involving <GeneName>MN1</GeneName> (located on chromosome 22q12.3), with fusion partners including <GeneName>BEND2</GeneName> and <GeneName>CXXC5</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> The CNS HGNET-MN1 subtype shows a striking female predominance, and it tends to occur in the second decade of life.<Reference refidx="4"/> This subtype contained most cases carrying a diagnosis of astroblastoma per the 2007 WHO classification scheme.<Reference refidx="4"/> This subtype has not been added to the WHO diagnostic lexicon. Two other reports that together examined 35 cases of histologically defined astroblastoma found that 14 showed methylation profiles consistent with CNS HGNET-MN1 and/or <GeneName>MN1</GeneName> alterations by fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Medulloepithelioma:</Strong> Medulloepithelioma with the classic <GeneName>C19MC</GeneName> amplification is considered an ETMR, <GeneName>C19MC</GeneName>-altered (see the ETMR information above). However, when a tumor has the histological features of medulloepithelioma, but without a <GeneName>C19MC</GeneName> amplification, it is still identified as an ETMR.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> Medulloepithelioma tumors are rare and tend to arise most commonly in infants and young children. Medulloepitheliomas, which histologically recapitulate the embryonal neural tube, tend to arise supratentorially, primarily intraventricularly, but may arise infratentorially, in the cauda, and even extraneurally, along nerve roots.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> Intraocular medulloepithelioma is biologically distinct from intra-axial medulloepithelioma.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS embryonal tumor with <GeneName>PLAGL</GeneName> amplification:</Strong> A retrospective analysis of more than 90,000 pediatric and adult brain tumors identified a small subset of embryonal tumors (n = 31) with distinct methylation profiles and high-level amplification and overexpression of either <GeneName>PLAGL1</GeneName> or <GeneName>PLAGL2</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="23"/> Additional recurrent genetic alterations observed in other pediatric CNS tumor types were not observed in these cases. These tumors occurred throughout the brain and were most commonly composed of primitive embryonal-like cells without markers of glial or neuronal differentiation. In this small cohort, differences in age at diagnosis and 10-year overall survival (OS) rates were reported between patients with <GeneName>PLAGL1</GeneName> amplification (median age, 10.5 years; OS rate, 66%) and patients with <GeneName>PLAGL2</GeneName> amplification (median age, 2 years; OS rate, 25%).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1948"><Title>Staging Evaluation</Title><Para id="_326">Patients with nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors are staged in a fashion similar to that used for children with medulloblastoma. However, these patients are not assigned to average-risk and high-risk subgroups for treatment purposes because all patients are considered high risk. For more information, see  the medulloblastoma <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1882" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Staging Evaluation</SummaryRef> section.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1953"><Title>Treatment of Childhood Nonmedulloblastoma Embryonal Tumors</Title><Para id="_756">For more information about the treatment of CNS AT/RTs, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000587224" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_758">For more information about the treatment of medulloepithelioma, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1962" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Childhood Embryonal Tumors With Multilayered Rosettes or Medulloepithelioma</SummaryRef> section.</Para><SummarySection id="_1954"><Title>Treatment of children aged  3 years and younger</Title><Para id="_2112">The optimal treatment of childhood nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors remains unclear and under study. Retrospective studies of fairly large numbers of patients have suggested management approaches for the more common subgroups, including AT/RTs, ETMRs, and <GeneName>FOXR2</GeneName>-activated tumors. For more information about the treatment of AT/RTs, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000587224" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_2011">Standard treatment options for children aged 3 years and younger with newly diagnosed nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, excluding AT/RTs, ETMRs, and <GeneName>FOXR2</GeneName>-activated tumors, include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_2012" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Adjuvant chemotherapy.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_68">Treatment of children aged 3 years and younger  with embryonal tumors  is similar to that outlined for children aged 3 years and younger with medulloblastoma.  Aggressive surgical resection is reasonable, given the improved rate of survival for medulloblastomas and other ETMRs after total or near-total resection.<Reference refidx="11"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1916" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of younger children with medulloblastoma</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_511">With the use of chemotherapy alone, outcome has been variable, with survival rates at 5 years ranging between 0% and  50%.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/>; <Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] The addition of craniospinal irradiation to chemotherapy-based regimens may successfully treat some children but with anticipated neurodevelopmental decline.<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] Localized radiation therapy to the tumor site, either before or after chemotherapy, has been given, although data supporting its efficacy are unclear.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1956"><Title>Treatment of children older than 3 years</Title><Para id="_501">Standard treatment options for children older than 3 years with newly diagnosed nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors, excluding AT/RTs, ETMRs, and <GeneName>FOXR2</GeneName>-activated tumors,  include the following:

</Para><OrderedList id="_502" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1957" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1960" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant radiation therapy.</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2014" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_1957"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_2033">Evidence (surgery): </Para><OrderedList id="_1959" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors are often amenable to resection. In reported case series, 50% to 75% of tumors in patients were totally or near-totally resected.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/>; <Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Attempting aggressive surgical resection is the first step in the management of newly diagnosed nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors. Although previous studies did not demonstrate that the extent of resection is predictive of outcome,<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/> one study demonstrated improved survival when the tumor was completely resected.<Reference refidx="32"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] A published study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00392327">COG-ACNS0332 [NCT00392327]</ProtocolRef>) of molecularly classified nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors revealed improved overall survival (OS) for patients who had less than 1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of residual disease, compared with patients who had more than 1.5 cm<Superscript>2</Superscript> of residual disease.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1960"><Title>Adjuvant radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_508">After surgery, children with nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors usually receive treatment similar to that received by children with high-risk medulloblastoma.</Para><Para id="_2013">Conventionally, patients are treated with  radiation to the entire neuraxis with local boost radiation therapy, as given for medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="31"/>  Local boost radiation therapy may be problematic because of the size of the tumor and its location in the cerebral cortex.  Also, there is no definitive evidence that craniospinal radiation therapy is superior to radiation to the primary tumor site alone in children with nondisseminated lesions.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2014"><Title>Adjuvant chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_2015">The chemotherapeutic approaches during and after radiation therapy are similar to those used for children with high-risk medulloblastoma. The 3-year to 5-year OS rates range from 25% to 50%.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/>; <Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="34"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_2016"> In a published study of nonpineal tumors that were diagnosed as CNS primitive neuroectodermal tumors (PNETs) by traditional pathology, 71% of cases were revealed to be glioblastoma or another diagnosis by DNA methylation studies. Patients with nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors (n = 36) (including pineoblastomas, n = 26) had a 5-year OS rate of 78.5% (95% confidence interval [CI], 62.2%–94.8%).  In contrast, the patients with glioblastoma had a 5-year OS rate of 12% (95% CI, 0%–24.7%). The study showed no benefit for children who received carboplatin or isotretinoin.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] This study highlights the importance of molecular classification of tumors traditionally termed CNS-PNET.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1962"><Title>Treatment of Childhood Embryonal Tumors With Multilayered Rosettes or Medulloepithelioma</Title><Para id="_2093">A registry-based review of 159 patients with a confirmed molecular diagnosis of ETMR reported survival results for different treatments.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_2113" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 2-year event-free survival (EFS) and OS rates were 0% for patients treated with conventional chemotherapy without radiation therapy, regardless of the degree of surgical resection.</ListItem><ListItem>The 2-year EFS rate was 21%  and the OS rate was 30% for patients who had a gross-total resection and were treated with high-dose chemotherapy without  radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>The 2-year EFS rate was 44% for children treated with high-dose chemotherapy and radiation therapy after a subtotal resection and 66% for patients treated with high-dose chemotherapy and radiation therapy after a gross-total resection. </ListItem><ListItem>The relative roles of focal radiation therapy versus craniospinal radiation therapy could not be assessed in this review. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2114">In a separate, but possibly overlapping, international retrospective review, 49 patients with histologically confirmed (by the treating institution) ETMRs were treated between 1988 to 2017 in a variety of ways.<Reference refidx="35"/> The 5-year progression-free survival rate was 18% (± 6%),  and the OS rate was 24% (± 6%). Most survivors received radiation therapy, including both local and craniospinal treatment, and there was no clear difference in outcomes between the types and extent of radiation therapy. The relative benefits of conventional chemotherapy compared with high-dose chemotherapy could not be assessed.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_2123">In a subsequent publication, likely including some of the patients from the retrospective study, treatment was limited to only those who received chemotherapy and radiation therapy on the prospective P-HIT study or per the study protocol. The P-HIT study included postsurgery chemotherapy, high-dose chemotherapy, and  radiation for some patients. In 35 patients with ETMRs, 8 long-term survivors were identified, 6 of whom had received either craniospinal or local radiation therapy, in addition to induction and high-dose chemotherapy. None of the patients who presented with brain stem disease survived. The 5-year survival was best for patients with localized disease, possibly for those treated with both induction and high-dose chemotherapy. The role of radiation therapy or the optimal volume of radiation therapy (local versus craniospinal) could not be determined.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_2124">These studies suggest that the outcome for children with ETMRs may not be as dire as suggested by initial studies, which found a 5-year survival rate of 25% or lower. Outcome is more favorable in children with localized disease at the time of diagnosis and those who were treated with aggressive postsurgical chemotherapy, including induction and high-dose consolidation treatment. The role of radiation therapy is still unproven, and there is no evidence that craniospinal radiation in patients with localized disease is superior to focal radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2115"><Title>Treatment of CNS Neuroblastoma, <GeneName>FOXR2</GeneName>-Activated</Title><Para id="_2116">The optimal treatment of patients with CNS neuroblastoma, <GeneName>FOXR2</GeneName>-activated tumors has not been confirmed by prospective studies. In a retrospective review of patients diagnosed between 1988 and 2007, the highest rates of survival were seen after complete or near-complete resections in patients with nonmetastatic tumors who also received craniospinal radiation therapy and possibly chemotherapy. With this type of approach, up to 75% of children (35 of 42) were alive 5 years after diagnosis and treatment. This tumor tends to occur in a somewhat older population than some of the other nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors.<Reference refidx="5"/> </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="34185076">Louis DN, Perry A, Wesseling P, et al.: The 2021 WHO Classification of Tumors of the Central Nervous System: a summary. Neuro Oncol 23 (8): 1231-1251, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="2">WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board, ed.: WHO Classification of Tumours: Central Nervous System Tumours. Vol. 6. 5th ed. IARC Press; 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="30332335">Hwang EI, Kool M, Burger PC, et al.: Extensive Molecular and Clinical Heterogeneity in Patients With Histologically Diagnosed CNS-PNET Treated as a Single Entity: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group Randomized ACNS0332 Trial. J Clin Oncol : JCO2017764720, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="26919435">Sturm D, Orr BA, Toprak UH, et al.: New Brain Tumor Entities Emerge from Molecular Classification of CNS-PNETs. Cell 164 (5): 1060-72, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="34077956">von Hoff K, Haberler C, Schmitt-Hoffner F, et al.: Therapeutic implications of improved molecular diagnostics for rare CNS embryonal tumor entities: results of an international, retrospective study. Neuro Oncol 23 (9): 1597-1611, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="27380723">Johann PD, Hovestadt V, Thomas C, et al.: Cribriform neuroepithelial tumor: molecular characterization of a SMARCB1-deficient non-rhabdoid tumor with favorable long-term outcome. Brain Pathol 27 (4): 411-418, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="24337497">Korshunov A, Sturm D, Ryzhova M, et al.: Embryonal tumor with abundant neuropil and true rosettes (ETANTR), ependymoblastoma, and medulloepithelioma share molecular similarity and comprise a single clinicopathological entity. Acta Neuropathol 128 (2): 279-89, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="22691720">Picard D, Miller S, Hawkins CE, et al.: Markers of survival and metastatic potential in childhood CNS primitive neuro-ectodermal brain tumours: an integrative genomic analysis. Lancet Oncol 13 (8): 838-48, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="24839957">Spence T, Sin-Chan P, Picard D, et al.: CNS-PNETs with C19MC amplification and/or LIN28 expression comprise a distinct histogenetic diagnostic and therapeutic entity. Acta Neuropathol 128 (2): 291-303, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="33908610">Juhnke BO, Gessi M, Gerber NU, et al.: Treatment of embryonal tumors with multilayered rosettes with carboplatin/etoposide induction and high-dose chemotherapy within the prospective P-HIT trial. Neuro Oncol 24 (1): 127-137, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="34599879">Khan S, Solano-Paez P, Suwal T, et al.: Clinical phenotypes and prognostic features of embryonal tumours with multi-layered rosettes: a Rare Brain Tumor Registry study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health 5 (11): 800-813, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="24316981">Kleinman CL, Gerges N, Papillon-Cavanagh S, et al.: Fusion of TTYH1 with the C19MC microRNA cluster drives expression of a brain-specific DNMT3B isoform in the embryonal brain tumor ETMR. Nat Genet 46 (1): 39-44, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="19962671">Li M, Lee KF, Lu Y, et al.: Frequent amplification of a chr19q13.41 microRNA polycistron in aggressive primitive neuroectodermal brain tumors. Cancer Cell 16 (6): 533-46, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="33536079">Korshunov A, Okonechnikov K, Schmitt-Hoffner F, et al.: Molecular analysis of pediatric CNS-PNET revealed nosologic heterogeneity and potent diagnostic markers for CNS neuroblastoma with FOXR2-activation. Acta Neuropathol Commun 9 (1): 20, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="26098867">Ueno-Yokohata H, Okita H, Nakasato K, et al.: Consistent in-frame internal tandem duplications of BCOR characterize clear cell sarcoma of the kidney. Nat Genet 47 (8): 861-3, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="26573325">Roy A, Kumar V, Zorman B, et al.: Recurrent internal tandem duplications of BCOR in clear cell sarcoma of the kidney. Nat Commun 6: 8891, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="28960623">Wood MD, Tihan T, Perry A, et al.: Multimodal molecular analysis of astroblastoma enables reclassification of most cases into more specific molecular entities. Brain Pathol 28 (2): 192-202, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="30876455">Lehman NL, Usubalieva A, Lin T, et al.: Genomic analysis demonstrates that histologically-defined astroblastomas are molecularly heterogeneous and that tumors with MN1 rearrangement exhibit the most favorable prognosis. Acta Neuropathol Commun 7 (1): 42, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="17618441">Louis DN, Ohgaki H, Wiestler OD, et al.: The 2007 WHO classification of tumours of the central nervous system. Acta Neuropathol 114 (2): 97-109, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="9548346">Sharma MC, Mahapatra AK, Gaikwad S, et al.: Pigmented medulloepithelioma: report of a case and review of the literature. Childs Nerv Syst 14 (1-2): 74-8, 1998 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="25748578">Jakobiec FA, Kool M, Stagner AM, et al.: Intraocular Medulloepitheliomas and Embryonal Tumors With Multilayered Rosettes of the Brain: Comparative Roles of LIN28A and C19MC. Am J Ophthalmol 159 (6): 1065-1074.e1, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="26183384">Korshunov A, Jakobiec FA, Eberhart CG, et al.: Comparative integrated molecular analysis of intraocular medulloepitheliomas and central nervous system embryonal tumors with multilayered rosettes confirms that they are distinct nosologic entities. Neuropathology 35 (6): 538-44, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="36437415">Keck MK, Sill M, Wittmann A, et al.: Amplification of the PLAG-family genes-PLAGL1 and PLAGL2-is a key feature of the novel tumor type CNS embryonal tumor with PLAGL amplification. Acta Neuropathol 145 (1): 49-69, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="16234523">Geyer JR, Sposto R, Jennings M, et al.: Multiagent chemotherapy and deferred radiotherapy in infants with malignant brain tumors: a report from the Children's Cancer Group. J Clin Oncol 23 (30): 7621-31, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="11813171">Marec-Berard P, Jouvet A, Thiesse P, et al.: Supratentorial embryonal tumors in children under 5 years of age: an SFOP study of treatment with postoperative chemotherapy alone. Med Pediatr Oncol 38 (2): 83-90, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="16054568">Grill J, Sainte-Rose C, Jouvet A, et al.: Treatment of medulloblastoma with postoperative chemotherapy alone: an SFOP prospective trial in young children. Lancet Oncol 6 (8): 573-80, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="17668858">Fangusaro J, Finlay J, Sposto R, et al.: Intensive chemotherapy followed by consolidative myeloablative chemotherapy with autologous hematopoietic cell rescue (AuHCR) in young children with newly diagnosed supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors (sPNETs): report of the Head Start I and II experience. Pediatr Blood Cancer 50 (2): 312-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="23223339">Friedrich C, von Bueren AO, von Hoff K, et al.: Treatment of young children with CNS-primitive neuroectodermal tumors/pineoblastomas in the prospective multicenter trial HIT 2000 using different chemotherapy regimens and radiotherapy. Neuro Oncol 15 (2): 224-34, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="7602359" MedlineID="95325887">Cohen BH, Zeltzer PM, Boyett JM, et al.: Prognostic factors and treatment results for supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors in children using radiation and chemotherapy: a Childrens Cancer Group randomized trial. J Clin Oncol 13 (7): 1687-96, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="10813733" MedlineID="20273504">Reddy AT, Janss AJ, Phillips PC, et al.: Outcome for children with supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors treated with surgery, radiation, and chemotherapy. Cancer 88 (9): 2189-93, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="11821469" MedlineID="21679506">Timmermann B, Kortmann RD, Kühl J, et al.: Role of radiotherapy in the treatment of supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors in childhood: results of the prospective German brain tumor trials HIT 88/89 and 91. J Clin Oncol 20 (3): 842-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="25704363">Jakacki RI, Burger PC, Kocak M, et al.: Outcome and prognostic factors for children with supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors treated with carboplatin during radiotherapy: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (5): 776-83, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="18796696">Chintagumpala M, Hassall T, Palmer S, et al.: A pilot study of risk-adapted radiotherapy and chemotherapy in patients with supratentorial PNET. Neuro Oncol 11 (1): 33-40, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="17619825">Johnston DL, Keene DL, Lafay-Cousin L, et al.: Supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors: a Canadian pediatric brain tumor consortium report. J Neurooncol 86 (1): 101-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="35982322">Liu APY, Dhanda SK, Lin T, et al.: Molecular classification and outcome of children with rare CNS embryonal tumors: results from St. Jude Children's Research Hospital including the multi-center SJYC07 and SJMB03 clinical trials. Acta Neuropathol 144 (4): 733-746, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1963"><Title>Childhood Pineoblastoma</Title><Para id="_2035">The World Health Organization classifies pineoblastomas in the tumors of the pineal region group. However, they are discussed in this summary because they share histological features with other embryonal tumors and are conventionally treated like other embryonal tumors.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><SummarySection id="_1964"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_1975">Pineoblastoma often results in hydrocephalus due to blockage of cerebrospinal fluid at the third ventricular level and other symptoms related to pressure on the back of the brain stem in the tectal region.  Symptoms may include a constellation of abnormalities in eye movements  (Parinaud syndrome), manifested by pupils that react poorly to light but better to accommodation, loss of upgaze, retraction or convergence nystagmus, and lid retraction.  As they grow, these tumors may also cause hemiparesis and ataxia.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1966"><Title>Cellular and Molecular Classification</Title><Para id="_751">Pineoblastoma is histologically similar to medulloblastoma and shares histological features with embryonal tumors. It is classified as a subgroup of pineal parenchymal tumors.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_2205">Pineoblastoma can be classified into four distinctive subtypes with unique clinical and molecular characteristics:<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_2206" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The microRNA (miRNA) processing–altered 1 (PB-miRNA1) and miRNA processing–altered 2 (PB-miRNA2) subtypes are characterized by somatic or germline variants involving microRNA biogenesis genes (<GeneName>DICER1</GeneName>, <GeneName>DROSHA</GeneName>, and <GeneName>DGCR8</GeneName>). They are distinguished from each other by their DNA methylation profiles.</ListItem><ListItem>The PB-MYC/FOXR2 subtype shows <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> activation and FOXR2 overexpression.</ListItem><ListItem>The PB-RB1 subtype has <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> alterations, and a minority of cases have a clinical diagnosis of trilateral retinoblastoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2207">Additional information about each of the subtypes is provided below.</Para><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000799201_581"><Title>Genomics of Pineoblastoma</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000799201_563">Pineoblastoma, which was previously conventionally grouped with embryonal tumors, is now categorized by the World Health Organization as a pineal parenchymal tumor. Given that therapies for pineoblastoma are quite similar to those used for embryonal tumors, the previous convention of including pineoblastoma with the central nervous system embryonal tumors is followed here. Pineoblastoma is associated with germline pathogenic variants in both the <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> gene and the <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> gene, as described below:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000799201_564" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Pineoblastoma is associated with germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>RB1</GeneName>. The term trilateral retinoblastoma is used to refer to ocular retinoblastoma in combination with a histologically similar brain tumor generally arising in the pineal gland or other midline structures. Historically, intracranial tumors have been reported in 5% to 15% of children with heritable retinoblastoma.<Reference refidx="8"/> Rates of pineoblastoma among children with heritable retinoblastoma who undergo current treatment programs may be lower than these historical estimates.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> In a study of patients with molecularly classified pineal parenchymal tumors, 6 of 221 cases (3%) had a clinical diagnosis of trilateral retinoblastoma.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem><ListItem>Germline <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> pathogenic variants occur in some patients with pineoblastoma.<Reference refidx="12"/> In one study, among 18 patients with pineoblastoma, 3 patients with <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants were identified, and an additional 3 patients known to be carriers of germline <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> pathogenic variants developed pineoblastoma.<Reference refidx="12"/> The <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> variants in patients with pineoblastoma are loss-of-function variants that appear to be distinct from the variants observed in DICER1 syndrome–related tumors such as pleuropulmonary blastoma.<Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000799201_583">Genomic methods have been applied to pineoblastoma in an attempt to learn more about the tumor biology and guide future molecular classification. A retrospective, international meta-analysis included 221 children and adults diagnosed with pineoblastoma (n = 178) and pineal parenchymal tumors of intermediate differentiation (PPTID) (n = 43).<Reference refidx="7"/> The evaluation identified four molecular groups of pineoblastoma based on DNA methylation, transcriptome profiling, and gene sequencing, as described below.</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000799201_586" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The microRNA (miRNA) processing–altered 1 (PB-miRNA1) and miRNA processing–altered 2 (PB-miRNA2) subtypes are characterized by somatic or germline variants involving miRNA biogenesis genes (<GeneName>DICER1</GeneName>, <GeneName>DROSHA</GeneName>, and <GeneName>DGCR8</GeneName>).<ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000799201_587" Style="bullet"><ListItem>PB-miRNA1 represented approximately 50% of molecularly classified pineoblastoma cases, while PB-miRNA2 represented approximately 15% of the cases.</ListItem><ListItem>The median age at presentation of PB-miRNA1 was approximately 8 years, and the median age at presentation of PB-miRNA2 was 12 years.</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year survival rate for patients with PB-miRNA2 (100%) exceeded that for patients with PB-miRNA1 (70%).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The PB-MYC/FOXR2 subtype shows <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> activation (sometimes with <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> copy number gain and occasionally with <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> amplification) and FOXR2 overexpression. <ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000799201_588" Style="bullet"><ListItem>PB-MYC/FOXR2 represented approximately 20% of molecularly classified pineoblastoma cases.</ListItem><ListItem>PB-MYC/FOXR2 cases presented at a young age (median, 1.4 years).</ListItem><ListItem>Approximately 40% of patients with PB-MYC/FOXR2 presented with metastatic disease.</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year survival rate for patients with PB-MYC/FOXR2 was approximately 20%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The PB-RB1 subtype has <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> alterations. In one study, 6 of 25 patients with the PB-RB1 subtype had a clinical diagnosis of trilateral retinoblastoma.<ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000799201_589" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The PB-RB1 subtype represented approximately 10% of molecularly classified pineoblastoma cases.</ListItem><ListItem>Approximately 70% of PB-RB1 cases presented with metastatic disease.</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year survival rate for patients with PB-RB1 was approximately 30%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Cases with DNA methylation profiles indicating PPTID sometimes had a histological diagnosis of pineoblastoma, but the clinical and biological characteristics of these cases were distinctive from those of the pineoblastoma subtypes described above.<ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000799201_590" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Approximately 75% of cases with a molecular classification of PPTID had tumors with variants in <GeneName>KBTBD4</GeneName>, a gene that is also altered in group 3 and 4 medulloblastomas.</ListItem><ListItem>Most PPTID cases occurred in adults, with a median age exceeding 30 years.</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year survival rate for patients with PPTID was 85%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1965"><Title>Staging Evaluation</Title><Para id="_324">Dissemination at the time of diagnosis occurs in 10% to 30% of patients with pineoblastoma.<Reference refidx="13"/> Because of the  location of the tumor, total resections are uncommon, and most patients have only a biopsy or a subtotal resection before postsurgical treatment.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> Staging for children with pineoblastomas is the same as for children with medulloblastoma. However, the patients are not assigned to average-risk and high-risk subgroups for treatment purposes.<Reference refidx="13"/> For more information, see the medulloblastoma <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1882" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Staging Evaluation</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1967"><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Childhood Pineoblastoma</Title><Para id="_1982"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1978" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Table 4</SummaryRef> describes the treatment options for newly diagnosed and recurrent childhood pineoblastoma.</Para><Table id="_1978"><Title>Table 4. Treatment Options for Childhood Pineoblastoma</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="18.97%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="44.02%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="37.00%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">Treatment Group</entry><entry>Treatment Options</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="5"><Strong>Newly diagnosed</Strong> childhood pineoblastoma</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Children aged 3 years and younger</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2030" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Biopsy</SummaryRef> (for diagnosis) and total resection, if possible </entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2031" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2032" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">High-dose, marrow-ablative chemotherapy with autologous bone marrow rescue or peripheral stem cell rescue</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Children older than 3 years</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1971" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1973" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2020" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Recurrent</Strong> childhood pineoblastoma </entry><entry>There are no standard treatment options. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_71" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Recurrent Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other CNS Embryonal Tumors</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1968"><Title>Treatment of Childhood Pineoblastoma</Title><SummarySection id="_1969"><Title>Treatment of children aged 3 years and younger</Title><Para id="_2017">No standard treatment options currently exist for children aged 3 years and younger with pineoblastoma.<Reference refidx="15"/> The following treatment approaches are available:</Para><OrderedList id="_2018" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2030" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Biopsy (for diagnosis) and total resection, if possible</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2031" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2032" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">High-dose, marrow-ablative chemotherapy with autologous bone marrow rescue or peripheral stem cell rescue</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_2030"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_433">Biopsy and, if possible, total resection, is usually performed to diagnose pineoblastoma.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2031"><Title>Adjuvant chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_60">Children aged 3 years and younger with pineoblastoma are usually treated initially with chemotherapy in the hope of delaying, if not obviating, the need for radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="16"/> Overall prognosis for this group remains very poor.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/> In two sequential, multicenter, prospective clinical trials, all five children younger than 3 years who were treated with chemotherapy died.<Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]  In children responding to chemotherapy, the timing and amount of radiation therapy required after chemotherapy is unclear. The addition of craniospinal irradiation to chemotherapy-based regimens may successfully treat some children but with anticipated neurodevelopmental decline.<Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] Two large pooled analyses both revealed dismal survival for children younger than 3 or 4 years with pineoblastoma.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2032"><Title>High-dose, marrow-ablative chemotherapy with autologous bone marrow rescue or peripheral stem cell rescue</Title><Para id="_434">High-dose, marrow-ablative chemotherapy with autologous bone marrow rescue or peripheral stem cell rescue has been used with some success in young children.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] Two pooled analyses also revealed this modality may have some efficacy.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1970"><Title>Treatment of children older than 3 years</Title><Para id="_513">Standard treatment options for children older than 3 years with newly diagnosed pineoblastoma include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_514" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1971" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_1973" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant radiation therapy.</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_2020" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_1971"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_517">Surgery is usually the initial treatment for patients with pineoblastoma to diagnose the tumor.<Reference refidx="23"/> Total resections have been associated with better outcomes.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1973"><Title>Adjuvant radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_519">The usual postsurgical treatment for patients with pineoblastoma begins with radiation therapy, although some trials have used preradiation chemotherapy.  The total dose of radiation therapy to the tumor site is 54 Gy to 55.8 Gy using conventional fractionation.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_2019">Craniospinal irradiation with doses of 23.4 Gy to 36 Gy are also recommended because of the propensity of this tumor to disseminate throughout the subarachnoid space.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="17"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2020"><Title>Adjuvant chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_2021">Chemotherapy is usually given in the same way as outlined for high-risk medulloblastomas in children with nondisseminated disease at the time of diagnosis.<Reference refidx="15"/>  For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_38" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of children older than 3 years with high-risk medulloblastoma</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_2022">The 5-year disease-free survival rate exceeds 50% in children with localized disease at diagnosis who undergo aggressive resection.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] The Children's Oncology Group (COG) <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00392327">COG-ACNS0332 (NCT00392327)</ProtocolRef> study of 36 patients with nonmedulloblastoma embryonal tumors (which included 26 pineoblastomas) reported a 5-year overall survival (OS) rate of 78.5% (95% confidence interval, 62.2%–94.8%).<Reference refidx="25"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_2023">For patients with disseminated disease at the time of diagnosis, survival is considerably poorer.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> In the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00392327">COG-ACNS0332 (NCT00392327)</ProtocolRef> study, there was no significant difference in event-free survival or OS according to metastatic status.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1974"><Title>Treatment options under clinical evaluation for childhood pineoblastoma</Title><Para id="_58">For patients with pineoblastoma, a variety of different treatment approaches are under evaluation, including the use of higher doses of chemotherapy after radiation therapy supported by peripheral stem cell rescue and the use of chemotherapy during radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_1813">Early-phase therapeutic trials may be available for selected patients. These trials may be available via the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.childrensoncologygroup.org/">COG</ExternalRef>, the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.pbtc.org/">Pediatric Brain Tumor Consortium</ExternalRef>, or other entities.  Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="27157931">Louis DN, Perry A, Reifenberger G, et al.: The 2016 World Health Organization Classification of Tumors of the Central Nervous System: a summary. Acta Neuropathol 131 (6): 803-20, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="34185076">Louis DN, Perry A, Wesseling P, et al.: The 2021 WHO Classification of Tumors of the Central Nervous System: a summary. Neuro Oncol 23 (8): 1231-1251, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3">WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board, ed.: WHO Classification of Tumours: Central Nervous System Tumours. Vol. 6. 5th ed. IARC Press; 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Chintagumpala MM, Paulino A, Panigrahy A, et al.: Embryonal and pineal region tumors. In: Pizzo PA, Poplack DG, eds.: Principles and Practice of Pediatric Oncology. 7th ed. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2015, pp 671-99.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31820118">Li BK, Vasiljevic A, Dufour C, et al.: Pineoblastoma segregates into molecular sub-groups with distinct clinico-pathologic features: a Rare Brain Tumor Consortium registry study. Acta Neuropathol 139 (2): 223-241, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="31768671">Pfaff E, Aichmüller C, Sill M, et al.: Molecular subgrouping of primary pineal parenchymal tumors reveals distinct subtypes correlated with clinical parameters and genetic alterations. Acta Neuropathol 139 (2): 243-257, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="33619588">Liu APY, Li BK, Pfaff E, et al.: Clinical and molecular heterogeneity of pineal parenchymal tumors: a consensus study. Acta Neuropathol 141 (5): 771-785, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25126964">de Jong MC, Kors WA, de Graaf P, et al.: Trilateral retinoblastoma: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Oncol 15 (10): 1157-67, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="23876864">Ramasubramanian A, Kytasty C, Meadows AT, et al.: Incidence of pineal gland cyst and pineoblastoma in children with retinoblastoma during the chemoreduction era. Am J Ophthalmol 156 (4): 825-9, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="24238207">Abramson DH, Dunkel IJ, Marr BP, et al.: Incidence of pineal gland cyst and pineoblastoma in children with retinoblastoma during the chemoreduction era. Am J Ophthalmol 156 (6): 1319-20, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="21826785">Turaka K, Shields CL, Meadows AT, et al.: Second malignant neoplasms following chemoreduction with carboplatin, etoposide, and vincristine in 245 patients with intraocular retinoblastoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 59 (1): 121-5, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="25022261">de Kock L, Sabbaghian N, Druker H, et al.: Germ-line and somatic DICER1 mutations in pineoblastoma. Acta Neuropathol 128 (4): 583-95, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="7751882" MedlineID="95271259">Jakacki RI, Zeltzer PM, Boyett JM, et al.: Survival and prognostic factors following radiation and/or chemotherapy for primitive neuroectodermal tumors of the pineal region in infants and children: a report of the Childrens Cancer Group. J Clin Oncol 13 (6): 1377-83, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="11821469" MedlineID="21679506">Timmermann B, Kortmann RD, Kühl J, et al.: Role of radiotherapy in the treatment of supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors in childhood: results of the prospective German brain tumor trials HIT 88/89 and 91. J Clin Oncol 20 (3): 842-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="39073785">Liu APY, Li BK, Vasiljevic A, et al.: SNO-EANO-EURACAN consensus on management of pineal parenchymal tumors. Neuro Oncol 26 (12): 2159-2173, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="9440745" MedlineID="98101695">Mason WP, Grovas A, Halpern S, et al.: Intensive chemotherapy and bone marrow rescue for young children with newly diagnosed malignant brain tumors. J Clin Oncol 16 (1): 210-21, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="31802236">Liu APY, Gudenas B, Lin T, et al.: Risk-adapted therapy and biological heterogeneity in pineoblastoma: integrated clinico-pathological analysis from the prospective, multi-center SJMB03 and SJYC07 trials. Acta Neuropathol 139 (2): 259-271, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="35664557">Hansford JR, Huang J, Endersby R, et al.: Pediatric pineoblastoma: A pooled outcome study of North American and Australian therapeutic data. Neurooncol Adv 4 (1): vdac056, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="28011926">Mynarek M, Pizer B, Dufour C, et al.: Evaluation of age-dependent treatment strategies for children and young adults with pineoblastoma: analysis of pooled European Society for Paediatric Oncology (SIOP-E) and US Head Start data. Neuro Oncol 19 (4): 576-585, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="16941074">Hinkes BG, von Hoff K, Deinlein F, et al.: Childhood pineoblastoma: experiences from the prospective multicenter trials HIT-SKK87, HIT-SKK92 and HIT91. J Neurooncol 81 (2): 217-23, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="23223339">Friedrich C, von Bueren AO, von Hoff K, et al.: Treatment of young children with CNS-primitive neuroectodermal tumors/pineoblastomas in the prospective multicenter trial HIT 2000 using different chemotherapy regimens and radiotherapy. Neuro Oncol 15 (2): 224-34, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="17668858">Fangusaro J, Finlay J, Sposto R, et al.: Intensive chemotherapy followed by consolidative myeloablative chemotherapy with autologous hematopoietic cell rescue (AuHCR) in young children with newly diagnosed supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors (sPNETs): report of the Head Start I and II experience. Pediatr Blood Cancer 50 (2): 312-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="25704363">Jakacki RI, Burger PC, Kocak M, et al.: Outcome and prognostic factors for children with supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors treated with carboplatin during radiotherapy: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (5): 776-83, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="12775745">Gururangan S, McLaughlin C, Quinn J, et al.: High-dose chemotherapy with autologous stem-cell rescue in children and adults with newly diagnosed pineoblastomas. J Clin Oncol 21 (11): 2187-91, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="30332335">Hwang EI, Kool M, Burger PC, et al.: Extensive Molecular and Clinical Heterogeneity in Patients With Histologically Diagnosed CNS-PNET Treated as a Single Entity: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group Randomized ACNS0332 Trial. J Clin Oncol : JCO2017764720, 2018.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_71"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000562071">recurrent childhood pineoblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042440">recurrent childhood medulloblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000612114">childhood medulloepithelioma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000788189">recurrent childhood nonmedulloblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other CNS Embryonal Tumors</Title><Para id="_72">Recurrence of all forms of central nervous system (CNS) embryonal tumors is not uncommon and usually occurs within 36 months of treatment. However, recurrent tumors may also develop many years after initial treatment.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  In such late relapses, especially those occurring 5 or more years after diagnosis, differentiation from secondary tumors such as high-grade gliomas can be difficult. Histological confirmation is recommended and usually required. In a 2021 report, a paired molecular cohort was assembled, consisting of 127 patients with tissue specimens available from both their primary medulloblastomas and subsequent tumors associated with relapse. Comparative molecular analyses were performed using the patient-matched tumor specimens. DNA methylation-based classification identified nine relapse cases (7%) as histologies other than medulloblastoma.<Reference refidx="4"/> Disease may recur at the primary site or may be disseminated at the time of relapse.  Sites of noncontiguous relapse may include the spinal leptomeninges, intracranial sites, and cerebrospinal fluid, in isolation or in any combination, and may be associated with primary tumor relapse.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  Extraneural disease relapse is rare and is seen primarily in patients who were treated with radiation therapy alone.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_654">Studies have found that even in patients with nondisseminated disease at diagnosis, and independent of the dose of radiation therapy or the type of chemotherapy, approximately one-third of patients will experience a relapse at the primary tumor site alone, one-third at the primary tumor site plus distant sites, and one-third at distant sites without relapse at the primary site.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/>   </Para><SummarySection id="_530"><Title>Treatment Options</Title><Para id="_2185">There are no standard treatment options for recurrent childhood CNS embryonal tumors. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000587224#_55" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Treatment for Recurrent Childhood CNS Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor</SummaryRef> section in Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment.</Para><Para id="_2186">For most children, treatment is palliative, and disease control  is transient in patients previously treated with radiation therapy and chemotherapy, with more than 80% of patients progressing within 2 years.<Reference refidx="3"/>; <Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]  The temporal and spatial patterns of relapse differ between molecular subgroups. Patients with group 4 medulloblastomas present with delayed relapse compared with patients in other subgroups. In children who develop relapsed disease after radiation-sparing strategies, patients with group 4 and SHH medulloblastomas have higher rates of local relapse (42% and 39%, respectively), compared with patients with group 3  disease (17%).<Reference refidx="8"/> For young children, predominantly those younger than 3 years  at diagnosis who were never treated with radiation therapy, longer-term control with reoperation, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy is possible.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_2187">Treatment approaches may include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_2188" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_448" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_450" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_452" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_456" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">High-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_723" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Molecularly targeted therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_448"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_449">At the time of relapse, a complete evaluation for extent of recurrence is indicated for all embryonal tumors.  Biopsy or surgical resection may be necessary for confirmation of relapse because other entities, such as secondary tumors and treatment-related brain necrosis, may be clinically indistinguishable from tumor recurrence.  The need for surgical intervention must be individualized based on the initial tumor type, the length of time between initial treatment and the reappearance of the lesion, and clinical symptoms.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_450"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_451">Patients with recurrent embryonal tumors who have already received radiation therapy and chemotherapy may be candidates for further radiation therapy depending on the site and dose of previous radiation. Treatment may include reirradiation at the primary tumor site,  focal areas of radiation therapy to sites of disseminated disease, and craniospinal irradiation (CSI).<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/>   However, long-term survival has been observed in a subset of patients who received chemotherapy alone at the time of diagnosis and had local relapse. This finding was primarily noted in young children with SHH-activated disease.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="15"/> In most cases, such therapy is palliative. Stereotactic radiation therapy  and/or salvage chemotherapy can also be used.<Reference refidx="16"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_452" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef> section.</Para><ItemizedList id="_2189" Style="bullet"><ListItem>One retrospective study reported the outcomes of infants and young children with relapsed medulloblastoma who were  initially treated in a variety of different chemotherapy clinical trials without CSI.<Reference refidx="8"/> <ItemizedList id="_2200" Style="bullet"><ListItem> At the time of relapse, 73% of these children were treated with CSI-based regimens. </ListItem><ListItem>The 3-year postrelapse survival rate was 52.4% for patients treated with curative intent. </ListItem><ListItem>The 3-year postrelapse survival rates for children with SHH, group 3, and group 4 medulloblastoma who received salvage radiation therapy  were 61%, 40%, and 79%, respectively. Patients with SHH disease were less likely to receive salvage radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Older age at diagnosis, local relapse, and the SHH infant subtype were associated with better postrelapse survival. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_452"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_2024">Recurrent CNS embryonal tumors can respond to chemotherapeutic agents used singularly or in combination, including cyclophosphamide, cisplatin, carboplatin, lomustine, etoposide, topotecan, temozolomide, the combination of irinotecan and temozolomide with or without bevacizumab, and antiangiogenic metronomic therapy.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/>; <Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]  Approximately 30% to 50% of these patients have objective responses  to conventional chemotherapy, but long-term disease control is rare.  </Para><Para id="_2025">For select patients with recurrent medulloblastoma—primarily infants and young children who were treated at the time of diagnosis with chemotherapy alone and who developed local recurrence—long-term disease control may be obtained after further treatment with chemotherapy plus local radiation therapy. This potential may be greatest in patients who are able to undergo complete resection of the recurrent disease.<Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="32"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] </Para><Para id="_2026">In a St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00602667">SJYC07 [NCT00602667])</ProtocolRef>,  29 patients with progressive disease received CSI (median dose, 36 Gy; interquartile range, 36–36). Of these 29 patients, 18 (62%) were alive at the time of publication, compared with 6 of 25 patients (24%) who did not receive CSI.<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_456"><Title>High-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue</Title><Para id="_457">For patients who have previously received radiation therapy, higher-dose chemotherapeutic regimens, supported with autologous bone marrow rescue or peripheral stem cell support, have been used with variable results.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><OrderedList id="_458" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>With such regimens, objective response is frequent, occurring in 50% to 75% of patients. However, long-term disease control is obtained in fewer than 30% of patients and is seen primarily in patients in first relapse and those with only localized disease at the time of relapse.<Reference refidx="11"/>; <Reference refidx="36"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="37"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Additionally,  results from national trials for relapsed medulloblastoma that specified intent to transplant as part of their treatment plan showed that only approximately 5% of patients initiating retrieval therapy achieved long-term disease-free survival with this strategy.<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="40"/>  Thus, studies that report from the time of transplant overestimate the benefit of transplant-based approaches for the total population of patients who have a relapse.</ListItem><ListItem>Long-term disease control for patients with disseminated disease is infrequent.<Reference refidx="41"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_723"><Title>Molecularly targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_724">
With increased knowledge of the molecular and genetic changes associated with different subtypes of medulloblastoma, molecularly targeted therapy, also called precision therapy, is being actively explored in children with recurrent disease. </Para><Para id="_2027">In patients with recurrent SHH-activated medulloblastomas, the SHH <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> inhibitor vismodegib demonstrated radiographic responses in 3 of 12 pediatric patients. Two of the responses were sustained for less than 2 months, and one response was sustained for more than 6 months. Response was only seen in patients with upstream variants of the SHH pathway, at the level of <GeneName>PTCH1</GeneName> or <GeneName>SMO</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="42"/> However, because of the development of irreversible growth plate fusions, the use of vismodegib is limited to skeletally mature children.<Reference refidx="43"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1797"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000562071">recurrent childhood pineoblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042440">recurrent childhood medulloblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000612114">childhood medulloepithelioma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000788189">recurrent childhood nonmedulloblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation for Recurrent Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other CNS Embryonal Tumors</Title><Para id="_1798">Early-phase therapeutic trials may be available for selected patients. These trials may be available via the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.childrensoncologygroup.org/">Children's Oncology Group (COG)</ExternalRef>, the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.pbtc.org/">Pediatric Brain Tumor Consortium</ExternalRef>, or other entities.  Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_1797_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_1797_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12697884">Taylor RE, Bailey CC, Robinson K, et al.: Results of a randomized study of preradiation chemotherapy versus radiotherapy alone for nonmetastatic medulloblastoma: The International Society of Paediatric Oncology/United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group PNET-3 Study. J Clin Oncol 21 (8): 1581-91, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10561268" MedlineID="20029997">Packer RJ, Goldwein J, Nicholson HS, et al.: Treatment of children with medulloblastomas with reduced-dose craniospinal radiation therapy and adjuvant chemotherapy: A Children's Cancer Group Study. J Clin Oncol 17 (7): 2127-36, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27423645">Sabel M, Fleischhack G, Tippelt S, et al.: Relapse patterns and outcome after relapse in standard risk medulloblastoma: a report from the HIT-SIOP-PNET4 study. J Neurooncol 129 (3): 515-524, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="33502920">Kumar R, Smith KS, Deng M, et al.: Clinical Outcomes and Patient-Matched Molecular Composition of Relapsed Medulloblastoma. J Clin Oncol 39 (7): 807-821, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="16034048">Oyharcabal-Bourden V, Kalifa C, Gentet JC, et al.: Standard-risk medulloblastoma treated by adjuvant chemotherapy followed by reduced-dose craniospinal radiation therapy: a French Society of Pediatric Oncology Study. J Clin Oncol 23 (21): 4726-34, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20133080">Mazloom A, Zangeneh AH, Paulino AC: Prognostic factors after extraneural metastasis of medulloblastoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 78 (1): 72-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="29432312">Johnston DL, Keene D, Strother D, et al.: Survival Following Tumor Recurrence in Children With Medulloblastoma. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 40 (3): e159-e163, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="36548930">Erker C, Mynarek M, Bailey S, et al.: Outcomes of Infants and Young Children With Relapsed Medulloblastoma After Initial Craniospinal Irradiation-Sparing Approaches: An International Cohort Study. J Clin Oncol 41 (10): 1921-1932, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="8084309" MedlineID="94366364">Gentet JC, Doz F, Bouffet E, et al.: Carboplatin and VP 16 in medulloblastoma: a phase II Study of the French Society of Pediatric Oncology (SFOP). Med Pediatr Oncol 23 (5): 422-7, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="18623206">Kadota RP, Mahoney DH, Doyle J, et al.: Dose intensive melphalan and cyclophosphamide with autologous hematopoietic stem cells for recurrent medulloblastoma or germinoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 51 (5): 675-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="19402050">Butturini AM, Jacob M, Aguajo J, et al.: High-dose chemotherapy and autologous hematopoietic progenitor cell rescue in children with recurrent medulloblastoma and supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumors: the impact of prior radiotherapy on outcome. Cancer 115 (13): 2956-63, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="29778738">Robinson GW, Rudneva VA, Buchhalter I, et al.: Risk-adapted therapy for young children with medulloblastoma (SJYC07): therapeutic and molecular outcomes from a multicentre, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 19 (6): 768-784, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="25080363">Wetmore C, Herington D, Lin T, et al.: Reirradiation of recurrent medulloblastoma: does clinical benefit outweigh risk for toxicity? Cancer 120 (23): 3731-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="34505229">Baroni LV, Freytes C, Fernández Ponce N, et al.: Craniospinal irradiation as part of re-irradiation for children with recurrent medulloblastoma. J Neurooncol 155 (1): 53-61, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="33222802">Hill RM, Richardson S, Schwalbe EC, et al.: Time, pattern, and outcome of medulloblastoma relapse and their association with tumour biology at diagnosis and therapy: a multicentre cohort study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health 4 (12): 865-874, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="16465076">Abe M, Tokumaru S, Tabuchi K, et al.: Stereotactic radiation therapy with chemotherapy in the management of recurrent medulloblastomas. Pediatr Neurosurg 42 (2): 81-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="3316521" MedlineID="88061527">Friedman HS, Oakes WJ: The chemotherapy of posterior fossa tumors in childhood. J Neurooncol 5 (3): 217-29, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="9142202" MedlineID="97287110">Needle MN, Molloy PT, Geyer JR, et al.: Phase II study of daily oral etoposide in children with recurrent brain tumors and other solid tumors. Med Pediatr Oncol 29 (1): 28-32, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="2249186" MedlineID="91064678">Gaynon PS, Ettinger LJ, Baum ES, et al.: Carboplatin in childhood brain tumors. A Children's Cancer Study Group Phase II trial. Cancer 66 (12): 2465-9, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="3546620" MedlineID="87140215">Allen JC, Walker R, Luks E, et al.: Carboplatin and recurrent childhood brain tumors. J Clin Oncol 5 (3): 459-63, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="8614374">Ashley DM, Longee D, Tien R, et al.: Treatment of patients with pineoblastoma with high dose cyclophosphamide. Med Pediatr Oncol 26 (6): 387-92, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="2153428">Lefkowitz IB, Packer RJ, Siegel KR, et al.: Results of treatment of children with recurrent medulloblastoma/primitive neuroectodermal tumors with lomustine, cisplatin, and vincristine. Cancer 65 (3): 412-7, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="3703192">Friedman HS, Mahaley MS, Schold SC, et al.: Efficacy of vincristine and cyclophosphamide in the therapy of recurrent medulloblastoma. Neurosurgery 18 (3): 335-40, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="2173440">Castello MA, Clerico A, Deb G, et al.: High-dose carboplatin in combination with etoposide (JET regimen) for childhood brain tumors. Am J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 12 (3): 297-300, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="24482446">Cefalo G, Massimino M, Ruggiero A, et al.: Temozolomide is an active agent in children with recurrent medulloblastoma/primitive neuroectodermal tumor: an Italian multi-institutional phase II trial. Neuro Oncol 16 (5): 748-53, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="31595663">Le Teuff G, Castaneda-Heredia A, Dufour C, et al.: Phase II study of temozolomide and topotecan (TOTEM) in children with relapsed or refractory extracranial and central nervous system tumors including medulloblastoma with post hoc Bayesian analysis: A European ITCC study. Pediatr Blood Cancer 67 (1): e28032, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="33844469">Levy AS, Krailo M, Chi S, et al.: Temozolomide with irinotecan versus temozolomide, irinotecan plus bevacizumab for recurrent medulloblastoma of childhood: Report of a COG randomized Phase II screening trial. Pediatr Blood Cancer 68 (8): e29031, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="21108437">Minturn JE, Janss AJ, Fisher PG, et al.: A phase II study of metronomic oral topotecan for recurrent childhood brain tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 56 (1): 39-44, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="22147459">Peyrl A, Chocholous M, Kieran MW, et al.: Antiangiogenic metronomic therapy for children with recurrent embryonal brain tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 59 (3): 511-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="37883081">Peyrl A, Chocholous M, Sabel M, et al.: Sustained Survival Benefit in Recurrent Medulloblastoma by a Metronomic Antiangiogenic Regimen: A Nonrandomized Controlled Trial. JAMA Oncol 9 (12): 1688-1695, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="17541945">Ridola V, Grill J, Doz F, et al.: High-dose chemotherapy with autologous stem cell rescue followed by posterior fossa irradiation for local medulloblastoma recurrence or progression after conventional chemotherapy. Cancer 110 (1): 156-63, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="21495027">Bakst RL, Dunkel IJ, Gilheeney S, et al.: Reirradiation for recurrent medulloblastoma. Cancer 117 (21): 4977-82, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="9440746" MedlineID="98101696">Dunkel IJ, Boyett JM, Yates A, et al.: High-dose carboplatin, thiotepa, and etoposide with autologous stem-cell rescue for patients with recurrent medulloblastoma. Children's Cancer Group. J Clin Oncol 16 (1): 222-8, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="20676326">Park JE, Kang J, Yoo KH, et al.: Efficacy of high-dose chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplantation in patients with relapsed medulloblastoma: a report on the Korean Society for Pediatric Neuro-Oncology (KSPNO)-S-053 study. J Korean Med Sci 25 (8): 1160-6, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="21744474">Gilman AL, Jacobsen C, Bunin N, et al.: Phase I study of tandem high-dose chemotherapy with autologous peripheral blood stem cell rescue for children with recurrent brain tumors: a Pediatric Blood and MarrowTransplant Consortium study. Pediatr Blood Cancer 57 (3): 506-13, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="21474302">Pizer B, Donachie PH, Robinson K, et al.: Treatment of recurrent central nervous system primitive neuroectodermal tumours in children and adolescents: results of a Children's Cancer and Leukaemia Group study. Eur J Cancer 47 (9): 1389-97, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="19019566">Massimino M, Gandola L, Spreafico F, et al.: No salvage using high-dose chemotherapy plus/minus reirradiation for relapsing previously irradiated medulloblastoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 73 (5): 1358-63, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="18755919">Gururangan S, Krauser J, Watral MA, et al.: Efficacy of high-dose chemotherapy or standard salvage therapy in patients with recurrent medulloblastoma. Neuro Oncol 10 (5): 745-51, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="20167818">Dunkel IJ, Gardner SL, Garvin JH, et al.: High-dose carboplatin, thiotepa, and etoposide with autologous stem cell rescue for patients with previously irradiated recurrent medulloblastoma. Neuro Oncol 12 (3): 297-303, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="20146223">Gajjar A, Pizer B: Role of high-dose chemotherapy for recurrent medulloblastoma and other CNS primitive neuroectodermal tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 54 (4): 649-51, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="17644914">Bowers DC, Gargan L, Weprin BE, et al.: Impact of site of tumor recurrence upon survival for children with recurrent or progressive medulloblastoma. J Neurosurg 107 (1 Suppl): 5-10, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="26169613">Robinson GW, Orr BA, Wu G, et al.: Vismodegib Exerts Targeted Efficacy Against Recurrent Sonic Hedgehog-Subgroup Medulloblastoma: Results From Phase II Pediatric Brain Tumor Consortium Studies PBTC-025B and PBTC-032. J Clin Oncol 33 (24): 2646-54, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="29050204">Robinson GW, Kaste SC, Chemaitilly W, et al.: Irreversible growth plate fusions in children with medulloblastoma treated with a targeted hedgehog pathway inhibitor. Oncotarget 8 (41): 69295-69302, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (04/11/2025)</Title><Para id="_6">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_2208">This summary was comprehensively reviewed.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000548358#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood medulloblastoma and other central nervous system embryonal tumors. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Kenneth J. Cohen, MD, MBA (Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Louis S. Constine, MD (James P. Wilmot Cancer Center at University of Rochester Medical Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Roger J. Packer, MD (Children's National Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Malcolm A. Smith, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389418]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2008-02-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-04-11</DateLastModified></Summary>
