<Summary id="CDR0000552550" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood medulloblastoma and other central nervous system embryonal tumors are treated with surgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy, high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue and targeted therapy. Learn more in this expert-reviewed summary. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/hp/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041539">childhood brain tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041638">childhood medulloblastoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000612114">childhood medulloepithelioma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000562070">childhood pineoblastoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_462">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood medulloblastoma and other central nervous system embryonal tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_463">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood brain tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood medulloblastoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood medulloepithelioma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood pineoblastoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Medulloblastoma &amp; Other CNS Embryonal Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Medulloblastoma &amp; Other CNS Embryonal Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other  Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Medulloblastoma and other central nervous system (CNS) embryonal tumors  may begin in embryonic (fetal) cells that remain in the brain after birth.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4778"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045780" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Medulloblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a fast-growing tumor that forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebellum</GlossaryTermRef> (the lower, back part of the brain). Medulloblastoma is the most common type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CNS</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embryonal tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. CNS embryonal tumors are uncontrolled growths of cells in the brain. These tumors form in cells that are left over from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000712879" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fetal</GlossaryTermRef> development, called embryonal cells. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046227" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pineoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a fast-growing type of brain tumor that forms in or around a tiny organ near the center of the brain called the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046226" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineal gland</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_366">These tumors may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045614" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign</GlossaryTermRef> (not cancer) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> (cancer). Benign brain tumors grow and press on nearby areas of the brain but rarely spread to other parts of the brain.  Malignant brain tumors are likely to grow quickly and spread into other parts of the brain. They may also spread to other parts of the body, but this is rare. When a tumor grows into and presses on an area of the brain or spreads to other parts of the brain, it may stop that part of the brain from working the way it should. Both benign and malignant brain tumors can cause serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and need treatment.</Para><Para id="_4746">Most medulloblastomas, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastomas in children are malignant. These tumors tend to spread through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of  the brain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_137">Although cancer is rare in children, brain tumors are the second most common type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000728326" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">childhood cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>. 

This summary is about  the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary</GlossaryTermRef> brain tumors (tumors that begin in the brain).</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000689771" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of the inside of the brain showing ventricles (fluid-filled spaces), choroid plexus, hypothalamus, pineal gland, pituitary gland, optic nerve, brain stem, cerebellum, cerebrum, medulla, pons, and spinal cord." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_373"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the inside of the brain, showing the pineal and pituitary glands, optic nerve, ventricles (with cerebrospinal fluid shown in blue), and other parts of the brain.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_6">There are different types of CNS embryonal tumors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_372">The different types of CNS embryonal tumors include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_125" Style="simple"><ListItem><Strong>Medulloblastomas</Strong><Para id="_128">Most CNS embryonal tumors are medulloblastomas. Medulloblastomas   are fast-growing tumors that  form in brain cells in the cerebellum.  The cerebellum is at the lower  back part of the brain  between the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrum</GlossaryTermRef> and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046491" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain stem</GlossaryTermRef>. The cerebellum controls movement, balance, and posture. It is rare for medulloblastomas to spread to the bone, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, or other parts of the body.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Other types of CNS embryonal tumors (nonmedulloblastoma)</Strong><Para id="_132">Other types of CNS embryonal tumors are fast-growing tumors and may form in brain cells anywhere in the brain, including the cerebrum, brain stem, or spinal cord. The cerebrum is at the top of the head and is the largest part of the brain. The cerebrum controls thinking, learning, problem-solving, emotions, speech, reading, writing, and voluntary movement. It is rare for these tumors to spread to the bone, bone marrow, lung, or other parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_399">There are many types of CNS embryonal (nonmedulloblastoma) tumors:</Para><ItemizedList id="_400" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Cribriform neuroepithelial tumors</Strong><Para id="_4747"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044331" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cribriform</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044827" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroepithelial</GlossaryTermRef> tumor forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ventricles</GlossaryTermRef> in the brain. This tumor most often occurs in infants and young children. Cribriform neuroepithelial tumor occurs more often in boys.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Embryonal tumors with multilayered rosettes</Strong><Para id="_472">Embryonal tumors with multilayered rosettes (ETMR) are rare tumors that form in the brain and spinal cord. ETMR most commonly occur in young children and are fast-growing tumors.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS neuroblastomas</Strong><Para id="_401">CNS <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastomas</GlossaryTermRef> are a very rare type of neuroblastoma that form in the nerve tissue of the cerebrum or the layers of tissue that cover the brain and spinal cord. CNS neuroblastomas may be large and    spread to other parts of the brain or spinal cord.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS high-grade neuroepithelial tumor with a change in the <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> gene</Strong><Para id="_4748">CNS <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386205" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-grade</GlossaryTermRef> neuroepithelial tumor is a very rare tumor that forms in the brain. This tumor occurs most often in children younger than 10 years, but can occur in older children and adolescents.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS Ewing sarcoma with a change in the <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene</Strong><Para id="_4749">CNS <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046031" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ewing sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a very rare tumor found in the brain or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>. This tumor most often occurs in children younger than 10 years.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS high-grade neuroepithelial tumor with a change in the <GeneName>MN1</GeneName> gene</Strong><Para id="_4750">CNS high-grade neuroepithelial tumor is a very rare tumor that forms in the brain or spinal cord. This tumor most often occurs in adolescents and females.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Medulloepitheliomas</Strong><Para id="_261">Medulloepithelioma  is a fast-growing tumor that usually forms  in the brain, spinal cord, or nerves just outside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000396787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal column</GlossaryTermRef>. It occurs most often in infants and young children.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS embryonal tumor with changes in the <GeneName>PLAGL</GeneName> gene</Strong><Para id="_4787">CNS embryonal tumor with changes in the <GeneName>PLAGL</GeneName> gene is a very rare tumor that forms in the brain. It affects both children and adults.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_365">CNS <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285639" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is also a type of embryonal tumor, but it is treated differently than other childhood CNS embryonal tumors. Learn more at <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574573" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_403"><KeyPoint id="_404">Pineoblastoma forms in cells of the pineal gland.</KeyPoint><Para id="_406">The pineal gland is a tiny organ in the center of the brain. The gland makes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440118" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melatonin</GlossaryTermRef>, a substance that helps control our sleep cycle. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046227" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pineoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> are usually malignant   fast-growing tumors with cells that  look very different from normal pineal gland cells. Pineoblastomas are not a type of CNS embryonal tumor but treatment for them is similar to treatment for CNS embryonal tumors.</Para><Para id="_464">Pineoblastoma is linked with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> changes in the retinoblastoma (<GeneName>RB1</GeneName>) gene. A child with the inherited form of  retinoblastoma (cancer that forms in the tissues of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retina</GlossaryTermRef>) has an increased risk of pineoblastoma. When retinoblastoma forms at the same time as a tumor in or near the pineal gland, it is called trilateral retinoblastoma. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging) testing in  children with retinoblastoma may detect pineoblastoma at an early stage when it can be treated successfully. It is rare for pineoblastoma to spread to the bone, bone marrow, lung, or other parts of the body.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_313"><KeyPoint id="_314">Certain genetic conditions increase the risk of childhood medulloblastoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4751">Childhood medulloblastoma is caused by certain changes to the way brain cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of the cell changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_315">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with one or more of these risk factors will develop medulloblastoma. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor.</Para><Para id="_411">The risk for medulloblastoma is increased in people who have any of the following inherited diseases:</Para><ItemizedList id="_316" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000751871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Turcot syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Rubinstein-Taybi syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000442897" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nevoid basal cell carcinoma (Gorlin) syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046322" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Li-Fraumeni syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fanconi anemia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_4788">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4752"><KeyPoint id="_4753">Genetic counseling may be done for children with medulloblastoma or pineoblastoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4754">It may not be clear from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> whether a child with a brain tumor has an inherited condition that increased their risk. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic counselors</GlossaryTermRef> and other specially trained health professionals can discuss your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> and the family's medical history to understand:</Para><ItemizedList id="_4755" Style="bullet"><ListItem>your options for <GeneName>ELP1</GeneName>, <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043977" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">APC</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName>, <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000802859" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">SUFU</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName>, <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000802855" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PTCH1</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName>, <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000796656" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TP53</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, or <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">BRCA2</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName> gene testing if your child has medulloblastoma</ListItem><ListItem>your options for <GeneName>RB1</GeneName> or <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> gene testing if your child has pineoblastoma</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of other cancers for your child</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of cancer for your child's siblings</ListItem><ListItem>the risks and benefits of learning <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> information</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_4756">Genetic counselors can also help you cope with your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef> results, including how to discuss the results with family members.</Para><Para id="_4789">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/genetic-testing-fact-sheet">Genetic Testing for Inherited Cancer Risk</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_318"><KeyPoint id="_319">Symptoms of medulloblastoma, other  CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma depend on the child's age and where the tumor is.</KeyPoint><Para id="_320">Children may not have symptoms of medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, or pineoblastoma until the tumor has grown bigger. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_321" Style="bullet"><ListItem>loss of balance, trouble walking, lack of coordination, or slow speech</ListItem><ListItem>a headache, especially in the morning, or headache that goes away after vomiting</ListItem><ListItem>general weakness</ListItem><ListItem>weakness on one side of the face</ListItem><ListItem>unusual sleepiness or change in energy level</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seizures</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>double vision or other eye problems</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and vomiting</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_322">Infants and young children with these tumors may be irritable or grow slowly. Also they may not eat well or meet <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000637716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">developmental milestones</GlossaryTermRef> such as sitting, walking, and talking in sentences. These tumors may also cause an increase in the size of an infant's head.</Para><Para id="_4757">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, or pineoblastoma. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">Tests that examine the brain and spinal cord are used to diagnose childhood medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4758">If your child has symptoms that suggest medulloblastoma, another type of CNS embryonal tumor, or pineoblastoma, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. They will ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on the results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with medulloblastoma, another type of CNS embryonal tumor, or pineoblastoma, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_18">The tests used to diagnose medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet">
    
    <ListItem><Strong>MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) of the brain and spinal cord with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597153" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gadolinium</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure that uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the brain and spinal cord. A substance called gadolinium is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). Sometimes magnetic resonance <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000600463" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spectroscopy</GlossaryTermRef> (MRS) is   
done during the MRI scan to look at the chemicals in brain tissue. </ListItem>
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine to make a series of detailed pictures inside the body from different angles. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046303" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lumbar puncture</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure used to collect cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) from the spinal column. This is done by placing a needle between two bones in the spine and into the lining around the spinal cord to remove a sample of CSF. The sample of CSF is     checked under a microscope for signs of tumor cells. The sample may also be checked for the amounts of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef>. A higher-than-normal amount of protein or lower-than-normal amount of glucose may be a sign of a tumor. This procedure is also called an LP or spinal tap.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000503953" type="image/jpeg" alt="Lumbar puncture; drawing shows a patient lying in a curled position on a table and a spinal needle (a long, thin needle) being inserted into the lower back. Inset shows a close-up of the spinal needle inserted into the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in the lower part of the spinal column." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_378"><Caption language="en">Lumbar puncture. A patient lies in a curled position on a table. After a small area on the lower back is numbed, a spinal needle (a long, thin needle) is inserted into the lower part of the spinal column to remove cerebrospinal fluid (CSF, shown in blue). The fluid may be sent to a laboratory for testing.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem>
    
    
    </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_238"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_239">A biopsy may be done to be sure of the diagnosis.</KeyPoint><Para id="_240">If doctors think your child may have medulloblastoma, another type of CNS embryonal tumor, or pineoblastoma, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> may be done. The biopsy is done by removing part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef> and using a needle to remove a sample of tissue. Sometimes, a computer-guided needle is used to remove the tissue sample. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells. If cancer cells are found, the doctor may remove as much tumor as safely possible during the same surgery. The piece of skull is usually put back in place after the procedure.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000691155" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of a craniotomy showing a section of the scalp that has been pulled back to remove a piece of the skull; the dura covering the brain has been opened to expose the brain. The layer of muscle under the scalp is also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_377"><Caption language="en">Craniotomy.  An opening is made in the skull and a piece of the skull is removed to show part of the brain.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_324">The following tests may be done on the sample of tissue that is removed:</Para><ItemizedList id="_358" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Immunohistochemistry</Strong> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient's tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Molecular testing</Strong> checks for certain genes, proteins, or other molecules in a sample of tissue, blood, or bone marrow. Molecular tests also check for certain changes in a gene or chromosome that may cause or affect the chance of developing medulloblastoma, another type of embryonal tumor, or pineoblastoma. A molecular test may be used to help plan treatment, find out how well treatment is working, or make a prognosis. Children with medulloblastoma, another type of embryonal tumor, or pineoblastoma may be eligible for molecular testing through the Molecular Characterization Initiative.<Para id="_md_4">The Molecular Characterization Initiative offers free molecular testing to children, adolescents, and young adults with certain types of newly diagnosed cancer. The program is offered through NCI's Childhood Cancer Data Initiative. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/areas/childhood/childhood-cancer-data-initiative/data-ecosystem/molecular-characterization">About the Molecular Characterization Initiative</ExternalRef>.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_281"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_282">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4759">If your child has been diagnosed with medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumor, or pineoblastoma, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_283">The prognosis and treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_284" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the type of tumor and where it is in the brain</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread within the brain and spinal cord when the tumor is found</ListItem><ListItem>the age of the child when the tumor is found</ListItem><ListItem>how much of the tumor remains after surgery</ListItem><ListItem>whether there are certain changes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosomes</GlossaryTermRef>, genes, or brain cells</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor has just been diagnosed or  has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_4779">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4760"><KeyPoint id="_4761">You may want to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4762">You may want to get a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">second opinion</GlossaryTermRef> to confirm your child's diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get important medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the genetic test results, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's tumor.</Para><Para id="_4763">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_180"><Title>Staging Childhood Medulloblastoma, Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors, and Pineoblastoma</Title><SummarySection id="_331"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_332">Medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma in children are treated based on the tumor type and the child's age.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4764">Cancer stage  describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging system</GlossaryTermRef> used for childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045780" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medulloblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>, other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> (CNS) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embryonal tumors,</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046227" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineoblastoma,</GlossaryTermRef> but the tests and procedures done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer are also used to help plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_4765">Treatment of other CNS embryonal tumors and pineoblastoma in children is based on the child's age. Children aged 3 years and younger  may be given different treatment than children older than 3 years.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_450"><KeyPoint id="_451">Treatment of medulloblastoma in children older than 3 years  also depends on whether the tumor is average risk or high risk.</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_452"><KeyPoint id="_453">Average risk</KeyPoint><Para id="_454">Medulloblastomas are called average risk when all of the following are true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_455" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The tumor was completely removed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> or there was only a very small amount remaining.</ListItem><ListItem>The cancer has not spread to other parts of the
				body.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_456"><KeyPoint id="_457">High risk</KeyPoint><Para id="_458">Medulloblastomas are called high risk if any of the following are true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_459" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Some of the tumor was not  removed by
				surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>The cancer has spread to other parts of the
				brain or spinal cord or to other parts of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_460">In general, cancer is more likely to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recur</GlossaryTermRef> (come back) after treatment in patients  with a high-risk tumor.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_181"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_182">The results of the tests and procedures done to diagnose medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma in children are used to plan cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_185">If your child is diagnosed with medulloblastoma, another type of CNS embryonal tumor, or pineoblastoma, they will be referred to a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270728" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuro-oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>. This is a doctor who specializes in staging and treating childhood cancers. They will recommend tests to determine the extent (stage) of cancer. Some of the tests used to diagnose the cancer are repeated after surgery. This is to find out how much tumor remains after surgery and to see if the cancer has spread from the brain to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef> or other parts of the body. It is important to know if the cancer has spread in order to plan the best treatment. Learn more about diagnostic tests in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550#_16" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_461">The following tests may be used to find out if the cancer has spread beyond the brain and spinal cord:</Para><ItemizedList id="_184" Style="bullet"> 
    <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046505" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone marrow aspiration</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046506" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> are procedures in which a sample of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> and bone is removed from the hipbone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000549425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breastbone</GlossaryTermRef> using a special needle. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the sample under a microscope to look for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer.
A bone marrow aspiration and biopsy are only done when there are signs the cancer has spread to the bone marrow.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775458" type="image/jpeg" alt="Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy; drawing shows a child lying face down on a table and a bone marrow needle being inserted into the right hip bone. An inset shows the bone marrow needle being inserted through the skin into the bone marrow of the hip bone." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_471"><Caption language="en">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy. After a small area of skin is numbed, a bone marrow needle  is inserted into the child’s hip bone.  Samples of blood, bone, and bone marrow are removed for examination under a microscope.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bone scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure to check if there are rapidly dividing cells, such as cancer cells, in the bone. A very small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> material is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein and travels through the bloodstream. The radioactive material collects in the bones with cancer and is detected by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef>. A bone scan is only done when there are signs or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> that       the cancer has spread to the bone.</ListItem> 
     
     
   </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_488"><KeyPoint id="_489">Sometimes childhood medulloblastoma and other central nervous system embryonal tumors come back after treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_241"> Childhood medulloblastoma and other types of CNS embryonal tumors most often recur (come back) within 3 years after treatment but may come back many years later. Recurrent childhood medulloblastoma and other CNS embryonal tumors may come back  in the same place as the original tumor and/or in a different place in the brain or spinal cord.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_147"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_148">There are different types of treatment for children who have medulloblastoma and other central nervous system (CNS) embryonal tumors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4766">There are different types of treatment for children and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adolescents</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045780" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medulloblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>, other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CNS</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embryonal tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046227" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>. You and your child's cancer care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_151"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_152">Children who have medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma should have their treatment planned by a team of health care providers who are experts in treating brain tumors in children. </KeyPoint><Para id="_153">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma. The pediatric oncologist works with other pediatric health care providers who are experts in treating children with brain tumors and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_237" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurosurgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318818" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuropathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318819" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroradiologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_4767">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>. It will be helpful to talk with your child's cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our downloadable booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_158"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_159">The following types of treatment may be used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_160"><KeyPoint id="_161">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_162">Surgery is used to diagnose and treat childhood medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma as described in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550#_16" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef> section of this summary. </Para><Para id="_280">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some patients may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, or both to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after the surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called adjuvant therapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_164"><KeyPoint id="_165">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_166">
      Radiation therapy uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, or pineoblastoma in children may be treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">external beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. External beam radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para><Para id="_490">Certain ways of giving external radiation therapy can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy tissue. These types of radiation therapy include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_491" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270731" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Conformal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>  uses a computer to make a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3-D) picture of the tumor and shapes the radiation beams to fit the tumor. This allows a high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> of radiation to reach the tumor and causes less damage to nearby healthy tissue.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stereotactic radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine that aims  radiation directly at the tumor, causing less damage to nearby healthy tissue.  The total dose of radiation is divided into several smaller doses given over several days. A rigid head frame is attached to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef> to keep the head still during this radiation treatment.  This procedure is also called stereotactic radiosurgery and stereotaxic radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_348">Because radiation therapy can affect growth and brain development in young children, especially children who are 3 years or younger, chemotherapy may be given to delay or reduce the need for radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_242">Radiation therapy to the brain can also affect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000637716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">growth and development</GlossaryTermRef> in children older than 3 years. For this reason, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> are studying new ways of giving radiation that may have fewer side effects than <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> methods.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_167"><KeyPoint id="_168">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_169">
     Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.   Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_4768">To treat medulloblastoma, other CNS embryonal tumors, and pineoblastoma, chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body.  Chemotherapy that may be used alone or in combination includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_4771" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537382" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecanhydrochloride">irinotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000725247" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/lomustine">lomustine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000586940" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/methotrexate-sodium">methotrexate</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496409" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/temozolomide">temozolomide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000765870" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/thiotepa">thiotepa</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495675" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/topotecanhydrochloride">topotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599877" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vincristinesulfate">vincristine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_4772">Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_4773">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_447"><KeyPoint id="_448">High-dose chemotherapy with autologous stem cell rescue</KeyPoint><Para id="_476">High doses of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells. This cancer treatment destroys healthy cells, including blood-forming cells. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment to replace the blood-forming cells. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stem cells</GlossaryTermRef> (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> of the patient and are frozen and stored. After the patient completes chemotherapy, the stored stem cells are thawed and given back to the patient through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These reinfused stem cells grow into (and restore) the body's blood cells.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_465"><KeyPoint id="_466">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_467">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to block the action of specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef>, or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef> involved in the growth and spread of cancer cells.</Para><Para id="_4774"><DrugRef href="CDR0000724515" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vismodegib">Vismodegib</DrugRef> may be used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> medulloblastoma in children who have finished growing.</Para><Para id="_473">Targeted therapy is also being studied for the treatment of childhood medulloblastoma and other CNS embryonal tumors that have recurred (come back) after treatment.</Para><Para id="_4783">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_296"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_297">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4775">A treatment clinical trial is a research study meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. For some patients, taking part in a clinical trial may be the best treatment choice.</Para><Para id="_4776">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.  
</Para><Para id="_4777">Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>. 
Because cancer in children is rare, taking part in a clinical trial should be considered. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_492"><Title>Treatment of Childhood Medulloblastoma</Title><Para id="_474">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550#_158" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_493"><Strong>Younger children with medulloblastoma</Strong></Para><Para id="_478">Treatment of newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045780" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medulloblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> in children aged 3 years and younger includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_494" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible, followed by chemotherapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_479">Other treatments that may be given after surgery include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_435" Style="bullet"><ListItem>High-dose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046144" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraventricular</GlossaryTermRef> chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">High-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell rescue</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy with or without radiation therapy to the area where the tumor was removed.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_251"><Strong>Children older than 3 years with average-risk medulloblastoma</Strong></Para><Para id="_431">Treatment of newly diagnosed average-risk medulloblastoma in children older than 3 years includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_418" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. This is followed by  radiation therapy to the brain and spinal cord. Chemotherapy may also be given during and after radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove the tumor, radiation therapy, and high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_252"><Strong>Children older than 3 years with high-risk medulloblastoma</Strong></Para><Para id="_432">Treatment of newly diagnosed high-risk medulloblastoma in children older than 3 years includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_419" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. This is followed by a larger dose of radiation therapy to the brain and spinal cord than the dose given for average-risk medulloblastoma. Chemotherapy is also given during and after radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove the tumor, radiation therapy, and high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_495"><Title>Treatment of Other CNS Embryonal (nonmedulloblastoma) Tumors in Children</Title><Para id="_4740">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550#_158" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_480"><Strong>Children aged 3 years and younger with nonmedulloblastoma, nonmedulloepithelioma embryonal tumors</Strong></Para><Para id="_481">Treatment of newly diagnosed nonmedulloblastoma,  nonmedulloepithelioma <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embryonal tumors</GlossaryTermRef> in children 3 years or younger includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_422" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible, followed by chemotherapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_262"><Strong>Children older than 3 years with nonmedulloblastoma, nonmedulloepithelioma embryonal tumors</Strong></Para><Para id="_437">Treatment of newly diagnosed nonmedulloblastoma, nonmedulloepithelioma embryonal tumors in children older than 3 years includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_420" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. This is followed by  radiation therapy to the brain and spinal cord. Chemotherapy is also given during and after radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_483"><Strong>Children with embryonal tumors with multilayered rosettes or medulloepithelioma</Strong></Para><Para id="_484">Treatment of  newly diagnosed embryonal tumor with multilayered rosettes (ETMR) or medulloepithelioma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_423" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. This is followed by chemotherapy. Radiation therapy may also be given.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove the tumor, followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell rescue</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_4743"><Strong>Children with CNS neuroblastoma</Strong></Para><Para id="_4744">Treatment of newly diagnosed CNS <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_4745" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. This is followed by radiation therapy to the brain and spinal cord. Chemotherapy may also be given.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_496"><Title>Treatment of Childhood Pineoblastoma</Title><Para id="_4741">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550#_158" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_485"><Strong>Children aged 3 years and  younger</Strong></Para><Para id="_486">Treatment of newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046227" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> in children aged 3 years and younger includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_429" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> to diagnose pineoblastoma and surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. Chemotherapy is usually given after surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell rescue</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>If  the tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">responds</GlossaryTermRef> to chemotherapy, radiation therapy is given when the child is older.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_388"><Strong>Children older than 3 years</Strong></Para><Para id="_445">Treatment of newly diagnosed pineoblastoma in children older than 3 years includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_428" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. This is followed by radiation therapy to the brain and spinal cord and chemotherapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_232"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000562071">recurrent childhood pineoblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042440">recurrent childhood medulloblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000612114">childhood medulloepithelioma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000788189">recurrent childhood nonmedulloblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors</Title><Para id="_4742">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550#_158" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_233">Treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045780" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medulloblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CNS</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embryonal tumors</GlossaryTermRef>  may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_234" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> to diagnose medulloblastoma and other CNS embryonal tumors. Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible may be done.</ListItem><ListItem>For children who previously received radiation therapy and chemotherapy, treatment may include repeat radiation at the site where the cancer started and where the tumor has spread. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stereotactic radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and/or chemotherapy may also be used.</ListItem><ListItem>For infants and young children who previously received chemotherapy only and have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local recurrence</GlossaryTermRef>,  treatment may be chemotherapy with radiation therapy to the tumor and the area close to it. Surgery to remove the tumor may also be done.</ListItem><ListItem>For patients who previously received radiation therapy, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell rescue</GlossaryTermRef> may be used. It is not known whether this treatment improves survival.</ListItem>
    
   <ListItem>Targeted therapy with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signal transduction inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000724515" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vismodegib">vismodegib</DrugRef>) for patients whose cancer has certain changes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_232_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4784"><Title>Side Effects</Title><SummarySection id="_155"><KeyPoint id="_156">The tumor and the treatment  may cause symptoms that continue after treatment ends. 
    
   </KeyPoint><Para id="_330"> 

<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Signs</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> caused by the tumor may begin before the cancer is diagnosed and continue for months or years.  It is important to talk with your child's doctors about signs or symptoms caused by the tumor that may continue after treatment.</Para><Para id="_4791">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_155_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_157">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_141" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Physical problems that affect:<ItemizedList id="_499" Style="bullet"><ListItem>bone and muscle growth and development</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046036" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef>, heart, or hearing function</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Second cancers</GlossaryTermRef> (new types of cancer), such as thyroid or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_347">Children diagnosed with medulloblastoma may have certain problems after surgery or radiation therapy, such as changes in the ability to think, learn, and pay attention. Also, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebellar mutism syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> may occur after surgery.  Signs of this syndrome include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_356" Style="bullet"><ListItem>delayed ability to speak</ListItem><ListItem>trouble swallowing and eating</ListItem><ListItem>loss of balance, trouble walking, and worsening handwriting</ListItem><ListItem>loss of muscle tone</ListItem><ListItem>mood swings and changes in personality</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_142">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the effects cancer treatment can have on your child and the types of symptoms to expect after cancer treatment has ended. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4785"><Title>Follow-Up Care</Title><Para id="_359">Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer or to find out the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests. This is sometimes called re-staging. Learn more about these tests in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550#_16" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_360">Some of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging tests</GlossaryTermRef> will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the brain tumor has recurred (come back). If the imaging tests show <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> tissue in the brain, a biopsy may also be done to find out if the tissue is made up of dead tumor cells or if new cancer cells are growing. These tests are sometimes called follow-up tests or check-ups.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4786"><Title>Coping With Cancer</Title><Para id="_4782">When a child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is also important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_288"><Title>Related Resources</Title><Para id="_289">For more information about  childhood medulloblastoma and other central nervous system embryonal tumor, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_290" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.pbtc.org/">Pediatric Brain Tumor Consortium (PBTC)</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_288_md_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_288_md_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood medulloblastoma and other central nervous system embryonal tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389401]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000548358"/><DateFirstPublished>2008-08-01</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-12-02</DateLastModified></Summary>
