<Summary id="CDR0000574573" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood central nervous system atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor treatment may include surgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy, and high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue. Learn more about newly diagnosed and recurrent childhood AT/RT in this expert-reviewed summary. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/hp/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038475">childhood atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041539">childhood brain tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_206">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood central nervous system atypical teratoid and rhabdoid tumor. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_207">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Childhood brain tumor</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Central nervous system (CNS) atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT) is  a cancer that forms in the tissues of the brain.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4">Central nervous system (CNS) atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT) is a very rare, fast-growing cancer that begins in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>.  It usually occurs in children aged 3 years and younger, although it can occur in older children and adults.    </Para><Para id="_154">About half of these tumors form in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebellum</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046491" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain stem</GlossaryTermRef>.  The cerebellum is the part of the brain that controls movement, balance, and posture. The brain stem controls breathing, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart rate</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef> and muscles used in seeing, hearing, walking, talking, and eating. AT/RT  can also begin in other parts of  the brain and spinal cord.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000772103" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the brain; the right panel shows the supratentorial area (the upper part of the brain) and the posterior fossa/infratentorial area (the lower back part of the brain). The supratentorial area contains the cerebrum, lateral ventricle and third ventricle (with cerebrospinal fluid shown in blue), choroid plexus, pineal gland, hypothalamus, pituitary gland, and optic nerve. The posterior fossa/infratentorial area contains the cerebellum, tectum, fourth ventricle, and brain stem (midbrain, pons, and medulla). The spinal cord is also shown. The left panel shows the cerebrum, ventricles (fluid-filled spaces), meninges, skull, cerebellum, brain stem (pons and medulla), and spinal cord." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_205"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the brain. The supratentorial area (the upper part of the brain) contains the cerebrum, lateral ventricle and third ventricle (with cerebrospinal fluid shown in blue), choroid plexus, pineal gland, hypothalamus, pituitary gland, and optic nerve.  The posterior fossa/infratentorial area (the lower back part of the brain) contains the cerebellum, tectum, fourth ventricle, and brain stem (midbrain, pons, and medulla).  The skull and meninges protect the brain and spinal cord.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Genetic aspects</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_10">Certain genetic changes may increase the risk of AT/RT.</KeyPoint><Para id="_136">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with one or more of these risk factors will develop AT/RT. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor.</Para><Para id="_129">AT/RT may be linked to  changes in the tumor suppressor genes <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> or <GeneName>SMARCA4.</GeneName> Tumor suppressor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> make a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> that helps control how and when cells grow. Changes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> of tumor suppressor genes like <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> or <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> may lead to cancer.</Para><Para id="_153">The changes in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> or <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>  genes may be    <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> (passed on from parents to offspring). When this gene change is inherited, tumors  may form in two parts of the body at the same time (for example, in the brain and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>).  For children with AT/RT,    <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> (a discussion with a trained professional about inherited diseases and a  possible need for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene testing</GlossaryTermRef>) may be recommended. </Para><Para id="_626">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_13">The symptoms of AT/RT are not the same in every person.</KeyPoint><Para id="_199"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_200" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the child's age</ListItem><ListItem>where the tumor has formed</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_201">Because AT/RT is fast growing, symptoms may develop quickly and get worse over a period of days or weeks. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet">
     
    <ListItem>a morning headache or headache that goes away after vomiting</ListItem> 
    <ListItem>nausea and vomiting</ListItem> 
    <ListItem>unusual sleepiness or change in activity level</ListItem> 
   <ListItem>loss of balance, lack of coordination, or trouble walking</ListItem><ListItem>an increase in head size (in infants)</ListItem><ListItem>pain, tingling, numbness, or paralysis in the face</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_627">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than AT/RT. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">CNS AT/RT is found with tests that examine the brain and spinal cord.</KeyPoint><Para id="_18">If your child has symptoms that suggest AT/RT, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, including a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurological exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with AT/RT, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_628">The tests used to diagnose AT/RT may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem><Strong>Magnetic resonance imaging (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef>)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the brain and spinal cord. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046303" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lumbar puncture</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure used to collect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> (CSF) from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000396787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal column</GlossaryTermRef>. This is done by placing a needle between two bones in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef> and into the lining around the spinal cord to remove a sample of the CSF. The sample of CSF is checked under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> for signs of tumor cells. The sample may also be checked for the amounts of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef>. This procedure is also called an LP or spinal tap.</ListItem>
    
    
    
    
   <ListItem><Strong><GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> and <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> gene testing</Strong> is a laboratory test in which a sample of blood or tissue is tested for certain changes in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> and <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>     genes. Children with AT/RT may be eligible for gene testing through the Molecular Characterization Initiative.<Para id="_md_4">The Molecular Characterization Initiative offers free molecular testing to children, adolescents, and young adults with certain types of newly diagnosed cancer. The program is offered through NCI's Childhood Cancer Data Initiative. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/areas/childhood/childhood-cancer-data-initiative/data-ecosystem/molecular-characterization">About the Molecular Characterization Initiative</ExternalRef>.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> exam</Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organs</GlossaryTermRef>, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>, and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>. This procedure is done to check for tumors that may also have formed in the kidney.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_131"><KeyPoint id="_132">Childhood AT/RT is diagnosed using a biopsy, and the tumor may be removed in the same surgery.</KeyPoint><Para id="_133">If doctors think there might be a brain tumor, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> may be done to remove a sample of tissue. For brain tumors, the biopsy can be done by removing part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef> or making a small hole in the skull and using a needle or surgical device to remove a sample of tissue.  Sometimes, when a needle is used, it is guided by a computer to remove the tissue sample. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells. If cancer cells are found, the doctor may remove as much tumor as safely possible during the same surgery. The pathologist checks the cancer cells to find out the type of brain tumor.  It is often difficult to completely remove AT/RT because of where the tumor is in the brain and because it may already have spread at the time of diagnosis. The piece of skull is usually put back in place after the procedure.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000691155" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of a craniotomy showing a section of the scalp that has been pulled back to remove a piece of the skull; the dura covering the brain has been opened to expose the brain. The layer of muscle under the scalp is also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_191"><Caption language="en">Craniotomy.  An opening is made in the skull and a piece of the skull is removed to show part of the brain.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_196">The following test may be done on the sample of tissue that is removed:</Para><ItemizedList id="_197" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000653117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunohistochemistry</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient's tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_21">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_24">If your child has been diagnosed with AT/RT, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_629">The prognosis depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_25" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>whether your child has certain inherited gene changes</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor has certain gene changes</ListItem><ListItem>your child's age</ListItem>
    <ListItem>the amount of tumor remaining after surgery</ListItem>
    <ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to other parts of the brain and spinal cord or to the kidney at the time of diagnosis</ListItem>
   <ListItem>whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has recurred (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_630">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Stages of Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor</Title><SummarySection id="_27"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_28">There is no standard staging system for central nervous system (CNS) atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT).</KeyPoint><Para id="_29">The process used to find out if cancer has spread to other parts of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>.  There is no standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging system</GlossaryTermRef> for central nervous system (CNS) atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT).</Para><Para id="_202">For treatment, this tumor is grouped as newly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef>. Treatment depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_203" Style="bullet"><ListItem>your child's age</ListItem><ListItem>how much cancer remains after surgery to remove the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to other parts of the CNS</ListItem><ListItem>the results of tests and procedures done to diagnose the cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_51"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_52">There are different types of treatment for children with central nervous system (CNS) atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT).</KeyPoint><Para id="_53">There are different types of treatment for children with AT/RT. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as where the cancer is located and your child's age and overall health.</Para><Para id="_631">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the tumor, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_55"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_56">Children with AT/RT should have their treatment planned by a team of health care providers who are experts in treating cancer in children.</KeyPoint><Para id="_57">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of AT/RT. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers  who are experts in treating children with CNS cancer and also specialize in other areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_58" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pediatric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurosurgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
    
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
    
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
    <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000723337" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">geneticist</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic counselor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem>
   <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_155"><KeyPoint id="_156">Childhood brain tumors may cause symptoms that begin before the cancer is diagnosed and continue for months or years.</KeyPoint><Para id="_157"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>  caused by the tumor may begin before diagnosis.  These signs or symptoms may continue for months or years. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about symptoms caused by the tumor that may continue after treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_63"> The following types of treatment may be used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_64"><KeyPoint id="_65">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_66">Surgery is used to treat CNS AT/RT. Learn more about how this tumor is <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574573#_17" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">diagnosed</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_67">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, most children will  receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and possibly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to try to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after surgery to lower the risk that the cancer will come back is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_159"><KeyPoint id="_160">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_161">Chemotherapy uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cells or stops them from dividing.   Chemotherapy may be given with other types of treatments.</Para><Para id="_632">Chemotherapy for AT/RT is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bloodstream</GlossaryTermRef> and can reach tumor cells throughout the body.  High <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of some chemotherapy drugs given into a vein can cross the blood-brain barrier and reach the tumor. Chemotherapy for AT/RT is also   placed directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>). <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses more than one anticancer drug.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000539773" type="image/jpeg" alt="Intrathecal chemotherapy; drawing shows the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in the brain and spinal cord, and an Ommaya reservoir (a dome-shaped container that is placed under the scalp during surgery; it holds the drugs as they flow through a small tube into the brain). Top section shows a syringe and needle injecting anticancer drugs into the Ommaya reservoir. Bottom section shows a syringe and needle injecting anticancer drugs directly into the cerebrospinal fluid in the lower part of the spinal column." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_639"><Caption language="en">Intrathecal chemotherapy. Anticancer drugs are injected into the intrathecal space, which is the space that holds the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF, shown in blue). There are two different ways to do this. One way, shown in the top part of the figure, is to inject the drugs into an Ommaya reservoir (a dome-shaped container that is placed under the scalp during surgery; it holds the drugs as they flow through a small tube into the brain). The other way, shown in the bottom part of the figure, is to inject the drugs directly into the CSF in the lower part of the spinal column, after a small area on the lower back is numbed.  </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_633">Chemotherapy drugs used alone or in combination to treat AT/RT in children include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_634" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000540242" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cytarabine">cytarabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000586940" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/methotrexate-sodium">methotrexate</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000765870" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/thiotepa">thiotepa</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_635">Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_636">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, and common side effects at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_68"><KeyPoint id="_69">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_70">
     Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para><Para id="_163"> Because radiation therapy can affect growth and brain development in young children, especially children who are 3 years old or younger, the dose of radiation therapy may be lower than in older children.</Para><Para id="_638">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><KeyPoint id="_89">Stem cell transplant</KeyPoint><Para id="_219">High doses of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells. This treatment destroys healthy cells, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>-forming cells. Stem cell transplant is a treatment to replace the blood-forming cells. Stem cells (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> of the patient and are frozen and stored. After the patient completes chemotherapy, the stored stem cells are thawed and given back to the patient through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These reinfused stem cells grow into (and restore) the body's blood cells.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_640"><KeyPoint id="_641">Clinical trials</KeyPoint><Para id="_90">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_100">You can find clinical trials for people with atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials/disease/atypical-teratoid-rhabdoid-tumor/treatment">Treatment Clinical Trials for Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor</ExternalRef> or use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><KeyPoint id="_60">Treatment for childhood CNS AT/RT may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_637">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_59_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_61">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_142" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">second cancers</GlossaryTermRef> (new types of cancer)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_143">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the  effects cancer treatment can have on your child.  Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><KeyPoint id="_149">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_175">As your  child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574573#_17" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">diagnose</SummaryRef> the cancer may be repeated. Some tests will be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_190">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back). </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_642"><KeyPoint id="_644">Resources and support are available to help you cope with your child's cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_643">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_164"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038475">childhood atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor</Title><Para id="_217">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574573#_62" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_167">There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for children with newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> (CNS) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285639" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (AT/RT). Because AT/RT  is fast-growing, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688810" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination</GlossaryTermRef> of treatments is usually given.</Para><Para id="_221">After surgery to remove the tumor, treatment for AT/RT may include  combinations  of:</Para><ItemizedList id="_168" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-dose chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_164_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_176"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038475">childhood atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor</Title><Para id="_218">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574573#_62" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_183">There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for children with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> central nervous system (CNS) atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT). </Para><Para id="_645">Treatment for recurrent childhood AT/RT may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_216" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative treatment</GlossaryTermRef> to improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_176_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_150"><Title>To Learn More about Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor and Other Childhood Brain Tumors</Title><Para id="_151">For more information about   childhood central nervous system atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor and other childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_152" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.pbtc.org/">Pediatric Brain Tumor Consortium (PBTC)</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_150_md_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_150_md_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood central nervous system atypical teratoid and rhabdoid tumor.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389341]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000587224"/><DateFirstPublished>2008-12-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-12-19</DateLastModified></Summary>
