<Summary id="CDR0000574548" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Genetics of Renal Cell Carcinoma includes the hereditary cancer syndromes von Hippel-Lindau disease, hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer, Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome, and hereditary papillary renal carcinoma. Get comprehensive information on these syndromes in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics">Genetics of Renal Cell Carcinoma (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/kidney-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Renal Cell Carcinoma (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038140">renal cell carcinoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_782">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of renal cell carcinoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_783">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>renal cell carcinoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Genetics of Renal Cell Carcinoma (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Genetics of Renal Cell Carcinoma (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Genetics of Renal Cell Carcinoma</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>Inheritance and Risk of Renal Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_7">Renal cell carcinoma (RCC)  is commonly diagnosed in both men and women. In the United States in 2025, about 80,980 new cases of kidney cancer and renal pelvis cancer will occur, along with an estimated 14,510 deaths.<Reference refidx="1"/> These cancers account for about 3.97% of all adult malignancies.<Reference refidx="1"/> The male-to-female ratio is 1.9:1.<Reference refidx="2"/> RCC is distinct from kidney cancer that involves the renal pelvis or renal medulla, and it only applies to cancer that forms in the lining of the kidney bed (i.e., in the renal tubules). This summary does not address non-RCCs of the kidney, including cancer of the renal pelvis or renal medulla. Genetic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> have been identified as the cause of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339343" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">inherited cancer</GlossaryTermRef> risk in some RCC-prone families; these pathogenic variants are estimated to account for only 5% to 8% of RCC cases overall.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  It is likely that other undiscovered <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> and background genetic factors contribute to the development of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> RCC along with nongenetic risk factors.</Para><Para id="_3177">Studies of several sequencing cohorts have evaluated patients with RCC using  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763019" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic testing panels</GlossaryTermRef> that included many genes not previously associated with hereditary RCC.
Many of these cohorts reinforce that the rate of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> alterations in classic RCC genes aligns with prior estimates. These cohorts also show a high incidence of other pathogenic variants, some of which occurred in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> repair genes. The rate of other pathogenic alterations ranged from 12.8% to 17.0%.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> The  incidence of other pathogenic alterations is higher than would be expected in the population. However, these cohorts are not population-based, and they are significantly enriched for cancer patients who have been recommended for germline testing.</Para><Para id="_3195">A  retrospective single-center study of patients with early-onset RCC (diagnosed before age 46 y), found that participants with clinical phenotypes suggestive of  RCC-associated pathogenic variants—like bilateral or multifocal tumors, non–clear cell renal histology, and extra-renal primary cancers—had the highest yields on germline RCC panel testing.<Reference refidx="10"/> There were 129 patients with clear cell RCC. A subset analysis of patients with unifocal, clear cell RCC did not reveal  pathogenic variants on RCC genetic testing panels. Other studies have confirmed that individuals with bilateral or multifocal tumors were more likely to have a pathogenic variant in an RCC- or cancer-related gene.<Reference refidx="11"/> However,  5% to 10% of individuals in these series had pathogenic variants in non-RCC–associated genes—primarily in DNA repair genes.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> At this time, it is unclear if there is a causal relationship between RCC and these pathogenic alterations; the relationship requires additional study. It is plausible that these pathogenic variants increase RCC risk. However, RCC risk could also be elevated by other factors like an enriched population of high-risk individuals or  overdetection of RCC from
frequent scans in high-risk patients.
</Para><Para id="_3196">In contrast, several studies reported that the incidence of germline pathogenic variants is much lower (4.1% to 6.4%) in unselected individuals with RCC who underwent sequencing during a research study.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> Most variants identified in these series were in genes classically associated with RCC. This finding suggests that the population studied may greatly influence the detection rate of pathogenic variants in cancer predisposition genes that are not typically associated with RCC.</Para><Para id="_560">RCC occurs in both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781848" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heritable</GlossaryTermRef> forms.  Four major RCC syndromes with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant inheritance</GlossaryTermRef> have been identified. PDQ summaries are available for each of these syndromes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_561" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803496" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/vhl-syndrome-hp-pdq">Von Hippel-Lindau Disease</SummaryRef> (VHL).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer</SummaryRef> (HLRCC).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Hereditary Papillary Renal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> (HPRC).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803628" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/bhd-syndrome-hp-pdq">Birt-Hogg-Dubé Syndrome</SummaryRef> (BHD).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_562">For more information about sporadic kidney cancer, see  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062894" url="/types/kidney/hp/kidney-treatment-pdq">Renal Cell Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062937" url="/types/kidney/hp/transitional-cell-treatment-pdq">Transitional Cell Cancer of the Renal Pelvis and Ureter Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_12"><Title>Natural History of Renal Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_13">The natural history of each RCC syndrome is distinct and influenced by several factors, including histological features and underlying genetic alterations. Although it is useful to follow the predominant reported natural history of each syndrome, each <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">affected</GlossaryTermRef> individual  must be evaluated and monitored for occasional individual variations.  The individual prognosis depends on the characteristics of the renal tumor at the time of detection and intervention, which differs for each syndrome (VHL, HLRCC, HPRC, and BHD).  Prognostic determinants at diagnosis include the stage of the RCC, whether the tumor is confined to the kidney, primary tumor size, Fuhrman nuclear grade, and multifocality.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><Title>Family History as a Risk Factor for Renal Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_15">Kidney cancer and renal pelvis cancer account for about 3.97% of all adult malignancies in the United States.<Reference refidx="1"/> Epidemiological studies of RCC suggest that a family history of RCC is a risk factor for the disease.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>  An analysis of individuals with RCCs diagnosed before the year 2000  in the Sweden Family-Cancer Database included all Swedes born since 1931 and their biological parents. The study observed that the risk of RCC was particularly high in the siblings of those with RCC.  Siblings of individuals with RCC had a higher relative risk (RR) than parent-child pairs.<Reference refidx="17"/>  Further work from this database confirms that 3% of individuals with RCC had a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460150" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">first-degree relative</GlossaryTermRef> (FDR) with RCC.<Reference refidx="19"/> Risk may be higher in individuals who have multiple FDRs with RCC and in women. Another study examined all patients in Iceland who developed RCC between 1955 and 1999 (1,078 cases).  Investigators used an extensive computerized database to perform a unique genealogical study that included more than 600,000 Icelandic individuals.  Results revealed that nearly 60% of Icelandic patients with RCC had a FDR or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000485395" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">second-degree relative</GlossaryTermRef> (SDR) with RCC. Siblings of patients with RCC had an estimated RR of 2.5.<Reference refidx="4"/> In a Korean study, individuals who had FDRs with RCC had a 2.29-fold increased risk of RCC. Risk did not appear to differ whether the FDR was a mother, father, or a sibling.<Reference refidx="20"/> Modifying factors like obesity and hyperglycemia may further increase RCC risk in this high-risk population. Another study evaluated 80,309 monozygotic twins and 123,382 same-sex dizygotic twins in Denmark, Finland, Norway, and Sweden.<Reference refidx="18"/> This study found excess cancer risk in twins whose co-twin was diagnosed with cancer. The estimated cumulative risks were an absolute 5% higher (95% confidence interval [CI], 4%–6%) in dizygotic twins (37%; 95% CI, 36%–38%)  and an absolute 14% higher (95% CI, 12%–16%) in monozygotic twins (46%; 95% CI, 44%–48%)—for those  whose co-twin also developed cancer—than in the overall cohort (32%). Overall <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781848" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heritability</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer, calculated by assessing the relative contribution of heredity versus shared environment, was estimated to be 33%. Kidney cancer heritability was estimated to be 38% (95% CI, 21%–55%). Shared environmental factors did not significantly contribute to overall risk.</Para><Para id="_16">   Young age at RCC onset is also a clue that hereditary etiology is possible. Unlike sporadic RCC, which is generally diagnosed during the fifth to seventh decades of life, hereditary forms of RCC are generally diagnosed at an earlier age. In a review of more than 600 cases of hereditary RCC from the National Cancer Institute, the median age of RCC diagnosis was 37 years, with 70% of cases being diagnosed at age 46 years or younger.<Reference refidx="3"/> This age is lower than the median age of RCC diagnosis in the general population, which is 64 years.<Reference refidx="21"/>  Heritable RCCs are often multifocal and bilateral.  A retrospective analysis of 1,235 patients with RCC who underwent genetic testing revealed that 6.1% of this population had positive genetic test results, 75.5% had negative test results, and 18.4% had a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556493" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant of unknown significance</GlossaryTermRef>.  Young age at RCC diagnosis was the only variable associated with a positive test result.<Reference refidx="8"/> Other series showed that patients with non-clear cell advanced RCC may have an enrichment for pathogenic variants when compared with patients who had clear cell RCC; however, current research data are limited.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_749">While there is much debate about the referral criteria for hereditary RCC genetic testing, the following organizations have offered some guidance:</Para><ItemizedList id="_750" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.vhl.org/clinicians/suggested-referral-criteria-vhl-clinical-care-centers/">VHL Alliance</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Kidney Cancer Research Network of Canada.<Reference refidx="23"/>
</ListItem><ListItem>National Comprehensive Cancer Network.<Reference refidx="24"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3182">These guidelines acknowledge that the following criteria can prompt a referral to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef>: early age of RCC onset, family history of RCC (≥1 FDR/SDR with RCC), bilateral or multifocal RCCs, and suspicious RCC histology. A consensus statement published by a group of kidney cancer experts provides additional guidance that may help  providers identify patients  who can be referred to genetic counseling.<Reference refidx="25"/></Para><Para id="_3197">When evaluating patients at risk of hereditary kidney cancer, specific clinical features help determine which test is the most appropriate to order. Single gene tests are available during family variant testing or when there is only suspicion for one specific kidney cancer syndrome. The following panel tests are also available: 1) broad cancer genetic panels of up to 100 genes associated with cancer predisposition, and 2) renal cancer genetic panels with 15 to 20 genes that have strong associations with hereditary kidney cancer syndromes. Most of these panels conduct targeted sequencing of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460146" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">exon</GlossaryTermRef> with little coverage of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660737" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">intron</GlossaryTermRef>, except for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783968" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">splice-site variants</GlossaryTermRef>. In  the future, RNA testing may be useful to evaluate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556493" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants of unknown significance</GlossaryTermRef> identified by DNA testing, to add additional support for pathogenicity. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Whole genome sequencing</GlossaryTermRef> (WGS) can be considered for rare cases with clinical suspicion that had negative panel testing. WGS may detect structural variants in introns that can contribute to cancer predisposition. In a series of over 1,300 unselected patients with RCC who underwent WGS, 6.9% of patients had germline pathogenic variants identified in cancer predisposition genes.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_21"><Title>Other Risk Factors for Renal Cell Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_22">Studies of environmental and lifestyle factors contributing to the risk of RCC focus almost exclusively on sporadic (i.e., nonhereditary) RCC.  Smoking, hypertension, and obesity   are the major  environmental and lifestyle risk factors associated with RCC.<Reference refidx="26"/> In addition, workers who were reportedly exposed to the environmental carcinogen trichloroethylene developed sporadic clear cell RCC, presumably resulting from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>VHL</GeneName> gene.<Reference refidx="27"/>  Dietary intake of vegetables and fruits has been inversely associated with RCC. Greater intake of red meat and milk products have been associated with increased RCC risk, although not consistently.<Reference refidx="28"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2">DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24378414">Shuch B, Vourganti S, Ricketts CJ, et al.: Defining early-onset kidney cancer: implications for germline and somatic mutation testing and clinical management. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 431-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12115533">Gudbjartsson T, Jónasdóttir TJ, Thoroddsen A, et al.: A population-based familial aggregation analysis indicates genetic contribution in a majority of renal cell carcinomas. Int J Cancer 100 (4): 476-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="29978187">Carlo MI, Mukherjee S, Mandelker D, et al.: Prevalence of Germline Mutations in Cancer Susceptibility Genes in Patients With Advanced Renal Cell Carcinoma. JAMA Oncol 4 (9): 1228-1235, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="32782288">Hartman TR, Demidova EV, Lesh RW, et al.: Prevalence of pathogenic variants in DNA damage response and repair genes in patients undergoing cancer risk assessment and reporting a personal history of early-onset renal cancer. Sci Rep 10 (1): 13518, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="33789101">Abou Alaiwi S, Nassar AH, Adib E, et al.: Trans-ethnic variation in germline variants of patients with renal cell carcinoma. Cell Rep 34 (13): 108926, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28787086">Nguyen KA, Syed JS, Espenschied CR, et al.: Advances in the diagnosis of hereditary kidney cancer: Initial results of a multigene panel test. Cancer 123 (22): 4363-4371, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="32830346">Smith PS, West H, Whitworth J, et al.: Pathogenic germline variants in patients with features of hereditary renal cell carcinoma: Evidence for further locus heterogeneity. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 60 (1): 5-16, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="34654685">Truong H, Sheikh R, Kotecha R, et al.: Germline Variants Identified in Patients with Early-onset Renal Cell Carcinoma Referred for Germline Genetic Testing. Eur Urol Oncol 4 (6): 993-1000, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="38127826">Nguyen CB, Knaus C, Li J, et al.: Pathogenic Germline Mutational Landscape in Patients With Renal Cell Carcinoma and Associated Clinicopathologic Features. JCO Precis Oncol 7: e2300168, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="35441217">Yngvadottir B, Andreou A, Bassaganyas L, et al.: Frequency of pathogenic germline variants in cancer susceptibility genes in 1336 renal cell carcinoma cases. Hum Mol Genet 31 (17): 3001-3011, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="35764097">Sekine Y, Iwasaki Y, Aoi T, et al.: Different risk genes contribute to clear cell and non-clear cell renal cell carcinoma in 1532 Japanese patients and 5996 controls. Hum Mol Genet 31 (12): 1962-1969, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="17441915">Vira MA, Novakovic KR, Pinto PA, et al.: Genetic basis of kidney cancer: a model for developing molecular-targeted therapies. BJU Int 99 (5 Pt B): 1223-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="12511666">Choyke PL, Glenn GM, Walther MM, et al.: Hereditary renal cancers. Radiology 226 (1): 33-46, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="17222609">Zbar B, Glenn G, Merino M, et al.: Familial renal carcinoma: clinical evaluation, clinical subtypes and risk of renal carcinoma development. J Urol 177 (2): 461-5; discussion 465, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="15069696">Hemminki K, Li X: Familial risks of cancer as a guide to gene identification and mode of inheritance. Int J Cancer 110 (2): 291-4, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="26746459">Mucci LA, Hjelmborg JB, Harris JR, et al.: Familial Risk and Heritability of Cancer Among Twins in Nordic Countries. JAMA 315 (1): 68-76, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="37862613">Jakobsson RG, Nasic S, Bratt O, et al.: Family History and Risk of Renal Cell Carcinoma: A National Multiregister Case-Control Study. J Urol 211 (1): 71-79, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="35298291">Lee SW, Kim HJ, Kazmi SZ, et al.: Familial Risk of Renal Cell Cancer and Interaction with Obesity and Hyperglycemia: A Population-Based Study. J Urol 208 (2): 251-258, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="21">National Cancer Institute: SEER Stat Fact Sheets: Kidney and Renal Pelvis Cancer. Bethesda, Md: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/kidrp.html">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 17, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="33442023">Santos M, Lanillos J, Roldan-Romero JM, et al.: Prevalence of pathogenic germline variants in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma. Genet Med 23 (4): 698-704, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="24319509">Reaume MN, Graham GE, Tomiak E, et al.: Canadian guideline on genetic screening for hereditary renal cell cancers. Can Urol Assoc J 7 (9-10): 319-23, 2013 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="24">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Kidney Cancer. Version 3.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2022. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/kidney.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed September 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="34343338">Bratslavsky G, Mendhiratta N, Daneshvar M, et al.: Genetic risk assessment for hereditary renal cell carcinoma: Clinical consensus statement. Cancer 127 (21): 3957-3966, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="10768591">McLaughlin JK, Lipworth L: Epidemiologic aspects of renal cell cancer. Semin Oncol 27 (2): 115-23, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="10340905">Brauch H, Weirich G, Hornauer MA, et al.: Trichloroethylene exposure and specific somatic mutations in patients with renal cell carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst 91 (10): 854-61, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="18836333">Chow WH, Devesa SS: Contemporary epidemiology of renal cell cancer. Cancer J 14 (5): 288-301, 2008 Sep-Oct.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_24"><Title>Major Heritable Renal Cell Carcinoma Syndromes</Title><Para id="_468">There are four major hereditary renal cell carcinoma (RCC) syndromes. These <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">syndromes</GlossaryTermRef> are summarized in detail in the following PDQ summaries and in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574548#_484" url="/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics">Table 1</SummaryRef> below:</Para><ItemizedList id="_3157" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803496" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/vhl-syndrome-hp-pdq">Von Hippel-Lindau Disease</SummaryRef> (VHL).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer </SummaryRef> (HLRCC).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Hereditary Papillary Renal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> (HPRC).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803628" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/bhd-syndrome-hp-pdq">Birt-Hogg-Dubé Syndrome</SummaryRef> (BHD).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Table id="_484"><Title>Table 1.  Hereditary Renal Cell Cancer (RCC) Syndromes and Susceptibility Genes</Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="31.88%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="18.86%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="17.55%"/><ColSpec ColName="col04" ColNum="4" ColWidth="4.53%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="27.16%"/><THead><Row><entry>Syndrome (Inheritance Pattern)</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Gene</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460162" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Locus</GlossaryTermRef>, Gene Type (Protein)</entry><entry>Renal Tumor Pathology </entry><entry>Cumulative Cancer Risk</entry><entry>Nonrenal Tumors and Associated Abnormalities</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">AD = autosomal dominant; ccRCC = clear cell renal cell carcinoma; CNS = central nervous system; PHEO = pheochromocytoma.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803496" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/vhl-syndrome-hp-pdq">Von Hippel-Lindau disease</SummaryRef>
(VHL) (AD)
<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></entry><entry><GeneName>VHL</GeneName> 3p26, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046657" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">tumor suppressor</GlossaryTermRef> 
(pVHL)
</entry><entry>ccRCC (multifocal)
</entry><entry>24%–45%</entry><entry>CNS hemangioblastoma, retinal hemangioblastomas, PHEO, pancreatic neuroendocrine tumor, endolymphatic sac tumor, cystadenoma of the pancreas, the epididymis, and the broad ligament</entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer</SummaryRef> (HLRCC)
(AD) <Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>
</entry><entry><GeneName>FH</GeneName>  1q42.1, tumor suppressor
(fumarate hydratase)
</entry><entry>HLRCC-associated RCC</entry><entry>Up to 32%</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765494" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Cutaneous leiomyomas</GlossaryTermRef>, uterine leiomyomas (fibroids)</entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Hereditary papillary renal carcinoma </SummaryRef> (HPRC)
(AD)
<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></entry><entry><GeneName>MET</GeneName>  7q34, proto-oncogene (hepatocyte growth factor receptor)</entry><entry>Papillary RCC (formerly known as type 1 papillary RCC)</entry><entry>Approaching 100%</entry><entry>None known</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803628" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/bhd-syndrome-hp-pdq">Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome</SummaryRef> (BHD) (AD) <Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></entry><entry MoreRows="1"><GeneName>FLCN</GeneName>  17p11.2, tumor suppressor (folliculin)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Hybrid oncocytic, chromophobe, oncocytoma, papillary, 
clear cell 

</entry><entry MoreRows="1">15%–30%</entry><entry>Cutaneous: fibrofolliculomas/ trichodiscomas
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Pulmonary: lung cysts, spontaneous pneumothoraces
</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry/><entry/><entry/></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_237">These major RCC syndromes are transmitted via an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460196" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">mode of inheritance</GlossaryTermRef>. This means that   the altered <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is present in one of the parents and that the chances of transmitting this gene and the disease to the offspring is 50% for each pregnancy. Genetic tests performed in Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)-certified laboratories are available for the genes associated with VHL, HLRCC, HPRC, and BHD. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> is a prerequisite for genetic testing.  For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling</SummaryRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="7862955">Choyke PL, Glenn GM, Walther MM, et al.: von Hippel-Lindau disease: genetic, clinical, and imaging features. Radiology 194 (3): 629-42, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="12814730">Lonser RR, Glenn GM, Walther M, et al.: von Hippel-Lindau disease. Lancet 361 (9374): 2059-67, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11248088">Launonen V, Vierimaa O, Kiuru M, et al.: Inherited susceptibility to uterine leiomyomas and renal cell cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 98 (6): 3387-92, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="16029320">Alam NA, Olpin S, Leigh IM: Fumarate hydratase mutations and predisposition to cutaneous leiomyomas, uterine leiomyomas and renal cancer. Br J Dermatol 153 (1): 11-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="12772087" MedlineID="22696721">Toro JR, Nickerson ML, Wei MH, et al.: Mutations in the fumarate hydratase gene cause hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer in families in North America. Am J Hum Genet 73 (1): 95-106, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15937070">Wei MH, Toure O, Glenn GM, et al.: Novel mutations in FH and expansion of the spectrum of phenotypes expressed in families with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. J Med Genet 43 (1): 18-27, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9140397">Schmidt L, Duh FM, Chen F, et al.: Germline and somatic mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the MET proto-oncogene in papillary renal carcinomas. Nat Genet 16 (1): 68-73, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="15371818">Schmidt LS, Nickerson ML, Angeloni D, et al.: Early onset hereditary papillary renal carcinoma: germline missense mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the met proto-oncogene. J Urol 172 (4 Pt 1): 1256-61, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="18234728">Toro JR, Wei MH, Glenn GM, et al.: BHD mutations, clinical and molecular genetic investigations of Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome: a new series of 50 families and a review of published reports. J Med Genet 45 (6): 321-31, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="10522666">Toro JR, Glenn G, Duray P, et al.: Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome: a novel marker of kidney neoplasia. Arch Dermatol 135 (10): 1195-202, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="11927500">Zbar B, Alvord WG, Glenn G, et al.: Risk of renal and colonic neoplasms and spontaneous pneumothorax in the Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 11 (4): 393-400, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="12459621" MedlineID="22346902">Pavlovich CP, Walther MM, Eyler RA, et al.: Renal tumors in the Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome. Am J Surg Pathol 26 (12): 1542-52, 2002.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_625"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/09/2025)</Title><Para id="_3184">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3208"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000574548#_4" url="/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics">Inheritance and Risk of Renal Cell Carcinoma</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_3209">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574548#_7" url="/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cancer cases and deaths for 2025 (cited American Cancer Society as reference 1).</Para><Para id="_3210"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000574548#_14" url="/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics">Family History as a Risk Factor for Renal Cell Carcinoma</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_3211">Added American Cancer Society as <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574548#_15" url="/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics">reference 1</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574548#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of renal cell carcinoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Genetics of Renal Cell Carcinoma are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Alexandra Perez Lebensohn, MS, CGC (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Brian Matthew Shuch, MD (UCLA Health)</ListItem><ListItem>Ramaprasad Srinivasan, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ Genetics of Renal Cell Carcinoma. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics">https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/hp/renal-cell-carcinoma-genetics</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389510]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2013-11-01</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-09</DateLastModified></Summary>
