<Summary id="CDR0000577190" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000547210"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>The last days of life for patients with cancer can involve a wide range of possible symptoms and ethical dilemmas. Learn about issues like delirium, fatigue, breathing and swallowing problems, constipation, muscle twitching, fever, bleeding, pain, and more in this expert-reviewed summary. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/last-days-pdq">Last Days of Life (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/last-days-hp-pdq">Last Days of Life (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000549861">end-of-life treatment/management</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_538">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about patient care during the last days to last hours of life. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_539">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>end-of-life treatment/management</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Last Days of Life (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Last Days of Life</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Last Days of Life</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_336">The end of life may be months, weeks, days, or hours. It   is a time when many decisions about treatment and care are  made for people with cancer. It is important for  families and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care providers</GlossaryTermRef> to talk openly with the person about their end-of-life plans and know their wishes ahead of time. This will make it easier for family members to make major decisions for the person at the end of life.</Para><Para id="_49">When treatment choices and plans are discussed before the end of life, it can lower the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef> on both the patient and the family.   It is most helpful if end-of life planning and decision-making begin soon after the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> is diagnosed and continue during the course of the disease. Having these decisions in writing can make the person's wishes clear to both the family and the health care team. </Para><Para id="_483">When a child is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044178" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">terminally ill</GlossaryTermRef>, end-of-life discussions with the child's doctor may reduce the time the child spends in the hospital and help the parents feel more prepared.</Para><Para id="_337">This summary is about end of life in adults with cancer and, where noted, children with cancer. It discusses care during the last days and last hours of life, including treatment of common <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000640058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ethical</GlossaryTermRef> questions that may come up. It may help patients and their families prepare for decisions they must make during this time. </Para><Para id="_338"> For more information on end-of-life planning, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hospice</GlossaryTermRef> care, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000814680" url="/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/planning/hospice-hp-pdq">Hospice</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_66"><Title>Care in the Final Hours</Title><SummarySection id="_67"><KeyPoint id="_248">Knowing what to expect in the final days or hours helps comfort the family.</KeyPoint><Para id="_249">Most people don't know the signs that show death is near. Knowing what to expect can help them get ready for the death of their loved one and make this time less <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stressful</GlossaryTermRef> and confusing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Health care providers</GlossaryTermRef> can give family members information about the changes they may see in their loved one in the final hours and how they may help their loved one through this. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_250"><KeyPoint id="_251">People may not want to eat or drink in the final days or hours.</KeyPoint><Para id="_68">In the final days to hours of life, people often lose the desire to eat or drink, and may not want food and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluids</GlossaryTermRef> that are offered to them. The family may give ice chips or swab the mouth and lips to keep them moist. Food and fluids should not be forced on the person because it can cause discomfort or choking. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_252"><KeyPoint id="_253">People near death may not respond to others.</KeyPoint><Para id="_245">People may withdraw and spend more time sleeping. They may answer questions slowly or not at all, seem <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">confused</GlossaryTermRef>, and may not be interested in what's going on around them. Most people are still able to hear after they are no longer able to speak.  It may give some comfort if family members continue to touch and talk to the person, even if they do not respond.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_254"><KeyPoint id="_255">A number of physical changes are common when a person is near death.</KeyPoint><Para id="_246">Certain physical changes may occur in a person at the end of life:</Para><ItemizedList id="_247" Style="bullet"><ListItem>They may feel tired or weak.</ListItem><ListItem>They may pass less <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef>, and it may be dark in color.</ListItem><ListItem>Their hands and feet may become blotchy, cold, or blue. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Caregivers</GlossaryTermRef> can use blankets to keep the person warm. Electric blankets or heating pads should not be used.</ListItem><ListItem>Their heart rate may go up or down and become irregular.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef> usually goes down. </ListItem><ListItem>Breathing may become irregular, with very shallow breathing, short periods of not breathing, or deep, rapid breathing.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_540">However, these  signs and changes don't always occur in everyone. For this reason, it may be hard to know  when a person is near death.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_256"><KeyPoint id="_257">Cultural or religious beliefs and customs may be important at the time of death.</KeyPoint><Para id="_258">After a person dies, family members and caregivers may wish to stay with them awhile. There may be certain customs or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476412" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rituals</GlossaryTermRef> that are important to the person and family at this time. These might include rituals for coping with death, handling the person's body, making final arrangements for the body, and honoring the death. It’s important to let the health care team know what customs or rituals are important to the person and their family after the person’s death.</Para><Para id="_259">Health care providers, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hospice</GlossaryTermRef> staff, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social workers</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef> leaders can explain the steps that need to be taken once death has occurred, including contacting a funeral home.</Para><Para id="_260">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000301599" url="/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality/spirituality-pdq">Spirituality in Cancer Care</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_56"><Title>Symptoms During the Final Months, Weeks, and  Days  of Life</Title><SummarySection id="_57"><Para id="_58">Common <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> at the end of life include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_484" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">delirium</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>feeling very tired</ListItem><ListItem>shortness of breath</ListItem><ListItem>pain</ListItem><ListItem>coughing</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>trouble swallowing</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000577034" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rattle</GlossaryTermRef> sound with breathing</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597160" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myoclonic jerks</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemorrhage</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><KeyPoint id="_131">Delirium</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_153"><KeyPoint id="_154">Delirium can have many causes at the end of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_155"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Delirium</GlossaryTermRef> is common during the final days of life. Most people have a lower  level of consciousness. They may be withdrawn, be less alert, and have less energy. Some people may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462659" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">agitated</GlossaryTermRef> or restless, and have  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hallucinations</GlossaryTermRef> (see or hear things not really there). People near death should be protected from having accidents or hurting themselves when they are confused or agitated.</Para><Para id="_215">Delirium can be caused by the direct effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, such as a growing tumor in the brain. Other causes include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_216" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A higher- or lower-than-normal amount of certain chemicals in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>  that keep the heart, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef>, and muscles working the way they should. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of drugs or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug interactions</GlossaryTermRef> (changes in the way a drug acts in the body when taken with certain other drugs, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbal medicine</GlossaryTermRef>, or foods).</ListItem><ListItem>Stopping the use of certain drugs or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044659" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Dehydration</GlossaryTermRef> (the loss of needed water from the body).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_156"><KeyPoint id="_157">Delirium may be controlled by finding and treating the cause.</KeyPoint><Para id="_217">Depending on the cause of the delirium, doctors may do the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_218" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Give drugs to fix the level of certain chemicals in the blood.</ListItem><ListItem>Stop or lower the dose of the drugs that are causing delirium, or are no longer useful at the end of life, such as drugs to lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cholesterol</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Treat dehydration by putting <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluids</GlossaryTermRef> into the bloodstream.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_158">For some people in the last hours of life, the decision may be to  treat only the symptoms of delirium and make the person as comfortable as possible.








There are drugs that work very well to relieve these symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_221"><KeyPoint id="_222">Hallucinations that are not related to delirium often occur at the end of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_223">  It is common for people near death to have  hallucinations that include loved ones who have already died. It is normal for family members to feel <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> when  these hallucinations occur. Speaking  with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430478" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clergy</GlossaryTermRef>, the hospital <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430477" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chaplain</GlossaryTermRef>, or other  religious advisors may help.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1"><KeyPoint id="_2">Fatigue</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_423"><KeyPoint id="_424">Fatigue is one of the most common symptoms in the last days of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_3">
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fatigue</GlossaryTermRef> (feeling very tired) is one of the most common symptoms in the last days of life. A person's fatigue may become worse every day during this time. Drowsiness, weakness, and sleep problems may occur.          Drugs that increase brain activity, alertness, and energy may be helpful.      For more information, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/fatigue">Cancer Fatigue</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_60"><KeyPoint id="_127">Shortness of Breath</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_141"><KeyPoint id="_142">Feeling short of breath is  common and may get worse during the final days or weeks of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_272">Shortness of breath or not being able to catch your breath is often caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Other causes include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_271" Style="bullet"><ListItem>build-up of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>loss of muscle strength</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597155" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypoxemia</GlossaryTermRef> (a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> in which there is not enough <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000524193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</GlossaryTermRef> (COPD)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pneumonia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_205"><KeyPoint id="_206">The use of opioids and other methods can help the person breathe more easily.</KeyPoint><Para id="_287"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045054" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Opioids</GlossaryTermRef> may relieve shortness of breath in people near death. Other drugs, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476099" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bronchodilators</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046601" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">steroids</GlossaryTermRef> may be considered if they are in line with the person’s goals of care. </Para><Para id="_207">Other ways to help people who feel short of breath include the following:     </Para><ItemizedList id="_208" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Give extra oxygen if    shortness of breath is caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597155" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypoxemia</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Aim a cool fan toward their face.</ListItem><ListItem>Have them sit up.</ListItem><ListItem>Give <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibiotics</GlossaryTermRef> if  the shortness of breath is caused by an infection.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><KeyPoint id="_263">Pain</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_276"><KeyPoint id="_277">Pain medicines can be given in several ways.</KeyPoint><Para id="_278">In the last days of life, a person may not be able to swallow pain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef>. When medicines cannot be taken by mouth, the pain medicine may be given by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These methods can be used at home with a doctor's order. 

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><KeyPoint id="_137">Pain during the final hours of life can usually be controlled. </KeyPoint><Para id="_126">Opioid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analgesics</GlossaryTermRef> work very well to relieve  pain and are commonly used at the end of life. Some patients and family members worry that the use of opioids may cause death to occur sooner, but <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">studies</GlossaryTermRef> have shown no link between opioid use and early death. For more information about opioids, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062845" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-pdq">Cancer Pain</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_292"><KeyPoint id="_293">Cough</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_425"><KeyPoint id="_426">Cough at the end of life can be treated in several ways.</KeyPoint><Para id="_294">Cough at the end of life may add to a person's discomfort. Repeated coughing can cause pain and loss of sleep, increase tiredness, and make shortness of breath worse. At the end of life, the decision may be to  treat the symptoms of the cough rather than to find and treat the cause. The following types of drugs may be used to make the person as comfortable as possible:</Para><ItemizedList id="_295" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044696" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Over-the-counter</GlossaryTermRef> cough medicines with expectorants to increase <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bronchial</GlossaryTermRef> fluids and loosen <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046274" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucus</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Medicines to decrease mucus production that can cause coughing in people who have trouble swallowing.</ListItem><ListItem>Opioids to stop the coughing.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_297">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000352193" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/cardiopulmonary-pdq">Cardiopulmonary Syndromes</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_346"><KeyPoint id="_347">Constipation</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_427"><KeyPoint id="_428">Constipation may occur  in the last days of life.</KeyPoint></SummarySection><Para id="_363">People with cancer may have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef> in the last days of life. People  who have trouble swallowing may not be able to take <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laxatives</GlossaryTermRef> by mouth to treat the constipation. If needed, laxatives may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044083" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectally</GlossaryTermRef> to make them comfortable.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_348"><KeyPoint id="_349">Trouble Swallowing</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_429"><KeyPoint id="_430">People may have trouble swallowing food and fluids at the end of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_364">People with cancer may have trouble swallowing in the last days of life. Both fluids and food may be hard to swallow, causing a  loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef>, weight loss  and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454763" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">muscle wasting</GlossaryTermRef>, and weakness. Small amounts of food that the person enjoys may be given if they want to eat. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Supplemental nutrition</GlossaryTermRef> does not benefit patients in the last days of life and may increase the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aspiration</GlossaryTermRef> and infections.</Para><Para id="_365">When the person cannot swallow, medicine may be given by placing it in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>, giving it by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>, or by placing a patch on the skin.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><KeyPoint id="_129">Death Rattle</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_147"><KeyPoint id="_148">Rattle occurs when saliva or other fluids collect in the throat and upper airways.</KeyPoint><Para id="_149"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000577034" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Rattle</GlossaryTermRef> occurs when <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257526" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">saliva</GlossaryTermRef> or other fluids build up in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef> and airways in a person who is too weak to clear the throat. There are two types of rattle. Death rattle is caused by saliva pooling at the back of the throat. The other kind of rattle is caused by fluid in the airways from an infection, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>, aspiration, or extra fluid in body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_262">Drugs may be given to decrease the amount of saliva in the mouth or to dry the upper airway.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_211"><KeyPoint id="_212">Non-drug treatments for rattle include changing the person's position and giving less   fluid.</KeyPoint><Para id="_213">Raising the head of the bed, propping the person up with pillows, or turning them to either side often relieves rattle. If the rattle is caused by fluid at the back of the throat, the fluid may be gently removed from the mouth using a suction tube.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_150"><KeyPoint id="_151">Death rattle is a sign that death may soon occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_152">Death rattle is a sign that death may occur in hours or days. Rattle can be very upsetting for those at the bedside. It  does not seem to be painful for the person and is not the same as shortness of breath.   </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_350"><KeyPoint id="_351">Myoclonic Jerking</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_431"><KeyPoint id="_432">Myoclonic jerks  may be caused by taking very high doses of opioids for a long time.</KeyPoint><Para id="_352"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597160" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Myoclonic jerks</GlossaryTermRef> are sudden muscle twitches or jerks that cannot be controlled by the person having them. A hiccup is one type of myoclonic jerk.  Brief, shock-like jerks can occur in one or more different muscle groups anywhere in the body. Taking very high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of an opioid for a long time may cause this <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effect</GlossaryTermRef>, but it can have other causes as well.   </Para><Para id="_353">When opioids are the cause of myoclonic jerking, changing to another opioid may help. People respond to opioids in different ways, and certain opioids may be more likely than others to cause myoclonic jerking in some people.</Para><Para id="_354">When a person is very near death, medicine to stop the myoclonic jerking may be given instead of changing the opioid. When  myoclonic jerking is severe, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> may be used to calm the person down, relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef>, and help them sleep.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_63"><KeyPoint id="_132">Fever</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_433"><KeyPoint id="_434">Fever may be caused by infection, medicines, or the cancer itself.</KeyPoint><Para id="_530">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef> in the last days of life depends on whether it causes the  person <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> or discomfort. Fever may be caused by  infection, medicines, or the cancer itself.  Although  infections may be treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibiotics</GlossaryTermRef>, people near the end of life may choose not to treat the  cause of the fever.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_64"><KeyPoint id="_134"> Hemorrhage</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_165"><KeyPoint id="_166">Sudden hemorrhage (heavy bleeding) may occur in people who have certain cancers or disorders.</KeyPoint><Para id="_167"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hemorrhage</GlossaryTermRef> (heavy bleeding in a short time) is rare but may occur in the last hours or minutes of life.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> may be damaged by certain cancers or cancer treatments. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, for example, can  weaken blood vessels in the area that was treated. Tumors can also damage blood vessels. People with the following conditions have an increased risk of hemorrhage:</Para><ItemizedList id="_226" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, especially <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390317" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulcers</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045789" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucositis</GlossaryTermRef> caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clotting</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disorders</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_274">The person and family should talk with the doctor about any concerns they have about the chance of hemorrhage.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_168"><KeyPoint id="_169">Making the person comfortable  is the main goal of care during hemorrhage at the end of life. </KeyPoint><Para id="_435">It is hard to know when hemorrhage might occur.   When sudden bleeding occurs at the end of life, people usually become  unconscious and die soon afterwards. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000744627" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Resuscitation</GlossaryTermRef> (restarting the heart) usually will not work.</Para><Para id="_227">The main goal of care is to make the person comfortable and to support family members. If hemorrhage occurs, it can be very upsetting, and it may be helpful for the family to ask questions about it and talk about their feelings with one another and their care team.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_474"><Title>Care Decisions in the Final Weeks, Days, and Hours of Life</Title><SummarySection id="_366"><KeyPoint id="_448">Decisions about Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_367">Decisions about whether to continue or stop <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are made by the patient and doctor together. About one-third of people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef> continue to receive chemotherapy or other treatment near the end of life.</Para><Para id="_475">Treatment with  chemotherapy  at this time  can result in the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_476" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side  effects</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>spending more days  in the hospital</ListItem><ListItem>spending the last days of life in an intensive care unit</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_370">However, some people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> choose to continue chemotherapy because they feel it helps them to live  in  the present and  focus on active treatment. Other people choose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative</GlossaryTermRef> or comfort care to  treat pain and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. These decisions are based on   the person's goals of care and the likely  risks and benefits of treatment. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_547"><KeyPoint id="_548">Decisions about Targeted Therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_549">Decisions about whether to continue or stop <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> are made by the patient and doctor together. Targeted therapies may help people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef> that have spread to other areas in the body.</Para><Para id="_550">Treatment with targeted therapy at the end of life can result in the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_551" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>spending the last days of life  in a hospital</ListItem><ListItem>poor awareness of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>less time to prepare for the end of life</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_541"><KeyPoint id="_546">Decisions about Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_542">Decisions about whether to continue or stop <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> are made by the patient and doctor together. Many people taking immunotherapy are older or are no longer helped by chemotherapy, but these drugs may still have unwanted side effects.</Para><Para id="_543">Treatment with immunotherapy at the end of life can result in the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_544" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>being less likely to use <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hospice</GlossaryTermRef> services</ListItem><ListItem>spending the last days of life in the hospital</ListItem><ListItem>having  problems related to medical costs (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790159" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">financial toxicity</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_368"><KeyPoint id="_449">Decisions about Hospice</KeyPoint><Para id="_371">Hospice care is an important end-of-life option for people with advanced cancer. People may feel that beginning hospice care means they have given up. Some people fear   losing the relationship with their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046260" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>. However, many patients and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">caregivers</GlossaryTermRef> feel they receive important benefits from hospice care.</Para><Para id="_477">People who receive hospice care seem to have the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_478" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>better mental outlook</ListItem><ListItem>better relief of symptoms</ListItem><ListItem>better communication</ListItem><ListItem>better end-of-life care</ListItem><ListItem>more days spent at home</ListItem><ListItem>less stressful death (without causing death to happen sooner)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_482">Hospice-related services include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_373" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>visiting <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nurse</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430477" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chaplain</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688836" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counselor</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>home health aide</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000661205" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respite care</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_374">Doctors, patients, and caregivers should discuss hospice care and when it should begin.</Para><Para id="_465">When hospice benefits are covered by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000640052" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Medicare</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physicians</GlossaryTermRef> are required to certify that  the person is not expected to live more than 6 months and is not being treated to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cured</GlossaryTermRef>. Other policies may be different, depending on the hospice and  the state.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_369"><KeyPoint id="_450">Decisions about Place of Death</KeyPoint><Para id="_376">Many people with advanced cancer wish to  die at home. People who die at home with hospice services and support seem to have better symptom control and quality of life. They also feel better prepared for death  than people who die in a hospital or intensive care unit. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Grieving</GlossaryTermRef> caregivers have less trouble adjusting to their loss and feel they have honored the person's wishes when their loved one dies at home.</Para><Para id="_377">People who get hospice care are more likely to be able to die at home.  Hospice care can help control the person's symptoms and give the caregiver the help  they need.</Para><Para id="_378">However, not all people choose to die at home. It is important for the person, caregivers, and doctors to discuss where the person wants to die and the best way to fulfill   the person's decision.</Para><Para id="_545">For children with advanced cancer, families and doctors should discuss wishes for the place of death early in the course of the disease. Children who die in the hospital may have more intense treatments and their parents may have more complicated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grief</GlossaryTermRef> than those of children who die at home.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_302"><Title>Decisions about Life-Sustaining Treatments in the Last Days of Life</Title><SummarySection id="_532"><KeyPoint id="_383">In the last days of life, patients and family members will have to make decisions about treatments to keep the person alive.</KeyPoint><Para id="_303">Decisions about whether to use life-sustaining treatments that may extend life in the final weeks or days cause a great deal of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">confusion</GlossaryTermRef> and  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef>. Some of these treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ventilator</GlossaryTermRef> use, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390306" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">parenteral nutrition</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dialysis</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_466">People near death may be guided by their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046260" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>, but they have the right to make their own choices about     life-sustaining treatments.   The following are some of the questions to discuss:</Para><ItemizedList id="_304" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>What are the person’s goals of care?</ListItem><ListItem>How would the possible benefits of  life-sustaining treatments help reach the person's goals of care, and how likely is the desired outcome? </ListItem><ListItem>How would  the possible harms of life-sustaining treatments affect the person's goals of care? Is the possible benefit worth the possible harm?</ListItem><ListItem>Besides possible benefits and harms of life-sustaining treatments, what else can affect the decision?</ListItem><ListItem>Are there other resources, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative care</GlossaryTermRef>, a  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430477" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chaplain</GlossaryTermRef>, or a medical ethicist, that could help the person or family make decisions about life-sustaining treatments?</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_485"><KeyPoint id="_486">Choices about care and treatment at the end of life should be made while the person is able to make them.</KeyPoint><Para id="_487">A person may wish to receive all possible treatments, only some treatments, or no treatment at all in the last days of life.         These decisions may be written down ahead of time in an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430404" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advance directive</GlossaryTermRef>, such as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441252" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">living will</GlossaryTermRef>. Advance directive is the general term for different types of legal documents that describe the treatment or care a patient wishes to receive or not receive when he or she is no longer able to speak their wishes.</Para><Para id="_552">Without knowing a person's wishes, the health care team will do everything medically possible to keep the person alive, such as cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) and the use of a ventilator (breathing machine). </Para><Para id="_488">Studies have shown that people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> who have end-of-life discussions with their doctors choose to have fewer procedures, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000744627" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resuscitation</GlossaryTermRef> or the use of a ventilator. They are also less likely to be in intensive care, and the cost of their health care is lower during their final week of life. Reports from their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">caregivers</GlossaryTermRef> show that these people live just as long as those who choose to have more procedures, and have a better <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> in their last days.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_489"><KeyPoint id="_490">Care that supports a person's spiritual health may improve quality of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_491">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef> assessment is a method or tool used by doctors to understand  the role that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000489395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">religious</GlossaryTermRef> and spiritual beliefs have in the person's life. This may help the doctor understand how these beliefs affect the way the person <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">copes</GlossaryTermRef> with cancer  and makes decisions about cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_492">Serious illnesses like cancer may cause people or family caregivers to have doubts about their beliefs or religious values and cause spiritual <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>.  Some studies show that people with cancer may feel anger at God or may have a loss of faith after being <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef>. Other people may have feelings of spiritual distress when coping with cancer.   Spiritual distress may affect end-of-life decisions and increase <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_493">Doctors and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nurses</GlossaryTermRef>, together with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social workers</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologists</GlossaryTermRef>,  may be able to offer care that supports a person's spiritual health. They may encourage the person to meet with their spiritual or religious leaders or join  a spiritual <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045917" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">support group</GlossaryTermRef>. This may improve a person's quality of life and ability to cope. When people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef> receive spiritual support from the medical team, they are  more likely to choose hospice care and less aggressive treatment at the end of life.</Para><Para id="_494">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000301599" url="/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality/spirituality-pdq">Spirituality in Cancer Care</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_495"><KeyPoint id="_496">Fluids</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_533"><KeyPoint id="_498">The goals of giving fluids at the end of life should be discussed by patient, family, and doctors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_499"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fluids</GlossaryTermRef> may be given when the person can no longer eat or drink  normally. Fluids may be given  with  an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> or through a needle under the skin.</Para><Para id="_500">Decisions about giving fluids should be based on the person's goals of care. Giving fluids   has not been shown to help patients live longer or improve their quality of life. However, the harms are minor and the family may feel there are benefits if the person is  less <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigued</GlossaryTermRef> and more alert.</Para><Para id="_501">The family may also be able to give the person sips of water or ice chips or swab the mouth and lips to keep them moist.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_502"><KeyPoint id="_503">Nutrition Support</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_534"><KeyPoint id="_504">The goals of nutrition support for patients in the last days of life are different from the goals during cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_505"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nutrition</GlossaryTermRef> support can improve health and boost healing during <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> treatment.  The goals of nutrition therapy for people  during the last days of life are different from the goals for people in active cancer treatment and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef>. In the final days of life, people often lose the desire to eat or drink and may not want food or fluids that are offered to them. Also, procedures used to put in feeding tubes may be hard on them.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_506"><KeyPoint id="_507">Making plans for  nutrition support in the last days is helpful.</KeyPoint><Para id="_508">The goal of end-of-life care is to prevent suffering and relieve symptoms. If nutrition support  causes the person more discomfort than help, then nutrition support near the end of life may be stopped. The needs and best interests of each person guide the decision to give nutrition support. When decisions and plans about nutrition support are made by the person near death, doctors and family members can be sure they are doing what the person wants.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_509"><KeyPoint id="_510">Two types of nutrition support are commonly used.</KeyPoint><Para id="_511">If the person cannot swallow, two types of nutrition support are commonly used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_512" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390275" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Enteral nutrition</GlossaryTermRef> uses a tube inserted into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestine</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390306" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Parenteral nutrition</GlossaryTermRef> uses an intravenous (IV) catheter inserted into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef>. 
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_513">Each type of nutrition support has benefits and risks.  
 For more information, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nutrition">Nutrition During Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_514"><KeyPoint id="_515">Antibiotics</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_535"><KeyPoint id="_516">The benefits of using antibiotics in the last days of life are  unclear.</KeyPoint><Para id="_517">The use of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibiotics</GlossaryTermRef> and other treatments for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef> is common in people in the last days of life, but it is hard to tell how well they work. It is also hard to tell if there are any benefits of using antibiotics at the end of life.</Para><Para id="_518">Overall, doctors want to make the person comfortable in the last days of life rather than  give treatments that may not help them live longer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_519"><KeyPoint id="_520">Transfusions</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_536"><KeyPoint id="_521">The decision to use blood transfusions in advanced cancer depends on goals of care and other factors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_522">Many people with advanced cancer have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef>. People with advanced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000733834" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood cancers</GlossaryTermRef> may have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045365" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thrombocytopenia</GlossaryTermRef> (a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> in which there is a lower-than-normal number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>). Deciding whether to  use <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045991" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood transfusions</GlossaryTermRef> for these conditions is based on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_523" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>goals of care</ListItem><ListItem>how long the person is expected to live</ListItem><ListItem>the   benefits and risks of the transfusion</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_524">The decision can be hard to make because people usually need to receive transfusions in a medical setting rather than at home.</Para><Para id="_525">Many people with cancer are used to receiving  blood transfusions during active treatment or  supportive care and may want to  continue transfusions to feel better. However, studies have not shown that transfusions are safe and effective at the end of life.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_526"><KeyPoint id="_527">Resuscitation</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_537"><KeyPoint id="_528">People should decide whether or not they want cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR).</KeyPoint><Para id="_529">An important decision for a person near death to make is whether to have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000744627" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cardiopulmonary resuscitation</GlossaryTermRef>    (CPR) (trying to restart the heart and breathing when it stops). It is best if people   talk with  their family, doctors, and caregivers about their wishes for CPR as early as possible (for example, when being admitted to the hospital or when active cancer treatment is stopped). A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430480" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">do-not-resuscitate (DNR) order</GlossaryTermRef> is written by a doctor to tell other health professionals not to perform CPR at the moment of death, so that the natural process of dying occurs. If the person wishes, he or she can ask the doctor to write a DNR order. The person can ask that the DNR order be changed or removed at any time.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_333"><Title>Last Days in the Hospital or Intensive Care Unit</Title><SummarySection id="_393"><KeyPoint id="_404">Choices about whether to use intensive care should be discussed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_405">Near the end of life, people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may be admitted to a hospital or   intensive care unit (ICU) if they have not made other choices for their care. In the ICU, patients or family members have to make hard decisions about whether to start, continue, or stop aggressive treatments that may make the person live longer but harm their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>. Families may be unsure of their feelings or have trouble deciding whether to limit or avoid  treatments.</Para><Para id="_406">Sometimes, treatments like <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dialysis</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045991" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood transfusions</GlossaryTermRef> may be tried for a short time. However, at any time, patients or families may talk with doctors about  whether they want to continue with ICU care. They may  choose instead to change over  to  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269449" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">comfort care</GlossaryTermRef> in the final days.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_394"><KeyPoint id="_397">Ventilator use may keep a person alive after normal breathing stops.</KeyPoint><Para id="_398"> A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ventilator</GlossaryTermRef> is a machine that helps people breathe. Sometimes, using a ventilator will not improve the person's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> but will keep them alive longer. If the goal of care is to help the person live longer, a ventilator may be used, according to  the person's wishes. If ventilator support stops  helping or is no longer what the person wants, the person, their family, and the health care team may decide to turn the ventilator off.</Para><SummarySection id="_400"><KeyPoint id="_401">Before a ventilator is turned off, family members will be given information about what to expect.</KeyPoint><Para id="_402">Family members will be given information about how the person may respond when the ventilator is removed and about pain relief or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sedation</GlossaryTermRef> to keep the person comfortable. Family members will be given time to contact other  loved ones who wish to be there. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430477" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chaplains</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social workers</GlossaryTermRef> may be called to support to the family.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_407"><Title>Suffering and Palliative Sedation at the End of Life</Title><SummarySection id="_408"><KeyPoint id="_409">The emotions of patients and caregivers are closely connected.</KeyPoint><Para id="_411">Patients and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">caregivers</GlossaryTermRef> share the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer,  with the caregiver's distress sometimes being greater than the patient's distress. Since caregiver suffering can affect the person's well-being and the caregiver's adjustment to loss, early and constant support of the caregiver is very important.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_412"><KeyPoint id="_413">Palliative sedation lowers the level of consciousness and relieves extreme pain and suffering.</KeyPoint><Para id="_416"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000744625" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Palliative sedation</GlossaryTermRef> uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450118" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sedatives</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve extreme suffering by making a person calm and unaware.</Para><Para id="_414">The decision whether to sedate a person at the end of life   is a hard one. Sedation may be  considered for a person's comfort or for a physical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> such as uncontrolled pain. Palliative sedation may be given on and off, or until death. A person's thoughts and feelings  about end-of-life sedation may depend greatly on his or her own <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476357" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">culture</GlossaryTermRef> and beliefs.
Some people who become anxious facing the end of life may want to be sedated. Some people and their families may wish to have a level of sedation that allows them to communicate with each other. Other people may wish to have no procedures, including sedation, just before death.</Para><Para id="_417">Studies have not shown that palliative sedation shortens life when used in the last days.</Para><Para id="_415">It is important for the person to tell family members and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650566" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health care providers</GlossaryTermRef> of their wishes about   sedation at the end of life. When a person makes their wishes about sedation known ahead of time, doctors and family members can be sure they are doing what the person would want. Families may need  support from the health care team and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mental health counselors</GlossaryTermRef> while palliative sedation is used.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_418"><Title>Grief and Loss</Title><Para id="_419"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Grief</GlossaryTermRef> is a normal reaction to the loss of a loved one. People who feel unable to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cope</GlossaryTermRef> with their loss may be helped by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476410" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grief counseling</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476411" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grief therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with trained professionals. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062828" url="/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/bereavement-pdq">Grief, Bereavement, and Coping With Loss</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about patient care during the last days to last hours of life.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Last Days of Life. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/last-days-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/last-days-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389429]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000543592"/><DateFirstPublished>2007-12-18</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-15</DateLastModified></Summary>
