<Summary id="CDR0000593427" LegacyPDQID="" ReplacementFor="CDR0000062816"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers screening means looking for cancer before there are symptoms. Currently, no standard or routine screening has shown to help reduce deaths from these types of cancer. Learn more in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/oral-screening-pdq">Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/oral-screening-pdq">Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040091">lip and oral cavity cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038961">head and neck cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_95">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers screening. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_96">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>head and neck squamous cell cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>lip and oral cavity cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>nasopharyngeal cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers Screening (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers Screening</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>What Is Screening?</Title><Para id="_2"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Screening</GlossaryTermRef> is looking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> before a person has any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. This can help find cancer at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> or cancer is found early, it may be easier to treat. By the time symptoms appear, cancer may have begun to spread.</Para><Para id="_3"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> are trying to better understand which people are more likely to get certain types of cancer. They also study the things we do and the things around us to see if they cause cancer. This information helps doctors recommend who should be screened for cancer, which screening tests should be used, and how often the tests should be done.</Para><Para id="_4">It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily think you have cancer if he or she suggests a screening test. Screening tests are given when you have no cancer symptoms.</Para><Para id="_5">If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045959" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><Title>General Information About Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers</Title><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_10">Oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers are diseases in which malignant (cancer) cells form in the mouth and throat.</KeyPoint><Para id="_111"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641672" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Oral cavity cancer</GlossaryTermRef> usually forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046056" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">squamous cells</GlossaryTermRef> (thin, flat cells lining the inside of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral cavity</GlossaryTermRef>).  </Para><Para id="_11">Oral cavity cancer forms in any of these tissues of the oral cavity:</Para><ItemizedList id="_103" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the lips</ListItem><ListItem>the front two thirds of the tongue</ListItem><ListItem>the gingiva (gums)</ListItem><ListItem>the buccal mucosa (the lining of the inside of the cheeks)</ListItem><ListItem>the floor (bottom) of the mouth under the tongue</ListItem><ListItem>the hard palate (the front of the roof of the mouth)</ListItem><ListItem>the retromolar trigone (the small area behind the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443581" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wisdom teeth</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000716338" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the oral cavity; drawing shows the lip, hard palate, soft palate, retromolar trigone, front two-thirds of the tongue, gingiva, buccal mucosa, and floor of mouth. Also shown are the teeth, uvula, and tonsil." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_94"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the oral cavity. The oral cavity includes the lips, hard palate (the bony front portion of the roof of the mouth), soft palate (the muscular back portion of the roof of the mouth), retromolar trigone (the area behind the wisdom teeth), front two-thirds of the tongue, gingiva (gums), buccal mucosa (the inner lining of the lips and cheeks), and floor of the mouth under the tongue.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_104"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445075" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pharyngeal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> forms in the tissues of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046061" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharynx</GlossaryTermRef> (throat), including the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharynx</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharynx</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046029" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypopharynx</GlossaryTermRef>. This summary covers <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharyngeal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, which forms in the tissue of the nasopharynx (the upper part of the throat behind the nose).</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000713970" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the pharynx; drawing shows the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and hypopharynx. Also shown are the nasal cavity, oral cavity, hyoid bone, larynx, esophagus, and trachea." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_107"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the pharynx. The pharynx is a hollow, muscular tube inside the neck that starts behind the nose and opens into the larynx and esophagus. The three parts of the pharynx are the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and hypopharynx.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_84">Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summaries containing information related to  oral cavity and nasopharyngeal  cancers include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_85" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000593570" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/oral-prevention-pdq">Oral Cavity, Oropharyngeal, Hypopharyngeal, and Laryngeal Cancers Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258017" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/lip-mouth-treatment-pdq">Lip and Oral Cavity Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062966" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Nasopharyngeal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">The number of new cases of oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers and the number of deaths from these cancers vary by sex and geographic region.</KeyPoint><Para id="_98">From 2012 to 2021, the number of new cases of oral cavity cancer in the United States increased slightly each year.</Para><Para id="_101">Oral cavity cancer is more common in men than in women. Although oral cavity cancer may occur in adults of any age, it occurs most often in those aged 75 to 84 years.</Para><Para id="_102">France, Brazil, and parts of Asia have much higher rates of oral cavity cancer than most other countries.</Para><Para id="_114">Nasopharyngeal cancer is rare in the United States. Some indigenous populations in Southeast Asia, the Arctic, North Africa, and the Middle East have higher rates of nasopharyngeal cancers.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Different factors increase or decrease the risk of oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_21">Anything that increases your chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Anything that decreases your chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factor</GlossaryTermRef>.

</Para><Para id="_120">Being infected with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef> (EBV) increases the risk of nasopharyngeal cancer.</Para><Para id="_97">Other PDQ summaries containing information related to  oral cavity and nasopharyngeal  cancers include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_121" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000593570" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/oral-prevention-pdq">Oral Cavity, Oropharyngeal, Hypopharyngeal, and Laryngeal Cancers Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258017" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/lip-mouth-treatment-pdq">Lip and Oral Cavity Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_24"><Title>Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_25"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Screening methods</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_26">Tests are used to screen for different types of cancer when a person does not have symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_28"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests to find those with the fewest harms and most benefits. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> screening trials also are meant to show whether early detection (finding cancer before it causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>) helps a person live longer or decreases a person's chance of dying from the disease. For some types of cancer, the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef> is better if the disease is found and treated at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><KeyPoint id="_31">There are no standard or routine screening tests for oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers.</KeyPoint><Para id="_116">No studies have shown that screening for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641672" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral cavity cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharyngeal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> would lower the risk of dying from these diseases.</Para><Para id="_64">A dentist or medical doctor may check the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral cavity</GlossaryTermRef> during a routine check-up. The exam will include looking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesions</GlossaryTermRef>, including areas of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045954" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukoplakia</GlossaryTermRef> (an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> white patch of cells) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046413" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">erythroplakia</GlossaryTermRef> (an abnormal red patch of cells). Leukoplakia and erythroplakia lesions on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucous membranes</GlossaryTermRef> may become cancerous.
</Para><Para id="_70"> If lesions are seen in the mouth, the following procedures may be used to find abnormal tissue that might become oral cavity cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Toluidine blue stain: A procedure in which lesions in the mouth are coated with a  blue dye. Areas that stain darker are more likely to be cancer or become cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Fluorescence staining: A procedure in which lesions in the mouth are viewed using a special light. After the patient uses a fluorescent mouth rinse, normal tissue looks different from abnormal tissue when seen under the light. </ListItem><ListItem>Exfoliative <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytology</GlossaryTermRef>: A procedure to collect cells from the oral cavity. A piece of cotton, a brush, or a small wooden stick is used to gently scrape cells from the lips, tongue, or mouth. The cells are viewed under a microscope to find out if they are abnormal.</ListItem><ListItem>Brush <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>: The removal of cells using a brush that is designed to collect cells from all layers of a lesion. The cells are viewed under a microscope to find out if they are abnormal.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_66">More than half of oral cancers have already spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> or other areas by the time they are found. </Para><Para id="_115"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef> (EBV) has been linked to nasopharyngeal cancer. Screening for nasopharyngeal cancer using the EBV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibody</GlossaryTermRef> test or EBV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> test has been studied. These are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory tests</GlossaryTermRef> used to check the blood for EBV antibodies or EBV DNA. If EBV antibodies or DNA are found in the blood,  more tests may be done to check for nasopharyngeal cancer. No studies have shown that screening would decrease the risk of dying from this disease.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><KeyPoint id="_119">Screening tests for oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers are being studied in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_118_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_72"><Title>Risks of Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_73"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risks of screening</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_74">Screening tests have risks.</KeyPoint><Para id="_75">Decisions about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests can be difficult. Not all screening tests are helpful and most have risks. Before having any screening test, you may want to discuss the test with your doctor. It is important to know the risks of the test and whether it has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><KeyPoint id="_77">The risks of screening for oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers include:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_86"><KeyPoint id="_87">Finding these cancers may not improve health or help a person live longer.

   </KeyPoint><Para id="_93">Some cancers never cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> or become life-threatening, but if found by a screening test, the cancer may be treated. Finding these cancers is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000759894" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overdiagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>. It is not known if treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641672" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral cavity cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharyngeal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> would help you live longer than if no treatment were given, and treatments for cancer, such as surgery and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, may have serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_78"><KeyPoint id="_79">False-negative test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_80">Screening test results may appear to be normal even though oral cavity cancer or nasopharyngeal cancer is present. A person who receives a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-negative test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical care even if there are symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_81"><KeyPoint id="_82">False-positive test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_83">Screening test results may appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> even though no cancer is present. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-positive test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and is usually followed by more tests and procedures (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>), which also have risks.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about oral cavity and nasopharyngeal cancers screening.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/oral-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/oral-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389441]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062752"/><DateFirstPublished>2008-07-01</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-08</DateLastModified></Summary>
