<Summary id="CDR0000062697" LegacyPDQID="1189"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Adult central nervous system tumor treatment may include surgery, radiosurgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy, surveillance, and targeted therapy. Treatment depends on the tumor type. Learn more about brain and spinal tumor treatment in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">Adult Central Nervous System Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/hp/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">Adult Central Nervous System Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038717">adult brain tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_616">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult central nervous system tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_617">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly, and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adult brain tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>anaplastic astrocytomas</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>astrocytic tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>brain stem gliomas</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>CNS germ cell tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>craniopharyngiomas
</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>diffuse astrocytomas</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>glioblastomas</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>medulloblastomas
</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>meningeal tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>mixed gliomas
ependymal tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>oligodendroglial tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>pilocytic astrocytomas</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>pineal astrocytic tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>pineal parenchymal tumors</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Adult Central Nervous System Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Adult Central Nervous System Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Adult Central Nervous System Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Adult Central Nervous System Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_373">An adult central nervous system (CNS) tumor is a disease in which abnormal cells form in the tissues of the brain and/or spinal cord.</KeyPoint><Para id="_475">There are many types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>. The tumors are formed by the abnormal growth of cells and may begin in different parts of the brain or spinal cord. Together, the brain and spinal cord make up the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef> (CNS).</Para><Para id="_4">The tumors may be either <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045614" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign</GlossaryTermRef> (not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> (cancer):</Para><ItemizedList id="_558" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Benign brain and spinal cord tumors grow and press on nearby areas of the brain. They rarely spread into other tissues and may recur (come back). </ListItem><ListItem>Malignant brain and spinal cord tumors are likely
		  to grow quickly and spread into other brain tissue. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_559">When a tumor grows into or presses on an area of the brain, it may stop that part of the brain from working the way it should. Both benign and malignant brain tumors cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and need treatment.</Para><Para id="_411">Brain  and spinal cord tumors can occur in both  adults and children. However, treatment for
		  children may be different than treatment for adults.</Para><Para id="_522">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> that begins in the brain, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258030" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/primary-cns-lymphoma-treatment-pdq">Primary CNS Lymphoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_514"><KeyPoint id="_515">A tumor that starts in another part of the body and spreads to the brain is called a metastatic brain tumor.</KeyPoint><Para id="_516">Tumors that start in the brain are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary</GlossaryTermRef> brain tumors.
Primary brain tumors may spread to other parts of the brain or to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>. They rarely spread to other parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_580">Often, tumors found in the brain have started somewhere else in the body and spread to one or more parts of the brain. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> brain tumors (or brain metastases). Metastatic
		  brain tumors are more common than primary brain tumors.  Up to half of metastatic brain tumors are from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.

</Para><Para id="_602">Cancer may spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leptomeninges</GlossaryTermRef> (the two innermost <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046294" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">membranes</GlossaryTermRef> covering the brain and spinal cord). This is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000747577" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leptomeningeal carcinomatosis</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_476"><KeyPoint id="_477">The brain controls many important body functions. 

</KeyPoint><Para id="_478">The brain has three major parts: 

</Para><ItemizedList id="_479" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrum</GlossaryTermRef> is the largest part of the brain. It is at the top of the head. The cerebrum controls thinking, learning, problem solving, emotions, speech, reading, writing, and voluntary movement. 
</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebellum</GlossaryTermRef> is in the lower back of the brain (near the middle of the back of the head). It controls movement, balance, and posture. 
</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046491" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain stem</GlossaryTermRef> connects the brain to the spinal cord. It is in the lowest part of the brain (just above the back of the neck). The brain stem controls breathing, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart rate</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef> and muscles used to see, hear, walk, talk, and eat.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000765034" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the brain; two-panel drawing showing the cerebrum, ventricles (fluid-filled spaces), cerebellum, brain stem (pons and medulla), and spinal cord. Also shown are the meninges and skull (left panel) and the choroid plexus, hypothalamus, pineal gland, pituitary gland, and optic nerve (right panel)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_599"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the brain showing the cerebrum, ventricles (with cerebrospinal fluid shown in blue), cerebellum, brain stem (pons and medulla), and other parts of the brain.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_492"><KeyPoint id="_498">The spinal cord connects the brain to nerves in most parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_494">The spinal cord is a column of nerve tissue that runs from the brain stem down the center of the back. It is covered by three thin layers of tissue called membranes. These membranes are surrounded by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vertebrae</GlossaryTermRef> (back bones). Spinal cord nerves carry messages between the brain and the rest of the body, such as a message from the brain to cause muscles to move or a message from the skin to the brain to feel touch.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><KeyPoint id="_381">There are different types of brain and spinal cord tumors. </KeyPoint><Para id="_210">Brain and spinal cord tumors are named based on the type of cell they formed in and where the tumor first formed in the CNS. The  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grade</GlossaryTermRef> of a  tumor may be used to tell the difference between slow-growing and fast-growing types of the tumor. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454794" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">World Health Organization</GlossaryTermRef> (WHO) tumor grades are based on how abnormal the cancer cells look under a microscope and how quickly the tumor is likely to grow and spread.</Para><ItemizedList id="_520" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>WHO Tumor Grading System</ListTitle><ListItem>Grade I (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">low-grade</GlossaryTermRef>) — The tumor cells look more like normal cells under a microscope and grow and spread more slowly than grade II, III, and IV tumor cells. They rarely spread into nearby tissues. Grade I brain tumors may be completely removed by surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Grade II — The tumor cells grow and spread more slowly than grade III and IV tumor cells. They may spread into nearby tissue and may recur (come back). Some tumors may become a higher-grade tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Grade III — The tumor cells look very different from normal cells under a microscope and grow more quickly than grade I and II tumor cells. They are likely to spread into nearby tissue.</ListItem><ListItem>Grade IV (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386205" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-grade</GlossaryTermRef>) — The tumor cells do not look like normal cells under a microscope and grow and spread very quickly. There may be areas of dead cells in the tumor. Grade IV tumors usually cannot be completely removed by surgery.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_585">The following types of primary tumors can form in the brain or spinal cord:</Para><SummarySection id="_495"><KeyPoint id="_499">Astrocytic Tumors</KeyPoint><Para id="_513">An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045602" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">astrocytic tumor</GlossaryTermRef> begins in star-shaped brain cells called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">astrocytes</GlossaryTermRef>, which help keep <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve cells</GlossaryTermRef> healthy. An astrocyte is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269440" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glial cell</GlossaryTermRef>. Glial cells sometimes form tumors called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gliomas</GlossaryTermRef>. Astrocytic tumors include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_500" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Brain stem glioma (usually high grade)</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045624" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain stem glioma</GlossaryTermRef> forms in the  brain stem, which is the part of the brain connected to the spinal cord. It is often a high-grade tumor, which spreads widely through the brain
			 stem. Brain stem gliomas are rare in adults. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Pineal astrocytic tumor (any grade)</Strong>: A pineal astrocytic tumor
			 forms in tissue around the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046226" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineal gland</GlossaryTermRef> and  may be any grade. The pineal gland is a tiny organ in the brain that makes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440118" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melatonin</GlossaryTermRef>, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef> that helps control the sleeping and waking cycle.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Pilocytic astrocytoma (grade I)</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pilocytic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045602" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">astrocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> grows slowly in the brain or spinal cord. It may be in the form of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046461" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyst</GlossaryTermRef> and
				rarely spreads into nearby tissues. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Diffuse astrocytoma (grade II)</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diffuse</GlossaryTermRef> astrocytoma grows slowly, but often spreads into nearby  tissues. The tumor cells look something like normal cells. It is also called a low-grade diffuse astrocytoma. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Anaplastic astrocytoma (grade III)</Strong>: An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> astrocytoma grows quickly and spreads into nearby  tissues. The tumor cells look
				different from normal cells. An anaplastic astrocytoma is also called a malignant astrocytoma or high-grade astrocytoma. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Glioblastoma (grade IV)</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glioblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> grows and spreads very quickly. The tumor cells look very different from normal cells. It is
				also called glioblastoma multiforme. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><KeyPoint id="_452">Oligodendroglial Tumors</KeyPoint><Para id="_69">An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045808" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oligodendroglial tumor</GlossaryTermRef> begins in brain cells called
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000540447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oligodendrocytes</GlossaryTermRef>, which help keep nerve cells healthy.  An oligodendrocyte is a type of glial cell. Oligodendrocytes sometimes form tumors called oligodendrogliomas. Grades of oligodendroglial tumors include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_368" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Oligodendroglioma (grade II)</Strong>: An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046257" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oligodendroglioma</GlossaryTermRef> grows slowly, but often spreads into nearby  tissues. The tumor cells look something like normal cells.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Anaplastic oligodendroglioma (grade III)</Strong>: An anaplastic oligodendroglioma grows quickly and spreads into nearby tissues. The tumor cells look different from normal cells.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><KeyPoint id="_453">Mixed Gliomas</KeyPoint><Para id="_78">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045344" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mixed glioma</GlossaryTermRef> is a brain tumor that has  two types of tumor cells in it — oligodendrocytes and astrocytes. This type of mixed tumor is called an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321382" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oligoastrocytoma</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><ItemizedList id="_369" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Oligoastrocytoma (grade II)</Strong>: An oligoastrocytoma is a slow-growing tumor. The tumor cells look something like normal cells.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Anaplastic oligoastrocytoma (grade III)</Strong>: An anaplastic oligoastrocytoma grows quickly and spreads into nearby tissues. The tumor cells look
				 different from normal cells. This type of tumor has a worse <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> than oligoastrocytoma (grade II). </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_55"><KeyPoint id="_454">Ependymal Tumors</KeyPoint><Para id="_57">An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045679" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ependymal tumor</GlossaryTermRef> usually begins in cells that line the
			 fluid-filled spaces in the brain and
			 around the spinal cord. An ependymal tumor may also be called an ependymoma. Grades of ependymomas include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_370" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Ependymoma (grade I or II)</Strong>: A grade I or II <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046432" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ependymoma</GlossaryTermRef> grows slowly and has cells
				that look something like normal cells. There are two types of  grade I ependymoma —  myxopapillary ependymoma and subependymoma. A grade II ependymoma grows in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045939" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ventricle</GlossaryTermRef> (fluid-filled space in the brain) and its connecting paths or in the spinal cord.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Anaplastic ependymoma (grade III)</Strong>: An anaplastic ependymoma grows quickly and spreads into nearby tissues. The tumor cells look different from normal cells. This type of tumor usually has a worse prognosis than a grade I or II ependymoma. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><KeyPoint id="_455">Medulloblastomas</KeyPoint><Para id="_81">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045780" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medulloblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embryonal tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. Medulloblastomas are most common in children or young adults. </Para><Para id="_332"> For more information about medulloblastomas in children, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_238"><KeyPoint id="_456">Pineal Parenchymal Tumors</KeyPoint><Para id="_240"> A pineal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044503" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">parenchymal</GlossaryTermRef> tumor forms in parenchymal cells or pineocytes,  which are the cells that make up most of  the pineal gland. These tumors are different  from pineal astrocytic tumors. Grades of pineal parenchymal
			 tumors include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_371" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Pineocytoma (grade II)</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046228" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a slow-growing pineal tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Pineoblastoma (grade IV)</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046227" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineoblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a rare tumor that is very likely to spread.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_567">For more information about pineal parenchymal tumors in  children, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552550" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-embryonal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Medulloblastoma and Other Central Nervous System Embryonal Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><KeyPoint id="_457">Meningeal Tumors</KeyPoint><Para id="_90">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045781" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meningeal</GlossaryTermRef> tumor, also called a meningioma, forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046295" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meninges</GlossaryTermRef> (thin layers of tissue that cover the
			 brain and spinal cord). It can form from different types of brain or spinal cord cells. Meningiomas are most common in adults. Types of meningeal tumors include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_372" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Meningioma (grade I)</Strong>: A grade I meningioma is the most common type of meningeal tumor. A grade I meningioma is a slow-growing tumor. It forms most often in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000743301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dura mater</GlossaryTermRef>. A grade I meningioma  may be completely removed by surgery.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Meningioma (grade II and III)</Strong>: This is a rare meningeal tumor.  It grows quickly
				and is likely
				to spread within the brain and spinal cord. The prognosis is worse than a grade I meningioma because the tumor usually cannot be completely removed by surgery. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_503">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045707" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemangiopericytoma</GlossaryTermRef> is not a meningeal tumor but is treated like a grade II or III meningioma. A hemangiopericytoma usually forms in the dura mater.  The prognosis is worse than a grade I meningioma because the tumor usually cannot be completely removed by surgery. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_241"><KeyPoint id="_458">Germ Cell Tumors</KeyPoint><Para id="_243">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ cell tumor</GlossaryTermRef> forms in germ cells, which are the cells that develop into <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257221" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sperm</GlossaryTermRef>  in men or ova (eggs) in women. There are different types of germ cell tumors. These include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046383" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germinomas</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">teratomas</GlossaryTermRef>, embryonal yolk sac <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045963" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinomas</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046753" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">choriocarcinomas</GlossaryTermRef>. Germ cell tumors can be either benign or malignant. </Para><Para id="_333"> For more information about childhood germ cell tumors in the brain, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719453" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cns-germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Germ Cell Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_244"><KeyPoint id="_459">Craniopharyngioma (Grade I)</KeyPoint><Para id="_587">A  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046131" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">craniopharyngioma</GlossaryTermRef> is a rare tumor that usually forms in the center of the brain just above the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pituitary gland</GlossaryTermRef> (a pea-sized organ at the bottom of the brain that controls other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glands</GlossaryTermRef>).  Craniopharyngiomas can form from different types of brain or spinal cord cells. </Para><Para id="_568">For more information about craniopharyngioma in children, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000574137" url="/types/brain/patient/child-cranio-treatment-pdq">Childhood Craniopharyngioma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_374">Having certain genetic syndromes may increase the risk of a CNS tumor.
 </KeyPoint><Para id="_480">Anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop a brain or spinal cord tumor, and they can develop in people who don't have any known risk factors. Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk. There are few known risk factors for brain tumors. The following conditions may increase the risk of  certain types of brain tumors: </Para><ItemizedList id="_481" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vinyl chloride</GlossaryTermRef> may increase the risk of   glioma.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Infection</GlossaryTermRef> with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef>, having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">AIDS</GlossaryTermRef>, or receiving an organ <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef> may increase the risk of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary CNS lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258030" url="/types/lymphoma/patient/primary-cns-lymphoma-treatment-pdq">Primary CNS Lymphoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Having certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">syndromes</GlossaryTermRef> may increase the risk brain tumors:<ItemizedList id="_521" Style="dash"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Neurofibromatosis type 1</GlossaryTermRef> (NF1) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">2</GlossaryTermRef> (NF2).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">von Hippel-Lindau disease</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tuberous sclerosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046322" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Li-Fraumeni syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Turcot syndrome type 1 or 2.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000442897" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_581"><KeyPoint id="_582">The cause of most adult brain and spinal cord tumors is not known.</KeyPoint></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_440">The signs and symptoms  of adult brain and spinal cord tumors are not the same in every person. </KeyPoint><Para id="_597">Signs and symptoms depend on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_598" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Where the tumor forms in the brain or spinal cord.</ListItem><ListItem>What the affected part of the brain controls.</ListItem><ListItem>The size of the tumor.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_441">These and other signs and symptoms may be caused by CNS tumors or by other conditions, including cancer that has spread to the brain. Check with your doctor if you have any of the  following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListTitle>Brain Tumor Symptoms</ListTitle><ListItem>Morning headache or headache that goes away after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Seizures</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Vision, hearing, and speech problems.</ListItem><ListItem>Loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Frequent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and vomiting. 
</ListItem><ListItem>Changes in personality, mood, ability to focus, or behavior.</ListItem><ListItem>Loss of balance and trouble walking.</ListItem><ListItem>Weakness.</ListItem><ListItem>Unusual sleepiness or change in activity level. 
</ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_501" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>Spinal Cord Tumor Symptoms</ListTitle><ListItem>Back pain or pain that spreads from the back towards the arms or legs.</ListItem><ListItem>A change in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef> habits or trouble <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinating</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Weakness or numbness in the arms or legs.</ListItem><ListItem>Trouble walking.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_376">Tests that examine the brain and spinal cord are used to 
		  diagnose adult brain and spinal cord tumors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_23">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_24" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><Strong>Neurological exam</Strong>: A series of questions and tests to check the brain, spinal cord, and nerve function. The exam checks a person's mental status, coordination, and ability to walk normally, and how well the muscles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">senses</GlossaryTermRef>, and reflexes work. This may also be called a neuro exam or a neurologic exam.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Visual field exam</Strong>: An exam to check a person's field of vision (the total area in which objects can be seen). This test measures both central vision (how much a person can see when looking straight ahead) and peripheral vision (how much a person can see in all other directions while staring straight ahead). Any loss of vision may be a sign of a tumor that has damaged or pressed on the parts of the brain that affect eyesight. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000732562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumor marker test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a sample of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef>, or tissue is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances made by organs, tissues, or tumor cells in the body. Certain substances are linked to specific types of cancer when found in increased levels in the body. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor markers</GlossaryTermRef>. This test may be done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> a germ cell tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gene testing</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> in which cells or tissue are analyzed to look for changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosomes</GlossaryTermRef>. These changes may be a sign that a person has or is at risk of having a specific disease or condition.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT
			 scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000753849" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan of the brain; drawing shows a patient lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes x-ray pictures of the brain." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_619"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan of the brain. The patient lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes x-ray pictures of the brain.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic
			 resonance imaging) with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597153" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gadolinium</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of the brain and spinal cord.  A substance called gadolinium is injected into  a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). MRI is often used to diagnose tumors in the spinal cord. Sometimes a procedure called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">magnetic resonance spectroscopy</GlossaryTermRef> (MRS) is done during the  MRI <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scan</GlossaryTermRef>. An MRS is used to diagnose tumors, based on their chemical make-up. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306534" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">SPECT</GlossaryTermRef> scan (single photon emission computed tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find malignant tumor cells in the brain. A small amount of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance is injected into a vein or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhaled</GlossaryTermRef> through the nose. As the substance travels through the blood, a camera rotates around the head and takes pictures of the brain. A computer uses the pictures to make a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3-D) image of the brain. There will be increased blood flow and more activity in areas where cancer cells are growing. These areas will show up brighter in the picture.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find malignant tumor cells in the body. A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into a vein. The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the brain. Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do. PET is used to tell the difference between a primary tumor and a tumor that has spread to the brain from somewhere else in the body.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000466545" type="image/jpeg" alt="PET (positron emission tomography) scan; drawing shows patient lying on table that slides through the PET machine." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_620"><Caption language="en">PET (positron emission tomography) scan. The patient lies on a table that slides through the PET machine.  The head rest and white strap help the patient lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the patient's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do.
</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem> 
		   
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_203"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_377">A biopsy is also used to diagnose a brain tumor.</KeyPoint><Para id="_529">If <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging tests</GlossaryTermRef> show there may be a brain tumor, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> is usually done. One of the following types of biopsies may be used:

</Para><ItemizedList id="_533" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Stereotactic biopsy</Strong>: When imaging tests show there may be a tumor deep in the brain in a hard to reach place, a stereotactic brain biopsy may be done. This kind of  biopsy uses a computer and a 3-dimensional (3-D) scanning device to find the tumor and guide the needle used to remove the  tissue. A small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> is made in the scalp, and a small hole is drilled through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef>. A biopsy needle is inserted through the hole to remove cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335492" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Open biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: When imaging tests show that there may be a tumor  that can be removed  by surgery, an open biopsy may be done. A part of the skull is removed in an operation called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">craniotomy</GlossaryTermRef>. A sample of brain tissue is removed and viewed under a microscope by a pathologist. If cancer cells are found, some or all of the  tumor may be removed during the same surgery.  Tests are done before surgery to find the areas around the tumor that are important for normal brain function. There are also ways to test brain function during surgery. The doctor will use the results of these tests to remove as much of the tumor as possible with the least damage to normal tissue in the brain. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000680519" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of a craniotomy showing a section of the scalp that has been pulled back to remove a piece of the skull; the dura covering the brain has been opened to expose the brain. The layer of muscle under the scalp is also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_588"><Caption language="en">Craniotomy:  An opening is made in the skull and a piece of the skull is removed to show part of the brain.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_532">The pathologist checks the biopsy sample to find out the type and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062697#_520" url="/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">grade</SummaryRef> of the brain tumor. The grade of the tumor is based on how the tumor cells look under a microscope, and how quickly the tumor is likely to grow and spread.
</Para><Para id="_483">The following tests may be done on the tumor tissue that is removed:</Para><ItemizedList id="_484" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000653117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunohistochemistry</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient's tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044052" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Light</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electron microscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test in which cells in a sample of tissue are viewed under regular and high-powered microscopes to look for certain changes in the cells. 
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cytogenetic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test in which the chromosomes of cells in a sample of brain tissue are counted and checked for any changes, such as broken, missing, rearranged, or extra chromosomes. Changes in certain chromosomes may be a sign of cancer. Cytogenetic analysis is used to help diagnose cancer, plan treatment, or find out how well treatment is working.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_551"><KeyPoint id="_552">Sometimes a biopsy or surgery cannot be done.</KeyPoint><Para id="_553">For some tumors, a biopsy or surgery cannot be done safely because of where the tumor formed in the brain or spinal cord. These tumors are diagnosed and treated based on the results of imaging tests and other procedures.</Para><Para id="_561">Sometimes the results of imaging tests and other procedures show that the tumor is very likely to be benign, and a biopsy is not done.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_379">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_217">The prognosis and treatment options for <Emphasis>primary</Emphasis> brain and spinal cord tumors depend on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_215" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The type and grade of the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem> Where the tumor is in the brain or spinal cord.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the tumor can be removed by surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether cancer cells remain after surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether there are certain changes in the chromosomes.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has recurred (come back).</ListItem><ListItem>The patient's general health.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_412">The prognosis and treatment options for <Emphasis>metastatic</Emphasis> brain and spinal cord tumors depend on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_413" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Whether there are more than two tumors in the brain or spinal cord.</ListItem><ListItem>Where the tumor is in the brain or spinal cord.</ListItem><ListItem>How well the tumor responds to treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the primary tumor continues to grow or spread.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><Title>Stages of Adult Central Nervous System Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_220"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_380">There is no standard staging system for adult brain and spinal cord tumors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_219">The process used to find out if cancer has spread to other areas of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> or to other parts of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef> that begin in the brain rarely spread to other parts of the body. There is no standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging system</GlossaryTermRef> for brain and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> tumors. </Para><Para id="_632">Treatment of primary brain and spinal cord tumors is based on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_583" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The type of cell in which the tumor began.</ListItem><ListItem>Where the tumor formed in the brain or spinal cord.</ListItem><ListItem>The amount of cancer left after surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grade</GlossaryTermRef> of the tumor.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_584">Treatment of tumors that have spread to the brain from other parts of the body is based on the number of tumors in the brain.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_485"><KeyPoint id="_486">Imaging tests may be repeated after surgery to help plan more treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_487">Some of the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062697#_20" url="/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">tests and procedures</SummaryRef> used to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> a brain or spinal cord tumor may be repeated after treatment to find out how much tumor is left. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_633"><KeyPoint id="_634">Central nervous system (CNS) tumors often recur, sometimes many years
		after treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_635">A recurrent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CNS</GlossaryTermRef> tumor is a  tumor that has recurred (come back)
		after it has been treated. The tumor may recur at the same place as the first tumor or in other parts of the CNS.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_102"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_103"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_384">There are different types of treatment for patients with adult
		  brain and spinal cord tumors. </KeyPoint><Para id="_105">Different types of treatment are available for patients with adult
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> tumors. Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and
		  some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical
		  trials</GlossaryTermRef>. A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new
		  treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new
		  treatment is better than the standard
		  treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment.
		  Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_107"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_386">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_608"><KeyPoint id="_609">Active surveillance</KeyPoint><Para id="_610">

<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000616060" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Active surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> is closely watching a patient’s condition but not giving any treatment unless there are changes in test results that show the condition is getting worse. Active surveillance may be used to avoid or delay the need for treatments such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> or surgery, which can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> or other problems. During active surveillance, certain exams and tests are done on a regular schedule. Active  surveillance may be used for very slow-growing tumors that do not cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_109"><KeyPoint id="_387">Surgery </KeyPoint><Para id="_111">Surgery may be used to diagnose and treat adult brain and spinal cord tumors. Removing tumor tissue helps decrease pressure of the tumor on nearby parts of the brain. See the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062697#_203" url="/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef> section of this summary.</Para><Para id="_443">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time  of the surgery, some patients may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or radiation therapy after surgery to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after the surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_112"><KeyPoint id="_388">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_199">Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000732668" type="image/jpeg" alt="External-beam radiation therapy of the brain; drawing shows a patient lying on a table under a machine that is used to aim high-energy radiation. An inset shows a mesh mask that helps keep the patient's head from moving during treatment. The mask has pieces of white tape with small ink marks on it. The ink marks are used to line up the radiation machine in the same position before each treatment." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_640"><Caption language="en">External-beam radiation therapy of the brain. A machine is used to aim high-energy radiation. The machine can rotate around the patient, delivering radiation from many different angles. A mesh mask helps keep the patient’s head from moving during treatment. Small ink marks are put on the mask. The ink marks are used to line up the radiation machine in the same position before each treatment.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_636">Certain ways of giving external radiation therapy can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy tissue. These types of radiation therapy include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_637" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270731" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Conformal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>:

   Conformal radiation therapy uses a computer to make a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3-D) picture of the tumor and shapes the radiation beams to fit the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (IMRT): IMRT is a type of 3-dimensional (3-D) radiation therapy that uses a computer to make pictures of the size and shape of the tumor.  Thin beams of radiation of different intensities (strengths) are aimed at the tumor from many angles.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stereotactic radiosurgery</GlossaryTermRef>: Stereotactic radiosurgery uses a rigid head frame that is attached to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef> to keep the head still during the radiation treatment.  A machine aims a single large <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> of radiation directly at the tumor. This procedure does not involve surgery.  It is also called stereotaxic radiosurgery, radiosurgery, and radiation surgery.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_115"><KeyPoint id="_389">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_200">Chemotherapy is a cancer treatment that uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).  Although most cannot, some chemotherapy drugs can cross the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046504" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood-brain barrier</GlossaryTermRef> and reach tumor cells in the brain. Chemotherapy that is placed directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef> is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. When chemotherapy is inserted in an organ, such as the brain, or a body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef>, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>). </Para><Para id="_641">To treat  brain tumors, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wafer</GlossaryTermRef> that dissolves may be used to deliver a chemotherapy drug directly to the brain tumor site after the tumor has been removed by surgery. The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the type and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774694" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grade</GlossaryTermRef> of tumor and where it is in the brain.</Para><Para id="_528">See <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/brain">Drugs Approved for Brain Tumors</ExternalRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_590"><KeyPoint id="_591">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_592"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. </Para><ItemizedList id="_638" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046066" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Monoclonal antibody</GlossaryTermRef>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>: Monoclonal antibodies are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef> made in the laboratory to treat many diseases, including cancer. As a cancer treatment, these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> can attach to a specific target on cancer cells or other cells that may help cancer cells grow. The antibodies are able to then kill the cancer cells, block their growth, or keep them from spreading. Monoclonal antibodies are given by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. They may be used alone or to carry drugs, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxins</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> material directly to cancer cells.<Para id="_639"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bevacizumab</GlossaryTermRef> is a monoclonal antibody that binds to  a protein called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vascular endothelial growth factor</GlossaryTermRef> (VEGF) and may prevent the growth of new <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> that tumors need to grow. Bevacizumab is used in the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glioblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><EmbeddedVideo id="_642" ref="CDR0000801837" hosting="youtube" unique_id="dxnjAc-rqz8" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>monoclonal antibodies: how monoclonal antibodies treat cancer</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">How do  monoclonal antibodies work to treat cancer? This video shows how monoclonal antibodies, such as trastuzumab, pembrolizumab, and rituximab, block molecules cancer cells need to grow, flag cancer cells for destruction by the body’s immune system, or deliver harmful substances to cancer cells. </Caption></EmbeddedVideo></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_596">Other types of targeted therapies are being studied for adult brain tumors, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044833" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tyrosine kinase inhibitors</GlossaryTermRef> and new VEGF inhibitors.</Para><Para id="_595">See <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/brain">Drugs Approved for Brain Tumors</ExternalRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_615"><KeyPoint id="_613">Supportive care is given to lessen the problems caused by the disease or its treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_614">This therapy controls problems or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by the disease or its treatment and improves <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>. For brain tumors, supportive care includes drugs to control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seizures</GlossaryTermRef> and  fluid buildup or swelling in the brain. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_119"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_390">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.
		  </KeyPoint><Para id="_465">This summary section refers to new treatments being studied in clinical trials, but it may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_539"><KeyPoint id="_540">Proton beam radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_541"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Proton beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>    is a type of high-energy, external radiation therapy that uses streams of protons (tiny particles with a positive charge) to kill tumor cells. This type of treatment can lower the amount of radiation damage to healthy tissue near a tumor. It is used to treat cancers of the head, neck, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef> and organs such as the brain, eye, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef>. Proton beam radiation is different from x-ray radiation.  
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_129"><KeyPoint id="_393">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_131"> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment that uses the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to fight cancer. Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the body's natural defenses against cancer.  </Para><Para id="_578">Immunotherapy is being studied for the treatment of some types of brain tumors. Treatments may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_579" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044949" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Dendritic cell vaccine</GlossaryTermRef> therapy.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gene therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_626"><KeyPoint id="_627">Treatment for adult central nervous system tumors may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_626_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_466"><KeyPoint id="_467">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_466_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_466_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_466_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_468"><KeyPoint id="_469">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_468_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_468_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_470"><KeyPoint id="_471">Follow-up tests may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_470_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_470_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_562">The following tests and procedures may be used to check whether a brain tumor has come back after treatment:</Para><ItemizedList id="_563" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306534" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">SPECT</GlossaryTermRef> scan (single photon emission computed tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> tumor cells in the brain. A small amount of a radioactive substance is injected into a vein or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inhaled</GlossaryTermRef> through the nose. As the substance travels through the blood, a camera rotates around the head and takes pictures of the brain. A computer uses the pictures to make a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3-D) image of the brain. There will be increased blood flow and more activity in areas where cancer cells are growing. These areas will show up brighter in the picture.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find malignant tumor cells in the body. A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into a vein. The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the brain. Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000466545" type="image/jpeg" alt="PET (positron emission tomography) scan; drawing shows patient lying on table that slides through the PET machine." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_621"><Caption language="en">PET (positron emission tomography) scan. The patient lies on a table that slides through the PET machine.  The head rest and white strap help the patient lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the patient's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do.
</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Primary Adult Brain Tumor by Type of Tumor </Title><Para id="_628">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062697#_107" url="/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><SummarySection id="_512"><Title>Astrocytic Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_257"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038825">adult brain stem glioma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Brain Stem Gliomas</Title><Para id="_542">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045624" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain stem gliomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_257_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_255"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000561966">adult pineal gland astrocytoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Pineal Astrocytic Tumors</Title><Para id="_320">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046226" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">astrocytic</GlossaryTermRef> tumors may include surgery and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. For high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grade</GlossaryTermRef> tumors, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also be given.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_255_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_247"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041741">adult pilocytic astrocytoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Pilocytic Astrocytomas</Title><Para id="_544">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pilocytic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045602" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">astrocytomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include surgery to remove the tumor. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also be given if some of the tumor remains after surgery.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_247_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_249"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041743">adult diffuse astrocytoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Diffuse Astrocytomas</Title><Para id="_140">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diffuse</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045602" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">astrocytomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_394" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery followed by radiation therapy and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_249_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_251"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040858">adult anaplastic astrocytoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Anaplastic Astrocytomas</Title><Para id="_144">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045602" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">astrocytomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include the
		  following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_395" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also be given.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery and chemotherapy.</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of chemotherapy placed into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> during surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of a new treatment added to  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_251_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_253"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038830">adult glioblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Glioblastomas</Title><Para id="_148">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glioblastomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include the
		  following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_396" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> given at the same time, followed by chemotherapy alone.  </ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>Surgery followed by radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy placed into the brain during surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy and chemotherapy given at the same time.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of a new treatment added to  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_253_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_259"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000430660">adult oligodendroglial tumors</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Oligodendroglial Tumors</Title><Para id="_163">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046257" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oligodendrogliomas</GlossaryTermRef> may
		  include surgery with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> may be given after radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_167"> Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> oligodendroglioma may include the
		  following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_586" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery followed by radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of a new treatment added to  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_259_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_261"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041195">adult mixed glioma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Mixed Gliomas</Title><Para id="_171">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045344" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mixed gliomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include surgery and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. Sometimes, 
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is also given. </Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_261_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_263"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000430659">adult ependymal tumors</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Ependymal Tumors</Title><Para id="_156">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grade</GlossaryTermRef> I and grade II <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046432" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ependymomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include surgery to remove the tumor. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also be given if some of the tumor remains after surgery.</Para><Para id="_159">Treatment of grade III <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> ependymoma may include surgery and radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_263_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_267"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038828">adult medulloblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Medulloblastomas</Title><Para id="_175">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045780" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medulloblastomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include the
		  following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_404" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain and
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> added to surgery and radiation therapy to the brain and
			 spine.</ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_267_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_265"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041196">adult pineal parenchymal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Pineal Parenchymal Tumors</Title><Para id="_180">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046226" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044503" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">parenchymal</GlossaryTermRef> tumors may include the
		  following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_403" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046228" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pineocytomas</GlossaryTermRef>, surgery and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>For pineoblastomas, surgery, radiation therapy, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_265_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_269"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000377472">adult meningeal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Meningeal Tumors</Title><Para id="_189">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grade</GlossaryTermRef> I <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045783" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meningiomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_405" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000616060" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Active surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> for tumors with no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove the tumor. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also be given if some of the tumor remains after surgery.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stereotactic radiosurgery</GlossaryTermRef> for tumors smaller than 3 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>Radiation therapy for  tumors that cannot be
			 removed by surgery. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_192"> Treatment of grade II and III meningiomas and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045707" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemangiopericytomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include the
		  following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_406" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery and radiation therapy. </ListItem> 
		   
		  </ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_269_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_271"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041197">adult central nervous system germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Germ Cell Tumors</Title><Para id="_184"> There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ cell tumors</GlossaryTermRef> (germinoma, embryonal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045963" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046753" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">choriocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">teratoma</GlossaryTermRef>). Treatment depends on what the tumor cells look like under a microscope, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor markers</GlossaryTermRef>, where the tumor is in the brain, and whether it can be removed by surgery.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_271_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_273"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038827">adult craniopharyngioma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Craniopharyngiomas</Title><Para id="_186"> Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046131" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">craniopharyngiomas</GlossaryTermRef> may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_407" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to completely remove the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible, followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_273_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_572"><Title>Treatment of Primary Adult Spinal Cord Tumors</Title><Para id="_629">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062697#_107" url="/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_573">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef> tumors may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_574" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to remove the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of a new treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_195"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038719">recurrent adult brain tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent  Adult Central Nervous System Tumors</Title><Para id="_630">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062697#_107" url="/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_275">There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000427310" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system (CNS) tumors</GlossaryTermRef>. Treatment depends on the patient's condition, the expected <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of the treatment, where the tumor is in the CNS, and whether the tumor can be removed by surgery. Treatment may include the
		following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_550" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> placed into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> during surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy with drugs not used to treat the original tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for recurrent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glioblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of a new treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_195_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_430"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040825">tumors metastatic to brain</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic Adult Brain Tumors</Title><Para id="_631">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062697#_107" url="/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_431">Treatment of one to four  tumors that have spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain</GlossaryTermRef> from another part of the body may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_433" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the whole brain with or without surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy to the whole brain with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stereotactic radiosurgery</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Stereotactic radiosurgery.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, if the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is one that responds to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639945" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anticancer</GlossaryTermRef> drugs. It may be combined with radiation therapy. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_611">Treatment of tumors that have spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leptomeninges</GlossaryTermRef> may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_612" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Chemotherapy (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic</GlossaryTermRef> and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046681" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrathecal</GlossaryTermRef>). Radiation therapy may also be given.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Supportive care</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_430_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_472"><Title>To Learn More About Adult Central Nervous System Tumors</Title><Para id="_473">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about adult <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000427310" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system (CNS) tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_474" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain">Brain Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/rare-brain-spine-tumor">NCI-CONNECT (Comprehensive Oncology Network Evaluating Rare CNS Tumors)</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/brain">Drugs Approved for Brain Tumors</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_472_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_472_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult central nervous system tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Adult Central Nervous System Tumors Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/brain/patient/adult-brain-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389458]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062900"/><DateLastModified>2024-01-05</DateLastModified></Summary>
