<Summary id="CDR0000062713" LegacyPDQID="1361"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Melanoma treatment options include surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy, immunotherapy, and targeted therapy. Learn more about the diagnosis and treatment of newly diagnosed and recurrent melanoma in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Melanoma (PDQ®):Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/hp/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Melanoma (PDQ®):Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038833">melanoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_325">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of melanoma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_326">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>melanoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Melanoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Melanoma Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Melanoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_67"><Title>General Information About Melanoma</Title><SummarySection id="_68"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_69">Melanoma is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form in melanocytes (cells that color the skin). </KeyPoint><Para id="_70">The skin is the body's largest organ. It protects against heat, sunlight, injury, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>. Skin also helps control body temperature and stores water, fat, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000427253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin D</GlossaryTermRef>. The skin has several layers, but the two main layers are the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epidermis</GlossaryTermRef> (upper or outer layer) and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046454" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dermis</GlossaryTermRef> (lower or inner layer). <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Skin cancer</GlossaryTermRef> begins in the epidermis, which is made up of three kinds of cells:</Para><ItemizedList id="_308" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046056" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Squamous cells</GlossaryTermRef>: Thin, flat cells that form the top layer of the epidermis.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046516" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Basal cells</GlossaryTermRef>: Round cells under the squamous cells.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Melanocytes</GlossaryTermRef>: Cells that make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046291" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanin</GlossaryTermRef> and are found in the lower part of the epidermis. Melanin is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pigment</GlossaryTermRef> that gives skin its natural color. When skin is exposed to the sun or artificial light, melanocytes make more pigment and cause the skin to darken.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000579033" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the skin with melanocytes; drawing shows normal skin anatomy, including the epidermis, dermis, hair follicles, sweat glands, hair shafts, veins, arteries, fatty tissue, nerves, lymph vessels, oil glands, and subcutaneous tissue. The pullout shows a close-up of the squamous cell and basal cell layers of the epidermis above the dermis with blood vessels. Melanin is shown in the cells. A melanocyte is shown in the layer of basal cells at the deepest part of the epidermis." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_241"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the skin, showing the epidermis, dermis, and subcutaneous tissue. Melanocytes are in the layer of basal cells at the deepest part of the epidermis.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_309"><KeyPoint id="_310">There are different types of cancer that start in the skin.</KeyPoint><Para id="_323">There are two main forms of skin cancer: melanoma and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046261" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nonmelanoma</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_311">Melanoma is a rare form of skin cancer. It is more likely to invade nearby tissues and spread to other parts of the body than other types of skin cancer. When melanoma starts in the skin, it is called cutaneous melanoma. Melanoma may also occur in mucous membranes (thin, moist layers of tissue that cover surfaces such as the lips). This summary is about cutaneous (skin) melanoma and melanoma that affects the mucous membranes.</Para><Para id="_315">Before age 50, rates of melanoma are higher in women than in men. After age 50, rates of melanoma are much higher in men. Melanoma is most common in adults, but it is sometimes found in children and
		  adolescents. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799744" url="/types/skin/patient/child-melanoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Melanoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_313">The most common types of skin cancer are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046515" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">basal cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046595" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">squamous cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>.  They are nonmelanoma skin cancers. Nonmelanoma skin cancers rarely spread to other parts of the body. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258035" url="/types/skin/patient/skin-treatment-pdq">Skin Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_77">Melanoma can occur anywhere on the skin.</KeyPoint><Para id="_78">In men,
		  melanoma is often found on the trunk (the area from the shoulders to the hips)
		  or the head and neck. In women, melanoma forms most often on the arms and legs.</Para><Para id="_314">When melanoma occurs in the eye, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269460" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraocular</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269467" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ocular melanoma</GlossaryTermRef>. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258015" url="/types/eye/patient/intraocular-melanoma-treatment-pdq">Intraocular (Uveal) Melanoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_80">Unusual moles, exposure to sunlight, and health history can
		  affect the risk of melanoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_417">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Some risk factors for melanoma, such as tanning bed use, can be changed. However, risk factors also include things people cannot change, like their genetics and their family history. Learning about risk factors for melanoma can help you make changes that might lower your risk of getting it.</Para><Para id="_322">Risk factors for melanoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_261" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having a fair complexion, which includes:
<ItemizedList id="_262" Style="dash"><ListItem>fair skin that freckles and burns easily, does not tan, or tans poorly</ListItem><ListItem>blue or green or other light-colored eyes</ListItem><ListItem>red or blond hair</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>being exposed to natural sunlight or artificial sunlight (such as from tanning beds)</ListItem><ListItem>being exposed to certain factors, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solvents</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vinyl chloride</GlossaryTermRef>, and PCBs, in the environment (the air, your home or workplace, and your food and water)  </ListItem><ListItem>having a history of many blistering sunburns, especially as a child or teenager
</ListItem><ListItem>having several large or many small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046286" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">moles</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of unusual moles (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000715624" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">atypical nevus</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>having a family or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of melanoma</ListItem><ListItem>being White</ListItem><ListItem>having a weakened <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having certain changes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> that are linked to melanoma</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_295">Being White or having a fair complexion increases the risk of melanoma, but anyone can have melanoma, including people with dark skin. </Para><Para id="_304">Learn more about risk factors for melanoma at <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552637" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Skin Cancer</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062802" url="/types/skin/patient/skin-prevention-pdq">Skin Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_83"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_84">Signs of melanoma include a change in the way a mole or pigmented area looks. </KeyPoint><Para id="_85">These and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by melanoma or by other conditions.
		  Check with your doctor if you have:</Para><ItemizedList id="_86" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>a mole that: 
			 <ItemizedList id="_87" Style="dash">
				<ListItem>changes in size, shape, or color</ListItem>
				<ListItem>has irregular edges or borders</ListItem>
				<ListItem>is more than one color</ListItem>
				<ListItem>is asymmetrical (if the mole is divided in half, the 2
				  halves are different in size or shape)</ListItem>
				<ListItem>itches</ListItem>
				<ListItem> oozes, bleeds, or is ulcerated (a hole forms in the skin when the top layer of cells breaks down and the tissue below shows through)</ListItem>
			 </ItemizedList></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>a change in  pigmented (colored) skin
			 </ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>satellite moles (new moles that grow near an existing
			 mole)</ListItem>
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_451">The acronym <Strong>ABCDE</Strong> can help you remember the signs of melanoma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_416" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>A</Strong>symmetrical</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>B</Strong>order</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>C</Strong>olor</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>D</Strong>iameter (melanoma is usually larger than 6 millimeters)</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>E</Strong>volving (the mole changes in size, shape, or color over time</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_293">Find pictures and descriptions of common moles and melanoma at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/moles-fact-sheet">Common Moles, Dysplastic Nevi, and Risk of Melanoma</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_89">Tests that examine the skin are used to diagnose melanoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_418">Melanoma is usually diagnosed with tests that examine the skin. The process used
		  to find out if cancer cells have spread beyond the skin is
		  called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. To plan treatment, it is important to know the stage of
		  the disease.</Para><Para id="_90">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures to find and diagnose melanoma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_91" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><Strong>Skin exam</Strong> is an exam where a doctor or nurse checks the skin for moles, birthmarks, or other pigmented areas that look abnormal in color,
			 size, shape, or texture.</ListItem>
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope to check for signs of cancer.  It can be hard to tell the difference between a colored mole and an early melanoma <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesion</GlossaryTermRef>. Patients may want to have the sample of tissue checked by a second pathologist. If the abnormal mole or lesion is cancer, the sample of tissue may also be tested for certain gene changes. This may help to plan treatment. Learn about the type of information that can be found in a pathologist's report about the cells or tissue removed during a biopsy at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/diagnosis/pathology-reports-fact-sheet">Pathology Reports</ExternalRef>.<Para id="_375">There are four main types of skin biopsies. The type of biopsy done depends on where the abnormal area formed and the size of the area.</Para><ItemizedList id="_376" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Shave biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sterile</GlossaryTermRef> razor blade to "shave off" the growth.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000410643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Punch biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a special instrument called a punch or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000423245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trephine</GlossaryTermRef> to remove a circle of tissue from the growth.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000578083" type="image/jpeg" alt="Punch biopsy; drawing shows a sharp, hollow, circular instrument being inserted into a lesion on the skin of a patient’s forearm. The instrument is turned clockwise and counterclockwise to cut into the skin and remove a small, round piece of tissue. A pullout shows that the instrument cuts about 4 millimeters (mm) down to the layer of fatty tissue below the skin." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_145"><Caption language="en">Punch biopsy. A sharp, hollow, circular instrument is used to remove a small, round piece of tissue from a lesion on the skin. The instrument is turned clockwise and counterclockwise to cut about 4 millimeters (mm) down to the layer of fatty tissue below the skin and remove the sample of tissue. Skin thickness is different on different parts of the body. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Incisional biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257527" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scalpel</GlossaryTermRef> to remove part of a growth.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046411" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Excisional biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a scalpel to remove the entire growth.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_422"><KeyPoint id="_423">After melanoma has been diagnosed, tests may be done to find out
		  if cancer cells have spread within the skin or to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_424">The process used to find out whether cancer has spread within the skin or to other parts
		  of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. The
		  information gathered from the staging process determines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the
		  disease. It is important to know the stage in order to plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_425">For melanoma that is not likely to spread to other parts of the body or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recur</GlossaryTermRef>, more tests may not be needed. For melanoma that is likely to spread to other parts of the body or recur, the following tests and procedures may be done after surgery to remove the melanoma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_426" Style="bullet"><ListItem> <Strong>Lymph node
			 mapping and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node
			 biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> includes the removal of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045876" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> during surgery. The sentinel lymph node is the first <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> in a group of lymph nodes to receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic drainage</GlossaryTermRef> from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. It is the first lymph node the cancer is likely to spread to from the primary tumor.  A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance or blue dye is injected near the tumor.  The substance or dye flows through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046441" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ducts</GlossaryTermRef> to the lymph nodes.  The first lymph node to receive the substance or dye is removed.   A pathologist views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells.  If cancer cells are not found, it may not be necessary to remove more lymph nodes. Sometimes, a sentinel lymph node is found in more than one group of nodes.  
		  </ListItem> 
		  
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT
			 scan)</Strong> is a procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an x-ray machine. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. For melanoma,
			 pictures may be taken of the neck, chest, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem>
		  
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron
			 emission tomography scan)</Strong> is a procedure to find malignant tumor cells in the body.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into a vein.  The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body.  Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.</ListItem>
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging) with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597153" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gadolinium</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the brain. A substance called gadolinium is injected into  a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> exam</Strong> is a procedure in which high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) are bounced off internal tissues, such as lymph nodes, or organs and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>. The picture can be printed to be looked at later.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. For melanoma, the blood is checked for an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lactate dehydrogenase</GlossaryTermRef> (LDH). High LDH levels may predict a poor response to treatment in people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> disease.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_427">The results of these tests are viewed together with the results of
		  the tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> to find out the stage of the melanoma.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_419"><KeyPoint id="_428">Some people decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_420">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your melanoma diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_421">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_93"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_94">Certain factors affect  prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_203">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_191" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the thickness of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> and where it is in the body</ListItem><ListItem>whether there was bleeding or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef> of the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>how much cancer is in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the number of places and where cancer has spread to in the body</ListItem><ListItem> the level of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lactate dehydrogenase</GlossaryTermRef> (LDH) in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutations</GlossaryTermRef> (changes) in a gene called <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">BRAF</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName></ListItem><ListItem>your age and
		  general health</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_96"><Title>Stages of Melanoma</Title><Para id="_429">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the melanoma stage to plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_430">There are several staging systems for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. Melanoma staging usually uses the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. The cancer may be described by this staging system in your pathology report. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to your cancer. When talking to you about your diagnosis, your doctor may describe the cancer as one of these stages.</Para><Para id="_431">Learn about  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062713#_422" url="/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">tests to stage melanoma</SummaryRef>. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_264"><KeyPoint id="_265">The stage of melanoma depends on the thickness of the tumor, whether cancer has spread to lymph nodes or other parts of the body, and other factors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_340">To find out the stage of melanoma, the tumor is completely removed and nearby lymph nodes are checked for signs of cancer. The stage of the cancer is used to determine which treatment is best. Check with your doctor to find out which stage of cancer you have.</Para><Para id="_341">The stage of melanoma depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_342" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The tumor's thickness, which is measured from the surface of the skin to the deepest part of the tumor.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000799465" type="image/jpeg" alt="Melanoma staging (tumor thickness); drawing shows different depths of cancer invasion (0, 1.0, 2.0, 3.0, 4.0, and 5.0 mm) into the epidermis (outer layer of the skin), the dermis (inner layer of the skin), and the subcutaneous tissue below the dermis." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_377"/></ListItem><ListItem>Whether the tumor is ulcerated (has broken through the skin). <MediaLink ref="CDR0000799466" type="image/jpeg" alt="Melanoma staging (tumor ulceration); drawing shows a tumor that is ulcerated (has broken through the skin) and a tumor that is not ulcerated." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_378"/></ListItem><ListItem>Whether cancer is found in lymph nodes by a physical exam, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging tests</GlossaryTermRef>, or a sentinel lymph node biopsy.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000799467" type="image/jpeg" alt="Melanoma staging (lymph node involvement); drawing shows cancer that has spread from the primary tumor to the lymph nodes." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_379"/></ListItem><ListItem>Whether the lymph nodes are matted (joined together). <MediaLink ref="CDR0000799461" type="image/jpeg" alt="Melanoma staging (matted lymph nodes); drawing shows matted lymph nodes with cancer." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_380"/></ListItem><ListItem>Whether there are:<ItemizedList id="_343" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000634135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Satellite tumors</GlossaryTermRef>: Small groups of tumor cells that have spread within 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> of the primary tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793846" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Microsatellite tumors</GlossaryTermRef>: Small groups of tumor cells that have spread to an area right beside or below the primary tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000634128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">In-transit metastases</GlossaryTermRef>: Tumors that have spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> in the skin more than 2 centimeters away from the primary tumor, but not to the lymph nodes.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000799462" type="image/jpeg" alt="Melanoma staging (in-transit metastases, satellite tumors, and microsatellite tumors); drawing shows in-transit metastases in a lymph vessel more than 2 centimeters away from the primary tumor and satellite tumors within 2 centimeters of the primary tumor. Microsatellite tumors are not shown because they can only be seen with a microscope." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_381"/></ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, brain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue</GlossaryTermRef> (including muscle), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive tract</GlossaryTermRef>, and/or distant lymph nodes. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000799463" type="image/jpeg" alt="Melanoma staging (cancer spread to other parts of the body); drawing shows cancer cells spreading from the primary cancer, through the blood and lymph system, to another part of the body where a metastatic tumor has formed." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_382"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_103"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_104">The following stages are used for melanoma:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_105"><KeyPoint id="_106">Stage 0 (melanoma in situ) </KeyPoint><Para id="_107">In stage 0, abnormal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanocytes</GlossaryTermRef> are found in the
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epidermis</GlossaryTermRef>.
			 These abnormal melanocytes may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. Stage 0 is also called melanoma in situ.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000579050" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage 0 melanoma; drawing shows an abnormal area on the surface of the skin and abnormal melanocytes in the epidermis (outer layer of the skin). Also shown are the dermis (inner layer of the skin) and the subcutaneous tissue below the dermis." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_383"><Caption language="en">Stage 0 melanoma. Abnormal melanocytes are found in the epidermis (outer layer of the skin). These abnormal melanocytes may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_108"><KeyPoint id="_109">Stage I (also called stage 1) melanoma</KeyPoint><Para id="_110"> In stage I, cancer has formed. Stage I is divided into stages IA and IB.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000578121" type="image/jpeg" alt="Millimeters; drawing shows millimeters (mm) using everyday objects. A sharp pencil point shows 1 mm, a new crayon point shows 2 mm, and a new pencil-top eraser shows 5 mm." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_344"><Caption language="en">Millimeters (mm). A sharp pencil point is about 1 mm, a new crayon point is about 2 mm, and a new pencil eraser is about 5 mm.</Caption></MediaLink><ItemizedList id="_111" Style="bullet"> 
			 <ListItem>Stage IA: The tumor is not more than 1
				  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeter</GlossaryTermRef>  thick, with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
			 <ListItem>Stage IB: The tumor is more than 1 but not more than 2 millimeters thick, without ulceration.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000579053" type="image/jpeg" alt="Two-panel drawing of stage I melanoma; the panel on the left shows a stage IA tumor that is not more than 1 millimeter thick, with ulceration (a break in the skin) and without ulceration. The panel on the right shows a stage IB tumor that is more than 1 but not more than 2 millimeters thick, without ulceration. Also shown are the epidermis (outer layer of the skin), the dermis (inner layer of the skin), and the subcutaneous tissue below the dermis." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_384"><Caption language="en">Stage I melanoma. In stage IA, the tumor is not more than 1 millimeter thick, with or without ulceration (a break in the skin). In stage IB, the tumor is more than 1 but not more than 2 millimeters thick, without ulceration. Skin thickness is different on different parts of the body.</Caption></MediaLink> </ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_115"><KeyPoint id="_116">Stage II (also called stage 2) melanoma </KeyPoint><Para id="_117">Stage II is divided
			 into stages IIA, IIB, and IIC.</Para><ItemizedList id="_118" Style="bullet"> 
			 <ListItem>Stage IIA: The tumor is either: 
				 
				<ItemizedList id="_120" Style="dash"> 
				  <ListItem>more than 1 but not more than 2  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeters</GlossaryTermRef> thick, with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef>;
					 or</ListItem> 
				  <ListItem>more than 2 but not more than 4 millimeters thick, without ulceration.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000579056" type="image/jpeg" alt="Two-panel drawing of stage IIA melanoma; the panel on the left shows a tumor that is more than 1 but not more than 2 millimeters thick, with ulceration (a break in the skin). The panel on the right shows a tumor that is more than 2 but not more than 4 millimeters thick, without ulceration. Also shown are the epidermis (outer layer of the skin), the dermis (inner layer of the skin), and the subcutaneous tissue below the dermis." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_385"><Caption language="en">Stage IIA melanoma. The tumor is more than 1 but not more than 2 millimeters thick, with ulceration (a break in the skin); OR it is more than 2 but not more than 4 millimeters thick, without ulceration. Skin thickness is different on different parts of the body.</Caption></MediaLink> </ListItem> 
				</ItemizedList> </ListItem> 
			 <ListItem>Stage IIB: The tumor is either: 
				 
				<ItemizedList id="_122" Style="dash"> 
				  <ListItem>more than 2 but not more than  4 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeters</GlossaryTermRef> thick, with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef>;
					 or</ListItem> 
				  <ListItem>more than 4 millimeters thick, without
					 ulceration.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000797843" type="image/jpeg" alt="Two-panel drawing of stage IIB melanoma; the panel on the left shows a tumor that is more than 2 but not more than 4 millimeters thick, with ulceration (a break in the skin). There is also an inset that shows 2 millimeters is about the size of a new crayon point and 5 millimeters is about the size of a pencil-top eraser. The panel on the right shows a tumor that is more than 4 millimeters thick, without ulceration. There is also an inset that shows 5 millimeters is about the size of a pencil-top eraser. Also shown are the epidermis (outer layer of the skin), the dermis (inner layer of the skin), and the subcutaneous tissue below the dermis." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_386"><Caption language="en">Stage IIB melanoma. The tumor is more than 2 but not more than 4 millimeters thick, with ulceration (a break in the skin); OR it is more than 4 millimeters thick, without ulceration. Skin thickness is different on different parts of the body.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem> 
				</ItemizedList> </ListItem> 
			 <ListItem>Stage IIC: The tumor is more than 4 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeters</GlossaryTermRef>
				  thick, with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000799927" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IIC melanoma; drawing shows a tumor that is more than 4 millimeters thick, with ulceration (a break in the skin). Also shown are the epidermis (outer layer of the skin), the dermis (inner layer of the skin), and the subcutaneous tissue below the dermis." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_387"><Caption language="en">Stage IIC melanoma. The tumor is more than 4 millimeters thick, with ulceration (a break in the skin). Skin thickness is different on different parts of the body.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_124"><KeyPoint id="_125">Stage III (also called stage 3) melanoma </KeyPoint><Para id="_345">Stage III is divided into stages IIIA, IIIB, IIIC, and IIID.</Para><ItemizedList id="_346" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Stage IIIA: The tumor is not more than 1 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeter</GlossaryTermRef> thick, with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef>, or not more than 2 millimeters thick, without ulceration. Cancer is found in 1 to 3 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIIB:<ItemizedList id="_347" Style="simple">
     <ListItem>(1) It is not known where the cancer began or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> can no longer be seen, and one of the following is true:<ItemizedList id="_348" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>cancer is found in 1 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> by physical exam or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging tests</GlossaryTermRef>; or</ListItem><ListItem>there are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793846" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microsatellite tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000634135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">satellite tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000634128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in-transit metastases</GlossaryTermRef> on or under the skin.<Para id="_354"><Emphasis><Strong>or</Strong></Emphasis></Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_361" Style="simple"><ListItem>(2) The tumor is not more than 1 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeter</GlossaryTermRef> thick, with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef>, or not more than 2 millimeters thick, without ulceration, and one of the following is true:<ItemizedList id="_349" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>cancer is found in 1 to 3 lymph nodes by physical exam or imaging tests; or </ListItem><ListItem>there are microsatellite tumors, satellite tumors, and/or in-transit metastases on or under the skin.<Para id="_360"><Strong><Emphasis>or</Emphasis></Strong></Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_362" Style="simple"><ListItem>(3) The tumor is more than 1 but not more than 2 millimeters thick, with ulceration, or more than 2 but not more than 4 millimeters thick, without ulceration, and one of the following is true: <ItemizedList id="_350" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>cancer is found in 1 to 3 lymph nodes; or </ListItem><ListItem>there are microsatellite tumors, satellite tumors, and/or in-transit metastases on or under the skin. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIIC: <ItemizedList id="_356" Style="simple">
     <ListItem>(1) It is not known where the cancer began, or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef> can no longer be seen. Cancer is found:<ItemizedList id="_351" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>in 2 or 3 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>; or </ListItem><ListItem>in 1 lymph node and there are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793846" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microsatellite tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000634135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">satellite tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000634128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in-transit metastases</GlossaryTermRef> on or under the skin; or </ListItem><ListItem>in 4 or more lymph nodes, or in any lymph nodes that are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">matted</GlossaryTermRef> together; or </ListItem><ListItem>in 2 or more lymph nodes and/or in any lymph nodes that are matted together. There are microsatellite tumors, satellite tumors, and/or in-transit metastases on or under the skin. <Para id="_357"><Strong><Emphasis>or</Emphasis></Strong></Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_363" Style="simple"><ListItem>(2) The tumor is not more than 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeters</GlossaryTermRef> thick, with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef>, or not more than 4 millimeters thick, without ulceration. Cancer is found:<ItemizedList id="_352" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>in 1 lymph node and there are microsatellite tumors, satellite tumors, and/or in-transit metastases on or under the skin; or </ListItem><ListItem>in 4 or more lymph nodes, or in any lymph nodes that are matted together; or </ListItem><ListItem>in 2 or more lymph nodes and/or in any lymph nodes that are matted together. There are microsatellite tumors, satellite tumors, and/or in-transit metastases on or under the skin. <Para id="_367"><Strong><Emphasis>or</Emphasis></Strong></Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_364" Style="simple"><ListItem>(3) The tumor is more than 2 but not more than 4 millimeters thick, with ulceration, or more than 4 millimeters thick, without ulceration. Cancer is found in 1 or more lymph nodes and/or in any lymph nodes that are matted together. There may be microsatellite tumors, satellite tumors, and/or in-transit metastases on or under the skin.<Para id="_368"><Strong><Emphasis>or</Emphasis></Strong></Para></ListItem></ItemizedList> <ItemizedList id="_365" Style="simple"><ListItem>(4) The tumor is more than 4 millimeters thick, with ulceration. Cancer is found in 1 or more lymph nodes and/or there are microsatellite tumors, satellite tumors, and/or in-transit metastases on or under the skin.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIID: The tumor is more than 4 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">millimeters</GlossaryTermRef> thick, with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ulceration</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer is found: <ItemizedList id="_353" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>in 4 or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, or in any lymph nodes that are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">matted</GlossaryTermRef> together; or </ListItem><ListItem>in 2 or more lymph nodes and/or in any lymph nodes that are matted together. There are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793846" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microsatellite tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000634135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">satellite tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000634128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in-transit metastases</GlossaryTermRef> on or under the skin.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_130"><KeyPoint id="_131">Stage IV (also called stage 4) melanoma </KeyPoint><Para id="_132">In stage IV,  the cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, brain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>, bone, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue</GlossaryTermRef> (including muscle), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive tract</GlossaryTermRef>, and/or distant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer may have spread to places in the skin far away from where it first started.</Para><Para id="_299">Stage IV melanoma is also called metastatic melanoma. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if melanoma spreads to the lung, the cancer cells in the lung are actually melanoma cells. The disease is called metastatic melanoma, not lung cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_448"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000579064" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IV melanoma; drawing shows other parts of the body where melanoma may spread, including the brain, spinal cord, lung, liver, gastrointestinal (GI) tract, bone, muscle, and distant lymph nodes. An inset shows cancer cells spreading through the blood and lymph system to another part of the body where a metastatic tumor has formed." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_388"><Caption language="en">Stage IV melanoma. Cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the brain, spinal cord, lung, liver, gastrointestinal (GI) tract, bone, muscle, and/or distant lymph nodes. Cancer may have spread to places in the skin far away from where it first started.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_414"><KeyPoint id="_412">Melanoma can recur
		(come back) after it has been treated. </KeyPoint><Para id="_413">Recurrent melanoma is melanoma that has come back after it has been treated. If melanoma comes back, it may come back in the area where it first started or in other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>. Tests will help determine where in the body the cancer has returned. The type of treatment that you have for recurrent melanoma will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_447">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_135"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_136"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_137">There are different types of treatment for people with
		  melanoma. </KeyPoint><Para id="_138">Different types of treatment are available for people with
		  melanoma. Some treatments are
		  standard (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.  A
		  treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current
		  treatments or obtain information on new treatments for people with cancer.
		  When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the
		  standard treatment, the new
		  treatment may become the standard treatment.  People may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to people who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_141">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_142"><KeyPoint id="_143">Surgery </KeyPoint><Para id="_144"> Surgery to remove the
			 tumor is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000589417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for
			 all <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stages</GlossaryTermRef> of melanoma. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wide local excision</GlossaryTermRef> is used to remove the melanoma and some of the normal tissue around it. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046581" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Skin grafting</GlossaryTermRef> (taking skin from another part of the body to replace the skin that is removed) may be done to cover the wound caused by surgery.</Para><Para id="_316">Sometimes, it is important to know whether cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045761" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph node mapping</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> are done to check for cancer in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045876" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node</GlossaryTermRef>, which is the first lymph node the cancer is likely to spread to from the primary tumor.</Para><Para id="_450">If  only a small amount of cancer cells are found during a sentinel lymph node biopsy, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000616060" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">active surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> with ultrasound may be recommended instead of more surgery.</Para><Para id="_147">After the doctor removes all the melanoma that can be seen at
			 the time of the surgery, some people may be given chemotherapy after surgery to kill
			 any cancer cells that are left. Chemotherapy given after the surgery to lower the risk that the cancer will come back is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_317">Surgery to remove cancer that has spread to the lymph nodes, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive tract</GlossaryTermRef>, bone, or brain may be done to improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> by controlling <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><KeyPoint id="_149">Chemotherapy </KeyPoint><Para id="_150">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.  When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or injected into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).  When chemotherapy is placed directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef>, an organ, or a body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef> such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>,  the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas (regional chemotherapy).</Para><Para id="_296">One type of regional chemotherapy is  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperthermic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">isolated limb perfusion</GlossaryTermRef>. With this method, anticancer drugs go directly to the arm or leg the cancer is in. The flow of blood to and from the limb is temporarily stopped with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000613900" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tourniquet</GlossaryTermRef>. A warm solution with the anticancer drug is put directly into the blood of the limb. This gives a high dose of drugs to the area where the cancer is.</Para><Para id="_204">The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the type and stage of the cancer being treated.</Para><Para id="_432">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_152"><KeyPoint id="_153">Radiation therapy
			 </KeyPoint><Para id="_154">Radiation therapy uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. External radiation therapy is used to treat melanoma and may also be used as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve symptoms and improve quality of life. </Para><Para id="_433">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_155"><KeyPoint id="_156">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_434">Immunotherapy helps a person's immune system fight cancer. Your doctor may suggest biomarker tests to help predict your response to certain immunotherapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_435">Immunotherapy drugs used to treat melanoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_436" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000781156" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/atezolizumab">atezolizumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045256" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-2</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000698294" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ipilimumab">ipilimumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000809173" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab-and-relatlimab-rmbw">nivolumab and relatimab</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_437">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_280"><KeyPoint id="_281">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_438">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. Your doctor may suggest <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000805418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biomarker tests</GlossaryTermRef> to help predict your response to certain targeted therapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_439">Targeted therapies used to treat melanoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_440" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000793920" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/binimetinib">binimetinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000776883" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cobimetinib">cobimetinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000750067" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dabrafenib">dabrafenib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000793919" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/encorafenib">encorafenib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000750074" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/trametinib">trametinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000709542" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vemurafenib">vemurafenib</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_441">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_158"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_159">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.
		  </KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_339"><KeyPoint id="_337">Vaccine therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_338">Vaccine therapy is a cancer treatment that uses a substance or group of substances to stimulate the immune system to find the tumor and kill it. Vaccine therapy is being studied in the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045138" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III melanoma</GlossaryTermRef> that can be removed by surgery.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_334"><KeyPoint id="_335">Treatment for melanoma may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_334_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_221"><KeyPoint id="_222">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_221_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_221_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_389"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042623">stage 0 melanoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage 0 (Melanoma in Situ)</Title><Para id="_390">Treatment of stage 0 is usually surgery to remove the area of abnormal cells and a small amount of normal tissue around it.</Para><Para id="_442">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062713#_140" url="/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_389_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_391"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038834">stage I melanoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage I Melanoma</Title><Para id="_392">Treatment of stage I melanoma is usually surgery to remove the tumor and some of the normal tissue around it, with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045761" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node mapping</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_443">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062713#_140" url="/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_391_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_394"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038835">stage II melanoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage II Melanoma</Title><Para id="_395">Treatment of stage II melanoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_396" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery to remove the tumor and some of the normal tissue
			 around it, with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045761" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node mapping</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel
			 lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>. If cancer is found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045876" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node</GlossaryTermRef>, more lymph nodes may be removed.</ListItem>
		  
		  <ListItem>surgery followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000764538" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pembrolizumab</GlossaryTermRef>  if there is a high risk that the cancer will come back</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_444">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062713#_140" url="/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_394_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_397"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038836">stage III melanoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III Melanoma That Can Be Removed By Surgery</Title><Para id="_398">Treatment of stage III melanoma that can be removed by surgery may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_399" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef> before surgery</ListItem><ListItem>surgery to remove the tumor and some of the normal tissue around it, with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046581" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skin grafting</GlossaryTermRef> to cover the wound caused by
			 surgery. Sometimes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045761" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node mapping</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046712" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel
			 lymph node biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> are done to check for cancer in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>  at the same time as the surgery to remove the tumor. If cancer is found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045876" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sentinel lymph node</GlossaryTermRef>, more lymph nodes may be removed.</ListItem>
		   
		  <ListItem>surgery followed by immunotherapy with  <DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef>, pembrolizumab, or <DrugRef href="CDR0000698294" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ipilimumab">ipilimumab</DrugRef>  if there is a high risk that the cancer will come back</ListItem><ListItem>surgery followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <DrugRef href="CDR0000750067" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dabrafenib">dabrafenib</DrugRef> and <DrugRef href="CDR0000750074" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/trametinib">trametinib</DrugRef> if there is a high risk that the cancer will come back</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_445">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062713#_140" url="/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_397_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_400"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038836">stage III melanoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038837">stage IV melanoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038838">recurrent melanoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III Melanoma That Cannot Be Removed By Surgery, Stage IV Melanoma, and Recurrent Melanoma</Title><Para id="_401">Treatment of stage III melanoma that cannot be removed by surgery, stage IV melanoma, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> melanoma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_402" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000698294" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ipilimumab">ipilimumab</DrugRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045256" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-2</GlossaryTermRef> (IL-2), <DrugRef href="CDR0000809173" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab-and-relatlimab-rmbw">nivolumab and relatimab</DrugRef>, or <DrugRef href="CDR0000781156" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/atezolizumab">atezolizumab</DrugRef>, given alone or in combination</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <DrugRef href="CDR0000750067" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dabrafenib">dabrafenib</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000750074" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/trametinib">trametinib</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000709542" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vemurafenib">vemurafenib</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000776883" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cobimetinib">cobimetinib</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000793919" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/encorafenib">encorafenib</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000793920" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/binimetinib">binimetinib</DrugRef>, given alone or in combination</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000615576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oncolytic virus therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000776640" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/talimogenelaherparepvec">talimogene laherparepvec</DrugRef>) injected into the tumor</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve symptoms and improve the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>:<ItemizedList id="_297" Style="dash"><ListItem>chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>surgery to remove <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> or tumors in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive tract</GlossaryTermRef>, bone, or brain</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the brain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>, or bone</ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_446">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062713#_140" url="/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_400_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_209"><Title>To Learn More About Melanoma</Title><Para id="_210">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  melanoma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_279" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin">Skin Cancer (Including Melanoma) Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062802" url="/types/skin/patient/skin-prevention-pdq">Skin Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258037" url="/types/skin/patient/skin-screening-pdq">Skin Cancer Screening</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging/sentinel-node-biopsy-fact-sheet">Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/melanoma">Drugs Approved for Melanoma</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://analysistools.nci.nih.gov/nevustool/">Moles to Melanoma: Recognizing the ABCDE Features</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_209_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_209_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of melanoma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Melanoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389388]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062917"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
