<Summary id="CDR0000062729" LegacyPDQID="1517"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Carcinoma of unknown primary (CUP) treatment can include surgery, radiation therapy, chemotherapy, or hormone therapy. Get detailed information about the diagnosis and treatment of CUP in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Carcinoma of Unknown Primary (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary/hp/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Carcinoma of Unknown Primary (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040456">carcinoma of unknown primary</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_201">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of carcinoma of unknown primary. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_202">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>carcinoma of unknown primary</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_3">Carcinoma of unknown primary (CUP) is a rare disease in which malignant (cancer) cells are found in the body but the place the cancer began is not known.</KeyPoint><Para id="_140"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> can form in any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> of the body. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (the cancer that first formed) can spread to other parts of the body. This process is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> usually look like the cells in the type of tissue in which the cancer began. For example, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cells may spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>. Because the cancer began in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef>, the cancer cells in the lung look like breast cancer cells.</Para><Para id="_154">Sometimes doctors find where the cancer has spread but cannot find where in the body the cancer first began to grow. This type of cancer is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> (CUP) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">occult primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. 
<MediaLink ref="CDR0000770048" type="image/jpeg" alt="Cancer of unknown primary; drawing shows a primary tumor that has spread from an unknown site to other parts of the body (the lung and the brain). An inset shows cancer cells spreading from the primary cancer, through the blood and lymph systems, to another part of the body where a metastatic tumor has formed." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_200"><Caption language="en">In cancer of unknown primary, cancer cells have spread in the body but the place where the primary cancer began is not known.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_155">Tests are done to find where the primary cancer began and to get information about where the cancer has spread. When tests are able to find the primary cancer, the cancer is no longer a CUP and treatment is based on the type of primary cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_156"><KeyPoint id="_157">Sometimes the primary cancer is never found.</KeyPoint><Para id="_158">The primary cancer (the cancer that first formed) may not be found for one of the following reasons:
</Para><ItemizedList id="_159" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The primary cancer is very small and grows slowly.
</ListItem><ListItem>The body’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> killed the primary cancer.
</ListItem><ListItem>The primary cancer was removed during <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> for another <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> and doctors didn’t know cancer had formed. For example, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef> with cancer may be removed during a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hysterectomy</GlossaryTermRef> to treat a serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_161"><KeyPoint id="_162">The signs and symptoms of CUP are different, depending on where the cancer has spread in the body.  </KeyPoint><Para id="_163">Sometimes CUP does not cause any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> or  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. Signs and symptoms may be caused by CUP or by other conditions. Check with your doctor if you have any of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_166" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lump or thickening in any part of the body. 
</ListItem><ListItem>Pain that is in one part of the body and does not go away. 
</ListItem><ListItem>A cough that does not go away or hoarseness in the voice.
</ListItem><ListItem>Change in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> habits, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>, or frequent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urination</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem><ListItem>Unusual bleeding or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443583" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">discharge</GlossaryTermRef>.	
</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fever</GlossaryTermRef> for no known reason that does not go away.
</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000801579" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Drenching night sweats</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Weight loss for no known reason or loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_6">Because the place where the cancer started is not known, many tests and procedures may be done to search for the primary cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_7">The following tests and procedures may be used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_167" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health history</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An exam of the body to check general signs of health, including checking for signs of disease, such as lumps or anything else that seems unusual. A history of the patient’s health habits and past illnesses and treatments will also be taken.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Urinalysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A test to check the color of urine and its contents, such as sugar, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bacteria</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organs</GlossaryTermRef> and tissues in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease. 
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045107" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Complete blood count</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure in which a sample of blood is drawn and checked for the following:
<ItemizedList id="_168" Style="dash"><ListItem>The number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemoglobin</GlossaryTermRef> (the protein that carries <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef>) in the red blood cells.</ListItem><ListItem>	The portion of the sample made up of red blood cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fecal occult blood test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A test to check <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046605" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stool</GlossaryTermRef> (solid waste) for blood that can only be seen with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef>. Small samples of stool are placed on special cards and returned to the doctor or laboratory for testing. Because some cancers bleed, blood in the stool may be a sign of cancer in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_169"><KeyPoint id="_170">If tests show there may be cancer, a biopsy is done.</KeyPoint><Para id="_171">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> is the removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef>. The pathologist views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells and to find out the type of cancer. The type of biopsy that is done depends on the part of the body being tested for cancer.
One of the following types of biopsies may be used: 
</Para><ItemizedList id="_172" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046411" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Excisional biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of an entire lump of tissue.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Incisional biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of part of a lump or a sample of tissue.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045657" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Core biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of tissue using a wide needle.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fine-needle aspiration</GlossaryTermRef> (FNA) biopsy</Strong>: The removal tissue or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef> using a thin needle.
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_173">If cancer is found, one or more of the following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory tests</GlossaryTermRef> may be used to study the tissue samples and find out the type of cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_174" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386202" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic analysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test in which the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> in a sample of cancer cells or tissue is studied to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutations</GlossaryTermRef> (changes) that may help predict the best treatment for carcinoma of unknown primary.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Histologic</GlossaryTermRef> study</Strong>: A laboratory test in which stains are added to a sample of cancer cells or tissue and viewed under a microscope to look for certain changes in the cells. Certain changes in the cells are linked to certain types of cancer.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000653117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunohistochemistry</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient’s tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer.  
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction</GlossaryTermRef> (RT–PCR) test</Strong>: A laboratory test in which the amount of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> substance called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000662001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mRNA</GlossaryTermRef> made by a specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is measured. An enzyme called reverse transcriptase is used to convert a specific piece of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046568" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RNA</GlossaryTermRef> into a matching piece of DNA, which can be amplified (made in large numbers) by another enzyme called DNA polymerase. The amplified DNA copies help tell whether a specific mRNA is being made by a gene. RT–PCR can be used to check the activation of certain genes that may indicate the presence of cancer cells. This test may be used to look for certain changes in a gene or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef>, which may help diagnose cancer.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cytogenetic analysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test in which the chromosomes of cells in a sample of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> tissue are counted and checked for any changes, such as broken, missing, rearranged, or extra chromosomes. Changes in certain chromosomes may be a sign of cancer. Cytogenetic analysis is used to help diagnose cancer, plan treatment, or find out how well treatment is working. Changes in certain chromosomes are linked to certain types of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044052" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Light</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electron microscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test in which cells in a sample of tissue are viewed under regular and high-powered microscopes to look for certain changes in the cells.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_175"><KeyPoint id="_176">When the type of cancer cells or tissue removed is different from the type of cancer cells expected to be found, a diagnosis of CUP may be made.</KeyPoint><Para id="_177">The cells in the body have a certain look that depends on the type of tissue they come from.  For example, a sample of cancer tissue taken from the breast is expected to be made up of breast cells. However, if the sample of tissue is a different type of cell (not made up of breast cells), it is likely that the cells have spread to the breast from another part of the body. In order to plan treatment, doctors first try to find the primary cancer (the cancer that first formed).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_178"><KeyPoint id="_179">Tests and procedures used to find the primary cancer depend on where the cancer has spread.</KeyPoint><Para id="_180">In some cases, the part of the body where cancer cells are first found helps the doctor decide which <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045959" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef> will be most helpful. </Para><ItemizedList id="_181" Style="bullet"><ListItem>When cancer is found above the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diaphragm</GlossaryTermRef> (the thin muscle under the lungs that helps with breathing), the primary cancer site is likely to be in the upper part of the body, such as in the lung or breast.
</ListItem><ListItem>When cancer is found below the diaphragm, the primary cancer site is likely to be in the lower part of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, or other organ in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Some cancers commonly spread to certain areas of the body. For cancer found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the neck, the primary cancer site is likely to be in the head or neck, because <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancers</GlossaryTermRef> often spread to the lymph nodes in the neck.
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_182">The following tests and procedures may be done to find where the cancer first began:</Para><ItemizedList id="_183" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest or abdomen, taken from different angles. The pictures are made by a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). 
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> tumor cells in the body. A small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef> (sugar) is injected into a vein. The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body. Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Mammogram</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An x-ray of the breast. 
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  A procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas.  An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscope</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> (cut) in the skin or opening in the body, such as the mouth.  An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue or lymph node samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of disease. For example, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> may be done.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000732562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumor marker test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  A procedure in which a sample of blood, urine, or tissue is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances made by organs, tissues, or tumor cells in the body. Certain substances are linked to specific types of cancer when found in increased levels in the body. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor markers</GlossaryTermRef>. The blood may be checked for the levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046490" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CA-125</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000721308" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CgA</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046208" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alpha-fetoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> (AFP), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354453" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta human chorionic gonadotropin</GlossaryTermRef> (beta-hCG), or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen (PSA)</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_184">Sometimes, none of the tests can find the primary cancer site. In these cases, treatment may be based on what the doctor thinks is the most likely type of cancer. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance
		  of recovery).</KeyPoint><Para id="_21">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> depends on the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_130" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Where the cancer began in the body and where it has spread.</ListItem><ListItem>The number of organs with cancer in them.</ListItem><ListItem>The way the tumor cells look when viewed under a microscope.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the patient is male or female.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_135">For most patients with CUP, current treatments do not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cure</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer. Patients may want to take part in one of the many <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> being done to improve treatment. Clinical trials for CUP are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><Title>Stages of Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><SummarySection id="_24"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_25">There is no standard staging system for carcinoma of unknown primary (CUP).</KeyPoint><Para id="_209">The extent or spread of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> is usually described as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stages</GlossaryTermRef>. The stage of the cancer is usually used to plan treatment. However, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> (CUP) has already spread to other parts of the body when it is found. There is no standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging system</GlossaryTermRef> for CUP.</Para><Para id="_210">Sometimes  CUP <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurs</GlossaryTermRef> (comes back) after treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_29">The information that is known about the cancer is used to plan treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_32"> Doctors use the following types of information to plan treatment:</Para><ItemizedList id="_185" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The place in the body where the cancer is found, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef> or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044102" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical</GlossaryTermRef> (neck), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">axillary</GlossaryTermRef> (armpit), or inguinal (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef>) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem><ListItem>The type of cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer cell is poorly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">differentiated</GlossaryTermRef> (looks very different from normal cells when viewed under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>
The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> caused by the cancer.
</ListItem><ListItem>The results of tests and procedures.
</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the cancer is newly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back).
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_63"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_64">There are different types of treatment for patients with carcinoma of unknown primary (CUP). </KeyPoint><Para id="_65">Different types of treatment are available for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527199" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CUP</GlossaryTermRef>. Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>. A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment. Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_68">Four types of standard treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_69"><KeyPoint id="_70">Surgery </KeyPoint><Para id="_71"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> is a common treatment for CUP. A doctor may remove the cancer and some of the healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> around it.</Para><Para id="_124">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some patients may be given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> after surgery to kill any cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> that are left. Treatment given after the surgery, to lower the risk that cancer will come back, is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_73"><KeyPoint id="_74">Radiation therapy
			 </KeyPoint><Para id="_75">Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. There are two types of radiation therapy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_203" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Certain ways of giving radiation therapy can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy tissue. This type of radiation therapy may include the following:<ItemizedList id="_204" Style="dash">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (IMRT): IMRT is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">3-dimensional</GlossaryTermRef> (3-D) radiation therapy that uses a computer to make pictures of the size and shape of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. Thin beams of radiation of different intensities (strengths) are aimed at the tumor from many angles. This type of external radiation therapy  causes less damage to nearby healthy tissue and is less likely to cause dry mouth, trouble swallowing, and  damage to the skin.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Internal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheters</GlossaryTermRef> that are placed directly into or near the cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_205">The way the radiation therapy is given depends on the type and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer being treated. External and internal radiation therapy are used to treat carcinoma of unknown primary.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><KeyPoint id="_77">Chemotherapy </KeyPoint><Para id="_131">Chemotherapy is a cancer treatment that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.   When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>). When chemotherapy is placed directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef>, an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef>, or a body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef> such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regional chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>). <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is the use of two or more anticancer drugs.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><KeyPoint id="_80">Hormone therapy
			 </KeyPoint><Para id="_132"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that removes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef> or blocks their action and stops cancer cells from growing. Hormones are substances made by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glands</GlossaryTermRef> in the body and circulated in the bloodstream. Some hormones can cause certain cancers to grow. If tests show that the cancer cells have places where hormones can attach (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">receptors</GlossaryTermRef>), drugs, surgery, or radiation therapy are used to reduce the production of hormones or block them from working.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_82"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_83">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_85">Information about clinical trials is available from the
			 <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_206"><KeyPoint id="_207">Treatment for carcinoma of unknown primary may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_206_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_143"><KeyPoint id="_144">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_143_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_143_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_143_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_145"><KeyPoint id="_146">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_145_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_145_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_86"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040835">newly diagnosed carcinoma of unknown primary</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Newly Diagnosed Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><SummarySection id="_87"><Title>Cervical (Neck) Lymph Nodes</Title><Para id="_211">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062729#_67" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_88"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> found in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044102" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical</GlossaryTermRef> (neck) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> may have spread from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> in the head or neck. Treatment of  cervical lymph node <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> (CUP) may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_89" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tonsils</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> alone. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (IMRT) may be used.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy followed by surgery to remove the lymph nodes.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove the lymph nodes, with or without radiation therapy.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		<ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of new types of treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_90">See the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef>  summary on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258020" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/metastatic-squamous-neck-treatment-pdq">Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer with Occult Primary Treatment</SummaryRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_91"><Title>Poorly Differentiated Carcinomas</Title><Para id="_212">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062729#_67" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_186"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> that are poorly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">differentiated</GlossaryTermRef> look very different from normal cells. The type of cell they came from is not known. Treatment of poorly differentiated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef>, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045803" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroendocrine</GlossaryTermRef> system (the part of the brain that controls <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef>-producing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glands</GlossaryTermRef> throughout the body) may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_187" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of new types of treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_97"><Title>Women with Peritoneal Cancer</Title><Para id="_213">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062729#_67" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_188">Treatment for women who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneal</GlossaryTermRef> (lining of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> may be the same as for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445074" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovarian cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Treatment may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_189" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of new types of treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_100">See the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summary on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062963" url="/types/ovarian/patient/ovarian-epithelial-treatment-pdq">Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_101"><Title>Isolated Axillary Lymph Node Metastasis</Title><Para id="_214">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062729#_67" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_190"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> found only in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045607" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">axillary (armpit) lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> may have spread from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_191">Treatment of axillary lymph node <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef> is usually:</Para><ItemizedList id="_103" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the lymph nodes.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_126">Treatment also may include one or more of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_192" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to remove the breast.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the breast.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of new types of treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_104"><Title>Inguinal Lymph Node Metastasis</Title><Para id="_215">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062729#_67" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_193"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> found only in the inguinal (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef>) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> most likely began in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476624" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genital</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044185" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anal</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044083" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectal</GlossaryTermRef> area. Treatment of inguinal lymph node <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef> may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_106" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the cancer and/or lymph nodes in the groin.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove the cancer and/or lymph nodes in the groin, followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_107"><Title>Melanoma in a Single Lymph Node Area</Title><Para id="_216">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062729#_67" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_194">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef> that is found only in a single <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> area is usually:</Para><ItemizedList id="_195" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the lymph nodes.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_110">See <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef>  summary on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062713" url="/types/skin/patient/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Melanoma Treatment</SummaryRef> for more information.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_111"><Title>Multiple Involvement</Title><Para id="_217">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062729#_67" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_196">There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> that is found in several different areas of the body. Treatment may include the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_113" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Internal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with one or more anticancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_TrialSearch_86_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041133">recurrent carcinoma of unknown primary</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><Para id="_208">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062729#_67" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_197">Treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> is usually within a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>. Treatment depends on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_198" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	The type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>How the cancer was treated before.</ListItem><ListItem>Where the cancer has come back in the body.</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> and wishes of the patient.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_118_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_149"><Title>To Learn More About Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><Para id="_150">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef>, see the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_151" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary">Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_149_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_149_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of carcinoma of unknown primary.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary/patient/unknown-primary-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389238]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062936"/><DateLastModified>2021-12-17</DateLastModified></Summary>
