<Summary id="CDR0000062739" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Depression, secondary to stress and emotional upset, can occur in adults and children with cancer. Get comprehensive information about assessing depression in patients, interventions, and more in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Depression (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">Depression (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000042480">depression</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_497">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about cancer-related depression and suicide risk in both the adult and the pediatric population. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_498">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>depression</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Depression (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Depression (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Depression</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_2">Depression is a comorbid, disabling syndrome that affects up to approximately 25% of cancer patients.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> This prevalence significantly exceeds the prevalence in the general population.<Reference refidx="4"/> However, most patients do not receive potentially effective treatments, and only 5% see a mental health professional.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_738">In contrast to depression in the general population, depression in people with cancer is believed to affect men and women equally.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Individuals and families who face a diagnosis of
cancer experience varying levels of stress and emotional upset. Depression in patients with cancer not only affects the patients themselves, but also has a major negative impact on their families.</Para><Para id="_563"><Strong><Emphasis>Definitions:</Emphasis></Strong> Depression is suspected when  a number of specific symptoms such as low affect, sleep disturbance, and distorted thought patterns are observed. These are specified in the categorization of psychiatric/behavioral disorders in the <Emphasis>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders,</Emphasis> 5th edition.<Reference refidx="6"/> </Para><Para id="_564">Normally, a patient’s initial emotional response to a diagnosis of cancer is
brief, extending over several days to weeks, and may include feelings of
disbelief, denial, or despair.     This normal response is part of a spectrum of
depressive symptoms that range from normal sadness to adjustment disorder with
depressed mood to major depression.<Reference refidx="6"/>  Other syndromes described include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_682" Style="bullet"><ListItem>
Dysthymia: a chronic mood disorder in which a
depressed mood is present on more days than not for at least 2 years.</ListItem><ListItem>Subsyndromal depression (also called minor depression or
subclinical depression): an acute mood disorder that is less severe
(some, but not all, diagnostic symptoms present) than major depression.</ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_565" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Possible Causes of Depressive Symptoms in People With Cancer</ListTitle><ListItem>Experience of loss or anticipated loss.</ListItem><ListItem>Uncontrolled pain.<Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Metabolic abnormalities:<ItemizedList id="_566" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Hypercalcemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Sodium/potassium imbalance.</ListItem><ListItem>Anemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Vitamin B12 or folate deficiency.</ListItem><ListItem>Fever.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Primary or metastatic central nervous system tumors.</ListItem><ListItem>Disruption of sleep due to medical treatments.</ListItem><ListItem>Endocrine abnormalities:<ItemizedList id="_627" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Hyperthyroidism or hypothyroidism.</ListItem><ListItem>Adrenal insufficiency.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Medications:<Reference refidx="8"/>;<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="10"/><ItemizedList id="_628" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Steroids.</ListItem><ListItem>Endogenous and exogenous cytokines, i.e., interferon-alfa and aldesleukin (interleukin-2 [IL-2]).<Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem><ListItem>Methyldopa.</ListItem><ListItem>Reserpine.</ListItem><ListItem>Barbiturates.</ListItem><ListItem>Propranolol.</ListItem><ListItem>Some antibiotics (e.g., amphotericin B).</ListItem><ListItem>Some chemotherapeutic agents (e.g.,                         
              procarbazine,
              asparaginase).</ListItem><ListItem>Hormone therapy (e.g., androgen deprivation therapy).<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_570">A survey in England  of women with breast cancer showed that among several factors, depression  was the strongest predictor of emotional and behavioral problems in their children.<Reference refidx="13"/>  Fear of
death, disruption of life plans, changes in body image and self-esteem, changes
in social role and lifestyle, and financial and legal concerns are significant
issues in the life of any person with cancer, yet not everyone who is diagnosed with cancer experiences serious depression or anxiety. However, many patients with cancer can experience moderately severe depression and anxiety. For example, in a study of 256 women who underwent chemotherapy treatment for early breast cancer, 26% and 41% of study participants reported moderately severe depression and anxiety, respectively. This treatment phase warrants close monitoring of patients’ psychological well-being.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_737">The use of hormone therapy or second-generation antiandrogen therapy is also associated with increased risk of depression. In a retrospective study of 210,804 patients with prostate cancer identified from the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results–Medicare (SEER-Medicare) and Texas Cancer Registry–Medicare linked databases, 3% of patients received second-generation antiandrogen therapy.<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]  Using a multivariable Cox proportional hazards model, patients who received second-generation antiandrogen therapy had a greater increased risk of depression, compared with a no-hormone-therapy group (hazard ratio [HR], 2.15; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.79–2.59; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001) and with a traditional-hormone-therapy group (HR, 2.26; 95% CI, 1.88–2.73; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]  While this secondary analysis was a limitation of this study, the large sample size merits consideration for monitoring for depression in patients undergoing hormone therapy, particularly second-generation antiandrogen therapy.</Para><Para id="_754">In a study of 149 women with nonmetastatic breast cancer, 40% reported at least mild depression at the end of chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="15"/> Up to 5.6 years postchemotherapy, 23% had received a new psychiatric diagnosis, 62% were prescribed a psychotropic medication, and 21% engaged in mental health specialty care.</Para><Para id="_374">Just as patients require ongoing evaluation for depression and anxiety throughout their course of treatment, so do family caregivers.  In a study of family caregivers of patients in the palliative phase of illness, both male and female caregivers experienced significantly more anxiety than did a sample of noncaregivers, while there was an increased incidence of Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale–defined depression among women.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_202">Some people may have more difficulty adjusting to the diagnosis of cancer than others do and will vary in their responses to the diagnosis. Sadness and grief are normal reactions to the
crises faced during cancer.  All people will experience these reactions periodically.  Because sadness is common, it is important to distinguish between
normal degrees of sadness and depressive disorders.  An end-of-life
care consensus panel review article describes details regarding this important
distinction and illustrates the major points using case vignettes.<Reference refidx="17"/>  A
critical part of cancer care is the recognition of the  levels of
depression present and determination of the appropriate level of intervention, ranging from brief counseling or support groups to medication and/or psychotherapy. For example, relaxation and counseling interventions have been shown to reduce psychological symptoms in women with a new diagnosis of gynecological cancer.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_571">Major depression, which is more common in cancer patients than in the general population,<Reference refidx="3"/>  has
recognizable symptoms whose diagnosis and treatment are essential because they have an impact on quality of life.<Reference refidx="19"/> Major depression may also impact survival. In a large study of 20,582 patients treated for breast, colorectal, gynecological, and prostate cancers across Scotland, United Kingdom, across all cancer diagnoses, having major depression was associated with worse survival (pooled HR, 1.41; 95% CI, 1.29–1.54; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>] Similarly, in a population-based study of 13,244 individuals with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma identified through the SEER-Medicare database,<Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>] compared with patients with no mental health disorders, those with depression had the highest 5-year mortality rate (HR, 1.37; 95% CI, 1.28–1.47), followed by those with co-occurring depression and anxiety (HR, 1.23; 95% CI, 1.08–1.41) and those with anxiety alone (HR, 1.17; 95% CI, 1.06–1.29).</Para><Para id="_776">Further, disparities in cancer care have been identified among individuals who have preexisting major depression and/or other severe mental illnesses. A large systematic review and meta-analysis (N = 299,193) <Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>] found that individuals with breast cancer with preexisting major depression, schizophrenia, and/or bipolar disorder received delayed and discordant care, compared with individuals with cancer without these disorders. Given the high prevalence of depression among patients with cancer, this health care disparity warrants attention.</Para><Para id="_775">Depression is also an underdiagnosed disorder in the general population.  Symptoms evident at the time of a cancer diagnosis may represent a preexisting condition and warrant separate evaluation and treatment.</Para><Para id="_429">Depression and anxiety disorders are common among patients receiving palliative care and contribute to a greatly diminished quality of life in these patients.<Reference refidx="23"/> In the Canadian National Palliative Care Survey, patients receiving palliative care for cancer (N = 381) were evaluated for depressive and anxiety disorders and for the impact of these disorders on quality of life.  The primary assessment tool was a modified version of the Primary Care Evaluation of Mental Disorders.  A significant number of participants (24.4%; 95% CI, 20.2%–29.0%) were found to fulfill diagnostic criteria for at least one depressive or anxiety disorder (20.7% prevalence for depressive disorder and 13.1% for anxiety disorder).</Para><Para id="_572">Participants diagnosed with a depressive or anxiety disorder had the following characteristics:</Para><ItemizedList id="_573" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Were significantly younger than the other participants (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002).</ListItem><ListItem>Had lower performance status (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .017).</ListItem><ListItem>Had smaller social networks (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .008).</ListItem><ListItem>Participated less in organized religious services (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .007).  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_574">They also reported more severe distress about physical symptoms, social concerns, and existential issues, suggesting significant negative impact on other aspects of their quality of life.<Reference refidx="23"/></Para><Para id="_579"> The importance of psychological issues was underscored by another study conducted in terminally ill cancer patients (n = 211) with life expectancies of less than 6 months.<Reference refidx="24"/> Investigators evaluated patient “sense of burden to others” and its correlation with physical, psychological, and existential issues, using specific validated psychometrics (e.g., visual analog scale). The variables most highly correlated  with sense of burden to others included:</Para><ItemizedList id="_575" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Depression (<Emphasis>r</Emphasis> = 0.460, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).</ListItem><ListItem> Hopelessness (<Emphasis>r</Emphasis> = 0.420,  <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).</ListItem><ListItem>Outlook (<Emphasis>r</Emphasis> = 0.362,  <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_576">In multiple regression analysis, four variables predicted perception of burden to others:</Para><ItemizedList id="_577" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Depression.</ListItem><ListItem>Hopelessness.</ListItem><ListItem>Level of fatigue.</ListItem><ListItem>Current quality of life.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_578">No association between sense of burden to others and actual degree of physical dependency was found, implying that this perception is mainly mediated through psychological distress and existential issues. A subanalysis of patient groups from different settings suggested that these findings were consistent across the inpatient and outpatient settings, with some minor variations.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para><Para id="_5">The emotional response to a diagnosis of cancer (or cancer relapse) may begin
as a dysphoric period marked by increasing turmoil.  The individual will
experience sleep and appetite disturbance, anxiety, ruminative thoughts, and
fears about the future.  Epidemiological studies, however, suggest that at least
one-half of all people diagnosed with cancer will successfully adapt.</Para><Para id="_580">Strategies to promote psychological adjustment to a diagnosis of cancer and other chronic diseases include the following:<Reference refidx="25"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_581" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Remaining as active and engaged in life as possible.</ListItem><ListItem>Expressing emotions in a way that helps to achieve insight.</ListItem><ListItem>Self-management (including healthy diet and exercise).</ListItem><ListItem>Focusing on potential positive outcomes of illness.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_582">Some studies suggest an association between maladaptive coping styles and higher levels of depression, anxiety, and fatigue symptoms.<Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/>  Examples of maladaptive coping behaviors include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_583" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Avoidant or negative coping.</ListItem><ListItem>Negative self-coping statements.</ListItem><ListItem>Preoccupation with physical symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem>Catastrophizing.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_584">One study conducted in a group of 86 mostly late-stage cancer patients suggested that maladaptive coping styles and higher levels of depressive symptoms are potential predictors of the timing of disease progression.<Reference refidx="27"/>    Another study examining coping strategies in women with breast cancer (n = 138) concluded that patients with better coping skills such as positive self-statements have lower levels of depressive and anxiety symptoms.<Reference refidx="26"/> The same study found racial differences in the use of coping strategies, with African American women reporting and benefiting  more from the use of religious coping strategies such as prayer and hopefulness than did White women.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para><Para id="_585">Preliminary data suggest a beneficial impact of spirituality on associated depression, as measured by the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy—Spiritual Well-Being questionnaire and the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale.<Reference refidx="28"/></Para><Para id="_460">The following indicators may suggest a need for early
intervention:</Para><ItemizedList id="_461" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A  history of depression.</ListItem><ListItem>A weak social support system (not
married, few friends, a solitary work environment).</ListItem><ListItem>Evidence of persistent
irrational beliefs or negativistic thinking regarding the diagnosis.</ListItem><ListItem>A more
serious prognosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Greater dysfunction related to cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_462">As shown by a study of adult cancer patients (n = 48) and their adult relatives (n = 99),  family functioning is an important factor that impacts patient and family distress.  Families that were able to act openly, express feelings directly, and solve problems effectively had lower levels of depression, and direct communication of information within the family was associated with lower levels of anxiety.<Reference refidx="29"/> Depressive symptoms in spouses of patients with cancer can also have a negative impact on their marital communication.  A preliminary study investigated 19 potential predictors of depression in spouses (n = 206) of women with nonmetastatic breast cancer.<Reference refidx="30"/> Spouses were more likely to experience depressive symptoms if they:</Para><ItemizedList id="_587" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Were older.</ListItem><ListItem>Were less well-educated.</ListItem><ListItem>Were more-recently married.</ListItem><ListItem>Reported heightened fears about  their spouse’s well-being.</ListItem><ListItem>Worried about their job performance.</ListItem><ListItem>Were more uncertain about their future.</ListItem><ListItem>Were in marriages that were less well-adjusted.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_195">Risk factors may be different, especially pain and other physical symptoms.<Reference refidx="31"/> When the
clinician begins to suspect that a patient is depressed, he or she will assess
the patient for symptoms.  Mild or subclinical levels of depression that
include some, but not all, of the diagnostic criteria for a major depressive
episode can cause considerable distress and may warrant interventions such as
supportive individual or group counseling, either by a mental health
professional or through participation in a self-help support group.<Reference refidx="32"/></Para><Para id="_588">Evidence-based recommendations have described various approaches to the problems of cancer-related fatigue, anorexia, depression, and dyspnea.<Reference refidx="33"/> Even in
the absence of any symptoms, many patients express interest in supportive
counseling; clinicians can accommodate these patients with
referrals to  qualified mental health professionals.  However, when symptoms are
more intense,  longer lasting, or recurrent after apparent resolution,
treatment to alleviate symptoms is essential.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/>  Anxiety and depression
in early treatment are good predictors of these same problems at 6 months.<Reference refidx="36"/>      In a  study of older women with breast cancer, a recent diagnosis of depression was associated with both a greater likelihood of not receiving definitive cancer treatment and poorer survival.<Reference refidx="37"/></Para><Para id="_1_md_4">In this summary, unless otherwise stated, evidence and practice issues as they relate to adults are discussed.  The evidence and application to practice related to children may differ significantly from information related to adults.  When specific information about the care of children is available, it is summarized under its own heading.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="24105788">Krebber AM, Buffart LM, Kleijn G, et al.: Prevalence of depression in cancer patients: a meta-analysis of diagnostic interviews and self-report instruments. Psychooncology 23 (2): 121-30, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="26360998">Walker J, Hansen CH, Martin P, et al.: Prevalence, associations, and adequacy of treatment of major depression in patients with cancer: a cross-sectional analysis of routinely collected clinical data. Lancet Psychiatry 1 (5): 343-50, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="21251875">Mitchell AJ, Chan M, Bhatti H, et al.: Prevalence of depression, anxiety, and adjustment disorder in oncological, haematological, and palliative-care settings: a meta-analysis of 94 interview-based studies. Lancet Oncol 12 (2): 160-74, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="29695476">Pitman A, Suleman S, Hyde N, et al.: Depression and anxiety in patients with cancer. BMJ 361: k1415, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="20574846">Miller S, Lo C, Gagliese L, et al.: Patterns of depression in cancer patients: an indirect test of gender-specific vulnerabilities to depression. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol 46 (8): 767-74, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6">American Psychiatric Association: Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-5. 5th ed. American Psychiatric Association, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="11268142" MedlineID="21169264">Ciaramella A, Poli P: Assessment of depression among cancer patients: the role of pain, cancer type and treatment. Psychooncology 10 (2): 156-65, 2001 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="2689852" MedlineID="90097701">Drugs that cause psychiatric symptoms. Med Lett Drugs Ther 31 (808): 113-8, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12082564" MedlineID="22077655">Capuron L, Ravaud A, Neveu PJ, et al.: Association between decreased serum tryptophan concentrations and depressive symptoms in cancer patients undergoing cytokine therapy. Mol Psychiatry 7 (5): 468-73, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="19724774">Rogers D, Pies R: General medical with depression drugs associated. Psychiatry (Edgmont) 5 (12): 28-41, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="15724946">Menzies H, Chochinov HM, Breitbart W: Cytokines, cancer and depression: connecting the dots. J Support Oncol 3 (1): 55-7, 2005 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="34940861">Nowakowska MK, Lei X, Wehner MR, et al.: Association of Second-generation Antiandrogens With Depression Among Patients With Prostate Cancer. JAMA Netw Open 4 (12): e2140803, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16317432">Watson M, St James-Roberts I, Ashley S, et al.: Factors associated with emotional and behavioural problems among school age children of breast cancer patients. Br J Cancer 94 (1): 43-50, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="32946156">Nakamura ZM, Deal AM, Nyrop KA, et al.: Serial Assessment of Depression and Anxiety by Patients and Providers in Women Receiving Chemotherapy for Early Breast Cancer. Oncologist 26 (2): 147-156, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="35044483">Nakamura ZM, Damone EM, Herrick HP, et al.: Anticipating mental health needs after chemotherapy in early-stage breast cancer using patient-reported symptom screening. Support Care Cancer 30 (5): 3933-3941, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="15849218">Grov EK, Dahl AA, Moum T, et al.: Anxiety, depression, and quality of life in caregivers of patients with cancer in late palliative phase. Ann Oncol 16 (7): 1185-91, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="10651602" MedlineID="20104803">Block SD: Assessing and managing depression in the terminally ill patient. ACP-ASIM End-of-Life Care Consensus Panel. American College of Physicians - American Society of Internal Medicine. Ann Intern Med 132 (3): 209-18, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="12013159" MedlineID="22004401">Petersen RW, Quinlivan JA: Preventing anxiety and depression in gynaecological cancer: a randomised controlled trial. BJOG 109 (4): 386-94, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="7751981" MedlineID="95271385">Lynch ME: The assessment and prevalence of affective disorders in advanced cancer. J Palliat Care 11 (1): 10-8, 1995 Spring.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="33938501">Walker J, Mulick A, Magill N, et al.: Major Depression and Survival in People With Cancer. Psychosom Med 83 (5): 410-416, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="37271158">Kuczmarski TM, Tramontano AC, Mozessohn L, et al.: Mental health disorders and survival among older patients with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma in the USA: a population-based study. Lancet Haematol 10 (7): e530-e538, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="36892099">Kisely S, Alotiby MKN, Protani MM, et al.: Breast cancer treatment disparities in patients with severe mental illness: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Psychooncology 32 (5): 651-662, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="17280918">Wilson KG, Chochinov HM, Skirko MG, et al.: Depression and anxiety disorders in palliative cancer care. J Pain Symptom Manage 33 (2): 118-29, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="17616329">Chochinov HM, Kristjanson LJ, Hack TF, et al.: Burden to others and the terminally ill. J Pain Symptom Manage 34 (5): 463-71, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="18640461">de Ridder D, Geenen R, Kuijer R, et al.: Psychological adjustment to chronic disease. Lancet 372 (9634): 246-55, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="16492656">Reddick BK, Nanda JP, Campbell L, et al.: Examining the influence of coping with pain on depression, anxiety, and fatigue among women with breast cancer. J Psychosoc Oncol 23 (2-3): 137-57, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="16684942">Beresford TP, Alfers J, Mangum L, et al.: Cancer survival probability as a function of ego defense (adaptive) mechanisms versus depressive symptoms. Psychosomatics 47 (3): 247-53, 2006 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="12075036" MedlineID="22070552">Nelson CJ, Rosenfeld B, Breitbart W, et al.: Spirituality, religion, and depression in the terminally ill. Psychosomatics 43 (3): 213-20, 2002 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="15295777">Edwards B, Clarke V: The psychological impact of a cancer diagnosis on families: the influence of family functioning and patients' illness characteristics on depression and anxiety. Psychooncology 13 (8): 562-76, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="18323552">Lewis FM, Fletcher KA, Cochrane BB, et al.: Predictors of depressed mood in spouses of women with breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 26 (8): 1289-95, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="12902440" MedlineID="22784336">Patrick DL, Ferketich SL, Frame PS, et al.: National Institutes of Health State-of-the-Science Conference Statement: Symptom Management in Cancer: Pain, Depression, and Fatigue, July 15-17, 2002. J Natl Cancer Inst 95 (15): 1110-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="7789344" MedlineID="95309215">Meyer TJ, Mark MM: Effects of psychosocial interventions with adult cancer patients: a meta-analysis of randomized experiments. Health Psychol 14 (2): 101-8, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="18688057">Dy SM, Lorenz KA, Naeim A, et al.: Evidence-based recommendations for cancer fatigue, anorexia, depression, and dyspnea. J Clin Oncol 26 (23): 3886-95, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="34">Massie MJ, Holland JC: Overview of normal reactions and prevalence of psychiatric disorders. In: Holland JC, Rowland JH, eds.: Handbook of Psychooncology: Psychological Care of the Patient With Cancer. Oxford University Press, 1989, pp 273-82.</Citation><Citation idx="35">Massie MJ, Shakin EJ: Management of depression and anxiety in cancer patients. In: Breitbart W, Holland JC, eds.: Psychiatric Aspects of Symptom Management in Cancer Patients. American Psychiatric Press, 1993, pp 470-91.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="10027324" MedlineID="99149570">Nordin K, Glimelius B: Predicting delayed anxiety and depression in patients with gastrointestinal cancer. Br J Cancer 79 (3-4): 525-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="14687323">Goodwin JS, Zhang DD, Ostir GV: Effect of depression on diagnosis, treatment, and survival of older women with breast cancer. J Am Geriatr Soc 52 (1): 106-11, 2004.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>Assessment and Diagnosis</Title><SummarySection id="_220"><Title>Symptoms and Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_222">There are two major classifications of symptoms for major depression: neurovegetative and emotional-cognitive.  In cancer patients whose neurovegetative symptoms may be affected by the disease process or treatment, assessing  the emotional-cognitive symptoms of their depression is likely to be more diagnostic and prevent false-positive results. Symptoms include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_223" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A depressed mood for most of the day and
on most days.</ListItem><ListItem> Diminished pleasure or interest in most activities.</ListItem><ListItem> Significant
change in appetite and sleep patterns.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychomotor agitation or slowing.</ListItem><ListItem>Fatigue.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem>Feelings of worthlessness or excessive, inappropriate guilt.</ListItem><ListItem> Poor
concentration.</ListItem><ListItem>Recurrent thoughts of death or suicide.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_224">Cognitive symptoms may express themselves as repeated and ruminative thoughts
such as “I brought this on myself,” “God is punishing me,” or “I’m letting my
family down,” and as fatalistic expectations concerning prognosis, despite
realistic evidence to the contrary.  Such thinking may predominate or may
alternate with more realistic thinking yet remain very stressful.  Some
individuals will share negativistic thoughts freely, and family members
may be aware of them.  Other patients will not volunteer such thinking but will
respond to brief inquiries such as the following (other examples are listed in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_356" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>):</Para><ItemizedList id="_225" Style="bullet"><ListItem>“Many people find themselves dwelling on thoughts about their cancer.
What kinds of thoughts do you have?”</ListItem>
<ListItem>“Do you find yourself ever thinking, ‘I brought this on myself. God is
punishing me’?  How often?  Only a few times a week, or all the
time?  Do you believe these thoughts are true?”</ListItem>
<ListItem>“In spite of these thoughts, are you still able to go on with your life and
find pleasure in things?  Or, are you so preoccupied that you can't sleep,
or feel hopeless?”</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_226">It is possible for a physician or nurse to ask these types of questions without
becoming engaged in providing counseling themselves.  Merely asking these
questions will express concern and increase the likelihood that the patient
will be receptive to suggestions for further counseling.</Para><Para id="_227">These questions can be followed by a statement such as, “Many people with cancer sometimes have these feelings.  You are not alone. 
But talking to someone else about them can greatly help.  I'd like to suggest
that you consider doing that. Would you be willing to talk to someone who has a
lot of experience helping people cope with the stress of having cancer?”</Para><Para id="_229">It is preferable at this time both to encourage patients to seek out someone
already known to them and to inform them about other resources in the
community.  Particularly for patients who have completed cancer treatment and
who have manageable physical symptoms, higher perceived availability of social
support has been associated with fewer depressive symptoms.<Reference refidx="2"/>  In some
instances, referral to a cleric or therapist may also be appropriate. 
Most therapists can address general issues of grief or fears about death; some
will specialize in clinical health psychology, medical social work, or even
working primarily with cancer patients.  For the hesitant patient, suggesting
multiple resources will increase the likelihood that some assistance will be
sought.  For other patients, a formal direct referral may be appropriate.</Para><Para id="_745">Evaluation of depression in people with cancer includes careful
assessment of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_746" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem>Treatment effects.</ListItem><ListItem>Laboratory data results.</ListItem><ListItem>Physical
status.</ListItem><ListItem>Mental status.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_739">Although the etiology of depression in patients with cancer is largely unknown, many risk factors  for depression have been identified.  The major risk factors for cancer-related depression include psychological and social factors. Preexisting mental health issues and impaired social support carry the highest risk.<Reference refidx="3"/> Certain comorbidities, such as fatigue, pain, and lower physical functioning, can also increase depression risk. Cancer-related risk factors such as cancer type, stage, and treatment may play a role, but they carry a lower risk than psychological and social factors.<Reference refidx="3"/> However, certain cancers—such as head and neck cancers and pancreatic cancer—carry a high risk of depression. Cancer-related risk factors can be divided into four broad categories, as shown in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_767" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>.</Para><Table id="_767"><Title>Table 1.  Risk Factors for Cancer-Related Depression</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Type of Risk Factor</entry><entry>Specific Risk Factors</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>High risk.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Moderate risk.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Psychological</entry><entry>History of depression or other mental illness<Superscript>a</Superscript>, neuroticism<Superscript>a</Superscript>, dysfunctional coping  behaviors<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry>Social, sociodemographic, and socioeconomic</entry><entry>Impaired social support<Superscript>a</Superscript>, single/separated/widowed<Superscript>a</Superscript>, female gender<Superscript>a</Superscript>, lower socioeconomic status<Superscript>b</Superscript>, lower educational level<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry>Comorbidities</entry><entry>Pain<Superscript>a</Superscript>, fatigue<Superscript>a</Superscript>, overall symptom burden<Superscript>a</Superscript>, lower physical functioning<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry>Cancer and cancer treatment</entry><entry>Specific cancer types (pancreatic, head and neck)<Superscript>a</Superscript>, advanced cancer<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_230">For
patients with head and neck cancer treated with curative intent, the following eight
pretreatment variables can
be used to predict which patients are likely to become depressed up to 3 years
after treatment:<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_629" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tumor stage.</ListItem><ListItem>Sex.</ListItem><ListItem>Depressive symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem>Openness to
discussing his/her cancer with family members.</ListItem><ListItem>Perceived available support.</ListItem><ListItem>Received emotional
support.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor-related symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem>Size of the informal social network.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_172"><Title>Screening and Assessment for Depression
</Title><Para id="_20">Because of  the common underrecognition and undertreatment of depression in people with cancer,<Reference refidx="6"/> screening tools can be used to prompt further assessment.<Reference refidx="7"/> Among the physically ill, in general, instruments used to measure depression
have not been shown to be more clinically useful than an interview and a
thorough examination of mental status.  Simply asking the patient whether he or she is
depressed may improve the identification of depression.</Para><Para id="_463">The following screening tools are commonly used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_464" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A single-item interview. In people with
advanced cancer, a single-item interview question has been found to have acceptable psychometric properties and can be useful.  One example is to ask “Are you depressed?”<Reference refidx="8"/>  Another example is to say, “Please grade your mood during the past week by assigning it a score from 0 to 100, with a score of 100 representing your usual relaxed mood.”  A score of 60 is considered a passing grade.<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression
Scale (HADS).   The HADS may be useful in the assessment of depression and anxiety in patients who have comorbid neurovegetative symptoms due to their disease or treatment, helping to avoid false-positive results on the scale caused by these symptoms.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem>The nine-item Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9).<Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Psychological Distress Inventory.<Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Edinburgh Depression Scale.<Reference refidx="15"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Brief Symptom
Inventory.<Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Zung Self-Rating Depression Scale.<Reference refidx="17"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Distress Thermometer.<Reference refidx="18"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_457">One study of women with newly diagnosed breast cancer (n = 236) successfully used brief screening instruments such as the Distress Thermometer and the PHQ-9 to identify women requiring further assessment to detect clinically significant levels of distress and psychiatric symptoms.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><Para id="_458">In a study of 321 women with newly diagnosed stage I to stage III breast cancer, the ability of the single-item Distress Thermometer to specifically predict depression, as measured by a self-report questionnaire of the nine <Emphasis>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders,</Emphasis> 4th edition (DSM-IV) symptoms for major depressive disorder, was investigated.  Sensitivity and specificity characteristics were evaluated, and the optimal cutoff score of 7 was identified, resulting in a sensitivity of 0.81 and a specificity of 0.85 for detecting depression.  Therefore, individuals scoring 7 or above will undergo a more thorough psychosocial evaluation.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_459">The Impact Thermometer, a modification of and accompaniment to the Distress Thermometer, has improved specificity for the detection of adjustment disorders and/or major depression, as compared with the Distress Thermometer.  The revised tool has a screening performance comparable to that of the HADS and is brief, potentially making it an effective tool for routine screening in oncology settings.<Reference refidx="21"/> The Mood Evaluation Questionnaire, a cognitive-based screening tool for depression, has moderate correlation with the structured clinical interview for the DSM, 3rd revised edition (DSM-III-R) and good acceptability in the  palliative care population.     With further validation, it may become a useful alternative in this population because it can be used by clinicians who are not trained in psychiatry.<Reference refidx="22"/>
</Para><Para id="_21">It is important that screening instruments be validated in cancer populations
and used in combination with structured diagnostic interviews.<Reference refidx="23"/>    A pilot
study of 25 patients used a simple, easily reproduced visual analog scale
suggesting the benefits of a single-item approach to screening for depression. 
This scale consists of a 10-cm line with a sad face at one end and a happy face
at the other end, on which patients make a mark to indicate their mood. 
Although the results do suggest that a visual analog scale may be useful as a
screening tool for depression, the small patient numbers and lack of clinical
interviews limit conclusions.  Furthermore, although very high correlations
with the HADS were reported (<Emphasis>r</Emphasis> = 0.87), no
indication of cutoffs was given.  Finally, it is emphasized that such
a tool is intended to suggest the need for further professional assessment. 
However, if validated further, this simple approach could greatly enhance
assessment and management of depression in cognitively intact advanced-cancer
patients.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/></Para><Para id="_676">In a study of 2,141 German cancer patients, the HADS and the PHQ-9 had similar sensitivity (89% and 83%, respectively) and specificity (43% and 61%, respectively) for detecting DSM-IV major depressive disorder at suggested cutoffs based on receiver operating characteristic curves.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para><Para id="_659">Other brief assessment tools for depression can be used.  To help patients distinguish normal anxiety reactions from depression, assessment includes discussion about common symptoms experienced by cancer patients.   Depression is reassessed over time.<Reference refidx="27"/>   Because of the increased risk of adjustment disorders and major
depression in cancer patients, routine screening with increased vigilance at
times of increased stress (e.g., diagnosis, recurrences, progression) is
recommended.<Reference refidx="28"/>  General risk factors for depression are noted in the list above.  Other
risk factors may pertain to specific populations, for example, patients with head and
neck cancer <Reference refidx="4"/> and women at high risk of developing breast
cancer.<Reference refidx="29"/></Para><SummarySection id="_355"><Title>Clinical interview</Title><Table id="_356">
<Title>Table 2.  Suggested Questions for the Assessment of
                 Depressive Symptoms in Adults With Cancer<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title>
<TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="66.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Question</entry><entry>Symptom</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Roth et al.<Reference refidx="30"/>
</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Emphasis><Strong>Depressive symptoms</Strong></Emphasis></entry></Row><Row><entry>How well are you coping with your cancer? Well?  Poorly?</entry><entry>Well-being</entry></Row><Row><entry>How are your spirits since diagnosis?           
   During treatment?  Down?  Blue?</entry><entry>Mood</entry></Row><Row><entry>Do you cry sometimes?  How often?  Only alone?</entry><entry>Mood</entry></Row><Row><entry>Are there things you still enjoy doing, or have you lost     
   pleasure in things you used to do before
   you had cancer?</entry><entry>Anhedonia</entry></Row><Row><entry>      

              

How does the future look to you? Bright?  Black?</entry><entry>Hopelessness</entry></Row><Row><entry>Do you feel you can influence your care, or is your care     
   totally under others' control?</entry><entry>Helplessness</entry></Row><Row><entry>Do you worry about being a burden to family/friends         
   during cancer treatment?</entry><entry>Guilt</entry></Row><Row><entry>Do you feel others might be better off without you?  </entry><entry> Worthlessness</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Left" NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Emphasis><Strong>Physical symptoms (evaluate in the context of cancer-related symptoms)</Strong></Emphasis></entry></Row><Row><entry>
Do you have pain that isn't controlled? </entry><entry>Pain</entry></Row><Row><entry>
How much time do you spend in bed?  </entry><entry>Fatigue</entry></Row><Row><entry>Do you feel weak?  Fatigue easily?  Rested after sleep?     
Any relationship between how you feel and a change in 
treatment or how you otherwise feel physically?</entry><entry>Fatigue</entry></Row><Row><entry>
How is your sleeping?  Trouble going to sleep?              
Awake early?  Often?</entry><entry>Insomnia</entry></Row><Row><entry>How is your appetite?  Food tastes good?                    
Weight loss or gain?</entry><entry>Appetite</entry></Row><Row><entry>How is your interest in sex?  Extent of sexual activity? </entry><entry>Libido</entry></Row><Row><entry>Do you think or move more slowly than usual?</entry><entry>Psychomotor slowing</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_357">Organic Mood Syndromes or Mood Syndromes Related to Another Medical Condition
(MSRAMC), as they are referred to in the DSM, 5th edition (DSM-5),<Reference refidx="31"/> often mimic the mood syndromes in
their presentation.  The assumption is made (perhaps based on their time course
or laboratory data) that an organic or medical factor has a role in the
etiology of the syndrome.  The DSM-5 suggests that prominent cognitive
abnormalities may be accompanying factors and therefore are useful in making
the diagnosis.
Consideration should be given to obtaining laboratory data to assist in
detection of electrolyte or endocrine imbalances or the presence of nutritional
deficiencies.  Clinical experience suggests that pharmacotherapy is more
advantageous than psychotherapy alone in the treatment of depression that is
caused by medical factors, particularly if the dosages of the causative
agent(s) (i.e., steroids, antibiotics, or other medications) cannot be
decreased or discontinued.<Reference refidx="32"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_218"><Title>Diagnosis</Title><Para id="_219">To make a diagnosis
of depression, the clinician confirms that these symptoms have lasted at least 2 weeks and are present on most days.  The
diagnosis of depression in people with cancer can be difficult because of the
problems inherent in distinguishing biological or physical symptoms of
depression from symptoms of illness or toxic side effects of treatment.  This
is particularly true of individuals who are receiving active treatment or those
with advanced disease.</Para><Para id="_599">The following cognitive symptoms are
probably the most useful in diagnosing depression in people with cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_600" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Guilt.</ListItem><ListItem>Worthlessness.</ListItem><ListItem>Hopelessness.</ListItem><ListItem>Helplessness.</ListItem><ListItem>Thoughts of suicide.</ListItem><ListItem>Loss of pleasure in activities.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_601">One German study comparing cancer patients  who had a current affective disorder with those who had a single depressive symptom found loss of interest, followed by depressed mood, to yield the highest power of discrimination between the two groups on multivariate analysis.<Reference refidx="33"/></Para><Para id="_221">The evaluation of depression in people with cancer also includes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_602" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Careful assessment of the person’s perception of the illness.</ListItem><ListItem>Medical history.</ListItem><ListItem>Personal or family history of depression or thoughts of suicide.</ListItem><ListItem>Current mental
status, and physical status, as well as treatment and disease effects.</ListItem><ListItem>Concurrent life stressors.</ListItem><ListItem>Availability of social supports.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_603">More than 90% of patients indicate that they
prefer to discuss emotional issues with their physician, but more than one-quarter
of patients feel that the physician must initiate any discussion of that
topic.<Reference refidx="34"/></Para><Para id="_728">Suicidal ideation is not uncommon among patients with cancer and, when it occurs, is frightening for the
individual, the health professional, and the family. In one study  of 354 health care providers working with oncology patients in Germany, 83.3% reported that they had at least one patient with suicidal ideation in the past year, and 59% reported having one to three suicidal patients annually. This experience was distressing for 88.1% of providers. In addition, over 20% of providers reported feeling overwhelmed when confronted with a suicidal patient.<Reference refidx="35"/><LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">[Level of evidence: II]</LOERef></Para><Para id="_729">Suicidal statements may range from an offhand comment resulting from frustration or
disgust with a treatment course—“If I have to have one more bone marrow
aspiration this year, I’ll jump out the window”—to a reflection of significant
despair and an emergent situation—“I can no longer bear what this disease is
doing to all of us, and I am going to kill myself.”  Exploring the seriousness
of the thoughts is imperative.  If the suicidal thoughts are believed to be
serious, it is imperative that a referral to a psychiatrist or psychologist is made
immediately and attention is given to the patient’s safety.<Reference refidx="34"/> For more information, see the
<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_98" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Suicide Risk in Cancer Patients</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_17">The most common form of depressive symptomatology in people with cancer is an
adjustment disorder with depressed mood, sometimes referred to as reactive
depression.  This disorder is manifested when a person has a dysphoric mood
that is accompanied by the inability to perform usual activities.<Reference refidx="36"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>] The symptoms
appear to be prolonged and in excess of a normal and expected reaction but do
not meet the criteria for a major depressive episode.  When these symptoms
significantly interfere with a person's daily functioning, such as attending to
work or school activities, shopping, or caring for a household, they are
treated in the same way that major depression is treated (i.e., with
crisis intervention, supportive psychotherapy, and medication, especially with
drugs that quickly relieve distressing symptoms).  Basing the diagnosis on
these symptoms can  be problematic when the individual has advanced
disease and the illness itself is undermining functioning.</Para><Para id="_640">It is also important to distinguish between fatigue and depression, which are often interrelated and can be part of a symptom  cluster.  The different mechanisms that  give rise to these conditions can be treated separately.<Reference refidx="1"/>  In more advanced
illness, focusing on despair, guilty thoughts, and a total lack of enjoyment of
life is helpful in diagnosing depression.
 For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000814132" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/cancer-symptom-clusters-hp-pdq">Symptom Clusters in Cancer</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062891" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-hp-pdq">Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="14613050">Jacobsen PB, Donovan KA, Weitzner MA: Distinguishing fatigue and depression in patients with cancer. Semin Clin Neuropsychiatry 8 (4): 229-40, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10668056" MedlineID="20134757">De Leeuw JR, De Graeff A, Ros WJ, et al.: Negative and positive influences of social support on depression in patients with head and neck cancer: a prospective study. Psychooncology 9 (1): 20-8, 2000 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="34990907">Riedl D, Schüßler G: Factors associated with and risk factors for depression in cancer patients - A systematic literature review. Transl Oncol 16: 101328, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11592237" MedlineID="21475693">de Leeuw JR, de Graeff A, Ros WJ, et al.: Prediction of depression 6 months to 3 years after treatment of head and neck cancer. Head Neck 23 (10): 892-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="12436073" MedlineID="22322611">Paice JA: Managing psychological conditions in palliative care. Am J Nurs 102 (11): 36-42; quiz 43, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="32946156">Nakamura ZM, Deal AM, Nyrop KA, et al.: Serial Assessment of Depression and Anxiety by Patients and Providers in Women Receiving Chemotherapy for Early Breast Cancer. Oncologist 26 (2): 147-156, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9552071" MedlineID="98211798">Passik SD, Dugan W, McDonald MV, et al.: Oncologists' recognition of depression in their patients with cancer. J Clin Oncol 16 (4): 1594-600, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9137124" MedlineID="97282990">Chochinov HM, Wilson KG, Enns M, et al.: "Are you depressed?" Screening for depression in the terminally ill. Am J Psychiatry 154 (5): 674-6, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12733160" MedlineID="22617776">Akizuki N, Akechi T, Nakanishi T, et al.: Development of a brief screening interview for adjustment disorders and major depression in patients with cancer. Cancer 97 (10): 2605-13, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="11982548" MedlineID="21978741">Love AW, Kissane DW, Bloch S, et al.: Diagnostic efficiency of the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale in women with early stage breast cancer. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 36 (2): 246-50, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="11738161" MedlineID="21602368">Lloyd-Williams M, Friedman T, Rudd N: An analysis of the validity of the Hospital Anxiety and Depression scale as a screening tool in patients with advanced metastatic cancer. J Pain Symptom Manage 22 (6): 990-6, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="31858249">Annunziata MA, Muzzatti B, Bidoli E, et al.: Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) accuracy in cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 28 (8): 3921-3926, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="10568646">Spitzer RL, Kroenke K, Williams JB: Validation and utility of a self-report version of PRIME-MD: the PHQ primary care study. Primary Care Evaluation of Mental Disorders. Patient Health Questionnaire. JAMA 282 (18): 1737-44, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="8692533" MedlineID="96295600">Morasso G, Costantini M, Baracco G, et al.: Assessing psychological distress in cancer patients: validation of a self-administered questionnaire. Oncology 53 (4): 295-302, 1996 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="12551809" MedlineID="22439988">Lloyd-Williams M, Riddleston H: The stability of depression scores in patients who are receiving palliative care. J Pain Symptom Manage 24 (6): 593-7, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="32021621">Calderon C, Ferrando PJ, Lorenzo-Seva U, et al.: Factor structure and measurement invariance of the Brief Symptom Inventory (BSI-18) in cancer patients. Int J Clin Health Psychol 20 (1): 71-80, 2020 Jan-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="9885089" MedlineID="99100827">Dugan W, McDonald MV, Passik SD, et al.: Use of the Zung Self-Rating Depression Scale in cancer patients: feasibility as a screening tool. Psychooncology 7 (6): 483-93, 1998 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="9587123" MedlineID="98246550">Roth AJ, Kornblith AB, Batel-Copel L, et al.: Rapid screening for psychologic distress in men with prostate carcinoma: a pilot study. Cancer 82 (10): 1904-8, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="17103381">Hegel MT, Moore CP, Collins ED, et al.: Distress, psychiatric syndromes, and impairment of function in women with newly diagnosed breast cancer. Cancer 107 (12): 2924-31, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="17957755">Hegel MT, Collins ED, Kearing S, et al.: Sensitivity and specificity of the Distress Thermometer for depression in newly diagnosed breast cancer patients. Psychooncology 17 (6): 556-60, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="15652442">Akizuki N, Yamawaki S, Akechi T, et al.: Development of an Impact Thermometer for use in combination with the Distress Thermometer as a brief screening tool for adjustment disorders and/or major depression in cancer patients. J Pain Symptom Manage 29 (1): 91-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="14594150">Meyer HA, Sinnott C, Seed PT: Depressive symptoms in advanced cancer. Part 1. Assessing depression: the Mood Evaluation Questionnaire. Palliat Med 17 (7): 596-603, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="7751981" MedlineID="95271385">Lynch ME: The assessment and prevalence of affective disorders in advanced cancer. J Palliat Care 11 (1): 10-8, 1995 Spring.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="10889619" MedlineID="20348060">Lees N, Lloyd-Williams M: Assessing depression in palliative care patients using the visual analogue scale: a pilot study. Eur J Cancer Care (Engl) 8 (4): 220-3, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="12458113" MedlineID="22345943">Passik SD, Kirsh KL, Theobald D, et al.: Use of a depression screening tool and a fluoxetine-based algorithm to improve the recognition and treatment of depression in cancer patients. A demonstration project. J Pain Symptom Manage 24 (3): 318-27, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="28654189">Hartung TJ, Friedrich M, Johansen C, et al.: The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) and the 9-item Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) as screening instruments for depression in patients with cancer. Cancer 123 (21): 4236-4243, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="12902440" MedlineID="22784336">Patrick DL, Ferketich SL, Frame PS, et al.: National Institutes of Health State-of-the-Science Conference Statement: Symptom Management in Cancer: Pain, Depression, and Fatigue, July 15-17, 2002. J Natl Cancer Inst 95 (15): 1110-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="24733793">Andersen BL, DeRubeis RJ, Berman BS, et al.: Screening, assessment, and care of anxiety and depressive symptoms in adults with cancer: an American Society of Clinical Oncology guideline adaptation. J Clin Oncol 32 (15): 1605-19, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="11496022" MedlineID="21387746">Wellisch DK, Lindberg NM: A psychological profile of depressed and nondepressed women at high risk for breast cancer. Psychosomatics 42 (4): 330-6, 2001 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="30">Roth AJ, Holland JC: Psychiatric complications in cancer patients. In: Brain MC, Carbone PP, eds.: Current Therapy in Hematology-Oncology. 5th ed. Mosby-Year Book, Inc., 1995, pp 609-18.</Citation><Citation idx="31">American Psychiatric Association: Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-5. 5th ed. American Psychiatric Association, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="32">Breitbart W, Holland JC: Psychiatric complications of cancer. Current Therapy in Hematology-Oncology  3: 268-74, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="15480816">Reuter K, Raugust S, Bengel J, et al.: Depressive symptom patterns and their consequences for diagnosis of affective disorders in cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 12 (12): 864-70, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="10986063" MedlineID="20442267">Detmar SB, Aaronson NK, Wever LD, et al.: How are you feeling? Who wants to know? Patients' and oncologists' preferences for discussing health-related quality-of-life issues. J Clin Oncol 18 (18): 3295-301, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="32672869">Senf B, Maiwurm P, Fettel J: Exposure to suicidality in professionals working with oncology patients: An online survey. Psychooncology 29 (10): 1620-1629, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="11747060" MedlineID="21612771">Nordin K, Wasteson E, Hoffman K, et al.: Discrepancies between attainment and importance of life values and anxiety and depression in gastrointestinal cancer patients and their spouses. Psychooncology 10 (6): 479-89, 2001 Nov-Dec.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_29"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042480">depression</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Intervention</Title><Para id="_30">The decision  to initiate therapy for depression depends on the probability
that the patient will recover spontaneously in the next 2 to 4 weeks, the
degree of functional impairment, and the severity and duration of the
depressive symptoms.<Reference refidx="1"/> It is important to assess the nature of emotional distress and factors  contributing to the depression symptomatology  (e.g., psychosocial factors, demoralization, and comorbid symptoms such as  pain or fatigue). Decisions about interventions depend on the severity of depression and on factors driving depression symptomatology.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Studies have shown that treatment of severe major depression
is optimized by a combination of pharmacotherapy and psychotherapy.<Reference refidx="2"/> Thus, even
if a primary care physician or oncologist undertakes the treatment of
depressive symptoms pharmacologically, a referral for psychotherapy or
supportive counseling should be considered.</Para><Para id="_31">For the following reasons, referral of individuals for a psychiatric consultation should be considered:<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_32" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The primary care physician or oncologist does not feel competent treating the
patient for depression because of specific clinical features in the
presentation (i.e., if prominent suicidal tendencies are present).</ListItem>
<ListItem>The depressive symptoms treated by the primary physician are resistant to
pharmacological interventions after 2 to 4 weeks of intervention.</ListItem>
<ListItem>The depressive symptoms are worsening rather than improving.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Initiating treatment with antidepressant drugs, titrating drug
doses, or continuing treatment is interrupted or made problematic by
adverse effects attributable to the medication.</ListItem>
<ListItem>The depressive symptoms are interfering with the patient’s ability to cooperate with medical treatment.</ListItem>
</ItemizedList><Para id="_762">In addition, among patients who have completed treatment for cancer and have comorbid depression, the use of antidepressants may decrease the risk of cancer recurrence. For example, in a population-based study,  men with prostate cancer with documented depression disorder (n = 10,017) were followed for over 20 years. The researchers found that those who took antidepressants had lower rates of prostate cancer recurrence than those who did not take antidepressants.<Reference refidx="5"/> While this evidence is intriguing, prospective, confirmatory trials and investigations are needed to better understand these findings and the underlying mechanisms.</Para><SummarySection id="_305"><Title>Pharmacological Intervention</Title><SummarySection id="_306"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_307">There is a dearth of randomized, placebo-controlled trials assessing the risks and benefits of antidepressants in patients with cancer and depression or depressive symptoms.  Furthermore, these studies are limited by methodological challenges and a lack of broad representation of children, adolescents, older adults, and minority groups.<Reference refidx="6"/> However, a systematic review and meta-analysis of the available studies suggest that antidepressants, regardless of their class (e.g., selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors [SSRIs] or tricyclic antidepressants [TCAs]), are more effective than placebo in treating depression in patients with cancer.<Reference refidx="7"/>

 Evidence also suggests that the efficacy of antidepressant treatment is related to the presence of clinically significant depression symptomatology,<Reference refidx="8"/> suggesting that antidepressants be reserved for patients presenting with clinical depression.</Para><Para id="_631">  A survey of prescribing patterns in outpatient oncology settings over a 2-year period found that antidepressants were prescribed  for about 14% of patients.<Reference refidx="9"/> In a systematic review of newer pharmacotherapies for
depression in adults, the response rate for treatment of depression with
antidepressants was found to be approximately 54%.<Reference refidx="10"/>  The efficacy of the
newer pharmacotherapies is similar to that of older antidepressants for general
medical patients, including older adults and those with medical or
psychiatric comorbidities.<Reference refidx="10"/>  The rates of dropout due to adverse effects are
approximately 11% for newer antidepressants and 16% for older
antidepressants.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_632">Because of the relative paucity of data regarding antidepressant use in
oncology settings, there is considerable variability in  practice patterns
related to prescribing antidepressants for cancer patients.  Although studies
generally indicate that about 25% of all cancer patients are depressed, one study found that only 16%
of cancer patients were receiving antidepressant medication.<Reference refidx="11"/> However, among depressed patients with advanced cancer who had an unplanned hospitalization, patients who were treated with a prescribed antidepressant had shorter hospitalizations than did patients who were not treated.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_501"><Title>Antidepressant classes</Title><Para id="_502">Antidepressants are divided into several classes on the basis of  their underlying mechanisms. Most inhibit uptake of neurotransmitters; some also have a direct impact on cell receptors (see Table 3).</Para><Table id="_653"><Title>Table 3.   Antidepressant Medications<Superscript>a</Superscript> and Adjunctive Pharmacological Treatments</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="31.82%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="18.08%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="26.40%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="23.68%"/><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">CYP = cytochrome P450 enzyme; GI = gastrointestinal; IR = immediate release; MAOI = monoamine oxidase inhibitor; NDRI = norepinephrine-dopamine reuptake inhibitor; SNRI = serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor; SR = sustained release; SSRI = selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor; TCA = tricyclic antidepressant; XL = extended release.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>All antidepressants carry a boxed warning about the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior, risk of mania, and risk of drug-drug interaction when combined with MAOIs (for more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_521" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">MAOIs</SummaryRef> section).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>For more information about side effects associated with SNRIs, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_505" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs)</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">  <Strong>SSRIs</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Medication</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Starting Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Maintenance Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Comments</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Citalopram</entry><entry MoreRows="1">10–20</entry><entry MoreRows="1">20–40</entry><entry>Better safety-tolerability profile than other antidepressants.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Potential for QTc prolongation (dose increase limited in patients with cardiac issues).</entry></Row><Row><entry>Escitalopram</entry><entry>5–10</entry><entry>10–20</entry><entry>Better safety-tolerability profile than other antidepressants.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Fluoxetine</entry><entry MoreRows="1">10–20</entry><entry MoreRows="1">20–60</entry><entry>Minimal risk of serotonin discontinuation syndrome due to long half-life.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Significant inhibitor of CYP2D6.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Fluvoxamine</entry><entry MoreRows="1">25–50</entry><entry MoreRows="1">100–300</entry><entry>Better anxiolytic properties than other SSRIs.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Significant inhibitor of CYP1A2 and CYP3A4.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Paroxetine</entry><entry MoreRows="2">10–20</entry><entry MoreRows="2">20–60</entry><entry>High risk of serotonin discontinuation syndrome.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Modest anticholinergic properties.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Significant inhibitor of CYP2D6.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Sertraline</entry><entry MoreRows="1">25–50</entry><entry MoreRows="1">100–200</entry><entry>Higher risk of GI side effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dose-dependent inhibition of CYP2D6.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Vilazodone</entry><entry MoreRows="1">10</entry><entry MoreRows="1">20–40</entry><entry>Risk of GI side effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Possibly less risk of sexual dysfunction, but evidence inconclusive.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Strong>SNRIs<Superscript>b</Superscript></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Medication</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Starting Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Maintenance Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Comments</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Desvenlafaxine</entry><entry>50</entry><entry>50–100</entry><entry>Positive impact on hot flashes.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Duloxetine</entry><entry MoreRows="2">30</entry><entry MoreRows="2">30–60</entry><entry>First-line treatment in patients with comorbid neuropathic pain (in doses as high as 120 mg).</entry></Row><Row><entry>Higher risk of GI side effects and hypertension.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Risk of hepatotoxicity.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Levomilnacipran</entry><entry MoreRows="2">20</entry><entry MoreRows="2">40–120</entry><entry>More-potent noradrenergic effects, activating effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Useful for comorbid cognitive and pain symptoms.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Increased risk of cardiovascular side effects, sweating, and urinary hesitancy.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Venlafaxine (IR and XL)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">37.5–75</entry><entry MoreRows="1">150–225</entry><entry>First-line treatment in patients with comorbid hot flashes.</entry></Row><Row><entry> 
Higher risk of serotonin discontinuation syndrome.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Strong>TCAs</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Medication (only most commonly used TCAs included below)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Starting Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Maintenance Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Comments</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Amitriptyline</entry><entry MoreRows="3">10–25</entry><entry MoreRows="3">150–300</entry><entry>Marked sedation and anticholinergic effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Weight gain.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Orthostatic hypotension.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dizziness.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Clomipramine</entry><entry>25</entry><entry>100–250</entry><entry>More serotonergic effects, less sedation, and fewer anticholinergic effects than other TCAs.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Desipramine</entry><entry MoreRows="1">25–50</entry><entry MoreRows="1">100–300</entry><entry>Mild sedation.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Minimal anticholinergic effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Doxepin</entry><entry MoreRows="3">10–25</entry><entry MoreRows="3">75–300</entry><entry>Marked sedation and anticholinergic effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Weight gain.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Orthostatic hypotension.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dizziness.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Imipramine</entry><entry MoreRows="4">25–50</entry><entry MoreRows="4">75–300</entry><entry>Moderate sedation. 
 
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Weight gain.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Anticholinergic effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Orthostatic hypotension.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dizziness.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Nortriptyline</entry><entry MoreRows="1">10–25</entry><entry MoreRows="1">90–150</entry><entry>Mild sedation.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Moderate anticholinergic effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Strong>NDRIs</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Medication</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Starting Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Maintenance Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Comments</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Bupropion (IR, SR, and XL)</entry><entry MoreRows="2">100–150 (SR and XL)</entry><entry MoreRows="2">150–450</entry><entry>Stimulating effects and  lack of sexual dysfunction.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dose-dependent seizure risk (rare), insomnia, headaches, and weight loss.</entry></Row><Row><entry>SR and XL commonly used to avoid anxiogenic effects and higher seizure risk associated with IR.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Atypical antidepressants</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Medication</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Starting Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Maintenance Dose (mg/day)</Emphasis></Strong></entry><entry><Strong><Emphasis>Comments</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Mirtazapine</entry><entry MoreRows="3">7.5–15</entry><entry MoreRows="3">30–45</entry><entry>Frequently used in cancer patients with comorbid insomnia and cachexia. Known for its antinausea effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Decreased elimination in elderly.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sedation, weight gain, and dizziness.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Risk of hepatotoxicity and neutropenia.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Trazodone</entry><entry MoreRows="2">25–50</entry><entry MoreRows="2">50–200</entry><entry>Primarily used as adjunct to other antidepressants. Useful for comorbid insomnia and anxiety.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Marked sedation and anxiolytic effects.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Risk of orthostatic hypotension, dizziness, and priapism (rare).</entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong>MAOIs</Strong><Strong>/Psychostimulants as adjunctive treatments to antidepressants/</Strong><Strong>Other adjunctive treatments</Strong></entry><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col2">See the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_521" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">text below</SummaryRef> for more information.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_660">The following sections describe the major antidepressant classes, their underlying mechanisms of action, their safety/tolerability profiles, and their potential use in cancer patient populations.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><SummarySection id="_503"><Title>Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors</Title><Para id="_504">SSRIs are most commonly used in patients with cancer because they have better safety-tolerability profiles than other antidepressants.  SSRIs block the reabsorption of serotonin (also called 5-hydroxytryptamine or 5-HT) by the presynaptic neurons by blocking the serotonin transporters. This causes more serotonin to be available to bind to the receptors of the postsynaptic neuron. Medications such as citalopram, escitalopram, and paroxetine work primarily by serotonin transporter blockade. Other SSRIs have additional mechanisms underlying their antidepressant effects. For example, fluoxetine binds to a specific serotonin receptor called the 5-HT<Subscript>2c</Subscript> receptor, sertraline blocks dopamine transporters, and vilazodone has partial agonism at the 5-HT<Subscript>1a</Subscript> serotonin receptor. The drugs in this class are similar in terms of their effectiveness. The most common side effects associated with this class of medications include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_683" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Gastrointestinal (GI) side effects (e.g., nausea, diarrhea, constipation).</ListItem><ListItem>Sexual dysfunction (e.g., delayed ejaculation, anorgasmia, decreased libido).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_684">However, the drugs  differ in severity of these side effects and can have additional effects related to their impact on other neurobiological systems such as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_685" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Anticholinergic effects (e.g., cognitive difficulties, confusion, dry mouth, dry skin, constipation, blurred vision, urinary retention).</ListItem><ListItem>Sedation.</ListItem><ListItem>Insomnia.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_633">SSRIs generally undergo hepatic metabolism, renal elimination, and differ significantly in terms of their half-lives. The half-life of the specific SSRI  depends on the half-lives of the parent compound and the metabolite. The serotonin discontinuation syndrome, a syndrome associated with abrupt discontinuation of SSRIs, is related to the half-life of the SSRI and its active metabolites. The shorter the half-life of the SSRI and its metabolites, the higher the risk of serotonin discontinuation syndrome. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_509" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Serotonin discontinuation syndrome</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_505"><Title>Serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs)</Title><Para id="_506">SNRIs increase levels of both 5-HT and norepinephrine (NE) in the synapse by blocking reuptake of these neurotransmitters by their respective transporters. SNRIs differ in their blockade of 5-HT and NE transporters, depending on their affinity for these transporters. Venlafaxine is primarily serotonergic at lower dosages, with mixed 5-HT and NE effects at higher dosages. Duloxetine and desvenlafaxine are known to block both 5-HT and NE transporters at low dosages, while levomilnacipran has the highest noradrenergic effects at lower dosages, compared with other SNRIs. These different 5-HT and NE effects may be associated with differential efficacy and side effect profiles in different patient populations. For example, serotonergic effects may be more beneficial in the treatment of depression with comorbid anxiety, while noradrenergic effects may be more beneficial in the treatment of depression with atypical features such as hypersomnia, lack of energy, and lack of motivation.</Para><Para id="_507">Many of the SNRIs are also known for their positive impact on pain syndromes, including neuropathic pain associated with chemotherapy. Like SSRIs, SNRIs can cause GI side effects and sexual side effects. Other side effects associated with SNRIs result from their anticholinergic and antihistamine properties and include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_686" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Sedation.</ListItem><ListItem>Dry mouth.</ListItem><ListItem>Constipation.</ListItem><ListItem>Dizziness (due to orthostatic hypotension).</ListItem><ListItem>Blurred vision.</ListItem><ListItem>Urinary retention.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_635">The precise underlying mechanisms of these side effects remain unknown. Other side effects of SNRIs include dose-related diastolic hypertension and increased risk of cardiovascular side effects, primarily resulting from their noradrenergic effects.  For this reason, a baseline electrocardiogram (ECG) is recommended in some cases.  SNRIs are also associated with increased risk of headaches and excessive sweating. Certain SNRIs, specifically venlafaxine and desvenlafaxine, are known to treat hot flashes associated with menopausal symptoms. Similar to SSRIs, SNRIs also carry a risk of serotonin syndrome and serotonin discontinuation syndrome with abrupt discontinuation.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_719"><Title>Tricyclic antidepressants</Title><Para id="_720">Similar to SNRIs, TCAs also increase levels of both 5-HT and NE in the synapse by blocking reuptake of these neurotransmitters by their respective transporters.  TCAs are converted to secondary amine metabolites by demethylation in the liver. Both the primary amines and their secondary amine metabolites are active compounds. The secondary amine active metabolites of imipramine (desipramine) and amitriptyline (nortriptyline) are much more potent NE reuptake inhibitors.</Para><Para id="_721">TCAs are not commonly used as first-line agents due to high risk of cardiotoxicity and neurotoxicity, including risk of seizures. Use of TCAs requires extreme caution because overdoses of even small amounts can be fatal.  A baseline ECG is recommended to evaluate for preexisting cardiac conduction abnormalities.  Other side effects include risk of weight gain and anticholinergic effects. These side effects are more prominent with TCAs than SNRIs.  </Para><Para id="_722">TCAs are primarily used as adjuncts in the treatment of refractory depression and in the treatment of comorbidities such as headaches,   neuropathy, and insomnia.  TCAs also carry a risk of serotonin syndrome and serotonin discontinuation syndrome with abrupt discontinuation.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_509"><Title>Serotonin discontinuation syndrome</Title><Para id="_510">A discontinuation syndrome has been associated with stoppage of serotonergic antidepressants, both SSRIs and SNRIs.<Reference refidx="14"/> This syndrome is particularly associated with abrupt discontinuation of these medications but can occur in certain cases even with gradual taper. The syndrome includes symptoms such as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_556" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> Dysphoric mood.</ListItem><ListItem> Anxiety.</ListItem><ListItem>Headaches.</ListItem><ListItem>Dizziness.</ListItem><ListItem>Confusion.</ListItem><ListItem>Agitation.</ListItem><ListItem>Sensory disturbances (such as paresthesia).</ListItem><ListItem> Insomnia.</ListItem><ListItem>Autonomic instability and seizures in rare cases.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_557">The syndrome is generally self-limiting but in rare cases requires medical attention. The treatment may include re-initiation of serotonergic medications at lower dosages, with gradual taper of these medications over a longer period.  Gradual tapering of all serotonergic medications,  especially medications with short half-lives such as paroxetine, is strongly recommended to avoid discontinuation syndrome. When taper schedules are recommended, it is also critical to consider individual patient factors such as history of discontinuation syndromes.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_511"><Title>Serotonin syndrome</Title><Para id="_512">Serotonin syndrome <Reference refidx="15"/> can result from a  high dose of one serotonergic medication. More frequently, it is caused by inadvertent concomitant use of two or more serotonergic medications (e.g., serotonergic antidepressants with tramadol, fentanyl, triptans, St. John’s wort, or monoamine oxidase inhibitors [MAOIs]). This syndrome may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_558" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>GI symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea).</ListItem><ListItem>Neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., rigidity, tremors, myoclonus, and hyperreflexia).</ListItem><ListItem>Autonomic instability in extreme cases (e.g., labile blood pressure, tachycardia, hyperthermia, and flushing).</ListItem><ListItem>Mental status changes in extreme cases (e.g., agitation, delirium, and coma).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_559">Careful review of all medications is recommended before any serotonergic medication is added to a patient’s medication regimen.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_513"><Title>Norepinephrine-dopamine reuptake inhibitors</Title><Para id="_514">Bupropion is the only medication with this mechanism of action. It blocks the dopamine transporter while its primary metabolite, 6-hydroxybupropion, is a potent NE reuptake inhibitor. Bupropion may be more effective in the treatment of atypical depression (i.e., depression with fatigue and hypersomnia). It is a unique alternative to SSRIs and SNRIs for treating persons with depression and cancer, especially when depression is accompanied by fatigue. Unlike serotonergic antidepressants, bupropion is not associated with sexual dysfunction; therefore, it may be useful in treating patients who wish to remain sexually active and those who have experienced sexual dysfunction with other antidepressants.</Para><Para id="_560">Bupropion is available in three formulations based on frequency of administration:<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_688" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Immediate release (three times daily).<Reference refidx="17"/></ListItem><ListItem>Sustained release (twice daily).<Reference refidx="18"/></ListItem><ListItem>Extended release (once daily).<Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_689">The sustained- and extended-release formulations are used more frequently because of the ease of administration and less risk of certain side effects, such as anxiety and seizures. The risk of seizures with bupropion is low but can be increased substantially by predisposing factors such as the following:<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_690" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>History of seizures.</ListItem><ListItem>Head trauma.</ListItem><ListItem>Brain tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Eating disorders.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_691"><Strong>Bupropion should be avoided in patients with malignant diseases involving the brain and
histories of cranial trauma or seizure disorder,</Strong><Reference refidx="16"/><Strong> and it is contraindicated in people with a
history of bulimia.</Strong><Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>] Other potential side effects with bupropion include anxiety and insomnia.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_515"><Title>Antidepressants with mixed pharmacological properties</Title><Para id="_516">The antidepressants in this category have multiple pharmacological properties, including combinations of blockade of monoamine transporters and direct receptor agonist or antagonist properties.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><SummarySection id="_517"><Title>Mirtazapine</Title><Para id="_518">Mirtazapine is an alpha-2 adrenergic receptor antagonist, blocks several serotonin receptors (5-HT<Subscript>2a</Subscript>, 5-HT<Subscript>2c</Subscript>, and 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>), and is a potent H<Subscript>1</Subscript> histamine receptor antagonist. Its blockade of presynaptic alpha-2 adrenergic receptors causes the release of NE which, in turn, causes the release of 5-HT. This increase in NE and 5-HT and  blockade of 5-HT<Subscript>2c</Subscript> and 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptors have been associated with mirtazapine’s antidepressant effects. The potent antihistaminic effects of mirtazapine can cause significant sedation; in addition, its blockade of histaminic and 5-HT<Subscript>2c</Subscript> receptors has been associated with increased appetite/weight gain, and its blockade of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptors causes mild antiemetic effects. Mirtazapine has minimal risk of drug-drug interactions because it does not have significant impact on cytochrome P450 enzymes. The sedation and increased appetite/weight gain side effects can be beneficial in patients with cancer struggling with insomnia and cachexia.</Para><Para id="_561">Mirtazapine is frequently used for cancer patients, specifically for the treatment of depression with comorbid insomnia and weight loss. It is also useful in this patient population because of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_692" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Minimal risk of drug-drug interactions.</ListItem><ListItem>Mild antiemetic effects.</ListItem><ListItem>Minimal impact on sexual function.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_693">Mirtazapine is associated with agranulocytosis/neutropenia and increased liver enzymes in rare cases. Monitoring of blood counts and liver enzymes is necessary, especially when patients are at risk of these side effects because of comorbid conditions and other cancer treatments. In rare cases, mirtazapine carries the risk of serotonin syndrome, primarily when taken in combination with other potent serotonergic medications; it is not associated with serotonin discontinuation syndrome. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_511" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Serotonin syndrome</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_519"><Title>Trazodone</Title><Para id="_520">Trazodone is a 5-HT<Subscript>2a</Subscript> and 5-HT<Subscript>2c</Subscript> receptor antagonist and weak serotonin reuptake inhibitor. It can be very beneficial as an adjunct in the treatment of depression with comorbid insomnia and anxiety. It has potent sedative effects even at low dosages because of its blockade of histamine, 5-HT<Subscript>2c</Subscript> receptors, and alpha-1 receptors. Trazodone is primarily used at low dosages (25–150 mg) to treat insomnia with or without depression/anxiety. Only high dosages (150–600 mg) of trazodone are associated with antidepressant effects. However, such high dosages carry a high risk of side effects, especially risk of significant daytime sedation, dizziness due to orthostatic hypotension, and other cardiovascular risks. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_521"><Title>MAOIs</Title><Para id="_522">MAOIs increase all three monoamines (dopamine, serotonin, and NE) simultaneously because of their inhibition of MAO enzymes. The older MAOIs cause irreversible inhibition of both MAO-A and MAO-B enzymes. These medications can be highly effective, especially in the treatment of refractory depression and anxiety symptoms. However, MAOIs are primarily used as last resort because of their risk of serious side effects, multiple drug-drug interactions, and the significant dietary restrictions patients must adhere to when using these medications.</Para><Para id="_636">Several classes of medications are contraindicated or used with extreme caution with MAOIs because of the risk of serious and even lethal interactions due to serotonin syndrome and hypertensive crisis. Such classes of medications include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_694" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Sympathomimetics.</ListItem><ListItem>Anesthetics.</ListItem><ListItem>Other noradrenergic agents.</ListItem><ListItem>Serotonergic  agents.</ListItem><ListItem>Dopaminergic agents.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_695">Opioids with serotonergic properties, such as meperidine and methadone, should also be avoided with MAOIs. Patients taking MAOIs must follow strict dietary restrictions to avoid potentially fatal hypertensive crises. Avoiding foods that contain significant amounts of tyramine (e.g., aged cheese and meats) is critical when these medications are taken. The hypertensive crisis with MAOIs is related to the rapid increase in NE levels because of lack of tyramine processing by the MAO enzymes. Other common side effects include orthostatic hypotension, dizziness, anticholinergic side effects, and headaches.</Para><Para id="_523">MAOIs include selegiline, phenelzine, and tranylcypromine. Selegiline, a reversible MAOI, is available as a transdermal patch. At low dosages, it is primarily a selective MAO-B inhibitor and therefore does not require dietary restrictions (up to 9-mg doses). Because of selegiline’s transdermal delivery, at higher doses it still bypasses most of the MAO-A enzyme in the gut while inhibiting both MAO-A and MAO-B in the brain needed for antidepressant effects. However, patients receiving high doses are required to follow dietary restrictions because of the potential for inhibition of MAO-A enzyme in the gut. Higher doses carry warnings for drug-drug interactions and other side effects similar to those for older MAOIs.</Para><Para id="_524">In patients with cancer, the use of MAOIs is limited to highly refractory cases due to additional cancer and cancer treatment–related risk factors (e.g., cardiovascular comorbidities due to certain cancer treatments and the use of pain medications such as tramadol and methadone). In most cases, MAOIs are prescribed and managed by psychiatric clinicians in this patient population because of the  multiple risks noted earlier. At a minimum, significant involvement of psychiatric prescribers and pharmacy consultation are strongly recommended during initiation and management of MAOIs.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_525"><Title>Augmentation strategies</Title><Para id="_661">A patient may show improvement with the primary antidepressant treatment, but this improvement may be inadequate from a clinical standpoint because of significant residual symptomatology affecting the patient’s well-being and functioning. In such cases, certain augmentation strategies may be helpful.<Reference refidx="21"/> However, before any augmentation strategies are considered, it is critical to ensure the adequacy of the primary antidepressant, especially in terms of dosing and duration. Selection of the augmentation strategy is driven by residual or comorbid symptomatology. The following sections describe certain augmentation agents and strategies.</Para><SummarySection id="_526"><Title>Benzodiazepines</Title><Para id="_527">Benzodiazepines can be used to effectively treat the anxiety that may be associated with depression. In patients receiving antidepressant medications and benzodiazepines concomitantly, the latter drugs may be discontinued after patients’ depressive symptoms begin to abate; however, both agents can be continued safely if needed. Benzodiazepines cannot be stopped abruptly because withdrawal symptoms with possible seizures may occur. The dose of benzodiazepines is tapered slowly, at a rate of approximately 25% every 3 to 4 days.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_528"><Title>Psychostimulants</Title><Para id="_529">Clinical experience suggests that analeptic agents (e.g., methylphenidate
and dextroamphetamine) are useful at low doses for patients whose
symptoms include the following:<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_696" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Depressed mood.</ListItem><ListItem>Apathy.</ListItem><ListItem>Decreased energy.</ListItem><ListItem>Poor concentration.</ListItem><ListItem>Weakness.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_697">These agents are usually prescribed at low dosages and as adjuncts to antidepressants. Analeptic agents are particularly useful for patients with advanced cancer who have a limited life expectancy (weeks to a few months). Psychostimulants often demonstrate antifatigue effects within a few days of starting treatment. They can be helpful in countering the sedating effects of opioids.</Para><Para id="_637">Adverse effects associated with analeptic agents include neuropsychiatric side effects such as insomnia, mood lability,  anxiety, agitation, anorexia, and even psychotic symptoms. They are also associated with adverse cardiovascular effects such as hypertension and arrhythmia. A baseline ECG is recommended.  These medications can also lower the seizure threshold. Finally, there is a risk of developing tolerance, misuse, and dependence on these medications. Considering risks and benefits is critical when the use of these medications is being contemplated. These medications, in appropriate cases and when used in optimal dosages, can have a significant positive impact on a patient’s quality of life, especially for those with advanced cancers.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_530"><Title>Adjunctive medications to treat medical and psychiatric comorbidities</Title><Para id="_531">Medical and psychiatric comorbidities (e.g., neuropathy, menopausal symptoms, and trauma symptoms) may play a role in depression severity. Such conditions frequently have a bidirectional interaction with depression, with one exacerbating the other and vice versa. Medications other than antidepressants that can treat medical/psychiatric comorbidities may play a crucial role in the management of depression in patients with psychiatric comorbidities. For example, gabapentin can be used as an adjunct to antidepressants to target comorbid neuropathic pain, menopausal symptoms, and anxiety symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_532"><Title>Adjunctive medications in treatment-refractory cases</Title><Para id="_533">Evidence from the noncancer (general psychiatry) literature suggests a role for other medications and medication classes as adjuncts to antidepressants in treatment-refractory cases.<Reference refidx="21"/> Such medications and medication classes include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_698" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> Antipsychotic medications.</ListItem><ListItem>Thyroid hormone.</ListItem><ListItem>Lithium.</ListItem><ListItem> Buspirone.</ListItem><ListItem>Certain combination strategies for different antidepressant classes.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_699">Buspirone is primarily used as an adjunct to treat comorbid anxiety symptoms. Some of these medications (e.g., antipsychotic medications and lithium) are associated with a significant burden of side effects. Referral to and/or extensive involvement of psychiatric clinicians is strongly recommended for treatment-refractory cases, especially if these medications and medication classes are considered as adjuncts.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_534"><Title>Antidepressant medication selection and management</Title><Para id="_535">Several general, cancer-related, and cancer treatment–related factors play an important role in the choice and management of antidepressants in cancer patients.<Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/> The general risks-benefits-alternatives principle is even more crucial in the selection of depression treatment for this patient population. Furthermore, full informed consent and patients’ active involvement in decisions about their treatments is critical in the selection and management of depression treatment and for the success of any antidepressant trial.</Para><SummarySection id="_536"><Title>Targeting symptoms</Title><Para id="_537">The predominance or lack of specific symptoms of depression (e.g., fatigue, insomnia, and cognitive difficulties) and related psychiatric comorbidities (e.g., anxiety disorders) play a role in the selection of an antidepressant.<Reference refidx="24"/> For example, patients with fatigue as the  predominant part of their depressive symptomatology may benefit from a trial of bupropion. The side effects of antidepressants may be clinically advantageous in some cases. For example, the sedation and weight gain associated with mirtazapine or certain TCAs may benefit depressed patients with comorbid insomnia and weight loss.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_538"><Title>Avoiding side effects</Title><Para id="_539">Patients with cancer frequently struggle with multiple physical and psychological adverse effects related to their cancer and cancer treatments. It is critical to select antidepressants to avoid further worsening of their health status, either by addition of side effects due to antidepressants or exacerbation of existing issues. For example, patients with cancer may be struggling with issues concerning their sexual function. Antidepressants exacerbating sexual dysfunction can heighten distress, which can worsen depression. Some patients may struggle with the GI side effects of their cancer  and cancer treatments. Certain antidepressants with known risks for significant GI side effects such as nausea and diarrhea (e.g., sertraline and duloxetine) may need to be avoided in these patients.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_540"><Title>Medical comorbidities </Title><Para id="_541">The presence or absence of certain medical comorbidities can drive antidepressant selection.<Reference refidx="24"/> For example, medications such as citalopram, which carries a warning about QTc prolongation, or potent noradrenergic antidepressants such as levomilnacipran may need to be avoided in patients with significant cardiovascular comorbidities. In patients with depression with comorbid chemotherapy-related neuropathy, duloxetine may be beneficial because it targets both depression and neuropathic symptoms. Similarly, patients with depression and menopausal symptoms may benefit from a trial of venlafaxine because it is known to treat both.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_542"><Title>Antidepressant pharmacology</Title><Para id="_543">Antidepressants, even from the same class, can have significant pharmacological differences. They can differ in their absorption; half-lives, including half-lives of their active metabolites; and metabolism via an impact on different cytochrome P450 enzymes. These differences can play an important role, depending on cancer types and cancer treatments.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_544"><Title>Concomitant medications</Title><Para id="_545">Consideration of pharmacodynamic and pharmacokinetic interactions with concomitant medical and psychiatric medications is critical when an antidepressant is being contemplated. For example, highly sedating antidepressants, such as mirtazapine, are not desirable in combination with sedating concomitant medications, such as opioids and benzodiazepines. Potent 2D6 cytochrome P450 enzyme inhibitors, such as paroxetine and duloxetine, are not recommended for patients receiving tamoxifen because of concerns about their impact on the efficacy of tamoxifen (because of the inhibition of tamoxifen’s  conversion to endoxifen, its active metabolite).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_546"><Title>Antidepressant trials for patient and biological family members</Title><Para id="_547">Information collected from patients and family members about experience with antidepressants  (i.e., positive responses or negative experiences such as side effects) can be crucial in the selection of an antidepressant. Genetic background (e.g., serotonin transporter polymorphism) shared by the patient and biological family members may play a role in responsiveness to specific medications or medication classes. Information about successful or failed antidepressants for biological family members can play an important role in antidepressant selection.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_548"><Title>Formulations</Title><Para id="_549">The availability of antidepressant formulations may play a crucial role in antidepressant selection for certain patient populations with cancer. For example, patients with head and neck cancers may have difficulty swallowing because of the disease, its treatment, or both. In such cases, the use of antidepressants in liquid form (e.g., citalopram and fluoxetine) or parenteral form (e.g., amitriptyline injection) may be necessary.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_550"><Title>Bioavailability</Title><Para id="_551">Certain cancers can affect medication absorption (e.g., GI cancers) or metabolism (e.g., liver and kidney cancers). Antidepressant selection may therefore be driven by the pharmacokinetic profile of individual antidepressants to circumvent any issues. In some cases, antidepressant dosages may need to be adjusted beyond recommended guidelines to derive maximum therapeutic benefit.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_552"><Title>Initial titration and management</Title><Para id="_553">Generally, there is a long latency period (3–6 weeks) from initiation of antidepressant medications to the onset of a therapeutic response.<Reference refidx="13"/> Antidepressant treatment begins at low doses, followed by a period of gradual dose titration to achieve an optimum individualized response. Initial low doses may help to avoid initial side effects, but dose escalation may be required to produce therapeutic effects. For some agents, there is a therapeutic window during which plasma concentrations correlate with a patient’s response to the antidepressant (e.g., nortriptyline). For patients receiving these agents, serial drug concentration monitoring guides therapy and helps provide an adequate therapeutic trial because plasma concentrations lower and higher than the defined therapeutic ranges are associated with treatment failure, suboptimal responses and, in the case of high drug concentrations, unnecessary toxicity.</Para><Para id="_638">It is recommended that an antidepressant be continued for at least 1 year for a major depressive episode. Continuation of an antidepressant beyond 1 year depends on several factors, including a patient’s psychological status at that time, their psychiatric history, their cancer and cancer treatment status and, more important, their thoughts about and experience with the antidepressant. As in the initiation, decisions are individualized according to the risks-benefits-alternatives principle and patient choice.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_663"><Title>Switching or discontinuing antidepressants</Title><Para id="_664">Switching from one antidepressant to another or discontinuing antidepressants is frequently indicated because of intolerable adverse effects or lack of treatment response.  Several factors play a role in the strategies employed during switching or stopping an antidepressant. These factors are primarily driven by the risk of serotonin syndrome (see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_511" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Serotonin syndrome</SummaryRef> section for more information) and serotonin discontinuation syndrome (see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_509" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Serotonin discontinuation syndrome</SummaryRef> section for more information). Such factors include antidepressant-dependent factors and patient- or illness-related factors:<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_665" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Antidepressant-dependent factors</ListTitle><ListItem>Half-life of the antidepressant (i.e., shorter half-life is associated with higher risk of withdrawal symptoms).</ListItem><ListItem>Antidepressant dose (i.e., higher dose needs a longer taper period).</ListItem><ListItem>Duration (i.e., longer duration of antidepressant use may need a longer taper period).</ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_666" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Patient- or illness-related factors</ListTitle><ListItem>History of withdrawal symptoms with discontinuation of antidepressants.</ListItem><ListItem>History of heightened sensitivity to medication side effects.</ListItem><ListItem>Severity of psychiatric symptomatology (i.e., more caution is needed with higher severity).</ListItem><ListItem>Medical and physical comorbidities.</ListItem><ListItem>Concomitant medications.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_667">Generally, when antidepressants are switched, either (1) discontinuing one antidepressant  followed by initiating the new one or (2) gradual cross-tapering between the two antidepressants is recommended. However, given the lack of controlled evidence, the switching strategy is highly individualized and driven by the pharmacological properties of both antidepressants and specific patient- and illness-related factors.<Reference refidx="27"/> There are differing opinions about the exact duration and schedule of dose titration because of the lack of evidence from controlled trials in this area.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_674">Switching from a serotonergic antidepressant with a longer half-life (or one that has an active metabolite with a longer half-life, e.g., fluoxetine) to another serotonergic antidepressant may carry the risk of developing serotonin syndrome, depending on when one medication is stopped and the second one is started. The risk of serotonin syndrome in these cases will also depend on the doses of both medications and the schedule of cross-taper.<Reference refidx="27"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_511" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Serotonin syndrome</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_675"> For the discontinuation of serotonergic antidepressants, it is strongly recommended that antidepressants be tapered gradually to minimize the risk of serotonin discontinuation syndrome. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_509" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Serotonin discontinuation syndrome</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_668">As with switching antidepressants, specific medication-related factors and patient- or illness-related factors need to be considered when patients are tapered off antidepressants, but the precise taper strategy is highly individualized. The half-life of antidepressants is a critical factor in stopping antidepressants. Generally, the shorter the half-life of an antidepressant, the higher the risk of discontinuation syndrome. See  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_670" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Table 4</SummaryRef> for a list of antidepressants and the risk of serotonin discontinuation syndrome.</Para><Table id="_670"><Title>Table 4.  Antidepressants and Risk of Serotonin Discontinuation Syndrome</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Agent</entry><entry>Risk<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>Comment(s)</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">MAOI = monoamine oxidase inhibitor; SNRI = serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor; SSRI = selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor; TCA = tricyclic antidepressant; + = low risk; ++ = moderate risk; +++ = high risk.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Risk based on half-life of antidepressant.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong><Emphasis>SSRIs</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Citalopram</entry><entry Align="Center">++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Escitalopram</entry><entry Align="Center">++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Fluoxetine</entry><entry Align="Center"/><entry>Very long half-life; generally, no taper required</entry></Row><Row><entry>Fluvoxamine</entry><entry Align="Center">++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Paroxetine</entry><entry Align="Center">+++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Sertraline</entry><entry Align="Center">++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Vilazodone</entry><entry Align="Center">++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong><Emphasis>SNRIs</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Desvenlafaxine</entry><entry Align="Center">+</entry><entry>~2% risk</entry></Row><Row><entry>Duloxetine</entry><entry Align="Center">++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Levomilnacipran</entry><entry Align="Center">++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Venlafaxine</entry><entry Align="Center">+++</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong><Emphasis>TCAs</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Clomipramine</entry><entry Align="Center">++</entry><entry>Most serotonergic TCA</entry></Row><Row><entry>Other TCAs</entry><entry Align="Center">+</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong><Emphasis>Other antidepressants</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Bupropion</entry><entry Align="Center"/><entry>Minimal to no risk</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong><Emphasis>MAOIs</Emphasis></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Mirtazapine</entry><entry Align="Center"/><entry>Minimal to no risk</entry></Row><Row><entry>Trazodone</entry><entry Align="Center"/><entry>Doses &lt;150 mg/d carry minimal to no risk</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_669">Educating patients about what to expect, close clinical monitoring, and frequent reassurance are crucial during the switching or discontinuing  of antidepressants. Consultation with pharmacy or psychiatric services is generally recommended for switching or stopping. In a minority of cases, despite gradual tapering, patients may experience severe withdrawal symptoms, sometimes lasting several weeks. In such cases, immediate consultation with psychiatric services is strongly recommended.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_554"><Title>Interferon-related depression</Title><Para id="_555">Most antidepressant prescribing is directed at the treatment of an existing
depressive disorder or significant depressive symptoms.  However, one study
supports the use of antidepressants to prevent depression in patients receiving
high-dose interferon for adjuvant therapy of malignant melanoma.<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]  The
rationale for this approach is that treatment with high-dose interferon is
associated with a particularly high rate of depression in this patient
population, and proinflammatory cytokines implicated in the biological changes
that result in depression may be directly reduced by antidepressants.</Para><Para id="_639">In a 
double-blind study of patients receiving high-dose interferon, 2 of 18 patients
in the paroxetine group developed depression during the first 12 weeks of
therapy, compared with 9 of 20 patients in the placebo group (relative risk [RR] =  0.24;
95% confidence interval [CI], 0.08–0.93).  Moreover, there were significantly fewer treatment
discontinuations in the paroxetine group (5% vs. 35%, RR = 0.14; 95% CI,
0.05–0.85).<Reference refidx="28"/>  Further study is required to confirm these findings and to
determine whether prophylactic use of antidepressants has benefit in
other treatment settings.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_447"><Title>Suicide risk of antidepressant medications</Title><Para id="_448">Over the past few years, significant concerns have been raised about the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior with the use of antidepressants in children, adolescents, and young adults.
 In October 2004, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) mandated pharmaceutical companies to add a boxed warning to the labeling of all antidepressants suggesting increased risk of suicidality in pediatric patients who were taking antidepressants. The FDA revised this boxed warning in May 2007 to include young adults younger than 25 years.<Reference refidx="29"/> The carefully worded revision emphasized that the risk of suicidality is associated with both antidepressants and depression. In addition to raising concerns about increased suicidality in children, adolescents, and young adults, the warning acknowledged a significant protective effect of antidepressants in adults aged 65 years and older.</Para><Para id="_474">The meta-analysis that led to the initial boxed warning in pediatric patients concluded that the antidepressants are associated with a twofold increase in suicidal ideation and behavior compared with the placebo in children and adolescents.<Reference refidx="30"/> A major meta-analysis published in the <Emphasis>Journal of the American Medical Association</Emphasis> re-analyzed the data from the child and adolescent studies (including seven studies not included in the initial meta-analysis), using a random-effects model.<Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] While this re-analysis found an overall increased risk of suicidal ideation/suicidal behavior consistent with the initial meta-analysis, the pooled risk differences were found to be smaller and statistically insignificant.</Para><Para id="_475">Concerns have been raised that the unintended consequence of the warnings will be overly restricted use of antidepressants among those who benefit the most and, hence, an increase in suicidality that the warning seeks to prevent.</Para><Para id="_476">In summary, the risks-benefits-alternatives principle favors appropriate use of antidepressants with careful monitoring for suicidality. None of the studies that led to the boxed warning included or focused on patients being treated for cancer. Clinical experience and results of small clinical trials suggest that antidepressants can be safely administered to adult cancer patients, although there are no large controlled clinical trials to support this position. When antidepressants are prescribed for patients with cancer, implementation of a careful monitoring plan should be considered by individuals with expertise, and consultation referral made for patients who do not respond as anticipated or who present other concerns.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_74"><Title>Psychotherapy</Title><SummarySection id="_376"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_377">Traditionally, depressive symptomatology was managed with insight-oriented
psychotherapy, which is quite useful for some people with cancer.      For many
other people, these symptoms are best managed with some combination of crisis
intervention, brief supportive psychotherapy, and cognitive-behavioral
techniques.</Para><Para id="_371"> Psychotherapy for depression has been offered in  a variety of forms. Most interventions have been time limited (range, 4–30 hours), have been offered in both individual and small-group formats, and have included a structured educational component about cancer or a specific relaxation component.<Reference refidx="32"/></Para><Para id="_372">Cognitive-behavioral psychotherapy has been one of the most prominent types of therapies studied. Cognitive-behavioral interventions focus on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_604" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Altering specific coping strategies aimed at improving overall adjustment.</ListItem><ListItem>Specific thoughts and their relationship to emotions and behaviors.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_605">Understanding and altering one’s thoughts can change emotional reactions and accompanying behaviors. For example, frequent, intrusive, uncontrollable thoughts about loss, life changes, or death can cause poor concentration and precipitate feelings of sadness, guilt, and worthlessness. In turn, these feelings can result in increased sleep, withdrawal, and isolation. A cognitive-behavioral intervention focuses on the intrusive thoughts, often challenging their accuracy or rationality and noting specific patterns of cognitive distortions. Simultaneously, patients develop specific cognitive coping strategies that are designed to alter emotional reactions and accompanying behaviors. The result is improved coping, enhanced adjustment, and better overall quality of life.</Para><Para id="_378">Other goals of psychotherapy include:<Reference refidx="33"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="37"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_606" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> Enhancing coping skills.</ListItem><ListItem>Directly reducing distress.</ListItem><ListItem> Improving problem-solving skills.</ListItem><ListItem>Mobilizing support.</ListItem><ListItem>Reshaping negative or self-defeating thoughts.</ListItem><ListItem>Developing a close personal bond with a knowledgeable, empathic health care provider.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_607">  Consultation with a cleric or a member of a pastoral care department may also help some individuals.</Para><Para id="_76">Specific goals of these therapies include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_77" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Assist people with cancer and their families by answering questions about the illness and its treatment, clarifying information, correcting misunderstandings, giving reassurance, and normalizing responses to the illness and its effect on patients’ families. Explore the present situation with the patient and how it relates to his or her previous experiences with cancer.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Assist with problem solving, bolster the patient’s usual adaptive defenses, and help the patient and family develop further supportive and adaptive coping mechanisms. Identify maladaptive coping mechanisms and assist the family in developing alternative coping strategies. Explore areas of related stressors (e.g., family role and lifestyle changes), and encourage family members to support and share concerns with each other.</ListItem>
<ListItem>When the focus of treatment changes from cure to palliation, strongly reinforce that, although curative treatment has ended, the team will aggressively treat symptoms as part of the palliation plan; the patient and family will not be abandoned; and staff members will work very hard to maintain comfort, control pain, and maintain the dignity of the patient and his or her family members.</ListItem>
</ItemizedList><Para id="_78">Cancer support groups can be useful adjunctive therapies in the treatment of
cancer patients.<Reference refidx="38"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]    Support group
interventions have demonstrated the following:<Reference refidx="39"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_700" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Significant effects on mood disturbance.</ListItem><ListItem>Use of
positive coping strategies.</ListItem><ListItem> Improvement in quality of life.</ListItem><ListItem>Positive immune
responses.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_701">Support groups can be found through the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancersupportcommunity.org/">Cancer Support Community</ExternalRef>,
the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/">American Cancer Society</ExternalRef>, and many other community resources, including
the social work departments of medical centers and hospitals.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_380"><Title>Empirical studies of the efficacy of psychotherapy</Title><Para id="_373">

Psychotherapy as a treatment for depression in the general adult mental health population has been extensively researched and found to be effective.<Reference refidx="40"/>  Reviews have also concluded that psychotherapy is an effective intervention for cancer patients experiencing depression.<Reference refidx="41"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="32"/> In studies designed to prevent the occurrence of depression (i.e., patients not selected because of their depressive symptoms), intervention effects are positive, although small to moderate effect sizes have been reported (effect size range, 0.19–0.54).<Reference refidx="32"/>  However, in those studies in which patients were intentionally selected because they exhibited depressive symptoms, intervention effects were strong (effect size, 0.94).<Reference refidx="41"/> An effect size of 0.94 indicates that the average patient in the treatment group was advantaged, compared with approximately 82% of patients in the control group.  </Para><Para id="_381">One well-designed randomized clinical trial of a cognitive-behavioral intervention for depressed cancer patients investigated the effect of problem-solving training on symptoms of depression.<Reference refidx="42"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] The intervention consisted of 10 1.5-hour weekly individual psychotherapy sessions focused on training to become an effective problem solver. Problem-solving tasks were emphasized, including skills in the following aspects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_702" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Better defining and formulating the nature of problems.</ListItem><ListItem>Generating a wide range of alternative solutions.</ListItem><ListItem>Systematically evaluating consequences of a solution while deciding on an optimal one.</ListItem><ListItem>Evaluating outcome after solution implementation.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_703">Between-session homework with tasks relevant to each step was assigned, and patients were provided with a written manual and encouraged to refer to it as problems arose. One hundred thirty-two adult cancer patients were randomly assigned to the problem-solving treatment (PST), PST with a significant other, or a wait-list control. Overall results showed that PST (alone or with a significant other) improved problem-solving abilities and clinically significantly decreased symptoms of depression.<Reference refidx="42"/></Para><Para id="_752">A potential intervention to address depression in survivors is mindfulness meditation and survivorship education. In a randomized clinical trial of 247 younger breast cancer survivors, compared with a wait-list control group, both groups had decreased depression from preintervention to postintervention.<Reference refidx="43"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] Notably, the improvements were maintained 6 months postintervention. The mindfulness meditation group also showed improvements that were sustained over 6 months for fatigue, insomnia, and vasomotor symptoms (e.g., hot flashes and night sweats). These types of interventions may be beneficial for other cancer populations.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_769"><Title>Physical Activity</Title><Para id="_770">Physical activity for  the management of depressive symptoms in individuals who completed treatment for breast cancer was studied in the Physical Activity for Cancer Survivors (PACES) randomized clinical trial. The trial included 336 participants, 3 months to 10 years after treatment for breast cancer, who were assessed to be insufficiently physically active (i.e., &lt;150 min/wk engagement in moderate-to-vigorous physical activity).<Reference refidx="44"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] Using the block randomization method, participants were assigned into one of 16 cohorts, whose interventions ranged from receiving physical activity educational materials only (all participants) to the full cadre of PACES intervention components: educational materials, active living every day (ALED; 12 biweekly educational sessions), facility access (i.e., 6-month local fitness facility membership), Fitbit wearable device, and supervised exercise. A linear mixed-effects model using the self-rate Quick Inventory of Depression Symptomology as the outcome measure was used in the analyses. Depressive symptoms improved over time for all participants. The greatest improvement was for the ALED intervention component. This study provides some evidence that engagement in physical activity, especially through a supportive educational program such as ALED, may benefit individuals with depressive symptoms who have completed treatment for breast cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_29_sid_3"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_29_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11136266" MedlineID="21012245">Whooley MA, Simon GE: Managing depression in medical outpatients. N Engl J Med 343 (26): 1942-50, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="22767203">Hart SL, Hoyt MA, Diefenbach M, et al.: Meta-analysis of efficacy of interventions for elevated depressive symptoms in adults diagnosed with cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst 104 (13): 990-1004, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25370277">Couper JW, Pollard AC, Clifton DA: Depression and cancer. Med J Aust 199 (S6): S13-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28665542">Singer S, Danker H, Roick J, et al.: Effects of stepped psychooncological care on referral to psychosocial services and emotional well-being in cancer patients: A cluster-randomized phase III trial. Psychooncology 26 (10): 1675-1683, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="36083407">Haque R, Reading S, Irwin MR, et al.: Antidepressant medication use and prostate cancer recurrence in men with depressive disorders. Cancer Causes Control 33 (11): 1363-1372, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15263050">Fisch M: Treatment of depression in cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr  (32): 105-11, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="23679841">Laoutidis ZG, Mathiak K: Antidepressants in the treatment of depression/depressive symptoms in cancer patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Psychiatry 13: 140, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="17548243">Stockler MR, O'Connell R, Nowak AK, et al.: Effect of sertraline on symptoms and survival in patients with advanced cancer, but without major depression: a placebo-controlled double-blind randomised trial. Lancet Oncol 8 (7): 603-12, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12720073">Ashbury FD, Madlensky L, Raich P, et al.: Antidepressant prescribing in community cancer care. Support Care Cancer 11 (5): 278-85, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="10787370" MedlineID="20236988">Williams JW, Mulrow CD, Chiquette E, et al.: A systematic review of newer pharmacotherapies for depression in adults: evidence report summary. Ann Intern Med 132 (9): 743-56, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="11">Fisch MJ, Callahan CM, Kesterson JG, et al.: The use of an electronic patient record system to identify advanced cancer patients and antidepressant drug use. J Palliat Med  2 (4): 403-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="30082486">Wong RL, El-Jawahri A, D'Arpino SM, et al.: Use of Antidepressant Medications Moderates the Relationship Between Depressive Symptoms and Hospital Length of Stay in Patients with Advanced Cancer. Oncologist 24 (1): 117-124, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="22147715">Gartlehner G, Hansen RA, Morgan LC, et al.: Comparative benefits and harms of second-generation antidepressants for treating major depressive disorder: an updated meta-analysis. Ann Intern Med 155 (11): 772-85, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="11347722">Haddad PM: Antidepressant discontinuation syndromes. Drug Saf 24 (3): 183-97, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="23145389">Iqbal MM, Basil MJ, Kaplan J, et al.: Overview of serotonin syndrome. Ann Clin Psychiatry 24 (4): 310-8, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="16">Lexicomp Online. Hudson, Ohio: Lexi-Comp, Inc., 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.wolterskluwer.com/en/solutions/uptodate/enterprise/lexidrug">Available online with subscription</ExternalRef>. Last accessed Jan. 15, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="17">GlaxoSmithKline, LLC: Wellbutrin (bupropion hydrochloride) immediate-release tablets. Research Triangle Park, NC: GlaxoSmithKline, LLC, 2022. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2011/018644s043lbl.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed June 27, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="18">GlaxoSmithKline, LLC: Wellbutrin (bupropion hydrochloride) sustained-release (SR) tablets. Research Triangle Park, NC: GlaxoSmithKline, LLC, 2022. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2022/020358s066lbl.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed June 27, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="19">Bausch Health US, LLC: Wellbutrin (bupropion hydrochloride) extended-release (XL) tablets. Bridgewater, NJ: Bausch Health US, LLC, 2022. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2022/021515s044lbl.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed June 27, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="3134343" MedlineID="88273040">Horne RL, Ferguson JM, Pope HG, et al.: Treatment of bulimia with bupropion: a multicenter controlled trial. J Clin Psychiatry 49 (7): 262-6, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="25539871">Epstein I, Szpindel I, Katzman MA: Pharmacological approaches to manage persistent symptoms of major depressive disorder: rationale and therapeutic strategies. Psychiatry Res 220 (Suppl 1): S15-33, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="11712722" MedlineID="21569122">Homsi J, Nelson KA, Sarhill N, et al.: A phase II study of methylphenidate for depression in advanced cancer. Am J Hosp Palliat Care 18 (6): 403-7, 2001 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="22648236">Gartlehner G, Thaler K, Hill S, et al.: How should primary care doctors select which antidepressants to administer? Curr Psychiatry Rep 14 (4): 360-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="24716500">Grassi L, Caruso R, Hammelef K, et al.: Efficacy and safety of pharmacotherapy in cancer-related psychiatric disorders across the trajectory of cancer care: a review. Int Rev Psychiatry 26 (1): 44-62, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="26834969">Wilson E, Lader M: A review of the management of antidepressant discontinuation symptoms. Ther Adv Psychopharmacol 5 (6): 357-68, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="23459282">Ogle NR, Akkerman SR: Guidance for the discontinuation or switching of antidepressant therapies in adults. J Pharm Pract 26 (4): 389-96, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="27346915">Keks N, Hope J, Keogh S: Switching and stopping antidepressants. Aust Prescr 39 (3): 76-83, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="11274622" MedlineID="21146521">Musselman DL, Lawson DH, Gumnick JF, et al.: Paroxetine for the prevention of depression induced by high-dose interferon alfa. N Engl J Med 344 (13): 961-6, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="29">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: Suicidality in Children and Adolescents Being Treated With Antidepressant Medications. Rockville, Md: Food and Drug Administration, Center for Drug Evaluation and Research, 2018. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket-drug-safety-information-patients-and-providers/suicidality-children-and-adolescents-being-treated-antidepressant-medications">Available online.</ExternalRef> Last accessed June 27, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="16520440">Hammad TA, Laughren T, Racoosin J: Suicidality in pediatric patients treated with antidepressant drugs. Arch Gen Psychiatry 63 (3): 332-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="17440145">Bridge JA, Iyengar S, Salary CB, et al.: Clinical response and risk for reported suicidal ideation and suicide attempts in pediatric antidepressant treatment: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. JAMA 297 (15): 1683-96, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="11817494">Barsevick AM, Sweeney C, Haney E, et al.: A systematic qualitative analysis of psychoeducational interventions for depression in patients with cancer. Oncol Nurs Forum 29 (1): 73-84; quiz 85-7, 2002 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="3966583" MedlineID="85094657">Forester B, Kornfeld DS, Fleiss JL: Psychotherapy during radiotherapy: effects on emotional and physical distress. Am J Psychiatry 142 (1): 22-7, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="2033413" MedlineID="91237385">Holland JC, Morrow GR, Schmale A, et al.: A randomized clinical trial of alprazolam versus progressive muscle relaxation in cancer patients with anxiety and depressive symptoms. J Clin Oncol 9 (6): 1004-11, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="1472184" MedlineID="92240127">Greer S, Moorey S, Baruch JD, et al.: Adjuvant psychological therapy for patients with cancer: a prospective randomised trial. BMJ 304 (6828): 675-80, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="6489742" MedlineID="85028390">Worden JW, Weisman AD: Preventive psychosocial intervention with newly diagnosed cancer patients. Gen Hosp Psychiatry 6 (4): 243-9, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="9190090" MedlineID="97333985">Lovejoy NC, Matteis M: Cognitive-behavioral interventions to manage depression in patients with cancer: research and theoretical initiatives. Cancer Nurs 20 (3): 155-67, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="11722855" MedlineID="21580372">Montazeri A, Jarvandi S, Haghighat S, et al.: Anxiety and depression in breast cancer patients before and after participation in a cancer support group. Patient Educ Couns 45 (3): 195-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="8357293" MedlineID="93363040">Fawzy FI, Fawzy NW, Hyun CS, et al.: Malignant melanoma. Effects of an early structured psychiatric intervention, coping, and affective state on recurrence and survival 6 years later. Arch Gen Psychiatry 50 (9): 681-9, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="40">Lambert MJ, Ogles BM: The efficacy and effectiveness of psychotherapy. In: Lambert MJ: Bergin and Garfield's Handbook of Psychotherapy and Behavior Change. 5th ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons Inc, 2004, pp 139-93.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="10468295">Sheard T, Maguire P: The effect of psychological interventions on anxiety and depression in cancer patients: results of two meta-analyses. Br J Cancer 80 (11): 1770-80, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="14622079">Nezu AM, Nezu CM, Felgoise SH, et al.: Project Genesis: assessing the efficacy of problem-solving therapy for distressed adult cancer patients. J Consult Clin Psychol 71 (6): 1036-48, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="34406839">Bower JE, Partridge AH, Wolff AC, et al.: Targeting Depressive Symptoms in Younger Breast Cancer Survivors: The Pathways to Wellness Randomized Controlled Trial of Mindfulness Meditation and Survivorship Education. J Clin Oncol 39 (31): 3473-3484, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="37081460">Rethorst CD, Carmody TJ, Argenbright KE, et al.: Considering depression as a secondary outcome in the optimization of physical activity interventions for breast cancer survivors in the PACES trial: a factorial randomized controlled trial. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act 20 (1): 47, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_98"><Title>Suicide Risk in Cancer Patients</Title><SummarySection id="_99"><Title>Demographics and Statistics</Title><Para id="_643">Epidemiological studies conducted across several countries indicate that cancer is a risk factor for suicide.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>] One retrospective cohort study (N = 3,594,750) found that patients with cancer had nearly twice the incidence of suicide as the general population.<Reference refidx="1"/> Another study (N = 6,754,704) found suicide rates three times higher than in the general population, and up to ten times higher in people with cancers with poorer prognosis, e.g., pancreatic cancer.<Reference refidx="4"/> Increased rates of suicidal ideation, suicidal behaviors, and suicide attempts have been documented in patients with cancer compared with the general population.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> The actual incidence of suicide in cancer patients is probably underestimated because there may be reluctance to report death by suicide in these circumstances and because of methodological issues related to the validity of suicide statistics.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_755">It is important to distinguish among suicidal ideation, attempted suicide, and actual suicide in assessing patients at greatest risk. Suicidal ideation is loosely defined as having thoughts, ideas, contemplation, wishes, and preoccupation with death and suicide. Some patients may have passive suicidal ideation, which is a general wish to end one’s life without an actual plan. A suicidal attempt is a planned and initiated suicide that does not result in death. An actual suicide is death through self-inflicted injury.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_644">Certain clinical and sociodemographic risk factors for suicide have been identified in patients with cancer.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="9"/> </Para><SummarySection id="_786"><Title>Gender</Title><Para id="_787">As in the general population, suicide risk is higher in male patients with cancer than in female patients.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>] In adolescents and young adults (AYAs), however, suicide risk is higher in female patients, according to a study using Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program data.<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]  Risk of suicide was measured by calculating the standardized mortality ratio (SMR) and odds ratio (OR). Specifically, the SMR is a percentage of the number of deaths (by suicide in this analysis) among the expected age- and sex-specific rates of death in a standard population. The OR was calculated for demographic and clinical factors associated with actual suicides in the AYAs.  Of note, actual suicides were greater among male AYAs, consistent with the adult population.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_788"><Title>Age and marital status</Title><Para id="_789">Older age is another significant risk factor for suicide in patients with cancer. One group of investigators found that suicide risk increased with age, with older men at the highest risk.<Reference refidx="1"/> This study found that the age-adjusted suicide rate was 52.4 per 100,000 person-years among patients aged 80 to 84 years, compared with 22.0 per 100,000 person-years for the same age group in the general population. Notably, the suicide rate for men with cancer in this age group was substantially higher (100.3 per 100,000 person-years) than the suicide rate for women. Race and marital status also played an important role. Single, divorced, or widowed White men had a higher suicide risk than other patient populations.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_790"><Title>Social and structural health determinants</Title><Para id="_791">Suicide risk also differs by social and structural health determinants. An investigation of more than 5.3 million individuals with cancer across 635 counties included in the SEER 18 database found that among the 6,357 of these individuals who died of suicide, the SMR of suicide among those in the lowest-income counties, compared with those in the highest-income counties, was significantly higher (SMR, 1.94; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.76–2.13 vs. SMR, 1.30; 95% CI, 1.26–1.34).<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>] Similarly, compared with individuals with cancer in urban counties (SMR, 1.35; 95% CI, 1.32–1.39), those in rural counties had a higher SMR of 1.81 (95% CI, 1.70–1.92). In addition, the suicide rates among individuals with cancer were higher in counties that had lower educational levels, greater unemployment rates, and a higher percentage of Black residents.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_792"><Title>Time since diagnosis</Title><Para id="_793">Another consistent risk factor is related to the time since diagnosis. Studies have consistently found higher risk of suicide in the first year after diagnosis, especially in the first 6 months.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> Generally, this risk declines over time. However, for certain cancer types, there is evidence of increased long-term suicide risk many years after the diagnosis.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_794">Poorer prognosis, nonlocalized disease, and aggressive or advanced cancer with a survival rate of fewer than 5 years have been found to be closely associated with higher suicide risk early after cancer diagnosis, with an even greater risk in populations with higher baseline risk factors (male, White race, aged 60 years and older).<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_795"><Title>Cancer types</Title><Para id="_796">Certain cancer types have been associated with higher suicide risk, including the following:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_797" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Pancreatic cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Head and neck cancer.</ListItem><ListItem> Bladder cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Lung cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancers of the upper digestive tract.</ListItem><ListItem>Brain cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Cervical cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_798">In addition, veteran survivors with head and neck cancer are at a particularly high risk for suicide. In a study of 7,803 U.S. veteran survivors of head and neck cancer (98.4% male; mean age, 65 years), the rate of suicidal self-directed violence was 922.7 per 100,000.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>] The rate of death by suicide was 653.6 per 100,000. These rates far exceed those associated with male sex and older age.<Reference refidx="1"/> Veterans treated for head and neck cancer should be screened for suicidal risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_799"><Title>Comorbidities</Title><Para id="_800">Certain comorbidities have also been associated with higher suicide risk, including the following:<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_801" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Substance use disorder.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer-related pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Comorbid psychiatric illness, specifically depression and anxiety.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_802">In a study of Japanese patients (n = 220) who had cancer and who were diagnosed with major depression after being referred for psychiatric consultation, approximately 50% reported suicidal ideation. In a retrospective analysis of predictors of suicidal ideation, researchers found that those with more symptoms of major depression and poorer physical functioning were significantly more likely to report suicidal ideation.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_803"><Title>Summary of Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_804">Risk factors for suicide in the cancer population are as follows:<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_805" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Sociodemographic factors:<ItemizedList id="_806" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Male sex.</ListItem><ListItem>Older age.</ListItem><ListItem>Single, divorced,  or widowed status.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Medical factors:<ItemizedList id="_807" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Advanced-stage, nonlocalized, or aggressive disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Poor prognosis (survival rate &lt;5 years).</ListItem><ListItem>Recent cancer diagnosis (highest risk within 3–5 months after diagnosis).</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer site such as prostate, lung, head and neck, and pancreas.</ListItem><ListItem>Physical symptoms such as uncontrollable pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Decreased function and performance status.</ListItem><ListItem>Inadequately controlled pain.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Psychiatric and psychosocial factors:<ItemizedList id="_808" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Comorbid depression or anxiety.</ListItem><ListItem>Feelings of hopelessness.</ListItem><ListItem>Demoralization.</ListItem><ListItem>Aggression; lack of therapeutic alliance with treatment team.</ListItem><ListItem>Preexisting psychopathology.</ListItem><ListItem>Comorbid substance use.</ListItem><ListItem>History of suicide attempts.</ListItem><ListItem>Family history of suicides.</ListItem><ListItem>Poor social support.</ListItem><ListItem>Loss of independence and feeling of being a burden; associated guilt.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18695257">Misono S, Weiss NS, Fann JR, et al.: Incidence of suicide in persons with cancer. J Clin Oncol 26 (29): 4731-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="17018788">Schairer C, Brown LM, Chen BE, et al.: Suicide after breast cancer: an international population-based study of 723,810 women. J Natl Cancer Inst 98 (19): 1416-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="36662522">Hu X, Ma J, Jemal A, et al.: Suicide Risk Among Individuals Diagnosed With Cancer in the US, 2000-2016. JAMA Netw Open 6 (1): e2251863, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="38018695">Kinslow CJ, Kumar P, Olfson M, et al.: Prognosis and risk of suicide after cancer diagnosis. Cancer 130 (4): 588-596, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18050260">Rasic DT, Belik SL, Bolton JM, et al.: Cancer, mental disorders, suicidal ideation and attempts in a large community sample. Psychooncology 17 (7): 660-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="10826468">Druss B, Pincus H: Suicidal ideation and suicide attempts in general medical illnesses. Arch Intern Med 160 (10): 1522-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="15483032">Hem E, Loge JH, Haldorsen T, et al.: Suicide risk in cancer patients from 1960 to 1999. J Clin Oncol 22 (20): 4209-16, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="8">Harmer B, Lee S, Rizvi A: Suicidal Ideation. In: StatPearls [Internet]. StatPearls Publishing, 2024, [no pagination]. <ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33351435/">Available online.</ExternalRef> Last accessed July 1, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="17053045">Kendal WS: Suicide and cancer: a gender-comparative study. Ann Oncol 18 (2): 381-7, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="34586755">Heynemann S, Thompson K, Moncur D, et al.: Risk factors associated with suicide in adolescents and young adults (AYA) with cancer. Cancer Med 10 (20): 7339-7346, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="15728750">Llorente MD, Burke M, Gregory GR, et al.: Prostate cancer: a significant risk factor for late-life suicide. Am J Geriatr Psychiatry 13 (3): 195-201, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="34665238">Suk R, Hong YR, Wasserman RM, et al.: Analysis of Suicide After Cancer Diagnosis by US County-Level Income and Rural vs Urban Designation, 2000-2016. JAMA Netw Open 4 (10): e2129913, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="15756279">Yousaf U, Christensen ML, Engholm G, et al.: Suicides among Danish cancer patients 1971-1999. Br J Cancer 92 (6): 995-1000, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="14522382">Innos K, Rahu K, Rahu M, et al.: Suicides among cancer patients in Estonia: a population-based study. Eur J Cancer 39 (15): 2223-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="24169626">Lu D, Fall K, Sparén P, et al.: Suicide and suicide attempt after a cancer diagnosis among young individuals. Ann Oncol 24 (12): 3112-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="34617963">Nugent SM, Morasco BJ, Handley R, et al.: Risk of Suicidal Self-directed Violence Among US Veteran Survivors of Head and Neck Cancer. JAMA Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 147 (11): 981-989, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="36633854">Potter AL, Haridas C, Neumann K, et al.: Incidence, Timing, and Factors Associated With Suicide Among Patients Undergoing Surgery for Cancer in the US. JAMA Oncol 9 (3): 308-315, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="8988260" MedlineID="97142010">Henriksson MM, Isometsä ET, Hietanen PS, et al.: Mental disorders in cancer suicides. J Affect Disord 36 (1-2): 11-20, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="12578898">Akechi T, Nakano T, Akizuki N, et al.: Clinical factors associated with suicidality in cancer patients. Jpn J Clin Oncol 32 (12): 506-11, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="11239127" MedlineID="21137618">Akechi T, Okamura H, Yamawaki S, et al.: Why do some cancer patients with depression desire an early death and others do not? Psychosomatics 42 (2): 141-5, 2001 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="21946906">Anguiano L, Mayer DK, Piven ML, et al.: A literature review of suicide in cancer patients. Cancer Nurs 35 (4): E14-26, 2012 Jul-Aug.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_236"><Title>Assessment and Management of Suicidal Patients</Title><SummarySection id="_262"><Title>Assessment</Title><Para id="_655">Suicide assessment occurs frequently along the cancer continuum. Components of suicide assessment include the following:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_708" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Evaluation of <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_803" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">risk factors</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Patient’s mental state.</ListItem><ListItem>Social context.</ListItem><ListItem>Nonverbal signs of extreme distress or depression (such as poor eye contact, agitation, or excessive slowing of speech and movement).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_709">  Hopelessness is a powerful predictor of suicidal ideation and completed suicides in the general population and in cancer patients.<Reference refidx="4"/>  Certain suicide screening tools such as the following are used to screen for suicide risk in the general population and in patients with mental illness:<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_710" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The Beck Hopelessness Scale.</ListItem><ListItem>The Suicide Intent Scale.</ListItem><ListItem>The Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_711"> However, these tools are not validated for cancer patients.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_656">Other complicating factors in suicide assessment include the demoralization syndrome and desire for hastened death.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> The concept of demoralization syndrome involves persistent inability to cope with feelings of hopelessness, helplessness, and loss of meaning of life.<Reference refidx="8"/> Demoralization syndrome can be assessed using the Demoralization Scale.<Reference refidx="9"/> Evidence suggests that demoralization syndrome can be present with or without depression symptomatology in cancer patients.<Reference refidx="10"/> A study conducted in Taiwanese patients (n = 200) found that demoralization was more predictive of suicidal ideation than was depression symptomatology.<Reference refidx="6"/> The study found that the loss of meaning was a critical factor in the effect of demoralization on suicidal ideation.</Para><Para id="_657">The relationships between suicidal ideation and the desire for hastened death, requests for physician-assisted suicide and/or euthanasia are complex and poorly understood.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="11"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000543592#_242" url="/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/last-days-hp-pdq">Requests for Hastened Death</SummaryRef> section in Last Days of Life. The desire for hastened death involves a hope for death to come quickly. Such a desire can be:<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_712" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Psychopathological, as an expression of despair with an exit plan (idea of suicide).</ListItem><ListItem>A socially driven desire to not be a burden to family or friends.</ListItem><ListItem>A healthy process of closure, i.e., a manifestation of letting go.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_263">Patients who are found to be suicidal require careful further assessment (see  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_362" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Table 5</SummaryRef>).  The risk of suicide increases if the
patient reports ideation (i.e., thoughts of suicide) plus a plan (i.e.,
description of the means).  Risk continues to increase to the extent that the
plan is lethal.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Lethality is determined by an assessment of how likely death
would follow, if the reported plan were carried out.</Para><Para id="_609">Factors to consider in
assessing lethality include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_610" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Availability of the means.</ListItem><ListItem>Reversibility of the
means. (Once begun, can it be stopped?)</ListItem><ListItem>Proximity of  help.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_611">For the cancer
patient reporting suicidal ideation, it is essential to determine whether the
underlying cause is the following:<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_713" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>A depressive illness.</ListItem><ListItem>A desire for hastened death.</ListItem><ListItem>An expression of the desire to have
ultimate control over intolerable symptoms.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_714">Prompt identification and
treatment of major depression is essential in lowering the risk of suicide in
cancer patients.  Risk factors, particularly hopelessness (which is an even
stronger predictive factor for suicidal ideation and completed suicides than is depression), requires careful assessment.<Reference refidx="4"/>  The assessment of hopelessness is not straightforward in the
patient with advanced disease with no hope of cure.  It is important to assess
the underlying reasons for hopelessness, which may be related to poor symptom
management, fears of painful death, or feelings of abandonment.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_264">Establishing rapport is of prime importance in working with suicidal cancer
patients as it serves as the foundation for other interventions.  The clinician
must believe that talking about suicide will not cause the patient to attempt
suicide.  On the contrary, talking about suicide legitimizes this concern and
permits patients to describe their feelings and fears, providing a sense of
control.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  A supportive therapeutic relationship is maintained, which
conveys the attitude that much can be done to alleviate emotional and physical
pain.  For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062738" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-hp-pdq">Cancer Pain</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_613">A crisis
intervention–oriented psychotherapeutic approach that
mobilizes as much of a patient’s support system as possible is initiated.<Reference refidx="2"/> Contributing
symptoms (e.g., pain) are aggressively controlled and depression,
psychosis, agitation, and underlying causes of delirium are treated.<Reference refidx="2"/> 
<Reference refidx="7"/>  These problems
are most frequently managed in the medical hospital or at home.  Although
uncommon, psychiatric hospitalization can be helpful when there is a clear
indication and the patient is medically stable.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Table id="_362"><Title>Table 5.  Suggested Questions for the Assessment of
                 Suicidal Symptoms in People With Cancer<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="66.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Questions </entry><entry> Assessment</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Roth et al.<Reference refidx="15"/>
</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Most people with cancer have passing              
thoughts about suicide such as, “I might         
do something if it gets bad enough.” </entry><entry>Acknowledge normality by opening with a statement recognizing that a discussion 
                                                  does not enhance risk</entry></Row><Row><entry>Have you ever had thoughts like that?                    
Any thoughts of not wanting to live or
wishing your illness might hasten your death?</entry><entry> Level of risk</entry></Row><Row><entry>Do you have thoughts of suicide?                          
Have you thought about how you would do it?
Do you intend to harm yourself?</entry><entry>Level of risk</entry></Row><Row><entry>Have you ever been depressed or made a suicide           
attempt?</entry><entry> History</entry></Row><Row><entry>Have you ever been treated for other psychiatric          
problems, or have you been psychiatrically
hospitalized before getting diagnosed with cancer?</entry><entry>History</entry></Row><Row><entry>Have you had a problem with alcohol or drugs? </entry><entry>Substance dependence</entry></Row><Row><entry>Have you lost anyone close to you recently?             
   (Family, friends, others with cancer.)</entry><entry>  Bereavement</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_265"><Title>Management</Title><Para id="_266">In clinical practice, the goal of management of suicidal patients is to attempt
to prevent suicide that is driven by desperation due to poorly controlled
symptoms.  Prolonged suffering due to poorly controlled symptoms can lead to
such desperation.  Thus, effective symptom management is critical to decrease
psychological distress in suicidal cancer patients.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  Patients close to the
end of life may be unable to maintain a wakeful state without high levels of
emotional or physical pain.  This frequently leads to suicidal thoughts or
requests for aid in dying.  Such patients may require sedation to ease their
distress.</Para><Para id="_267">At times, it may be important  to limit access to potentially lethal medications for patients considered at risk of suicide.  When potentially lethal medications are limited, it is important to weigh the impact on symptom management against the impact on suicide risk because  poorly controlled symptoms may contribute to risk.  Furthermore, suicidal patients will often have other means available to complete suicide attempts and these must also be evaluated.  Strategies to lessen suicidal risk include frequent contact to reassess suicidal risk and symptom control, as well as regular delivery of limited quantities of medications  facilitating rapid dose titration for effective management of poorly controlled symptoms when necessary.  For patients receiving parenteral or intrathecal opioids, programmable pumps with limited access to programming and locked, inaccessible cartridges may provide an element of safety.</Para><Para id="_268">Strategies to lessen suicide risk in  cancer patients include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_269" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Make a referral to a psychologist or other mental health professional.</ListItem><ListItem>Use medications that work rapidly to alleviate distress (e.g., a
benzodiazepine for anxiety or a stimulant for fatigue) while waiting for
the clinical effects from antidepressant therapy.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Pay scrupulous attention to symptom management.</ListItem><ListItem>Limit access as appropriate to quantities of medications that are lethal
in overdose and ensure that the family has a home-use naloxone kit in states/locations where available.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Maintain frequent contact with and closely observe the patient.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Avoid having the patient spend long periods of time alone.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Mobilize support for the patient.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Carefully assess the patient's psychological responses at each crisis point
over the course of the disease.</ListItem>
</ItemizedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20605728">Spoletini I, Gianni W, Caltagirone C, et al.: Suicide and cancer: where do we go from here? Crit Rev Oncol Hematol 78 (3): 206-19, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="27713849">K Hughes M: Suicide Screening in the Oncology Population. J Adv Pract Oncol 7 (1): 101-104, 2016 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23886963">Morriss R, Kapur N, Byng R: Assessing risk of suicide or self harm in adults. BMJ 347: f4572, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="16643692">Abbey JG, Rosenfeld B, Pessin H, et al.: Hopelessness at the end of life: the utility of the hopelessness scale with terminally ill cancer patients. Br J Health Psychol 11 (Pt 2): 173-83, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="26552947">Bolton JM, Gunnell D, Turecki G: Suicide risk assessment and intervention in people with mental illness. BMJ 351: h4978, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24935648">Fang CK, Chang MC, Chen PJ, et al.: A correlational study of suicidal ideation with psychological distress, depression, and demoralization in patients with cancer. Support Care Cancer 22 (12): 3165-74, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="23372105">Cooke L, Gotto J, Mayorga L, et al.: What do I say? Suicide assessment and management. Clin J Oncol Nurs 17 (1): E1-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12406115">Clarke DM, Kissane DW: Demoralization: its phenomenology and importance. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 36 (6): 733-42, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15690829">Kissane DW, Wein S, Love A, et al.: The Demoralization Scale: a report of its development and preliminary validation. J Palliat Care 20 (4): 269-76, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="22120003">Lee CY, Fang CK, Yang YC, et al.: Demoralization syndrome among cancer outpatients in Taiwan. Support Care Cancer 20 (10): 2259-67, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="21946906">Anguiano L, Mayer DK, Piven ML, et al.: A literature review of suicide in cancer patients. Cancer Nurs 35 (4): E14-26, 2012 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11516596">Filiberti A, Ripamonti C, Totis A, et al.: Characteristics of terminal cancer patients who committed suicide during a home palliative care program. J Pain Symptom Manage 22 (1): 544-53, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="19482401">Nissim R, Gagliese L, Rodin G: The desire for hastened death in individuals with advanced cancer: a longitudinal qualitative study. Soc Sci Med 69 (2): 165-71, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Breitbart W, Passik SD: Psychiatric aspects of palliative care. In: Doyle D, Hanks GW, MacDonald N, eds.: Oxford Text Book of Palliative Medicine. Oxford University Press, 1993, pp 609-26.</Citation><Citation idx="15">Roth AJ, Holland JC: Psychiatric complications in cancer patients. In: Brain MC, Carbone PP, eds.: Current Therapy in Hematology-Oncology. 5th ed. Mosby-Year Book, Inc., 1995, pp 609-18.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_243"><Title>Considerations for Pediatric Depression</Title><Para id="_244">Information concerning the incidence of depression in healthy
children is limited.  One study of children seen in a general practice showed that 38% had
problems that required major intervention by a psychiatrist.  Another study
of children aged 7 to 12 years showed a 1.9% incidence of depression.  If
applied to the general population of the United States, these results show that
40,000 12-year-olds are depressed.  Teachers have estimated that as many as 10%
to 15% of their students are depressed.  The Joint Commission on Mental Health
of Children states that 1.4 million children younger than 18 years need immediate help
for disorders such as depression; only one-third of these children receive help
for their disorder.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_245">Most children cope with the emotional upheaval related to cancer and
demonstrate not only evidence of adaptation but positive psychosocial growth
and development.  A minority of children, however, develops the following psychological problems:<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_622" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Depression.</ListItem><ListItem>Anxiety.</ListItem><ListItem>Sleep disturbances.</ListItem><ListItem>Difficulties in
interpersonal relationships.</ListItem><ListItem>Noncompliance with treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_623">These children
require referral to and intervention by a mental health specialist.</Para><Para id="_246">In one of the first studies of depression in childhood cancer, 114 children and
adolescents were studied, and 59% were found to have mild psychiatric
problems.<Reference refidx="3"/>  A study of 17 adolescent and 21 pediatric oncology patients, all
of whom were administered a self-report psychosocial life events inventory,
showed that the adolescent samples had a mean level of depressive symptoms
similar to that of the general population.  The pediatric oncology sample
demonstrated significantly lower depressive symptoms than the general
population.<Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]  Forty-one adolescent survivors of childhood cancer were
assessed using questionnaires and interviews to determine the psychosocial
status of the survivors; most survivors were functioning well, and depression
was rare.<Reference refidx="5"/>
</Para><Para id="_641">A study of long-term cancer survivors and their mothers,
comparing the survivors with a group of 92 healthy children, showed that most former patients were functioning within normal limits.  Not
surprisingly, children with severe late effects had more depressive
symptoms.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]  One researcher looked at the characteristics of psychiatric
consultations in a pediatric cancer center and found that adjustment disorder
was the chief psychosocial diagnosis.  This finding is similar to results
obtained from studies of adult cancer patients.  This study also found that anxiety
reactions were more common in the younger pediatric patients, and depressive
disorders were more common in older patients.<Reference refidx="7"/>  In a study conducted in 1988
with a sample of 30 adolescent cancer patients, the rate of major depression
was not higher than the rate for the population at large.<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]  One review
reported a 17% incidence of depression using the criteria of the <Emphasis>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders,</Emphasis> 3rd edition.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_247">Most cancer survivors demonstrate general resiliency and successful
psychological adjustment to the disease and its treatment.  Despite evidence
for successful adaptation, most studies document psychological difficulties in
a significant subset of cancer survivors.
</Para><SummarySection id="_248"><Title>Assessment and Diagnosis of Pediatric Depression</Title><SummarySection id="_249"><Title>Assessment</Title><Para id="_250">The term <Emphasis>depression</Emphasis> refers to a symptom, a syndrome, a set of psychological
responses, or an illness.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Duration and intensity of the behavioral
manifestation (e.g., sadness) differentiates the symptoms from the disorder. 
For example, a sad affect can be a child’s response to trauma and is usually
of short duration; however, a depressive illness is characterized by long
duration, and is associated with the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_715" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Insomnia.</ListItem><ListItem>Irritability.</ListItem><ListItem>Changes in eating
habits.</ListItem><ListItem>Severe impairment of the child’s scholastic and social adjustment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_716">Depression should be considered whenever any behavior problem persists. 
Depression does not refer to transitory moments of sadness, but rather to a
disorder that affects development and interferes with realization of the
child’s innate potential.<Reference refidx="1"/>
</Para><Para id="_251">Some manifestations of depression in a school-aged child include the following:<Reference refidx="1"/>
</Para><ItemizedList id="_624" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Anorexia.</ListItem><ListItem>
Lethargy.</ListItem><ListItem>Sad affect.</ListItem><ListItem>Aggression.</ListItem><ListItem>Weeping.</ListItem><ListItem>Hyperactivity.</ListItem><ListItem>Somatization.</ListItem><ListItem>Fear of
death.</ListItem><ListItem>Frustration.</ListItem><ListItem> Feelings of sadness or hopelessness.</ListItem><ListItem>Self-criticism.</ListItem><ListItem>Frequent daydreaming.</ListItem><ListItem>Low self-esteem.</ListItem><ListItem>School refusal.</ListItem><ListItem>Learning problems.</ListItem><ListItem>Slow
movements.</ListItem><ListItem>Vacillating hostility toward parents and teachers.</ListItem><ListItem>Loss of
interest in previously pleasurable activities.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_625">Differentiating these symptoms
from behavioral responses to normal developmental stages is important.</Para><Para id="_252">Assessment of depression includes determination of the child’s:<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_626" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Family
situation.</ListItem><ListItem>Level of emotional maturity.</ListItem><ListItem>Ability to
cope with illness and treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Age.</ListItem><ListItem>State of development.</ListItem><ListItem>Previous experience with illness.</ListItem><ListItem>Personal ego strength.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_253">A comprehensive assessment for childhood depression is the basis for accurate
diagnosis and treatment.  Evaluation of the child and family situation focuses
on  the pediatric health history,  behaviors observed by the
practitioner or reported by others (e.g., parents and teachers),  interviews
with the child, and  judicial use of tests such as the Beck Depression
Inventory or the Child Behavior Checklist.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_254"><Title>Diagnosis</Title><Para id="_255">In discussing the diagnosis of childhood depression, experts stress the
importance of understanding childhood depression as an entity distinct from
depression in adults because developmental issues in
childhood are distinctly different from those of adulthood.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><Para id="_256">A model of childhood affective disorders uses the following explicit criteria:<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_282" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Dysphoric mood (children younger than 6 years must also have a sad
facial expression).</ListItem><ListItem>At least 4 of the following signs or symptoms present every
day for a period of at least 2 weeks:<ItemizedList id="_283" Style="dash"><ListItem>Appetite disturbance.</ListItem><ListItem>Insomnia or
hypersomnia.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychomotor agitation or retardation.</ListItem><ListItem>Loss of interest or pleasure in usual activities (children younger
than 6 years must also have signs of apathy).</ListItem><ListItem>Fatigue or loss of energy.</ListItem><ListItem>Feelings of worthlessness,
self-reproach, or excessive, inappropriate guilt.</ListItem><ListItem>Diminished ability to
think or concentrate.</ListItem><ListItem>Recurrent thoughts of death or suicide.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_257"><Title>Management of Pediatric Depression</Title><Para id="_258">Treatment regimens implemented for childhood depression reflect theoretical
models, etiology, and manifestations of the disorder.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Individual and group
psychotherapy are commonly utilized as the primary treatment modality and are
directed at helping the child to master his or her difficulties and to enable
the child to develop in an optimal manner.  Play therapy may be used as a means
of exploring a younger child’s view of himself or herself, the disease, and its
treatment.  The child needs to be helped from the beginning to explore and
understand, at a level appropriate for his or her developmental age, the
diagnosis of cancer and the treatments involved.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_260">

As is the case with depression in adult cancer patients, there are few, if any,
revealing trials of antidepressants in children with cancer.  One author
described rapid clinical response to low doses (&lt;2 mg/kg/d)
of imipramine or amitriptyline for eight depressed children with cancer.<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>] 
Another author described the use of benzodiazepines such as lorazepam,
diazepam, alprazolam, and clonazepam for the treatment of anxiety disorders. 
Trials of benzodiazepines are short term.  These drugs are tapered
slowly when they are discontinued.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><SummarySection id="_259"><Title>Pharmacological management</Title><Para id="_261">The combined use of tricyclic antidepressants and neuroleptics in the
management of three children with severe symptoms of depression and anxiety has
been reported.  The children studied were in the terminal phases of their
disease and were treated with a combination of low-dose amitriptyline and
haloperidol.  Levels of anxiety and depression were decreased, and this
intervention allowed the patients and their families to deal with issues
involved in death and dying.<Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="7133571" MedlineID="83037740">Deuber CM: Depression in the school-aged child: implications for primary care. Nurse Pract 7 (8): 26-30, 68, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2921738" MedlineID="89157378">Kazak AE: Psychological issues in childhood cancer survivors. J Assoc Pediatr Oncol Nurses 6 (1): 15-6, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="495703" MedlineID="80039901">O'Malley JE, Koocher G, Foster D, et al.: Psychiatric sequelae of surviving childhood cancer. Am J Orthopsychiatry 49 (4): 608-16, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="3667512" MedlineID="88032788">Kaplan SL, Busner J, Weinhold C, et al.: Depressive symptoms in children and adolescents with cancer: a longitudinal study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry 26 (5): 782-7, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3228162" MedlineID="89148393">Fritz GK, Williams JR, Amylon M: After treatment ends: psychosocial sequelae in pediatric cancer survivors. Am J Orthopsychiatry 58 (4): 552-61, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2921697" MedlineID="89157263">Greenberg HS, Kazak AE, Meadows AT: Psychologic functioning in 8- to 16-year-old cancer survivors and their parents. J Pediatr 114 (3): 488-93, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3344854" MedlineID="88148152">Rait DS, Jacobsen PB, Lederberg MS, et al.: Characteristics of psychiatric consultations in a pediatric cancer center. Am J Psychiatry 145 (3): 363-4, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="3177808" MedlineID="89023825">Tebbi CK, Bromberg C, Mallon JC: Self-reported depression in adolescent cancer patients. Am J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 10 (3): 185-90, 1988 Fall.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="6982747" MedlineID="83050478">Kashani J, Hakami N: Depression in children and adolescents with malignancy. Can J Psychiatry 27 (6): 474-7, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Archenbach TM, ed.: Manual for the Child Behavior Checklist and Revised Child Behavior Profile. T.M. Achenbach, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="11">American Psychiatric Association: Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-IV-TR. 4th rev. ed. American Psychiatric Association, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="12">Malmquist CP: Major depression in childhood: why don't we know more? Am J Orthopsychiatry  53 (2): 262-8, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="6869596" MedlineID="83253511">Pfefferbaum-Levine B, Kumor K, Cangir A, et al.: Tricyclic antidepressants for children with cancer. Am J Psychiatry 140 (8): 1074-6, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Coffey BJ: Review and update: benzodiazepines in childhood and adolescence. Psychiatr Ann  23 (6): 332-9, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="4019979" MedlineID="85262462">Maisami M, Sohmer BH, Coyle JT: Combined use of tricyclic antidepressants and neuroleptics in the management of terminally ill children: a report on three cases. J Am Acad Child Psychiatry 24 (4): 487-9, 1985.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_183"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (07/25/2024)</Title><Para id="_188">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_783"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_98" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Suicide Risk in Cancer Patients</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_809">Updated Harmer et al. as <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_755" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">reference 8</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_784">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_643" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> about a study that found suicide rates in people with cancer were three times higher than in the general population, and up to ten times higher in people with cancers with poorer prognosis, e.g., pancreatic cancer (cited Kinslow et al. as reference 4).</Para><Para id="_785">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_794" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that poorer prognosis, nonlocalized disease, and aggressive or advanced cancer with a survival rate of fewer than 5 years have been found to be closely associated with higher suicide risk early after cancer diagnosis, with an even greater risk in populations with higher baseline risk factors (male, White race, aged 60 years and older).</Para><Para id="_810">This section was reformatted.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062739#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about cancer-related depression and suicide risk in both the adult and the pediatric populations. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Depression are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Marilyn J. Hammer, PhD, DC, RN, FAAN (Dana-Farber Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Natalie Jacobowski, MD (Nationwide Children's Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Jayesh Kamath, MD, PhD (University of Connecticut Health Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Amy Wachholtz, PhD, MDiv, MS, ABPP (University of Colorado)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000660468" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Depression. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389407]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-07-25</DateLastModified></Summary>
