<Summary id="CDR0000062748" LegacyPDQID="1647"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Pruritus (itching of the skin) can be a complication of cancer or its treatment. Get detailed information about the etiology, assessment, and interventions for pruritus in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq">Pruritus (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-pdq">Pruritus (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000042504">pruritus</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_305">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the pathophysiology and treatment of pruritus. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_306">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>pruritus</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Pruritus (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Pruritus (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Pruritus</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_2">Pruritus is usually an unpleasant sensation that elicits a desire to
scratch, subjectively quantified by intensity, severity, location, and intractability.  It may be proposed that itch is akin to pain because both sensations are thought to be transmitted from the skin to the central nervous system (CNS) through nociceptive small-caliber C nerve fibers.<Reference refidx="1"/> The perception of pruritus, much like the perception of pain, is greatly altered by psychological and CNS factors, accounting for great subjective variability between individuals in perceived pruritus from the same pruritogen.  Because of the
subjective nature of pruritus, the lack of a precise definition, and only recent development of a suitable murine model, pruritus is a disorder that has not been researched
adequately.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_307">This summary will focus on pruritus in the absence of a primary dermatosis, as is often encountered in patients receiving cancer treatment.  However, there may still be significant secondary skin changes noted in the form of lichen simplex chronicus, prurigo nodules, linear excoriations, linear petechiae, or superficial erosions in places the patient can reach to scratch (either with fingernails, back scratchers, or makeshift tools).</Para><Para id="_308">Pruritus is a manifestation of an underlying systemic disease in approximately 10% to 25% of affected individuals.<Reference refidx="3"/>  In a single-institution retrospective review, patients seeking care for pruritus were more likely to have a concomitant diagnosis of cancer than patients without pruritus (odds ratio [OR], 5.76; 95% confidence interval, 5.53–6.00). The OR for malignancy was higher in White patients than in African American patients.<Reference refidx="4"/> Nondermatological conditions that can lead to generalized pruritus include the following:<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_309" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Hepatic, renal, or thyroid dysfunction.</ListItem><ListItem>Malignancies, including lymphoma, chronic lymphocytic leukemia, and cancers of the liver, gallbladder, biliary tract, and skin.<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem><ListItem>Myeloproliferative neoplasms (e.g., polycythemia vera).</ListItem><ListItem>HIV or parasitic infections.</ListItem><ListItem>Neuropsychiatric disorders.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_310">Despite the wide array of diseases that may present with pruritus, a systematic evaluation of the differential using a good history, review of systems, and appropriate blood work will lead to a rational and finite group of etiologies. Then correction of the underlying cause (if possible) and treatment of pruritus may ensue.</Para><Para id="_1_md_4">In this summary, unless otherwise stated, evidence and practice issues as they relate to adults are discussed.  The evidence and application to practice related to children may differ significantly from information related to adults.  When specific information about the care of children is available, it is summarized under its own heading.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11135635">Schmelz M: A neural pathway for itch. Nat Neurosci 4 (1): 9-10, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="29081531">Feng J, Yang P, Mack MR, et al.: Sensory TRP channels contribute differentially to skin inflammation and persistent itch. Nat Commun 8 (1): 980, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Weisshaar E, Fleischer AB Jr, Bernhard JD, et al.: Pruritus and dysesthesia. In: Bolognia JL, Jorizzo JL, Schaffer JV: Dermatology. 3rd ed. Elsevier Saunders, 2012, pp 111-25.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="30217520">Larson VA, Tang O, Ständer S, et al.: Association between itch and cancer in 16,925 patients with pruritus: Experience at a tertiary care center. J Am Acad Dermatol 80 (4): 931-937, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>Etiology and Pathophysiology</Title><Para id="_7">When a primary dermatitis is present, the differential may be narrowed by the history and physical findings, such as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_367" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Stigmata of atopic dermatitis.</ListItem><ListItem>Psoriasis.</ListItem><ListItem>Scabies.</ListItem><ListItem>Allergic contact dermatitis.</ListItem><ListItem>Primary cutaneous lymphoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_368">Biopsy of skin dermatitis may be extraordinarily helpful in this scenario if the etiology is not readily evident from history and physical examination alone.  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062748#_342" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef> provides a list of differential diagnoses for when there is little or no primary dermatitis identifiable.  Where available, the incidence of pruritus in that condition is given.</Para><Table id="_342"><Title>Table 1.  Pruritus Differential With Little or No Primary Dermatitis</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Disease State</entry><entry>Prevalence of Pruritus (%)</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">HMG-CoA = 3-hydroxy-3-methyl-glutaryl–coenzyme A; IgE = immunoglobulin E.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Neoplastic:</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Hodgkin disease</entry><entry>30 <Reference refidx="1"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>– Non-Hodgkin lymphoma</entry><entry>15 <Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>– Leukemias</entry><entry>5 <Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>– Carcinoid syndrome</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Paraproteinemias</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Iron deficiency anemia</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Polycythemia rubra vera</entry><entry>≤50 <Reference refidx="4"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Hyper-IgE syndromes</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Parasitic helminthic infection</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Drug-induced eosinophilia</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Chronic renal insufficiency</entry><entry>57 <Reference refidx="5"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Liver disease:</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Primary biliary cirrhosis</entry><entry>69 <Reference refidx="6"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>– Viral hepatitis infection</entry><entry>15 <Reference refidx="7"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>– Cholestatic disease</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Autoimmune hepatitis</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Thyroid dysfunction:</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Hashimoto thyroiditis</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Hypothyroidism</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Hyperthyroidism</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Medication induced:</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Opioids (codeine, morphine, butorphanol)</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Hydroxyethyl starch</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Antimalarials (chloroquine, hydroxychloroquine, quinacrine)</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– 8-methoxypsoralen</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Beta blockers</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Hormones (estrogens, testosterone, progestins, anabolic steroids)</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Phenothiazines</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– Aspirin</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>– HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Diabetes mellitus</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>HIV infection</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Postherpetic neuralgia</entry><entry>≤60 <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Pregnancy</entry><entry>18 <Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Xerosis</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Psychogenic (somatization, anxiety, depression, neurosis)</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Stroke sequelae</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Multiple sclerosis</entry><entry/></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_8">As evident from the differential, a solid history and physical examination are essential for sorting through the possibilities.  To corroborate the clinical impression, a limited number of laboratory and radiological examinations also may be used to rule in or rule out many of the possibilities.  For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062748#_34" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq">Assessment</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_11">Hypothesized mechanisms of pruritus have been inferred from studies of pain because pain and itching share common molecular and neurophysiological
mechanisms.<Reference refidx="9"/>  Both itch and pain sensations result from the activation of a
network of free nerve endings at the dermal-epidermal junction.  Activation may
be the result of internal or external thermal, mechanical, chemical, or
electrical stimulation.  The cutaneous nerve stimulation is activated or
mediated by several substances, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_311" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Histamine.</ListItem><ListItem> Vasoactive peptides.</ListItem><ListItem>Enkephalins.</ListItem><ListItem>Substance P (a tachykinin that affects smooth muscle).</ListItem><ListItem>Prostaglandins.</ListItem><ListItem>Interleukins (IL-4, IL-13, IL-31).<Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_312">It is believed that nonanatomical factors (such as psychological
stress, tolerance, and presence and intensity of other sensations and/or
distractions) determine itch sensitivity in different regions of the body.</Para><Para id="_12">The itch impulse is transmitted along the same neural pathway as pain impulses,
i.e., traveling from peripheral nerves to the dorsal horn of the spinal cord,
across the cord via the anterior commissure, and ascending along the
spinothalamic tract to the laminar nuclei of the contralateral thalamus. 
Thalamocortical tracts of tertiary neurons are believed to relay the impulse
through the integrating reticular activating system of the thalamus to several
areas of the cerebral cortex.  Factors that are believed to enhance the
sensation of itch include:<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_369" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Dryness of the epidermis and dermis.</ListItem><ListItem>Anoxia of
tissues.</ListItem><ListItem>Dilation of the capillaries.</ListItem><ListItem>Irritating stimuli.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychological
responses.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_13">The motor response of scratching follows the perception of itch.  Scratching is
modulated at the corticothalamic center and is a spinal reflex.  Itching may be relieved for 15 to 25 minutes after scratching.  The mechanism
through which the itch is relieved by scratching is unknown.  It is
hypothesized that scratching generates sensory impulses that break circuits
in the relay areas of the spinal cord.  However, scratching may actually enhance the
sensation of itching, creating a characteristic itch-scratch-itch cycle.  Other
physical stimuli such as vibration, heat, cold, and ultraviolet radiation
diminish itching and increase the release of proteolytic enzymes, potentially
eliciting the itch-scratch-itch cycle.</Para><Para id="_14">A pinprick near or in the same dermatome as an itchy point will abolish the
itch sensation.<Reference refidx="12"/>  It is known that hard scratching may substitute pain for
the itch, and in some instances, the patient might find pain the more tolerable
sensation.  It is thought that spinal modulation of afferent stimuli (Gate
theory) and central mechanisms may play a role in the relief of itch.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_15">Hypothesized pathogenesis of pruritus associated with underlying disease states
is varied.  Biliary, hepatic, renal, and malignant diseases are thought to
produce pruritus through circulating toxic substances.  Histamine released from
circulating basophils and the release of leukopeptidase from white blood cells
may trigger pruritus associated with lymphomas and leukemias.  Elevated blood
levels of kininogen in Hodgkin lymphoma, the release of histamine or bradykinin
precursors from solid tumors, and the release of serotonin in carcinoids may all be
related to pruritus.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_16">People receiving cytotoxic chemotherapy, radiation therapy, and/or biologic response
modifiers for the treatment of malignancy are likely to experience pruritus.  This
population is likely to be exposed to many of the other etiological
factors related to pruritus, ranging from nutrition-related xerosis (dry
skin) to radiation desquamation, chemotherapy-induced and biologic agent–induced side
effects, antibiotic reactions, and other drug sensitivities. Because many of these therapies lead to decreased cell turnover, skin can become thin, atrophic, and dehydrated.  Long-term xerosis may also occur with poor recovery of sweat, sebaceous, and apocrine gland function after a course of cytotoxic therapy.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="6831358">Gobbi PG, Attardo-Parrinello G, Lattanzio G, et al.: Severe pruritus should be a B-symptom in Hodgkin's disease. Cancer 51 (10): 1934-6, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="17642814">Kumar SS, Kuruvilla M, Pai GS, et al.: Cutaneous manifestations of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol 69 (1): 12-5, 2003 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19688144">Weisshaar E, Dalgard F: Epidemiology of itch: adding to the burden of skin morbidity. Acta Derm Venereol 89 (4): 339-50, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11736946">Diehn F, Tefferi A: Pruritus in polycythaemia vera: prevalence, laboratory correlates and management. Br J Haematol 115 (3): 619-21, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="16995341">Duque MI, Thevarajah S, Chan YH, et al.: Uremic pruritus is associated with higher kt/V and serum calcium concentration. Clin Nephrol 66 (3): 184-91, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="18176748">Rishe E, Azarm A, Bergasa NV: Itch in primary biliary cirrhosis: a patients' perspective. Acta Derm Venereol 88 (1): 34-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9779254">Cribier B, Samain F, Vetter D, et al.: Systematic cutaneous examination in hepatitis C virus infected patients. Acta Derm Venereol 78 (5): 355-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="14622691">Oaklander AL, Bowsher D, Galer B, et al.: Herpes zoster itch: preliminary epidemiologic data. J Pain 4 (6): 338-43, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Greaves MW: Pathophysiology of pruritus. In: Fitzpatrick TB, Eisen AZ, Wolff K, et al., eds.: Dermatology in General Medicine. 3rd ed. McGraw-Hill, 1987, Chapter 7, pp 74-78.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="29929604">Erickson S, Nahmias Z, Rosman IS, et al.: Immunomodulating Agents as Antipruritics. Dermatol Clin 36 (3): 325-334, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="11">Abel EA, Farber EM: Malignant cutaneous tumors. In: Rubenstein E, Federman DD, eds.: Scientific American Medicine. Scientific American, Inc, Chapter 2: Dermatology, Section XII, 1-20, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="12">Bernhard JD: Clinical aspects of pruritus. In: Fitzpatrick TB, Eisen AZ, Wolff K, et al., eds.: Dermatology in General Medicine. 3rd ed. McGraw-Hill, 1987, Chapter 7, pp 78-90.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="2199335" MedlineID="90337356">Duncan WC, Fenske NA: Cutaneous signs of internal disease in the elderly. Geriatrics 45 (8): 24-30, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Abel EA, Farber EM: Drug eruptions and urticaria. In: Rubenstein E, Federman DD, eds.: Scientific American Medicine. Scientific American, Inc, Chapter 2: Dermatology, Section VI, 1-11, 1990.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_34"><Title>Assessment</Title><Para id="_35">Pruritus is a symptom, not a diagnosis or disease.  Generalized pruritus should be investigated because of its strong medical significance, as outlined above, particularly if it interferes with daily activities or sleep, and/or is intractable. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062748#_6" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq">Etiology and Pathophysiology</SummaryRef> section. Assessment of pruritus must incorporate an accurate and thorough history and
physical examination.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_36">A history includes the following data:</Para><ItemizedList id="_104" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Location, onset, duration, and intensity of itching.</ListItem><ListItem>Effect on activities of daily living or sleep.</ListItem><ListItem>Factors that relieve and aggravate itching.</ListItem><ListItem>Other family members or pets affected.</ListItem><ListItem>History of pruritus.</ListItem><ListItem>History of malignant disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Current malignant disease and treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Nonmalignant systemic diseases.</ListItem><ListItem>Use of medications (analgesics, antibiotics, and other prescription and nonprescription drugs, including illicit drugs).</ListItem><ListItem>Nutritional and fluid level status.</ListItem><ListItem>Social history (hobbies, occupation, sexual history, and travel).</ListItem><ListItem>Current skin care practices.</ListItem><ListItem>Patient’s emotional state.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_52">A physical examination provides data from an assessment of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_105" Style="bullet"><ListItem>All skin surfaces for signs of infection.</ListItem><ListItem>All skin surfaces for signs of primary dermatitis (e.g., drug reaction, psoriasis, atopic dermatitis, connective tissue disease, and lichen planus).</ListItem><ListItem>All skin surfaces for signs of secondary dermatitis (e.g., macular erythema, dryness, excoriation, linear petechiae, prurigo nodules, and lichen simplex chronicus).</ListItem><ListItem>Environmental factors (temperature, humidity).</ListItem><ListItem>Physical factors (tight, constrictive clothing).</ListItem><ListItem>Skin turgor, texture, color, temperature, and cutaneous neoplasms.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_313">First-line studies should include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_314" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Complete blood count with differential and platelet count.</ListItem><ListItem>Renal function (blood urea nitrogen, serum creatinine).</ListItem><ListItem>Hepatic function (transaminases, alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin).</ListItem><ListItem>Lactate dehydrogenase.</ListItem><ListItem>Thyroid function (thyroid-stimulating hormone, thyroxin levels).</ListItem><ListItem>Chest x-ray.</ListItem><ListItem>Erythrocyte sedimentation rate.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_315">Second-line laboratory studies guided by a review of systems and a physical examination may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_316" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Skin biopsy (routine histology with and without direct immunofluorescence).</ListItem><ListItem>HIV screening.</ListItem><ListItem>Serum iron, total iron-binding capacity, and ferritin.</ListItem><ListItem>Fasting glucose and hemoglobin A1C.</ListItem><ListItem>Parathyroid function (calcium, phosphate, and parathyroid hormone levels).</ListItem><ListItem>Viral hepatitis screening.</ListItem><ListItem>Serum immunoglobulin E levels.</ListItem><ListItem>Serum protein electrophoresis/serum immunofixation electrophoresis.</ListItem><ListItem>Tissue transglutaminase and endomysial antibodies.</ListItem><ListItem>Serum tryptase, histamine, and/or chromogranin-A levels.</ListItem><ListItem>Urine for sediment; 24-hour urine collection for 5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid (serotonin metabolite) and methylimidazoleacetic acid (histamine metabolite).</ListItem><ListItem>Stool for occult blood, ova, and parasite.</ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Weisshaar E, Fleischer AB Jr, Bernhard JD, et al.: Pruritus and dysesthesia. In: Bolognia JL, Jorizzo JL, Schaffer JV: Dermatology. 3rd ed. Elsevier Saunders, 2012, pp 111-25.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><Title>Interventions</Title><Para id="_303">Note: Some citations in this section are followed by a level of evidence. The PDQ Editorial Boards use a formal ranking system to help the reader judge the strength of evidence linked to the reported results of a therapeutic strategy. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000660468" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">Levels of Evidence</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_317">If an underlying cause of pruritus is identified, treatment of the primary disease or correction of the underlying abnormality is the primary therapy. For example, iron supplementation in the setting of iron-deficiency anemia or thyroid supplementation for hypothyroidism should be initiated first. However, gentle skin techniques are considered helpful adjuvant therapies, even if they are not expected to completely alleviate the symptoms.</Para><Para id="_318">Interventions for pruritus can be categorized into four distinct groups:</Para><OrderedList id="_319" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Prevention and elimination of provocative factors.</ListItem><ListItem>Topical therapies.</ListItem><ListItem>Systemic therapies.</ListItem><ListItem>Physical modalities.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_108"><Title>Prevention and Elimination of Provocative Factors</Title><Para id="_68">Patients and caregivers must be included in planning and providing care to
the extent possible.  Education is an important aspect of symptom control. 
Skin care regimens incorporate protection from the environment, good cleansing practices, and internal and
external hydration.<Reference refidx="1"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]  The intensity of the regimen and the techniques
used will vary according to etiological factors and the degree of distress
associated with pruritus.</Para><Para id="_70">Adequate nutrition is essential to the maintenance of healthy skin.  An optimal
diet should include a balance of proteins, carbohydrates, fats, vitamins,
minerals, and fluids.  Daily fluid intake of at least 3,000 mL is
suggested as a guideline but may not be possible for some individuals.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_71">Aggravating factors should be avoided, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_72" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Fluid loss secondary to fever, diarrhea, nausea and vomiting, or decreased
fluid intake.</ListItem>

<ListItem>Bathing with hot water.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Using bubble baths or soaps that contain detergents.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Bathing more than once a day or bathing for longer than 30 minutes.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Using soap and adding oil early in a bath.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Using a reusable fomite for scrubbing (e.g., buff-puff or loofah sponge).</ListItem><ListItem>Using scents, fragrances, and perfumes.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Dry environment.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Laundering sheets and clothing with detergent containing scents, dyes, and preservatives.</ListItem><ListItem>Using fabric softener sheets.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Wearing tight restrictive clothing or clothing made of wool, synthetics, or other
harsh/scratchy fabric.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Using underarm deodorants or antiperspirants.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Applying topical preparations containing scents, dyes, or preservatives.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Emotional stress.</ListItem>
</ItemizedList><Para id="_73">Alleviating factors should be promoted, as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_74" Style="bullet">
<ListItem>Applying unscented emollient creams or ointments.</ListItem><ListItem>Bathing in tepid water.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Using mild skin cleansers (nonsoap) or soaps made for sensitive skin (e.g., Cetaphil cleanser, Dove for Sensitive Skin, Oilatum, Basis).</ListItem><ListItem>Using soap only for dirty areas; otherwise, water is sufficient.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Limiting bathing to 30 minutes daily or every other day.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Adding oil and using soap at the end of a bath or adding a colloidal oatmeal treatment     
early to the bath.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Gently washing, if needed, with a clean, soft cotton washcloth.</ListItem><ListItem>Rinsing all residue from bathing with fresh tepid water.</ListItem><ListItem>Drying off by patting skin instead of rubbing.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Maintaining a humid environment (e.g., using a humidifier).</ListItem>
<ListItem>Using cotton flannel blankets, if needed.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Washing sheets, clothing, and undergarments in mild soaps for infant         
clothing containing no scents, dyes, or preservatives (e.g., Dreft, All Free Clear, Tide Free and Gentle).</ListItem><ListItem>Using liquid fabric softener that is rinsed out in the wash (e.g., All Free Clear Fabric Softener) or avoiding fabric softener altogether.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Wearing loose-fitting clothing and clothing made of cotton or other soft
fabrics.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Using distraction, relaxation, positive imagery, or cutaneous stimulation.</ListItem>



</ItemizedList><Para id="_320">Heat increases cutaneous blood flow and may enhance itching.  Heat also lowers
humidity, and skin loses moisture when the relative humidity falls below 40%.
A cool, humid environment may reverse these processes.
Extensive bathing aggravates dry skin, and hot baths exacerbate fluid loss by causing vasodilation. The vasodilation results in increased blood flow, which   enhances itching. Tepid baths have an antipruritic effect, possibly resulting from capillary vasoconstriction.</Para><Para id="_321">The goal of skin cleansing is to remove dirt and prevent odor, but actual
hygienic practices are influenced by skin type, lifestyle, and culture. 
Bathing should be limited to 30 minutes every day or every 2 days.</Para><Para id="_343">Many soaps are salts of fatty acids with an alkali
base,  leading to excessive defatting of the skin lipids and altered skin pH, irritating the skin. Older adults or individuals with dry skin should limit the use of soaps to areas with apocrine glands. Plain water should suffice for cleaning other skin surfaces. Mild soaps have less soap or detergent content. Soap is a degreaser and can also irritate skin.  Superfatted soaps deposit a film of
oil on the skin surface, but there is no proof that they are less drying than
other soaps, and they may be more expensive.</Para><Para id="_322">Residue left by detergents after bathing or used in laundering clothes and linens, as well as fabric softeners and antistatic products, may aggravate pruritus. Clothing detergent residue can be neutralized by the addition of vinegar (1 teaspoon per quart of water) to rinse water. Mild laundry soaps marketed for infant items also may offer a solution.</Para><Para id="_323">Loose-fitting, lightweight cotton clothes and cotton bed sheets are suggested.
The elimination of heavy bedcovers may alleviate itching by decreasing body
heat.  Wool and some synthetic fabrics may be irritating.  Distraction, music
therapy, relaxation, and imagery may be useful to relieve symptoms.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_109"><Title>Topical Therapies</Title><SummarySection id="_324"><Title>Over-the-counter products</Title><Para id="_325">Some topical agents—including cornstarch, talcum powder, perfumed powders, and bubble baths—can irritate the skin and cause pruritus.  Cornstarch has been
an acceptable intervention for pruritus associated with dry desquamation
related to radiation therapy; however, it should not  be applied to moist skin surfaces,
areas with hair, sebaceous glands, skin folds (intertriginous zones), or areas close to mucosal
surfaces, such as the vagina and rectum.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  Glucose is formed when
cornstarch is moistened, providing an excellent medium for fungal growth.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_344">Agents with metal ions (i.e., talcum and aluminum used in antiperspirants)
enhance skin reactions during external-beam radiation therapy and should be
avoided throughout the course of radiation therapy.  Talcum-based agents are otherwise preferred over cornstarch-based modalities when needed, particularly for intertriginous zones. Other common ingredients
in over-the-counter lotions and creams that may enhance skin reactions include
alcohol, topical antibiotics, and topical anesthetics.</Para><Para id="_326">If pruritus is thought to be primarily related to dry skin, interventions to
improve skin hydration can be used.  The main source of hydration for skin
is moisture from the vasculature of underlying tissues.  Water, not lipid,
regulates the pliability of the epidermis, providing the rationale for using
emollients.<Reference refidx="7"/>  Emollients reduce evaporation by forming occlusive and
semi-occlusive films over the skin surface, encouraging the production of
moisture in the layer of epidermis beneath the film.<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_327">Knowledge about the ingredients in skin care products is essential because many
ingredients may enhance skin reactions.  The three main ingredients of emollients
are as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_352" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Petrolatum, which is poorly absorbed by irradiated skin and is not easily removed.  A
thick layer could produce an undesired bolus effect when applied within a
radiation treatment field.<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Lanolin, which may cause allergic sensitization in some individuals.<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Mineral oil, which is used in combination with
petrolatum and lanolin to create creams and lotions and may be an active
ingredient in bath oils.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_353">Other ingredients added to these products—such as
thickeners, opacifiers, preservatives, fragrances, and colorings—may cause
allergic skin reactions.</Para><Para id="_328">Product selection and recommendations must be made in consideration of each
patient’s unique needs and should incorporate variables such as the following:<Reference refidx="1"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]  </Para><ItemizedList id="_370" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Individual’s skin.</ListItem><ListItem>Desired effect.</ListItem><ListItem> Consistency and texture of the
preparation.</ListItem><ListItem>Cost and acceptability to the patient.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_371">Emollient creams
or lotions should be applied at least two or three times daily and after
bathing.  Gels with a local anesthetic (0.5%–5% lidocaine) can be used on some small areas (with the caveat that gels are composed of mostly alcohol-based vehicles) as often as every 2 hours if necessary.<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_329">Over-the-counter products containing menthol, camphor, pramoxine, or capsaicin can be used for certain areas of severe pruritus.  These substances soothe, cool, or inhibit itch sensations, raising the threshold for itch perception. Capsaicin-based therapies are more likely to be beneficial in pruritus of neuropathic origin.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_331"><Title>Prescription products</Title><Para id="_332">Topical steroids can reduce itching, but they reduce blood flow
to the skin, resulting in thinning of the skin and increased susceptibility to
injury.<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]
Topical steroids should therefore be reserved for pruritic skin with associated primary dermatitis or inflammatory etiologies.  Some practitioners may formulate their own mixture of dilute steroid-containing moisturizer by compounding menthol 0.5% and fluocinonide 0.0125% into a Vanicream base (fluocinonide 0.05% 60 g, menthol 480 mg, and Vanicream QSAD 240 g).  Topical steroids should not be applied to skin surfaces inside a radiation field during treatment but may be used successfully for radiation-induced dermatitis after the treatment course has concluded.</Para><Para id="_333">For more-severe xerosis or keratoderma, humectants may be indicated.  These products not only provide an occlusive or semi-occlusive barrier for water, but also chemically exfoliate an excessively cornified layer while drawing dermal fluid into the epidermal compartment.  Humectant choices include:<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]  </Para><ItemizedList id="_372" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Salicylic acid 6% cream.</ListItem><ListItem>Ammonium lactate 12% cream.</ListItem><ListItem>Creams and ointments containing urea 10% to 50%.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_373">Humectants can significantly improve skin pliability and reduce fissuring, but care must be taken that they do not get into fissures because they can cause stinging sensations on open erosions.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_354"><Title>Systemic Therapies</Title><Para id="_355">Systemic medications used to manage pruritus include those directed toward the underlying disease or control of symptoms. Antibiotics can reduce symptoms associated with infection. Oral antihistamines may provide symptomatic relief in histamine-related itching; however, they are not considered useful in pruritus of neuropathic origin. It is believed that the sedative effect of antihistamines adds to their antipruritic efficacy; therefore, a higher dose of antihistamine at bedtime may produce desirable potentiation of the antipruritic effect by also providing this sedative effect. If one antihistamine is ineffective, one from another class may provide relief (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062748#_347" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>).</Para><Para id="_356">Second-generation antihistamines have several advantages over first-generation antihistamines.<Reference refidx="14"/> Decreased activity on nonhistamine receptors results in fewer adverse effects.  In addition, second-generation antihistamines dissociate slowly from histamine receptors, allowing for once-daily dosing.  Compared with first-generation antihistamines, second-generation antihistamines produce less central nervous system penetration and therefore less sedation.  Given these advantages, using doses of levocetirizine and desloratadine higher than those approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration has been suggested to provide relief for some patients with chronic urticarial conditions.<Reference refidx="15"/> However, studies of cetirizone have produced conflicting results.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Table id="_347"><Title>Table 2.  Antihistamines Used to Alleviate Pruritus<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="20.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Drug Category</entry><entry>Medication</entry><entry>Dose</entry><entry>Comments</entry><entry>Reference</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1">SR = sustained release.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Table abstracted from Lexicomp Online.<Reference refidx="18"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="3">First generation</entry><entry>Diphenhydramine</entry><entry>25–100 mg q6h</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Hydroxyzine	</entry><entry>25–50 mg q6–8h</entry><entry>Abrupt withdrawal may cause confusion.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="20"/>; <Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cyproheptadine	</entry><entry>4 mg q6–8h</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Chlorpheniramine	</entry><entry>4 mg q4–6h</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Second generation</entry><entry>Cetirizine	</entry><entry>5–10 mg daily</entry><entry>Conflicting results when 20–40 mg/day studied.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]; 

<Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Levocetirizine	</entry><entry>2.5–5 mg daily</entry><entry>Safe to increase dose up to 20 mg daily; may provide better symptom control.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Loratadine	</entry><entry>10 mg daily</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Desloratadine	</entry><entry>5 mg daily</entry><entry>Safe to increase dose up to 20 mg daily; may provide better symptom control.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="23"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Fexofenadine	</entry><entry>60 mg q12h or 180 mg daily (SR tablet)</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="25"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_357">Several alternative medications can be used to alleviate pruritus (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062748#_348" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq">Table 3</SummaryRef>). Antidepressants can have strong antihistamine and antipruritic effects.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]   Tricyclic antidepressants such as doxepin, amitriptyline, nortriptyline, and trimipramine have additional antihistaminic effects, making them of additional benefit in dermatological conditions such as urticaria. However, the generally more-favorable side-effect profile of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors  and selective norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors has made them the first-line agents in the management of psychogenic pruritus.<Reference refidx="26"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_358">Aspirin may reduce pruritus in some individuals with polycythemia vera, while increasing
pruritus in others.  Patients with thrombocytopenic cancer should be cautioned
against using aspirin.  Cimetidine alone or in combination with aspirin has
been used with some effectiveness for pruritus associated with Hodgkin lymphoma and polycythemia vera.<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_359">Novel agents to try in recalcitrant cases of pruritus include gabapentin, pregabalin, and botulinum toxin injection, particularly for neurogenic itch such as post-herpetic neuralgia.<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/> Aprepitant has been used successfully in the treatment of pruritus by blocking the neurokinin-1 receptor, which is activated by substance P.<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para><Table id="_348"><Title>Table 3.  Alternative Medications Used to Alleviate Pruritus<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="20.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Drug Category</entry><entry>Medication</entry><entry>Dose</entry><entry>Comments</entry><entry>Reference</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1">ESRD = end-stage renal disease; GABA = gamma-aminobutyric acid; IV = intravenously; tid = 3 times a day.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Table abstracted from Lexicomp Online.<Reference refidx="18"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Tricyclic antidepressant</entry><entry>Amitriptyline</entry><entry>25–150 mg daily</entry><entry>Start as 10 mg tid or 25 mg at bedtime.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Doxepin</entry><entry>10–25 mg q8h</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor</entry><entry>Fluvoxamine</entry><entry>50–100 mg daily</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="32"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Mirtazapine</entry><entry>7.5–15 mg at bedtime</entry><entry>No value to  &gt;15 mg.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Paroxetine</entry><entry>20 mg daily</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="33"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sertraline</entry><entry>75–100 mg daily</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="34"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">GABA analogue</entry><entry>Gabapentin</entry><entry>100–300 mg daily, titrated to effect</entry><entry>Dose must be adjusted for renal dysfunction.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="35"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Pregabalin</entry><entry>75 mg daily</entry><entry>Dose must be adjusted for renal dysfunction.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="36"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Sequestrant agent</entry><entry>Ursodiol (ursodeoxycholic acid)</entry><entry>10–15 mg/kg of body weight per day</entry><entry>For pruritus of cholestasis.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="37"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cholestyramine</entry><entry>4–16 g daily</entry><entry>For pruritus of cholestasis.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="37"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Opioid antagonist</entry><entry>Naloxone</entry><entry>0.2 µg/kg of body weight per min IV</entry><entry>Efficacy in cholestatic pruritus; conflicting results in ESRD itch. Can cause pain by antagonizing mu-receptor.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="38"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="39"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Naltrexone</entry><entry>25–100 mg daily</entry><entry>Efficacy in cholestatic pruritus, atopic eczema; conflicting results in ESRD itch. Can cause pain by antagonizing mu-receptor.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="39"/>; <Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Butorphanol</entry><entry>1–4 mg q4–6h intranasally</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="42"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Nalbuphine</entry><entry>2.5–5 mg IV</entry><entry>For opioid-induced pruritus.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="43"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="6">Miscellaneous agent</entry><entry>Aprepitant</entry><entry>80 mg daily</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Aspirin</entry><entry>500 mg q8–24h</entry><entry>Only used for polycythemia vera. Positive and negative data.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Botulinum toxin</entry><entry>16–25 units injected into the dermatome</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Capsaicin 0.025%</entry><entry>Apply 5 times daily × 1 week, then 3 times daily</entry><entry>For neurological pruritus.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="44"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cimetidine</entry><entry>200 mg q6h</entry><entry>Only used for polycythemia vera.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cyclosporine</entry><entry>3–4.5 mg/kg of body weight per day</entry><entry>Requires close monitoring for renal toxicity.</entry><entry><Reference refidx="45"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Pimecrolimus 1% cream</entry><entry>Apply twice daily</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="46"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_360">Sequestrant agents may be effective in relieving pruritus associated with renal
or hepatic disease through binding and removing pruritogenic substances in the
gut and reducing bile salt concentration. Choices include ursodeoxycholic acid and cholestyramine; however, cholestyramine is not always effective and produces gastric side effects.<Reference refidx="47"/> Because of the association of pruritus with opioid receptor agonism, increased catabolism of endogenous opioids using rifampin in uremia may be beneficial.<Reference refidx="48"/>  Opioid antagonists such as naloxone, naltrexone, nalmefene, butorphanol, and nalbuphine may also have some benefit, particularly in patients with uremic pruritus.<Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="40"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_113"><Title>Physical Modalities</Title><Para id="_95">Alternatives to scratching for the relief of pruritus can help the patient
interrupt the itch-scratch-itch cycle.  Substituting the application of emollients for scratching may help reduce skin breakdown. The application of a cool washcloth or ice
over the site may be useful.  Firm pressure at the site of itching, at a site
contralateral to the site of itching, and at acupressure points may break the
neural pathway.  Rubbing, pressure, and vibration can be used to relieve
itching.<Reference refidx="49"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_96">There are anecdotal reports of the use of transcutaneous electronic nerve stimulators (TENS) and acupuncture in the management of pruritus.<Reference refidx="50"/> 
Ultraviolet phototherapy has been used with limited success to treat pruritus
related to uremia.<Reference refidx="50"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Detz W, Berman B: Aids that preserve hydration and mitigate its loss. Consultant  24: 46-62, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Lydon J, Purl S, Goodman M: Integumentary and mucous membrane alterations. In: Groenwald SL, Frogge MH, Goodman M, et al., eds.: Cancer Nursing: Principles and Practice. 2nd ed. Jones and Bartlett, 1990, pp 594-635.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Pace KB, Bord MA, McCray N, et al.: Pruritus. In: McNally JC, Stair JC, Somerville ET, eds.: Guidelines for Cancer Nursing Practice. Grune and Stratton, Inc., 1985, pp 85-88.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Yasko JM, Hogan CM: Pruritus. In: Yasko J, ed.: Guidelines for Cancer Care: Symptom Management. Reston Publishing Company, Inc., 1983, pp 125-129.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3655092" MedlineID="88008598">Hassey KM: Skin care for patients receiving radiation therapy for rectal cancer. J Enterostomal Ther 14 (5): 197-200, 1987 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="3357836" MedlineID="88189901">Maienza J: Alternatives to cornstarch for itchiness. Oncol Nurs Forum 15 (2): 199-200, 1988 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Blank L: Factors which influence the water content of the stratum corneum. J Invest Dermatol  18 (2): 133-39, 1952.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="3204210" MedlineID="89079965">Klein L: Maintenance of healthy skin. J Enterostomal Ther 15 (6): 227-31, 1988 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="6346274" MedlineID="83246750">Hilderley L: Skin care in radiation therapy. A review of the literature. Oncol Nurs Forum 10 (1): 51-6, 1983 Winter.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="2030300" MedlineID="91231732">De Conno F, Ventafridda V, Saita L: Skin problems in advanced and terminal cancer patients. J Pain Symptom Manage 6 (4): 247-56, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="24912513">Misery L, Brenaut E, Le Garrec R, et al.: Neuropathic pruritus. Nat Rev Neurol 10 (7): 408-16, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="6215631" MedlineID="83038944">Hassey KM, Rose CM: Altered skin integrity in patients receiving radiation therapy. Oncol Nurs Forum 9 (4): 44-50, 1982 Fall.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="22913439">Nolan K, Marmur E: Moisturizers: reality and the skin benefits. Dermatol Ther 25 (3): 229-33, 2012 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="16297006">O'Donoghue M, Tharp MD: Antihistamines and their role as antipruritics. Dermatol Ther 18 (4): 333-40, 2005 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="16445787">Nettis E, Colanardi MC, Barra L, et al.: Levocetirizine in the treatment of chronic idiopathic urticaria: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Br J Dermatol 154 (3): 533-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="8430920">Hannuksela M, Kalimo K, Lammintausta K, et al.: Dose ranging study: cetirizine in the treatment of atopic dermatitis in adults. Ann Allergy 70 (2): 127-33, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="17042777">Asero R: Chronic unremitting urticaria: is the use of antihistamines above the licensed dose effective? A preliminary study of cetirizine at licensed and above-licensed doses. Clin Exp Dermatol 32 (1): 34-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="18">Lexicomp Online. Hudson, Ohio: Lexi-Comp, Inc., 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.wolterskluwer.com/en/solutions/uptodate/enterprise/lexidrug">Available online with subscription</ExternalRef>. Last accessed Jan. 15, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="6549725" MedlineID="83097710">Geltman RL, Paige RL: Symptom management in hospice care. Am J Nurs 83 (1): 78-85, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="20">Levy M: Symptom control manual. In: Cassileth BR, Cassileth PA, eds.: Clinical Care of the Terminal Cancer Patient. Lea and Febiger, 1982, pp 214-262.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="1445478">Monroe EW, Bernstein DI, Fox RW, et al.: Relative efficacy and safety of loratadine, hydroxyzine, and placebo in chronic idiopathic urticaria. Arzneimittelforschung 42 (9): 1119-21, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="6752601" MedlineID="83035533">Winkelmann RK: Pharmacologic control of pruritus. Med Clin North Am 66 (5): 1119-33, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="20226302">Staevska M, Popov TA, Kralimarkova T, et al.: The effectiveness of levocetirizine and desloratadine in up to 4 times conventional doses in difficult-to-treat urticaria. J Allergy Clin Immunol 125 (3): 676-82, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="8198236">Langeland T, Fagertun HE, Larsen S: Therapeutic effect of loratadine on pruritus in patients with atopic dermatitis. A multi-crossover-designed study. Allergy 49 (1): 22-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="15984599">Kaplan AP, Spector SL, Meeves S, et al.: Once-daily fexofenadine treatment for chronic idiopathic urticaria: a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol 94 (6): 662-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="22960808">Zhang H, Yang Y, Cui J, et al.: Gaining a comprehensive understanding of pruritus. Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol 78 (5): 532-44, 2012 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="3094711" MedlineID="87027309">Daly BM, Shuster S: Effect of aspirin on pruritus. Br Med J (Clin Res Ed) 293 (6552): 907, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="12786883">Scheinfeld N: The role of gabapentin in treating diseases with cutaneous manifestations and pain. Int J Dermatol 42 (6): 491-5, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="18318883">Yosipovitch G, Samuel LS: Neuropathic and psychogenic itch. Dermatol Ther 21 (1): 32-41, 2008 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="20532044">Ständer S, Siepmann D, Herrgott I, et al.: Targeting the neurokinin receptor 1 with aprepitant: a novel antipruritic strategy. PLoS One 5 (6): e10968, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="11226766">Krajnik M, Zylicz Z: Understanding pruritus in systemic disease. J Pain Symptom Manage 21 (2): 151-68, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="19197541">Ständer S, Böckenholt B, Schürmeyer-Horst F, et al.: Treatment of chronic pruritus with the selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitors paroxetine and fluvoxamine: results of an open-labelled, two-arm proof-of-concept study. Acta Derm Venereol 89 (1): 45-51, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="14654262">Zylicz Z, Krajnik M, Sorge AA, et al.: Paroxetine in the treatment of severe non-dermatological pruritus: a randomized, controlled trial. J Pain Symptom Manage 26 (6): 1105-12, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="17326161">Mayo MJ, Handem I, Saldana S, et al.: Sertraline as a first-line treatment for cholestatic pruritus. Hepatology 45 (3): 666-74, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="15575002">Gunal AI, Ozalp G, Yoldas TK, et al.: Gabapentin therapy for pruritus in haemodialysis patients: a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind trial. Nephrol Dial Transplant 19 (12): 3137-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="22909343">Solak Y, Biyik Z, Atalay H, et al.: Pregabalin versus gabapentin in the treatment of neuropathic pruritus in maintenance haemodialysis patients: a prospective, crossover study. Nephrology (Carlton) 17 (8): 710-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="21809485">Kremer AE, Oude Elferink RP, Beuers U: Pathophysiology and current management of pruritus in liver disease. Clin Res Hepatol Gastroenterol 35 (2): 89-97, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="7598296">Bergasa NV, Alling DW, Talbot TL, et al.: Effects of naloxone infusions in patients with the pruritus of cholestasis. A double-blind, randomized, controlled trial. Ann Intern Med 123 (3): 161-7, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="20465602">Wang H, Yosipovitch G: New insights into the pathophysiology and treatment of chronic itch in patients with end-stage renal disease, chronic liver disease, and lymphoma. Int J Dermatol 49 (1): 1-11, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="8950882">Peer G, Kivity S, Agami O, et al.: Randomised crossover trial of naltrexone in uraemic pruritus. Lancet 348 (9041): 1552-4, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="19453814">Malekzad F, Arbabi M, Mohtasham N, et al.: Efficacy of oral naltrexone on pruritus in atopic eczema: a double-blind, placebo-controlled study. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol 23 (8): 948-50, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="16488311">Dawn AG, Yosipovitch G: Butorphanol for treatment of intractable pruritus. J Am Acad Dermatol 54 (3): 527-31, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="26650717">Jannuzzi RG: Nalbuphine for Treatment of Opioid-induced Pruritus: A Systematic Review of Literature. Clin J Pain 32 (1): 87-93, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="7829721">Wallengren J, Klinker M: Successful treatment of notalgia paresthetica with topical capsaicin: vehicle-controlled, double-blind, crossover study. J Am Acad Dermatol 32 (2 Pt 1): 287-9, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="22790094">Weisshaar E, Szepietowski JC, Darsow U, et al.: European guideline on chronic pruritus. Acta Derm Venereol 92 (5): 563-81, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="16436149">Kaufmann R, Bieber T, Helgesen AL, et al.: Onset of pruritus relief with pimecrolimus cream 1% in adult patients with atopic dermatitis: a randomized trial. Allergy 61 (3): 375-81, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="47">Abel EA, Farber EM: Malignant cutaneous tumors. In: Rubenstein E, Federman DD, eds.: Scientific American Medicine. Scientific American, Inc, Chapter 2: Dermatology, Section XII, 1-20, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="849823">Miguet JP, Mavier P, Soussy CJ, et al.: Induction of hepatic microsomal enzymes after brief administration of rifampicin in man. Gastroenterology 72 (5 Pt 1): 924-6, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="3632855" MedlineID="86093840">Dangel RB: Pruritus and cancer. Oncol Nurs Forum 13 (1): 17-21, 1986 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="50">Bernhard JD: Clinical aspects of pruritus. In: Fitzpatrick TB, Eisen AZ, Wolff K, et al., eds.: Dermatology in General Medicine. 3rd ed. McGraw-Hill, 1987, Chapter 7, pp 78-90.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_298"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (01/17/2025)</Title><Para id="_299">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_374">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062748#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the pathophysiology and treatment of pruritus. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewer for Pruritus is:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Larry D. Cripe, MD (Indiana University School of Medicine)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000660468" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Pruritus. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/skin-nail-changes/pruritus-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389231]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-01-17</DateLastModified></Summary>
