<Summary id="CDR0000062747" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatment-related nausea and vomiting (acute, delayed, anticipatory, breakthrough, refractory, and chronic) are of paramount concern in cancer care. Get detailed information about prevention and treatment approaches for treatment-related nausea and vomiting in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">Nausea and Vomiting Related to Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041395">nausea and vomiting</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_513">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the pathophysiology and treatment of nausea and vomiting (emesis) (N&amp;V). It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_514">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>nausea and vomiting</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Nausea and Vomiting Related to Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Nausea and Vomiting Related to Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Nausea and Vomiting Related to Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_2">Prevention and control of nausea and vomiting  (N&amp;V) are paramount in the treatment of
patients with cancer.  Chemotherapy-induced N&amp;V is one of the most common and distressing acute side effects of cancer treatment. It occurs in up to 80% of patients and can have a significant impact on a patient’s quality of life. N&amp;V can also result in the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_409" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Serious metabolic
derangements.</ListItem><ListItem>Nutritional depletion and anorexia.</ListItem><ListItem>Deterioration of the patient’s
physical and mental status.</ListItem><ListItem>Esophageal tears.</ListItem><ListItem>Fractures.</ListItem><ListItem>Wound dehiscence.</ListItem><ListItem>Withdrawal from potentially useful and curative antineoplastic treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Degeneration of self-care and functional ability.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1_md_4">In this summary, unless otherwise stated, evidence and practice issues as they relate to adults are discussed.  The evidence and application to practice related to children may differ significantly from information related to adults.  When specific information about the care of children is available, it is summarized under its own heading.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><Title>Pathophysiology of N&amp;V</Title><Para id="_430"><Strong>Nausea</Strong> is the subjective experience of an unpleasant, wavelike sensation
in the back of the throat and/or the epigastrium that may culminate in vomiting.  <Strong>Vomiting</Strong> (emesis) is the forceful expulsion of the contents
of the stomach, duodenum, or jejunum through the oral cavity.  Retching (dry heaves) involves the gastric and esophageal movements of vomiting without expulsion of vomitus.</Para><Para id="_12">Progress has been made in understanding the neurophysiological mechanisms that
control nausea and vomiting (N&amp;V).  Both are controlled or mediated by the central
nervous system but by different mechanisms.  Nausea is mediated through the
autonomic nervous system.  Vomiting results from stimulation of a complex
reflex that includes a convergence of afferent stimulation from the following:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_13" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A chemoreceptor trigger zone (CTZ, area postrema).</ListItem>
<ListItem>The cerebral cortex and the limbic system in response to sensory            
stimulation (particularly smell and taste), psychological distress, and pain.</ListItem>
<ListItem>The vestibular-labyrinthine apparatus of the inner ear in response to body
motion.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Peripheral stimuli from visceral organs and vasculature (via vagal and      
spinal sympathetic nerves) as a result of exogenous chemicals and           
endogenous substances that accumulate during inflammation, ischemia, and    
irritation.</ListItem>
</ItemizedList><Para id="_431">Neurotransmitters (including serotonin, substance P, and dopamine) found in the CTZ, the  vomiting center (thought to be located in the nucleus tractus solitarius), and enterochromaffin cells in the gastrointestinal tract release efferent impulses. These impulses are transmitted to the abdominal musculature, salivation center, and respiratory center. The relative contribution from these multiple pathways, culminating in N&amp;V symptoms, is complex. It is postulated to account for agents' variable emetogenicity (intrinsic emetogenicity and mitigating factors such as dosage, administration route, and exposure duration) and emetogenic profile (i.e., time to onset, symptom severity, and duration).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="22488022">Wickham R: Evolving treatment paradigms for chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Cancer Control 19 (2 Suppl): 3-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="19284365">Navari RM: Antiemetic control: toward a new standard of care for emetogenic chemotherapy. Expert Opin Pharmacother 10 (4): 629-44, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="20071282">Cefalo MG, Ruggiero A, Maurizi P, et al.: Pharmacological management of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in children with cancer. J Chemother 21 (6): 605-10, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19022231">Darmani NA, Crim JL, Janoyan JJ, et al.: A re-evaluation of the neurotransmitter basis of chemotherapy-induced immediate and delayed vomiting: evidence from the least shrew. Brain Res 1248: 40-58, 2009.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>General Risk Factors and Etiologies</Title><Para id="_432">Although most patients receiving chemotherapy are at risk of nausea and vomiting (N&amp;V), the onset, severity, triggers, and duration vary. Factors related to the tumor, treatment, and patient all contribute to N&amp;V, including tumor location, chemotherapy agents used, and radiation exposure.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_433">Patient-related factors may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_412" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Incidence and severity of N&amp;V during past courses of chemotherapy. Patients with poor control of N&amp;V during past chemotherapy cycles are likely to experience N&amp;V in subsequent cycles.</ListItem><ListItem> History of chronic alcohol
use. Patients with a history of chronic high intake of alcohol are less likely to experience cisplatin-induced N&amp;V.<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem><ListItem>Age. N&amp;V is more likely to occur in patients younger than 50 years.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem>Gender. N&amp;V is more likely to occur in women.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem>History of morning sickness or emesis during pregnancy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_424">Additional causal factors may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_413" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Fluid and electrolyte imbalances, such as
hypercalcemia, volume depletion, or water intoxication.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor invasion or
growth in the gastrointestinal tract, liver, or central nervous system,
especially the posterior fossa.</ListItem><ListItem>Constipation.</ListItem><ListItem>Certain drugs, such as opioids.</ListItem><ListItem>
Infection or septicemia.</ListItem><ListItem> Uremia.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_19">Clinicians must be aware of all potential causes and factors of N&amp;V,
especially in patients with cancer who may receive several
treatments and medications.  For more
information about opioid-induced N&amp;V, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062738#_77" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-hp-pdq">Adverse effects</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Pain.</Para><SummarySection id="_434"><Title>Classifications</Title><Para id="_435">N&amp;V have been classified as acute, delayed, anticipatory, breakthrough, refractory, and chronic, as outlined below:<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_436" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Acute N&amp;V:</Strong> N&amp;V experienced during the first 24 hours after chemotherapy administration.<Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Delayed (or late) N&amp;V:</Strong> N&amp;V that occurs more than 24
hours after chemotherapy administration. 
Delayed N&amp;V is associated with cisplatin, cyclophosphamide, and other drugs
(e.g., doxorubicin and ifosfamide) given at high doses or on 2 or more
consecutive days.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Anticipatory N&amp;V (ANV):</Strong> N&amp;V that
occurs before a new cycle of chemotherapy  in response to
conditioned stimuli such as the smells, sights, and sounds of the treatment
room.  ANV is a classically conditioned response that typically occurs after three
or four chemotherapy treatments that led to
acute or delayed N&amp;V.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Breakthrough N&amp;V:</Strong>  Vomiting that occurs within 5 days of prophylactic  use of antiemetics and requires rescue.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Refractory N&amp;V:</Strong> N&amp;V that does not respond to treatment.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Chronic N&amp;V in patients with advanced cancer:</Strong> N&amp;V associated with a
variety of potential etiologies.  These etiologies are neither
well known nor well researched, but potential causal factors include
gastrointestinal, cranial, metabolic, drug-induced (e.g., morphine), cytotoxic
chemotherapy–induced, and radiation-induced mechanisms.<Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_697">The National Cancer Institute has published a descriptive terminology for adverse event reporting (see Table 1).  
A grading 
(severity) scale is provided for each term.</Para><Table id="_471"><Title>Table 1.  National Cancer Institute’s Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events: N&amp;V<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Adverse Event </entry><entry>Grade</entry><entry>Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">IV = intravenous; N&amp;V = nausea and vomiting (emesis); TPN = total parenteral nutrition.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from National Cancer Institute.<Reference refidx="12"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Definition: A disorder characterized by a queasy sensation and/or the urge to vomit.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Definition: A disorder characterized by the reflexive act of ejecting the contents of the stomach through the mouth.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Nausea<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>1</entry><entry>Loss of appetite without alteration in eating habits</entry></Row><Row><entry>2</entry><entry>Oral intake decreased without significant weight loss, dehydration, or malnutrition</entry></Row><Row><entry>3</entry><entry>Inadequate oral caloric or fluid intake; tube feeding, TPN, or hospitalization indicated</entry></Row><Row><entry>4</entry><entry>Grade not assigned</entry></Row><Row><entry>5</entry><entry>Grade not assigned</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Vomiting<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry><entry>1</entry><entry>Intervention not indicated</entry></Row><Row><entry>2</entry><entry>Outpatient IV hydration; 
medical intervention 
indicated</entry></Row><Row><entry>3</entry><entry>Tube feeding, TPN, or hospitalization indicated </entry></Row><Row><entry>4</entry><entry>Life-threatening consequences; urgent intervention indicated</entry></Row><Row><entry>5</entry><entry>Death</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="22610269">Farrell C, Brearley SG, Pilling M, et al.: The impact of chemotherapy-related nausea on patients' nutritional status, psychological distress and quality of life. Support Care Cancer 21 (1): 59-66, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="22763232">Dranitsaris G, Bouganim N, Milano C, et al.: Prospective validation of a prediction tool for identifying patients at high risk for chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. J Support Oncol 11 (1): 14-21, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23300365">Bouganim N, Dranitsaris G, Hopkins S, et al.: Prospective validation of risk prediction indexes for acute and delayed chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Curr Oncol 19 (6): e414-21, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6684209" MedlineID="83297552">Sullivan JR, Leyden MJ, Bell R: Decreased cisplatin-induced nausea and vomiting with chronic alcohol ingestion. N Engl J Med 309 (13): 796, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2054311" MedlineID="91274229">Tonato M, Roila F, Del Favero A: Methodology of antiemetic trials: a review. Ann Oncol 2 (2): 107-14, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="3543234" MedlineID="87111676">Roila F, Tonato M, Basurto C, et al.: Antiemetic activity of high doses of metoclopramide combined with methylprednisolone versus metoclopramide alone in cisplatin-treated cancer patients: a randomized double-blind trial of the Italian Oncology Group for Clinical Research. J Clin Oncol 5 (1): 141-9, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21370520">Kris MG, Urba SG, Schwartzberg LS: Clinical roundtable monograph. Treatment of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a post-MASCC 2010 discussion. Clin Adv Hematol Oncol 9 (1): suppl 1-15, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="18525044">Hesketh PJ: Chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. N Engl J Med 358 (23): 2482-94, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15599601">Grunberg SM, Osoba D, Hesketh PJ, et al.: Evaluation of new antiemetic agents and definition of antineoplastic agent emetogenicity--an update. Support Care Cancer 13 (2): 80-4, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Wickham R: Nausea and vomiting. In: Yarbo CH, Frogge MH, Goodman M, eds.: Cancer Symptom Management. 2nd ed. Jones and Bartlett Publishers, 1999, pp 228-263.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="16499138">Schwartzberg L: Chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: state of the art in 2006. J Support Oncol 4 (2 Suppl 1): 3-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="12">National Cancer Institute: Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 5.0. Bethesda, Md: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, National Institutes of Health, 2017. <ExternalRef xref="https://ctep.cancer.gov/protocolDevelopment/electronic_applications/docs/CTCAE_v5_Quick_Reference_8.5x11.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed Dec. 18, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><Title>Anticipatory Nausea and Vomiting</Title><SummarySection id="_21"><Title>Prevalence</Title><Para id="_22">The prevalence of anticipatory nausea and vomiting (ANV) has varied because of
changing definitions and assessment methods.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Anticipatory nausea
appears to occur in approximately 29% of patients receiving chemotherapy, while anticipatory vomiting appears to occur in 11% of
patients.<Reference refidx="2"/>  With the introduction of pharmacological agents
such as 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>) receptor antagonists, the prevalence of ANV
was expected to decline, but studies have shown mixed results.  One study found a
lower incidence of ANV,<Reference refidx="3"/> and three studies found comparable incidence
rates.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  It appears that the 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> agents reduce postchemotherapy
vomiting but not postchemotherapy nausea,<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/> and the resulting impact on ANV
is unclear.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><Title>Classical Conditioning</Title><Para id="_24">Although other theoretical mechanisms have been proposed,<Reference refidx="6"/> ANV appears to be
best explained by classical conditioning, also known as Pavlovian or respondent
conditioning.<Reference refidx="7"/>  In classical conditioning, a previously neutral stimulus
(e.g., smells of the chemotherapy environment) elicits a conditioned
response (e.g., ANV) after a number of pairings or learning trials.  In
cancer chemotherapy, the first few chemotherapy infusions are the learning
trials.  The chemotherapy drugs are the unconditioned stimuli that elicit
postchemotherapy nausea and vomiting (N&amp;V) in some patients.  The drugs are paired with
a variety of other neutral, environmental stimuli (e.g., smells of the setting,
presence of the oncology nurse, chemotherapy room).  These previously neutral stimuli then
become conditioned stimuli and elicit ANV in future chemotherapy cycles.  ANV
is not an indication of psychopathology. It is a learned response that, in
other life situations (e.g., food poisoning), results in adaptive avoidance.</Para><Para id="_415">  A
variety of correlational studies provide empirical support for classical
conditioning.  For example, the prevalence of ANV before treatment with any chemotherapy is
rare, and few patients ever experience ANV without previous postchemotherapy
nausea.<Reference refidx="8"/>  Also, most studies have found (1) a higher probability of ANV with
an increasing number of chemotherapy infusions and (2) the intensity of ANV
increasing as patients get closer to the time of their infusion.<Reference refidx="9"/>  In
one experimental study, it was shown that a novel beverage could become a
conditioned stimulus to nausea when paired with several chemotherapy
treatments.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><Title>Variables Correlated with ANV</Title><Para id="_26">Many variables have been investigated as potential risk factors that correlate with
the incidence of ANV.  There is
no agreement on which factors predict ANV.  However, a patient with fewer than
three of the first eight characteristics listed below is unlikely to develop ANV. Screening after the first chemotherapy infusion could identify patients at increased risk.<Reference refidx="11"/>
</Para><OrderedList id="_177" Style="Arabic"><ListTitle>Variables Found to Correlate With ANV</ListTitle><ListItem>Age younger than 50 years.</ListItem><ListItem>N&amp;V after the last chemotherapy session.</ListItem><ListItem>
Posttreatment nausea described as moderate, severe, or intolerable.</ListItem><ListItem>Posttreatment vomiting described as moderate, severe, or intolerable.</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling warm or hot all over after the last chemotherapy session.</ListItem><ListItem>
Susceptibility to motion sickness.</ListItem><ListItem>Female gender.</ListItem><ListItem>High-state anxiety (anxiety reactive to specific situations).<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem><ListItem>Greater reactivity of the autonomic nervous system and slower reaction
time.<Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem>Patient expectations of chemotherapy-related nausea before beginning
treatment.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem><ListItem>Percentage of chemotherapy infusions followed by nausea.<Reference refidx="17"/></ListItem><ListItem>Postchemotherapy dizziness.</ListItem><ListItem>Longer latency of onset of
posttreatment N&amp;V.<Reference refidx="18"/></ListItem><ListItem>Emetogenic potential of various chemotherapeutic agents.  Patients receiving drugs with a moderate to severe potential for
posttreatment N&amp;V are more likely to develop ANV.<Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem>History of morning sickness during pregnancy.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><Title>Treatment of ANV</Title><Para id="_31">Antiemetic drugs do not seem to control ANV once it has developed;<Reference refidx="2"/>  however,
a variety of behavioral interventions has been investigated.<Reference refidx="19"/>  These
interventions include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_416" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Progressive muscle relaxation with guided imagery.<Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem><ListItem>Hypnosis.<Reference refidx="21"/></ListItem><ListItem>Systematic desensitization.<Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem><ListItem> Electromyography and thermal biofeedback.<Reference refidx="23"/></ListItem><ListItem>Distraction via the use of video games.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_417">Progressive muscle relaxation
with guided imagery, hypnosis, and systematic desensitization has been studied
the most and should be considered as treatment.  Referral to a psychologist or
other mental health professional with specific training and experience in
working with cancer patients should be considered when ANV is identified.  The
earlier ANV is identified, the more likely treatment will be effective, so early screening and referral are essential.
However, physicians and nurses often underestimate the incidence of chemotherapy-induced N&amp;V.<Reference refidx="26"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_439">Clearly, the most important aspect of ANV is prevention of acute and delayed N&amp;V associated with chemotherapy. Most antiemetics have not shown benefit for the treatment of ANV, but their use during chemotherapy may markedly decrease the incidence of ANV. The only class of medication that has shown benefit in some studies is benzodiazepines, most commonly lorazepam.<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3367372" MedlineID="88214875">Andrykowski MA: Defining anticipatory nausea and vomiting: differences among cancer chemotherapy patients who report pretreatment nausea. J Behav Med 11 (1): 59-69, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9629877" MedlineID="98291829">Morrow GR, Roscoe JA, Kirshner JJ, et al.: Anticipatory nausea and vomiting in the era of 5-HT3 antiemetics. Support Care Cancer 6 (3): 244-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8180031" MedlineID="94235456">Aapro MS, Kirchner V, Terrey JP: The incidence of anticipatory nausea and vomiting after repeat cycle chemotherapy: the effect of granisetron. Br J Cancer 69 (5): 957-60, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="8883231" MedlineID="97037584">Fernández-Marcos A, Martín M, Sanchez JJ, et al.: Acute and anticipatory emesis in breast cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 4 (5): 370-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10989249" MedlineID="20446002">Roscoe JA, Morrow GR, Hickok JT, et al.: Nausea and vomiting remain a significant clinical problem: trends over time in controlling chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in 1413 patients treated in community clinical practices. J Pain Symptom Manage 20 (2): 113-21, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="1969324" MedlineID="90199628">Reesal RT, Bajramovic H, Mai F: Anticipatory nausea and vomiting: a form of chemotherapy phobia? Can J Psychiatry 35 (1): 80-2, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Stockhorst U, Klosterhalfen S, Steingruber HJ: Conditioned nausea and further side-effects in cancer chemotherapy:  a review. Journal of Psychophysiology  12 (suppl 1): 14-33, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8692550" MedlineID="96305513">Morrow GR, Rosenthal SN: Models, mechanisms and management of anticipatory nausea and emesis. Oncology 53 (Suppl 1): 4-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9145945" MedlineID="97291351">Montgomery GH, Bovbjerg DH: The development of anticipatory nausea in patients receiving adjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer. Physiol Behav 61 (5): 737-41, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="1454956" MedlineID="93087708">Bovbjerg DH, Redd WH, Jacobsen PB, et al.: An experimental analysis of classically conditioned nausea during cancer chemotherapy. Psychosom Med 54 (6): 623-37, 1992 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="11">Morrow GR, Roscoe JA, Hickok JT: Nausea and vomiting. In: Holland JC, Breitbart W, Jacobsen PB, et al., eds.: Psycho-oncology. Oxford University Press, 1998, pp 476-484.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="4031199" MedlineID="85290176">Andrykowski MA, Redd WH, Hatfield AK: Development of anticipatory nausea: a prospective analysis. J Consult Clin Psychol 53 (4): 447-54, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="19780257">Roscoe JA, Morrow GR, Hickok JT, et al.: Biobehavioral factors in chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 2 (5): 501-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="7803940" MedlineID="95102238">Kvale G, Psychol C, Hugdahl K: Cardiovascular conditioning and anticipatory nausea and vomiting in cancer patients. Behav Med 20 (2): 78-83, 1994 Summer.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="9989316" MedlineID="99143861">Montgomery GH, Tomoyasu N, Bovbjerg DH, et al.: Patients' pretreatment expectations of chemotherapy-related nausea are an independent predictor of anticipatory nausea. Ann Behav Med 20 (2): 104-9, 1998 Spring.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="18243641">Shelke AR, Roscoe JA, Morrow GR, et al.: Effect of a nausea expectancy manipulation on chemotherapy-induced nausea: a university of Rochester cancer center community clinical oncology program study. J Pain Symptom Manage 35 (4): 381-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="8838605" MedlineID="96435719">Tomoyasu N, Bovbjerg DH, Jacobsen PB: Conditioned reactions to cancer chemotherapy: percent reinforcement predicts anticipatory nausea. Physiol Behav 59 (2): 273-6, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="1590283" MedlineID="92272045">Chin SB, Kucuk O, Peterson R, et al.: Variables contributing to anticipatory nausea and vomiting in cancer chemotherapy. Am J Clin Oncol 15 (3): 262-7, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="3062654" MedlineID="89099489">Carey MP, Burish TG: Etiology and treatment of the psychological side effects associated with cancer chemotherapy: a critical review and discussion. Psychol Bull 104 (3): 307-25, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="6749917" MedlineID="83007926">Lyles JN, Burish TG, Krozely MG, et al.: Efficacy of relaxation training and guided imagery in reducing the aversiveness of cancer chemotherapy. J Consult Clin Psychol 50 (4): 509-24, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="7056907" MedlineID="82120691">Redd WH, Andresen GV, Minagawa RY: Hypnotic control of anticipatory emesis in patients receiving cancer chemotherapy. J Consult Clin Psychol 50 (1): 14-9, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="6128673" MedlineID="83062680">Morrow GR, Morrell C: Behavioral treatment for the anticipatory nausea and vomiting induced by cancer chemotherapy. N Engl J Med 307 (24): 1476-80, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="7034793" MedlineID="82113830">Burish TG, Shartner CD, Lyles JN: Effectiveness of multiple muscle-site EMG biofeedback and relaxation training in reducing the aversiveness of cancer chemotherapy. Biofeedback Self Regul 6 (4): 523-35, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="3858296" MedlineID="85208603">Kolko DJ, Rickard-Figueroa JL: Effects of video games on the adverse corollaries of chemotherapy in pediatric oncology patients: a single-case analysis. J Consult Clin Psychol 53 (2): 223-8, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="8433358" MedlineID="93164238">Vasterling J, Jenkins RA, Tope DM, et al.: Cognitive distraction and relaxation training for the control of side effects due to cancer chemotherapy. J Behav Med 16 (1): 65-80, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="18941272">Chan CW, Cheng KK, Lam LW, et al.: Psycho-educational intervention for chemotherapy-associated nausea and vomiting in paediatric oncology patients: a pilot study. Hong Kong Med J 14 (5 Suppl): 32-5, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="24792499">Rock EM, Limebeer CL, Parker LA: Anticipatory nausea in animal models: a review of potential novel therapeutic treatments. Exp Brain Res 232 (8): 2511-34, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><Title>Etiology of Acute or Delayed Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting</Title><SummarySection id="_33"><Title>Acute Nausea and Vomiting (N&amp;V)</Title><Para id="_440"> The incidence of acute N&amp;V with moderate- or high-risk chemotherapy ranges from 30% to 90%.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> It can result in significant morbidity and can negatively affect quality of life. However, in recent years many new antiemetic medications and combinations have become available, dramatically decreasing the incidence and severity of this dreaded complication. Risk factors include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_772" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The emetogenic potential of the specific drug.</ListItem><ListItem>The dose used.</ListItem><ListItem>The treatment schedule.</ListItem><ListItem>How chemotherapy agents are combined.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_773">A drug with a low emetogenic potential given in high doses may cause a dramatic increase in the potential to induce N&amp;V.<Reference refidx="4"/> For example, standard doses of cytarabine rarely produce N&amp;V, but high doses often do. Another influence is the use of drug combinations. Because most patients receive combination chemotherapy, the emetogenic potential of all of the drugs combined and individual drug doses needs to be considered.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_472">Other risk factors include the following:<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_473" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Poor control with previous chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Female gender.</ListItem><ListItem>Age younger than 50 years.</ListItem><ListItem>Experience with previous chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>History of motion sickness.</ListItem><ListItem>History of morning sickness during pregnancy.</ListItem><ListItem>Dehydration.</ListItem><ListItem>Malnutrition.</ListItem><ListItem>Recent surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_474">The American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) provides a summary of intravenous chemotherapeutic agents and their respective risk of acute and delayed emesis.<Reference refidx="10"/> For more information, see Table 2.</Para><Table id="_825"><Title>Table 2.  Intravenous Chemotherapeutic Agents and Their Risk of Acute and Delayed Emesis<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>High Risk</entry><entry>Moderate Risk</entry><entry>Low Risk</entry><entry>Minimal Risk</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>From Hesketh et al.<Reference refidx="10"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Emesis has been documented in &gt;90% of patients.</entry><entry>Emesis has been documented in 30%–90% of patients.</entry><entry>Emesis has been documented in 10%–30% of patients.</entry><entry>Emesis has been documented in &lt;10% of patients.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Anthracycline/cyclophosphamide combination</entry><entry>Alemtuzumab</entry><entry>Aflibercept</entry><entry>Bevacizumab</entry></Row><Row><entry>Carmustine</entry><entry>Azacitidine</entry><entry>Atezolizumab</entry><entry>Bleomycin</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cisplatin</entry><entry>Bendamustine</entry><entry>Belinostat</entry><entry>Busulfan</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cyclophosphamide (≥1,500 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>)</entry><entry>Carboplatin</entry><entry>Blinatumomab</entry><entry>Cladribine</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dacarbazine</entry><entry>Clofarabine</entry><entry>Bortezomib</entry><entry>Daratumumab</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dactinomycin</entry><entry>Cyclophosphamide (&lt;1,500 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>)</entry><entry>Brentuximab.</entry><entry>Fludarabine</entry></Row><Row><entry>Mechlorethamine</entry><entry>Cytarabine (&gt;1,000 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>)</entry><entry>Cabazitaxel</entry><entry>Nivolumab</entry></Row><Row><entry>Streptozotocin</entry><entry>Daunorubicin</entry><entry>Carfilzomib</entry><entry>Obinutuzumab</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Doxorubicin</entry><entry>Cetuximab</entry><entry>Ofatumumab</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Epirubicin</entry><entry>Cytarabine (&lt;1,000 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>)</entry><entry>Pembrolizumab</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Idarubicin</entry><entry>Docetaxel</entry><entry>Pralatrexate</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Ifosfamide</entry><entry>Elotuzumab</entry><entry>Ramucirumab</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Irinotecan</entry><entry>Eribulin</entry><entry>Rituximab</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Irinotecan liposomal injection</entry><entry>Etoposide</entry><entry>Trastuzumab</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Oxaliplatin</entry><entry>Fluorouracil</entry><entry>Vinblastine</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Romidepsin</entry><entry>Gemcitabine</entry><entry>Vincristine</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Temozolomide</entry><entry>Ipilimumab</entry><entry>Vinorelbine</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Thiotepa</entry><entry>Ixabepilone</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Trabectedin</entry><entry>Methotrexate</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Mitomycin</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Mitoxantrone</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Nab-paclitaxel</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Necitumumab</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Paclitaxel</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Panitumumab</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Pegylated liposomal doxorubicin</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Pemetrexed</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Pertuzumab</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Temsirolimus</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Topotecan</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Trastuzumab-emtansine</entry><entry/></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_683">	ASCO also provides a summary of oral chemotherapeutic agents and their respective risk of acute and delayed emesis.<Reference refidx="10"/> For more information, see Table 3.</Para><Table id="_827"><Title>Table 3.  Oral Chemotherapeutic Agents and Their Risk of Acute and Delayed Emesis<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>High Risk</entry><entry>Moderate Risk</entry><entry>Low Risk</entry><entry>Minimal Risk</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>From Hesketh et al.<Reference refidx="10"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Emesis has been documented in &gt;90% of patients.</entry><entry>Emesis has been documented in 30%–90% of patients.</entry><entry>Emesis has been documented in 10%–30% of patients.</entry><entry>Emesis has been documented in &lt;10% of patients.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Altretamine</entry><entry>Bosutinib</entry><entry>Afatinib</entry><entry>Chlorambucil</entry></Row><Row><entry>Procarbazine</entry><entry>Cabozantinib</entry><entry>Alectinib</entry><entry>Erlotinib</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Ceritinib</entry><entry>Axitinib</entry><entry>Gefitinib</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Crizotinib</entry><entry>Capecitabine</entry><entry>Hydroxyurea</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Cyclophosphamide</entry><entry>Cobimetinib</entry><entry>Melphalan</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Dabrafenib</entry><entry>Methotrexate</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Lenvatinib</entry><entry>Dasatinib</entry><entry>Pomalidomide</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Temozolomide</entry><entry>Etoposide</entry><entry>Ruxolitinib</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Trifluridine-tipiracil</entry><entry>Everolimus</entry><entry>Sorafenib</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Vinorelbine</entry><entry>Fludarabine</entry><entry>Thioguanine</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Ibrutinib</entry><entry>Vemurafenib</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Idelalisib</entry><entry>Vismodegib</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Ixazomib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Lapatinib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Lenalidomide</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Olaparib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Osimertinib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Nilotinib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Palbociclib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Panobinostat</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Pazopanib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Ponatinib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Regorafenib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Sonidegib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Sunitinib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Thalidomide</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Trametinib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Vandetanib</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Venetoclax</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Vorinostat</entry><entry/></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Delayed N&amp;V</Title><Para id="_51">Delayed (or late) N&amp;V occurs
more than 24 hours after chemotherapy administration.  Delayed N&amp;V is associated with
cisplatin, cyclophosphamide, and other drugs (e.g., doxorubicin and ifosfamide)
given at high doses or given on 2 or more consecutive days.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_154" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Etiologies: Patients who experience acute emesis with chemotherapy are significantly more
likely to have delayed emesis.</ListItem><ListItem>Risk factors: All predictive characteristics for acute emesis are considered risk
factors for delayed emesis.</ListItem><ListItem>Emetic classifications: For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062747#_33" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">Acute Nausea and Vomiting (N&amp;V)</SummaryRef> section.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21553313">Hesketh PJ, Sanz-Altamira P, Bushey J, et al.: Prospective evaluation of the incidence of delayed nausea and vomiting in patients with colorectal cancer receiving oxaliplatin-based chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 20 (5): 1043-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25227565">Schwartzberg L: Addressing the value of novel therapies in chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Expert Rev Pharmacoecon Outcomes Res 14 (6): 825-34, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23480814">Sekine I, Segawa Y, Kubota K, et al.: Risk factors of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: index for personalized antiemetic prophylaxis. Cancer Sci 104 (6): 711-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10989249" MedlineID="20446002">Roscoe JA, Morrow GR, Hickok JT, et al.: Nausea and vomiting remain a significant clinical problem: trends over time in controlling chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in 1413 patients treated in community clinical practices. J Pain Symptom Manage 20 (2): 113-21, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="22842698">Viale PH, Grande C, Moore S: Efficacy and cost: avoiding undertreatment of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Clin J Oncol Nurs 16 (4): E133-41, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="22763232">Dranitsaris G, Bouganim N, Milano C, et al.: Prospective validation of a prediction tool for identifying patients at high risk for chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. J Support Oncol 11 (1): 14-21, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21370520">Kris MG, Urba SG, Schwartzberg LS: Clinical roundtable monograph. Treatment of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a post-MASCC 2010 discussion. Clin Adv Hematol Oncol 9 (1): suppl 1-15, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="20824866">Phillips RS, Gopaul S, Gibson F, et al.: Antiemetic medication for prevention and treatment of chemotherapy induced nausea and vomiting in childhood. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (9): CD007786, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="20803222">Olver I, Clark-Snow RA, Ballatori E, et al.: Guidelines for the control of nausea and vomiting with chemotherapy of low or minimal emetic potential. Support Care Cancer 19 (Suppl 1): S33-6, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="28759346">Hesketh PJ, Kris MG, Basch E, et al.: Antiemetics: American Society of Clinical Oncology Clinical Practice Guideline Update. J Clin Oncol 35 (28): 3240-3261, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="15718327">Geling O, Eichler HG: Should 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 receptor antagonists be administered beyond 24 hours after chemotherapy to prevent delayed emesis? Systematic re-evaluation of clinical evidence and drug cost implications. J Clin Oncol 23 (6): 1289-94, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="22942805">Fleishman SB, Mahajan D, Rosenwald V, et al.: Prevalence of Delayed Nausea and/or Vomiting in Patients Treated With Oxaliplatin-Based Regimens for Colorectal Cancer. J Oncol Pract 8 (3): 136-40, 2012.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_66"><Title>Prevention and Management of Acute or Delayed Nausea and Vomiting</Title><Para id="_67">Several organizations—including the American Society of Clinical Oncology, the National Comprehensive Cancer Network, and the Pediatric Oncology Group of Ontario—have published antiemetic guidelines for their members.  PDQ does not endorse specific guidelines, but examples can be found in the literature.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_508">Antiemetic agents are the most common intervention for
treatment-related nausea and vomiting (N&amp;V).  The basis for antiemetic therapy is the
neurochemical control of vomiting.  Although the exact mechanism is not well
understood, peripheral neuroreceptors and the chemoreceptor trigger zone (CTZ)
are known to contain receptors for serotonin, histamine (H1 and H2), dopamine,
acetylcholine, opioids, and numerous other endogenous neurotransmitters.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> Many antiemetics act by competitively blocking receptors for these substances,
which inhibit stimulation of peripheral nerves at the CTZ and possibly at
the vomiting center.</Para><Para id="_501">Current guidelines <Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  recommend that prechemotherapy management of chemotherapy-induced N&amp;V (CINV) be based on the emetogenic potential of the chemotherapy agent(s) selected.  For patients receiving regimens with high emetogenic potential, the combination of a 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>) receptor antagonist, neurokinin-1 (NK-1) receptor antagonist, and dexamethasone with or without olanzapine is recommended prechemotherapy.  Aprepitant (if chosen as the NK-1 receptor antagonist prechemotherapy), olanzapine, and dexamethasone are recommended for the prevention of delayed emesis. Guidelines differ with respect to using a three- or four-drug regimen for prophylaxis for highly emetogenic chemotherapy. One guideline includes the option of omitting an NK-1 antagonist completely if dexamethasone, palonosetron, and olanzapine are used.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_502">For patients receiving moderately emetogenic chemotherapy, the combination of a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist and dexamethasone is used prechemotherapy.  Patients receiving carboplatin (area under the curve ≥4 mg/mL) may also receive an NK-1 receptor antagonist.  Postchemotherapy, a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, dexamethasone, or both are recommended for the prevention of delayed emesis.</Para><Para id="_503">For regimens with low emetogenic potential, dexamethasone or a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist is recommended.  For regimens with minimal emetogenic risk, no prophylaxis is recommended.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_504">Antiemetic guidelines <Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  have included oral 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists as optional therapy for the prevention of delayed emesis, but the level of evidence supporting this practice is low.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_505">Studies have strongly suggested that patients experience more acute and delayed CINV  than is perceived by practitioners.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> One study suggested that patients who are highly expectant of nausea appear to experience more postchemotherapy nausea.<Reference refidx="11"/>   In addition, the current and new agents that have been used as prophylaxis for acute and  delayed CINV  have not been studied for use in established CINV. One study reported the effective use of intravenous (IV) palonosetron and dexamethasone to prevent CINV in patients receiving multiple-day chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_506">Table 4 summarizes prechemotherapy and postchemotherapy recommendations by emetogenic potential.</Para><Table id="_696"><Title>Table 4.  Antiemetic Recommendations by Emetic Risk Categories<Superscript>a,b</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Emetic Risk Category</entry><entry>ASCO Guidelines</entry><entry>MASCC Guidelines</entry><entry>NCCN Guidelines</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> = 5-hydroxytryptamine-3; ASCO = American Society of Clinical Oncology; AUC = area under the curve; MASCC = Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer; NCCN = National Comprehensive Cancer Network; NK-1 = neurokinin-1.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from National Comprehensive Cancer Network,<Reference refidx="7"/> Roila et al.,<Reference refidx="13"/> and Hesketh et al.<Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Order of listed antiemetics does not reflect preference.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="5">High risk (&gt;90%) </entry><entry MoreRows="1">4-drug combination of NK-1 antagonist, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, dexamethasone, and olanzapine recommended prechemotherapy</entry><entry MoreRows="5">3-drug combination of NK-1 antagonist, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, and dexamethasone recommended prechemotherapy</entry><entry>3-drug combination of NK-1 antagonist, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, and dexamethasone prechemotherapy</entry></Row><Row><entry>Note: Depending on NK-1 antagonist, dosing may be ≥1 day</entry></Row><Row><entry>Olanzapine and dexamethasone to be continued on days 2–4</entry><entry><Emphasis><Strong>OR:</Strong></Emphasis> Olanzapine (5–10 mg), palonosetron (0.25 mg), and dexamethasone (12 mg) prechemotherapy, followed by olanzapine (5–10 mg) daily on days 2–4</entry></Row><Row><entry>For anthracycline and cyclophosphamide combinations only, olanzapine to be continued on days 2–4</entry><entry><Emphasis><Strong>OR:</Strong></Emphasis> Four-drug combination of NK-1 antagonist, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, dexamethasone, and olanzapine  recommended prechemotherapy</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Note: Depending on NK-1 antagonist, dosing may be ≥1 day</entry><entry>Olanzapine and dexamethasone to be continued on days 2–4</entry></Row><Row><entry>Note: Depending on NK-1 antagonist, dosing may be ≥1 day</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Moderate risk (30%–90%) </entry><entry>Carboplatin AUC ≥4 mg/mL per min; 3-drug combination of NK-1 antagonist, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, and dexamethasone recommended prechemotherapy</entry><entry>For carboplatin-containing regimens, 3-drug combination of NK-1 antagonist, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, and dexamethasone recommended prechemotherapy</entry><entry>2-drug combination of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist and dexamethasone followed by dexamethasone (8 mg) on days 2–3 <Emphasis><Strong>OR:</Strong></Emphasis> 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist monotherapy on days 2–3</entry></Row><Row><entry>For patients receiving chemotherapies of moderate emetic risk excluding carboplatin AUC ≥4 mg/mL per min, 2-drug combination of  5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist and dexamethasone recommended prechemotherapy</entry><entry>For patients receiving chemotherapies of moderate emetic risk excluding carboplatin, 2-drug combination of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist and dexamethasone recommended prechemotherapy</entry><entry><Emphasis><Strong>OR:</Strong></Emphasis> Olanzapine (5–10 mg), palonosetron (0.25 mg), and dexamethasone (12 mg) prechemotherapy, followed by olanzapine (5–10 mg daily) on days 2–3</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">For patients receiving cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, oxaliplatin, and other moderate-emetic-risk antineoplastic agents known to cause delayed nausea, dexamethasone may be offered on days 2–3 for prevention of delayed emesis</entry><entry MoreRows="1">For patients receiving cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, or oxaliplatin, dexamethasone may be offered on days 2–3 for prevention of delayed emesis</entry><entry><Emphasis><Strong>OR:</Strong></Emphasis> 3-drug combination of  NK-1 antagonist, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, and dexamethasone recommended prechemotherapy, followed by dexamethasone (8 mg) on days 2–3</entry></Row><Row><entry>Note: depending on NK-1 antagonist, dosing may be ≥1 day</entry></Row><Row><entry>Low risk  (10%–30%) </entry><entry>Single dose of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist or dexamethasone (8 mg) recommended</entry><entry>Single dose of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist or dexamethasone or dopamine antagonist recommended</entry><entry>Single dose of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist or dexamethasone (8–12 mg) or  metoclopramide (10–20 mg) or prochlorperazine (10 mg) recommended</entry></Row><Row><entry>Minimal risk (&lt;10%) </entry><entry>No antiemetic administered routinely pre- or postchemotherapy</entry><entry>No routine prophylaxis recommended</entry><entry>No routine prophylaxis recommended</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_481">Most drugs with proven antiemetic activity can be
categorized into one of the following groups:</Para><ItemizedList id="_193" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Competitive antagonists at
dopaminergic (D<Subscript>2</Subscript> subtype) receptors: <ItemizedList id="_194" Style="dash"><ListItem>Phenothiazines.</ListItem><ListItem>Butyrophenones (droperidol, haloperidol).</ListItem><ListItem>Substituted benzamides (metoclopramide).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Competitive antagonists at serotonergic (5-hydroxytryptamine-3 or
5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> subtype) receptors.</ListItem><ListItem>Substance P antagonists (NK-1 receptor antagonists).</ListItem><ListItem>Corticosteroids.</ListItem><ListItem>Benzodiazepines (lorazepam).</ListItem><ListItem>Cannabinoids.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_195">Although Table 5 lists all routes of administration, the intramuscular (IM) route is used only when no
other access is available.  IM delivery is painful, is associated
with erratic absorption of drug, and may lead to sterile abscess formation or
fibrosis of the tissues.  This is particularly important when more than one or two
doses of a drug are to be given.</Para><Table id="_694"><Title>Table 5.  Prevention of Acute or Delayed CINV</Title><TGroup Cols="6"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="15.55%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="17.69%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="20.54%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="11.87%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="18.52%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="15.79%"/><THead><Row><entry>Drug Category</entry><entry>Medication</entry><entry>Dose</entry><entry>Available Route</entry><entry>Comment(s)</entry><entry>Reference(s)</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1">5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> = 5-hydroxytryptamine-3; bid = twice a day; CINV = chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting; EPS = extrapyramidal symptoms; IM = intramuscular; IV = intravenous; NK-1 = neurokinin-1; PO = oral; PR = rectal; qd = every day; SL = sublingual; SQ = subcutaneous.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Dolasetron may be difficult to obtain from the manufacturer.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Dopamine antagonists: phenothiazines</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Chlorpromazine</entry><entry>10–25 mg PO q4–6h</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO, IM </entry><entry MoreRows="1">Prolongs QT interval</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/> <Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>25–50 mg IM q3–4h</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Prochlorperazine</entry><entry>25 mg PR q12h</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO, IM, IV, PR</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Less sedation but increased risk of EPS</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>5–10 mg PO/IM/IV q6–8h</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Promethazine</entry><entry MoreRows="1">12.5–25 mg q4–6h</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO, IM, IV, PR</entry><entry>Vesicant</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Weak antiemetic</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Dopamine antagonists: butyrophenones</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Haloperidol</entry><entry MoreRows="2">0.5–5 mg q24h in divided doses</entry><entry MoreRows="2">PO, IV, IM</entry><entry>Used for treatment</entry><entry MoreRows="2"><Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Rarely used for prophylaxis</entry></Row><Row><entry>Prolongs QT interval</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Droperidol</entry><entry MoreRows="1">1–2.5 mg/dose q2–6h</entry><entry MoreRows="1">IV, IM</entry><entry>Prolongs QT interval</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/> <Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Used primarily for treatment</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Dopamine antagonists: substituted benzamides</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Metoclopramide</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Prevention of CINV: 1–2 mg/kg IV x1 dose prechemotherapy; then x2 doses q2h; then x3 doses q3h</entry><entry MoreRows="2">PO, IM, IV</entry><entry>EPS associated with higher doses; patients &lt;30 y</entry><entry MoreRows="2"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Pretreat with diphenhydramine to prevent EPS</entry></Row><Row><entry>Treatment of CINV: 10–40 mg PO q4–6h; up to 0.5 mg/kg PO q6h</entry><entry>Enhances gastric emptying</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Trimethobenzamide</entry><entry>300 mg PO q6–8h</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO, IM</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Unavailable in the United States</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/> <Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>200 mg IM q6–8h</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="7">Serotonin (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>) receptor antagonists</entry><entry>Dolasetron<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>100 mg within 1 h prechemotherapy</entry><entry>PO</entry><entry>IV form withdrawn from market due to QTc prolongation</entry><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Granisetron</entry><entry>1–2 mg PO or 10 µg/kg up to 1 mg IV within 1 h of chemotherapy</entry><entry MoreRows="2">IV, PO, topical, SQ</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Transdermal patch applied 24 h prechemotherapy; may be left in place ≤1 wk</entry><entry MoreRows="2"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>3.1 mg/24 h transdermally</entry></Row><Row><entry>10 mg SQ ≥30 min prechemotherapy</entry><entry>SQ extended release should  not be given more than once q7d</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Ondansetron</entry><entry>0.15 mg/kg IV 30 min prechemotherapy; then may be repeated 4 and 8 h later; maximum: 16 mg/24 h</entry><entry MoreRows="2">PO, IV</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Doses &gt;16 mg not recommended due to QTc prolongation</entry><entry MoreRows="2"><Reference refidx="14"/> <Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>24 mg PO 30 min before highly emetogenic single-day chemotherapy</entry></Row><Row><entry>8 mg PO 30 min before moderate-emetogenic-risk chemotherapy, followed in 8 h by 8 mg then 8 mg PO q12h for 1–2 d</entry><entry>Post-approval studies show 8 mg IV equivalent to larger doses</entry></Row><Row><entry>Palonosetron</entry><entry>0.25 mg IV or 0.5 mg PO 30 min prechemotherapy day 1</entry><entry>IV, PO</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="11">Substance P antagonists (NK-1 receptor antagonists)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Aprepitant</entry><entry MoreRows="1">125 mg prechemotherapy day 1, then 80 mg daily x2 d</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO</entry><entry>CYP3A4 enzyme inhibitor</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>CYP2C9 enzyme inducer</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Aprepitant, emulsion</entry><entry MoreRows="2">130 mg prechemotherapy day 1</entry><entry MoreRows="2">IV</entry><entry>Dose equivalent to fosaprepitant 150 mg</entry><entry MoreRows="2"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>CYP3A4 enzyme inhibitor</entry></Row><Row><entry>CYP2C9 enzyme inducer</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Fosaprepitant</entry><entry MoreRows="1">150 mg prechemotherapy day 1</entry><entry MoreRows="1">IV</entry><entry>CYP3A4 enzyme inhibitor</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>CYP2C9 enzyme inducer</entry></Row><Row><entry>Netupitant (combined with palonosetron)</entry><entry>Netupitant 300 mg/palonosetron 0.5 mg prechemotherapy day 1</entry><entry>PO</entry><entry>CYP3A4 enzyme inhibitor</entry><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Fosnetupitant (combined with palonosetron)</entry><entry>Fosnetupitant 235 mg/palonosetron 0.25 mg prechemotherapy day 1</entry><entry>IV</entry><entry>CYP3A4 enzyme inhibitor</entry><entry><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="18"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Rolapitant</entry><entry MoreRows="2">180 mg prechemotherapy day 1</entry><entry MoreRows="2">PO/IV</entry><entry>Anaphylactic reactions have occurred with IV infusion</entry><entry MoreRows="2"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Doses must be separated by ≥14 d</entry></Row><Row><entry>CYP2D6 enzyme inhibitor</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Corticosteroids</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Dexamethasone</entry><entry>12–20 mg before high-emetic-risk chemotherapy, followed by 8 mg 1–2 times/d for 3 d</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO, IV</entry><entry>Combined with a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>8 mg before moderate-emetic-risk chemotherapy, followed by 8 mg/d for 2 d</entry><entry>When given with (fos)aprepitant or (fos)netupitant, 12 mg = 20 mg on day 1, and 8 mg is equivalent on subsequent days due to drug interaction</entry></Row><Row><entry>Methylprednisolone</entry><entry>0.5–1 mg/kg 30 min pre- and 4 and 8 h postchemotherapy</entry><entry>PO, IV</entry><entry>Maximum 4 mg/kg/d; may also be given as single dose prechemotherapy</entry><entry><Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Benzodiazepines</entry><entry>Alprazolam</entry><entry>0.25–1 mg q6–8h</entry><entry>PO</entry><entry>Shortest half-life in drug class</entry><entry><Reference refidx="14"/> <Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Lorazepam</entry><entry>0.5–2 mg q6h</entry><entry>PO, SL, IM, IV</entry><entry>Most-commonly used in drug class</entry><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Atypical antipsychotics</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Olanzapine</entry><entry>Prevention of acute and delayed CINV in combination with 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, dexamethasone, and NK-1 antagonist: 10 mg PO qd days 1–4</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Consider giving at bedtime due to sedation</entry><entry><Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Treatment of breakthrough CINV: 10 mg PO daily x3 d</entry><entry><Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Other pharmacological agents</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Dronabinol</entry><entry>5 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> PO 1–3 h prechemotherapy, followed every 2–4 h by same dose, up to 4–6 doses/d</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO</entry><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Dose may be increased in increments of 2.5 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, up to maximum 15 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry>Nabilone</entry><entry>1–2 mg bid, maximum 6 mg/d in 3 doses</entry><entry>PO</entry><entry>May be continued up to 48 h postchemotherapy</entry><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName></entry><entry>No current data on dosing</entry><entry>Inhaled, PO</entry><entry>Currently, not enough data to recommend <ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName> products for prevention/treatment of CINV</entry><entry><Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Ginger</entry><entry>0.5–2 g/d prechemotherapy</entry><entry>PO</entry><entry>Current literature demonstrates conflicting efficacy results</entry><entry><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_698"><Title>Competitive Dopamine (D<Subscript>2</Subscript>) Antagonists</Title><SummarySection id="_699"><Title>Phenothiazines</Title><Para id="_700">Phenothiazines act on dopaminergic receptors at the CTZ, possibly at other central nervous system (CNS) centers, and peripherally.</Para><Para id="_701">In selecting phenothiazines, the primary consideration is assessing differences in adverse effect profiles, which correlate
with the structural classes of the drugs.  Generally, aliphatic phenothiazines (e.g.,
chlorpromazine) produce sedation and anticholinergic
effects, while piperazines (e.g., prochlorperazine) are associated with less sedation but higher
incidence of extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS) such as acute dystonias, akathisia, neuroleptic malignant syndrome (uncommon), and, rarely, akinesias and dyskinesias. Marked hypotension may also result if IV doses are administered rapidly at high doses. The concomitant use of H1 blockers, such as diphenhydramine, can often decrease the risk and severity of EPS. Phenothiazines may be of particular value in treating patients who experience delayed N&amp;V with cisplatin regimens.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] Given their anticholinergic properties, phenothiazines are listed in the American Geriatrics Society Beers Criteria for Potentially Inappropriate Medication Use in Older Adults.<Reference refidx="30"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_702"><Title>Butyrophenones</Title><Para id="_703">Droperidol and haloperidol represent butyrophenones, another class of dopaminergic (D<Subscript>2</Subscript> subtype) receptor
antagonists that are structurally and pharmacologically similar to the
phenothiazines.  While droperidol is used primarily as an adjunct to anesthesia
induction, haloperidol is indicated as a neuroleptic antipsychotic drug. However, both agents have some antiemetic activity.   Results of small, uncontrolled, open-label studies show  some efficacy for haloperidol in patients receiving palliative care.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/>  Both agents may produce
EPS, akathisia, hypotension, and sedation.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_704"><Title>Substituted benzamides</Title><Para id="_705">Metoclopramide is  a substituted benzamide, which, before  serotonin (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>)
receptor antagonists were introduced, was considered the most effective antiemetic agent
against highly emetogenic chemotherapy.  Although
metoclopramide is a competitive antagonist at dopaminergic (D<Subscript>2</Subscript>) receptors, it
is most effective against acute vomiting when given  IV at high doses, probably because it is a weak competitive antagonist
(relative to other serotonin antagonists) at 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptors.  It may act on
the CTZ and the periphery.  Metoclopramide also increases lower esophageal
sphincter pressure and enhances the rate of gastric emptying, which may factor
into its overall antiemetic effect.  Metoclopramide has also been safely given by IV bolus
injection at higher single doses (up to 6 mg/kg) and by continuous IV
infusion, with or without a loading bolus dose, with efficacy comparable to
that of multiple intermittent dosing schedules.<Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/></Para><Para id="_706">Metoclopramide is associated
with akathisia and dystonic EPS. Akathisia is seen more
frequently in patients older than 30 years, and dystonic EPS are seen more
commonly in patients younger than 30 years.  Diphenhydramine, benztropine
mesylate, and trihexyphenidyl are commonly used prophylactically or
therapeutically to pharmacologically antagonize EPS.<Reference refidx="36"/>  While cogwheeling rigidity, acute dystonia, and tremor are
responsive to anticholinergic medications, akathisia is best treated by lowering the metoclopramide dose, changing to a different agent, or adding a benzodiazepine.</Para><Para id="_707">Trimethobenzamide is believed to act centrally on the CTZ by blocking emetic impulses. It has been studied in a limited number of oncology patients experiencing nausea from various chemotherapy regimens.   Compared with placebo, trimethobenzamide, 200 mg IM every 6 hours for 2 days, significantly reduced episodes of N&amp;V.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_708"><Title>5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> Receptor Antagonists</Title><Para id="_709">Four serotonin receptor antagonists—ondansetron, granisetron, dolasetron,
and palonosetron—are available in the United States. Agents in this class are thought to
prevent N&amp;V by preventing serotonin, which is released from
enterochromaffin cells in the gastrointestinal (GI) mucosa, from initiating afferent
transmission to the CNS via vagal and spinal sympathetic nerves.<Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/>   The 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>
receptor antagonists may also block serotonin stimulation at the CTZ and other CNS
structures. Major side effects of this class of medications include mild headache and constipation. Multiple studies have shown that the 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists are most effective when given in conjunction with steroids.</Para><SummarySection id="_710"><Title>Comparison of agents</Title><Para id="_711">Studies suggest that there are no major
differences in efficacy or toxicity of the three first-generation 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists
(dolasetron, granisetron,  and ondansetron) in the treatment of acute CINV.  These three agents are equivalent in efficacy and
toxicity when used in appropriate doses.<Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/>; <Reference refidx="42"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]
These agents have  been shown to be effective in the first 24 hours postchemotherapy (acute phase), but not on days 2 to 5 postchemotherapy (delayed phase).</Para><Para id="_712">Palonosetron, the second-generation 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, has been approved for acute emesis with highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy and for delayed emesis in patients receiving moderately emetogenic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="43"/>; <Reference refidx="44"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_713">Despite the use of both first- and second-generation 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists, the control of acute CINV, especially delayed N&amp;V, is suboptimal. There is considerable opportunity for improvement with either the addition or substitution of new agents in current regimens.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="47"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_714"><Title>Ondansetron</Title><Para id="_715">Several studies have demonstrated that ondansetron produces an antiemetic
response that is equal or  superior to that of high doses of metoclopramide, but
with an improved toxicity profile, compared with that of dopaminergic antagonist
agents.<Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/>  A randomized trial of ondansetron, 8 mg and 32 mg,  given prophylactically to patients receiving cisplatin found no difference between the doses.<Reference refidx="54"/> A single-center, retrospective chart review has reported ondansetron-loading doses of 16 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> IV (maximum, 24 mg) to be safe in infants, children, and adolescents.<Reference refidx="55"/> However, data reported to the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) raise concerns about QT prolongation and potentially fatal arrhythmias with a single  32-mg IV dose. Current drug labeling calls for a maximum single 16-mg IV dose.<Reference refidx="56"/></Para><Para id="_716">Currently, oral and injectable ondansetron formulations are approved for
use without dosage modification in patients older than 4 years,
including elderly patients and patients with renal insufficiency.  Oral ondansetron
is given 3 times daily starting 30 minutes before chemotherapy and continuing
for up to 2 days after chemotherapy is completed.  Ondansetron clearance is diminished in patients
with severe hepatic insufficiency; these patients receive a
single injectable or oral dose no higher than 8 mg.  There is currently no
information evaluating the safety of repeated daily ondansetron doses
in patients with hepatic insufficiency. Other effective dosing schedules, such as a continuous IV infusion
(e.g., 1 mg/h for 24 h) or oral administration, have also been
evaluated.<Reference refidx="57"/></Para><Para id="_717">The major adverse effects of ondansetron include the following:<Reference refidx="58"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_718" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Headache (which can be
treated with mild analgesics).</ListItem><ListItem>Constipation.</ListItem><ListItem>Fatigue.</ListItem><ListItem>Dry mouth.</ListItem><ListItem>Transient asymptomatic elevations in liver function tests (alanine and aspartate transaminases), which may be related to concurrent
cisplatin administration.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_719">Ondansetron has been etiologically implicated in
a few case studies involving thrombocytopenia, renal insufficiency, and
thrombotic events.<Reference refidx="59"/>  Rare electrocardiogram changes in the form of QTc prolongation may occur. In addition, a few case reports have implicated
ondansetron in causing EPS.  However, it is not clear whether
the events described were in fact EPS. In other
reports, the evidence is confounded by concurrent use of other agents that are
known to produce EPS.  Nevertheless, the greatest advantage of serotonin
receptor antagonists over dopaminergic receptor antagonists is that they have
fewer adverse effects.
Despite prophylaxis with ondansetron, many patients receiving doxorubicin, cisplatin, or carboplatin will  experience acute and delayed N&amp;V.<Reference refidx="60"/> Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials support the addition of aprepitant, an NK-1 receptor antagonist, for additional mitigation of N&amp;V.<Reference refidx="61"/><Reference refidx="62"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_720"><Title>Granisetron</Title><Para id="_721">Granisetron has shown efficacy in preventing and controlling N&amp;V at a broad range of doses.  In the United States, granisetron injection, extended-release injection, transdermal patch, and oral tablets are
approved for initial and repeat prophylaxis for patients receiving emetogenic
chemotherapy, including high-dose cisplatin.  Granisetron is pharmacologically
and pharmacokinetically distinct from ondansetron. However, clinically it
is equally efficacious and equally safe.<Reference refidx="60"/><Reference refidx="61"/><Reference refidx="62"/><Reference refidx="63"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_722">The subcutaneous extended-release formulation of granisetron was compared with palonosetron to prevent CINV for patients receiving moderately or highly emetogenic chemotherapy in a randomized, double-blind noninferiority phase III trial.<Reference refidx="64"/>  Patients were randomly assigned to receive IV palonosetron, 0.25 mg; or subcutaneous granisetron, 5 mg or 10 mg.  Patients who received palonosetron in cycle 1 were then randomly assigned  to receive granisetron in cycles 2 through 4. Both subcutaneous doses of granisetron were noninferior to palonosetron in cycle 1 of moderately emetogenic chemotherapy (74.8% and 76.9% for granisetron 5 mg and 10 mg, respectively, vs. 75.0% for palonosetron) and highly emetogenic chemotherapy (77.7% and 81.3% for granisetron 5 mg and 10 mg, respectively, vs. 80.7% for palonosetron). Subcutaneous granisetron was not superior to palonosetron in the prevention of delayed CINV after highly emetogenic chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_723">Currently, granisetron is approved for use without dosage
modification in patients older than 2 years, including elderly patients and
patients with hepatic and renal insufficiency.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_724"><Title>Dolasetron</Title><Para id="_725">Oral formulations of dolasetron are indicated for the prevention of N&amp;V associated with moderately emetogenic cancer chemotherapy,
including initial and repeat courses. However, the drug may be difficult to obtain from the manufacturer.  Oral dolasetron may be dosed as 100
mg within 1 hour before chemotherapy.  Dolasetron was given IV or orally at 1.8
mg/kg as a single dose approximately 30 minutes before chemotherapy. However, injection formulations are no longer approved for CINV because of the risk of QTc interval prolongation.<Reference refidx="65"/></Para><Para id="_726">The effectiveness of oral dolasetron in the prevention of CINV has been proven in a large randomized, double-blind,
comparative trial of 399 patients.<Reference refidx="66"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]  Oral dolasetron was administered in the
range of 25  to 200 mg 1 hour before chemotherapy.  The other study arm
consisted of oral ondansetron (8 mg) administered 1.5 hours before chemotherapy
and every 8 hours after chemotherapy for a total of three doses.  Rates of complete response (CR), defined as no emetic
episodes and no use of escape antiemetic medications, improved with increasing doses of dolasetron.  Both dolasetron 200 mg and
ondansetron had significantly higher CR rates than did
dolasetron  25 or 50 mg.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_727"><Title>Palonosetron</Title><Para id="_728">Palonosetron is a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist   (second generation) that has antiemetic activity at both central and GI sites. Palonosetron is FDA approved for the prevention of acute N&amp;V associated with initial and repeat courses of moderately and highly emetogenic cancer chemotherapy and for the prevention of delayed N&amp;V associated with initial and repeat courses of moderately emetogenic cancer chemotherapy. Compared with the older 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists, palonosetron has a higher binding affinity to the 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptors, a higher potency, a significantly longer half-life (approximately 40 hours, four to five times longer than that of dolasetron, granisetron, or ondansetron), and an excellent safety profile.<Reference refidx="67"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] A dose-finding study demonstrated that the effective dose was 0.25 mg or higher.<Reference refidx="68"/><Reference refidx="69"/><Reference refidx="70"/><Reference refidx="71"/><Reference refidx="72"/></Para><Para id="_729">In two large studies of patients receiving moderately emetogenic chemotherapy, CR (no emesis, no rescue) was significantly improved in the acute and delayed periods for  patients who received 0.25 mg of palonosetron alone, compared with either ondansetron or dolasetron alone.<Reference refidx="43"/>; <Reference refidx="44"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] Dexamethasone was not given with the 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>  receptor antagonists in these studies, and it is not yet known whether  the differences in CR would persist if it were used.</Para><Para id="_795">In another study,<Reference refidx="73"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] 650 patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy (cisplatin ≥60 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) also received either dexamethasone and one of two doses of palonosetron (0.25 mg or 0.75 mg) or dexamethasone and ondansetron (32 mg). Single-dose palonosetron was as effective as ondansetron in preventing acute CINV with dexamethasone pretreatment. It was significantly more effective than ondansetron throughout the 5-day postchemotherapy period.  In an analysis of the patients in the above studies who received repeated cycles of chemotherapy, one study <Reference refidx="74"/>  reported that the CR rates for both  acute and delayed CINV  were maintained with  single IV doses of  palonosetron without concomitant corticosteroids.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_730"><Title>NK-1 Receptor Antagonists (Substance P Antagonists)</Title><Para id="_731">Substance P, found in the vagal afferent neurons in the nucleus tractus solitarius, the abdominal vagus, and the area postrema, induces vomiting. NK-1 receptor antagonists, including aprepitant, fosaprepitant, netupitant, fosnetupitant, and rolapitant, block substance P from binding to the NK-1 receptor.  In combination with a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist and a corticosteroid, NK-1 receptor antagonists are indicated for the prevention of acute and delayed N&amp;V associated with initial and repeat courses of highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy. There have been no randomized trials comparing the individual NK-1 receptor antagonists.  All are considered effective at their FDA-approved doses.</Para><SummarySection id="_732"><Title>Aprepitant and fosaprepitant</Title><Para id="_733">Clinical trials <Reference refidx="75"/><Reference refidx="76"/><Reference refidx="77"/><Reference refidx="78"/> demonstrated that the addition of aprepitant to a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist plus dexamethasone before cisplatin chemotherapy improved the control of acute emesis, compared with a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist plus dexamethasone. This regimen also improved the control of delayed emesis, compared with placebo. In two randomized, double-blind, parallel, controlled studies, patients received cisplatin (≥70 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) and were randomly assigned to receive either (1) standard therapy with ondansetron and dexamethasone prechemotherapy and dexamethasone on days 2 to 4 postchemotherapy or (2) standard therapy plus aprepitant prechemotherapy on days 2 and 3.<Reference refidx="79"/><Reference refidx="80"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] The CR (no emesis, no rescue) of the aprepitant group in both studies was significantly higher in both the acute and the delayed periods. An additional study confirmed the efficacy of aprepitant in the delayed period, when it was compared with ondansetron.<Reference refidx="81"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] Finally, aprepitant has been shown to be efficacious in preventing N&amp;V in breast cancer patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy with cyclophosphamide and doxorubicin.<Reference refidx="82"/></Para><Para id="_734">The benefit of aprepitant has also been demonstrated outside of highly emetogenic chemotherapy. The addition of aprepitant to ondansetron and dexamethasone before moderately emetogenic chemotherapy versus ondansetron and dexamethasone alone resulted in improved CINV outcomes.<Reference refidx="83"/><Reference refidx="84"/><Reference refidx="85"/> An alternative dosing strategy was evaluated in a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase III crossover study in patients receiving 5-day cisplatin combination chemotherapy for germ cell tumors.<Reference refidx="86"/> In addition to standard antiemetic therapy, patients received aprepitant 125 mg on day 3, followed by aprepitant 80 mg on days 4 through 7.  There was a significant improvement in CINV CR with the three-drug regimen.</Para><Para id="_735">Fosaprepitant dimeglumine, a water-soluble, phosphorylated analog of aprepitant, is rapidly converted to aprepitant after IV administration.<Reference refidx="87"/> Fosaprepitant is approved as a single dose of 150 mg before chemotherapy on day 1, as an alternative to the 3-day oral aprepitant regimen. As demonstrated in a randomized, double-blind study of patients receiving cisplatin chemotherapy, single-dose IV fosaprepitant (150 mg) given with ondansetron and dexamethasone was noninferior to the standard 3-day dosing of oral aprepitant in preventing CINV.<Reference refidx="87"/> Fosaprepitant is formulated with polysorbate 80, a solubilizing agent, which can cause rare but serious hypersensitivity reactions.<Reference refidx="88"/><Reference refidx="89"/> Aprepitant is also available in a parenteral emulsion form, which has a reduced risk of thrombophlebitis and hypersensitivity reactions.<Reference refidx="90"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_736"><Title>Netupitant and fosnetupitant</Title><Para id="_737">Netupitant  is a competitive antagonist to the NK-1 receptor that is marketed as either an oral fixed-combination product containing 300 mg of netupitant and 0.5 mg of palonosetron (NEPA) or an IV fixed-combination product containing 235 mg of fosnetupitant and 0.25 mg of palonosetron. Of note, the IV formulation of NEPA does not contain the surfactant polysorbate 80 or any other allergenic excipients and could be considered for patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to fosaprepitant.<Reference refidx="91"/><LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">[Level of evidence: I]</LOERef> It is given with dexamethasone before chemotherapy to prevent both acute and delayed CINV.  This drug combination has been used successfully for prevention of CINV in a single cycle of both highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy regimens.<Reference refidx="92"/><Reference refidx="93"/> </Para><Para id="_797">The antiemetic benefit of NEPA was demonstrated throughout multiple cycles of chemotherapy in a randomized, double-blind, controlled trial.<Reference refidx="94"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] Patients starting combination anthracycline/cyclophosphamide regimens were randomly assigned to receive oral fixed-dose NEPA with 12 mg of dexamethasone or 0.5 mg of oral palonosetron with 20 mg of dexamethasone. The percentage of patients with a CR was significantly greater for NEPA than for oral palonosetron for cycles 1 to 4. The most common treatment-related side effects, headache and constipation, were similar between the two arms.</Para><Para id="_798">A Japanese study compared single-agent fosnetupitant to fosaprepitant combined with palonosetron and dexamethasone in patients receiving highly emetic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="95"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] Fosnetupitant was found to be noninferior to the fosaprepitant regimen. Additionally, fosnetupitant had an improved safety profile with fewer injection site reactions (11% vs. 20.6%, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). Single-agent fosnetupitant is not currently FDA approved in the United States.</Para><Para id="_785">Similarly, NEPA has been compared with granisetron and aprepitant in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy.  In a phase III, randomized, double-blind study, a single dose of NEPA was shown to be noninferior to  a 3-day regimen of granisetron and aprepitant.  Additionally, significantly more patients did not need rescue medications when they received NEPA (96.6%), compared with those who received  granisetron plus aprepitant (93.5%). Toxicities were similar between treatment arms.<Reference refidx="96"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_738"><Title>Rolapitant</Title><Para id="_739">Rolapitant is an oral competitive NK-1 receptor inhibitor. It is approved for the prevention of delayed N&amp;V associated with highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy. In addition to granisetron and dexamethasone, rolapitant significantly increases CINV CR versus standard therapy plus placebo for patients receiving both highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy.  Unlike other drugs in its class, rolapitant has no effect on cytochrome P450 3A4 enzymes; therefore, no dose adjustment for dexamethasone is required.<Reference refidx="97"/><Reference refidx="98"/><Reference refidx="99"/> The IV formulation has been associated with hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, which have limited its use.<Reference refidx="100"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_740"><Title>Corticosteroids</Title><Para id="_741">Steroids are commonly used in combination with other antiemetics. Their antiemetic mechanism of action is not fully
understood, but they may affect prostaglandin activity in the brain.
Clinically, steroids quantitatively decrease or eliminate episodes of N&amp;V and may improve patients’ mood, producing a subjective sense
of well-being or euphoria (although they also can cause depression and
anxiety).  Steroids are sometimes used as single agents against mildly emetogenic chemotherapy but are more often used in antiemetic drug
combinations.<Reference refidx="101"/><Reference refidx="102"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="103"/></Para><Para id="_742">Steroids are given orally or intravenously before chemotherapy and may be repeated.  Dosages and administration schedules are selected empirically.
Dexamethasone is often the treatment of choice for N&amp;V
in patients receiving radiation to the brain, as it also reduces cerebral
edema.  It is administered orally or intravenously in the
dose range of 8 mg  to 40 mg (pediatric dose, 0.25–0.5 mg/kg).<Reference refidx="104"/><Reference refidx="105"/> 
Methylprednisolone is also administered orally or
intravenously at doses and schedules that vary from 40 mg  to 500 mg every 6 to
12 hours for up to 20 doses.<Reference refidx="102"/><Reference refidx="106"/></Para><Para id="_743">Dexamethasone is also used orally for delayed N&amp;V.  Long-term
corticosteroid use, however, is inappropriate and may cause substantial  
morbidity, including the following:<Reference refidx="107"/><Reference refidx="108"/><Reference refidx="109"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_744" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Immunosuppression.</ListItem><ListItem>Proximal muscle weakness (especially  
involving the thighs and upper arms).</ListItem><ListItem>Aseptic necrosis of the long bones.</ListItem><ListItem>Cataract formation.</ListItem><ListItem>Hyperglycemia and exacerbation of preexisting diabetes or
escalation of subclinical diabetes to clinical pathology.</ListItem><ListItem>Adrenal suppression
with hypocortisolism.</ListItem><ListItem>Lethargy.</ListItem><ListItem>Weight gain.</ListItem><ListItem>GI irritation.</ListItem><ListItem>Insomnia.</ListItem><ListItem>Anxiety.</ListItem><ListItem>Mood changes.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychosis.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_745">A study that examined chemotherapy in a group of patients with ovarian cancer found that short-term use of glucocorticoids as antiemetics had  no negative effects on outcomes (e.g., overall survival or efficacy of chemotherapy).<Reference refidx="110"/> As previously shown with metoclopramide,
numerous studies have demonstrated that dexamethasone potentiates the
antiemetic properties of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor–blocking agents.<Reference refidx="107"/><Reference refidx="111"/>  If administered intravenously, dexamethasone may be given over 10 to 15 minutes because rapid
administration may cause sensations of generalized warmth, pharyngeal tingling
or burning, or acute transient perineal and/or rectal pain.<Reference refidx="112"/><Reference refidx="113"/><Reference refidx="114"/><Reference refidx="115"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_746"><Title>Benzodiazepines</Title><Para id="_747">Benzodiazepines, such as lorazepam and alprazolam, are valuable adjuncts in the prevention and treatment of anxiety and
the symptoms of anticipatory N&amp;V associated with chemotherapy,
especially with the highly emetogenic regimens given to children.<Reference refidx="107"/><Reference refidx="108"/><Reference refidx="109"/>  Benzodiazepines have not demonstrated intrinsic
antiemetic activity as single agents, so they are adjuncts to other antiemetic agents in antiemetic
prophylaxis and treatment.<Reference refidx="116"/> 
Benzodiazepines presumably act on higher CNS structures, the brainstem, and
spinal cord, and they produce anxiolytic, sedative, and anterograde amnesic
effects.  In addition, these drugs markedly decrease the severity of EPS, especially
akathisia, associated with dopaminergic receptor antagonist antiemetics.</Para><Para id="_748">The adverse effects of lorazepam include sedation, perceptual and vision disturbances, anterograde amnesia, confusion, ataxia, and depressed mental acuity.<Reference refidx="117"/>;<Reference refidx="118"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="119"/><Reference refidx="120"/> Alprazolam has been shown to be effective when
given in combination with metoclopramide and methylprednisolone.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_749"><Title>Olanzapine</Title><Para id="_750">Olanzapine is an antipsychotic in the thienobenzodiazepine drug class that blocks multiple neurotransmitters: dopamine at D<Subscript>1</Subscript>, D<Subscript>2</Subscript>, D<Subscript>3</Subscript>, and D<Subscript>4</Subscript> brain receptors; serotonin at 5-HT<Subscript>2a</Subscript>, 5-HT<Subscript>2c</Subscript>, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>, and 5-HT<Subscript>6</Subscript> receptors; catecholamines at alpha-1 adrenergic receptors;  acetylcholine at muscarinic receptors; and histamine at H<Subscript>1</Subscript> receptors.<Reference refidx="121"/>  Common side effects include the following:<Reference refidx="122"/><Reference refidx="123"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_751" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Sedation.</ListItem><ListItem>Dry mouth.</ListItem><ListItem>Increased appetite.</ListItem><ListItem>Weight gain.</ListItem><ListItem>Postural hypotension.</ListItem><ListItem>Dizziness.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_752">Olanzapine’s activity at multiple receptors, particularly at the D<Subscript>2</Subscript> and 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptors that appear to be involved in N&amp;V, suggests that it may have significant antiemetic properties.<Reference refidx="124"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>] Subsequent studies have shown its effectiveness as a CINV antiemetic.<Reference refidx="125"/><Reference refidx="126"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]  A large study <Reference refidx="127"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] demonstrated that in patients receiving either highly emetogenic chemotherapy or moderately emetogenic chemotherapy, the addition of olanzapine to azasetron and dexamethasone improved the CR of delayed CINV.</Para><Para id="_753">A randomized, double-blind, phase III trial evaluated olanzapine versus placebo in addition to standard antiemetics for the prevention of CINV associated with highly emetogenic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]  Chemotherapy-naïve patients receiving either (1) cisplatin at least 70 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> of body surface area (BSA) with or without additional agents or (2) doxorubicin 60 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> of BSA with cyclophosphamide 600 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> of BSA were randomly assigned to receive olanzapine 10 mg orally on days 1 through 4 or matching placebo with guideline-directed antiemetics.  The antiemetic regimen included an NK-1 antagonist (fosaprepitant or aprepitant), 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist (palonosetron, granisetron, or ondansetron), and dexamethasone 12 mg on day 1, followed by 8 mg orally daily on days 2 through 4.  Patients were stratified by sex, chemotherapy regimen, and the specific 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist chosen.  The primary endpoint, no nausea, was defined as a score of 0 on the visual analogue scale of 0 to 10 and assessed at three time points postchemotherapy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_774" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Early, 0 to 24 hours.</ListItem><ListItem>Later,  25 to 120 hours.</ListItem><ListItem>Overall, 0 to 120 hours.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_754">The percentage of patients experiencing no nausea was significantly higher in the olanzapine group than in the placebo group at the early (74% vs. 45%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002), later (42% vs. 25%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002), and overall time points (37% vs. 22%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002).  CR rate and freedom from clinically significant nausea (a score lower than 3 on the visual analog scale of 0–10) were also significantly improved with the addition of olanzapine at all time points.  Patients receiving olanzapine reported increased sedation from baseline on  day 2, which resolved on days 3 through 5. Based on these data and additional clinical trials, olanzapine appears to be safe and effective in controlling acute and delayed CINV in patients receiving highly emetogenic and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="128"/><Reference refidx="129"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_380"><Title>Other Pharmacological Agents</Title><SummarySection id="_457"><Title><ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName></Title><Para id="_458">The plant <ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName> contains more than 60 different types of cannabinoids, or components that have physiological activity.  The most popular, and perhaps the most psychoactive, is delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol (delta-9-THC).<Reference refidx="130"/>   There are two FDA-approved <ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName> products for CINV:</Para><ItemizedList id="_459" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://medlineplus.gov/druginfo/meds/a607054.html">Dronabinol</ExternalRef> (a synthetic delta-9-THC), as prophylaxis for CINV, 5 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> orally 1 to 3 hours before chemotherapy and every 2 to 4 hours after chemotherapy, for a total of no more than 6 doses per day.</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://medlineplus.gov/druginfo/meds/a607048.html">Nabilone</ExternalRef>, for CINV that has failed to respond to other antiemetics, 1 to 2 mg orally twice a day.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_460">With respect to CINV, <ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName> products probably target  cannabinoid-1 and cannabinoid-2 receptors, which are in the CNS.<Reference refidx="131"/></Para><Para id="_461">Much of the research on agents in this class, conducted in the late 1970s and 1980s, compared nabilone, dronabinol, or levonantradol to older antiemetic agents that targeted the dopamine receptor, such as prochlorperazine (Compazine) and metoclopramide (Reglan).<Reference refidx="132"/><Reference refidx="133"/><Reference refidx="134"/><Reference refidx="135"/><Reference refidx="136"/> This group of studies demonstrated that cannabinoids were as effective as dopaminergic antiemetics for moderately emetogenic chemotherapy or were more effective than placebo.<Reference refidx="130"/>  Side effects included euphoria, dizziness, dysphoria, hallucinations, and hypotension.<Reference refidx="130"/> Despite earlier reports of efficacy, in at least one study, patients did not significantly prefer nabilone because of the side effects.<Reference refidx="132"/></Para><Para id="_462">Since the 1990s, research in N&amp;V has elucidated newer and more physiological targets, namely 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> and NK-1 receptors. Subsequently, 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> and NK-1 receptor antagonists have become standard prophylactic therapy for CINV.  Few studies have investigated the role of <ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName> extract and cannabinoids with these newer agents, so only limited conclusions can be drawn.  In published trials, however,  <ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName> extract and cannabinoids have not demonstrated more efficacy than 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists, and synergistic or additive effects have not been fully investigated.<Reference refidx="137"/><Reference refidx="138"/></Para><Para id="_463">In summary, <ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName> and cannabinoids' role in the prevention and treatment of CINV is not fully known.  Discussions with patients about their use may include responses to available agents, known side effects of <ScientificName>Cannabis</ScientificName>, and an assessment of the risks versus benefits of this therapy.<Reference refidx="139"/> For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000683767" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/cannabis-pdq">Cannabis and Cannabinoids</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_381"><Title>Ginger</Title><Para id="_405">There are conflicting data on the efficacy of ginger for prophylaxis of CINV. A phase III, randomized, dose-finding trial of 576 patients with cancer evaluated 0.5 g, 1 g, and 1.5 g of ginger versus placebo in twice-a-day dosing for the prevention of acute nausea (defined as day 1 postchemotherapy). Patients experienced some level of nausea (as measured on an 11-point scale) caused by their current chemotherapy regimen, despite standard prophylaxis with a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist.  Patients began taking ginger or placebo capsules 3 days before each chemotherapy treatment and continued them for 6 days. For average nausea severity, 0.5 g of ginger was significantly better than placebo. For maximum nausea severity, both 0.5 g and 1 g were significantly better than placebo. Effects for delayed N&amp;V were not significant. This trial did not control for emetogenicity of the chemotherapy regimens.  Adverse events were infrequent and were not severe.<Reference refidx="23"/> </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><Para id="_794">Conversely, data on ginger used to prevent N&amp;V have not been as promising.  A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study evaluated the use of ginger 160 mg per day in  patients receiving high-dose cisplatin (&gt;50 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>). Patients (N = 251) were assigned to receive either ginger or placebo.  The incidence of delayed nausea, intercycle nausea, and anticipatory nausea did not differ between the two treatment arms.<Reference refidx="140"/></Para><SummarySection id="_559"><Title>Multiday Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_560">Regimens that include chemotherapy doses on multiple sequential days (multiday chemotherapy) present a unique challenge to preventing CINV because after the first dose of chemotherapy, nausea may be both acute and delayed.  Although there is no standard antiemetic regimen for multiday chemotherapy, a corticosteroid and a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist should be given with each day of highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="141"/>  Evidence demonstrates benefit for the addition of an NK-1 antagonist to highly and moderately emetogenic multiday chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="141"/>  The choice of antiemetic drugs and their schedule should be matched to the emetogenicity of the individual chemotherapy agents and their sequence.  In addition, the length of delayed nausea varies and will depend on the emetogenicity of the last day’s chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_561">Dexamethasone is scheduled on each day of a multiday chemotherapy regimen and for 2 to 3 days after if there is a risk of delayed nausea.  Additional dexamethasone is not necessary if the chemotherapy regimen contains a corticosteroid.  It is not known whether dexamethasone 20 mg given each day of a 5-day cisplatin regimen provides additional antiemetic benefit, and it may add toxicity.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="142"/> Therefore, an alternative dexamethasone schedule (20 mg on days 1 and 2, followed by 8 mg twice daily on days 6 and 7, and 4 mg twice daily on day 8), based on the timing of CINV and to reduce the total steroid dose, has been studied in patients receiving 5-day cisplatin regimens.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_562">Standard antiemetic prophylaxis includes a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist given before the first chemotherapy dose each day of a multiday chemotherapy regimen.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="141"/>  No 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist is favored over other agents in the class for multiday chemotherapy.  Palonosetron is a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist with a longer half-life and higher receptor-binding affinity than other members in its class, allowing it to be given less frequently.<Reference refidx="71"/>  A prospective, uncontrolled trial demonstrated that palonosetron, as a single IV dose with dexamethasone 20 mg before two 3-day chemotherapy regimens, resulted in an 80% CR.<Reference refidx="143"/> Palonosetron was also studied with dexamethasone as prophylaxis for a 5-day cisplatin-based regimen for germ cell tumors.<Reference refidx="12"/>  When palonosetron plus dexamethasone was given on days 1, 3, and 5, 51% of patients experienced no emesis on days 1 to 5, and 83% experienced no emesis on days 6 to 9.  </Para><Para id="_671">Alternative methods of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist delivery have been studied. Granisetron as a 7-day continuous transdermal patch was compared with daily oral granisetron in patients receiving multiday chemotherapy in a double-blind, phase III, noninferiority study.<Reference refidx="63"/>  The patch demonstrated complete control in 60% of patients, while the oral formulation did so in 65% of patients, achieving noninferiority.</Para><Para id="_563">The NK-1 antagonist aprepitant and its IV formulation, fosaprepitant, have been studied with multiday chemotherapy in dosing schedules that differ from their FDA-approved schedules.  A nonrandomized trial evaluated the use of aprepitant, granisetron, and dexamethasone for CINV prophylaxis with 3- and 5-day highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="144"/>  Aprepitant was given at 125 mg  orally before the first dose of chemotherapy, then 80 mg orally on each day of chemotherapy and for 2 following days (total, 5–7 days).   CR was seen in 57.9% and 72.5% of patients receiving highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy, respectively.  Similarly promising results were found in a subsequent single-arm trial looking at a 7-day oral aprepitant regimen with dexamethasone and a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist for 5-day cisplatin-based chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="145"/></Para><Para id="_672">A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover trial of aprepitant, a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, and dexamethasone was conducted in patients receiving 5-day cisplatin-based chemotherapy for germ cell tumors.<Reference refidx="86"/>  Oral aprepitant 125 mg was given on day 3, followed by oral aprepitant 80 mg daily on days 4 to 7.  More patients achieved CR with aprepitant  than with placebo, 42% versus 13% (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).  IV fosaprepitant 150 mg given on days 3 and 5 was studied in a small phase II trial evaluating its use with a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist and dexamethasone in 5-day cisplatin-based chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="146"/>  Preliminary results showed a CR rate of 28.1%, lower than results of the oral aprepitant trial conducted by the same institution.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_564"><Title>High-Dose Chemotherapy With Stem Cell Transplant</Title><Para id="_565">Prevention of emesis during high doses of chemotherapy, with or without total-body irradiation, continues to be a challenging area of patient care.<Reference refidx="147"/> Current <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062747#_67" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">guidelines</SummaryRef>  primarily address single-day therapies. In addition, while emesis prevention for the multiple days of chemotherapy or radiation therapy used in this setting is based on single-day experiences, additional research is needed to improve symptom control for these patients.<Reference refidx="147"/> This has led to the addition of NK-1 antagonists to the daily dosing of a serotonin antagonist plus dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="147"/><Reference refidx="148"/><Reference refidx="149"/>  Additional evidence is needed to determine optimal combinations, as CR rates range as low as 30%.<Reference refidx="149"/>  Also, experience has primarily been with aprepitant. The newer NK-1 antagonists may offer additional benefit.</Para><Para id="_659">Overall, these antiemetic combinations are well tolerated, with most side effects involving the dexamethasone component. In addition, while drug interactions were originally a concern, they do not appear to be clinically significant.<Reference refidx="150"/>   Also, emesis is controlled to a much greater extent than is nausea, which continues to be challenging for many patients.<Reference refidx="147"/><Reference refidx="151"/> Finally, a randomized phase III trial studied the use of aprepitant, granisetron, and dexamethasone for the prevention of CINV in multiple myeloma  patients receiving high-dose melphalan with autologous stem cell transplant. A statistically positive benefit, without an increase in side effects,  was seen in patients who received the three-drug regimen.<Reference refidx="148"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_66_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_66_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20974571">García Gómez J, Pérez López ME, García Mata J, et al.: SEOM clinical guidelines for the treatment of antiemetic prophylaxis in cancer patients receiving chemotherapy. Clin Transl Oncol 12 (11): 770-4, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="28759346">Hesketh PJ, Kris MG, Basch E, et al.: Antiemetics: American Society of Clinical Oncology Clinical Practice Guideline Update. J Clin Oncol 35 (28): 3240-3261, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23512831">Dupuis LL, Boodhan S, Holdsworth M, et al.: Guideline for the prevention of acute nausea and vomiting due to antineoplastic medication in pediatric cancer patients. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (7): 1073-82, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="24753095">Dupuis LL, Robinson PD, Boodhan S, et al.: Guideline for the prevention and treatment of anticipatory nausea and vomiting due to chemotherapy in pediatric cancer patients. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (8): 1506-12, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15510975">Hesketh PJ: Understanding the pathobiology of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Providing a basis for therapeutic progress. Oncology (Williston Park) 18 (10 Suppl 6): 9-14, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Rudd JA, Andrews PLR: Mechanisms of acute, delayed, and anticipatory emesis induced by anticancer therapies. In: Hesketh PJ, ed.: Management of Nausea and Vomiting in Cancer and Cancer Treatment. Jones and Bartlett Publishers, Inc., 2005, pp 15-66.</Citation><Citation idx="7">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Antiemesis. Version 2.2024. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/PDF/antiemesis.pdf">Available online with free registration</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="15352652">Navari RM: Pathogenesis-based treatment of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting--two new agents. J Support Oncol 1 (2): 89-103, 2003 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15139073">Grunberg SM, Deuson RR, Mavros P, et al.: Incidence of chemotherapy-induced nausea and emesis after modern antiemetics. Cancer 100 (10): 2261-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="12618925">Fabi A, Barduagni M, Lauro S, et al.: Is delayed chemotherapy-induced emesis well managed in oncological clinical practice? An observational study. Support Care Cancer 11 (3): 156-61, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="18521919">Colagiuri B, Roscoe JA, Morrow GR, et al.: How do patient expectancies, quality of life, and postchemotherapy nausea interrelate? Cancer 113 (3): 654-61, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="17436025">Einhorn LH, Brames MJ, Dreicer R, et al.: Palonosetron plus dexamethasone for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients receiving multiple-day cisplatin chemotherapy for germ cell cancer. Support Care Cancer 15 (11): 1293-300, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="27664248">Roila F, Molassiotis A, Herrstedt J, et al.: 2016 MASCC and ESMO guideline update for the prevention of chemotherapy- and radiotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting and of nausea and vomiting in advanced cancer patients. Ann Oncol 27 (suppl 5): v119-v133, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Lexicomp Online. Hudson, Ohio: Lexi-Comp, Inc., 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.wolterskluwer.com/en/solutions/uptodate/enterprise/lexidrug">Available online with subscription</ExternalRef>. Last accessed Jan. 15, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="2732782">Gez E, Brufman G, Kaufman B, et al.: Methylprednisolone and chlorpromazine in patients receiving cancer chemotherapy: a prospective non-randomized study. J Chemother 1 (2): 140-3, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="10326616">ASHP Therapeutic Guidelines on the Pharmacologic Management of Nausea and Vomiting in Adult and Pediatric Patients Receiving Chemotherapy or Radiation Therapy or Undergoing Surgery. Am J Health Syst Pharm 56 (8): 729-64, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="7400373">Hurley JD, Eshelman FN: Trimethobenzamide HCl in the treatment of nausea and vomiting associated with antineoplastic chemotherapy. J Clin Pharmacol 20 (5-6 Pt 1): 352-6, 1980 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="29722791">Schwartzberg L, Roeland E, Andric Z, et al.: Phase III safety study of intravenous NEPA: a novel fixed antiemetic combination of fosnetupitant and palonosetron in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy. Ann Oncol 29 (7): 1535-1540, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="8392288" MedlineID="93318792">Mori K, Saito Y, Tominaga K: Antiemetic efficacy of alprazolam in the combination of metoclopramide plus methylprednisolone. Double-blind randomized crossover study in patients with cisplatin-induced emesis. Am J Clin Oncol 16 (4): 338-41, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="27410922">Navari RM, Qin R, Ruddy KJ, et al.: Olanzapine for the Prevention of Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting. N Engl J Med 375 (2): 134-42, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="23314603">Navari RM, Nagy CK, Gray SE: The use of olanzapine versus metoclopramide for the treatment of breakthrough chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 21 (6): 1655-63, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="22491047">Todaro B: Cannabinoids in the treatment of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 10 (4): 487-92, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="21818642">Ryan JL, Heckler CE, Roscoe JA, et al.: Ginger (Zingiber officinale) reduces acute chemotherapy-induced nausea: a URCC CCOP study of 576 patients. Support Care Cancer 20 (7): 1479-89, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="23550785">Marx WM, Teleni L, McCarthy AL, et al.: Ginger (Zingiber officinale) and chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a systematic literature review. Nutr Rev 71 (4): 245-54, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="2591437" MedlineID="90076319">Olver IN, Webster LK, Bishop JF, et al.: A dose finding study of prochlorperazine as an antiemetic for cancer chemotherapy. Eur J Cancer Clin Oncol 25 (10): 1457-61, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="4040552" MedlineID="85263757">Carr BI, Bertrand M, Browning S, et al.: A comparison of the antiemetic efficacy of prochlorperazine and metoclopramide for the treatment of cisplatin-induced emesis: a prospective, randomized, double-blind study. J Clin Oncol 3 (8): 1127-32, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="1389512" MedlineID="93001582">Olver IN, Wolf M, Laidlaw C, et al.: A randomised double-blind study of high-dose intravenous prochlorperazine versus high-dose metoclopramide as antiemetics for cancer chemotherapy. Eur J Cancer 28A (11): 1798-802, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="2875701" MedlineID="86322351">Levinson DF, Simpson GM: Neuroleptic-induced extrapyramidal symptoms with fever. Heterogeneity of the 'neuroleptic malignant syndrome'. Arch Gen Psychiatry 43 (9): 839-48, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="6840019" MedlineID="83182206">Wampler G: The pharmacology and clinical effectiveness of phenothiazines and related drugs for managing chemotherapy-induced emesis. Drugs 25 (Suppl 1): 35-51, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="22376048">American Geriatrics Society 2012 Beers Criteria Update Expert Panel: American Geriatrics Society updated Beers Criteria for potentially inappropriate medication use in older adults. J Am Geriatr Soc 60 (4): 616-31, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="20619214">Hardy JR, O'Shea A, White C, et al.: The efficacy of haloperidol in the management of nausea and vomiting in patients with cancer. J Pain Symptom Manage 40 (1): 111-6, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="28772094">Digges M, Hussein A, Wilcock A, et al.: Pharmacovigilance in Hospice/Palliative Care: Net Effect of Haloperidol for Nausea or Vomiting. J Palliat Med 21 (1): 37-43, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="2544688" MedlineID="89293188">Navari RM: Comparison of intermittent versus continuous infusion metoclopramide in control of acute nausea induced by cisplatin chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol 7 (7): 943-6, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="3402181" MedlineID="88295669">Agostinucci WA, Gannon RH, Golub GR, et al.: Continuous i.v. infusion versus multiple bolus doses of metoclopramide for prevention of cisplatin-induced emesis. Clin Pharm 7 (6): 454-7, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="3880660" MedlineID="85074040">Kris MG, Gralla RJ, Tyson LB, et al.: Improved control of cisplatin-induced emesis with high-dose metoclopramide and with combinations of metoclopramide, dexamethasone, and diphenhydramine. Results of consecutive trials in 255 patients. Cancer 55 (3): 527-34, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="6877305" MedlineID="83271340">Kris MG, Tyson LB, Gralla RJ, et al.: Extrapyramidal reactions with high-dose metoclopramide. N Engl J Med 309 (7): 433-4, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="20844345">Hsu ES: A review of granisetron, 5-hydroxytryptamine3 receptor antagonists, and other antiemetics. Am J Ther 17 (5): 476-86, 2010 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="23512709">Trammel M, Roederer M, Patel J, et al.: Does pharmacogenomics account for variability in control of acute chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting with 5-hydroxytryptamine type 3 receptor antagonists? Curr Oncol Rep 15 (3): 276-85, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="21533811">Hatoum HT, Lin SJ, Buchner D, et al.: Comparative clinical effectiveness of various 5-HT3 RA antiemetic regimens on chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting associated with hospital and emergency department visits in real world practice. Support Care Cancer 20 (5): 941-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="21808994">Aogi K, Sakai H, Yoshizawa H, et al.: A phase III open-label study to assess safety and efficacy of palonosetron for preventing chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting (CINV) in repeated cycles of emetogenic chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 20 (7): 1507-14, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="10705879" MedlineID="20170057">Hesketh PJ: Comparative review of 5-HT3 receptor antagonists in the treatment of acute chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Cancer Invest 18 (2): 163-73, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="7738628" MedlineID="95256949">Navari R, Gandara D, Hesketh P, et al.: Comparative clinical trial of granisetron and ondansetron in the prophylaxis of cisplatin-induced emesis. The Granisetron Study Group. J Clin Oncol 13 (5): 1242-8, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="14635083">Eisenberg P, Figueroa-Vadillo J, Zamora R, et al.: Improved prevention of moderately emetogenic chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting with palonosetron, a pharmacologically novel 5-HT3 receptor antagonist: results of a phase III, single-dose trial versus dolasetron. Cancer 98 (11): 2473-82, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="14504060">Gralla R, Lichinitser M, Van Der Vegt S, et al.: Palonosetron improves prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting following moderately emetogenic chemotherapy: results of a double-blind randomized phase III trial comparing single doses of palonosetron with ondansetron. Ann Oncol 14 (10): 1570-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="23354552">Boccia R, Grunberg S, Franco-Gonzales E, et al.: Efficacy of oral palonosetron compared to intravenous palonosetron for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting associated with moderately emetogenic chemotherapy: a phase 3 trial. Support Care Cancer 21 (5): 1453-60, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="16198982">Hickok JT, Roscoe JA, Morrow GR, et al.: 5-Hydroxytryptamine-receptor antagonists versus prochlorperazine for control of delayed nausea caused by doxorubicin: a URCC CCOP randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 6 (10): 765-72, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="14559888">Kris MG: Why do we need another antiemetic? Just ask. J Clin Oncol 21 (22): 4077-80, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="1387245" MedlineID="92376560">Tyers MB: Pharmacology and preclinical antiemetic properties of ondansetron. Semin Oncol 19 (4 Suppl 10): 1-8, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="2141487" MedlineID="90290881">Kaasa S, Kvaløy S, Dicato MA, et al.: A comparison of ondansetron with metoclopramide in the prophylaxis of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a randomized, double-blind study. International Emesis Study Group. Eur J Cancer 26 (3): 311-4, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="1826739" MedlineID="91202194">Hainsworth J, Harvey W, Pendergrass K, et al.: A single-blind comparison of intravenous ondansetron, a selective serotonin antagonist, with intravenous metoclopramide in the prevention of nausea and vomiting associated with high-dose cisplatin chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol 9 (5): 721-8, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="2146911" MedlineID="91052789">De Mulder PH, Seynaeve C, Vermorken JB, et al.: Ondansetron compared with high-dose metoclopramide in prophylaxis of acute and delayed cisplatin-induced nausea and vomiting. A multicenter, randomized, double-blind, crossover study. Ann Intern Med 113 (11): 834-40, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="2137902" MedlineID="90174240">Marty M, Pouillart P, Scholl S, et al.: Comparison of the 5-hydroxytryptamine3 (serotonin) antagonist ondansetron (GR 38032F) with high-dose metoclopramide in the control of cisplatin-induced emesis. N Engl J Med 322 (12): 816-21, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="1387248" MedlineID="92376563">Hesketh PJ: Comparative trials of ondansetron versus metoclopramide in the prevention of acute cisplatin-induced emesis. Semin Oncol 19 (4 Suppl 10): 33-40, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="8978584">Pectasides D, Mylonakis A, Varthalitis J, et al.: Comparison of two different doses of ondansetron plus dexamethasone in the prophylaxis of cisplatin-induced emesis. Oncology 54 (1): 1-6, 1997 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="17940810">Hasler SB, Hirt A, Ridolfi Luethy A, et al.: Safety of ondansetron loading doses in children with cancer. Support Care Cancer 16 (5): 469-75, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="56">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: FDA Drug Safety Communication: New information regarding QT prolongation with ondansetron (Zofran). Silver Spring, Md: U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2012. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/drug-safety-and-availability/fda-drug-safety-communication-new-information-regarding-qt-prolongation-ondansetron-zofran">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="1453211" MedlineID="93085401">Beck TM, Hesketh PJ, Madajewicz S, et al.: Stratified, randomized, double-blind comparison of intravenous ondansetron administered as a multiple-dose regimen versus two single-dose regimens in the prevention of cisplatin-induced nausea and vomiting. J Clin Oncol 10 (12): 1969-75, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="1387251" MedlineID="92376566">Finn AL: Toxicity and side effects of ondansetron. Semin Oncol 19 (4 Suppl 10): 53-60, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="1450061" MedlineID="93081347">Coates AS, Childs A, Cox K, et al.: Severe vascular adverse effects with thrombocytopenia and renal failure following emetogenic chemotherapy and ondansetron. Ann Oncol 3 (9): 719-22, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="8265095" MedlineID="94089080">Ruff P, Paska W, Goedhals L, et al.: Ondansetron compared with granisetron in the prophylaxis of cisplatin-induced acute emesis: a multicentre double-blind, randomised, parallel-group study. The Ondansetron and Granisetron Emesis Study Group. Oncology 51 (1): 113-8, 1994 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="8398291" MedlineID="94001001">Jantunen IT, Muhonen TT, Kataja VV, et al.: 5-HT3 receptor antagonists in the prophylaxis of acute vomiting induced by moderately emetogenic chemotherapy--a randomised study. Eur J Cancer 29A (12): 1669-72, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="8082100" MedlineID="94363663">Gebbia V, Cannata G, Testa A, et al.: Ondansetron versus granisetron in the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Results of a prospective randomized trial. Cancer 74 (7): 1945-52, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="20835873">Boccia RV, Gordan LN, Clark G, et al.: Efficacy and tolerability of transdermal granisetron for the control of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting associated with moderately and highly emetogenic multi-day chemotherapy: a randomized, double-blind, phase III study. Support Care Cancer 19 (10): 1609-17, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="25179689">Raftopoulos H, Cooper W, O'Boyle E, et al.: Comparison of an extended-release formulation of granisetron (APF530) versus palonosetron for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting associated with moderately or highly emetogenic chemotherapy: results of a prospective, randomized, double-blind, noninferiority phase 3 trial. Support Care Cancer 23 (3): 723-32, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="65">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: FDA Drug Safety Communication: Abnormal heart rhythms associated with use of Anzemet (dolasetron mesylate). Silver Spring, Md: U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2010. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/drug-safety-and-availability/fda-drug-safety-communication-abnormal-heart-rhythms-associated-use-anzemet-dolasetron-mesylate">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="8911112" MedlineID="97067764">Fauser AA, Duclos B, Chemaissani A, et al.: Therapeutic equivalence of single oral doses of dolasetron mesilate and multiple doses of ondansetron for the prevention of emesis after moderately emetogenic chemotherapy. European Dolasetron Comparative Study Group. Eur J Cancer 32A (9): 1523-9, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="14760130">Eisenberg P, MacKintosh FR, Ritch P, et al.: Efficacy, safety and pharmacokinetics of palonosetron in patients receiving highly emetogenic cisplatin-based chemotherapy: a dose-ranging clinical study. Ann Oncol 15 (2): 330-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="23810058">Tricco AC, Soobiah C, Antony J, et al.: Safety of serotonin (5-HT3) receptor antagonists in patients undergoing surgery and chemotherapy: protocol for a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Syst Rev 2: 46, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="24991390">Faria C, Li X, Nagl N, et al.: Outcomes Associated with 5-HT3-RA Therapy Selection in Patients with Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting: A Retrospective Claims Analysis. Am Health Drug Benefits 7 (1): 50-8, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="24141698">Schwartzberg L, Barbour SY, Morrow GR, et al.: Pooled analysis of phase III clinical studies of palonosetron versus ondansetron, dolasetron, and granisetron in the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting (CINV). Support Care Cancer 22 (2): 469-77, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="25228819">Affronti ML, Bubalo J: Palonosetron in the management of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients receiving multiple-day chemotherapy. Cancer Manag Res 6: 329-37, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="21188135">Navari RM: Palonosetron for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: approval and efficacy. Cancer Manag Res 1: 167-76, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="16766588">Aapro MS, Grunberg SM, Manikhas GM, et al.: A phase III, double-blind, randomized trial of palonosetron compared with ondansetron in preventing chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting following highly emetogenic chemotherapy. Ann Oncol 17 (9): 1441-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="17026451">Navari RM: Palonosetron: a second-generation 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor antagonist. Future Oncol 2 (5): 591-602, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="75" PMID="23950658">Humphreys S, Pellissier J, Jones A: Cost-effectiveness of an aprepitant regimen for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients with breast cancer in the UK. Cancer Manag Res 5: 215-24, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="20461438">Warr DG, Street JC, Carides AD: Evaluation of risk factors predictive of nausea and vomiting with current standard-of-care antiemetic treatment: analysis of phase 3 trial of aprepitant in patients receiving adriamycin-cyclophosphamide-based chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 19 (6): 807-13, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="19756774">Hesketh PJ, Aapro M, Street JC, et al.: Evaluation of risk factors predictive of nausea and vomiting with current standard-of-care antiemetic treatment: analysis of two phase III trials of aprepitant in patients receiving cisplatin-based chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 18 (9): 1171-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="24748417">Hu W, Fang J, Nie J, et al.: Addition of aprepitant improves protection against cisplatin-induced emesis when a conventional anti-emetic regimen fails. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 73 (6): 1129-36, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="79" PMID="12784346" MedlineID="22668841">Poli-Bigelli S, Rodrigues-Pereira J, Carides AD, et al.: Addition of the neurokinin 1 receptor antagonist aprepitant to standard antiemetic therapy improves control of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Results from a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in Latin America. Cancer 97 (12): 3090-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="80" PMID="14559886">Hesketh PJ, Grunberg SM, Gralla RJ, et al.: The oral neurokinin-1 antagonist aprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a multinational, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in patients receiving high-dose cisplatin--the Aprepitant Protocol 052 Study Group. J Clin Oncol 21 (22): 4112-9, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="81" PMID="16524979">Schmoll HJ, Aapro MS, Poli-Bigelli S, et al.: Comparison of an aprepitant regimen with a multiple-day ondansetron regimen, both with dexamethasone, for antiemetic efficacy in high-dose cisplatin treatment. Ann Oncol 17 (6): 1000-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="82" PMID="15837996">Warr DG, Hesketh PJ, Gralla RJ, et al.: Efficacy and tolerability of aprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients with breast cancer after moderately emetogenic chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol 23 (12): 2822-30, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="83" PMID="29090385">Bubalo JS, Herrington JD, Takemoto M, et al.: Phase II open label pilot trial of aprepitant and palonosetron for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting (CINV) in patients receiving moderately emetogenic FOLFOX chemotherapy for the treatment of colorectal cancer. Support Care Cancer 26 (4): 1273-1279, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="84" PMID="19568773">Rapoport BL, Jordan K, Boice JA, et al.: Aprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting associated with a broad range of moderately emetogenic chemotherapies and tumor types: a randomized, double-blind study. Support Care Cancer 18 (4): 423-31, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="85" PMID="23062719">Aapro MS, Schmoll HJ, Jahn F, et al.: Review of the efficacy of aprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in a range of tumor types. Cancer Treat Rev 39 (1): 113-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="86" PMID="22915652">Albany C, Brames MJ, Fausel C, et al.: Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase III cross-over study evaluating the oral neurokinin-1 antagonist aprepitant in combination with a 5HT3 receptor antagonist and dexamethasone in patients with germ cell tumors receiving 5-day cisplatin combination chemotherapy regimens: a hoosier oncology group study. J Clin Oncol 30 (32): 3998-4003, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="87" PMID="21383291">Grunberg S, Chua D, Maru A, et al.: Single-dose fosaprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting associated with cisplatin therapy: randomized, double-blind study protocol--EASE. J Clin Oncol 29 (11): 1495-501, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="88">EMEND 
(Fosaprepitant 
Dimeglumine) 
for Injection, for Intravenous 
Use. Whitehouse Station, NJ: Merck &amp; Co., Inc., 2022. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.merck.com/product/usa/pi_circulars/e/emend_iv/emend_iv_lowedta_pi.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="89" PMID="7746084">Shelley WB, Talanin N, Shelley ED: Polysorbate 80 hypersensitivity. Lancet 345 (8960): 1312-3, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="90">CINVANTI (aprepitant): highlights of prescribing information. San Diego, Calif: Heron Therapeutics, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2024/209296Orig1s015lbl.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="91" PMID="32162813">Schwartzberg L, Navari R, Clark-Snow R, et al.: Phase IIIb Safety and Efficacy of Intravenous NEPA for Prevention of Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting (CINV) in Patients with Breast Cancer Receiving Initial and Repeat Cycles of Anthracycline and Cyclophosphamide (AC) Chemotherapy. Oncologist 25 (3): e589-e597, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="92" PMID="24608196">Hesketh PJ, Rossi G, Rizzi G, et al.: Efficacy and safety of NEPA, an oral combination of netupitant and palonosetron, for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting following highly emetogenic chemotherapy: a randomized dose-ranging pivotal study. Ann Oncol 25 (7): 1340-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="93" PMID="24603643">Aapro M, Rugo H, Rossi G, et al.: A randomized phase III study evaluating the efficacy and safety of NEPA, a fixed-dose combination of netupitant and palonosetron, for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting following moderately emetogenic chemotherapy. Ann Oncol 25 (7): 1328-33, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="94" PMID="27885469">Aapro M, Karthaus M, Schwartzberg L, et al.: NEPA, a fixed oral combination of netupitant and palonosetron, improves control of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting (CINV) over multiple cycles of chemotherapy: results of a randomized, double-blind, phase 3 trial versus oral palonosetron. Support Care Cancer 25 (4): 1127-1135, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="95" PMID="34793245">Hata A, Okamoto I, Inui N, et al.: Randomized, Double-Blind, Phase III Study of Fosnetupitant Versus Fosaprepitant for Prevention of Highly Emetogenic Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting: CONSOLE. J Clin Oncol 40 (2): 180-188, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="96" PMID="29092012">Zhang L, Lu S, Feng J, et al.: A randomized phase III study evaluating the efficacy of single-dose NEPA, a fixed antiemetic combination of netupitant and palonosetron, versus an aprepitant regimen for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting (CINV) in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy (HEC). Ann Oncol 29 (2): 452-458, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="97" PMID="26272768">Schwartzberg LS, Modiano MR, Rapoport BL, et al.: Safety and efficacy of rolapitant for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting after administration of moderately emetogenic chemotherapy or anthracycline and cyclophosphamide regimens in patients with cancer: a randomised, active-controlled, double-blind, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 16 (9): 1071-8, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="98" PMID="26272769">Rapoport BL, Chasen MR, Gridelli C, et al.: Safety and efficacy of rolapitant for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting after administration of cisplatin-based highly emetogenic chemotherapy in patients with cancer: two randomised, active-controlled, double-blind, phase 3 trials. Lancet Oncol 16 (9): 1079-89, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="99">VARUBI (rolapitant): highlights of prescribing information. Lake Forest, Ill: TerSera Therapeutics LLC, 2020. <ExternalRef xref="https://documents.tersera.com/varubi/VarubiPrescribingInformation.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="100">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: Postmarket Drug Safety Information for Patients and Providers: Varubi (rolapitant) injectable emulsion. Silver Spring, Md: U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2018. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket-drug-safety-information-patients-and-providers/varubi-rolapitant-injectable-emulsion">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="101" PMID="1567690" MedlineID="92232424">Bishop JF, Matthews JP, Wolf MM, et al.: A randomised trial of dexamethasone, lorazepam and prochlorperazine for emesis in patients receiving chemotherapy. Eur J Cancer 28 (1): 47-50, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="102" PMID="3296735" MedlineID="87238537">Chiara S, Campora E, Lionetto R, et al.: Methylprednisolone for the control of CMF-induced emesis. Am J Clin Oncol 10 (3): 264-7, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="103" PMID="1855281" MedlineID="91309186">Parry H, Martin K: Single-dose i.v. dexamethasone--an effective anti-emetic in cancer chemotherapy. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 28 (3): 231-2, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="104" PMID="6712035" MedlineID="84176884">Cassileth PA, Lusk EJ, Torri S, et al.: Antiemetic efficacy of high-dose dexamethasone in induction therapy in acute nonlymphocytic leukemia. Ann Intern Med 100 (5): 701-2, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="105" PMID="6539363" MedlineID="84215224">Aapro MS, Plezia PM, Alberts DS, et al.: Double-blind crossover study of the antiemetic efficacy of high-dose dexamethasone versus high-dose metoclopramide. J Clin Oncol 2 (5): 466-71, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="106" PMID="3888430" MedlineID="85202154">Schallier D, Van Belle S, De Greve J, et al.: Methylprednisolone as an antiemetic drug. A randomised double blind study. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 14 (3): 235-7, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="107" PMID="3912039" MedlineID="86133326">Kris MG, Gralla RJ, Clark RA, et al.: Consecutive dose-finding trials adding lorazepam to the combination of metoclopramide plus dexamethasone: improved subjective effectiveness over the combination of diphenhydramine plus metoclopramide plus dexamethasone. Cancer Treat Rep 69 (11): 1257-62, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="108" PMID="3567983" MedlineID="87187347">Greenberg DB, Surman OS, Clarke J, et al.: Alprazolam for phobic nausea and vomiting related to cancer chemotherapy. Cancer Treat Rep 71 (5): 549-50, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="109" PMID="2204886" MedlineID="90377768">Hockenberry-Eaton M, Benner A: Patterns of nausea and vomiting in children: nursing assessment and intervention. Oncol Nurs Forum 17 (4): 575-84, 1990 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="110" PMID="15468188">Münstedt K, Borces D, Bohlmann MK, et al.: Glucocorticoid administration in antiemetic therapy: is it safe? Cancer 101 (7): 1696-702, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="111" PMID="1829757" MedlineID="91294838">Roila F, Tonato M, Cognetti F, et al.: Prevention of cisplatin-induced emesis: a double-blind multicenter randomized crossover study comparing ondansetron and ondansetron plus dexamethasone. J Clin Oncol 9 (4): 675-8, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="112" PMID="3510410" MedlineID="86093127">Zaglama NE, Rosenblum SL, Sartiano GP, et al.: Single, high-dose intravenous dexamethasone as an antiemetic in cancer chemotherapy. Oncology 43 (1): 27-32, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="113" PMID="1586446" MedlineID="92265119">Klygis LM: Dexamethasone-induced perineal irritation in head injury. Am J Emerg Med 10 (3): 268, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="114" PMID="3713767" MedlineID="86230736">More on dexamethasone-induced perineal irritation. N Engl J Med 314 (25): 1643-4, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="115" PMID="3945280" MedlineID="86118580">Baharav E, Harpaz D, Mittelman M, et al.: Dexamethasone-induced perineal irritation. N Engl J Med 314 (8): 515-6, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="116" PMID="2896534" MedlineID="88209940">Triozzi PL, Goldstein D, Laszlo J: Contributions of benzodiazepines to cancer therapy. Cancer Invest 6 (1): 103-11, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="117" PMID="4040158" MedlineID="85236446">Laszlo J, Clark RA, Hanson DC, et al.: Lorazepam in cancer patients treated with cisplatin: a drug having antiemetic, amnesic, and anxiolytic effects. J Clin Oncol 3 (6): 864-9, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="118" PMID="6374058" MedlineID="84215256">Bishop JF, Olver IN, Wolf MM, et al.: Lorazepam: a randomized, double-blind, crossover study of a new antiemetic in patients receiving cytotoxic chemotherapy and prochlorperazine. J Clin Oncol 2 (6): 691-5, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="119" PMID="1934919">Henry DW, Burwinkle JW, Klutman NE: Determination of sedative and amnestic doses of lorazepam in children. Clin Pharm 10 (8): 625-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="120" PMID="3385522" MedlineID="88258698">van Hoff J, Olszewski D: Lorazepam for the control of chemotherapy-related nausea and vomiting in children. J Pediatr 113 (1 Pt 1): 146-9, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="121" PMID="11711053">Bymaster FP, Falcone JF, Bauzon D, et al.: Potent antagonism of 5-HT(3) and 5-HT(6) receptors by olanzapine. Eur J Pharmacol 430 (2-3): 341-9, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="122">ZYPREXA (olanzapine): highlights of prescribing information. Indianapolis, Ind: Eli Lilly and Company, 2021. <ExternalRef xref="http://pi.lilly.com/us/zyprexa_relprevv.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="123" PMID="24522741">Hocking CM, Kichenadasse G: Olanzapine for chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a systematic review. Support Care Cancer 22 (4): 1143-51, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="124" PMID="12067777" MedlineID="22063540">Passik SD, Lundberg J, Kirsh KL, et al.: A pilot exploration of the antiemetic activity of olanzapine for the relief of nausea in patients with advanced cancer and pain. J Pain Symptom Manage 23 (6): 526-32, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="125" PMID="15700131">Navari RM, Einhorn LH, Passik SD, et al.: A phase II trial of olanzapine for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a Hoosier Oncology Group study. Support Care Cancer 13 (7): 529-34, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="126" PMID="17375339">Navari RM, Einhorn LH, Loehrer PJ, et al.: A phase II trial of olanzapine, dexamethasone, and palonosetron for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a Hoosier oncology group study. Support Care Cancer 15 (11): 1285-91, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="127" PMID="19775450">Tan L, Liu J, Liu X, et al.: Clinical research of Olanzapine for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. J Exp Clin Cancer Res 28: 131, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="128" PMID="22024310">Navari RM, Gray SE, Kerr AC: Olanzapine versus aprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a randomized phase III trial. J Support Oncol 9 (5): 188-95, 2011 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="129" PMID="23856100">Mizukami N, Yamauchi M, Koike K, et al.: Olanzapine for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients receiving highly or moderately emetogenic chemotherapy: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. J Pain Symptom Manage 47 (3): 542-50, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="130" PMID="16540272">Ben Amar M: Cannabinoids in medicine: A review of their therapeutic potential. J Ethnopharmacol 105 (1-2): 1-25, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="131" PMID="18095921">Davis MP: Oral nabilone capsules in the treatment of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting and pain. Expert Opin Investig Drugs 17 (1): 85-95, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="132" PMID="6315040">Ahmedzai S, Carlyle DL, Calder IT, et al.: Anti-emetic efficacy and toxicity of nabilone, a synthetic cannabinoid, in lung cancer chemotherapy. Br J Cancer 48 (5): 657-63, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="133" PMID="3035479">Chan HS, Correia JA, MacLeod SM: Nabilone versus prochlorperazine for control of cancer chemotherapy-induced emesis in children: a double-blind, crossover trial. Pediatrics 79 (6): 946-52, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="134" PMID="6299551">Johansson R, Kilkku P, Groenroos M: A double-blind, controlled trial of nabilone vs. prochlorperazine for refractory emesis induced by cancer chemotherapy. Cancer Treat Rev 9 (Suppl B): 25-33, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="135" PMID="3002167">Niiranen A, Mattson K: A cross-over comparison of nabilone and prochlorperazine for emesis induced by cancer chemotherapy. Am J Clin Oncol 8 (4): 336-40, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="136" PMID="11440936">Tramèr MR, Carroll D, Campbell FA, et al.: Cannabinoids for control of chemotherapy induced nausea and vomiting: quantitative systematic review. BMJ 323 (7303): 16-21, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="137" PMID="17355735">Meiri E, Jhangiani H, Vredenburgh JJ, et al.: Efficacy of dronabinol alone and in combination with ondansetron versus ondansetron alone for delayed chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Curr Med Res Opin 23 (3): 533-43, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="138" PMID="16849753">Strasser F, Luftner D, Possinger K, et al.: Comparison of orally administered cannabis extract and delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol in treating patients with cancer-related anorexia-cachexia syndrome: a multicenter, phase III, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial from the Cannabis-In-Cachexia-Study-Group. J Clin Oncol 24 (21): 3394-400, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="139" PMID="18685302">Coffman KL: The debate about marijuana usage in transplant candidates: recent medical evidence on marijuana health effects. Curr Opin Organ Transplant 13 (2): 189-95, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="140" PMID="28666335">Bossi P, Cortinovis D, Fatigoni S, et al.: A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicenter study of a ginger extract in the management of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting (CINV) in patients receiving high-dose cisplatin. Ann Oncol 28 (10): 2547-2551, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="141" PMID="15480812">Einhorn LH, Rapoport B, Koeller J, et al.: Antiemetic therapy for multiple-day chemotherapy and high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell transplant: review and consensus statement. Support Care Cancer 13 (2): 112-6, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="142">Baltzer L, Pisters KM, Kris MG, et al.: High dose ondansetron (OND) plus dexamethasone (DEX) for the prevention of nausea and vomiting with multiple day cisplatin chemotherapy. [Abstract] Proceedings of the American Society of Clinical Oncology  12: A-1607, 462, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="143" PMID="22534864">Lorusso V, Giampaglia M, Petrucelli L, et al.: Antiemetic efficacy of single-dose palonosetron and dexamethasone in patients receiving multiple cycles of multiple day-based chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 20 (12): 3241-6, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="144" PMID="19135359">Jordan K, Kinitz I, Voigt W, et al.: Safety and efficacy of a triple antiemetic combination with the NK-1 antagonist aprepitant in highly and moderately emetogenic multiple-day chemotherapy. Eur J Cancer 45 (7): 1184-7, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="145" PMID="23274926">Olver IN, Grimison P, Chatfield M, et al.: Results of a 7-day aprepitant schedule for the prevention of nausea and vomiting in 5-day cisplatin-based germ cell tumor chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 21 (6): 1561-8, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="146" PMID="26838019">Adra N, Albany C, Brames MJ, et al.: Phase II study of fosaprepitant + 5HT3 receptor antagonist + dexamethasone in patients with germ cell tumors undergoing 5-day cisplatin-based chemotherapy: a Hoosier Cancer Research Network study. Support Care Cancer 24 (7): 2837-42, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="147" PMID="22863840">Stiff PJ, Fox-Geiman MP, Kiley K, et al.: Prevention of nausea and vomiting associated with stem cell transplant: results of a prospective, randomized trial of aprepitant used with highly emetogenic preparative regimens. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 19 (1): 49-55.e1, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="148" PMID="25225424">Schmitt T, Goldschmidt H, Neben K, et al.: Aprepitant, granisetron, and dexamethasone for prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting after high-dose melphalan in autologous transplantation for multiple myeloma: results of a randomized, placebo-controlled phase III trial. J Clin Oncol 32 (30): 3413-20, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="149" PMID="24619827">Sakurai M, Mori T, Kato J, et al.: Efficacy of aprepitant in preventing nausea and vomiting due to high-dose melphalan-based conditioning for allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Int J Hematol 99 (4): 457-62, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="150" PMID="21415280">Bubalo JS, Cherala G, McCune JS, et al.: Aprepitant pharmacokinetics and assessing the impact of aprepitant on cyclophosphamide metabolism in cancer patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. J Clin Pharmacol 52 (4): 586-94, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="151" PMID="24317849">Yeh SP, Lo WC, Hsieh CY, et al.: Palonosetron and dexamethasone for the prevention of nausea and vomiting in patients receiving allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Support Care Cancer 22 (5): 1199-206, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_347"><Title>Nonpharmacological Management of Nausea and Vomiting</Title><Para id="_348">Nonpharmacological strategies are also used to manage nausea and vomiting (N&amp;V). These strategies include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_369" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Dietary alterations. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000276584#_117" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/appetite-loss/nutrition-hp-pdq">Behavioral strategies for symptom management</SummaryRef> section in  Nutrition in Cancer Care.</ListItem><ListItem>Hypnosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Acupuncture. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000445441" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/acupuncture-pdq">Acupuncture</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Acupressure.</ListItem><ListItem>Relaxation techniques.</ListItem><ListItem>Behavioral therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Guided imagery.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_370">Guided imagery, hypnosis, and systematic desensitization as means to progressive muscle relaxation have been the most frequently studied treatments for anticipatory N&amp;V (ANV). They are the recommended treatments for this classically conditioned response. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062747#_30" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">Treatment of ANV</SummaryRef>   section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><Title>Radiation-Induced Nausea and Vomiting</Title><SummarySection id="_566"><Para id="_567">Radiation therapy (RT)   is an important cause of nausea and vomiting (N&amp;V) in patients with cancer.  Observational studies suggest that some degree of N&amp;V occurs in 80% of patients undergoing RT.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Risk factors for developing N&amp;V are known. Radiation-induced N&amp;V (RINV) worsen quality of life, leading to treatment delays and cancelled appointments and compromising cancer control.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_568"><Title>Epidemiology</Title><Para id="_569">Two large prospective observational studies provide information on the frequency of RINV and antiemetic measures. The Italian Group for Antiemetic Research in Radiotherapy  analyzed the incidence of RINV in 1,020 patients receiving various kinds of RT.<Reference refidx="4"/>  Overall, 28% of patients reported nausea, vomiting, or both. The median time to the first episode of vomiting was 3 days. Antiemetic drugs were administered to 17% of the patients, including 12% treated prophylactically and 5% given rescue therapy. In a second cohort of 368 patients receiving RT, the overall incidence rate for nausea was 39% and for vomiting, 7%.<Reference refidx="5"/> Nausea was more frequent in patients receiving RT to the lower abdomen or pelvis (66%), compared with patients receiving RT to the head-and-neck area (48%). Antiemetics during RT are underprescribed.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_570"><Title>Pathophysiology of RINV</Title><Para id="_571">The pathophysiology of RINV is incompletely understood.  Serotonin, substance P, and dopamine are neurotransmitters involved in radiation-induced emesis.<Reference refidx="7"/> RINV bears a close similarity to chemotherapy-induced N&amp;V (CINV). The effectiveness of serotonin antagonists in RINV supports a role for   serotonin in radiation-induced emesis.<Reference refidx="7"/> Substance P antagonists   have not been used in RINV as extensively as in CINV. Preclinical work suggests a role for substance P in RINV.<Reference refidx="8"/>  Substance P antagonists are only beginning to be studied for RINV. Substance P may play a role in prolonged N&amp;V after the administration of RT.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_572"><Title>Risk Stratification</Title><Para id="_573">The incidence and severity of RINV are determined by:</Para><ItemizedList id="_775" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Radiation site.</ListItem><ListItem>Volume.</ListItem><ListItem>Fractionation schedule.</ListItem><ListItem>Single and total dose.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_776">The most important factor appears to be the radiation field. The risk of N&amp;V for a patient being treated with RT depends on multiple other factors in addition to the emetogenicity of the specific RT regimen. Patient-specific factors include the following:<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_777" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Simultaneous administration of chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Age.</ListItem><ListItem>Gender.</ListItem><ListItem>Alcohol consumption.</ListItem><ListItem>Anxiety.</ListItem><ListItem>Previous experience of RINV or CINV.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_574"><Title>Prevention and Treatment of RINV</Title><Para id="_575">The body of literature describing treatments for RINV is much smaller than for CINV.<Reference refidx="9"/>  Most of the studies were for patients with moderate- to high-risk features for RINV.</Para><SummarySection id="_576"><Title>Antiemetic therapy: Prevention and treatment of N&amp;V</Title><Para id="_577">Several studies show the superiority of serotonin antagonists for the prophylaxis of RINV.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> 	For example, ondansetron and dolasetron have shown superiority   over placebo or metoclopramide.  Dosing of the serotonin antagonists has been single-dose pretreatment or for consecutive days (up to 5–7 days total). Most studies have been conducted in patients at moderate to high risk of RINV.</Para><Para id="_663">Recommended dosing is ondansetron 8 mg, regardless of schedule given.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Granisetron dosing is 2 mg orally per day.<Reference refidx="3"/> A recent meta-analysis covering nine clinical trials showed   differing rates of control when emesis versus nausea is considered. Compared with placebo, fewer patients had residual emesis (40% vs. 57%; relative risk [RR], 0.7), and fewer patients required rescue medication (6.5% vs. 36%; RR, 0.18).<Reference refidx="16"/> The control of nausea seems to be more difficult. Most patients developed RT-induced nausea despite treatment (70% vs. 83% with placebo; RR, 0.84).<Reference refidx="17"/>   In summary, these trials show that patients receiving upper-abdomen irradiation are more likely to control RINV with 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>) receptor antagonists than metoclopramide, phenothiazines, or placebo.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> </Para><Para id="_664">The adverse effects of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists are generally mild, consisting mainly of headache, constipation, and asthenia.<Reference refidx="18"/>  Randomized   trials   in   RINV   have   examined the use of different   5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists, but there are no data comparing them and no consensus on optimal dosing for RINV.<Reference refidx="19"/> A   systematic   review   of 25 randomized and nonrandomized trials revealed that 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists were most commonly administered for the entire duration of a course of RT. Optimal duration and timing of 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> use before, during, and after RT administration needs to be determined.<Reference refidx="20"/> With   regard   to   palonosetron, the   appropriate   dosing   and   frequency   in   the   RINV   setting are still unclear, with once-weekly dosing possible when the drug is combined with other agents.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_578"><Title>Corticosteroids</Title><Para id="_579">Corticosteroids are an attractive therapeutic antiemetic option because of their widespread availability and low cost. For short-term use, the side effects are few and do not outweigh the benefit of these agents. One randomized trial showed that dexamethasone   was   significantly   more   effective   than   placebo   in patients receiving RT to the upper abdomen.<Reference refidx="22"/> Combining corticosteroids with a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>  receptor antagonist  was assessed in a well-designed randomized trial, in which a 5-day course of dexamethasone plus ondansetron was compared with  ondansetron plus placebo in 211 patients who received RT to the  upper abdomen.<Reference refidx="23"/> During the first 5 days, there was a statistically nonsignificant trend toward complete control of nausea (50% vs. 38% with placebo) and vomiting (78% vs. 71%), which was the primary objective of the trial. The effects of dexamethasone extended beyond the initial   5-day period, and significantly more patients had complete control of emesis over the entire course of RT (23% vs. 12% with placebo), a secondary objective of the trial. The addition of dexamethasone has a modest effect on RINV and is potentially a   useful   addition   to   a   5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>   receptor   antagonist in this setting.<Reference refidx="23"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_580"><Title>Neurokinin-1 (NK-1) receptor antagonists</Title><Para id="_581">NK-1   receptor antagonists have an established role in the management of CINV; however, no studies have evaluated their impact solely on the risk of RINV. Although preclinical data indicate that RINV is mediated in part by substance P,<Reference refidx="8"/> recommendation of these agents is premature, and   NK-1   receptor   antagonists   are   not included in the antiemetic guidelines  for RINV.<Reference refidx="3"/> A phase III, randomized, placebo-controlled trial compared an NK-1 receptor antagonist, fosaprepitant, combined with palonosetron and dexamethasone, with palonosetron and dexamethasone alone in the prevention of N&amp;V in patients who received concomitant RT and cisplatin.<Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>] Patients received fractionated radiation therapy with weekly cisplatin, 40 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>. All patients received dexamethasone on the same schedule: 16 mg on day 1, 8 mg twice a day on day 2, 4 mg twice a day on day 3, and 4 mg once on day 4. More patients who received the three-drug regimen reached a complete response (65.7% for the fosaprepitant group vs.  48.7% for the placebo group).</Para><Para id="_755">Fosaprepitant has also been compared with olanzapine for the prevention of N&amp;V in patients with head and neck or esophageal cancer who received RT concurrently with highly emetogenic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="24"/>  For those who received olanzapine, palonosetron,  and  dexamethasone  (OPD), dosing was as follows: dexamethasone 20 mg and palonosetron 0.25 mg intravenously (IV) on day 1 of chemotherapy, and olanzapine 10 mg on days 1 to 4 of chemotherapy.  For those who received fosaprepitant, palonosetron, and dexamethasone (FPD), dosing was as follows: dexamethasone 12 mg, palonosetron 0.25 mg IV, and fosaprepitant 150 mg IV on day 1 of chemotherapy, followed by dexamethasone 4 mg bid on days 2 to 3 of chemotherapy.  Complete response was similar between the two groups, with a rate of 76% overall in  the OPD arm and 74% overall in the FPD arm.  This suggests that NK-1 receptor antagonists may play a role in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_582"><Title>Other agents</Title><Para id="_583">Older, less-specific antiemetic drugs, such as prochlorperazine, metoclopramide, and cannabinoids, have shown limited efficacy in the prevention or treatment of RINV, although they may have a role in treating patients with milder symptoms and as rescue 
agents.<Reference refidx="25"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_584"><Title>Duration of Prophylaxis</Title><Para id="_585">The appropriate duration of antiemetic prophylaxis for patients receiving fractionated RT is not clear. There have been no randomized trials using 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists that compared   a   5-day   course   of   treatment   with   a   more   protracted course.<Reference refidx="7"/> A systematic review that included 25 randomized and nonrandomized trials revealed that 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists were most commonly administered for the entire duration of a course of RT.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_586"><Title>Rescue Therapy</Title><Para id="_587">Studies suggest the   benefit of   5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>   receptor   antagonists   once   nausea   or vomiting occurs, but there are no   trials   specifically   in   this   setting.<Reference refidx="26"/> The emerging role of olanzapine in breakthrough emesis in patients with CINV has not been studied in RINV.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_588"><Title>Guidelines and Patient Management</Title><Para id="_589">For   patients   at   high   risk   of   developing   RINV, prophylaxis   with   a   5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>   receptor   antagonist   is   recommended in   the   clinical  practice  guidelines  from  the Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer (MASCC) and American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO).   Based on    results   from   patients   receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy, the addition of dexamethasone to the 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist is suggested. The  antiemetic  clinical  practice  guidelines  from  both  MASCC and ASCO  also recommend  that  patients  receiving moderately emetogenic RT be  given  with a  5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, with  or  without  a  short  course  of  dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="7"/> There are no fully published comparative clinical trials on  the use of NK-1 receptor antagonists in preventing RINV; therefore, its use cannot be recommended.</Para><Para id="_650">Antiemetic dosing suggestions for the prevention of RINV are summarized in Table 6.</Para><Table id="_670"><Title>Table 6.  Antiemetic Dosing for Radiation Therapy<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="19.80%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="19.80%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="15.84%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="24.40%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="20.12%"/><THead><Row><entry>Drug Category</entry><entry>Antiemetic</entry><entry>Dose</entry><entry>Comment</entry><entry>Reference</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1">5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> = 5-hydroxytryptamine-3; bid = twice a day; IV = intravenously; PO = by mouth; prn = as needed; RT = radiation therapy; TBI = total-body irradiation; tid = 3 times a day.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Roila et al.<Reference refidx="3"/> and Hesketh et al.<Reference refidx="28"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Serotonin (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>) receptor antagonists</entry><entry>Granisetron</entry><entry>2 mg PO daily</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Ondansetron</entry><entry>8 mg PO or 0.15 mg/kg IV daily</entry><entry>bid–tid with TBI</entry><entry><Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Palonosetron</entry><entry>0.25 mg IV or 0.5 mg PO</entry><entry>Not studied in RT; no data available on frequency of administration</entry><entry><Reference refidx="28"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Dolasetron</entry><entry>100 mg PO only</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="11"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Corticosteroids</entry><entry>Dexamethasone</entry><entry>4 mg PO or IV</entry><entry>During fractions 1–5</entry><entry><Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Dopamine receptor antagonists</entry><entry>Metoclopramide</entry><entry>20 mg PO</entry><entry>prn during minimal-emetic-risk RT; inferior to 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonists</entry><entry><Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Prochlorperazine</entry><entry>10 mg PO or IV</entry><entry>prn during minimal-emetic-risk RT</entry><entry><Reference refidx="28"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="22098284">Dennis K, Maranzano E, De Angelis C, et al.: Radiotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. Expert Rev Pharmacoecon Outcomes Res 11 (6): 685-92, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11693797">Maranzano E: Radiation-induced emesis: a problem with many open questions. Tumori 87 (4): 213-8, 2001 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27664248">Roila F, Molassiotis A, Herrstedt J, et al.: 2016 MASCC and ESMO guideline update for the prevention of chemotherapy- and radiotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting and of nausea and vomiting in advanced cancer patients. Ann Oncol 27 (suppl 5): v119-v133, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19963296">Maranzano E, De Angelis V, Pergolizzi S, et al.: A prospective observational trial on emesis in radiotherapy: analysis of 1020 patients recruited in 45 Italian radiation oncology centres. Radiother Oncol 94 (1): 36-41, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18528717">Enblom A, Bergius Axelsson B, Steineck G, et al.: One third of patients with radiotherapy-induced nausea consider their antiemetic treatment insufficient. Support Care Cancer 17 (1): 23-32, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15519770">Horiot JC: Prophylaxis versus treatment: is there a better way to manage radiotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting? Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 60 (4): 1018-25, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="24157983">Feyer P, Jahn F, Jordan K: Radiation induced nausea and vomiting. Eur J Pharmacol 722: 165-71, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="16098569">Yamamoto K, Nohara K, Furuya T, et al.: Ondansetron, dexamethasone and an NK1 antagonist block radiation sickness in mice. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 82 (1): 24-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="26489389">Chow E, Meyer RM, Ding K, et al.: Dexamethasone in the prophylaxis of radiation-induced pain flare after palliative radiotherapy for bone metastases: a double-blind, randomised placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 16 (15): 1463-72, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="9424001">Aass N, Håtun DE, Thoresen M, et al.: Prophylactic use of tropisetron or metoclopramide during adjuvant abdominal radiotherapy of seminoma stage I: a randomised, open trial in 23 patients. Radiother Oncol 45 (2): 125-8, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8883232">Bey P, Wilkinson PM, Resbeut M, et al.: A double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of i.v. dolasetron mesilate in the prevention of radiotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 4 (5): 378-83, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="19468247">Volk A, Kersting S, Konopke R, et al.: Surgical therapy of intrapancreatic metastasis from renal cell carcinoma. Pancreatology 9 (4): 392-7, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="8879372">Franzén L, Nyman J, Hagberg H, et al.: A randomised placebo controlled study with ondansetron in patients undergoing fractionated radiotherapy. Ann Oncol 7 (6): 587-92, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="11768028">Lanciano R, Sherman DM, Michalski J, et al.: The efficacy and safety of once-daily Kytril (granisetron hydrochloride) tablets in the prophylaxis of nausea and emesis following fractionated upper abdominal radiotherapy. Cancer Invest 19 (8): 763-72, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="8934050">Priestman TJ, Dunn J, Brada M, et al.: Final results of the Royal College of Radiologists' trial comparing two different radiotherapy schedules in the treatment of cerebral metastases. Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol) 8 (5): 308-15, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="8305355">Priestman TJ, Roberts JT, Upadhyaya BK: A prospective randomized double-blind trial comparing ondansetron versus prochlorperazine for the prevention of nausea and vomiting in patients undergoing fractionated radiotherapy. Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol) 5 (6): 358-63, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="22130630">Chow E, Zeng L, Salvo N, et al.: Update on the systematic review of palliative radiotherapy trials for bone metastases. Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol) 24 (2): 112-24, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="12401905">Goodin S, Cunningham R: 5-HT(3)-receptor antagonists for the treatment of nausea and vomiting: a reappraisal of their side-effect profile. Oncologist 7 (5): 424-36, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="21075553">Salvo N, Doble B, Khan L, et al.: Prophylaxis of radiation-induced nausea and vomiting using 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 serotonin receptor antagonists: a systematic review of randomized trials. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 82 (1): 408-17, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="21901298">Dennis K, Nguyen J, Presutti R, et al.: Prophylaxis of radiotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in the palliative treatment of bone metastases. Support Care Cancer 20 (8): 1673-8, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="26952945">Ruhlmann CH, Christensen TB, Dohn LH, et al.: Efficacy and safety of fosaprepitant for the prevention of nausea and emesis during 5 weeks of chemoradiotherapy for cervical cancer (the GAND-emesis study): a multinational, randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 17 (4): 509-18, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="10784638">Kirkbride P, Bezjak A, Pater J, et al.: Dexamethasone for the prophylaxis of radiation-induced emesis: a National Cancer Institute of Canada Clinical Trials Group phase III study. J Clin Oncol 18 (9): 1960-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="16849762">Wong RK, Paul N, Ding K, et al.: 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 receptor antagonist with or without short-course dexamethasone in the prophylaxis of radiation induced emesis: a placebo-controlled randomized trial of the National Cancer Institute of Canada Clinical Trials Group (SC19). J Clin Oncol 24 (21): 3458-64, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="27152512">Navari RM, Nagy CK, Le-Rademacher J, et al.: Olanzapine versus fosaprepitant for the prevention of concurrent chemotherapy radiotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting. J Community Support Oncol 14 (4): 141-7, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="21188425">Roila F, Herrstedt J, Gralla RJ, et al.: Prevention of chemotherapy- and radiotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: guideline update and results of the Perugia consensus conference. Support Care Cancer 19 (Suppl 1): S63-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="16720926">Mystakidou K, Katsouda E, Linou A, et al.: Prophylactic tropisetron versus rescue tropisetron in fractionated radiotherapy to moderate or high emetogenic areas: a prospective randomized open label study in cancer patients. Med Oncol 23 (2): 251-62, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="23314603">Navari RM, Nagy CK, Gray SE: The use of olanzapine versus metoclopramide for the treatment of breakthrough chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 21 (6): 1655-63, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="28759346">Hesketh PJ, Kris MG, Basch E, et al.: Antiemetics: American Society of Clinical Oncology Clinical Practice Guideline Update. J Clin Oncol 35 (28): 3240-3261, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_590"><Title>Pediatric Chemotherapy-Induced Acute Nausea and Vomiting</Title><SummarySection id="_591"><Title>Pediatric Guidelines  for Acute Nausea and Vomiting (N&amp;V)</Title><Para id="_592">Chemotherapy-induced N&amp;V (CINV) is an important problem in the pediatric population. As in adults, nausea in children is more of a problem than vomiting. Parents of children who received active antineoplastic therapy in Ontario, Canada, identified nausea as the fourth most prevalent and bothersome treatment-related symptom.<Reference refidx="1"/> Current approaches to prevent CINV are based on an accurate description of the potential of antineoplastic therapies to cause N&amp;V. Current recommendations, based on published guidelines,<Reference refidx="2"/>  include patients aged 1 month to 18 years who are about to receive their first-ever course of antineoplastic therapy.  These recommendations focus on the prevention of acute CINV (i.e., within 24 hours of administration of an antineoplastic agent).</Para><Para id="_673">Guidelines define optimal control of acute CINV as no vomiting, no retching, no nausea, no use of antiemetic agents other than those given for CINV prevention, and no nausea-related change in the child’s usual appetite and diet. This level of CINV control is to be achieved on each day that antineoplastic therapy is administered and for 24 hours after administration of the last agent in the antineoplastic therapy cycle.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_593"><Title>Emetic Risk</Title><Para id="_594">In children receiving antineoplastic agents who were not given antiemetic prophylaxis or who were given ineffective prophylaxis, expected rates of complete CINV control  were as follows:<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_778" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>High emetic risk, less than 10%.</ListItem><ListItem>Moderate emetic risk, 10% to less than 30%.</ListItem><ListItem>Low emetic risk, 30% to less than 90%.</ListItem><ListItem>Minimal emetic risk, more than 90%.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_779">The expected rate of complete CINV control in children receiving antiemetic prophylaxis (5-hydroxytryptamine-3 [5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>] receptor antagonist with or without dexamethasone) is more than 70% to 80%.<Reference refidx="2"/> Each chemotherapy agent carries an inherent risk of emesis, which is the first issue to consider when planning chemotherapy treatment. For more information about preventing acute or delayed CINV, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062747#_694" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">Table 5</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_595"><Title>Acute Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting—Antiemetic Prophylaxis</Title><SummarySection id="_596"><Title>Highly emetogenic chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_597">Guidelines <Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> recommend that children aged 6 months and older who are receiving antineoplastic agents of high emetic risk that are not known or suspected to interact with aprepitant receive aprepitant, a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist, and dexamethasone. Children older than 6 months  who cannot receive dexamethasone should receive a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist plus aprepitant.  Children who cannot receive aprepitant should receive a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist plus dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_598"><Title>Moderately emetogenic chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_599">Children receiving antineoplastic agents of moderate emetogenicity should receive ondansetron, granisetron, or palonosetron plus dexamethasone. Children aged 6 months and older and whose antineoplastic agents do not interact with aprepitant and who cannot receive dexamethasone should receive a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist plus aprepitant.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_600"><Title>Low emetogenic  chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_601">Children receiving antineoplastic agents of low emetogenicity should receive a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_602"><Title>Minimal emetogenic potential</Title><Para id="_603">Children receiving antineoplastic agents of minimal emetogenicity should receive no routine prophylaxis.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_604"><Title>Other Antiemetic Modalities</Title><Para id="_605">Current consensus is that the following modalities may be effective in children receiving antineoplastic agents:<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_780" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Acupuncture.</ListItem><ListItem>Acupressure.</ListItem><ListItem>Guided imagery.</ListItem><ListItem>Music therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Progressive muscle relaxation.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychoeducational support and information.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_781">In addition, virtual reality may convey some benefit. Other recommendations (low level of evidence) include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_782" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Eating smaller, more-frequent meals.</ListItem><ListItem>Reducing food aromas and other stimuli with strong odors.</ListItem><ListItem>Avoiding foods that are spicy, fatty, or highly salty.</ListItem><ListItem>Taking antiemetics before meals so that the effect is present during and after meals.</ListItem><ListItem>Using measures and foods (e.g., “comfort foods”) that previously helped minimize nausea.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_783">Despite a lack of strong evidence, most experts think that these recommendations are unlikely to result in undesirable effects or to adversely affect quality of life, and they may convey benefit.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_606"><Title>Antiemetics</Title><Para id="_674">Prophylaxis with a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist alone leads to poor CINV control in pediatric patients receiving antineoplastic agents of moderate and high emetic risk. A synthesis of three studies that evaluated alternative antiemetic agents (chlorpromazine and  metoclopramide) in children receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy observed a complete CINV control rate of 9% (95% confidence interval: 0, 20).<Reference refidx="2"/>  When corticosteroids are contraindicated, it is recommended that nabilone or chlorpromazine be administered together with ondansetron or granisetron to children receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy. Metoclopramide is a third option for children receiving moderately emetogenic chemotherapy. Corticosteroids combined with a serotonin antagonist are recommended for patients receiving highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_675">Antiemetic dosing suggestions for pediatric patients are summarized in Table 7.</Para><Table id="_676"><Title>Table 7.  Pediatric Antiemetic Dosing</Title><TGroup Cols="6"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="16.66%"/><THead><Row><entry>Drug Category</entry><entry>Medication</entry><entry>Dose</entry><entry>Available Route</entry><entry>Comment</entry><entry>Reference</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1">5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> = 5-hydroxytryptamine-3; bid = twice a day; BSA = body surface area; EPS = extrapyramidal symptoms; IM = intramuscular; IV = intravenous; NK-1 = neurokinin-1; PO = oral; PR = rectal; prn = as needed; qd = every day; SL = sublingual; tid = 3 times a day.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Palonosetron prescribing information lists the pediatric maximum dose at 1.5 mg.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Phenothiazines</entry><entry>Chlorpromazine</entry><entry>0.5 mg/kg/dose q6h; may increase to 1 mg/kg/dose q6h; maximum dose: 50 mg</entry><entry>IV</entry><entry>Prolongs QTc interval; use with 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist when corticosteroid contraindicated;

dose adjustments based on efficacy and sedation
</entry><entry><Reference refidx="6"/>; <Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Prochlorperazine</entry><entry>9–13 kg: 2.5 mg PO qd–bid; maximum dose: 7.5 mg/d</entry><entry MoreRows="2">PO, IM, IV</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Less sedation, but increased risk of EPS</entry><entry MoreRows="2"><Reference refidx="6"/>; <Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>13–18 kg: 2.5 mg PO bid–tid; maximum dose: 10 mg/d</entry></Row><Row><entry>18–39 kg: 2.5 mg tid or 5 mg bid; maximum dose: 15 mg/d</entry></Row><Row><entry>Promethazine</entry><entry>Age &gt;2 y:
0.25–1 mg/kg/dose q4–6h;
maximum dose: 25 mg
</entry><entry>PO, IM, IV, PR</entry><entry>Vesicant</entry><entry><Reference refidx="6"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Substituted benzamides</entry><entry>Metoclopramide</entry><entry>Moderately emetogenic chemotherapy:
1 mg/kg/dose IV once prechemotherapy, then 0.0375 mg/kg/dose PO q6h</entry><entry>PO, IM, IV</entry><entry>EPS associated with higher doses; pretreat with benztropine or diphenhydramine to prevent EPS; enhances gastric emptying </entry><entry><Reference refidx="6"/>; <Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Serotonin (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>) receptor antagonists </entry><entry>Granisetron</entry><entry>40 μg/kg IV daily; 40 μg/kg PO q12h;

maximum: 1 mg/dose</entry><entry>IV, PO</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Ondansetron</entry><entry>Age 0–&lt;12 y:
0.15 mg/kg/dose
(5 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/dose) prechemotherapy, then q8h for highly emetogenic or q12h for moderately emetogenic chemotherapy</entry><entry MoreRows="2">PO, IV</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Avoid IV doses &gt;16 mg due to QTc prolongation; age &gt;12 y: follow adult dosing</entry><entry MoreRows="2"><Reference refidx="6"/>; <Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Low emetogenic chemotherapy:
0.3 mg/kg/dose (10 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/dose) once prechemotherapy</entry></Row><Row><entry>Maximum PO dose:
24 mg; maximum IV dose: 16 mg</entry></Row><Row><entry>Palonosetron</entry><entry>Age 1 mo–17 y:
20 μg/kg; maximum dose: 0.75 mg<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>IV, PO</entry><entry> Due to pediatric half-life of  30 h, administered q2–3d during multiday chemotherapy</entry><entry><Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]; maximum dose: <Reference refidx="11"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Substance P antagonists (NK-1 receptor antagonists)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Aprepitant</entry><entry>Capsule:  Age &gt;12 y: 125 mg prechemotherapy day 1, then 80 mg qd x2 d</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO</entry><entry>CYP3A4 enzyme inhibitor; CYP2C9 enzyme inducer</entry><entry MoreRows="1"><Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Suspension:
Age 6 mo–12 y (and &gt;6 kg): 3 mg/kg prechemotherapy day 1, then 2 mg/kg qd x2 d
</entry><entry>Suspension:
Maximum dose day 1: 125 mg; 
maximum dose days 2–3: 80 mg</entry></Row><Row><entry>Fosaprepitant</entry><entry>Age 13–17 y: 150 mg</entry><entry>IV</entry><entry>CYP3A4 enzyme inhibitor; CYP2C9 enzyme inducer</entry><entry><Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Corticosteroids</entry><entry MoreRows="3">Dexamethasone</entry><entry>Highly emetogenic chemotherapy:
6 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/dose q6h</entry><entry MoreRows="3">PO, IV</entry><entry>May be omitted in some brain tumor, osteosarcoma, and carcinoma protocols due to fear of reducing cytotoxic effects of chemotherapy</entry><entry MoreRows="3"><Reference refidx="6"/>; <Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Moderately emetogenic chemotherapy:
BSA ≤0.6 m<Superscript>2</Superscript>: 2 mg q12h</entry><entry>Combined with 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist</entry></Row><Row><entry>BSA &gt;0.6 m<Superscript>2</Superscript>: 4 mg q12h</entry><entry>When given with aprepitant or fosaprepitant, reduce dose by 50%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Maximum: 20 mg/dose</entry><entry>Most effective for delayed nausea</entry></Row><Row><entry>Methylprednisolone</entry><entry>4–10 mg/kg/dose</entry><entry>PO, IV</entry><entry>Given with 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist</entry><entry><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Benzodiazepines</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Lorazepam</entry><entry>Anticipatory:
0.02–0.05 mg/kg/dose (maximum: 2 mg/dose) once at
bedtime the night before chemotherapy and once prechemotherapy</entry><entry MoreRows="1">PO, SL, IM, IV</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Most-commonly used drug in class</entry><entry><Reference refidx="6"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Breakthrough:
0.02–0.05 mg/kg/dose IV (maximum: 2 mg)
q6h prn</entry><entry><Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry>Atypical antipsychotics</entry><entry>Olanzapine</entry><entry>0.1–0.14 mg/kg/dose qd; maximum: 10 mg</entry><entry>PO</entry><entry/><entry><Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Other pharmacological agents</entry><entry>Dronabinol</entry><entry>Age 6–18 y: 
2.1 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> 1–3 h prechemotherapy   </entry><entry>PO</entry><entry>Single-institution experience only; benefit of appetite stimulant properties</entry><entry><Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Nabilone</entry><entry>Age &gt;4 y:</entry><entry MoreRows="4">PO</entry><entry MoreRows="4">May be continued up to 48 h postchemotherapy; has not been compared with 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist with or without corticosteroid; use with 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist when corticosteroid contraindicated</entry><entry MoreRows="4"><Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>&lt;18 kg: 0.5 mg q12h</entry></Row><Row><entry>18–30 kg: 1 mg q12h</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;30 kg: 1 mg  q8–12h</entry></Row><Row><entry>Maximum dose: 0.06 mg/kg/d</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_625"><Title>Multiagent, single-day chemotherapy regimens</Title><Para id="_626">Experience in pediatrics and guidelines recommend basing the emetogenicity of  combination antineoplastic regimens on that of the agent of highest emetic risk.<Reference refidx="20"/> The emetogenicity of the antineoplastic combinations in the following list appears to be higher than would be appreciated by assessment of the emetic risk of the individual agents.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_658" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>High Level of Emetic Risk (&gt;90% Frequency of Emesis in Absence of Prophylaxis)</ListTitle><ListItem>Cyclophosphamide + anthracycline.</ListItem><ListItem>Cyclophosphamide + etoposide.</ListItem><ListItem>Cytarabine (150–200 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) + daunorubicin.</ListItem><ListItem>Cytarabine (300 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) + etoposide.</ListItem><ListItem>Cytarabine (300 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) + teniposide.</ListItem><ListItem>Doxorubicin + ifosfamide.</ListItem><ListItem>Doxorubicin + methotrexate (5 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>).</ListItem><ListItem>Etoposide + ifosfamide.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="19513763">Dupuis LL, Milne-Wren C, Cassidy M, et al.: Symptom assessment in children receiving cancer therapy: the parents' perspective. Support Care Cancer 18 (3): 281-99, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="23512831">Dupuis LL, Boodhan S, Holdsworth M, et al.: Guideline for the prevention of acute nausea and vomiting due to antineoplastic medication in pediatric cancer patients. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (7): 1073-82, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27565788">Dupuis LL, Sung L, Molassiotis A, et al.: 2016 updated MASCC/ESMO consensus recommendations: Prevention of acute chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in children. Support Care Cancer 25 (1): 323-331, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="36221901">Patel P, Robinson PD, Cohen M, et al.: Prevention of acute and delayed chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in pediatric cancer patients: A clinical practice guideline. Pediatr Blood Cancer 69 (12): e30001, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10989464">White L, Daly SA, McKenna CJ, et al.: A comparison of oral ondansetron syrup or intravenous ondansetron loading dose regimens given in combination with dexamethasone for the prevention of nausea and emesis in pediatric and adolescent patients receiving moderately/highly emetogenic chemotherapy. Pediatr Hematol Oncol 17 (6): 445-55, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Lexicomp Online. Hudson, Ohio: Lexi-Comp, Inc., 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.wolterskluwer.com/en/solutions/uptodate/enterprise/lexidrug">Available online with subscription</ExternalRef>. Last accessed Jan. 15, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="8229497">Relling MV, Mulhern RK, Fairclough D, et al.: Chlorpromazine with and without lorazepam as antiemetic therapy in children receiving uniform chemotherapy. J Pediatr 123 (5): 811-6, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="3035479">Chan HS, Correia JA, MacLeod SM: Nabilone versus prochlorperazine for control of cancer chemotherapy-induced emesis in children: a double-blind, crossover trial. Pediatrics 79 (6): 946-52, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9809818">Köseoglu V, Kürekçi AE, Sarici U, et al.: Comparison of the efficacy and side-effects of ondansetron and metoclopramide-diphenhydramine administered to control nausea and vomiting in children treated with antineoplastic chemotherapy: a prospective randomized study. Eur J Pediatr 157 (10): 806-10, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="17372773">Berrak SG, Ozdemir N, Bakirci N, et al.: A double-blind, crossover, randomized dose-comparison trial of granisetron for the prevention of acute and delayed nausea and emesis in children receiving moderately emetogenic carboplatin-based chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 15 (10): 1163-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="11">Kadota R, Shen V, Messinger Y: Safety, pharmacokinetics, and efficacy of palonosetron in pediatric patients: a multicenter, stratified, double-blind, phase 3, randomized study. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  25 (18 suppl): A-9570, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="25770814">Kang HJ, Loftus S, Taylor A, et al.: Aprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in children: a randomised, double-blind, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 16 (4): 385-94, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="4093665">Siddiqui MA, Ghaznawi HI: Some observations on intestinal parasites in Hajis visiting Saudi Arabia, during 1983 G (1403 H.) Pilgrimage. J Egypt Soc Parasitol 15 (2): 705-12, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="10779025">Small BE, Holdsworth MT, Raisch DW, et al.: Survey ranking of emetogenic control in children receiving chemotherapy. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 22 (2): 125-32, 2000 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="8259853">Hirota T, Honjo T, Kuroda R, et al.: [Antiemetic efficacy of granisetron in pediatric cancer treatment--(2). Comparison of granisetron and granisetron plus methylprednisolone as antiemetic prophylaxis]. Gan To Kagaku Ryoho 20 (15): 2369-73, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="12956617">Dupuis LL, Nathan PC: Options for the prevention and management of acute chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in children. Paediatr Drugs 5 (9): 597-613, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="25328089">Flank J, Thackray J, Nielson D, et al.: Olanzapine for treatment and prevention of acute chemotherapy-induced vomiting in children: a retrospective, multi-center review. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (3): 496-501, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="26766935">Elder JJ, Knoderer HM: Characterization of Dronabinol Usage in a Pediatric Oncology Population. J Pediatr Pharmacol Ther 20 (6): 462-7, 2015 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="3013104">Dalzell AM, Bartlett H, Lilleyman JS: Nabilone: an alternative antiemetic for cancer chemotherapy. Arch Dis Child 61 (5): 502-5, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="21465637">Dupuis LL, Boodhan S, Sung L, et al.: Guideline for the classification of the acute emetogenic potential of antineoplastic medication in pediatric cancer patients. Pediatr Blood Cancer 57 (2): 191-8, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="16404740">Holdsworth MT, Raisch DW, Frost J: Acute and delayed nausea and emesis control in pediatric oncology patients. Cancer 106 (4): 931-40, 2006.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_627"><Title>Pediatric Delayed Nausea and Vomiting</Title><Para id="_628">The   nature   and   prevalence   of   delayed   nausea and vomiting (N&amp;V) in children after administration of antineoplastic agents   have   not   been   well described.<Reference refidx="1"/> Additionally, most pediatric chemotherapy regimens are given over multiple days, making the onset and duration of risk of delayed versus acute N&amp;V unclear.</Para><Para id="_629">Research on   chemotherapy-induced N&amp;V (CINV) in children has been limited in part by the lack of assessment tools and the subjective nature of nausea.  In the pediatric population, vomiting is more easily recognizable and measurable than nausea.<Reference refidx="1"/> Difficulties   in   assessing nausea   in   young   children may   contribute   to the common perception that   young children experience   CINV less frequently than older children.  In addition, caregivers may      have   a   higher   tolerance   for   vomiting   in   young   children and may miss detecting nausea.<Reference refidx="1"/> In view of these limitations, studies often use dietary intake to assess the extent of nausea.</Para><Para id="_630">Several investigators have attempted to determine the prevalence of delayed N&amp;V in the pediatric population. One early study suggested a low incidence.<Reference refidx="2"/> A large study assessed the nature and prevalence of delayed CINV in children.<Reference refidx="1"/> Nausea   was   self-assessed daily using a numeric scale reflecting the effect of nausea on activities and a faces scale for children aged 3 to 6 years. Diet was also assessed daily.  Results showed a 33% rate of delayed vomiting in patients who received    cyclophosphamide,   cisplatin,   or   carboplatin   and   an 11%   rate   in   those   who received   other antineoplastic agents.   No antiemetics were given on 412 (79%) of 522 study days. Nevertheless, on 381 (93%) of those 412 study days,   patients were   completely   free   from   vomiting. Antiemetics   were   most   often   given   as   single agents (ondansetron, on 54 study days; dimenhydrinate, on 17 study days; dexamethasone, on 6 study days).    Diet was not affected. The authors concluded that antineoplastic-induced delayed N&amp;V may be less prevalent in children than in adults.<Reference refidx="1"/> The high percentage of children who did not experience delayed vomiting may reflect a lack of significant emetogenic potential   among   many   of the regimens in the study. In   100   of   174 chemotherapy cycles, no antiemetics were administered. In addition, there was no characterization of antiemetic response in moderate and severe chemotherapy regimens.</Para><Para id="_631">Another study evaluated the incidence of delayed N&amp;V in pediatric patients receiving moderately and highly emetogenic chemotherapy as well as premedications (ondansetron alone or with dexamethasone, depending on a treatment’s emetogenic potential).<Reference refidx="3"/> Investigators measured nausea severity   and   duration,   vomiting   severity, the number of vomiting episodes, interference with daily activities, and assessment of appetite. The authors found that delayed N&amp;V occurred with both moderately and highly emetogenic chemotherapy regimens, but that the severity of N&amp;V varied. In addition, toddlers had better antiemetic control than older children, which may be the result of anxiety differences between the age groups. The reasons for toddler patients' greater complete control are unclear but are consistent with a previous study of N&amp;V control rates in children.<Reference refidx="4"/> Anxiety and patient perception may be   important   contributors   to   N&amp;V   in older   children; a relationship between control of acute N&amp;V and the occurrence of delayed N&amp;V was found.</Para><Para id="_632">Another  study suggested a higher incidence of delayed N&amp;V than was previously found in a pediatric population.<Reference refidx="5"/> In 40 pediatric cancer patients receiving chemotherapy, N&amp;V was measured from the child’s perspective using the Adapted Rhodes Index of Nausea and Vomiting for Pediatrics; from the primary caregiver’s perspective using the Adapted Rhodes Index of Nausea and Vomiting for Parents; and from the nurses' perspective using the National Cancer Institute Nausea and Vomiting Grading Criteria. The highest frequency of nausea occurred in the delayed period, with 60% of patients (n = 24) reporting delayed nausea. The authors concluded that CINV occurred throughout the chemotherapy course, with delayed N&amp;V  occurring most frequently and with greater severity and distress. Delayed N&amp;V in the pediatric population requires further study.</Para><Para id="_668">Because well-designed studies on the prevention of delayed N&amp;V in children are not available,  the best available evidence comes from adult data and a pediatric clinical practice guideline.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="7"/></Para><SummarySection id="_801"><Title>Delayed Chemotherapy-Induced Nausea and Vomiting—Antiemetic Prophylaxis</Title><SummarySection id="_802"><Title>Highly emetogenic chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_803">Palonosetron is the preferred 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>) receptor antagonist in the acute phase in patients at high risk of delayed CINV. Guidelines recommend that children who can receive aprepitant and dexamethasone continue to do so during the delayed phase. If dexamethasone cannot be used, aprepitant should be continued. If aprepitant cannot be used, dexamethasone should be continued. If olanzapine was started during the acute phase, it should be continued during the delayed phase.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_804">In a phase III, double-blind, randomized controlled trial, 128 patients aged 3 to 18 years receiving highly emetogenic chemotherapy were randomly assigned to receive intravenous ondansetron and dexamethasone plus olanzapine or placebo on days 1 and 2. More patients in the olanzapine group had complete control of vomiting in the delayed phase (73% vs. 48%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .005), although there was no difference in control in the acute phase or overall. More patients in the placebo group required rescue medications for vomiting than in the olanzapine group (29% vs. 14%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .025). Grade 1/2 sedation was greater in the olanzapine group than in the placebo group (46% vs. 14%).<Reference refidx="8"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_805"><Title>Moderately emetogenic chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_806">In the delayed phase, children receiving antineoplastic agents of moderate emetogenicity who received a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor inhibitor and dexamethasone in the acute phase should consider dexamethasone during the delayed phase.</Para><Para id="_807">Children receiving a 1-day regimen of antineoplastic agents of moderate emetogenicity who received a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor inhibitor and fosaprepitant or aprepitant in the acute phase should continue oral aprepitant in the delayed phase. Children receiving a multiday regimen of antineoplastic agents of moderate emetogenicity who received a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor inhibitor and fosaprepitant or aprepitant in the acute phase should consider not using oral aprepitant in the delayed phase.</Para><Para id="_808">Children receiving a 5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor inhibitor with olanzapine during the acute phase should consider continuing olanzapine during the delayed phase.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_809"><Title>Low emetogenic chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_810">Children receiving antineoplastic agents of low emetogenicity should not receive routine prophylaxis during the delayed phase.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_811"><Title>Minimal emetogenic potential</Title><Para id="_812">Children receiving antineoplastic agents of minimal emetogenicity should not receive routine prophylaxis during the delayed phase.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11496349">Dupuis LL, Lau R, Greenberg ML: Delayed nausea and vomiting in children receiving antineoplastics. Med Pediatr Oncol 37 (2): 115-21, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="7826125">Foot AB, Hayes C: Audit of guidelines for effective control of chemotherapy and radiotherapy induced emesis. Arch Dis Child 71 (5): 475-80, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="16404740">Holdsworth MT, Raisch DW, Frost J: Acute and delayed nausea and emesis control in pediatric oncology patients. Cancer 106 (4): 931-40, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10779025">Small BE, Holdsworth MT, Raisch DW, et al.: Survey ranking of emetogenic control in children receiving chemotherapy. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 22 (2): 125-32, 2000 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21915041">Rodgers C, Kollar D, Taylor O, et al.: Nausea and vomiting perspectives among children receiving moderate to highly emetogenic chemotherapy treatment. Cancer Nurs 35 (3): 203-10, 2012 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="36221901">Patel P, Robinson PD, Cohen M, et al.: Prevention of acute and delayed chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in pediatric cancer patients: A clinical practice guideline. Pediatr Blood Cancer 69 (12): e30001, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="27565788">Dupuis LL, Sung L, Molassiotis A, et al.: 2016 updated MASCC/ESMO consensus recommendations: Prevention of acute chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in children. Support Care Cancer 25 (1): 323-331, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="35091522">Moothedath AW, Meena JP, Gupta AK, et al.: Efficacy and Safety of Olanzapine in Children Receiving Highly Emetogenic Chemotherapy: A Randomized, Double-blind Placebo-controlled Phase 3 Trial. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 44 (8): 446-453, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_633"><Title>Pediatric Anticipatory Nausea and Vomiting</Title><Para id="_634">Patients with cancer who have received chemotherapy may experience nausea and vomiting (N&amp;V) when anticipating further chemotherapy. Study differences in methodology, timing, and assessment instruments; small samples; and a focus on nausea or vomiting but not both has led to difficulties in capturing the prevalence of anticipatory N&amp;V (ANV) in children. Accurate prevalence is also stymied by using parent or caregiver proxy reports of nausea and nonvalidated nausea assessment tools.</Para><Para id="_662">In patients receiving 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 (5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript>) receptor antagonists and corticosteroids as antiemetic agents, approximately one-third of adults experienced ANV, while 6% to 11% reported anticipatory vomiting.<Reference refidx="1"/> A study of children in the pre–5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist era reported anticipatory nausea in 23 (29%) of  80 children and anticipatory vomiting in 16 (20%) of  80 children who had received 11 cycles of antineoplastic therapy, on average, before evaluation.<Reference refidx="2"/> In the post–5-HT<Subscript>3</Subscript> receptor antagonist era, the reported prevalence of anticipatory nausea in children has ranged from 0% to 59%.<Reference refidx="3"/> Similar to observations in adult patients, the reported prevalence of anticipatory  nausea is always higher than that of anticipatory vomiting in children, although one study reported an equivalent prevalence (5 [26%] of 19 patients) for these conditions.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_667">This section focuses on the management of ANV in children aged 1 month to 18 years who are receiving antineoplastic medication. Optimal control of ANV is defined as no vomiting, no retching, no nausea, no use of antiemetic agents other than those given for the prevention or treatment of chemotherapy-induced N&amp;V (CINV), and no nausea-related change in the child’s usual appetite and diet. This level of ANV control is to be achieved during the 24 hours before administration of the first antineoplastic agent of the upcoming planned antineoplastic cycle.</Para><SummarySection id="_635"><Title>Approaches to Prevent ANV in Children</Title><Para id="_636">ANV appears to be a conditioned response to CINV experienced in the acute phase (24 hours after administration of chemotherapy) and delayed phase (more than 24 hours after and within 7 days of administration of chemotherapy).<Reference refidx="3"/> The anxiety and distress attendant to CINV reinforce the conditioned response.<Reference refidx="3"/> It follows, then, that a higher rate of complete control of acute and delayed CINV would result in lower rates of ANV. Adherence to evidence-based recommendations for CINV prevention has been shown to substantially improve complete control of acute CINV.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_661">Optimized control of acute and delayed CINV may help minimize exposure to the negative stimuli required for conditioning to occur. Consensus recommendations call for antiemetic interventions to be based on published guidelines for the prevention of acute CINV in children receiving antineoplastic agents,<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>   including antineoplastic agent–naïve patients. Once antineoplastic therapy has been initiated, the selection of antiemetic interventions should be informed by evidence-based guidelines and tailored to the patient's CINV control and any adverse effects associated with antiemetic agents.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_637"><Title>Interventions to Control ANV in Children</Title><SummarySection id="_638"><Title>Hypnosis</Title><Para id="_639">Hypnosis has been defined as an intervention that “provides suggestions for changes in sensation, perception, cognition, affect, mood, or behavior.”<Reference refidx="8"/> Two trials evaluated the role of hypnosis in controlling ANV in children. One study  recruited 54 children aged 5 to 17 years who had reported experiencing anticipatory nausea, anticipatory vomiting, or both in a previous study and who were about to receive at least two identical antineoplastic treatment courses.<Reference refidx="9"/> On average, children were 15.8 months (range, 0.5–118 months) from their cancer diagnosis at the time of the study. The control group had received antineoplastic therapy for much longer than the other two groups (29.5 months vs. 8 or 11.5 months).</Para><Para id="_677">Although it is not possible to precisely ascertain the emetogenicity of the antineoplastic therapy these children received, it appears that most received highly emetogenic treatment. The antiemetic agents taken for prophylaxis were not reported, but children’s antiemetic regimens were unchanged during the trial. The severity of N&amp;V was assessed through semistructured interviews. Children were randomly assigned to receive one of three possible interventions: hypnosis training (imagination-focused therapy), active cognitive distraction (relaxation), or contact with a therapist (control). The authors reported a significant improvement in complete control of anticipatory vomiting in the group who received hypnosis training (12 [57%] of 21 patients at baseline vs. 18 [86%] of 21 patients after hypnosis training; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05). Complete control of anticipatory nausea increased from 5 (24%) of 21 patients at baseline to 8 (38%) of 21 patients after hypnosis training.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_660">Another  study  evaluated hypnosis as a means of preventing ANV in 20 children aged 6 to 18 years who were naïve to chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="10"/> Controls were matched for age (±3 years) and the emetogenicity of their antineoplastic treatment. Insufficient information is available to determine the emetogenicity of the antineoplastic regimens. Children randomly assigned to receive hypnosis did not receive antiemetic prophylaxis but did receive antiemetic agents as needed. Children in the control group received standard antiemetic prophylaxis for 4 to 6 hours after antineoplastic therapy. Ondansetron was given to more children in the control group (7 of 10 patients) than in the hypnosis group (3 of 10 patients).</Para><Para id="_678">Children randomly assigned to receive hypnosis were taught self-hypnosis during the initial antineoplastic treatment, while children in the control group spent equivalent time in conversation with a therapist. Researchers used a daily structured interview with the children to assess ANV at 1 to 2 months, and at 4 to 6 months after diagnosis. At the time of first assessment, children who had been taught self-hypnosis reported significantly less anticipatory nausea than did the control group, although the incidence was not reported. The rate of anticipatory vomiting was identical in each group (1 of 10 patients). By the time of the second assessment, there was no difference between the groups in the rate of anticipatory nausea. The rate of anticipatory vomiting between the groups was also similar (hypnosis, 0 of 10 patients vs. control, 2 of 10 patients).<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_640"><Title>Pharmacological interventions</Title><Para id="_642">Studies of pharmacological interventions for ANV have been conducted only in adults and are limited to benzodiazepines. Because patients who experience ANV have been observed to be more anxious than patients who do not experience ANV,<Reference refidx="11"/>  anxiolytics have been studied. Studies in adults have evaluated benzodiazepines as a treatment for ANV.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> In one randomized trial, adult patients with cancer received a placebo or lorazepam 2 mg by mouth the night before antineoplastic treatment, the morning of treatment, and at bedtime for the next 5 days during 180 antineoplastic treatment courses containing cisplatin.<Reference refidx="12"/> Patients also received metoclopramide 2 mg/kg per dose, clemastine, and dexamethasone for antiemetic prophylaxis. At the time of randomization, approximately two-thirds of patients were naïve to antineoplastic agents. ANV was defined as nausea, vomiting, or both that occurred within 12 hours before antineoplastic therapy or 1 hour after the start of antineoplastic therapy. A significantly higher proportion of treatments  with lorazepam were associated with complete ANV control, compared with the control group (52% vs. 32%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05). Few adverse effects occurred; 76% of the patients who received lorazepam and 32% of the controls had mild sedation.</Para><Para id="_643">Women with breast cancer who were  naïve to antineoplastic treatment were enrolled in a double-blind placebo-controlled trial comparing the incidence of ANV after relaxation training and either alprazolam (n = 29) or placebo (n = 28). Alprazolam 0.25 mg or placebo was given twice daily by mouth for 6 to 12 months. Triazolam was also given as needed to patients in both study arms to manage insomnia. The proportion of patients who experienced complete control of anticipatory nausea and anticipatory vomiting before the fourth antineoplastic treatment was similar in both study arms (26% vs. 25% and 4% vs. 0%, respectively). Diazepam 5 mg twice daily was given to 29 adult cancer patients with ANV for 3 days before each of four consecutive antineoplastic treatment courses.<Reference refidx="13"/> Thirteen patients (45%) experienced complete ANV control at some time over the four antineoplastic treatment courses.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_644"><Title>Conclusions</Title><Para id="_645">While the improvement in complete control of ANV provided by psychological interventions such as hypnosis or systematic desensitization may not be dramatic, these interventions may benefit individual patients with minimal risk. For this reason, one guideline development panel recommends that such interventions be offered to age-appropriate patients who experience ANV where the expertise and resources exist to deliver them.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_646">Despite the lack of evidence supporting the use of benzodiazepines to treat ANV in children, guidelines based on clinical experience recommend using lorazepam for ANV in children.<Reference refidx="14"/>  The recommended initial dose was based on current pediatric dosing recommendations, with the usual adult dose as the maximum dose.<Reference refidx="15"/> This dose should be titrated to the needs of each child, with dose lowering recommended for excessive sedation.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="9458536">Morrow GR, Roscoe JA, Hynes HE, et al.: Progress in reducing anticipatory nausea and vomiting: a study of community practice. Support Care Cancer 6 (1): 46-50, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="3975125" MedlineID="85139431">Dolgin MJ, Katz ER, McGinty K, et al.: Anticipatory nausea and vomiting in pediatric cancer patients. Pediatrics 75 (3): 547-52, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9055147">Tyc VL, Mulhern RK, Bieberich AA: Anticipatory nausea and vomiting in pediatric cancer patients: an analysis of conditioning and coping variables. J Dev Behav Pediatr 18 (1): 27-33, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10970680">Stockhorst U, Spennes-Saleh S, Körholz D, et al.: Anticipatory symptoms and anticipatory immune responses in pediatric cancer patients receiving chemotherapy: features of a classically conditioned response? Brain Behav Immun 14 (3): 198-218, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="22396444">Aapro M, Molassiotis A, Dicato M, et al.: The effect of guideline-consistent antiemetic therapy on chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting (CINV): the Pan European Emesis Registry (PEER). Ann Oncol 23 (8): 1986-92, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="23512831">Dupuis LL, Boodhan S, Holdsworth M, et al.: Guideline for the prevention of acute nausea and vomiting due to antineoplastic medication in pediatric cancer patients. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (7): 1073-82, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="33686754">Patel P, Robinson PD, Devine KA, et al.: Prevention and treatment of anticipatory chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in pediatric cancer patients and hematopoietic stem cell recipients: Clinical practice guideline update. Pediatr Blood Cancer 68 (5): e28947, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="23168491">Montgomery GH, Schnur JB, Kravits K: Hypnosis for cancer care: over 200 years young. CA Cancer J Clin 63 (1): 31-44, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="2057271" MedlineID="91279330">Zeltzer LK, Dolgin MJ, LeBaron S, et al.: A randomized, controlled study of behavioral intervention for chemotherapy distress in children with cancer. Pediatrics 88 (1): 34-42, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="7798371">Jacknow DS, Tschann JM, Link MP, et al.: Hypnosis in the prevention of chemotherapy-related nausea and vomiting in children: a prospective study. J Dev Behav Pediatr 15 (4): 258-64, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2204952" MedlineID="90378039">Andrykowski MA: The role of anxiety in the development of anticipatory nausea in cancer chemotherapy: a review and synthesis. Psychosom Med 52 (4): 458-75, 1990 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="7900711">Malik IA, Khan WA, Qazilbash M, et al.: Clinical efficacy of lorazepam in prophylaxis of anticipatory, acute, and delayed nausea and vomiting induced by high doses of cisplatin. A prospective randomized trial. Am J Clin Oncol 18 (2): 170-5, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="8315437">Razavi D, Delvaux N, Farvacques C, et al.: Prevention of adjustment disorders and anticipatory nausea secondary to adjuvant chemotherapy: a double-blind, placebo-controlled study assessing the usefulness of alprazolam. J Clin Oncol 11 (7): 1384-90, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="3385522" MedlineID="88258698">van Hoff J, Olszewski D: Lorazepam for the control of chemotherapy-related nausea and vomiting in children. J Pediatr 113 (1 Pt 1): 146-9, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="15">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Antiemesis. Version 2.2024. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/PDF/antiemesis.pdf">Available online with free registration</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 4, 2025.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_189"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (03/10/2025)</Title><Para id="_263">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_828">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062747#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the prevention and control of treatment-related nausea and vomiting in cancer patients. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Nausea and Vomiting Related to Cancer Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Jared R. Lowe, MD, HMDC (University of North Carolina School of Medicine)</ListItem><ListItem>Maria Petzel, RD, CSO, LD, CNSC, FAND (University of TX MD Anderson Cancer Center)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000660468" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Nausea and Vomiting Related to Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389491]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-03-10</DateLastModified></Summary>
