<Summary id="CDR0000062750" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Skin cancer screening may be done by visual inspection, either by oneself or a clinician, but has not been shown to reduce mortality from skin cancer.  Get detailed information about skin cancer risk factors and the benefits and harms of screening for it in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/hp/skin-screening-pdq">Skin Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/patient/skin-screening-pdq">Skin Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038781">skin cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_111">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about skin cancer screening. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_112">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>skin cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Skin Cancer Screening (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Skin Cancer Screening (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Skin Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title> Overview</Title><Para id="_2">Note: The Overview section summarizes the published evidence on this topic. The rest of the summary describes the evidence in more detail.</Para><Para id="_162">Other PDQ summaries containing information related to skin cancer screening include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_163" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062764" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-prevention-pdq">Skin Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062909" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-treatment-pdq">Skin Cancer
Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000552637" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Skin Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">Levels of Evidence for Cancer Screening and Prevention Studies</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Interventions</Title><Para id="_23">The only  widely proposed  screening procedure  for   skin cancer is visual examination of the skin, including both self-examination by the patient and clinical examination by the health care provider. Mobile phone applications that evaluate skin lesions to detect skin cancer and malignant melanoma have been launched.<Reference refidx="1"/> However, the use of such applications to assess skin cancer has been problematic because of the lack of evidence of their diagnostic accuracy and because they have not been studied in large-scale screening programs.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> The use of convolutional neural networks to classify images of melanoma and skin cancer is a growing area of research.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_24"><Title>Benefits</Title><Para id="_25">There is insufficient evidence that population screening for skin cancer reduces skin cancer mortality. The evidence is inadequate to determine whether visual examination of the skin in asymptomatic individuals leads to a reduction in mortality from melanomatous skin cancer. Further, in asymptomatic populations, the effect of visual skin examination  on mortality from nonmelanomatous skin cancers is unknown.</Para><Para id="_90"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>:  Unknown.</Para><ItemizedList id="_46" Style="simple"><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Direct evidence limited to a single ecological study.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Poor.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Not applicable.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Poor.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_29"><Title>Harms</Title><Para id="_30">Based on fair—though unquantified—evidence,  visual examination of the skin in asymptomatic individuals may lead to adverse consequences. These consequences include  complications of diagnostic or treatment interventions (such as poor cosmetic or functional outcomes) and the psychological effects of being labeled with a potentially fatal disease.  Other harmful consequences are overdiagnosis, leading to the detection of biologically benign disease that would otherwise go undetected,   and possible misdiagnosis of a benign lesion as malignant.</Para><Para id="_91"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Unknown.</Para></SummarySection><ItemizedList id="_41" Style="simple"><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Case series, ecological studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="29247099">Buechi R, Faes L, Bachmann LM, et al.: Evidence assessing the diagnostic performance of medical smartphone apps: a systematic review and exploratory meta-analysis. BMJ Open 7 (12): e018280, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25600815">Kassianos AP, Emery JD, Murchie P, et al.: Smartphone applications for melanoma detection by community, patient and generalist clinician users: a review. Br J Dermatol 172 (6): 1507-1518, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23325302">Wolf JA, Moreau JF, Akilov O, et al.: Diagnostic inaccuracy of smartphone applications for melanoma detection. JAMA Dermatol 149 (4): 422-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="31494983">Udrea A, Mitra GD, Costea D, et al.: Accuracy of a smartphone application for triage of skin lesions based on machine learning algorithms. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol 34 (3): 648-655, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31518967">Hekler A, Utikal JS, Enk AH, et al.: Superior skin cancer classification by the combination of human and artificial intelligence. Eur J Cancer 120: 114-121, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="28117445">Esteva A, Kuprel B, Novoa RA, et al.: Dermatologist-level classification of skin cancer with deep neural networks. Nature 542 (7639): 115-118, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="31617929">Phillips M, Marsden H, Jaffe W, et al.: Assessment of Accuracy of an Artificial Intelligence Algorithm to Detect Melanoma in Images of Skin Lesions. JAMA Netw Open 2 (10): e1913436, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><Title>Incidence and Mortality of Skin Cancer</Title><Para id="_71">There are two main types of skin cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_149" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Keratinocyte carcinoma.<ItemizedList id="_150" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Basal cell carcinoma (BCC).</ListItem><ListItem>Squamous cell carcinoma (SCC).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Melanoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_96">BCC and SCC are the most common forms of skin cancer but have substantially better prognoses than the less common, generally more aggressive melanoma.</Para><Para id="_72">Keratinocyte carcinoma is the most commonly occurring cancer in the United States.  Its incidence appears to be increasing in some <Reference refidx="1"/> but not all <Reference refidx="2"/> areas of the United States.  Overall U.S. incidence rates have likely been increasing for a number of years.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  At least some of this increase may be attributable to increased skin cancer awareness and resultant increasing investigation and biopsy of skin lesions.   A precise estimate of the total number and incidence rate of keratinocyte carcinoma is not possible because reporting to cancer registries is not required.  However, it was estimated that in 2012, 5.4 million cases of keratinocyte carcinoma were diagnosed among 3.3 million people in the United States.<Reference refidx="5"/> That number exceeds all other cases of cancer estimated by the American Cancer Society for 2025, which is about 2 million.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_73">Melanoma is reportable in U.S. cancer registries, so there are more reliable estimates of incidence than for keratinocyte carcinoma.  In 2025, it is estimated that 104,960 individuals in the United States will be diagnosed with invasive melanoma and 107,240 will be diagnosed with melanoma <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis>. Approximately 8,430 individuals will die of melanoma in 2025.  Since the early 2000s, melanoma incidence rates among individuals younger than 50 years have stabilized in women but declined by about 1% per year in men.  However, among individuals aged 50 years and older in recent years, the incidence rates appeared to have stabilized in men but increased by about 3% per year in women.<Reference refidx="5"/>  From 2013 to 2022, melanoma mortality rates declined by about 4% per year and 3% per year in men and women, respectively.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_130">A study of skin biopsy rates in relation to melanoma incidence rates obtained from the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program of the National Cancer Institute indicated that much of the observed increase in incidence between 1986 and 2001 was confined to local disease and was most likely caused by overdiagnosis as a result of increased skin biopsy rates during this period.<Reference refidx="6"/> A second study that used SEER data between 2002 and 2009 reported similar findings.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_74">The incidence of melanoma also increased in children and adolescents until 2001. However, between 2001 and 2022, there was a 4.3% reduction in the yearly incidence rate of melanoma among children and adolescents in the National Childhood Cancer Registry databases.<Reference refidx="8"/> During that time, the average annual incidence in this group was exceptionally low (4.5 per 1 million), which may have resulted in spurious trends.<Reference refidx="8"/> Nevertheless, similar trends have been seen in Sweden.<Reference refidx="9"/> In the U.S. study of pediatric melanoma, nearly one-half of the patients had local disease (22% of patients had <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> disease, and 25% of patients had superficial spreading), and nearly one-half of the patients had disease with a thickness of less than one millimeter. Given that mortality from pediatric melanoma had been fairly stable during  those years,<Reference refidx="10"/> it is likely that the increase in incidence could be explained, at least in part, by overdiagnosis.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="14578151">Athas WF, Hunt WC, Key CR: Changes in nonmelanoma skin cancer incidence between 1977-1978 and 1998-1999 in Northcentral New Mexico. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 12 (10): 1105-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11568742">Harris RB, Griffith K, Moon TE: Trends in the incidence of nonmelanoma skin cancers in southeastern Arizona, 1985-1996. J Am Acad Dermatol 45 (4): 528-36, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="20231499">Rogers HW, Weinstock MA, Harris AR, et al.: Incidence estimate of nonmelanoma skin cancer in the United States, 2006. Arch Dermatol 146 (3): 283-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25207363">Leiter U, Eigentler T, Garbe C: Epidemiology of skin cancer. Adv Exp Med Biol 810: 120-40, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16081427">Welch HG, Woloshin S, Schwartz LM: Skin biopsy rates and incidence of melanoma: population based ecological study. BMJ 331 (7515): 481, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="27639256">Weinstock MA, Lott JP, Wang Q, et al.: Skin biopsy utilization and melanoma incidence among Medicare beneficiaries. Br J Dermatol 176 (4): 949-954, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8">National Cancer Institute: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://NCCRExplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="24210187">Austin MT, Xing Y, Hayes-Jordan AA, et al.: Melanoma incidence rises for children and adolescents: an epidemiologic review of pediatric melanoma in the United States. J Pediatr Surg 48 (11): 2207-13, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="18093205">Lewis KG: Trends in pediatric melanoma mortality in the United States, 1968 through 2004. Dermatol Surg 34 (2): 152-9, 2008.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Risk Factors for Skin Cancer</Title><Para id="_75">Epidemiological evidence suggests that exposure to UV radiation and the sensitivity of an individual’s skin to UV radiation are risk factors for skin cancer, although the type of exposure (high-intensity and short-duration vs. chronic exposure) and pattern of exposure (continuous vs. intermittent) may differ among the three main types of skin cancer.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>   In addition, genetic predisposition and the immune system may play roles in the pathogenesis of skin cancers.<Reference refidx="4"/>  Organ-transplant recipients receiving immunosuppressive drugs are at elevated risk of skin cancers, particularly squamous cell carcinoma (SCC).  Arsenic exposure also increases the risk of cutaneous SCC.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_10">The incidence of melanoma rises rapidly in White individuals after age 20 years.  Fair-skinned individuals exposed to the sun are at higher risk.    Individuals with certain types of pigmented lesions
(dysplastic or atypical nevi), with several large nondysplastic nevi, many small nevi, or moderate freckling have a twofold to threefold increased  risk of
developing melanoma.<Reference refidx="7"/> Individuals with familial dysplastic nevus syndrome
or with several dysplastic or atypical nevi are at high (&gt;fivefold) risk of
developing melanoma.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_135">It is important to note that, for the general population, most melanomas may  not arise from preexisting nevi. A meta-analysis of studies published between 1948 and 2016 found that the prevalence of nevus-associated melanomas was only 29%, compared with 71% for the prevalence of de novo melanomas.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1805813" MedlineID="91270330">Koh HK: Cutaneous melanoma. N Engl J Med 325 (3): 171-82, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1435901" MedlineID="93063090">Preston DS, Stern RS: Nonmelanoma cancers of the skin. N Engl J Med 327 (23): 1649-62, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9663594" MedlineID="98326727">English DR, Armstrong BK, Kricker A, et al.: Case-control study of sun exposure and squamous cell carcinoma of the skin. Int J Cancer 77 (3): 347-53, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27899192">Hawkes JE, Truong A, Meyer LJ: Genetic predisposition to melanoma. Semin Oncol 43 (5): 591-597, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Thomas VD, Aasi SZ, Wilson LD, et al.: Cancer of the skin. In: DeVita VT Jr, Hellman S, Rosenberg SA, eds.: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. Vols. 1 &amp; 2. 8th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2008, pp 1863-87.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16445778">Le Mire L, Hollowood K, Gray D, et al.: Melanomas in renal transplant recipients. Br J Dermatol 154 (3): 472-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="15617989">Gandini S, Sera F, Cattaruzza MS, et al.: Meta-analysis of risk factors for cutaneous melanoma: I. Common and atypical naevi. Eur J Cancer 41 (1): 28-44, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28864306">Pampena R, Kyrgidis A, Lallas A, et al.: A meta-analysis of nevus-associated melanoma: Prevalence and practical implications. J Am Acad Dermatol 77 (5): 938-945.e4, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_86"><Title>Accuracy of Making a Clinical Diagnosis of Melanoma</Title><Para id="_78">Observer variability among physicians has been noted in the evaluation of skin lesions and subsequent biopsy specimens. A systematic review of 32 studies that compared the accuracy of dermatologists and primary care physicians in making a clinical diagnosis of melanoma concluded that there was no statistically significant difference in accuracy.  However, the results were inconclusive, owing to small sample sizes and study design weaknesses.<Reference refidx="1"/> Subsequent studies have noted a higher accuracy for dermatologists in the diagnosis of melanocytic lesions,<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> yet there is a shortage of dermatologists to meet the demands of population-level screening.</Para><Para id="_137">A study of 187 pathologists who practiced in the United States found that cases of moderately dysplastic nevi to early-stage invasive melanoma had less than 50% agreement with a reference diagnosis defined by consensus of experienced pathologists.<Reference refidx="4"/> At a U.S. population level, it is estimated that 82.8% (95% confidence interval, 81.0%–84.5%) of melanocytic skin biopsy diagnoses would be verified if they were reviewed by a consensus reference panel of experienced pathologists.<Reference refidx="4"/> In addition, differentiating between benign and malignant melanocytic tumors during histological examinations of biopsy specimens has been shown to be  inconsistent, even in the hands of experienced dermatopathologists.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> This variability in the diagnosis of melanocytic lesions undermines the results of studies that examine screening effectiveness and also may undermine the effectiveness of any screening intervention. Furthermore, this finding suggests that requesting a second opinion regarding the pathology of biopsy specimens may be important.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> A standardized approach to pathologists’ classifying of the interpretations of melanocytic skin lesions may also reduce confusion and improve communication between clinicians.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11735713">Chen SC, Bravata DM, Weil E, et al.: A comparison of dermatologists' and primary care physicians' accuracy in diagnosing melanoma: a systematic review. Arch Dermatol 137 (12): 1627-34, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16808765">Chen SC, Pennie ML, Kolm P, et al.: Diagnosing and managing cutaneous pigmented lesions: primary care physicians versus dermatologists. J Gen Intern Med 21 (7): 678-82, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="22971304">Corbo MD, Wismer J: Agreement between dermatologists and primary care practitioners in the diagnosis of malignant melanoma: review of the literature. J Cutan Med Surg 16 (5): 306-10, 2012 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28659278">Elmore JG, Barnhill RL, Elder DE, et al.: Pathologists' diagnosis of invasive melanoma and melanocytic proliferations: observer accuracy and reproducibility study. BMJ 357: j2813, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="8666360" MedlineID="96251214">Farmer ER, Gonin R, Hanna MP: Discordance in the histopathologic diagnosis of melanoma and melanocytic nevi between expert pathologists. Hum Pathol 27 (6): 528-31, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="27189823">Lott JP, Elmore JG, Zhao GA, et al.: Evaluation of the Melanocytic Pathology Assessment Tool and Hierarchy for Diagnosis (MPATH-Dx) classification scheme for diagnosis of cutaneous melanocytic neoplasms: Results from the International Melanoma Pathology Study Group. J Am Acad Dermatol 75 (2): 356-63, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="31603483">Piepkorn MW, Longton GM, Reisch LM, et al.: Assessment of Second-Opinion Strategies for Diagnoses of Cutaneous Melanocytic Lesions. JAMA Netw Open 2 (10): e1912597, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="24176521">Piepkorn MW, Barnhill RL, Elder DE, et al.: The MPATH-Dx reporting schema for melanocytic proliferations and melanoma. J Am Acad Dermatol 70 (1): 131-41, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="32935869">Radick AC, Reisch LM, Shucard HL, et al.: Terminology for melanocytic skin lesions and the MPATH-Dx classification schema: A survey of dermatopathologists. J Cutan Pathol 48 (6): 733-738, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_81"><Title>Evidence of Benefit Associated With Screening</Title><Para id="_82">More than 90% of melanomas that arise in the skin can be recognized with the naked
eye.  Very often there is a prolonged horizontal growth phase, during which
the tumor expands centrifugally beneath the epidermis but does not invade
the underlying dermis.  This horizontal growth phase may  provide lead time for
early detection.  Melanoma is more easily cured  if treated before the onset of the
vertical growth phase with its metastatic potential.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_83">The probability of tumor recurrence within 10 years after curative resection  is less than 10% with tumors
less than 1.4 mm in thickness.  For patients with tumors less than 0.76 mm in
thickness, the likelihood of recurrence is less than 1% in 10 years.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_76">A systematic review of skin cancer screening examined evidence available through mid-2005. The review concluded that direct evidence of improved health outcomes associated with skin cancer screening is lacking.<Reference refidx="3"/> An updated review published in 2016 found limited evidence that skin cancer screening reduces melanoma mortality.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_85">No randomized trials evaluating the efficacy of skin cancer screening on mortality have been completed. A population-based trial (using cluster randomization) to determine the effect of skin cancer screening on melanoma mortality was initiated in Queensland, Australia, but lost its funding after the initial pilot phase, and no health outcomes were ever reported.<Reference refidx="6"/>   
 </Para><Para id="_145">Two ecological studies have been conducted using data from Germany. The first study was a pilot project conducted in 2003 and 2004, in which a skin cancer screening program was implemented in one federal state. Suggestion of a reduction in melanoma mortality with screening led to the establishment of countywide skin cancer screening programs in 2008.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> The programs offered a whole-body skin examination once every 2 years for individuals older than 35 years.  The second ecological study compared the melanoma mortality experience in Germany with the melanoma mortality experience of subregions of 22 European countries—none of which had organized screening programs—for the years 2000 to 2013. After adjustment for potential confounders, Germany and the 22 European regions had similar malignant mortality rates, suggesting no benefit of screening.<Reference refidx="9"/> </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3921200" MedlineID="85176248">Friedman RJ, Rigel DS, Kopf AW: Early detection of malignant melanoma: the role of physician examination and self-examination of the skin. CA Cancer J Clin 35 (3): 130-51, 1985 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="6883293" MedlineID="83284790">Blois MS, Sagebiel RW, Abarbanel RM, et al.: Malignant melanoma of the skin. I. The association of tumor depth and type, and patient sex, age, and site with survival. Cancer 52 (7): 1330-41, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19189909">Wolff T, Tai E, Miller T: Screening for skin cancer: an update of the evidence for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. Ann Intern Med 150 (3): 194-8, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27458949">Wernli KJ, Henrikson NB, Morrison CC, et al.: Screening for Skin Cancer in Adults: Updated Evidence Report and Systematic Review for the US Preventive Services Task Force. JAMA 316 (4): 436-47, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="27458948">Bibbins-Domingo K, Grossman DC, Curry SJ, et al.: Screening for Skin Cancer: US Preventive Services Task Force Recommendation Statement. JAMA 316 (4): 429-35, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11943795">Aitken JF, Elwood JM, Lowe JB, et al.: A randomised trial of population screening for melanoma. J Med Screen 9 (1): 33-7, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="22517033">Katalinic A, Waldmann A, Weinstock MA, et al.: Does skin cancer screening save lives? An observational study comparing trends in melanoma mortality in regions with and without screening. Cancer 118 (21): 5395-402, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="29169295">Eisemann N, Waldmann A, Holleczek B, et al.: Observed and expected mortality in the German skin cancer screening pilot project SCREEN. J Med Screen 25 (3): 166-168, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="28353004">Kaiser M, Schiller J, Schreckenberger C: The effectiveness of a population-based skin cancer screening program: evidence from Germany. Eur J Health Econ 19 (3): 355-367, 2018.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_92"><Title>Evidence of Harms Associated With Screening</Title><Para id="_93">Harms have not been well studied or reported in quantitative terms, but the potential for adverse consequences from skin cancer screening exists.  In the SCREEN pilot project  in Germany, 4.4% of all screened participants underwent a skin excision for a suspicious lesion, but most biopsies did not result in a cancer diagnosis. The detection rate was especially affected by age. One case of melanoma was detected per 28 excisions overall (for both men and women), while 52 skin excisions were required to detect one melanoma in men aged 20 to 34 years.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_117">Visual examination of the skin in asymptomatic individuals may lead to cosmetic or functional complications of diagnostic or treatment interventions and psychological effects of being labeled with a potentially fatal disease. However, robust data on the frequency of such events are lacking. Other harmful consequences are overdiagnosis, leading to the detection of biologically benign disease that would otherwise go undetected,<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> and possible misdiagnosis of a benign lesion as malignant. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062750#_86" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-screening-pdq">Accuracy of Making a Clinical Diagnosis of Melanoma</SummaryRef> section.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="22911184">Waldmann A, Nolte S, Geller AC, et al.: Frequency of excisions and yields of malignant skin tumors in a population-based screening intervention of 360,288 whole-body examinations. Arch Dermatol 148 (8): 903-10, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16081427">Welch HG, Woloshin S, Schwartz LM: Skin biopsy rates and incidence of melanoma: population based ecological study. BMJ 331 (7515): 481, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27639256">Weinstock MA, Lott JP, Wang Q, et al.: Skin biopsy utilization and melanoma incidence among Medicare beneficiaries. Br J Dermatol 176 (4): 949-954, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27919243">Schoffer O, Schülein S, Arand G, et al.: Tumour stage distribution and survival of malignant melanoma in Germany 2002-2011. BMC Cancer 16 (1): 936, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/09/2025)</Title><Para id="_21">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_156"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062750#_88" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-screening-pdq">Incidence and Mortality of Skin Cancer</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_164">Added American Cancer Society as <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062750#_72" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-screening-pdq">reference 5</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_165">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062750#_73" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-screening-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cases of melanoma and melanoma <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> and deaths due to melanoma for 2025. Also revised text to state that from 2013 to 2022, melanoma mortality rates declined by about 4% per year and 3% per year in men and women, respectively.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062750#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-screening-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about skin cancer screening. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Skin Cancer Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/hp/skin-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/skin/hp/skin-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389300]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-05-09</DateLastModified></Summary>
