<Summary id="CDR0000062757" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>For stomach (gastric) cancer, there is no standard or routine screening test for the general U.S. population. Review the evidence on the benefits and harms of screening for gastric cancer using barium-meal photofluorography, gastric endoscopy, or serum pepsinogen in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/stomach/hp/stomach-screening-pdq">Stomach (Gastric) Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039821">gastric cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_94">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about stomach (gastric) cancer screening. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_95">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>gastric cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Stomach (Gastric) Cancer Screening (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Stomach (Gastric) Cancer Screening (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Stomach (Gastric) Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title> Overview</Title><Para id="_2">Note: The Overview section summarizes the published evidence on this topic. The rest of the summary describes the evidence in more detail.</Para><Para id="_119">Other PDQ summaries on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062830" url="/types/stomach/hp/stomach-prevention-pdq">Stomach (Gastric) Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef>;  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062911" url="/types/stomach/hp/stomach-treatment-pdq">Gastric Cancer
Treatment</SummaryRef>; and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">Levels of Evidence for Cancer Screening and Prevention Studies</SummaryRef> are also available.</Para><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Inadequate Evidence of Benefit Associated With Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_96"><Title>Barium-meal gastric photofluorography and serum pepsinogen</Title><Para id="_97">Based on fair evidence, screening with barium-meal photofluorography or serum pepsinogen would not result in a decrease in mortality from gastric cancer in areas with relatively low incidence of the disease, such as the United States.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_98"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Fair evidence for no reduction in mortality.</Para><ItemizedList id="_99" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Evidence obtained from  case-control and cohort studies, primarily from high-risk areas such as East Asia.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Poor in prospective studies.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Poor.  Studies on populations in high-risk areas may not be applicable to low-risk areas such as the United States.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_110"><Title>Gastric endoscopy</Title><Para id="_111"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Inadequate evidence for mortality reduction.</Para><ItemizedList id="_112" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>:  Evidence from case-control and cohort studies from East Asia are generally consistent with a substantial reduction in gastric cancer mortality associated with endoscopic screening.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair to poor. All of the studies are observational and subject to selection bias on the basis of the individual who chooses to be screened.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good among the observational studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Poor. Studies on populations in high-risk areas (East Asia) may not be applicable to low-risk areas such as the United States.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_108"><Title>Harms</Title><Para id="_109">Based on solid evidence,  screening would result in uncommon but serious  side effects associated with endoscopy, which may include perforation, cardiopulmonary events, aspiration pneumonia, and bleeding requiring hospitalization.</Para><Para id="_102"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Solid evidence for rare but serious harms.</Para><ItemizedList id="_103" Style="simple">
     <ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Evidence obtained from screening programs and case series.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Inadequate evidence.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Poor.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Hirayama T, Hisamichi S, Fujimoto I, et al.: Screening for gastric cancer. In: Miller AB, ed.: Screening for Cancer. Academic Press, 1985, pp 367-376.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Tytgat GN, Mathus-Vliegen EM, Offerhaus J: Value of endoscopy in the surveillance of high-risk groups for gastrointestinal cancer. In: Sherlock P, Morson BC, Barbara L, et al., eds.: Precancerous Lesions of the Gastrointestinal Tract. Raven Press, 1983, pp 305-318.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11749093" MedlineID="21625002">Riecken B, Pfeiffer R, Ma JL, et al.: No impact of repeated endoscopic screens on gastric cancer mortality in a prospectively followed Chinese population at high risk. Prev Med 34 (1): 22-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10205207" MedlineID="99221688">Kitahara F, Kobayashi K, Sato T, et al.: Accuracy of screening for gastric cancer using serum pepsinogen concentrations. Gut 44 (5): 693-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18308253">Leung WK, Wu MS, Kakugawa Y, et al.: Screening for gastric cancer in Asia: current evidence and practice. Lancet Oncol 9 (3): 279-87, 2008.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_85">In 2025,  an estimated 30,300 Americans will be diagnosed with 
gastric cancer, and 10,780 will die of the disease.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Two-thirds of people diagnosed with gastric cancer are older than 66 years.  Gastric cancer is the fifth most common cause of cancer mortality in the world. The disease is  common in places such as East Asia, Western Asia,
South America, and Eastern Europe.  Gastric cancer is
a major cause of death worldwide.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_86">The
major type of gastric cancer is adenocarcinoma (95%).  The remaining malignant tumors
include lymphomas, sarcomas, carcinoid tumors, and other rare types. Distinguishing the common adenocarcinoma from the uncommon lymphoma may sometimes be difficult, but it is important because of major differences in staging, treatment, and prognosis.<Reference refidx="3"/> Gastric adenocarcinomas
can be further categorized into an intestinal type and a diffuse type.<Reference refidx="4"/> 
Intestinal-type lesions are frequently ulcerative and occur in the distal
stomach more often than the diffuse type.  Diffuse-type lesions are associated with a
worse prognosis than the intestinal type.  The intestinal type tends to
be predominant in geographic regions with a high incidence of gastric carcinoma. 
The decline in the incidence of gastric cancer worldwide largely results from a
decrease in the number of intestinal-type lesions.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="38572751">Bray F, Laversanne M, Sung H, et al.: Global cancer statistics 2022: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin 74 (3): 229-263, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Pisters PWT, Kelsen DP, Tepper JE: Cancer of the stomach. In: DeVita VT Jr, Hellman S, Rosenberg SA, eds.: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. Vols. 1 &amp; 2. 8th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2008, pp 1043-1079.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Lauren P: The two histological main types of gastric carcinoma: diffuse and so-called intestinal-type carcinoma: an attempt at a histo-clinical classification. Acta Pathol Microbiol Scand  64(1): 31-49, 1965.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15214826">Henson DE, Dittus C, Younes M, et al.: Differential trends in the intestinal and diffuse types of gastric carcinoma in the United States, 1973-2000: increase in the signet ring cell type. Arch Pathol Lab Med 128 (7): 765-70, 2004.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_10">The incidence of gastric cancer in the United States has decreased fourfold since
1930, to approximately seven cases per 100,000 people.<Reference refidx="1"/>  The reasons for this
striking decrease in incidence are  not fully understood but are suspected to be related to
improved storage of food and changes in diet, such as decreased salt intake. Some populations of Americans are at elevated risk, including older patients with atrophic gastritis or pernicious anemia; patients with sporadic gastric adenomas,<Reference refidx="2"/> familial adenomatous polyposis,<Reference refidx="3"/> or hereditary nonpolyposis colon cancer;<Reference refidx="4"/> and immigrant ethnic populations from countries with high rates of gastric carcinoma.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_68"> 
Risk factors for gastric cancer include the presence of precursor conditions
such as chronic atrophic gastritis and intestinal metaplasia, pernicious
anemia, and gastric adenomatous polyps.  Genetic and environmental factors
include a family history of gastric cancer; low consumption of fruits and
vegetables; consumption of salted, smoked, or poorly preserved foods; and
cigarette smoking.<Reference refidx="7"/> <Reference refidx="8"/>  There is consistent evidence that <ScientificName>Helicobacter pylori</ScientificName>
infection of the stomach is strongly associated with both the initiation and promotion
of  carcinoma of the gastric body and antrum, and of gastric lymphoma.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> The International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC) classifies <ScientificName>H. pylori</ScientificName> infection as a cause of noncardia gastric carcinoma and low-grade B-cell mucosa-associated lymphatic tissue gastric lymphoma (i.e., a Group 1 human carcinogen).<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/>  Compared with the general population,
people with duodenal ulcer disease may have a lower risk of gastric cancer.<Reference refidx="14"/> 

</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">National Cancer Institute: SEER Cancer Stat Facts: Stomach Cancer. Bethesda, Md: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/stomach.html">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 21, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="14297468">MING SC, GOLDMAN H: Gastric polyps: a histogenetic classification and its relation to carcinoma. Cancer 18: 721-6, 1965.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="4852134" MedlineID="74301962">Utsunomiya J, Maki T, Iwama T, et al.: Gastric lesion of familial polyposis coli. Cancer 34 (3): 745-54, 1974.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="9355980" MedlineID="98016057">Aarnio M, Salovaara R, Aaltonen LA, et al.: Features of gastric cancer in hereditary non-polyposis colorectal cancer syndrome. Int J Cancer 74 (5): 551-5, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3975641" MedlineID="85142212">Kurtz RC, Sherlock P: The diagnosis of gastric cancer. Semin Oncol 12 (1): 11-8, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2036128" MedlineID="91177935">Boeing H: Epidemiological research in stomach cancer: progress over the last ten years. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 117 (2): 133-43, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="16489633">Crew KD, Neugut AI: Epidemiology of gastric cancer. World J Gastroenterol 12 (3): 354-62, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="18308253">Leung WK, Wu MS, Kakugawa Y, et al.: Screening for gastric cancer in Asia: current evidence and practice. Lancet Oncol 9 (3): 279-87, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="8145781" MedlineID="94195344">Parsonnet J, Hansen S, Rodriguez L, et al.: Helicobacter pylori infection and gastric lymphoma. N Engl J Med 330 (18): 1267-71, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="16482615">Ando T, Goto Y, Maeda O, et al.: Causal role of Helicobacter pylori infection in gastric cancer. World J Gastroenterol 12 (2): 181-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8678045" MedlineID="96283058">Aromaa A, Kosunen TU, Knekt P, et al.: Circulating anti-Helicobacter pylori immunoglobulin A antibodies and low serum pepsinogen I level are associated with increased risk of gastric cancer. Am J Epidemiol 144 (2): 142-9, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="12">IARC Working Group on the Evaluation of Carcinogenic Risks to Humans: A review of human carcinogens--Part B: biological agents. Volume 100. IARC Press, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="19350698">Bouvard V, Baan R, Straif K, et al.: A review of human carcinogens--Part B: biological agents. Lancet Oncol 10 (4): 321-2, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="8657240" MedlineID="96266386">Hansson LE, Nyrén O, Hsing AW, et al.: The risk of stomach cancer in patients with gastric or duodenal ulcer disease. N Engl J Med 335 (4): 242-9, 1996.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_69"><Title>Inadequate Evidence of Benefit Associated With Screening</Title><Para id="_70">Several screening techniques, including barium-meal photofluorography, gastric endoscopy, and serum pepsinogen, have been proposed as screening methods for the early detection of gastric cancer. No randomized trials evaluating the impact of screening on mortality from gastric cancer have been reported.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Even in very high-risk areas, the positive predictive value (PPV) of the screening tests may be very low.  In a screening program of 17,647 men aged 40 to 60 years in Wakayama City, Japan, the PPV of combined serum pepsinogen and barium meal with digital radiography over the 7-year period was 0.85%.<Reference refidx="3"/>  The positive test rates were 19.5% for serum pepsinogen and 22.5% for radiography, with a cancer detection rate of 0.28%.  Over the 7-year period, there was no reduction in gastric cancer mortality compared with an age-matched surrounding population.  </Para><SummarySection id="_71"><Title>Barium-Meal Gastric Photofluorography</Title><Para id="_72">A national program of population-based screening for gastric cancer using barium-meal photofluorography has been ongoing since the 1960s in Japan.  Participation rates have been in the range of only 10% to 20%.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  Although there has been a coincident decrease in mortality from gastric cancer in Japan, mortality rates have been decreasing in many developed countries without screening programs.  Case-control studies from Japan show decreases in gastric mortality in people who have undergone screening, but results from prospective studies were not consistent.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_73">A pilot study of community-based photofluorography was conducted in Costa Rica using the same techniques as those used in Japan’s national program (with consultation from Japanese experts).<Reference refidx="4"/>  People were invited by letter from a population registry to attend two rounds of screening, and a total of 6,200 eligible screened participants (of a planned 12,000) were analyzed.  Their gastric cancer mortality from 2 to 7 years after screening was compared with four control groups that had not been invited to be screened, and the relative risk was about 0.5 (no <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> value reported).  The study was, however, prone to strong biases, including selection bias, and likely differential exclusion of people with previously diagnosed gastric cancer favoring the screened population.  In addition, unlike the community controls, patients diagnosed with gastric cancer through the screening program were treated at a single referral center.  The PPV of a suspicious fluorograph was 3%; the specificity in the two rounds was 67% and 80%; and the positivity rates were 34% and 20%.  Despite the authors’ belief that their results provided substantial evidence that routine screening would decrease gastric cancer mortality, they concluded that the costs of screening with photofluorography would be far too high in their country.</Para><Para id="_74">A screening study was begun in Venezuela in 1980, using radiographic fluorography.<Reference refidx="5"/> The efficacy of this program in reducing mortality from gastric cancer was evaluated by means of a case-control study. The study showed no detectable reduction in mortality from gastric cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_75"><Title>Gastric Endoscopy</Title><Para id="_76">Endoscopy appears to be more sensitive than photofluorography for the detection of gastric cancer.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_77"> A meta-analysis of gastric cancer endoscopic screening studies in Asia identified ten relevant studies, all nonrandomized.<Reference refidx="7"/> These studies were conducted between 1989 and 2014 in South Korea, China, and Japan. Of the ten studies, a never-screened group was the comparator in six studies, a radiographic-screening group was the comparator in one study, and expected deaths based on population rates was the comparator in three studies. In some of the studies, the endoscopic screening was performed as part of a national screening program. The meta-analysis pooled risk ratio (RR) estimate of gastric cancer mortality associated with endoscopic screening was 0.60 (95% confidence interval [CI], 0.49–0.73), with all but one study showing an individual RR of 0.72 or lower. There was significant heterogeneity across studies (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001), which was because of the one study with an RR greater than 1 (1.01); removing that study resulted in no significant heterogeneity (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .14). Pooled estimates for the four nested case-control studies and six cohort studies were 0.60 (95% CI, 0.47–0.76) and 0.57 (95% CI, 0.39–0.83), respectively. The pooled estimate for the six studies with the never-screened comparator group was 0.58 (95% CI, 0.48–0.70).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_78"><Title>Serum Pepsinogen</Title><Para id="_79">There are no studies evaluating the effect of screening with serum pepsinogen on gastric cancer mortality, and there are important limitations to its use as a screening test. Low serum pepsinogen levels indicate the presence of atrophic gastritis and are therefore applicable to the detection of presumed precursors for intestinal-type gastric cancer rather than the diffuse type.<Reference refidx="3"/>  In addition, there are no standard cut-off values of abnormality.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="8"/>  Finally, eradication of <ScientificName>H. pylori</ScientificName> and use of proton pump inhibitors for the management of indigestion change pepsinogen levels, making interpretation of results difficult in the setting of widespread use of these interventions.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_80">In Japan, one study measured serum pepsinogen levels I and II (PGI and PGII)     in 5,113 patients who were also screened by endoscopy (13 gastric cancers detected). This study  used  cut-off points for identifying risk of gastric cancer, which were less than 70 ng/mL for PGI and less than 3 ng/mL for the PGI:PGII ratio. This combination provided  a sensitivity  of 84.6%,  a specificity of 73.5%,  a PPV of 0.81%, and a negative predictive value of 99.6%.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_81"><Title>Clinical Considerations for High-Risk Groups
</Title><Para id="_82">There may be justification for screening some populations of Americans at
higher risk, although there is considerable discussion about how much incidence
would make the examination worthwhile.  Potential subgroups might include
older patients with atrophic gastritis or pernicious anemia; patients with partial
gastrectomy;<Reference refidx="10"/> patients with the diagnosis of sporadic adenomas,<Reference refidx="11"/>  
familial adenomatous  polyposis,<Reference refidx="12"/> 	 or hereditary nonpolyposis colon cancer;<Reference refidx="13"/>  and immigrant ethnic populations from countries with high 
rates of gastric carcinoma.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18308253">Leung WK, Wu MS, Kakugawa Y, et al.: Screening for gastric cancer in Asia: current evidence and practice. Lancet Oncol 9 (3): 279-87, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="18344316">Hamashima C, Shibuya D, Yamazaki H, et al.: The Japanese guidelines for gastric cancer screening. Jpn J Clin Oncol 38 (4): 259-67, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="16232204">Ohata H, Oka M, Yanaoka K, et al.: Gastric cancer screening of a high-risk population in Japan using serum pepsinogen and barium digital radiography. Cancer Sci 96 (10): 713-20, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="17912238">Rosero-Bixby L, Sierra R: X-ray screening seems to reduce gastric cancer mortality by half in a community-controlled trial in Costa Rica. Br J Cancer 97 (7): 837-43, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="8198977" MedlineID="94257438">Pisani P, Oliver WE, Parkin DM, et al.: Case-control study of gastric cancer screening in Venezuela. Br J Cancer 69 (6): 1102-5, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16937471">Tashiro A, Sano M, Kinameri K, et al.: Comparing mass screening techniques for gastric cancer in Japan. World J Gastroenterol 12 (30): 4873-4, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="29723507">Zhang X, Li M, Chen S, et al.: Endoscopic Screening in Asian Countries Is Associated With Reduced Gastric Cancer Mortality: A Meta-analysis and Systematic Review. Gastroenterology 155 (2): 347-354.e9, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="18398025">Yanaoka K, Oka M, Mukoubayashi C, et al.: Cancer high-risk subjects identified by serum pepsinogen tests: outcomes after 10-year follow-up in asymptomatic middle-aged males. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 17 (4): 838-45, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="10205207" MedlineID="99221688">Kitahara F, Kobayashi K, Sato T, et al.: Accuracy of screening for gastric cancer using serum pepsinogen concentrations. Gut 44 (5): 693-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="1947767" MedlineID="92054216">Staël von Holstein C, Eriksson S, Huldt B, et al.: Endoscopic screening during 17 years for gastric stump carcinoma. A prospective clinical trial. Scand J Gastroenterol 26 (10): 1020-6, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="14297468">MING SC, GOLDMAN H: Gastric polyps: a histogenetic classification and its relation to carcinoma. Cancer 18: 721-6, 1965.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="4852134" MedlineID="74301962">Utsunomiya J, Maki T, Iwama T, et al.: Gastric lesion of familial polyposis coli. Cancer 34 (3): 745-54, 1974.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="9355980" MedlineID="98016057">Aarnio M, Salovaara R, Aaltonen LA, et al.: Features of gastric cancer in hereditary non-polyposis colorectal cancer syndrome. Int J Cancer 74 (5): 551-5, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="3975641" MedlineID="85142212">Kurtz RC, Sherlock P: The diagnosis of gastric cancer. Semin Oncol 12 (1): 11-8, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="2036128" MedlineID="91177935">Boeing H: Epidemiological research in stomach cancer: progress over the last ten years. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 117 (2): 133-43, 1991.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_83"><Title>Evidence of Harm Associated With Screening</Title><Para id="_84">Harms of routine screening for gastric cancer are poorly quantitated or reported and derive chiefly from screening experiences in very high-risk areas such as Japan.<Reference refidx="1"/>  The most frequent harm is the occurrence of false-positive tests.<Reference refidx="2"/> Exposure to the low doses of radiation (about 0.6 mSv in photofluorography) carries a theoretical but poorly quantified risk of carcinogenesis.  Additional rare complications of screening may include adverse effects of premedication (used for endoscopy and sometimes photofluorography) and bleeding or perforation from endoscopy.<Reference refidx="1"/> As with any screening test, there is a possibility of overdiagnosis with attendant overtreatment.  Since harms such as perforation and bleeding may vary with the experience of the screening center, the harms may be higher in populations at low risk for gastric cancer, such as the United States, than in mass screening programs in Japan.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18344316">Hamashima C, Shibuya D, Yamazaki H, et al.: The Japanese guidelines for gastric cancer screening. Jpn J Clin Oncol 38 (4): 259-67, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16232204">Ohata H, Oka M, Yanaoka K, et al.: Gastric cancer screening of a high-risk population in Japan using serum pepsinogen and barium digital radiography. Cancer Sci 96 (10): 713-20, 2005.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (04/07/2025)</Title><Para id="_17">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_117"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062757#_65" url="/types/stomach/hp/stomach-screening-pdq">Incidence and Mortality</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_118">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062757#_85" url="/types/stomach/hp/stomach-screening-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cases and deaths for 2025 (cited American Cancer Society as reference 1 and Bray et al. as reference 2).</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062757#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/stomach/hp/stomach-screening-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about stomach (gastric) cancer screening. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Stomach (Gastric) Cancer Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/stomach/hp/stomach-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/stomach/hp/stomach-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389174]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-04-07</DateLastModified></Summary>
