<Summary id="CDR0000062770" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Breast cancer is the most common cancer in pregnant women and can be hard to detect because of changes in the breast that occur with pregnancy. Learn about the incidence, diagnosis, and treatment of breast cancer during pregnancy, as well as the effect a history of breast cancer can have on future pregnancies and children.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/patient/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038832">breast cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_109">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of breast cancer during pregnancy. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_110">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>breast cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038832">breast cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy</Title><SummarySection id="_101"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_2">Breast cancer is the most common cancer in pregnant and postpartum women and occurs in about 1 in 3,000 pregnant women.  The average patient is between the ages of 32 years and 38 years. Because many women are choosing to delay childbearing, it is
likely that the incidence of breast cancer during pregnancy will increase.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><Title>Anatomy</Title><Para id="_149"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415520" type="image/jpeg" alt="Illustration of the female breast anatomy. On the left, a front view shows lymph nodes inside the breast going from the breast to the armpit. On the right, a cross-section shows the chest wall, ribs, fatty tissue, lobes, ducts, and lobules. Also shown in both panels are the muscle, nipple, and areola." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_147"><Caption language="en">The female breast contains lobes, lobules, and ducts that produce and transport milk to the nipple. Fatty tissue gives the breast its shape, while muscles and the chest wall provide support. The lymphatic system, including lymph nodes, filter lymph and store white blood cells that help fight infection and disease. </Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_103"><Title>Diagnostic Evaluation</Title><Para id="_56">The natural tenderness and engorgement of the breasts of pregnant and lactating
women may hinder detection of discrete masses and early diagnosis
of breast cancer.  Delays in diagnosis are common, with an average reported
delay of 5 to 15 months from the onset of symptoms.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  Because of this
delay, cancers are typically detected at a later stage than in a nonpregnant,
age-matched population.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_120">The following tests and procedures may be used to diagnose breast cancer during pregnancy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_121" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Breast self-examination.</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical breast examination.</ListItem><ListItem>Ultrasound.</ListItem><ListItem>Biopsy and hormone receptor assays.</ListItem><ListItem>Mammography.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_122">To detect breast cancer, pregnant and lactating
women should consider practicing self-examination and undergo a clinical breast examination as part
of the routine prenatal examination by a doctor.  If an abnormality is found,
diagnostic approaches such as ultrasound and mammography may be used.  With
proper shielding, mammography poses little risk of radiation exposure to the
fetus.<Reference refidx="6"/>  However, mammograms are only used  to evaluate dominant masses
and to locate occult carcinomas in the presence of other suspicious physical
findings.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_123">Because at least 25% of mammograms in pregnancy may be negative in
the presence of cancer, a biopsy is essential for the diagnosis of any palpable
mass.  Diagnosis may be safely accomplished with a fine-needle aspiration, core biopsy, or
excisional biopsy under local anesthesia.  To avoid a false-positive diagnosis
as a result of misinterpretation of pregnancy-related changes, the pathologist
should be advised that the patient is pregnant.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_43">Breast cancer pathology is similar in age-matched pregnant and nonpregnant
women.  Hormone receptor assays using a competitive binding assay are usually negative in pregnant patients with breast cancer, but this may be the result of receptor binding by high serum estrogen
levels associated with the pregnancy.  Enzyme immunocytochemical
receptor assays  are more sensitive than competitive binding assays.  A study
that used both assay methods indicated similar receptor positivity between pregnant
and nonpregnant women with breast cancer.<Reference refidx="8"/>  The study concluded that
increased estrogen levels during pregnancy could result in a higher incidence
of receptor positivity detected with immunohistochemistry than is detected by
radiolabeled ligand-binding assay because of competitive inhibition by high levels of
endogenous estrogen.</Para><Para id="_124">For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062787#_6" url="/types/breast/hp/breast-treatment-pdq">Diagnosis</SummaryRef> section in Breast Cancer Treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_104"><Title>Prognosis</Title><Para id="_105">The overall survival of pregnant women with breast cancer may be worse than that of nonpregnant women at all stages.<Reference refidx="6"/>  However, this discrepancy may be primarily the result of  delayed diagnosis.<Reference refidx="9"/>
Termination of pregnancy has not shown any beneficial effect on
breast cancer outcome and is not usually considered as a therapeutic
option.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/>  </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2218825" MedlineID="91019801">Hoover HC: Breast cancer during pregnancy and lactation. Surg Clin North Am 70 (5): 1151-63, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11271981" MedlineID="21089385">Gwyn K, Theriault R: Breast cancer during pregnancy. Oncology (Huntingt) 15 (1): 39-46; discussion 46, 49-51, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11130471" MedlineID="21013027">Moore HC, Foster RS: Breast cancer and pregnancy. Semin Oncol 27 (6): 646-53, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12594943" MedlineID="22483516">Rugo HS: Management of breast cancer diagnosed during pregnancy. Curr Treat Options Oncol 4 (2): 165-73, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2486467" MedlineID="91084305">Clark RM, Chua T: Breast cancer and pregnancy: the ultimate challenge. Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol) 1 (1): 11-8, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16484353">Yang WT, Dryden MJ, Gwyn K, et al.: Imaging of breast cancer diagnosed and treated with chemotherapy during pregnancy. Radiology 239 (1): 52-60, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="12942575">Middleton LP, Amin M, Gwyn K, et al.: Breast carcinoma in pregnant women: assessment of clinicopathologic and immunohistochemical features. Cancer 98 (5): 1055-60, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8095853" MedlineID="93201474">Elledge RM, Ciocca DR, Langone G, et al.: Estrogen receptor, progesterone receptor, and HER-2/neu protein in breast cancers from pregnant patients. Cancer 71 (8): 2499-506, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="1991259" MedlineID="91121375">Petrek JA, Dukoff R, Rogatko A: Prognosis of pregnancy-associated breast cancer. Cancer 67 (4): 869-72, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="2218844" MedlineID="91019822">Barnavon Y, Wallack MK: Management of the pregnant patient with carcinoma of the breast. Surg Gynecol Obstet 171 (4): 347-52, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2678487" MedlineID="90019585">Gallenberg MM, Loprinzi CL: Breast cancer and pregnancy. Semin Oncol 16 (5): 369-76, 1989.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information  for  Breast Cancer Treatment and Pregnancy</Title><SummarySection id="_125"><Title>Staging Evaluation</Title><Para id="_126">The following procedures are used to determine the extent of the cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_127" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Chest x-ray.</ListItem><ListItem>Bone scan.</ListItem><ListItem>Ultrasound of the liver.</ListItem><ListItem>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_64">Procedures used for determining the stage of breast cancer are modified for pregnant women to avoid
radiation exposure to the fetus.  Nuclear scans cause fetal
radiation exposure.<Reference refidx="1"/>  If such scans are essential for evaluation, hydration and
Foley catheter drainage of the bladder can be used to prevent retention of
radioactivity.  Timing of the exposure to radiation relative to the gestational
age of the fetus may be more critical than the actual dose of radiation
delivered.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Radiation exposure during the first trimester (&gt;0.1 Gy) may lead to
congenital malformations, intellectual disability, and increased relative risk of carcinogenesis.  </Para><Para id="_6">  Chest x-rays with abdominal shielding are considered
safe, but as with all radiological procedures, they are used only when
essential for making treatment decisions.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  A chest x-ray delivers 0.00008 Gy.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_65">For the diagnosis of bone
metastases, a bone scan is preferable to a skeletal series because the bone
scan delivers a smaller amount of radiation and is more sensitive.  A bone scan
delivers 0.001 Gy.<Reference refidx="5"/> </Para><Para id="_128">Evaluation
of the liver can be performed with ultrasound, and brain metastases can be
diagnosed with an MRI scan.   Data on MRI during pregnancy are not available, but gadolinium crosses the placenta and is associated with fetal abnormalities in rats.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_129"><Title>American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) Stage Groupings and Definitions of TNM </Title><Para id="_130">For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062787#_27" url="/types/breast/hp/breast-treatment-pdq">Stage Information for Breast Cancer</SummaryRef> section in Breast Cancer Treatment.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11271981" MedlineID="21089385">Gwyn K, Theriault R: Breast cancer during pregnancy. Oncology (Huntingt) 15 (1): 39-46; discussion 46, 49-51, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2218844" MedlineID="91019822">Barnavon Y, Wallack MK: Management of the pregnant patient with carcinoma of the breast. Surg Gynecol Obstet 171 (4): 347-52, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11130469" MedlineID="21013025">Nicklas AH, Baker ME: Imaging strategies in the pregnant cancer patient. Semin Oncol 27 (6): 623-32, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="2678487" MedlineID="90019585">Gallenberg MM, Loprinzi CL: Breast cancer and pregnancy. Semin Oncol 16 (5): 369-76, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="16484353">Yang WT, Dryden MJ, Gwyn K, et al.: Imaging of breast cancer diagnosed and treated with chemotherapy during pregnancy. Radiology 239 (1): 52-60, 2006.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038902">stage I breast cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038954">stage II breast cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Early/Localized/Operable Breast Cancer During Pregnancy</Title><Para id="_111">Generally, pregnant women with stage I or stage II breast cancer are treated in the same way as nonpregnant patients, with 
some modifications to protect the fetus.   </Para><Para id="_131">Treatment options for early/localized/operable breast cancer in pregnant women include:</Para><OrderedList id="_132" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062770#_134" url="/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>. Postpartum radiation therapy may also be given to women diagnosed with breast cancer late in pregnancy.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062770#_136" url="/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef> (after the first trimester).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062770#_137" url="/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">Endocrine therapy</SummaryRef> (after delivery).</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_133">The use of <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062770#_138" url="/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">trastuzumab</SummaryRef> during pregnancy is contraindicated.</Para><SummarySection id="_134"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_23">Surgery is recommended as the primary treatment of breast cancer in pregnant
women. </Para><Para id="_135">The data 
regarding safety of sentinel lymph node biopsy in pregnant patients are limited to several retrospective case 
series.  One study examined sentinel lymph node biopsy in eight  patients in the first trimester, nine patients in the second trimester,
and eight  patients in the third 
trimester.  Technetium Tc 99m alone was used in 16 patients, methylene blue dye alone 
was used in seven patients, and two patients had unknown mapping methods.  All 25 patients had live-born infants, 
of whom 24 were healthy, and one had a cleft palate (in the setting of other maternal risk factors).<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_112">Because radiation in therapeutic doses may expose the fetus to
potentially harmful scatter radiation,<Reference refidx="2"/>  modified radical mastectomy is the
treatment of choice if the breast cancer was diagnosed early in 
pregnancy.  If diagnosed late in pregnancy, breast-conserving surgery with postpartum radiation therapy
has been used for breast preservation.<Reference refidx="3"/>  An analysis has been performed that
helps to  predict the risk of waiting to have radiation.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_113">Data suggest that it is safe to administer certain chemotherapeutic drugs after the first trimester, with most pregnancies resulting in live births with low
 rates of morbidity in the newborns. </Para><Para id="_140">Anthracycline-based 
chemotherapy (doxorubicin plus cyclophosphamide or fluorouracil, doxorubicin, and 
cyclophosphamide [FAC]) appears to be safe to administer during the second and/or third trimester 
on the basis of  limited prospective data.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> Safety data on the use of taxanes during pregnancy are limited.</Para><Para id="_141">Evidence (use of chemotherapy during the second and/or third trimester of pregnancy):</Para><OrderedList id="_142" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A multicenter 
case-control study compared pediatric outcomes of 129 children whose mothers had breast cancer 
with  matched children of women without cancer. 
 In the pregnancy study group, 96 children 
(74.4%) were exposed to chemotherapy, 11 (8.5%) to radiation therapy, 13 (10.1%) to surgery alone, 2 
(1.7%) to other drug treatments, and 14 (10.9%) to no treatment.<Reference refidx="9"/><ItemizedList id="_148" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The study 
showed that there was no 
significant difference in birth weight below the 10th
 percentile (22% in the breast cancer treatment‒exposed 
group vs. 15.2% in the control group,  <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .16) or in cognitive development based on the Bayley 
score (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .08). The gestational age at birth was correlated with cognitive outcome in the two study 
groups.</ListItem><ListItem>Evaluation of cardiac function among 47 children, who were age 36 months in the study group, showed 
normal cardiac findings.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>  In a prospective
 single-arm study, 57 pregnant patients 
with breast cancer were treated with FAC in the adjuvant or neoadjuvant
 setting.<Reference refidx="6"/><ItemizedList id="_143" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Survey data 
collected when the children were aged 2 months to 157 months revealed that no stillbirths, miscarriages, or 
perinatal deaths occurred.</ListItem><ListItem>One child born vaginally at a gestational age of 38 weeks had a 
subarachnoid hemorrhage on day 2 postpartum, one child 
had Down syndrome, and two children had congenital 
anomalies (club foot and bilateral ureteral reflux).</ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem><ListItem>The findings of the prospective single-arm study above were consistent with other smaller 
retrospective series of anthracycline-based chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem>A systematic review studied 40 case 
reports of taxane administration during the second or 
third trimesters of pregnancy.<Reference refidx="10"/><ItemizedList id="_144" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Minimal maternal, fetal, or neonatal toxicity 
was observed.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_155"><Title>Fluorouracil dosing</Title><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000813769_3"><Para id="_sm_CDR0000813769_4">The <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> gene encodes an enzyme that catabolizes pyrimidines and fluoropyrimidines, like capecitabine and fluorouracil. An estimated 1% to 2% of the population has germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName>, which lead to reduced DPD protein function and an accumulation of pyrimidines and fluoropyrimidines in the body.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Patients with the <GeneName>DPYD*2A</GeneName> variant who receive fluoropyrimidines may experience severe, life-threatening toxicities that are sometimes fatal. Many other <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> variants have been identified,  with a range of clinical effects.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> Fluoropyrimidine avoidance or a dose reduction of 50% may be recommended based on  the patient's <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> genotype and number of functioning <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> alleles.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/> <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> genetic testing costs less than $200, but insurance coverage varies due to  a lack of national guidelines.<Reference refidx="17"/> In addition, testing may delay therapy by 2 weeks, which would not be advisable in urgent situations. This controversial issue requires further evaluation.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_137"><Title>Endocrine Therapy</Title><Para id="_116">Endocrine therapy is generally avoided
 until after delivery.  Case reports and a literature review of 
tamoxifen during pregnancy show that tamoxifen administration during pregnancy is associated with vaginal bleeding, miscarriage, congenital 
abnormalities such as  Goldenhar syndrome, and fetal death.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/>  Breastfeeding is also not recommended 
concurrently with endocrine therapy.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>Targeted Therapy</Title><Para id="_115">The use of trastuzumab during pregnancy is contraindicated
 based on results of a systematic review of 
17 studies (18 pregnancies, 19 newborns).<Reference refidx="23"/> Of the fetal 
complications noted, occurrence of oligohydramnios/anhydramnios was the most common (61.1%) 
adverse event. Of the pregnancies exposed to trastuzumab during the second or third trimester, 73.3% of the pregnancies  were 
complicated with oligohydramnios/anhydramnios. Of the pregnancies exposed to 
trastuzumab exclusively during the first trimester, 0%
 (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .043) of the pregnancies were complicated with oligohydramnios/anhydramnios. The mean gestational age at 
delivery was 33.8 weeks, and the mean weight of newborns at delivery was 2,261 grams or 4.984 pounds. In 52.6% of 
cases, a healthy neonate was born. At the long-term evaluation, all children who were without complications at birth 
were healthy, with a median follow-up of 9 months, and four of nine children with complications at birth 
had died within an interval ranging from birth to  5.25 months. All children exposed to trastuzumab in 
utero exclusively in the first trimester were completely 
healthy at birth. The data suggest that for women 
who become pregnant during trastuzumab administration and wish to 
continue pregnancy, trastuzumab should be stopped and pregnancy would be allowed to continue.  </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="24756813">Gropper AB, Calvillo KZ, Dominici L, et al.: Sentinel lymph node biopsy in pregnant women with breast cancer. Ann Surg Oncol 21 (8): 2506-11, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15863381">Kal HB, Struikmans H: Radiotherapy during pregnancy: fact and fiction. Lancet Oncol 6 (5): 328-33, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11271981" MedlineID="21089385">Gwyn K, Theriault R: Breast cancer during pregnancy. Oncology (Huntingt) 15 (1): 39-46; discussion 46, 49-51, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="8598965" MedlineID="96176502">Nettleton J, Long J, Kuban D, et al.: Breast cancer during pregnancy: quantifying the risk of treatment delay. Obstet Gynecol 87 (3): 414-8, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="11812971" MedlineID="21672050">Kuerer HM, Gwyn K, Ames FC, et al.: Conservative surgery and chemotherapy for breast carcinoma during pregnancy. Surgery 131 (1): 108-10, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16894524">Hahn KM, Johnson PH, Gordon N, et al.: Treatment of pregnant breast cancer patients and outcomes of children exposed to chemotherapy in utero. Cancer 107 (6): 1219-26, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3276379">Turchi JJ, Villasis C: Anthracyclines in the treatment of malignancy in pregnancy. Cancer 61 (3): 435-40, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="1546920">Zemlickis D, Lishner M, Degendorfer P, et al.: Fetal outcome after in utero exposure to cancer chemotherapy. Arch Intern Med 152 (3): 573-6, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="26415085">Amant F, Vandenbroucke T, Verheecke M, et al.: Pediatric Outcome after Maternal Cancer Diagnosed during Pregnancy. N Engl J Med 373 (19): 1824-34, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="19887464">Mir O, Berveiller P, Goffinet F, et al.: Taxanes for breast cancer during pregnancy: a systematic review. Ann Oncol 21 (2): 425-6, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="34506675">Sharma BB, Rai K, Blunt H, et al.: Pathogenic DPYD Variants and Treatment-Related Mortality in Patients Receiving Fluoropyrimidine Chemotherapy: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Oncologist 26 (12): 1008-1016, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="27569869">Lam SW, Guchelaar HJ, Boven E: The role of pharmacogenetics in capecitabine efficacy and toxicity. Cancer Treat Rev 50: 9-22, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="33410339">Shakeel F, Fang F, Kwon JW, et al.: Patients carrying DPYD variant alleles have increased risk of severe toxicity and related treatment modifications during fluoropyrimidine chemotherapy. Pharmacogenomics 22 (3): 145-155, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="29152729">Amstutz U, Henricks LM, Offer SM, et al.: Clinical Pharmacogenetics Implementation Consortium (CPIC) Guideline for Dihydropyrimidine Dehydrogenase Genotype and Fluoropyrimidine Dosing: 2017 Update. Clin Pharmacol Ther 103 (2): 210-216, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="30348537">Henricks LM, Lunenburg CATC, de Man FM, et al.: DPYD genotype-guided dose individualisation of fluoropyrimidine therapy in patients with cancer: a prospective safety analysis. Lancet Oncol 19 (11): 1459-1467, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="34996412">Lau-Min KS, Varughese LA, Nelson MN, et al.: Preemptive pharmacogenetic testing to guide chemotherapy dosing in patients with gastrointestinal malignancies: a qualitative study of barriers to implementation. BMC Cancer 22 (1): 47, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="35668003">Brooks GA, Tapp S, Daly AT, et al.: Cost-effectiveness of DPYD Genotyping Prior to Fluoropyrimidine-based Adjuvant Chemotherapy for Colon Cancer. Clin Colorectal Cancer 21 (3): e189-e195, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="36821823">Baker SD, Bates SE, Brooks GA, et al.: DPYD Testing: Time to Put Patient Safety First. J Clin Oncol 41 (15): 2701-2705, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="8201729">Cullins SL, Pridjian G, Sutherland CM: Goldenhar's syndrome associated with tamoxifen given to the mother during gestation. JAMA 271 (24): 1905-6, 1994 Jun 22-29.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="9250188">Tewari K, Bonebrake RG, Asrat T, et al.: Ambiguous genitalia in infant exposed to tamoxifen in utero. Lancet 350 (9072): 183, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="11263941">Isaacs RJ, Hunter W, Clark K: Tamoxifen as systemic treatment of advanced breast cancer during pregnancy--case report and literature review. Gynecol Oncol 80 (3): 405-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="12196882">Helewa M, Lévesque P, Provencher D, et al.: Breast cancer, pregnancy, and breastfeeding. J Obstet Gynaecol Can 24 (2): 164-80; quiz 181-4, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="23242615">Zagouri F, Sergentanis TN, Chrysikos D, et al.: Trastuzumab administration during pregnancy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Breast Cancer Res Treat 137 (2): 349-57, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039029">stage III breast cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039108">stage IV breast cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Advanced Breast Cancer During Pregnancy</Title><Para id="_145">There is no standard treatment for patients with advanced (stage III or stage IV) breast cancer during pregnancy. Most studies show a 5-year survival rate of 10% in pregnant
patients with stage III or IV disease.</Para><Para id="_24">First-trimester radiation therapy should be avoided.  Chemotherapy may be given
after the first trimester as discussed in the section on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062770#_10" url="/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Early/Localized/Operable Breast Cancer During Pregnancy</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_146">Because the mother's life span may be
limited, and there is a risk of fetal damage
with treatment during the first trimester,<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> issues regarding continuation of
the pregnancy should be discussed with the patient and her family.  Therapeutic
abortion does not improve prognosis.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2218825" MedlineID="91019801">Hoover HC: Breast cancer during pregnancy and lactation. Surg Clin North Am 70 (5): 1151-63, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="12594943" MedlineID="22483516">Rugo HS: Management of breast cancer diagnosed during pregnancy. Curr Treat Options Oncol 4 (2): 165-73, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11271981" MedlineID="21089385">Gwyn K, Theriault R: Breast cancer during pregnancy. Oncology (Huntingt) 15 (1): 39-46; discussion 46, 49-51, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="2486467" MedlineID="91084305">Clark RM, Chua T: Breast cancer and pregnancy: the ultimate challenge. Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol) 1 (1): 11-8, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2218844" MedlineID="91019822">Barnavon Y, Wallack MK: Management of the pregnant patient with carcinoma of the breast. Surg Gynecol Obstet 171 (4): 347-52, 1990.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Special Considerations for Pregnancy and Breast Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_58"><Title>Lactation</Title><Para id="_59">Suppression of lactation does not improve prognosis. If surgery  is
planned, however, lactation is suppressed to decrease the size and vascularity of
the breasts.  If chemotherapy is to be given, lactation is also suppressed because many antineoplastic agents (i.e., cyclophosphamide and methotrexate), when 
given systemically,  may occur in high levels in breast milk and would
affect the nursing baby.  Women receiving chemotherapy should not
breastfeed.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_60"><Title>Fetal Consequences of Maternal Breast Cancer</Title><Para id="_61">No damaging effects on the fetus from maternal breast cancer have been
demonstrated,<Reference refidx="2"/> and there are no reported cases of maternal-fetal transfer of
breast cancer cells.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_66"><Title>Pregnancy in Patients With a History of Breast Cancer</Title><Para id="_67">Based on limited retrospective data, pregnancy does not appear to compromise the survival of women with a previous
history of breast cancer, and no
deleterious effects have been demonstrated in the fetus.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/>  Some
physicians recommend that patients wait 2 years after diagnosis before
attempting to conceive.  This allows early recurrence to become manifest, which
may influence the decision to become a parent.  </Para><Para id="_139">Little is known about pregnancy
after bone marrow transplant and high-dose chemotherapy with or without
total-body irradiation.  In one report of pregnancies after bone marrow
transplant for hematologic disorders, a 25% incidence of preterm labor and low
birth weight for gestational-age infants was noted.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12196882">Helewa M, Lévesque P, Provencher D, et al.: Breast cancer, pregnancy, and breastfeeding. J Obstet Gynaecol Can 24 (2): 164-80; quiz 181-4, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="26415085">Amant F, Vandenbroucke T, Verheecke M, et al.: Pediatric Outcome after Maternal Cancer Diagnosed during Pregnancy. N Engl J Med 373 (19): 1824-34, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2486467" MedlineID="91084305">Clark RM, Chua T: Breast cancer and pregnancy: the ultimate challenge. Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol) 1 (1): 11-8, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="7292273" MedlineID="82040141">Harvey JC, Rosen PP, Ashikari R, et al.: The effect of pregnancy on the prognosis of carcinoma of the breast following radical mastectomy. Surg Gynecol Obstet 153 (5): 723-5, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="8004628" MedlineID="94273142">Petrek JA: Pregnancy safety after breast cancer. Cancer 74 (1 Suppl): 528-31, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="7844605" MedlineID="95147029">von Schoultz E, Johansson H, Wilking N, et al.: Influence of prior and subsequent pregnancy on breast cancer prognosis. J Clin Oncol 13 (2): 430-4, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="14659129">Kroman N, Mouridsen HT: Prognostic influence of pregnancy before, around, and after diagnosis of breast cancer. Breast 12 (6): 516-21, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8960142" MedlineID="97119319">Malamos NA, Stathopoulos GP, Keramopoulos A, et al.: Pregnancy and offspring after the appearance of breast cancer. Oncology 53 (6): 471-5, 1996 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11250996" MedlineID="21150315">Gelber S, Coates AS, Goldhirsch A, et al.: Effect of pregnancy on overall survival after the diagnosis of early-stage breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 19 (6): 1671-5, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="11271981" MedlineID="21089385">Gwyn K, Theriault R: Breast cancer during pregnancy. Oncology (Huntingt) 15 (1): 39-46; discussion 46, 49-51, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="12594943" MedlineID="22483516">Rugo HS: Management of breast cancer diagnosed during pregnancy. Curr Treat Options Oncol 4 (2): 165-73, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="8639928" MedlineID="96220004">Sanders JE, Hawley J, Levy W, et al.: Pregnancies following high-dose cyclophosphamide with or without high-dose busulfan or total-body irradiation and bone marrow transplantation. Blood 87 (7): 3045-52, 1996.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_39"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (12/04/2024)</Title><Para id="_32">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_158">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062770#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of breast cancer during pregnancy. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Fumiko Chino, MD (MD Anderson Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Tarek Hijal, MD (McGill University Health Centre)</ListItem><ListItem>Joseph L. Pater, MD (NCIC-Clinical Trials Group)</ListItem><ListItem>Carol Tweed, MD (Maryland Oncology Hematology)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Breast Cancer Treatment During Pregnancy. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/hp/pregnancy-breast-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389427]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-12-04</DateLastModified></Summary>
