<Summary id="CDR0000062806" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Depression is a treatable condition that can affect adults and children with cancer.  Get detailed information about depression, risk factors, diagnosis, and treatment in adults and children with cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">Depression (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-hp-pdq">Depression (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000042480">depression</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_207">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about cancer-related depression and suicide risk in both the adult and the pediatric population. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_208">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>depression</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Depression (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Depression</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Depression</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General information about depression</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><KeyPoint id="_6">Depression is different from normal sadness.</KeyPoint><Para id="_53"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Depression</GlossaryTermRef> is more than feeling down or sad from time to time. It is a medical problem marked by ongoing feelings of sadness, despair, loss of energy, and difficulty dealing with daily life. If you have these feelings most of the day for longer than 2 weeks, it may be a sign of major depression.</Para><Para id="_273">Other symptoms of major depression include</Para><ItemizedList id="_274" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>loss of pleasure and interest in activities you used to enjoy</ListItem><ListItem>changes in eating and sleeping habits</ListItem><ListItem>slow physical and mental responses</ListItem><ListItem>feeling restless or jittery</ListItem><ListItem>unexplained tiredness</ListItem><ListItem>feeling worthless, hopeless, or helpless</ListItem><ListItem>feeling a lot of guilt for no reason</ListItem><ListItem>not being able to pay attention</ListItem><ListItem>thinking the same thoughts over and over</ListItem><ListItem>frequent thoughts of death or suicide</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_275">People diagnosed with cancer may also have other symptoms of depression, such as</Para><ItemizedList id="_276" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>feelings of disbelief or denial</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> or worry about the future</ListItem><ListItem>grief</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_277">Symptoms of depression are not the same for every person. </Para><Para id="_291"> Cancer-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> such as cancer type, stage, and treatment may contribute to depression, but having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mental health</GlossaryTermRef> issues or  a lack of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440116" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social support</GlossaryTermRef> are more important factors. Cancer-related  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, pain, and weaker physical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> can also increase depression risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_284"><KeyPoint id="_285">Depression can be treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_286">It's important to know that help is available for people with depression. Tell your health care team how you are feeling and discuss your treatment options with them. Getting the help you need is important for your life and your health.</Para><Para id="_287">If you have thoughts of suicide, dial 911 in an emergency or call, text, or chat 988 to reach the 988 Suicide and Crisis Lifeline. Counselors are available 24 hours a day, 7 days a week, including for people who are deaf or hard of hearing.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_69"><KeyPoint id="_70">Some people with cancer may have a higher risk of depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_288">A person diagnosed with cancer faces many stressful issues, which may increase the risk of depression. These may include</Para><ItemizedList id="_289" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>being confronted with our mortality</ListItem><ListItem>changes in life plans</ListItem><ListItem>changes in body image and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450120" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">self-esteem</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>changes in day-to-day living</ListItem><ListItem>worry about money and legal issues</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_278">About 2 out of every 10 people diagnosed with cancer become depressed. The number of men and women affected are about the same.</Para><Para id="_71"> Certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> may increase your chance of developing depression after a cancer diagnosis. Risk factors related to cancer that may cause depression include</Para><ItemizedList id="_226" Style="bullet"><ListItem>learning you have  cancer when you are already depressed</ListItem><ListItem>having cancer pain that is not well controlled</ListItem><ListItem>being physically  weakened by the cancer</ListItem><ListItem>having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or a poor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>taking certain  drugs, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">corticosteroids</GlossaryTermRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000675532" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/procarbazinehydrochloride">procarbazine</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000717920" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/asparaginase-erwinia-chrysanthemi">L-asparaginase</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000744420" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/recombinant-interferon-alfa-2b">interferon alfa</DrugRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000596071" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/aldesleukin">interleukin-2</DrugRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">amphotericin B</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_227">Risk factors not related to cancer that may cause depression include</Para><ItemizedList id="_228" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of depression, suicide attempts, or other mental health problems</ListItem><ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of depression or suicide</ListItem><ListItem>a personal history of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcoholism</GlossaryTermRef> or drug abuse</ListItem><ListItem>lacking support from family or friends</ListItem><ListItem>stress caused by life events other than cancer</ListItem><ListItem>having other health problems, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stroke</GlossaryTermRef> or heart attack that may also cause depression</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_281">Not everyone who is diagnosed with cancer reacts in the same way. Some people with cancer may not have depression or anxiety, while others may have major depression or an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797031" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety disorder</GlossaryTermRef>. For more information on anxiety disorders, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000269124" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-pdq">Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_93"><KeyPoint id="_94">There are many medical conditions that can cause depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_95">Medical conditions that may cause  depression in people with cancer include</Para><ItemizedList id="_96" Style="bullet"><ListItem>pain that doesn't go away with treatment</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045632" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">calcium</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044731" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sodium</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044344" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">potassium</GlossaryTermRef> in the blood</ListItem><ListItem>not enough <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin B12</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">folate</GlossaryTermRef> in your diet</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>fever</ListItem><ListItem>too much or too little <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid hormone</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem> too little <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adrenal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>side effects caused by certain drugs</ListItem><ListItem>cancer in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>poor sleep</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><KeyPoint id="_62">Family members of people with cancer are also at risk of depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_63"> Anxiety and depression may occur in family members who are caring for loved ones with cancer. Family members who talk about their feelings and solve problems together are less likely to have high levels of depression and anxiety.</Para><Para id="_290">If you are a caregiver, watch for signs of depression or anxiety in yourself and talk with your doctor even if you think what you are feeling is normal. It's important that you take care of your own health and seek help when you need it. For more information, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support">Support for Caregivers of Cancer Patients</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_49"><Title>Diagnosis of depression</Title><SummarySection id="_87"><KeyPoint id="_88">Your health care provider will talk with you to find out if you have symptoms of depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_104"> Your health care provider may want to discuss the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_105" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Your feelings about having cancer. Talk with your doctor to see if your feelings are normal sadness or more serious. </ListItem><ListItem>Your  moods. You may be asked to rate your mood on a scale. </ListItem><ListItem>Any symptoms of depression you may have and how long they have lasted.</ListItem><ListItem>How the symptoms of depression affect your daily life, such as your relationships, your work, and your ability to enjoy your usual activities.</ListItem><ListItem>Other parts of your life that are causing stress.</ListItem><ListItem>How strong your social support system is.</ListItem><ListItem>A list of the drugs and supplements you are taking and other treatments you are receiving. Sometimes, side effects of drugs or the cancer seem like symptoms of depression. This is more likely during active cancer treatment or if you have advanced cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_98">Your health care team will continue to monitor your symptoms  to  keep your depression from getting worse. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_99"><KeyPoint id="_100">Physical exams and lab tests are also used to diagnose depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_101">In addition to talking with you, your doctor may</Para><ItemizedList id="_102" Style="bullet"><ListItem>ask about your personal and family medical history to learn more about your possible risk factors for depression</ListItem><ListItem> do a physical exam  to check general signs of health, which can help rule out other causes of your symptoms</ListItem><ListItem>run <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory tests</GlossaryTermRef> to rule out a medical condition that may be causing symptoms of depression</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><Title>Treatment of depression</Title><SummarySection id="_75"><KeyPoint id="_76">The decision to treat depression depends on how long it has lasted and how much it affects your life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_125">You may have depression that needs to be treated if you are not able to perform your usual activities, have severe symptoms, or the symptoms do not go away. Treatment of depression may  include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000457962" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">talk therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, medicines, or both.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_246"><KeyPoint id="_247">Counseling or talk therapy helps some  people with depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_248">Your doctor may suggest you see a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychiatrist</GlossaryTermRef> because</Para><ItemizedList id="_249" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>your  symptoms have been treated with medicine for 2 to 4  weeks and are not getting better</ListItem><ListItem>your depression is getting worse</ListItem><ListItem>you are experiencing unwanted side effects from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antidepressants</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>depression keeps you from continuing with your cancer treatment</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_250">Most <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counseling</GlossaryTermRef> or talk therapy programs for depression are offered in both individual and small-group settings. These programs include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450099" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">crisis intervention</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450116" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cognitive-behavior therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_252">More than one type of therapy program may be  right for you. A therapy program can help you learn about</Para><ItemizedList id="_253" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>coping and problem-solving skills</ListItem><ListItem>relaxation skills and ways to lower stress</ListItem><ListItem>ways to get rid of or change negative thoughts</ListItem><ListItem>cancer and its treatment</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_254">Talking with a clergy member may also be helpful for some people.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_266"><KeyPoint id="_267">Physical activity may help relieve depression symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_268">Being physically active may help relieve depression and its symptoms. At least 150 minutes of moderate-to-vigorous exercise per week has been shown to reduce depression in breast cancer survivors. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><KeyPoint id="_10">Antidepressants help some people with depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_209">Antidepressants may help relieve depression and its symptoms. When you are taking antidepressants, it's important that you use them under the care of a doctor. Some antidepressants take 3 to 6 weeks to work. To avoid side effects, you usually begin at a low dose that is slowly increased to find the right dose for you.  </Para><Para id="_282">You may be treated with a number of drugs during your cancer care. Some anticancer drugs may not mix safely with certain antidepressants or with certain foods, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbals</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutritional supplements</GlossaryTermRef>. It's important to tell your health care providers about all the drugs, herbals, and nutritional supplements you are taking, including drugs used as patches on the skin, and any other diseases, conditions, or symptoms you have. This can help prevent unwanted reactions with your antidepressant.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_213"><KeyPoint id="_214">There are different types of antidepressants.</KeyPoint><Para id="_215">Most  antidepressants help treat depression by changing  the levels of chemicals called neurotransmitters in the brain, while some affect cell <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">receptors</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nerves</GlossaryTermRef> use these chemicals to send messages to one another. Increasing the amount of these chemicals helps to improve mood. 

 The different types of antidepressants act on these chemicals in different ways  and have different side effects.</Para><Para id="_216">Several types of antidepressants are  used to treat depression:</Para><ItemizedList id="_217" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>SSRIs (selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors) are drugs that stop serotonin (a substance that nerves use to send messages to one another) from being reabsorbed by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve cells</GlossaryTermRef> that make it. This means there is more serotonin for other nerve cells to use. SSRIs include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">citalopram</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">escitalopram</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluoxetine</GlossaryTermRef>. SSRIs are  commonly used  antidepressants in people with cancer and  work well to treat depression. </ListItem><ListItem>SNRIs (serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors) are  drugs that stop the brain chemicals serotonin and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">norepinephrine</GlossaryTermRef> from being reabsorbed by the nerve cells that make it. This means there is more serotonin and norepinephrine for other nerve cells to use. Some SNRIs may also help relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046041" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuropathy</GlossaryTermRef> caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or hot flashes caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopause</GlossaryTermRef>.  SNRIs include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">venlafaxine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000589399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">duloxetine</GlossaryTermRef>,  and levomilnacipran.</ListItem><ListItem>Tricyclic antidepressants work the same way SNRIs do. Tricyclic antidepressants may be used for depression that does not respond to other types of antidepressants. They can  also help relieve headaches, neuropathy caused by chemotherapy, and problems falling or staying asleep. Tricyclic antidepressants  include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000589423" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">amitriptyline</GlossaryTermRef>, doxepin, and imipramine.</ListItem><ListItem>NDRIs (norepinephrine-dopamine reuptake inhibitors) are  drugs that stop the brain chemicals norepinephrine and dopamine from being reabsorbed. This means there is more norepinephrine and dopamine for other nerve cells to use.  The only NDRI currently approved to treat depression is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045082" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bupropion</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_218">Other antidepressants include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450112" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mirtazapine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740690" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trazodone</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561433" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monoamine oxidase inhibitors</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_234">Sometimes, other drugs, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000694849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benzodiazepines</GlossaryTermRef> or psychostimulants, are given along with antidepressants to decrease anxiety or improve energy and concentration.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_235"><KeyPoint id="_236">The antidepressant that is best for you depends on several factors. 

</KeyPoint><Para id="_237">Choosing the best antidepressant for you depends on</Para><ItemizedList id="_222" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>your symptoms</ListItem><ListItem>side effects of the antidepressant</ListItem><ListItem>your medical history</ListItem><ListItem>other medicines you are taking</ListItem><ListItem>how you or your family members responded to antidepressants in the past</ListItem><ListItem>the form of medicine you are able to take (such as a pill or a liquid)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_238">You may have to try different treatments to find the one that is right for you. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_256"><KeyPoint id="_257">Your doctor will watch you closely if you need to change your antidepressant.</KeyPoint><Para id="_258">You may need to change your antidepressant if severe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> occur or your symptoms are not getting better. Check with your doctor before you stop taking an antidepressant. Your doctor will reduce the dose slowly before starting another antidepressant. This is to prevent side effects that can occur if you suddenly stop taking your antidepressant. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Suicide risk in people with cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_23"><KeyPoint id="_24">People with cancer may feel hopeless at times and think about suicide.</KeyPoint><Para id="_25">Some people with cancer  feel hopeless. Talk with your doctor if you feel hopeless. There are ways your doctor can help you. </Para><Para id="_239">Feelings of hopelessness may lead to thinking about suicide. If you or someone you know is thinking about suicide, get help as soon as possible. You can get help from  the <ExternalRef xref="https://suicidepreventionlifeline.org/">National Suicide Prevention Lifeline</ExternalRef>, 1-800-273-TALK (8255). The Lifeline is available 24 hours a day, 7 days a week. The deaf and hard of hearing can contact the TTY Lifeline at 1-800-799-4889. All calls are confidential. More information about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/topics/depression/index.shtml">depression</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/topics/suicide-prevention/index.shtml">suicide prevention</ExternalRef> is available from the National Institute of Mental Health.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><KeyPoint id="_27">Certain factors may increase the risk of suicidal thoughts in people with cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_292">Higher rates of suicidal thoughts, suicidal behaviors, and suicide attempts have been noted  in patients with cancer.</Para><Para id="_28">Some factors that may increase the risk of suicide include older age, being male, and</Para><ItemizedList id="_240" Style="bullet"><ListItem>being single, divorced, or widowed</ListItem><ListItem>having a personal history of depression, anxiety, or other mental health problem, or suicide attempts</ListItem><ListItem>having a family member who has attempted suicide</ListItem><ListItem>having a personal history of drug or alcohol abuse</ListItem><ListItem>feeling hopeless or  that you are a burden to others</ListItem><ListItem>lacking support from family and friends</ListItem><ListItem>being unable to live a normal, independent life because of problems with day-to-day activities, pain, or other symptoms</ListItem><ListItem>being within the first 6 months of your cancer diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>having advanced cancer or a poor prognosis</ListItem><ListItem>having cancer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck</GlossaryTermRef>, or pancreas</ListItem><ListItem>having uncontrolled symptoms or side effects of cancer and/or cancer treatment, such as pain</ListItem><ListItem>not getting along well with the treatment team</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_154"><KeyPoint id="_155">The health care team will ask if you have thoughts of suicide and help manage the cause of the thoughts.</KeyPoint><Para id="_283">Talk to your doctor if you have thoughts of hopelessness and are thinking of suicide. You may feel more in control of your emotions  once you describe your feelings and fears.</Para><Para id="_156">People with cancer may feel desperate to stop any discomfort or pain they have.  Keeping pain and other symptoms under control  will help to</Para><ItemizedList id="_197" Style="bullet"><ListItem>relieve distress</ListItem><ListItem>make you feel more comfortable</ListItem><ListItem>prevent thoughts of suicide</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_269">Ask your doctor what may be done to help relieve your emotional and physical pain. Treatment may include antidepressants. Some antidepressants take a few weeks to work. The doctor may prescribe other drugs  that work quickly to relieve distress until the antidepressant begins to work. For your safety, it's important to have frequent contact with a health care professional and avoid being alone until your symptoms are controlled. Your health care team can help you find social support.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><Title>Depression in children</Title><KeyPoint id="_255">Some children have depression or other problems related to cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_168">Most children cope well with cancer. However, a small number of children may have</Para><ItemizedList id="_202" Style="bullet"><ListItem>depression</ListItem><ListItem>anxiety</ListItem><ListItem>trouble sleeping</ListItem><ListItem>problems getting along with family or friends</ListItem><ListItem>problems following the treatment plan</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_203"> These problems can affect the child's cancer treatment and enjoyment of life. They can occur at any time from diagnosis to well after treatment ends. Survivors of childhood cancer who have severe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef> from cancer treatment may be more likely to have symptoms of depression. </Para><Para id="_242">A  psychologist or psychiatrist can help children with depression.</Para><SummarySection id="_113"><KeyPoint id="_114">Your child will be examined for signs of depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_169">Your health care team may ask the following questions:</Para><ItemizedList id="_172" Style="bullet"><ListItem>How is your child eating and sleeping?</ListItem><ListItem>Is your child more tired than usual?</ListItem><ListItem>How has your child coped with past illnesses? </ListItem><ListItem>How is your child's behavior at home and at school? Have they had trouble getting along with others or learning?</ListItem><ListItem>Does your child have more anger, outbursts, or crying than usual?</ListItem><ListItem>Has your child withdrawn from activities they used to enjoy?</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_116"><KeyPoint id="_117">The symptoms of depression are not the same in every child.</KeyPoint><Para id="_176">A diagnosis of depression depends on the symptoms and how long they have lasted. Symptoms of depression in children may include 
	</Para><ItemizedList id="_183" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef> changes</ListItem><ListItem>not sleeping or sleeping too much</ListItem><ListItem>feeling very tired or having little energy</ListItem><ListItem>being unable to relax and be still (such as pacing, fidgeting, and pulling at clothing)</ListItem><ListItem>frequent crying</ListItem><ListItem>
	loss of interest in usual activities</ListItem><ListItem>lack of emotion in children younger than 6 years</ListItem><ListItem>feelings of worthlessness, blame, or guilt</ListItem><ListItem>unable to think or pay attention  and frequent daydreaming</ListItem><ListItem>trouble learning in school, not getting along with others, and refusing to go to school</ListItem><ListItem>frequent thoughts of death or suicide</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_119"><KeyPoint id="_120">Treatment may be talk therapy or antidepressants.</KeyPoint><Para id="_270">Talk therapy is the main treatment for depression in children. The child may talk to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688836" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">counselor</GlossaryTermRef> alone or with a small group of other children. Talk therapy may include play therapy for younger children. Therapy will help the child cope with feelings of depression and understand their cancer and treatment.</Para><Para id="_271">Antidepressants may be given to children with major depression or anxiety. In some children, teenagers, and young adults, antidepressants may make depression   worse or cause thoughts of suicide. The Food and Drug Administration has warned that people younger than age 25 who are taking antidepressants should be watched closely for signs that the depression is getting worse and for suicidal thinking or behavior.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>To learn more about depression</Title><Para id="_44">For more information from the National Cancer Institute 
        about depression, see</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet">
   <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000269124" url="/about-cancer/coping/feelings/anxiety-distress-pdq">Adjustment to Cancer: Anxiety and Distress</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/advanced-cancer">Coping with Advanced Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings">Emotions and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem>
   
   
  </ItemizedList><Para id="_244">For general information about depression and suicide prevention from the National Institute of Mental Health, see</Para><ItemizedList id="_245" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/topics/depression/index.shtml">Depression</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/topics/suicide-prevention/index.shtml">Suicide Prevention</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/topics/psychotherapies/index.shtml">Psychotherapies (Talk Therapy)</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/topics/mental-health-medications/index.shtml">Mental Health Medications</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about cancer-related depression and suicide risk in both the adult and the pediatric population.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Depression. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings/depression-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389474]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062739"/><DateLastModified>2024-08-27</DateLastModified></Summary>
