<Summary id="CDR0000062825" LegacyPDQID="2876"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Prevention</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Lung cancer prevention approaches include avoiding exposure to risk factors like tobacco smoke, radon, radiation, asbestos, and other substances. Learn more about preventing lung cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/lung-prevention-pdq">Lung Cancer (PDQ®): Prevention</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/hp/lung-prevention-pdq">Lung Cancer (PDQ®): Prevention</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040209">lung cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041588">cancer prevention</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_167">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about lung cancer prevention. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_168">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer prevention</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>lung cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Lung Cancer Prevention (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Lung Cancer Prevention</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Lung Cancer Prevention</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_29"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Rationale for prevention</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>What Is Prevention?</Title><Para id="_30">Cancer prevention is action taken to lower the chance of getting 
         cancer. By preventing cancer, the number of new cases of cancer 
         in a group or population is lowered. Hopefully, this will lower 
         the number of deaths caused by cancer.</Para><Para id="_31">To prevent new cancers from starting, scientists look at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk 
         factors</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factors</GlossaryTermRef>. Anything that increases your 
         chance of developing cancer is called a cancer risk factor; 
         anything that decreases your chance of developing cancer is 
         called a cancer protective factor.</Para><Para id="_32">Some risk factors for cancer can be avoided, but many cannot. 
         For example, both smoking and inheriting certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> are 
         risk factors for some types of cancer, but only smoking can be 
         avoided. Regular exercise and a healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef> may be protective 
         factors for some types of cancer. Avoiding risk factors and 
         increasing protective factors may lower your risk, but it does 
         not mean that you will not get cancer.</Para><Para id="_33">Different ways to prevent cancer are being studied, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_34" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>changing lifestyle or eating habits</ListItem>
    <ListItem>avoiding things known to cause cancer</ListItem>
    <ListItem>taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicines</GlossaryTermRef> to treat a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">precancerous</GlossaryTermRef> condition or to 
         keep cancer from starting</ListItem>
  </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>General Information About Lung Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_6">Lung cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form
		  in the tissues of the lung.</KeyPoint><Para id="_7">The lungs are a pair of cone-shaped breathing organs in the chest.
		  The lungs bring <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> into the body as you breathe in. They release <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538147" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carbon dioxide</GlossaryTermRef>,  a
		  waste product of the body's cells, as you breathe out.
		  Each lung has sections called lobes. The
		  left lung has two lobes. The right
		  lung is slightly larger, and has three lobes. A thin membrane called the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045842" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pleura</GlossaryTermRef> surrounds the lungs.      Two
		  tubes called bronchi lead from the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> (windpipe) to the right and
		  left lungs. The bronchi are sometimes also involved in lung cancer. Tiny air sacs called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alveoli</GlossaryTermRef> and small tubes called
		  bronchioles make up the inside of
		  the lungs. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000466533" type="image/jpeg" alt="Respiratory system anatomy; drawing shows the right lung with the upper, middle, and lower lobes, the left lung with the upper and lower lobes, and the trachea, bronchi, lymph nodes, and diaphragm. An inset shows the bronchioles, alveoli, artery, and vein." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_93"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the respiratory system showing the trachea, the right and left lungs and their lobes, and the bronchi. The lymph nodes and the diaphragm are also shown. Oxygen is inhaled into the lungs and passes through the alveoli (the tiny air sacs at the end of the bronchioles) and into the bloodstream (see inset), where it travels to the tissues throughout the body.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_8">There are two main types of lung cancer: <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045327" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small
		  cell lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-small cell
		  lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_82">Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summaries containing information related to  lung cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_83" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000258019" url="/types/lung/patient/lung-screening-pdq">Lung Cancer Screening</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062956" url="/types/lung/patient/non-small-cell-lung-treatment-pdq">Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062947" url="/types/lung/patient/small-cell-lung-treatment-pdq">Small Cell Lung Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062889" url="/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-pdq">Cigarette Smoking:  Health Risks and How to Quit</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_10">Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer death in both men and women.</KeyPoint><Para id="_173">Lung cancer rates and deaths are higher in Black men than in   other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">racial</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784950" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ethnic group</GlossaryTermRef>  in the United States.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><Title>Lung Cancer Prevention</Title><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_14">Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may
		  help prevent lung cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_13_md_53">Avoiding <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> may help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> certain cancers. Risk factors include smoking, having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overweight</GlossaryTermRef>, and not getting enough exercise.  Increasing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factors</GlossaryTermRef> such as quitting smoking and exercising may also help prevent some cancers. Talk to your doctor or other health care professional about how you might lower your risk of cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_37">The following  are <Emphasis>risk</Emphasis> factors  for lung cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_18"><KeyPoint id="_19">Cigarette, cigar, and pipe smoking </KeyPoint><Para id="_20"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439432" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tobacco</GlossaryTermRef> smoking is the most important <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef> for  lung cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748148" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cigarette</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748146" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cigar</GlossaryTermRef>,  and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748824" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pipe</GlossaryTermRef> smoking all  increase the risk of lung cancer. Tobacco smoking causes about 9 out of 10 cases of lung cancer in men and about 8 out of 10 cases of lung cancer in women.</Para><Para id="_128">Studies have shown that smoking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">low tar</GlossaryTermRef>   or low <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nicotine</GlossaryTermRef> cigarettes does not lower    the risk of lung cancer.   </Para><Para id="_105">Studies also show that the risk of lung cancer from smoking cigarettes increases with the number of cigarettes smoked per day and the number of years smoked. People who smoke have about 20 times the risk of lung cancer compared to those who do not smoke.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_90"><KeyPoint id="_91">Secondhand smoke</KeyPoint><Para id="_92">Being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538647" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">secondhand tobacco smoke</GlossaryTermRef> is also  a risk factor for lung cancer. Secondhand smoke is the smoke that comes from a burning cigarette or other tobacco product, or   that is exhaled by smokers. People who inhale secondhand smoke are exposed to  the same cancer-causing agents as smokers, although in  smaller amounts. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044600" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Inhaling</GlossaryTermRef> secondhand smoke is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476297" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">involuntary</GlossaryTermRef> or passive smoking.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_129"><KeyPoint id="_130">Family history</KeyPoint><Para id="_162">Having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of lung cancer is a risk factor for lung cancer. People with a relative who has had lung cancer may be twice as likely to have lung cancer as  people  who do not have a relative who has had lung cancer.  Because cigarette smoking tends to run  in families and  family members are exposed to secondhand smoke,  it is hard to know whether the increased risk of lung cancer is from the family history of lung cancer or from being exposed to cigarette smoke.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_164"><KeyPoint id="_165">HIV infection</KeyPoint><Para id="_166">Being <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infected</GlossaryTermRef> with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044366" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human immunodeficiency virus</GlossaryTermRef> (HIV), the cause of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044365" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acquired immunodeficiency syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (AIDS), is linked with a higher risk of lung cancer. People infected with HIV may have more than twice the risk of lung cancer than those who are not infected. Since smoking rates are higher in those infected with HIV than in those not infected, it is not clear  whether the increased risk of lung cancer   is  from HIV infection or from being exposed to cigarette smoke.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><KeyPoint id="_23">Environmental risk factors</KeyPoint><ItemizedList id="_95" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation</GlossaryTermRef> exposure:</Strong> Being exposed to radiation is a risk factor for lung cancer. Atomic bomb radiation, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging tests</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046554" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radon</GlossaryTermRef> are sources of radiation exposure: <ItemizedList id="_169" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Atomic bomb radiation: Being exposed to radiation after an atomic bomb explosion increases the risk of lung cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy: Radiation therapy to the chest may be used to treat certain cancers, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hodgkin lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef>.  Radiation therapy uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gamma rays</GlossaryTermRef>, or other  types of radiation that may increase the risk of lung cancer. The higher the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> of radiation received, the higher the risk. The risk of lung cancer following radiation therapy is higher in patients who smoke than in nonsmokers.</ListItem><ListItem>Imaging tests:  Imaging tests, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scans</GlossaryTermRef>, expose patients to radiation. Low-dose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiral CT scans</GlossaryTermRef> expose patients to less radiation than higher dose CT scans. In lung cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef>, the use of low-dose spiral CT scans can lessen the harmful effects of radiation.</ListItem><ListItem>Radon: Radon is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> gas that comes from the breakdown of uranium in rocks and soil. It seeps up through the ground, and leaks into the air or water supply. Radon can enter homes through cracks in floors, walls, or the foundation, and levels of radon can build up over time. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_170">Studies show that high levels of radon gas inside the  home or workplace increase the number of new cases of lung cancer  and the number of deaths caused by lung cancer. The risk of lung cancer is higher in smokers exposed to radon than in nonsmokers who are exposed to it. In people who have never smoked, about 26% of deaths caused by lung cancer have been linked to being exposed to radon.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Workplace exposure:</Strong> Studies show that being exposed to the following substances increases the risk of lung cancer:<ItemizedList id="_101" Style="dash"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046528" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">asbestos</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044303" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">arsenic</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>chromium</ListItem><ListItem>nickel</ListItem><ListItem>beryllium</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000344348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cadmium</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>tar and soot</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_102">These substances can cause lung cancer in people  who are exposed to them in the workplace and have never smoked. As the level of exposure to these substances increases, the risk of lung cancer also increases. The risk of lung cancer is even higher in people who are exposed and also smoke.</Para> </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Air pollution:</Strong> Studies show  that living in areas with  higher levels of  air pollution increases the  risk of lung cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><KeyPoint id="_26">Beta carotene supplements in heavy smokers</KeyPoint><Para id="_27">Taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta carotene</GlossaryTermRef> supplements (pills) increases the risk of
			  lung cancer, especially in smokers who smoke one or more packs a day. The risk
			 is higher in smokers who have at least one <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcoholic</GlossaryTermRef> drink every day.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_39">The following are <Emphasis>protective</Emphasis> factors  for lung cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_43"><KeyPoint id="_44">Not smoking</KeyPoint><Para id="_45">The best way to prevent lung cancer is to not smoke.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_97"><KeyPoint id="_98">Quitting smoking</KeyPoint><Para id="_99">Smokers can
			 decrease their risk of lung cancer by quitting. In smokers who have been treated for lung cancer, quitting smoking lowers the risk of new lung cancers. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Counseling</GlossaryTermRef>,  the use of
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nicotine</GlossaryTermRef> replacement products, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antidepressant</GlossaryTermRef> therapy have
			 helped smokers quit for good.</Para><Para id="_100">In a person who has quit smoking, the chance of preventing lung cancer  depends on how many years and how much the person smoked and the length of time since quitting. After a person has quit smoking for 10 years, the risk of lung cancer decreases 30% to 60%.</Para><Para id="_171">Although the risk of dying from lung cancer can be greatly decreased by quitting smoking for  a long period of time, the risk will never be as low as the risk in nonsmokers. This is why it is important for young people not to start smoking.</Para><Para id="_103">See the following for more information on quitting smoking:</Para><ItemizedList id="_163" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco">Tobacco</ExternalRef> (includes help with quitting)</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062889" url="/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-pdq">Cigarette Smoking:  Health Risks and How to Quit</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><KeyPoint id="_107">Lower exposure to workplace risk factors </KeyPoint><Para id="_108">Laws that protect workers from being exposed   to  cancer-causing substances, such as asbestos, arsenic, nickel, and chromium, may help lower their risk of developing lung cancer. Laws that prevent smoking in the workplace help lower the risk of lung cancer caused by secondhand smoke.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_109"><KeyPoint id="_110">Lower exposure to radon</KeyPoint><Para id="_111"> Lowering radon levels may lower the risk of lung cancer, especially among cigarette smokers. High levels of radon in homes may be reduced by taking steps to prevent radon leakage, such as sealing basements.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_112"><KeyPoint id="_113">It is not clear  if the following decrease the risk of lung cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_114"><KeyPoint id="_115">Diet</KeyPoint><Para id="_116"> Some studies show that people who eat high amounts of  fruits or vegetables have a  lower risk of lung cancer than those who eat low amounts. However, since smokers tend to have less healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diets</GlossaryTermRef> than nonsmokers, it is hard to know whether the decreased risk  is from having a healthy diet or from not smoking.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_117"><KeyPoint id="_118">Physical activity</KeyPoint><Para id="_119">Some studies show that  people who are  physically active have a lower risk of lung cancer than people who are not. However, since smokers tend to have different levels of physical activity  than nonsmokers, it is hard to know if physical activity  affects the risk of lung cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_152"><KeyPoint id="_153">The following do not decrease the risk of lung cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_156"><KeyPoint id="_157">Beta carotene supplements in nonsmokers</KeyPoint><Para id="_159">Studies of nonsmokers show that taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta carotene</GlossaryTermRef> supplements does not lower their risk of lung cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_125"><KeyPoint id="_126">Vitamin E supplements </KeyPoint><Para id="_127">
     
     Studies show that taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin E</GlossaryTermRef> supplements  does not affect the risk of lung cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_60"><KeyPoint id="_61">Cancer prevention clinical trials are used to study ways 
    to prevent cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_60_md_14">Cancer prevention <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> are used to study ways to lower the risk of developing certain types of cancer. Some cancer prevention trials include healthy people who may or may not have an increased risk of cancer. Other prevention trials include people who have had cancer and are trying to prevent recurrence or a second cancer.</Para><Para id="_60_md_15">The purpose of some cancer prevention clinical trials is to find out whether actions people take can prevent cancer. These may include eating fruits and vegetables, exercising, quitting smoking, or taking certain medicines, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>, or food <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_66">
      
     New ways to prevent lung cancer are being studied in clinical 
     trials. </KeyPoint><Para id="_65_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about lung cancer prevention.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Lung Cancer Prevention. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/lung-prevention-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/lung-prevention-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389497]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062824"/><DateLastModified>2025-03-11</DateLastModified></Summary>
