<Summary id="CDR0000062828" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Grief, bereavement (mourning), and coping with loss are common challenges following the loss of a loved one from cancer. Learn about coping and the grief process in adults and children in this expert-reviewed information summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/bereavement-pdq">Grief, Bereavement, and Loss (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/bereavement-hp-pdq">Grief, Bereavement, and Loss (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000042917">loss, grief, and bereavement</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_257">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about how individuals cope with grief, bereavement, and mourning. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_258">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>loss, grief, and bereavement</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Grief, Bereavement, and Loss (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Grief, Bereavement, and Loss</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Grief, Bereavement, and Loss</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><Para id="_44">Grief and mourning are part of the normal process of dealing with a loss. Bereavement is the period of grief and mourning after a death of a loved one. Most people  will adjust to the loss over time. Others will have longer periods of bereavement and may benefit from treatment. </Para><Para id="_245">This summary explains how grief, mourning, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bereavement</GlossaryTermRef> are different and describes the different types of grief, treatments for grief,  and important  issues for grieving children. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><Title>Grief, Mourning, and Bereavement</Title><SummarySection id="_12"><KeyPoint id="_13">Grief is the emotional response to the loss of a loved one.</KeyPoint><Para id="_56">Common grief reactions include: 

 </Para><ItemizedList id="_53" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Feeling emotionally numb.</ListItem><ListItem>Being unable to believe the loss occurred.
</ListItem><ListItem>Having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> of being separated from the loved one.</ListItem><ListItem>Mourning along with feeling depressed.</ListItem><ListItem>A feeling of acceptance.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_262"><KeyPoint id="_264">Mourning is the way we show grief in public.</KeyPoint><Para id="_265">The way people mourn is affected by beliefs, religious practices, and culture. Grief and mourning are closely related. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_267"><KeyPoint id="_268">Bereavement is the period of sadness after  a death of a loved one.</KeyPoint><Para id="_269">Grief and mourning occur during the period of bereavement. People who are grieving are described as bereaved.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_21"><Title>Types of Grief</Title><SummarySection id="_305"><KeyPoint id="_306">There are three types of grief: anticipatory, normal or common, and complicated. </KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_307"><KeyPoint id="_308">Anticipatory grief occurs before death. </KeyPoint><Para id="_352">Anticipatory grief is grief that occurs leading up to a death. It may be felt by the person dying or person's family. When a patient experiences distress, pain, and medical complications, it can add to anticipatory grief. Anticipatory grief is different from grief that occurs after the death.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_353"><KeyPoint id="_354">Anticipatory grief does not affect everyone.</KeyPoint><Para id="_355">Research has shown that about one in four patients with incurable cancer feels anticipatory grief. Anticipatory grief is less likely to occur when the patient and family accept death. Talking with someone who is trained in grief and bereavement may help patients and their family come to terms with impending death. </Para><Para id="_365">In a study of parents who have lost a child to cancer, parents who felt prepared for their child's end of life were better able to function  in social roles and activities in the first 2 years after their loss.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_315"><KeyPoint id="_316">Normal or common grief begins soon after a loss and symptoms go away over time.</KeyPoint><Para id="_356">Normal grief occurs in most people who have experienced a loss. During normal grief, the bereaved person accepts the loss and continues with daily activities even though it is hard to do. Common emotional reactions include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_357" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Emotional numbness, shock, disbelief, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450101" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">denial</GlossaryTermRef>. These often occur  right after the death, especially if the death was not expected.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> over being separated from the loved one. The bereaved may wish to  bring the person back and become lost in  thoughts of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476461" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">deceased</GlossaryTermRef>. Images of death may occur often in the person’s thoughts.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Distress</GlossaryTermRef> that leads to crying; sighing; having dreams, illusions, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hallucinations</GlossaryTermRef> of the deceased; and looking for places or things that were shared with the deceased.</ListItem><ListItem>Anger.</ListItem><ListItem> Periods of sadness, loss of sleep, loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef>, fatigue, guilt, and loss of interest in life. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_358">Grief bursts or pangs are short periods (20-30 minutes) of very intense distress. These bursts are caused by reminders of the deceased person, such as during holidays, the anniversary of the loved one’s death, or when giving away items that belonged to the person. At other times they seem to happen for no reason.</Para><Para id="_359">In normal grief, symptoms will occur less often and will feel less severe as time passes. Recovery time will vary with each person. For most bereaved people, symptoms lessen between 6 months and 2 years after the loss. Although many bereaved people have similar responses as they cope with their losses, there is no typical grief response.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_360"><KeyPoint id="_361">Normal grief is different from major depression.</KeyPoint><Para id="_362">When a person grieves they can have symptoms that overlap with major depression, such as sleep problems, feelings of guilt, repeated thoughts, and lack of interest. Normal grief is different from major depression in the following ways:</Para><ItemizedList id="_363" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Painful feelings come and go instead of being constant.</ListItem><ListItem>There are feelings of emptiness rather than sadness or not feeling pleasure.</ListItem><ListItem>People have good self-esteem and do not feel worthless or badly about themselves.</ListItem><ListItem>If there are thoughts of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">suicide</GlossaryTermRef>, they are focused on the deceased person, such as a wish to join them in death, instead of thoughts about oneself.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_364">A bereaved person can be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> with major depression if they have symptoms that occur outside of the normal grief process.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_331"><KeyPoint id="_332">Complicated grief lasts longer than normal grief.</KeyPoint><Para id="_333">Complicated grief is when symptoms don't improve and last for a long period of time, cause extreme distress, affect multiple areas of their lives, and decrease the ability to take part in daily activities.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Factors that Affect Grief</Title><SummarySection id="_121"><KeyPoint id="_122">There are factors that affect the response to grief.</KeyPoint><Para id="_276">A person’s grief is affected by their:</Para><ItemizedList id="_277" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Personality, age, and sex.</ListItem><ListItem>Cultural and religious background.</ListItem><ListItem>Coping skills and mental health history.</ListItem><ListItem>Amount of support they have.</ListItem><ListItem>Social and financial position.</ListItem><ListItem>Relationship with the person who died. </ListItem><ListItem>The deceased's cancer experience and the way the disease progressed. </ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_334"><KeyPoint id="_335">The personality, age, and sex of the bereaved may affect whether they are more likely to experience depression with their grief.</KeyPoint><Para id="_336">Studies have found that people with certain personality traits are more likely to have long-lasting depression after a loss. These include people who are  dependent on a loved one (such as a spouse), and people who deal with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> by thinking about it all the time.</Para><Para id="_337">In general, younger bereaved people have more problems after a loss than older bereaved people do. They have more severe health problems, grief symptoms, and other mental and physical symptoms. Younger bereaved people, however, may recover more quickly than older bereaved people do, because they tend to have more resources and social support.</Para><Para id="_338">Men have more problems than women do after a spouse’s death. Men tend to have worse depression and more health problems than women do after the loss. Some researchers think this may be because men tend to have less social support after a loss.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_339"><KeyPoint id="_340">Culture and religion play a part in grief and bereavement.</KeyPoint><Para id="_341">Grief occurs in all cultures. However, some cultures have different beliefs about death that affect the attitudes and practices of the bereaved. They use what will best meet their needs to deal with death.</Para><Para id="_342">Some studies show that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000489395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">religion</GlossaryTermRef> helps people <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cope</GlossaryTermRef> better with grief, while other studies  show it does not help or causes more distress. Regular church attendance and social support from a religious setting are linked to positive grief outcomes, such as coping and understanding the loss.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_343"><KeyPoint id="_344">Coping skills and mental health history affect the response to an expected or unexpected loss.</KeyPoint><Para id="_345">It may seem that any sudden, unexpected loss might lead to more difficult grief. However, studies have found that bereaved people with high self-esteem and/or a feeling that they have control over life are likely to have a normal grief reaction even after an unexpected loss. Bereaved people with low self-esteem and/or a sense that life cannot be controlled are more likely to have complicated grief after an unexpected loss. This includes more depression and physical problems. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_346"><KeyPoint id="_347">Social support for the bereaved.</KeyPoint><Para id="_348">Lack of social support increases the chance of having problems  coping with a loss. Social support includes the person's family, friends, neighbors, and community members who can give <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef>, physical, and financial help. After the death of a close family member, many people have  related losses. The death of a spouse, for example, may cause a loss of income and changes in lifestyle and day-to-day living. These are all related to social support.

</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_171"><Title>Treatment of Grief</Title><SummarySection id="_129"><KeyPoint id="_172">Normal grief may not need to be treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_130">Most <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bereaved</GlossaryTermRef> people work through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grief</GlossaryTermRef> and recover within the first 6 months to 2 years. Researchers are studying whether bereaved people who have normal grief would be helped by treatment. They are also studying whether treatment might prevent complicated grief  in people who are likely to have it. </Para><Para id="_157">For people who have serious grief reactions or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>,  treatment may be helpful. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_301"><KeyPoint id="_304">Cognitive behavioral therapy may help people with complicated grief.</KeyPoint><Para id="_302"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cognitive behavioral therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (CBT)   helps a person learn skills that change negative thoughts and behaviors about grief. 
</Para><Para id="_303">A clinical trial compared CBT to counseling for complicated grief. Results showed that patients treated with CBT had  more improvement in symptoms and general mental distress than those in  the counseling group.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><KeyPoint id="_137">Depression related to grief may be treated with drugs.</KeyPoint><Para id="_138">There is no standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for depression that occurs with  grief. The decision to treat grief-related depression with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> is up to the patient and the health care professional. </Para><Para id="_225">Clinical trials of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antidepressants</GlossaryTermRef> for depression related to grief have found that the drugs can help relieve depression. However, they give less relief and take longer to work than they do when used for depression that is not related to grief. Some clinical trials have found that psychotherapy while on antidepressants can improve depression and reduce the intensity of grief.  </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><Title>Children and Grief</Title><SummarySection id="_139"><KeyPoint id="_140">Children have a different grief experience than adults.</KeyPoint><Para id="_229">Children do not react to loss in the same ways as adults. These are some of the ways children's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grief</GlossaryTermRef> is different:</Para><ItemizedList id="_230" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Children show grief once in a while and for  a short time span. A child who grieves may be sad one minute and playful the next. 
Often families think the child doesn’t understand the loss or has gotten over
it quickly.  Usually, neither is true. Children’s minds protect them from what is too
much for them to handle.</ListItem><ListItem>The bereavement process may
continue as the child gets older. Children will revisit the loss repeatedly,  especially at important times, such as
going to camp, graduating from school, getting married, or having children.
</ListItem><ListItem>Grieving children
may not show their feelings as openly as adults.  Grieving children may jump right
into activities  instead of withdrawing or showing grief.</ListItem><ListItem>Children cannot think through their thoughts and feelings like adults. Children may have trouble putting their feelings about grief into words. Strong feelings of anger and fears
of death or being left alone may show up in the behavior of grieving children. 
Children often play death games as a way of working out their feelings and
worries.  These games give children a safe
way to express their feelings.
</ListItem><ListItem>While grieving adults may withdraw and not talk to other people about the loss, children often talk to the people around them (even strangers) to see
 how they react and to get clues for how they should respond to the loss.  </ListItem><ListItem>Children may
ask confusing questions such as, "I know grandpa died,
but when will he come home?"  This is a way of testing reality and making sure
the story of the death has not changed.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_226"><KeyPoint id="_227">Several factors can affect how a child will cope with grief.</KeyPoint><Para id="_176">Although grief is different for each child, several factors can affect the grief process of a child:</Para><ItemizedList id="_177" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The child's age and stage
of development.</ListItem><ListItem>The child's personality.</ListItem><ListItem>The child's previous experiences with death.</ListItem><ListItem>The child's relationship with the
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476461" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">deceased</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The child’s surroundings.</ListItem><ListItem>The cause of death.</ListItem><ListItem>The way the child acts and
communicates within the family.</ListItem><ListItem>How stable the family life is after the loss.</ListItem><ListItem>How
the child continues to be cared for.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the child is given the chance to
share and express feelings and memories.</ListItem><ListItem>How the parents <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cope</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the child has ongoing relationships with other adults.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_142"><KeyPoint id="_143">A child’s understanding of death and the events near death depend on their age and developmental stage.</KeyPoint><Para id="_219"><Strong>Infants</Strong></Para><Para id="_218">
Infants do not recognize death, but feelings of loss and separation are part of their awareness of death. Children who have been separated from their mother may be sluggish and quiet, may not respond to a smile or a coo, may have physical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> (such as weight loss), and may sleep less.</Para><Para id="_220"><Strong>Age 2-3 years</Strong></Para><Para id="_179">
Children at this age often confuse death with sleep and may feel <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> as early as age 3. They may stop talking and appear to feel overall <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_221"><Strong>Age 3-6 years</Strong></Para><Para id="_180">
At this age children see death as a kind of sleep; the person is alive, but only in a limited way. The child cannot fully separate death from life. Children may think that the person is still living, even though he or she might have been buried. The child may ask questions about the deceased (for example, how does the deceased eat, go to the bathroom, breathe, or play?). Young children know that death is physical, but think it is  not final. </Para><Para id="_231">A child may think death involves "magical thinking." For example, the child may think that his or her thoughts can cause another person to become sick or die.</Para><Para id="_232">Grieving children under 5 may have trouble eating, sleeping, and controlling their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_222"><Strong>Age 6-9 years</Strong></Para><Para id="_181">
Children at this age are often very curious about death and may ask what happens to the body when it dies. Death is thought of as a person or spirit separate from the person who was alive, such as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044221" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skeleton</GlossaryTermRef>, ghost, angel, or bogeyman. They may see death as final and scary but as something that happens mostly to old people (and not to themselves). </Para><Para id="_233">Grieving children can become afraid of school, have learning problems, show <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antisocial</GlossaryTermRef> or aggressive behavior, or become overly worried about their own health and complain of  imaginary symptoms. Children this age may either withdraw from others or become too attached and clingy.</Para><Para id="_235">Boys may become more aggressive and destructive (for example, acting out in school), instead of  showing their sadness openly. </Para><Para id="_236">When one parent dies, children may feel abandoned by both the deceased parent and the living parent, whose grief  may make him or her unable to emotionally support the child. 

</Para><Para id="_223"><Strong>Age 9 and older</Strong></Para><Para id="_182">Children aged 9 and older know that death cannot be avoided and do not see it as a punishment. By the time a child is 12 years old, death is seen as final and something that happens to everyone.</Para><Table id="_183"><Title>Grief and Developmental Stages</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="40.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="40.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Age </entry><entry> Understanding of Death </entry><entry> Expressions of Grief </entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">0-2 years</entry><entry>Is not yet able to understand death.</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Quietness, crankiness, decreased activity, poor sleep, and weight
           loss.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Separation from mother causes  changes. </entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="6">2-6 years</entry><entry MoreRows="3">Death is like sleeping.</entry><entry>Asks many questions (How does she go to the bathroom?  How does he eat?).</entry></Row><Row><entry>Problems with eating, sleeping, and bladder and bowel control.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Fear of being left alone.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Tantrums.</entry></Row><Row><entry> Dead person continues to live   
           and function in some ways.</entry><entry MoreRows="2">"Magical thinking" (Did I think  or do something that caused the death?  Like when I said I hate you and I wish you would die?).</entry></Row><Row><entry>Death is  not final.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dead person can come back to  life.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5">6-9 years</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Death is thought of as a       person or spirit (skeleton,    ghost, or bogeyman).  </entry><entry>Curious about death.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Asks specific questions.</entry></Row><Row><entry>May have  fears about
           school.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Death is final and scary. </entry><entry>May have aggressive behavior
           (especially boys).</entry></Row><Row><entry>Worries about imaginary 
           illnesses.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Death happens to others, but it    won’t happen to me.</entry><entry>May feel abandoned.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="8">9 and older</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Everyone will die. </entry><entry> Strong  emotions, guilt,       
           anger, shame. </entry></Row><Row><entry>Increased anxiety over own death.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Mood swings.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Death is final.</entry><entry>Fear of rejection; not wanting to
           be different from peers.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Even I will die.</entry><entry>Changes in eating habits.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sleeping problems.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Regressive behavior (loss of
           interest in outside activities).
           </entry></Row><Row><entry>Impulsive behavior.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Feels guilty about being alive
           (especially related to death of a
           sibling or peer).</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_184"><KeyPoint id="_185">There are three common worries children coping with a loss have about death.</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_247"><KeyPoint id="_248">Did I make the death  happen?</KeyPoint><Para id="_188">Children often think that they have "magical powers." If a mother is irritated and says, "You’ll be the death of me" and later dies, her child may wonder if he or she caused the mother’s death. Also, when children argue, one may say (or think), "I wish you were dead." If that child dies, the surviving child may think that those thoughts caused the death.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_249"><KeyPoint id="_250">Is it going to happen to me?
</KeyPoint><Para id="_189">The death of another child may be very hard for a child. If the child thinks that the death may have been prevented (by either a parent or a doctor) the child may fear that he or she could also die.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_251"><KeyPoint id="_252">Who is going to take care of me?</KeyPoint><Para id="_190">Since children depend on parents and other adults to take care of them, a grieving child may wonder who will care for him or her after the death of an important person.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_191"><KeyPoint id="_192">Talking honestly about the death and including the child in rituals may help the child cope with the loss.</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_237"><KeyPoint id="_238">Explain the death and answer questions.</KeyPoint><Para id="_209">
Talking about death helps children learn to cope with loss. When talking about death with children, describe it simply. Each child should be told the truth with as much detail as he or she is able to understand. Answer questions in a way the child can understand. 

</Para><Para id="_243">Children often worry that they will also die, or that their surviving parent will go away. They need to be told that they will be safe and taken care of. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_239"><KeyPoint id="_240">Use the correct language.</KeyPoint><Para id="_210">
When talking with the child  about death, include the correct words, such as "<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>," "died," and "death." Other phrases such as,  “he passed away,” “he is sleeping,” or “we lost him,” can confuse children. 

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_241"><KeyPoint id="_242">Include the child in planning and attending memorial services.</KeyPoint><Para id="_211">
When a death occurs, children may feel better if they are included in planning and attending memorial services. These events help children remember the loved one. Children should be encouraged to take part when they feel comfortable doing so and not be forced. Before a child attends a funeral, wake, or memorial service, give the child a full explanation of what to expect. A familiar adult or family member may help with this if the surviving parent's grief  makes him or her unable to. 
</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_194"><KeyPoint id="_195">There are books and other resources with information on helping a grieving child.</KeyPoint><Para id="_196">The following books and videos may be helpful  with grieving children:</Para><OrderedList id="_213" Style="Arabic"><ListItem> Worden JW: <Strong>Children and Grief: When a Parent Dies</Strong>. New York, NY: The Guilford
Press, 1996.</ListItem><ListItem>Doka KJ, ed.: <Strong>Children Mourning, Mourning Children</Strong>. Washington, DC: Hospice
Foundation of America, 1995.</ListItem><ListItem>Wass H, Corr CA: <Strong>Childhood and Death</Strong>. Washington, DC: Hemisphere Publishing
Corporation, 1984.</ListItem><ListItem>Corr CA, McNeil JN: <Strong>Adolescence and Death</Strong>. New York, NY: Springer Publishing
Company, 1986.
</ListItem><ListItem>Corr CA, Nabe CM, Corr DM: <Strong>Death and Dying, Life and Living</Strong>. 2nd ed.,
Pacific Grove: Brooks/Cole Publishing Company, 1997.
</ListItem><ListItem>Grollman EA: <Strong>Talking About Death: A Dialogue Between Parent and Child</Strong>. 3rd
ed., Boston, MA: Beacon Press, 1990.
</ListItem><ListItem>Schaefer D, Lyons C: <Strong>How Do We Tell the Children? Helping Children
Understand and Cope When Someone Dies</Strong>. New York, NY: Newmarket Press, 1988.
</ListItem><ListItem>Wolfelt A: <Strong>Helping Children Cope with Grief</Strong>. Muncie: Accelerated
Development, 1983.
</ListItem><ListItem>Walker A: <Strong>To Hell with Dying</Strong>. San Diego, CA: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1988.
</ListItem><ListItem>Williams M: <Strong>Velveteen Rabbit</Strong>. Garden City: Doubleday, 1922.</ListItem><ListItem>Viorst J: <Strong>The Tenth Good Thing About Barney</Strong>. New York, NY: Atheneum, 1971.
</ListItem><ListItem> Tiffault BW: <Strong>A Quilt for Elizabeth</Strong>. Omaha, NE: Centering Corporation, 1992.
</ListItem><ListItem>Levine JR: <Strong>Forever in My Heart: a Story to Help Children Participate in
Life as a Parent Dies</Strong>. Burnsville, NC: Mountain Rainbow Publications, 1992.
</ListItem><ListItem>Knoderer K: <Strong>Memory Book: a Special Way to Remember Someone You Love</Strong>.
Warminster, PA: Mar-Co Products, 1995.
</ListItem><ListItem>de Paola T: <Strong>Nana Upstairs and Nana Downstairs</Strong>. New York, NY: GP Putnam’s
Sons, 1973.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_259"><Title>To Learn More About Grief, Bereavement, and Loss</Title><Para id="_260">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> 
        about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grief</GlossaryTermRef>, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_261" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/feelings">Coping With Your Feelings During Advanced Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/self-care">Taking Care of Yourself</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about how individuals cope with grief, bereavement, and mourning.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Grief, Bereavement, and Loss. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/bereavement-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers/planning/bereavement-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389267]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062821"/><DateLastModified>2025-02-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
