<Summary id="CDR0000062849" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Neuroblastoma screening does not reduce the chance of dying from the disease. Not all screening tests are helpful and most have risks. Learn more about neuroblastoma and the potential benefits and harms of screening in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/neuroblastoma/patient/neuroblastoma-screening-pdq">Neuroblastoma (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/neuroblastoma/hp/neuroblastoma-screening-pdq">Neuroblastoma (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000042067">neuroblastoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_69">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about neuroblastoma screening. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_70">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>neuroblastoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Neuroblastoma Screening (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Neuroblastoma Screening</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Neuroblastoma Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>What is screening?</Title><Para id="_2"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Screening</GlossaryTermRef> is looking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> before a person has any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. This can help find cancer at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> or cancer is found early, it may be easier to treat. By the time symptoms appear, cancer may have begun to spread.</Para><Para id="_3"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> are trying to better understand which people are more likely to get certain types of cancer. They also study the things we do and the things around us to see if they cause cancer. This information helps doctors recommend who should be screened for cancer, which screening tests should be used, and how often the tests should be done.</Para><Para id="_4">It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily think you have cancer if he or she suggests a screening test. Screening tests are given when you have no cancer symptoms.</Para><Para id="_5">If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045959" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><Title>General Information About Neuroblastoma Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_10">Neuroblastoma is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form in nerve tissue.</KeyPoint><Para id="_11"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> often begins in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adrenal glands</GlossaryTermRef>. There are two adrenal glands, one on top of each <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>, in the back of the upper <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>. The adrenal glands make important <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef> that help control heart rate, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658770" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood sugar</GlossaryTermRef>, and the way the body reacts to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef>. Neuroblastoma may also begin in the abdomen,  chest, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>, or in nerve tissue near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef> in the neck.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000756627" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows parts of the body where neuroblastoma may be found, including the paraspinal nerve tissue and the adrenal glands. Also shown are the spine and right and left kidney." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_68"><Caption language="en">Neuroblastoma may be found in the adrenal glands and paraspinal nerve tissue from the neck to the pelvis.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_65">Neuroblastoma most often begins during early childhood, usually in children younger than 5 years of age.</Para><Para id="_66">For more information about neuroblastoma, see  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258023" url="/types/neuroblastoma/patient/neuroblastoma-treatment-pdq">Neuroblastoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_13">Most cases of neuroblastoma are
diagnosed before 1 year of age.
</KeyPoint><Para id="_57">Neuroblastoma is the most common type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> in infants.  The number of new
cases of neuroblastoma is greatest among children under 1 year of age. As children get older, the number of new cases 
decreases.  Neuroblastoma is slightly more common in males  than
females.
</Para><Para id="_14">Neuroblastoma sometimes forms before birth but is usually found later, when the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> begins to grow and cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. In rare cases, neuroblastoma may be found before birth by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046400" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fetal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_16">The risk factors for neuroblastoma are not known. 
</KeyPoint></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><Title>Neuroblastoma Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_20"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Screening methods</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_21">Tests are used to screen for different types of cancer when a person does not have symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_23"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests to find those with the fewest harms and most benefits. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> screening trials also are meant to show whether early detection (finding cancer before it causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>) helps a person live longer or decreases a person's chance of dying from the disease. For some types of cancer, the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef> is better if the disease is found and treated at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><KeyPoint id="_26">There is no standard or routine screening test for neuroblastoma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_58">There is no standard or routine screening test used to find <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>. A  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef> test is sometimes used  to check for  neuroblastoma,  usually when the child is 6 months old. This is a test in which urine is collected for 24 hours to measure the amounts of certain substances. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> that makes it. A higher than normal amount of homovanillic acid (HMA) and vanillyl mandelic acid (VMA) may be a sign of neuroblastoma. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><KeyPoint id="_63">Screening for neuroblastoma may not help the child live longer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_61">Studies have shown  that  screening for neuroblastoma does not decrease  the chance of dying from the
disease. Almost all neuroblastomas that are found by screening children at 6 months of age are the type that have a good <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> (chance of recovery).

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_71"><KeyPoint id="_72">Screening tests for neuroblastoma are being studied in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_71_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><Title>Risks of Neuroblastoma Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_43"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risks of screening</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_44">Screening tests have risks.</KeyPoint><Para id="_45">Decisions about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> tests can be difficult. Not all screening tests are helpful and most have risks. Before having any screening test, you may want to discuss the test with your doctor. It is important to know the risks of the test and whether it has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_46"><KeyPoint id="_47">The risks of neuroblastoma screening include the following:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_59"><KeyPoint id="_60"> Neuroblastoma may be overdiagnosed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_64"> When a screening test result leads to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment of a disease that may never have caused <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> or become life-threatening, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000759894" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overdiagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>. For example, when a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef> test result shows a higher than normal amount of homovanillic acid (HMA) or vanillyl mandelic acid (VMA), tests and treatments for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> are likely to be done, but may not be needed. At this time, it is not possible to know which neuroblastomas found by a screening test will cause symptoms and which neuroblastomas will not. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045959" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef> (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsies</GlossaryTermRef>) and cancer treatments (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>) can have serious risks, including physical and emotional problems.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><KeyPoint id="_49">False-negative test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_50">Screening test results may appear to be normal even though neuroblastoma is present. A person who receives a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-negative test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical care even if there are symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_51"><KeyPoint id="_52">False-positive test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_53">Screening test results may appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> even though no cancer is present. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-positive test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and is usually followed by more tests and procedures, which also have risks.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about neuroblastoma screening.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Neuroblastoma Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/neuroblastoma/patient/neuroblastoma-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/neuroblastoma/patient/neuroblastoma-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389302]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062795"/><DateLastModified>2023-07-24</DateLastModified></Summary>
