<Summary id="CDR0000062840" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Liver (hepatocellular) cancer screening, even in high risk individuals, has not been shown to be beneficial. Get detailed information about liver cancer screening, potential screening modalities, and research directions in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/hp/liver-screening-pdq">Liver (Hepatocellular)  Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038968">liver and intrahepatic biliary tract cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_95">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about liver (hepatocellular) cancer screening. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_96">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>liver and intrahepatic biliary tract cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Screening (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Screening (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Summary of Evidence</Title><Para id="_2">Note: The Summary of Evidence section summarizes the published evidence on this topic. The rest of the summary describes the evidence in more detail.</Para><Para id="_109">Other PDQ summaries on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062906" url="/types/liver/hp/adult-liver-treatment-pdq">Primary Liver Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef> and
<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062836" url="/types/liver/hp/child-liver-treatment-pdq">Childhood Liver Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef> are also available.
</Para><SummarySection id="_36"><Title>Benefits</Title><Para id="_37">Based on fair evidence,  screening of persons at elevated risk does not result in a decrease in mortality from hepatocellular cancer.</Para><Para id="_66"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: No reduction in mortality.</Para><ItemizedList id="_40" Style="simple"><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Randomized controlled trials.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Multiple studies, large number of participants.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><Title>Harms</Title><Para id="_39">Based on fair evidence, screening would result in rare but serious side effects associated with needle aspiration cytology such as needle-track seeding, particularly of lesions more than 2 cm in diameter, and hemorrhage, bile peritonitis, and pneumothorax.  Transjugular liver biopsy is rarely associated with major complications such as perforation of the hepatic capsule or cholangitis.</Para><Para id="_71"><Strong>Magnitude of Effect</Strong>: Good evidence for uncommon but serious harms.</Para><ItemizedList id="_67" Style="simple"><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Randomized controlled trials and observational studies.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Fair.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Multiple studies, large number of participants.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>Significance</Title><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>Incidence, Mortality, and Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_8">In 2022, liver cancer was the sixth most common cancer and third leading cause of cancer death in the world.<Reference refidx="1"/>  In the United States, liver cancer will cause an estimated 42,240 new cases and 30,090 deaths in 2025.<Reference refidx="2"/> There is a
distinct male preponderance among all ethnic groups in the United States.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_104">Chronic hepatitis B and C are recognized as the major
factors worldwide increasing the risk of hepatocellular cancer (HCC), with   risk being greater in the
presence of coinfection with hepatitis B virus and hepatitis C virus.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  The
incidence of HCC in individuals with chronic hepatitis is as high as 0.46% per
year.  In the United States, chronic hepatitis B and C account for about 30% to
40% of HCC.  Chronic hepatitis G infection is not associated with HCC in either
hepatitis B surface antigen–positive carriers or noncarriers.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_9">Cirrhosis is also a risk factor for HCC, irrespective of the etiology of the
cirrhosis.  The annual risk of developing HCC among individuals with cirrhosis is
between 1% and 6%.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Other risk factors include alcoholic cirrhosis,
hemochromatosis, alpha-l-antitrypsin deficiency, glycogen storage disease,
porphyria cutanea tarda, tyrosinemia, and Wilson disease,<Reference refidx="8"/> but rarely
biliary cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="9"/>  A retrospective case-control study found that features suggestive of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis, including obesity, type 2 diabetes, dyslipidemia, and insulin resistance, were more frequently observed in patients with HCC associated with cryptogenic cirrhosis than in those with HCC of viral or alcohol etiology.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> Aflatoxins,  which are  mycotoxins formed by certain   <ScientificName>Aspergillus </ScientificName> species, are
a frequent contaminant of improperly stored grains and nuts.  In parts of
Africa, the high incidence of HCC in humans may be related to ingestion of
foods contaminated with aflatoxins.   This association, however, is blurred by the
frequent coexistence of hepatitis B infection in those population groups.   The likely etiology of HCC is summarized in the following table.<Reference refidx="12"/>
</Para><Table id="_27"><Title> Likely Etiology of HCC</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><TBody><Row><entry><Strong>Causative Agents</Strong></entry><entry><Strong>Dominant Geographical Area</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry>Hepatitis B virus </entry><entry>Asia and  Africa</entry></Row><Row><entry>Hepatitis C virus </entry><entry>Europe, United States, and Japan</entry></Row><Row><entry>Alcohol</entry><entry>Europe and United States</entry></Row><Row><entry>Aflatoxins</entry><entry>East Asia and Africa</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="38572751">Bray F, Laversanne M, Sung H, et al.: Global cancer statistics 2022: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin 74 (3): 229-263, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="2">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Surveillance Research Program, National Cancer Institute: SEER*Explorer: An interactive website for SEER cancer statistics. 	Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statistics-network/explorer/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="7922998" MedlineID="95007381">Benvegnù L, Fattovich G, Noventa F, et al.: Concurrent hepatitis B and C virus infection and risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in cirrhosis. A prospective study. Cancer 74 (9): 2442-8, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7686879" MedlineID="93315129">Ikeda K, Saitoh S, Koida I, et al.: A multivariate analysis of risk factors for hepatocellular carcinogenesis: a prospective observation of 795 patients with viral and alcoholic cirrhosis. Hepatology 18 (1): 47-53, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="10326690" MedlineID="99256622">Chiaramonte M, Stroffolini T, Vian A, et al.: Rate of incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with compensated viral cirrhosis. Cancer 85 (10): 2132-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="11023453" MedlineID="20477975">Yuan JM, Govindarajan S, Gao YT, et al.: Prospective evaluation of infection with hepatitis G virus in relation to hepatocellular carcinoma in Shanghai, China. J Infect Dis 182 (5): 1300-3, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9755258" MedlineID="98429581">Di Bisceglie AM, Carithers RL, Gores GJ: Hepatocellular carcinoma. Hepatology 28 (4): 1161-5, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="7530737" MedlineID="95138453">Farinati F, Floreani A, De Maria N, et al.: Hepatocellular carcinoma in primary biliary cirrhosis. J Hepatol 21 (3): 315-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="12105842">Bugianesi E, Leone N, Vanni E, et al.: Expanding the natural history of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis: from cryptogenic cirrhosis to hepatocellular carcinoma. Gastroenterology 123 (1): 134-40, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="15508101">Fattovich G, Stroffolini T, Zagni I, et al.: Hepatocellular carcinoma in cirrhosis: incidence and risk factors. Gastroenterology 127 (5 Suppl 1): S35-50, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="12113033" MedlineID="22108434">Shiratori Y, Yoshida H, Omata M: Management of hepatocellular carcinoma: advances in diagnosis, treatment and prevention. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther 1 (2): 277-90, 2001.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>Evidence of Benefit</Title><SummarySection id="_11"><Title>Rationale for Screening</Title><Para id="_12">The rationale for screening for hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is based on the
concept that populations at high risk for HCC, such as those with cirrhosis,
can be identified.  However, 20% to 50% of patients presenting with HCC have
previously undiagnosed cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  These patients would not be recruited
into a surveillance program if the presence of cirrhosis is used to define a
target population.<Reference refidx="3"/>  The modalities potentially available for screening
include serum alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) and ultrasonography. 
 Abnormal screening results may lead to liver biopsy for diagnosis. Complications of liver biopsy are reported in 0.06% to 0.32% of patients, and typically occur within the first few hours after the biopsy. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_56"><Title>Tumor Markers for the Detection of Hepatocellular Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_57">Four categories of tumor markers are currently used or studied for the detection of hepatocellular carcinoma.  These categories include oncofetal antigens and glycoprotein antigens; enzymes and isoenzymes; genes; and cytokines.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><SummarySection id="_58"><Title>Alpha-fetoprotein</Title><Para id="_59">Serum AFP, a fetal-specific glycoprotein antigen, is the most widely used tumor marker for detecting HCC. The reported sensitivity of AFP for detecting  HCC varies widely in both
hepatitis B virus (HBV)-positive and HBV-negative populations, which is attributable to overlap
between screening and diagnosis study designs.<Reference refidx="3"/>  When AFP is used to screen
high-risk populations, a sensitivity of 39% to 97%, specificity of 76% to 95%,
and positive predictive value (PPV) of 9% to 32% have been reported.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> AFP is
not specific for HCC.  Titers also rise in acute or chronic hepatitis,<Reference refidx="10"/>
in pregnancy, and in the presence of germ cell tumors.
</Para><Para id="_60">A prospective, 16-year, population-based, observational study of screening for
HCC included 1,487 Alaska Native individuals chronically infected with
 HBV. The study compared survival among screen-detected patients with HCC with a
historical comparison group of clinically diagnosed patients with HCC.<Reference refidx="8"/>  The screening
program’s target was AFP determination every 6 months.  It achieved 97%
sensitivity and 95% specificity (excluding pregnant women) for HCC.  Such high
sensitivity and specificity have not been found for other high-risk groups,
such as individuals with cirrhosis.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>  Whether screening actually improved
survival is not clear.  </Para><Para id="_97">A case-control study conducted within the U.S. Veterans Affairs (VA) health care system assessed whether screening with AFP and/or ultrasound reduced HCC mortality.  The cases were 238 patients with cirrhosis who died of HCC from 2013 to 2015 and who had been in VA care with a diagnosis of cirrhosis for 4 years or more before the diagnosis of HCC.  The controls, who did not die of HCC and had also been in VA care for 4 years or more, were matched for date of <Strong>entry</Strong> (or focal time) and for age, sex, race, model for end-stage liver disease (MELD) score, and etiology of cirrhosis (mainly hepatitis C virus).  The study examiners, blinded to outcome status, used chart extraction to assess exposure to ultrasound and AFP screening.  The reason for testing (screening vs. other indication) was assessed, also blinded to outcome.  The study found no difference between cases and controls regarding the proportion of patients who underwent screening ultrasound (52.9% vs. 54.2%), AFP screening (74.8% vs. 73.5%), or both.  The lack of difference persisted for tests within 1, 2, or 3 years of the outcome.<Reference refidx="13"/>  Given the paucity of randomized controlled trials and their lack of strength, as noted elsewhere in this section, this case-control study—done with great care to avoid bias—represented perhaps the strongest evidence of the efficacy of AFP or ultrasound screening; however, it  showed no benefit in HCC mortality.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Hepatic Ultrasonography</Title><Para id="_17">Limitations in the sensitivity and specificity of AFP in surveillance of high-risk populations led to the use of ultrasonography  as an additional method for
detection of HCC.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Studies in both healthy hepatitis B
surface antigen carriers <Reference refidx="5"/> and in patients with cirrhosis <Reference refidx="7"/> have defined
the performance characteristics of ultrasound as a screening test for HCC. 
Sensitivity in the former was 71% and in the latter 78%, with 93% specificity. 
The PPVs were 14% and 73%, respectively.
In a study of patients who were on a waiting list for liver transplant, ultrasonography was found to have a sensitivity of 58%, specificity of 94%, negative predictive value of 91%, and PPV of 68%.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_98">A case-control study conducted in the VA population assessed whether screening with AFP and/or ultrasonography reduced HCC mortality. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062840#_58" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-screening-pdq">Alpha-fetoprotein</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><Title>Computed Tomography </Title><Para id="_19">Limitations in the sensitivity and specificity of AFP and  ultrasonography in
surveillance of high-risk populations, such as individuals with cirrhosis, led
to the assessment of computed tomography (CT) as an additional method for
detection of HCC.  Studies in patients with cirrhosis
suggest that CT may be a more sensitive test for HCC than ultrasonography or an AFP level of more than 20 μg/L.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><Title>Efficacy of Screening and Surveillance Programs</Title><Para id="_32">A controlled trial of 18,816 individuals aged 35 to 59 years with hepatitis B in Shanghai randomly assigned patients to a screening group using AFP and ultrasonography every 6 months versus a usual-care group. HCC mortality was lower in the screened group (83.2 vs. 131.5   per 100,000; mortality rate ratio of 0.63 [95% confidence interval (CI), 0.41–0.98]). While these results are promising, there were problems, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_92" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The results varied in different publications.<Reference refidx="15"/></ListItem><ListItem> The comparison group was not actively followed.</ListItem><ListItem>The CI was near 1.0.</ListItem><ListItem>Intention-to-treat analysis was not used.</ListItem><ListItem> Assessment of outcome was not blinded.</ListItem><ListItem>Generalizability to other populations is uncertain.<Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_41">A randomized controlled trial studied 5,581 men aged 30 to 69 years who were chronic carriers of HBV between 1989 and 1995 in Qidong, China.  Of these men, 3,712 were randomly assigned to a screening group and 1,869 to a control group.  Screening entailed six-monthly AFP assays, with follow-up of patients having an abnormal (≥20 μg/L) test result.  All patients were followed up for liver cancer and/or death.  The overall sensitivity and specificity of the program were 55.3% and 86.5%, respectively.  In patients who complied with all scheduled screening tests, sensitivity was 80% and specificity was 80.9%.  The mortality rate in the screening group (1,138 per 100,000 person-years) was not significantly different from that in the control group (1,114 per 100,000 person-years), although AFP screening resulted in an earlier diagnosis of liver cancer (i.e., percentage of cases in stage I was significantly higher in the screened group [29.0%] than in the control group [6%]).<Reference refidx="17"/> A  review concluded that the method of measuring AFP was not sensitive enough to detect HCC, affecting interpretation of the negative result of this trial.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2155700" MedlineID="90182557">Zaman SN, Johnson PJ, Williams R: Silent cirrhosis in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma. Implications for screening in high-incidence and low-incidence areas. Cancer 65 (7): 1607-10, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2155591" MedlineID="90179284">Primary liver cancer in Japan. Clinicopathologic features and results of surgical treatment. Liver Cancer Study Group of Japan. Ann Surg 211 (3): 277-87, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9425947" MedlineID="98085916">Collier J, Sherman M: Screening for hepatocellular carcinoma. Hepatology 27 (1): 273-8, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="16534867">Zhou L, Liu J, Luo F: Serum tumor markers for detection of hepatocellular carcinoma. World J Gastroenterol 12 (8): 1175-81, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7543434" MedlineID="95362166">Sherman M, Peltekian KM, Lee C: Screening for hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic carriers of hepatitis B virus: incidence and prevalence of hepatocellular carcinoma in a North American urban population. Hepatology 22 (2): 432-8, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="7506227" MedlineID="94102709">Oka H, Tamori A, Kuroki T, et al.: Prospective study of alpha-fetoprotein in cirrhotic patients monitored for development of hepatocellular carcinoma. Hepatology 19 (1): 61-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="7515408" MedlineID="94260083">Pateron D, Ganne N, Trinchet JC, et al.: Prospective study of screening for hepatocellular carcinoma in Caucasian patients with cirrhosis. J Hepatol 20 (1): 65-71, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11003632" MedlineID="20459038">McMahon BJ, Bulkow L, Harpster A, et al.: Screening for hepatocellular carcinoma in Alaska natives infected with chronic hepatitis B: a 16-year population-based study. Hepatology 32 (4 Pt 1): 842-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12820452">Soresi M, Magliarisi C, Campagna P, et al.: Usefulness of alpha-fetoprotein in the diagnosis of hepatocellular carcinoma. Anticancer Res 23 (2C): 1747-53, 2003 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="2478280" MedlineID="90030104">Di Bisceglie AM, Hoofnagle JH: Elevations in serum alpha-fetoprotein levels in patients with chronic hepatitis B. Cancer 64 (10): 2117-20, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="10520857" MedlineID="99449167">Chalasani N, Horlander JC, Said A, et al.: Screening for hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with advanced cirrhosis. Am J Gastroenterol 94 (10): 2988-93, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11110938" MedlineID="20564699">Peterson MS, Baron RL, Marsh JW, et al.: Pretransplantation surveillance for possible hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with cirrhosis: epidemiology and CT-based tumor detection rate in 430 cases with surgical pathologic correlation. Radiology 217 (3): 743-9, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29981779">Moon AM, Weiss NS, Beste LA, et al.: No Association Between Screening for Hepatocellular Carcinoma and Reduced Cancer-Related Mortality in Patients With Cirrhosis. Gastroenterology 155 (4): 1128-1139.e6, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="1326883">Dodd GD, Miller WJ, Baron RL, et al.: Detection of malignant tumors in end-stage cirrhotic livers: efficacy of sonography as a screening technique. AJR Am J Roentgenol 159 (4): 727-33, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="22972059">Aghoram R, Cai P, Dickinson JA: Alpha-foetoprotein and/or liver ultrasonography for screening of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with chronic hepatitis B. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 9: CD002799, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="15042359">Zhang BH, Yang BH, Tang ZY: Randomized controlled trial of screening for hepatocellular carcinoma. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 130 (7): 417-22, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="14738659">Chen JG, Parkin DM, Chen QG, et al.: Screening for liver cancer: results of a randomised controlled trial in Qidong, China. J Med Screen 10 (4): 204-9, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><Title>Evidence of Harms</Title><Para id="_77">Two kinds of harms or complications may result from screening. Direct harms may result from complications of liver biopsy done as part of the diagnostic workup. Such complications are reported in 0.06% to 0.32% of patients, and they typically occur within the first few hours after the biopsy. Complications include hemorrhage, bile peritonitis, penetration of viscera, and pneumothorax. Rarely, death occurs as a direct result of liver biopsy (0.009%–0.12%). About one third of patients experience pain at the site of entry, in the right upper quadrant, or in the right shoulder.<Reference refidx="1"/> Needle aspiration cytology and liver biopsy are rarely associated with needle-track implantation of malignant cells. Lead-time bias (earlier diagnosis in the natural
history of hepatocellular carcinoma [HCC] rather than improved survival from earlier diagnosis and
treatment), length bias (earlier detection of slower-growing and less
aggressive tumors through screening), and/or overdiagnosis of HCC (detection of
tumors that will not affect morbidity or mortality) may wholly or partially
account for the improved 5-year and 10-year survival rates reported.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="8542662" MedlineID="96127523">Tobkes AI, Nord HJ: Liver biopsy: review of methodology and complications. Dig Dis 13 (5): 267-74, 1995 Sep-Oct.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (04/30/2025)</Title><Para id="_26">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_111"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062840#_6" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-screening-pdq">Significance</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_112">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062840#_8" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-screening-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cases and deaths for 2025 (cited Bray et al. as reference 1 and American  Cancer Society as reference 2).</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062840#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/liver/hp/liver-screening-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about liver (hepatocellular) cancer screening. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Liver (Hepatocellular) Cancer Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/hp/liver-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/hp/liver-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389228]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-04-30</DateLastModified></Summary>
