<Summary id="CDR0000062841" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Ewing sarcoma treatment options include multidrug chemotherapy, surgery, and radiation therapy. Treatment approaches titrate therapeutic aggressiveness to maximizing local control while minimizing morbidity. Get detailed treatment information for Ewing sarcoma  and undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas of bone and soft tissue in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Ewing Sarcoma and Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas of Bone and Soft Tissue (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">Ewing Sarcoma and Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas of Bone and Soft Tissue (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000546979">Ewing sarcoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000546986">peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_614">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood Ewing sarcoma and undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas of bone and soft tissue. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_615">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Ewing sarcoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas of bone and soft tissue</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Ewing Sarcoma and Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas of Bone and Soft Tissue Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Ewing Sarcoma Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Ewing Sarcoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039466">Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor (PNET)</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Ewing Sarcoma and Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas of Bone and Soft Tissue</Title><Para id="_88">Dramatic improvements in survival have been achieved for children and adolescents with cancer.<Reference refidx="1"/> Between 1975 and 2020, childhood cancer mortality decreased by more than 50%.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> For Ewing sarcoma, the 5-year survival rate has increased from 59% to a range of 80% to 85% for children younger than 15 years and from 20% to 69% for adolescents aged 15 to 19 years.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  </Para><Para id="_187">Studies using immunohistochemical markers,<Reference refidx="4"/> cytogenetics,<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> molecular genetics, and tissue culture <Reference refidx="7"/> indicate that Ewing sarcoma originates from a primordial bone marrow–derived mesenchymal stem cell.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  Older terms such as peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor, Askin tumor (Ewing sarcoma of chest wall), and extraosseous Ewing sarcoma  (often combined in the term Ewing sarcoma family of tumors) refer to this same tumor. 
</Para><Para id="_1984">The World Health Organization (WHO) classification of tumors of soft tissue and bone was modified in 2020 to introduce a new chapter on undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas of bone and soft tissue. This WHO chapter consists of Ewing sarcoma and three main categories, including round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::non-ETS fusions, <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged sarcoma, and sarcomas with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> genetic alterations.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_1985">Before the widespread availability of genomic testing, Ewing sarcoma was identified by the appearance of small, round, blue cells on light microscopic examination, along with positive staining for CD99 by immunohistochemistry.  The identification of the recurring t(11;22) translocation in most Ewing sarcoma tumors led to the discovery that most tumors classified as Ewing sarcoma had a translocation that juxtaposed a portion of the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> gene to a portion of a gene in the ETS family, resulting in a transforming transcript.   Not all undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas of bone and soft tissue have such a translocation.  Further research identified additional genetic changes, including tumors with translocations of the <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene or the <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> gene.  These groups of tumors occur much less frequently than Ewing sarcoma, and data on these patients are based on smaller sample sizes and less homogeneous treatment; therefore, patient outcomes are harder to quantify with precision.  Most of these tumors have been treated with regimens designed for Ewing sarcoma, and the consensus was that they were often included in clinical trials for the treatment of Ewing sarcoma, sometimes  referred to as translocation-negative Ewing sarcoma.  It is now agreed that these tumors are sufficiently different from Ewing sarcoma and that they should be stratified and analyzed separately from Ewing sarcoma, even if they are treated with similar therapy.  In this summary, these tumors are described separately. For more information about these smaller groups of tumors, see the following sections:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2011" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1911" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas With <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> Genetic Alterations</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1916" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas With <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> Genetic Alterations</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2001" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas With <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::non-ETS Fusions</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_153"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_2521">In the United States between 2016 and 2020, the National Childhood Cancer Registry (NCCR) reported an incidence rate of Ewing sarcoma and related sarcomas of bone of 3.0 cases per 1 million in children and adolescents younger than 20 years.<Reference refidx="2"/> This incidence is unchanged from that reported between 1973 and 2004.<Reference refidx="11"/> The incidence rates by age groups in the U.S. pediatric population for Ewing sarcoma and related sarcomas of bone are shown in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2528" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2540" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Figure 1</SummaryRef>. While well-characterized cases of Ewing sarcoma in neonates and infants have been described, the incidence is low in infants and young children and then increases in adolescents.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Table id="_2528"><Title>Table 1.  5-Year Age-Adjusted Incidence Rates for Ewing Sarcoma by Age (2016–2020)<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Age (years)</entry><entry>Rate per 1,000,000</entry><entry>95% Confidence Interval</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Source: National Childhood Cancer Registry (NCCR) Explorer.<Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>&lt;1</entry><entry>0.5</entry><entry>0.2–1.1</entry></Row><Row><entry>1–4</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>0.7–1.3</entry></Row><Row><entry>5–9</entry><entry>2.3</entry><entry>1.9–2.6</entry></Row><Row><entry>10–14</entry><entry>4.3</entry><entry>3.9–4.9</entry></Row><Row><entry>15–19</entry><entry>4.5</entry><entry>4.0–5.0</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><MediaLink ref="CDR0000816650" type="image/jpeg" alt="Graph showing the incidence rates of Ewing tumor and related sarcomas of bone by age at diagnosis in the National Childhood Cancer Registry from 2016 to 2020." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_2540"><Caption language="en">Figure 1.  Incidence rates of Ewing tumor and related sarcomas of bone by age at diagnosis in the National Childhood Cancer Registry (NCCR) from 2016 to 2020. Credit: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics [Internet]. National Cancer Institute; 2023 Sep 7. [updated: 2023 Sep 8; cited 2024 Sep 4]. Available from: https://nccrexplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_616">The incidence of Ewing sarcoma in the United States is nine times greater in White people than in Black people, with an intermediate incidence in Asian people.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> The relative paucity of Ewing sarcoma in people of African or Asian descent may be explained, in part, by a specific polymorphism in the <GeneName>EGR2</GeneName> gene.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_125">Based on data from 1,426 patients entered on European Intergroup Cooperative Ewing Sarcoma Studies,  59% of patients are male and 41% are female.<Reference refidx="17"/>  These results match the 58%-to-42% male-to-female distribution in the United States (age &lt;20 years) in the NCCR dataset (3.5 and 2.5 cases per million incidence rate for males and females, respectively).<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2428"><Title>Genetic Predisposition to Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_2429">Conventional understanding of translocation-driven sarcoma such as Ewing sarcoma suggests that these patients do not have a genetic predisposition.<Reference refidx="18"/> A retrospective European-focused and panancestry case-controlled analysis was performed. The purpose of this study was to screen for enrichment of pathogenic germline variants in 141 known cancer predisposition genes in 1,147 pediatric patients diagnosed with sarcomas (226 Ewing sarcomas, 438 osteosarcomas, 180 rhabdomyosarcomas, and 303 other sarcomas), and compared the results to identically processed cancer-free control individuals. A distinct pattern of pathogenic germline variants was seen in Ewing sarcoma compared with other sarcoma types. <GeneName>FANCC</GeneName> was the only gene with an enrichment signal for heterozygous pathogenic variants in the European Ewing sarcoma discovery cohort (three individuals; odds ratio [OR], 12.6; 95% confidence interval [CI], 3.0–43.2; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003; false discovery rate, 0.40). This enrichment in <GeneName>FANCC</GeneName> heterozygous pathogenic variants was again observed in the European Ewing sarcoma validation cohort (three individuals; OR, 7.0; 95% CI, 1.7–23.6; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .014).</Para><Para id="_392">Genome-wide association studies have identified susceptibility loci for Ewing sarcoma at 1p36.22, 10q21, and 15q15.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/>  Deep sequencing through the 10q21.3 region identified a polymorphism in the <GeneName>EGR2</GeneName> gene, which appears to cooperate with and magnify the enhanced activity of the gene product of the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>FLI1</GeneName> fusion gene that is seen in most patients with Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="16"/>  The polymorphism associated with the increased risk is found at a much higher frequency in White people than in Black or Asian people, possibly contributing to the epidemiology of the relative infrequency of Ewing sarcoma in the latter populations. Three new susceptibility loci have been identified at 6p25.1, 20p11.22, and 20p11.23.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_377"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_2539">Clinical presentation of Ewing sarcoma varies and depends on the tumor’s size and location.</Para><Para id="_378">Primary sites of bone disease are listed in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2527" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Table id="_2527"><Title>Table 2.  Incidence Rates of Primary Sites of Bone Disease</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Primary Site</entry><entry>Incidence Rate</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry>Skull</entry><entry>5%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Spine</entry><entry>7%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Rib</entry><entry>11%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sternum, scapula, and clavicle</entry><entry>5%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Humerus</entry><entry>7%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Radius, ulna, hand</entry><entry>2%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Pelvis</entry><entry>18%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Femur</entry><entry>11%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Tibia, fibula, patella, foot</entry><entry>14%</entry></Row><Row><entry>Soft  tissue</entry><entry>19%</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_244">The time from the first symptom to diagnosis of Ewing sarcoma is often long, with a median interval reported from 2 to 5 months. Longer times are associated with older age and pelvic primary sites. Time from the first symptom to diagnosis has not been associated with metastasis, surgical outcome, or survival.<Reference refidx="22"/> </Para><Para id="_2523">Approximately 25% of patients with Ewing sarcoma have metastatic disease at the time of diagnosis, with lung, bone, and bone marrow being the most common metastatic sites.<Reference refidx="11"/> </Para><Para id="_2522">A retrospective analysis examined patients treated on two Children's Oncology Group (COG) studies, INT-0154 and <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00006734">AEWS0031 (NCT00006734)</ProtocolRef>. This study compared the clinical characteristics of 213 patients with extraskeletal primary Ewing sarcoma with those of 826 patients with primary Ewing sarcoma of bone.<Reference refidx="23"/> Patients with extraskeletal tumors were more likely to be non-White, have axial primary tumors, and have smaller tumors than patients with primary Ewing sarcoma of bone.</Para><Para id="_302">The Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program database was used to compare patients younger than 40  years  with Ewing sarcoma who presented with skeletal and extraosseous primary sites (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_304" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Table 3</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="24"/> Patients with extraosseous Ewing sarcoma were more likely to be older, female, of non-White race, and have axial primary sites, and they were less likely to have pelvic primary sites than were patients with skeletal Ewing sarcoma.</Para><Table id="_304"><Title>Table 3.  Characteristics of Patients With Extraosseous Ewing Sarcoma and Skeletal Ewing Sarcoma<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Characteristic</entry><entry>Extraosseous Ewing Sarcoma</entry><entry>Skeletal Ewing Sarcoma</entry><entry>	<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> Value</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Applebaum et al.<Reference refidx="24"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Mean age (range), years</entry><entry Align="Center">20 (0–39)</entry><entry Align="Center">16 (0–39)</entry><entry Align="Center">&lt;.001




</entry></Row><Row><entry>Male</entry><entry Align="Center">53%</entry><entry Align="Center">63%</entry><entry Align="Center">&lt;.001</entry></Row><Row><entry>White race</entry><entry Align="Center">85%</entry><entry Align="Center">93%</entry><entry Align="Center">&lt;.001</entry></Row><Row><entry>Axial primary sites</entry><entry Align="Center">73%</entry><entry Align="Center">54%</entry><entry Align="Center">&lt;.001</entry></Row><Row><entry>Pelvic primary sites
</entry><entry Align="Center">20%</entry><entry Align="Center">27%</entry><entry Align="Center">.001</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_607"><Title>Diagnostic Evaluation</Title><Para id="_20">The following tests and procedures may be used to diagnose or stage Ewing sarcoma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet">
    
    <ListItem>Physical examination and history.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of primary tumor site.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Computed tomography (CT) scan of chest.</ListItem>
    <ListItem>Positron emission tomography (PET) scan.</ListItem><ListItem>Bone scan. Bone scan was traditionally routinely performed on all patients with Ewing sarcoma for staging. However, many investigators believe that the PET scan can replace the bone scan.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/></ListItem><ListItem>Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy.</ListItem>
   <ListItem>X-ray of primary bone sites.</ListItem><ListItem>Complete blood count.</ListItem><ListItem>Blood chemistry studies, such as lactate dehydrogenase (LDH).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2449">Skip metastasis evaluation is important for primary appendicular bone tumors. Thus, imaging of the entire involved bone is standardly performed.  In one retrospective study, skip metastasis was seen in 15.8% of patients. The presence of skip metastasis was associated with an increased risk of distant metastatic disease.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_1822">  Omission of bone marrow biopsy and aspiration may be considered, when fluorine F 18-fludeoxyglucose (18F-FDG) PET imaging is used, in patients with otherwise localized disease after initial staging studies. A systematic review of Ewing sarcoma studies was performed  to assess the incidence of bone marrow metastasis  and the role of 18F-FDG PET imaging to detect bone marrow metastasis.<Reference refidx="28"/> The review reported a pooled incidence of bone marrow metastasis of 4.8% in all patients with newly diagnosed Ewing sarcoma and 17.5% in patients with metastatic disease. Only 1.2% of patients had bone marrow metastasis as their sole metastatic site. Compared with bone marrow biopsy and aspiration, 18F-FDG PET detection of bone marrow metastasis demonstrated pooled 100% sensitivity and 96% specificity, positive predictive value of 75%, and negative predictive value of 100%. For more information about diagnostic biopsy, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_28" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview for Ewing Sarcoma</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_154"><Title>Prognostic Factors</Title><Para id="_155">The two major types of prognostic factors for patients with Ewing sarcoma are grouped as follows: </Para><ItemizedList id="_321" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_156" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Pretreatment factors</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_158" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Response to initial therapy factors</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_156"><Title>Pretreatment factors</Title><ItemizedList id="_157" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Metastases:</Strong> The presence or absence of metastatic disease is the single most powerful predictor of outcome. Any metastatic disease defined by standard imaging techniques or bone marrow aspirate/biopsy by morphology is an adverse prognostic factor.  Metastases at diagnosis are detected in about  25% of patients.<Reference refidx="11"/> <Para id="_388">Patients with metastatic disease confined to the lung have a better prognosis than patients with extrapulmonary metastatic sites.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/> The number of pulmonary lesions does not seem to correlate with outcome, but patients with unilateral lung involvement have a better prognosis than patients with bilateral lung involvement.<Reference refidx="33"/></Para><Para id="_389">Patients with metastasis to only bone seem to have a better outcome than patients with metastases to both bone and lung.<Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/></Para><Para id="_390">Based on an analysis from the SEER database, regional lymph node involvement in patients is associated with an inferior overall outcome when compared with patients without regional lymph node involvement.<Reference refidx="36"/></Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Site of tumor:</Strong> Patients with Ewing sarcoma in the distal extremities have more favorable outcomes.  Patients with Ewing sarcoma in the proximal extremities have an intermediate prognosis, followed by patients with central or pelvic sites.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="37"/> However, a trial from the COG showed similar outcomes for patients with pelvic primary tumors compared with other sites.<Reference refidx="21"/><Para id="_2530">One study retrospectively analyzed a single-institution's experience with visceral Ewing sarcoma. The study focused on surgical management and compared the outcomes of patients with visceral Ewing sarcoma with those of patients with osseous and soft tissue Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="38"/> There were 156 patients with Ewing sarcoma identified: 117 osseous Ewing sarcomas, 20 soft tissue Ewing sarcomas, and 19 visceral Ewing sarcomas. Visceral Ewing sarcomas arose in the kidneys (n = 5), lungs (n = 5), intestines (n = 2), esophagus (n = 1), liver (n = 1), pancreas (n = 1), adrenal gland (n = 1), vagina (n = 1), brain (n = 1), and spinal cord (n = 1).  Visceral Ewing sarcoma was more frequently metastatic at presentation (63.2%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .005). However, there was no significant difference in overall survival (OS) or relapse-free survival among the Ewing sarcoma groups, with similar follow-up intervals.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>	Extraskeletal versus skeletal primary tumors:</Strong> The COG performed a retrospective analysis from two large cooperative trials that used similar treatment regimens.<Reference refidx="23"/> They identified 213 patients with extraskeletal primary tumors and 826 patients with skeletal primary tumors.  Patients with extraskeletal primary tumors were more likely to have an axial primary site, less likely to have large primary tumors, and had a statistically significant better prognosis than did patients with skeletal primary tumors.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Tumor size or volume:</Strong> Most studies have shown that tumor size or volume is an important prognostic factor.  Cutoffs of a volume of 100 mL or 200 mL and/or single dimension greater than 8 cm are used to define larger tumors.  Larger tumors tend to occur in unfavorable sites.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="39"/></ListItem> <ListItem><Strong>Age:</Strong> Younger patients generally have a better prognosis than older patients, as noted in the following studies:<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/> <ItemizedList id="_1820" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In North American studies, patients younger than 10 years had a better outcome than those aged 10 to 17 years at diagnosis (relative risk [RR], 1.4).  Patients older than 18 years had an inferior outcome (RR, 2.5).<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/></ListItem><ListItem>A retrospective review of two consecutive German trials for Ewing sarcoma identified 47 patients older than 40 years.<Reference refidx="46"/>  With adequate multimodal therapy, survival was comparable to the survival observed in adolescents treated on the same trials.</ListItem><ListItem>Review of the SEER database from 1973 to 2011 identified 1,957 patients with Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="47"/>  Thirty-nine of these patients (2.0%) were younger than 12 months at diagnosis.  Infants were less likely to receive radiation therapy and more likely to have soft tissue primary sites.  Early death was more common in infants, but the OS did not differ significantly from  that of older patients.</ListItem><ListItem>A European retrospective review  identified 2,635 patients with Ewing sarcoma of bone.<Reference refidx="48"/>  Sites of primary and metastatic tumors differed according to the age groups of young children (0–9 years), early adolescence (10–14 years), late adolescence (15–19 years), young adults (20–24 years), and adults (older than 24 years). Young children had the most striking differences in site of disease, with a lower proportion of pelvic primary and axial tumors. Young children also presented less often with metastatic disease at diagnosis.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Sex:</Strong> Females with Ewing sarcoma have a better prognosis than males with Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="37"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Serum LDH:</Strong> Increased serum LDH levels before treatment are associated with inferior prognosis.  Increased LDH levels are also associated with large primary tumors and metastatic disease.<Reference refidx="37"/></ListItem><ListItem> <Strong>Pathological fracture:</Strong> A single-institution retrospective analysis of 78 patients with Ewing sarcoma suggested that pathological fracture at initial presentation was associated with inferior event-free survival (EFS) and OS.<Reference refidx="49"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] Another study found that pathological fracture at the time of diagnosis did not preclude surgical resection and was not associated with an adverse outcome.<Reference refidx="50"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Previous treatment for cancer:</Strong> In the SEER database, 58 patients with Ewing sarcoma were diagnosed after treatment for a previous malignancy (2.1% of patients with Ewing sarcoma). These patients were compared with 2,756 patients with Ewing sarcoma as a first cancer over the same period.  Patients with Ewing sarcoma as a second malignant neoplasm were older (secondary Ewing sarcoma, mean age of 47.8 years; primary Ewing sarcoma, mean age of 22.5 years), more likely to have a primary tumor in an axial or extraskeletal site, and had a worse prognosis (5-year OS rates of 43.5% for patients with secondary Ewing sarcoma and 64.2% for patients with primary Ewing sarcoma).<Reference refidx="51"/> </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Chromosomal alterations:</Strong> <ItemizedList id="_1992" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Complex karyotype (defined as the presence of five or more independent chromosome abnormalities at diagnosis) and modal chromosome numbers lower than 50 appear to have adverse prognostic significance.<Reference refidx="52"/></ListItem><ListItem>Gain of chromosome 1q and/or deletion of chromosome 16q has been associated with inferior prognosis for patients with Ewing sarcoma in several cohorts.<Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/><Reference refidx="55"/> These two chromosomal alterations commonly occur together across a range of cancer types, including Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="56"/> Their co-occurrence is likely a result of their derivation from an unbalanced t(1;16) translocation resulting in gain of chromosome 1q together with loss of chromosomal material from 16q.<Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="58"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Detectable Ewing sarcoma cells, fusion transcripts, or circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) in peripheral blood:</Strong> Several techniques to evaluate the presence of Ewing sarcoma in the peripheral blood have been proposed.  Flow cytometry for cells that express the CD99 antigen was not sufficiently sensitive to serve as a reliable biomarker.<Reference refidx="59"/><Reference refidx="60"/>   Reverse transcriptase–polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) for the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>FLI1</GeneName> translocation was also not considered a reliable biomarker.<Reference refidx="61"/><Para id="_1821">A more sensitive technique used patient-specific primers designed after identification of the specific translocation breakpoint in combination with droplet digital PCR to detect the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> fusion. This technique reported a sensitivity threshold of 0.009% to 0.018%.<Reference refidx="62"/> Levels of circulating cell-free DNA were higher in patients with metastatic disease than in patients with localized disease.  </Para><Para id="_2525">A next-generation sequencing hybrid capture assay and an ultra-low-pass whole-genome sequencing assay were used to detect the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> fusion in ctDNA in banked plasma from patients with Ewing sarcoma.  Among patients with newly diagnosed localized Ewing sarcoma, detectable ctDNA was associated with inferior 3-year EFS rates (48.6% vs. 82.1%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006) and OS rates (79.8% vs. 92.6%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01).<Reference refidx="63"/> </Para><Para id="_2526">ctDNA was separately assayed by digital-droplet PCR in 102 patients who were treated in the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00987636">EWING2008 (NCT00987636)</ProtocolRef> trial.<Reference refidx="64"/> Pretreatment ctDNA copy numbers correlated with EFS and OS. A reduction in ctDNA levels below the detection limit was observed in most patients after only two blocks of vincristine, ifosfamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide (VIDE) induction chemotherapy. The persistence of ctDNA after two blocks of VIDE was a strong predictor of poor outcomes.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Detectable fusion transcripts in morphologically normal marrow:</Strong> RT-PCR can be used to detect fusion transcripts in bone marrow.  In a single retrospective study using patients with normal marrow morphology and no other metastatic site, fusion transcript detection in marrow or peripheral blood was associated with an increased risk of relapse.<Reference refidx="60"/> However, a larger cohort (n = 225) of patients with localized Ewing sarcoma did not show a difference in EFS or OS based on the detection of fusion transcripts in blood or bone marrow.<Reference refidx="65"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Gene alterations:</Strong> A prospective analysis of <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants and/or <GeneName>CDKN2A</GeneName> deletions was done in patients with Ewing sarcoma enrolled on COG clinical trials. The analysis found no association of these alterations with EFS.<Reference refidx="66"/><Para id="_1993">In a study of 299 patients with Ewing sarcoma, 41 patients (14%) had <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName> variants and 16 patients (5%) had <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants.<Reference refidx="55"/> There was no association with OS for patients with either the <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName> or <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variant alone. However, the nine patients (3%) with tumors that had both <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName> and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants had a significantly decreased OS rate (&lt;20% at 4 years).</Para><Para id="_2448">The COG analyzed STAG2 expression by immunohistochemistry in children with Ewing sarcoma who participated in frontline treatment trials.<Reference refidx="67"/> STAG2 was lost in 29 of 108 patients with localized disease and in 6 of 27 patients with metastatic disease. Among patients who had immunohistochemistry and sequencing performed, no  cases (0 of 17) with STAG2 expression had <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName> variants, and 2 of 7 cases with STAG2 loss had <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName> variants. Among patients with localized disease, the 5-year EFS rate was 54% (95% CI, 34%–70%) for those with STAG2 loss, compared with 75% (95% CI, 63%–84%) for those with STAG2 expression (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0034).</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_246">The following are <Strong>not</Strong> considered to be adverse prognostic factors for Ewing sarcoma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_247" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Histopathology: The degree of neural differentiation is not a prognostic factor in Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="68"/><Reference refidx="69"/></ListItem><ListItem>Fusion subtype: The <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::ETS translocation associated with Ewing sarcoma can occur at several potential breakpoints in each of the genes that join to form the novel segment of DNA. Once thought to be significant,<Reference refidx="70"/> two large series have shown that the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::ETS translocation breakpoint site is not an adverse prognostic factor.<Reference refidx="71"/><Reference refidx="72"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_158"><Title>Response to initial therapy factors</Title><Para id="_159">Multiple studies have shown that patients with minimal or no residual viable tumor after presurgical chemotherapy have a significantly better EFS than do patients with larger amounts of viable tumor.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="73"/><Reference refidx="74"/><Reference refidx="75"/><Reference refidx="76"/>; <Reference refidx="77"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>] In particular, patients with localized disease who have no viable tumor seen at the time of local-control surgery appear to have markedly favorable outcomes.<Reference refidx="21"/>; <Reference refidx="77"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>] Female sex and younger age predict a good histological response to preoperative therapy.<Reference refidx="78"/> For patients who receive preinduction- and postinduction-chemotherapy PET scans, decreased PET uptake after chemotherapy correlated with good histological response and  better outcome.<Reference refidx="79"/><Reference refidx="80"/><Reference refidx="81"/></Para><Para id="_391">Patients with poor response to presurgical chemotherapy have an increased risk of local recurrence.<Reference refidx="82"/></Para><Para id="_1951">A retrospective analysis of risk factors for recurrence was performed in patients who received initial chemotherapy and underwent surgical resection of the primary tumor.<Reference refidx="83"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]  Among 982 patients with a median follow-up of 7.6 years, the following was reported:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2397" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Adverse risk factors for local recurrence were pelvic primary tumors  (hazard ratio [HR], 2.04; 95% CI, 1.10–3.80) and  marginal/intralesional resection (HR, 2.28; 95% CI, 1.25–4.16). The addition of radiation therapy was associated with improved outcome (HR, 0.52; 95% CI, 0.28–0.95).  </ListItem><ListItem>Adverse risk factors for developing new pulmonary metastasis were less than 90% necrosis (HR, 2.13; 95% CI, 1.13–4.00) and previous pulmonary metastasis (HR, 4.90; 95% CI, 2.28–8.52).   </ListItem><ListItem>Adverse risk factors for death included pulmonary metastasis (HR, 8.08; 95% CI, 4.01–16.29), bone or other metastasis (HR, 10.23; 95% CI, 4.90–21.36), and less than 90% necrosis (HR, 6.35; 95% CI, 3.18–12.69). </ListItem><ListItem>Early local recurrence (0–24 months) negatively influenced survival (HR, 3.79; 95% CI, 1.34–10.76).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2520">In a retrospective cohort of 148 patients with pulmonary metastatic Ewing sarcoma, 41.2% had radiographic resolution of lung nodules after  initial induction chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="84"/> These patients had superior OS compared with patients who had residual nodules at end-induction (71.2% vs. 50.2% at 5 years). Particularly favorable outcomes were seen in the patients who had early clearance of lung nodules and received consolidative whole-lung radiation therapy (5-year OS rate, 85.2%).</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="24853691">Smith MA, Altekruse SF, Adamson PC, et al.: Declining childhood and adolescent cancer mortality. Cancer 120 (16): 2497-506, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="2">National Cancer Institute: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://NCCRExplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Surveillance Research Program, National Cancer Institute: SEER*Explorer: An interactive website for SEER cancer statistics. 	Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statistics-network/explorer/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="16528378">Olsen SH, Thomas DG, Lucas DR: Cluster analysis of immunohistochemical profiles in synovial sarcoma, malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumor, and Ewing sarcoma. Mod Pathol 19 (5): 659-68, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="8022439" MedlineID="94293971">Delattre O, Zucman J, Melot T, et al.: The Ewing family of tumors--a subgroup of small-round-cell tumors defined by specific chimeric transcripts. N Engl J Med 331 (5): 294-9, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11846300" MedlineID="21834863">Dagher R, Pham TA, Sorbara L, et al.: Molecular confirmation of Ewing sarcoma. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 23 (4): 221-4, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="1701108" MedlineID="91064697">Llombart-Bosch A, Carda C, Peydro-Olaya A, et al.: Soft tissue Ewing's sarcoma. Characterization in established cultures and xenografts with evidence of a neuroectodermic phenotype. Cancer 66 (12): 2589-601, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="19208848">Suvà ML, Riggi N, Stehle JC, et al.: Identification of cancer stem cells in Ewing's sarcoma. Cancer Res 69 (5): 1776-81, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="17482132">Tirode F, Laud-Duval K, Prieur A, et al.: Mesenchymal stem cell features of Ewing tumors. Cancer Cell 11 (5): 421-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="32960834">Choi JH, Ro JY: The 2020 WHO Classification of Tumors of Soft Tissue: Selected Changes and New Entities. Adv Anat Pathol 28 (1): 44-58, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="18525458">Esiashvili N, Goodman M, Marcus RB: Changes in incidence and survival of Ewing sarcoma patients over the past 3 decades: Surveillance Epidemiology and End Results data. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 30 (6): 425-30, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="18176172">Kim SY, Tsokos M, Helman LJ: Dilemmas associated with congenital ewing sarcoma family tumors. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 30 (1): 4-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="17635001">van den Berg H, Dirksen U, Ranft A, et al.: Ewing tumors in infants. Pediatr Blood Cancer 50 (4): 761-4, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="19548262">Jawad MU, Cheung MC, Min ES, et al.: Ewing sarcoma demonstrates racial disparities in incidence-related and sex-related differences in outcome: an analysis of 1631 cases from the SEER database, 1973-2005. Cancer 115 (15): 3526-36, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="22749036">Beck R, Monument MJ, Watkins WS, et al.: EWS/FLI-responsive GGAA microsatellites exhibit polymorphic differences between European and African populations. Cancer Genet 205 (6): 304-12, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="26214589">Grünewald TG, Bernard V, Gilardi-Hebenstreit P, et al.: Chimeric EWSR1-FLI1 regulates the Ewing sarcoma susceptibility gene EGR2 via a GGAA microsatellite. Nat Genet 47 (9): 1073-8, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="18802150">Paulussen M, Craft AW, Lewis I, et al.: Results of the EICESS-92 Study: two randomized trials of Ewing's sarcoma treatment--cyclophosphamide compared with ifosfamide in standard-risk patients and assessment of benefit of etoposide added to standard treatment in high-risk patients. J Clin Oncol 26 (27): 4385-93, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="35512711">Gillani R, Camp SY, Han S, et al.: Germline predisposition to pediatric Ewing sarcoma is characterized by inherited pathogenic variants in DNA damage repair genes. Am J Hum Genet 109 (6): 1026-1037, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="22327514">Postel-Vinay S, Véron AS, Tirode F, et al.: Common variants near TARDBP and EGR2 are associated with susceptibility to Ewing sarcoma. Nat Genet 44 (3): 323-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="30093639">Machiela MJ, Grünewald TGP, Surdez D, et al.: Genome-wide association study identifies multiple new loci associated with Ewing sarcoma susceptibility. Nat Commun 9 (1): 3184, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="34652968">Leavey PJ, Laack NN, Krailo MD, et al.: Phase III Trial Adding Vincristine-Topotecan-Cyclophosphamide to the Initial Treatment of Patients With Nonmetastatic Ewing Sarcoma: A Children's Oncology Group Report. J Clin Oncol 39 (36): 4029-4038, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="24841977">Brasme JF, Chalumeau M, Oberlin O, et al.: Time to diagnosis of Ewing tumors in children and adolescents is not associated with metastasis or survival: a prospective multicenter study of 436 patients. J Clin Oncol 32 (18): 1935-40, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="27297500">Cash T, McIlvaine E, Krailo MD, et al.: Comparison of clinical features and outcomes in patients with extraskeletal versus skeletal localized Ewing sarcoma: A report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 63 (10): 1771-9, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="21692057">Applebaum MA, Worch J, Matthay KK, et al.: Clinical features and outcomes in patients with extraskeletal Ewing sarcoma. Cancer 117 (13): 3027-32, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="32815877">Tal AL, Doshi H, Parkar F, et al.: The Utility of 18FDG PET/CT Versus Bone Scan for Identification of Bone Metastases in a Pediatric Sarcoma Population and a Review of the Literature. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 43 (2): 52-58, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="28965545">Costelloe CM, Chuang HH, Daw NC: PET/CT of Osteosarcoma and Ewing Sarcoma. Semin Roentgenol 52 (4): 255-268, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="36100697">Saifuddin A, Michelagnoli M, Pressney I: Skip metastases in appendicular Ewing sarcoma: relationship to distant metastases at diagnosis, chemotherapy response and overall survival. Skeletal Radiol 52 (3): 585-591, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="33219750">Campbell KM, Shulman DS, Grier HE, et al.: Role of bone marrow biopsy for staging new patients with Ewing sarcoma: A systematic review. Pediatr Blood Cancer 68 (2): e28807, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="10963639" MedlineID="20420055">Cotterill SJ, Ahrens S, Paulussen M, et al.: Prognostic factors in Ewing's tumor of bone: analysis of 975 patients from the European Intergroup Cooperative Ewing's Sarcoma Study Group. J Clin Oncol 18 (17): 3108-14, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="15254055">Miser JS, Krailo MD, Tarbell NJ, et al.: Treatment of metastatic Ewing's sarcoma or primitive neuroectodermal tumor of bone: evaluation of combination ifosfamide and etoposide--a Children's Cancer Group and Pediatric Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 22 (14): 2873-6, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="17569105">Rodríguez-Galindo C, Liu T, Krasin MJ, et al.: Analysis of prognostic factors in ewing sarcoma family of tumors: review of St. Jude Children's Research Hospital studies. Cancer 110 (2): 375-84, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="26257296">Karski EE, McIlvaine E, Segal MR, et al.: Identification of Discrete Prognostic Groups in Ewing Sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 63 (1): 47-53, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="9738574" MedlineID="98408954">Paulussen M, Ahrens S, Craft AW, et al.: Ewing's tumors with primary lung metastases: survival analysis of 114 (European Intergroup) Cooperative Ewing's Sarcoma Studies patients. J Clin Oncol 16 (9): 3044-52, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="9602261" MedlineID="98264971">Paulussen M, Ahrens S, Burdach S, et al.: Primary metastatic (stage IV) Ewing tumor: survival analysis of 171 patients from the EICESS studies. European Intergroup Cooperative Ewing Sarcoma Studies. Ann Oncol 9 (3): 275-81, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="20547982">Ladenstein R, Pötschger U, Le Deley MC, et al.: Primary disseminated multifocal Ewing sarcoma: results of the Euro-EWING 99 trial. J Clin Oncol 28 (20): 3284-91, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="22184129">Applebaum MA, Goldsby R, Neuhaus J, et al.: Clinical features and outcomes in patients with Ewing sarcoma and regional lymph node involvement. Pediatr Blood Cancer 59 (4): 617-20, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="16760184">Bacci G, Longhi A, Ferrari S, et al.: Prognostic factors in non-metastatic Ewing's sarcoma tumor of bone: an analysis of 579 patients treated at a single institution with adjuvant or neoadjuvant chemotherapy between 1972 and 1998. Acta Oncol 45 (4): 469-75, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="36774201">Wallace MW, Niec JA, Ghani MOA, et al.: Distribution and Surgical Management of Visceral Ewing Sarcoma Among Children and Adolescents. J Pediatr Surg 58 (9): 1727-1735, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="10064186">Ahrens S, Hoffmann C, Jabar S, et al.: Evaluation of prognostic factors in a tumor volume-adapted treatment strategy for localized Ewing sarcoma of bone: the CESS 86 experience. Cooperative Ewing Sarcoma Study. Med Pediatr Oncol 32 (3): 186-95, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="23382839">De Ioris MA, Prete A, Cozza R, et al.: Ewing sarcoma of the bone in children under 6 years of age. PLoS One 8 (1): e53223, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="27696711">Huh WW, Daw NC, Herzog CE, et al.: Ewing sarcoma family of tumors in children younger than 10 years of age. Pediatr Blood Cancer 64 (4): , 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="28964585">Ahmed SK, Randall RL, DuBois SG, et al.: Identification of Patients With Localized Ewing Sarcoma at Higher Risk for Local Failure: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 99 (5): 1286-1294, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="12594313" MedlineID="22482785">Grier HE, Krailo MD, Tarbell NJ, et al.: Addition of ifosfamide and etoposide to standard chemotherapy for Ewing's sarcoma and primitive neuroectodermal tumor of bone. N Engl J Med 348 (8): 694-701, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="19349548">Granowetter L, Womer R, Devidas M, et al.: Dose-intensified compared with standard chemotherapy for nonmetastatic Ewing sarcoma family of tumors: a Children's Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 27 (15): 2536-41, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="23091096">Womer RB, West DC, Krailo MD, et al.: Randomized controlled trial of interval-compressed chemotherapy for the treatment of localized Ewing sarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 30 (33): 4148-54, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="19060503">Pieper S, Ranft A, Braun-Munzinger G, et al.: Ewing's tumors over the age of 40: a retrospective analysis of 47 patients treated according to the International Clinical Trials EICESS 92 and EURO-E.W.I.N.G. 99. Onkologie 31 (12): 657-63, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="26173989">Wong T, Goldsby RE, Wustrack R, et al.: Clinical features and outcomes of infants with Ewing sarcoma under 12 months of age. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (11): 1947-51, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="29856530">Worch J, Ranft A, DuBois SG, et al.: Age dependency of primary tumor sites and metastases in patients with Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 65 (9): e27251, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="29656296">Schlegel M, Zeumer M, Prodinger PM, et al.: Impact of Pathological Fractures on the Prognosis of Primary Malignant Bone Sarcoma in Children and Adults: A Single-Center Retrospective Study of 205 Patients. Oncology 94 (6): 354-362, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="17698347">Bramer JA, Abudu AA, Grimer RJ, et al.: Do pathological fractures influence survival and local recurrence rate in bony sarcomas? Eur J Cancer 43 (13): 1944-51, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="22847990">Applebaum MA, Goldsby R, Neuhaus J, et al.: Clinical features and outcomes in patients with secondary Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (4): 611-5, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="18064647">Roberts P, Burchill SA, Brownhill S, et al.: Ploidy and karyotype complexity are powerful prognostic indicators in the Ewing's sarcoma family of tumors: a study by the United Kingdom Cancer Cytogenetics and the Children's Cancer and Leukaemia Group. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 47 (3): 207-20, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="12087464">Hattinger CM, Pötschger U, Tarkkanen M, et al.: Prognostic impact of chromosomal aberrations in Ewing tumours. Br J Cancer 86 (11): 1763-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="21822310">Mackintosh C, Ordóñez JL, García-Domínguez DJ, et al.: 1q gain and CDT2 overexpression underlie an aggressive and highly proliferative form of Ewing sarcoma. Oncogene 31 (10): 1287-98, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="25223734">Tirode F, Surdez D, Ma X, et al.: Genomic landscape of Ewing sarcoma defines an aggressive subtype with co-association of STAG2 and TP53 mutations. Cancer Discov 4 (11): 1342-53, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="9714002">Mrózek K, Bloomfield CD: Der(16)t(1;16) is a secondary chromosome aberration in at least eighteen different types of human cancer. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 23 (1): 78-80, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="3163262">Mugneret F, Lizard S, Aurias A, et al.: Chromosomes in Ewing's sarcoma. II. Nonrandom additional changes, trisomy 8 and der(16)t(1;16). Cancer Genet Cytogenet 32 (2): 239-45, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="8946192">Hattinger CM, Rumpler S, Ambros IM, et al.: Demonstration of the translocation der(16)t(1;16)(q12;q11.2) in interphase nuclei of Ewing tumors. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 17 (3): 141-50, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="19711435">Dubois SG, Epling CL, Teague J, et al.: Flow cytometric detection of Ewing sarcoma cells in peripheral blood and bone marrow. Pediatr Blood Cancer 54 (1): 13-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="12506175" MedlineID="22393562">Schleiermacher G, Peter M, Oberlin O, et al.: Increased risk of systemic relapses associated with bone marrow micrometastasis and circulating tumor cells in localized ewing tumor. J Clin Oncol 21 (1): 85-91, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="9495359">Zoubek A, Ladenstein R, Windhager R, et al.: Predictive potential of testing for bone marrow involvement in Ewing tumor patients by RT-PCR: a preliminary evaluation. Int J Cancer 79 (1): 56-60, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="29629425">Shukla NN, Patel JA, Magnan H, et al.: Plasma DNA-based molecular diagnosis, prognostication, and monitoring of patients with EWSR1 fusion-positive sarcomas. JCO Precis Oncol 2017: , 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="30131550">Shulman DS, Klega K, Imamovic-Tuco A, et al.: Detection of circulating tumour DNA is associated with inferior outcomes in Ewing sarcoma and osteosarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Br J Cancer 119 (5): 615-621, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="34426444">Krumbholz M, Eiblwieser J, Ranft A, et al.: Quantification of Translocation-Specific ctDNA Provides an Integrating Parameter for Early Assessment of Treatment Response and Risk Stratification in Ewing Sarcoma. Clin Cancer Res 27 (21): 5922-5930, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="26861456">Vo KT, Edwards JV, Epling CL, et al.: Impact of Two Measures of Micrometastatic Disease on Clinical Outcomes in Patients with Newly Diagnosed Ewing Sarcoma: A Report from the Children's Oncology Group. Clin Cancer Res 22 (14): 3643-50, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="25464386">Lerman DM, Monument MJ, McIlvaine E, et al.: Tumoral TP53 and/or CDKN2A alterations are not reliable prognostic biomarkers in patients with localized Ewing sarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (5): 759-65, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="36221002">Shulman DS, Chen S, Hall D, et al.: Adverse prognostic impact of the loss of STAG2 protein expression in patients with newly diagnosed localised Ewing sarcoma: A report from the Children's Oncology Group. Br J Cancer 127 (12): 2220-2226, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="10452503" MedlineID="99379572">Parham DM, Hijazi Y, Steinberg SM, et al.: Neuroectodermal differentiation in Ewing's sarcoma family of tumors does not predict tumor behavior. Hum Pathol 30 (8): 911-8, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="10363075" MedlineID="99291254">Luksch R, Sampietro G, Collini P, et al.: Prognostic value of clinicopathologic characteristics including neuroectodermal differentiation in osseous Ewing's sarcoma family of tumors in children. Tumori 85 (2): 101-7, 1999 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="9552022" MedlineID="98211748">de Alava E, Kawai A, Healey JH, et al.: EWS-FLI1 fusion transcript structure is an independent determinant of prognosis in Ewing's sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 16 (4): 1248-55, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="20308669">van Doorninck JA, Ji L, Schaub B, et al.: Current treatment protocols have eliminated the prognostic advantage of type 1 fusions in Ewing sarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 28 (12): 1989-94, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="20308673">Le Deley MC, Delattre O, Schaefer KL, et al.: Impact of EWS-ETS fusion type on disease progression in Ewing's sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor: prospective results from the cooperative Euro-E.W.I.N.G. 99 trial. J Clin Oncol 28 (12): 1982-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="11251014" MedlineID="21150333">Paulussen M, Ahrens S, Dunst J, et al.: Localized Ewing tumor of bone: final results of the cooperative Ewing's Sarcoma Study CESS 86. J Clin Oncol 19 (6): 1818-29, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="10430250" MedlineID="99357319">Rosito P, Mancini AF, Rondelli R, et al.: Italian Cooperative Study for the treatment of children and young adults with localized Ewing sarcoma of bone: a preliminary report of 6 years of experience. Cancer 86 (3): 421-8, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="75" PMID="9698007" MedlineID="98361472">Wunder JS, Paulian G, Huvos AG, et al.: The histological response to chemotherapy as a predictor of the oncological outcome of operative treatment of Ewing sarcoma. J Bone Joint Surg Am 80 (7): 1020-33, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="11742482" MedlineID="21607627">Oberlin O, Deley MC, Bui BN, et al.: Prognostic factors in localized Ewing's tumours and peripheral neuroectodermal tumours: the third study of the French Society of Paediatric Oncology (EW88 study). Br J Cancer 85 (11): 1646-54, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="36305090">Lozano-Calderón SA, Albergo JI, Groot OQ, et al.: Complete tumor necrosis after neoadjuvant chemotherapy defines good responders in patients with Ewing sarcoma. Cancer 129 (1): 60-70, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="17551396">Ferrari S, Bertoni F, Palmerini E, et al.: Predictive factors of histologic response to primary chemotherapy in patients with Ewing sarcoma. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 29 (6): 364-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="79" PMID="16314643">Hawkins DS, Schuetze SM, Butrynski JE, et al.: [18F]Fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography predicts outcome for Ewing sarcoma family of tumors. J Clin Oncol 23 (34): 8828-34, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="80" PMID="20505933">Denecke T, Hundsdörfer P, Misch D, et al.: Assessment of histological response of paediatric bone sarcomas using FDG PET in comparison to morphological volume measurement and standardized MRI parameters. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging 37 (10): 1842-53, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="81" PMID="27645694">Palmerini E, Colangeli M, Nanni C, et al.: The role of FDG PET/CT in patients treated with neoadjuvant chemotherapy for localized bone sarcomas. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging 44 (2): 215-223, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="82" PMID="17177205">Lin PP, Jaffe N, Herzog CE, et al.: Chemotherapy response is an important predictor of local recurrence in Ewing sarcoma. Cancer 109 (3): 603-11, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="83" PMID="31389188">Bosma SE, Rueten-Budde AJ, Lancia C, et al.: Individual risk evaluation for local recurrence and distant metastasis in Ewing sarcoma: A multistate model: A multistate model for Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 66 (11): e27943, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="84" PMID="38679864">Reiter AJ, Huang L, Craig BT, et al.: Survival outcomes in pediatric patients with metastatic Ewing sarcoma who achieve a rapid complete response of pulmonary metastases. Pediatr Blood Cancer 71 (7): e31026, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039466">Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor (PNET)</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular Classification of Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_16"> Ewing sarcoma belongs to the group of neoplasms
commonly referred to as small round blue cell tumors of childhood.  The individual cells of Ewing sarcoma contain round-to-oval nuclei, with fine dispersed chromatin without nucleoli. Occasionally, cells with smaller, more hyperchromatic, and probably degenerative nuclei are present, giving a light cell/dark cell pattern. The cytoplasm varies in amount, but in the classic case, it is clear and contains glycogen, which can be highlighted with a periodic acid-Schiff stain. The tumor cells are tightly packed and grow in a diffuse pattern without evidence of structural organization. Tumors with the requisite translocation that show neuronal differentiation are not considered a separate entity, but rather, part of a continuum of differentiation.</Para><Para id="_323">CD99 is a surface membrane protein that is expressed in most
cases of   Ewing sarcoma and is useful in   diagnosing these tumors when the results are interpreted in the context of clinical and
pathological parameters.<Reference refidx="1"/> CD99  positivity is not unique to Ewing sarcoma, and
positivity by immunochemistry is found in several other tumors, including
synovial sarcoma, non-Hodgkin lymphoma,  and gastrointestinal stromal tumors. NKX2.2 is a nuclear antigen that is also commonly assessed by immunohistochemistry to support a diagnosis of Ewing sarcoma, although it is also not 100% specific for this diagnosis.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_2009">For more information about the cellular classification of other undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1910" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Undifferentiated Small Round Cell (Ewing-Like) Sarcomas</SummaryRef> section.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10452503" MedlineID="99379572">Parham DM, Hijazi Y, Steinberg SM, et al.: Neuroectodermal differentiation in Ewing's sarcoma family of tumors does not predict tumor behavior. Hum Pathol 30 (8): 911-8, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="22446943">Yoshida A, Sekine S, Tsuta K, et al.: NKX2.2 is a useful immunohistochemical marker for Ewing sarcoma. Am J Surg Pathol 36 (7): 993-9, 2012.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_624"><Title>Genomics of Ewing Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000777838_13"><Title>Molecular Features of Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000777838_15">The World Health Organization identifies the presence of a gene fusion involving <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> or <GeneName>FUS</GeneName> and a gene in the ETS family  as a defining element of Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="1"/> The <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> gene located on chromosome 22 band q12 is a member of the FET family (<GeneName>FUS</GeneName>, <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>, <GeneName>TAF15</GeneName>) of RNA-binding proteins.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Characteristically, the amino terminus of the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>
gene is juxtaposed with the carboxy terminus of a gene from the ETS family of DNA-binding transcription factors (see Table 4). The <GeneName>FLI1</GeneName> gene located on chromosome 11 band q24 is a member of the ETS family and is the ETS family fusion partner for <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> in 85% to 90% of pediatric cases of Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> 
Other ETS family members  that may combine with the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> gene are <GeneName>ERG</GeneName>, <GeneName>ETV1</GeneName>, <GeneName>ETV4</GeneName>, and <GeneName>FEV</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="6"/>  Rarely, <GeneName>FUS</GeneName>, another FET family member, can substitute for <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="7"/> Finally, there are a few rare cases in which <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> has translocated with partners that are not members of the ETS family of oncogenes. These tumors are thought to be distinct from Ewing sarcoma and are discussed separately. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1910" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Undifferentiated Small Round Cell (Ewing-Like) Sarcomas</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000777838_1898">The <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>FLI1</GeneName> translocation associated with Ewing sarcoma can occur at several potential breakpoints in each of the genes that join to form the novel segment of DNA. Once thought to be significant,<Reference refidx="8"/> two large series have shown that the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>FLI1</GeneName> translocation breakpoint site is not an adverse prognostic factor.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000777838_387">Besides the 
consistent aberrations involving the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> gene, secondary numerical
and structural chromosomal aberrations are observed in most cases of Ewing sarcoma. Chromosome gains are more common than chromosome losses, and structural chromosome imbalances are also observed.<Reference refidx="11"/> Two of the more common chromosome aberrations are those involving chromosome 8 or chromosomes 1 and 16.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000777838_1899" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Gain of whole chromosome 8 (trisomy 8).</Strong> Trisomy 8 is the most frequent chromosomal alteration in Ewing sarcoma, occurring in nearly 50% of tumors.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Gain of chromosome 8 does not appear to have prognostic significance.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Gain of chromosome 1q and loss of chromosome 16q.</Strong> These occur in approximately 20% of patients and often occur together.  Gain of chromosome 1q and/or deletion of chromosome 16q has been associated with inferior prognosis for patients with Ewing sarcoma in several cohorts.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> These two chromosomal alterations commonly occur together across a range of cancer types, including Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="15"/> Their co-occurrence is likely a result of their derivation from an unbalanced t(1;16) translocation resulting in gain of chromosome 1q together with loss of chromosomal material from 16q.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000777838_388">The genomic landscape of Ewing sarcoma is characterized by a relatively silent genome, with a paucity of variants in pathways that might be amenable to treatment with novel targeted therapies.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Recurring genomic alterations are described below. For some of these genomic alterations, claims of prognostic significance have been made. However, these claims need to be viewed cautiously because of the relatively small size of most studies, the low frequency of many of the genomic alterations, the variable use of tumor tissue from diagnosis versus relapse specimens, and the need to consider clinical prognostic factors such as tumor size and the presence of metastatic disease.</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000777838_1894" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>STAG2</GeneName> variants.</Strong> Variants in  <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName>, a member of the cohesin complex, occur in about 15% to 20% of the cases.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> These variants lead to loss of STAG2 expression and function in tumor cells.<Reference refidx="5"/> Loss of STAG2 expression (detected by immunohistochemistry [IHC]) has been observed in tumors in which a <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName> variant cannot be detected. In one report, loss of STAG2 expression by IHC was associated with inferior prognosis.<Reference refidx="17"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>CDKN2A</GeneName> deletions.</Strong> <GeneName>CDKN2A</GeneName> deletions have been noted in 12% to 22% of cases.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> </ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants.</Strong> <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants were identified in about 6% to 7% of Ewing sarcoma cases reported by pediatric research teams.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Higher rates of <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants (up to 19%) have been described in cohorts from single institutions that contain higher proportions of adult patients.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/> The coexistence of <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName> and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants has been associated with a  poor clinical outcome in one retrospective report.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>ERF</GeneName> alterations.</Strong> Genomic alterations in <GeneName>ERF</GeneName> leading to loss of function (frameshift, missense, and deep deletion) were reported in 7% of Ewing sarcoma tumors.<Reference refidx="18"/> A second report observed <GeneName>ERF</GeneName> alterations at a rate of 3% in another Ewing sarcoma cohort.<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Other genes with recurring genomic alterations in Ewing sarcoma.</Strong> Recurring genomic alterations present in fewer than 5% of Ewing sarcoma patients were reported: <GeneName>EZH2,</GeneName><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="19"/> <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>,<Reference refidx="3"/> <GeneName>SMARCA4,</GeneName><Reference refidx="19"/> <GeneName>CREBBP</GeneName>,<Reference refidx="19"/> <GeneName>TERT</GeneName>, and <GeneName>FGFR1</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="18"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000777838_390">Ewing sarcoma translocations can all be found with standard cytogenetic analysis.  A fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization (FISH) rapid analysis looking for a break apart of the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> gene is now frequently done to confirm the diagnosis of Ewing sarcoma molecularly.<Reference refidx="20"/> This test result must be considered with caution, however.  Ewing sarcomas that harbor <GeneName>FUS</GeneName> translocations will have negative tests because the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> gene is not translocated in those cases.  In addition, other small round tumors also contain translocations of different ETS family members with <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>, such as desmoplastic small round cell tumor, clear cell sarcoma, extraskeletal myxoid chondrosarcoma, and myxoid liposarcoma, all of which may be positive with a <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> FISH break-apart probe.   A detailed analysis of 85 patients with small round blue cell tumors that were negative for <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> rearrangement by FISH (with an <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> break-apart probe) identified eight patients with <GeneName>FUS</GeneName> rearrangements.<Reference refidx="21"/>  Four patients who had <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>ERG</GeneName> fusions were not detected by FISH with an <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> break-apart probe.  The authors do not recommend relying solely on <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> break-apart probes for analyzing small round blue cell tumors with strong immunohistochemical positivity for CD99. Next-generation sequencing assays, including dedicated fusion panels, are now commonly used in the evaluation of these tumors.</Para><Table id="_sm_CDR0000777838_386"><Title>Table 4.  <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> and <GeneName>FUS</GeneName> Fusions and Translocations in Ewing Sarcoma</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="15.77%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="35.96%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="23.02%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.23%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">FET Family Partner		</entry><entry Align="Center">Fusion With ETS-Like Oncogene Partner	</entry><entry Align="Center">Translocation</entry><entry Align="Center">Comment</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>These partners  are not members of the ETS family of oncogenes; therefore, these tumors are not classified as Ewing sarcoma.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="9"><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName></entry><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>FLI1</GeneName></entry><entry>t(11;22)(q24;q12)</entry><entry>Most common; approximately 85% to 90% of cases</entry></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>ERG</GeneName></entry><entry>t(21;22)(q22;q12)</entry><entry>Second most common; approximately 10% of cases</entry></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>ETV1</GeneName></entry><entry>t(7;22)(p22;q12)</entry><entry>Rare</entry></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>ETV4</GeneName></entry><entry>t(17;22)(q12;q12)</entry><entry>Rare</entry></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>FEV</GeneName></entry><entry>t(2;22)(q35;q12)</entry><entry>Rare</entry></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName><Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>t(20;22)(q13;q12)</entry><entry>Rare</entry></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>POU5F1</GeneName><Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>t(6;22)(p21;q12)</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>SMARCA5</GeneName><Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>t(4;22)(q31;q12)</entry><entry>Rare</entry></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>PATZ1</GeneName><Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>t(6;22)(p21;q12)</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>SP3</GeneName><Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>t(2;22)(q31;q12)</entry><entry>Rare</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"><GeneName>FUS</GeneName></entry><entry><GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>ERG</GeneName></entry><entry>t(16;21)(p11;q22)</entry><entry>Rare</entry></Row><Row><entry><GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>FEV</GeneName></entry><entry>t(2;16)(q35;p11)</entry><entry>Rare</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board: WHO Classification of Tumours. Volume 3: Soft Tissue and Bone Tumours. 5th ed., IARC Press, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25494299">Schwartz JC, Cech TR, Parker RR: Biochemical Properties and Biological Functions of FET Proteins. Annu Rev Biochem 84: 355-79, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25223734">Tirode F, Surdez D, Ma X, et al.: Genomic landscape of Ewing sarcoma defines an aggressive subtype with co-association of STAG2 and TP53 mutations. Cancer Discov 4 (11): 1342-53, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25186949">Crompton BD, Stewart C, Taylor-Weiner A, et al.: The genomic landscape of pediatric Ewing sarcoma. Cancer Discov 4 (11): 1326-41, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="25010205">Brohl AS, Solomon DA, Chang W, et al.: The genomic landscape of the Ewing Sarcoma family of tumors reveals recurrent STAG2 mutation. PLoS Genet 10 (7): e1004475, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="10451705" MedlineID="99381012">Hattinger CM, Rumpler S, Strehl S, et al.: Prognostic impact of deletions at 1p36 and numerical aberrations in Ewing tumors. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 24 (3): 243-54, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21872822">Sankar S, Lessnick SL: Promiscuous partnerships in Ewing's sarcoma. Cancer Genet 204 (7): 351-65, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9552022" MedlineID="98211748">de Alava E, Kawai A, Healey JH, et al.: EWS-FLI1 fusion transcript structure is an independent determinant of prognosis in Ewing's sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 16 (4): 1248-55, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="20308669">van Doorninck JA, Ji L, Schaub B, et al.: Current treatment protocols have eliminated the prognostic advantage of type 1 fusions in Ewing sarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 28 (12): 1989-94, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20308673">Le Deley MC, Delattre O, Schaefer KL, et al.: Impact of EWS-ETS fusion type on disease progression in Ewing's sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor: prospective results from the cooperative Euro-E.W.I.N.G. 99 trial. J Clin Oncol 28 (12): 1982-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="18064647">Roberts P, Burchill SA, Brownhill S, et al.: Ploidy and karyotype complexity are powerful prognostic indicators in the Ewing's sarcoma family of tumors: a study by the United Kingdom Cancer Cytogenetics and the Children's Cancer and Leukaemia Group. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 47 (3): 207-20, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="8946192">Hattinger CM, Rumpler S, Ambros IM, et al.: Demonstration of the translocation der(16)t(1;16)(q12;q11.2) in interphase nuclei of Ewing tumors. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 17 (3): 141-50, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="12087464">Hattinger CM, Pötschger U, Tarkkanen M, et al.: Prognostic impact of chromosomal aberrations in Ewing tumours. Br J Cancer 86 (11): 1763-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="21822310">Mackintosh C, Ordóñez JL, García-Domínguez DJ, et al.: 1q gain and CDT2 overexpression underlie an aggressive and highly proliferative form of Ewing sarcoma. Oncogene 31 (10): 1287-98, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="9714002">Mrózek K, Bloomfield CD: Der(16)t(1;16) is a secondary chromosome aberration in at least eighteen different types of human cancer. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 23 (1): 78-80, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="3163262">Mugneret F, Lizard S, Aurias A, et al.: Chromosomes in Ewing's sarcoma. II. Nonrandom additional changes, trisomy 8 and der(16)t(1;16). Cancer Genet Cytogenet 32 (2): 239-45, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="36221002">Shulman DS, Chen S, Hall D, et al.: Adverse prognostic impact of the loss of STAG2 protein expression in patients with newly diagnosed localised Ewing sarcoma: A report from the Children's Oncology Group. Br J Cancer 127 (12): 2220-2226, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="35952322">Ogura K, Elkrief A, Bowman AS, et al.: Prospective Clinical Genomic Profiling of Ewing Sarcoma: ERF and FGFR1 Mutations as Recurrent Secondary Alterations of Potential Biologic and Therapeutic Relevance. JCO Precis Oncol 6: e2200048, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="37888109">Rock A, Uche A, Yoon J, et al.: Bioinformatic Analysis of Recurrent Genomic Alterations and Corresponding Pathway Alterations in Ewing Sarcoma. J Pers Med 13 (10): , 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="10078922">Monforte-Muñoz H, Lopez-Terrada D, Affendie H, et al.: Documentation of EWS gene rearrangements by fluorescence in-situ hybridization (FISH) in frozen sections of Ewing's sarcoma-peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor. Am J Surg Pathol 23 (3): 309-15, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="26690869">Chen S, Deniz K, Sung YS, et al.: Ewing sarcoma with ERG gene rearrangements: A molecular study focusing on the prevalence of FUS-ERG and common pitfalls in detecting EWSR1-ERG fusions by FISH. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 55 (4): 340-9, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039466">Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor (PNET)</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_2529">Pretreatment staging studies for Ewing sarcoma may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_393" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the primary site.</ListItem><ListItem>Computed tomography (CT) scan of the primary site and chest.</ListItem><ListItem>Positron emission tomography using fluorine F 18-fludeoxyglucose (18F-FDG PET) or 18F-FDG PET-CT.</ListItem><ListItem>Bone scan has traditionally been part of the staging evaluation for Ewing sarcoma. However, many investigators believe that PET scan can replace bone scan.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem>Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_131">For patients with confirmed Ewing sarcoma, pretreatment staging studies include MRI  and/or CT scan, depending on the primary site. Despite the fact that CT and MRI are both equivalent in terms of staging, use of both imaging modalities may help radiation therapy planning.<Reference refidx="3"/> Whole-body MRI may provide additional information that could potentially alter therapy planning.<Reference refidx="4"/> Additional pretreatment staging studies include bone scan and CT scan of the chest.  In certain studies, determination of pretreatment tumor volume is an important variable.</Para><Para id="_308">18F-FDG PET-CT scans have demonstrated high sensitivity and specificity in Ewing sarcoma and are now routinely used to complete staging. In one institutional study, 18F-FDG PET had a very high correlation with bone scan; the investigators suggested that it could replace bone scan for the initial extent of disease evaluation.<Reference refidx="5"/> This finding was confirmed in a single-institution retrospective review.<Reference refidx="6"/> 18F-FDG PET-CT is more accurate than 18F-FDG PET alone in Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_381">Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy have been considered the standard of care for Ewing sarcoma.  However, two retrospective studies showed that for patients (N = 141) who were evaluated by bone scan and/or PET scan and lung CT without evidence of metastases,  bone marrow aspirates and biopsies were negative in every case.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="10"/>  A single-institution retrospective review of 504 patients with Ewing sarcoma identified 12 patients with bone marrow metastasis.<Reference refidx="11"/>  Only one patient was found to have bone marrow involvement without any other sites of metastatic disease, for an incidence of 1 per 367 (0.3%) in patients with clinically localized disease.  The need for routine use of bone marrow aspirates and biopsies in patients without bone metastases is now in question.</Para><Para id="_132">For Ewing sarcoma, tumors are practically staged as localized or metastatic, and other staging systems are not commonly used. The tumor is defined as localized when, by clinical and imaging techniques, there is no spread beyond the primary site or regional lymph node involvement.  Continuous extension into adjacent soft tissue may occur. If there is a question of regional lymph node involvement, pathological confirmation is indicated.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="28965545">Costelloe CM, Chuang HH, Daw NC: PET/CT of Osteosarcoma and Ewing Sarcoma. Semin Roentgenol 52 (4): 255-268, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="32815877">Tal AL, Doshi H, Parkar F, et al.: The Utility of 18FDG PET/CT Versus Bone Scan for Identification of Bone Metastases in a Pediatric Sarcoma Population and a Review of the Literature. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 43 (2): 52-58, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="18454470">Meyer JS, Nadel HR, Marina N, et al.: Imaging guidelines for children with Ewing sarcoma and osteosarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group Bone Tumor Committee. Pediatr Blood Cancer 51 (2): 163-70, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15243716">Mentzel HJ, Kentouche K, Sauner D, et al.: Comparison of whole-body STIR-MRI and 99mTc-methylene-diphosphonate scintigraphy in children with suspected multifocal bone lesions. Eur Radiol 14 (12): 2297-302, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="23192939">Newman EN, Jones RL, Hawkins DS: An evaluation of [F-18]-fluorodeoxy-D-glucose positron emission tomography, bone scan, and bone marrow aspiration/biopsy as staging investigations in Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (7): 1113-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24660717">Ulaner GA, Magnan H, Healey JH, et al.: Is methylene diphosphonate bone scan necessary for initial staging of Ewing sarcoma if 18F-FDG PET/CT is performed? AJR Am J Roentgenol 202 (4): 859-67, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="18048826">Völker T, Denecke T, Steffen I, et al.: Positron emission tomography for staging of pediatric sarcoma patients: results of a prospective multicenter trial. J Clin Oncol 25 (34): 5435-41, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="18006618">Gerth HU, Juergens KU, Dirksen U, et al.: Significant benefit of multimodal imaging: PET/CT compared with PET alone in staging and follow-up of patients with Ewing tumors. J Nucl Med 48 (12): 1932-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="22072239">Treglia G, Salsano M, Stefanelli A, et al.: Diagnostic accuracy of ¹⁸F-FDG-PET and PET/CT in patients with Ewing sarcoma family tumours: a systematic review and a meta-analysis. Skeletal Radiol 41 (3): 249-56, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="25174337">Kopp LM, Hu C, Rozo B, et al.: Utility of bone marrow aspiration and biopsy in initial staging of Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (1): 12-5, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="30724024">Cesari M, Righi A, Colangeli M, et al.: Bone marrow biopsy in the initial staging of Ewing sarcoma: Experience from a single institution. Pediatr Blood Cancer 66 (6): e27653, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039466">Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor (PNET)</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_1823"> It is important that patients be evaluated by specialists from the appropriate disciplines (e.g.,
medical oncologists, surgical or orthopedic oncologists, and
radiation oncologists) as early as possible. Multidisciplinary review with radiologists and pathologists is often performed at sarcoma specialty centers.</Para><Para id="_29">Appropriate imaging studies of the suspected primary site are obtained before biopsy. To ensure that the biopsy incision is placed in an acceptable location, the surgical or orthopedic
oncologist (who will perform the definitive surgery) is consulted on biopsy-incision placement.  This
is especially important if it is thought that the lesion can subsequently be totally excised after initial systemic therapy
or if a limb salvage procedure may be attempted.  It is almost never appropriate to attempt a primary resection of known Ewing sarcoma at initial diagnosis.  With rare exceptions, Ewing sarcoma is sensitive to chemotherapy and will respond to initial systemic therapy. This therapy reduces the risk of tumor spread to surrounding tissues and  makes ultimate surgery easier and safer.  Biopsy should be from soft tissue as often as possible to avoid increasing the risk of fracture.<Reference refidx="1"/> If the initial biopsy sample is obtained from bone, reserving some tissue without decalcification is required because decalcification denatures DNA and makes genomic profiling of tumor tissue impossible.<Reference refidx="2"/> The pathologist is consulted before biopsy/surgery to ensure
that the incision will not compromise the radiation port and that multiple
types of adequate tissue samples are obtained. It is important to obtain fresh tissue, whenever possible, for cytogenetics and molecular pathology. A second option is to perform a needle biopsy, as long as adequate tissue is obtained for molecular studies.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_608"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_604" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Table 5</SummaryRef> describes the treatment options for localized, metastatic, and recurrent Ewing sarcoma.</Para><Table id="_604"><Title>Table 5.  Standard Treatment Options for Ewing Sarcoma</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="28.49%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="12.95%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="58.54%"/><THead><Row><entry>Treatment Group</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Standard Treatment Options</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Localized Ewing sarcoma</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_410" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_413" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Local-control measures</SummaryRef>:</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_415" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_422" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef> </entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1811" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">High-dose chemotherapy with autologous stem cell rescue</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Metastatic Ewing sarcoma</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_430" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_433" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_433" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Recurrent Ewing sarcoma</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_447" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef> (not considered standard treatment)</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1987" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef> (not considered standard treatment)</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_451" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef> (not considered standard treatment)</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1854" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">High-dose chemotherapy with stem cell support</SummaryRef> (not considered standard treatment)</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_452" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Other therapies</SummaryRef> (not considered standard treatment)</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_133">The successful treatment of patients with Ewing sarcoma requires systemic chemotherapy <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> in conjunction with surgery and/or radiation therapy for local tumor control.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>   In general, patients receive chemotherapy before instituting local-control measures.  In patients who undergo surgery, surgical margins and histological response are considered in planning postoperative therapy.  Patients with metastatic disease often have a good initial response to preoperative chemotherapy, but in most cases, the disease is only partially controlled or recurs.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/>  Patients with lung as the only metastatic site have a better prognosis than do patients with metastases to bone and/or bone marrow.  Adequate local control for metastatic sites, particularly bone metastases, may be an important consideration.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><SummarySection id="_134"><Title>Chemotherapy for Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_135">Multidrug chemotherapy for Ewing sarcoma always includes vincristine, doxorubicin, ifosfamide, and etoposide.  Most protocols also use cyclophosphamide and some incorporate dactinomycin.  The mode of administration and dose intensity of cyclophosphamide within courses differs markedly between protocols. A European Intergroup Cooperative Ewing Sarcoma Study (EICESS)  trial suggested that 1.2 g of cyclophosphamide produced a similar event-free survival (EFS) compared with 6 g of ifosfamide in patients with lower-risk disease. The trial also identified a trend toward better EFS for patients with localized Ewing sarcoma and higher-risk disease when treatment included etoposide (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00002516">GER-GPOH-EICESS-92 [NCT00002516]</ProtocolRef>).<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </Para><Para id="_394">Protocols in the United States generally alternate courses of vincristine, cyclophosphamide, and doxorubicin (VDC) with courses of ifosfamide and etoposide (IE),<Reference refidx="8"/> using interval compression.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/> For many years, European protocols generally combined vincristine, doxorubicin, and an alkylating agent with or without etoposide in a single treatment cycle.<Reference refidx="10"/> After the completion of the  randomized EURO EWING 2012 (EE2012) trial (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_396" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">below</SummaryRef>), European investigators shifted to therapy with cycles of VDC alternating with cycles of IE.<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] The duration of primary chemotherapy ranges from 6 months to approximately 1 year.  </Para><Para id="_395">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_396" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>An international consortium of European countries conducted the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00020566">EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 (NCT00020566)</ProtocolRef> trial from 2000 to 2010.<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  All patients received induction therapy with six cycles of vincristine, ifosfamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide (VIDE), followed by local control, and then one cycle of vincristine, dactinomycin, and ifosfamide (VAI). Patients were classified as standard risk if they had localized disease and good histological response to therapy or if they had localized tumors less than 200 mL in volume at presentation; they were treated with radiation therapy alone as local treatment. Standard-risk patients (n = 856) were randomly assigned to receive maintenance therapy with either seven cycles of vincristine, dactinomycin, and cyclophosphamide (VAC) or VAI. <ItemizedList id="_397" Style="bullet"><ListItem>There was no significant difference in EFS or overall survival (OS) between patients who received VAC  and patients who received VAI.</ListItem><ListItem>The 3-year EFS rate for this low-risk population was 77%.</ListItem><ListItem>It is difficult to compare this outcome with that of other large series because the study population excluded patients with poor response to initial therapy or patients with tumors more than 200 mL in volume who received local-control therapy with radiation alone. All other published series report results for all patients who present without clinically detectable metastasis; thus, these other series included patients with poor response and patients with larger primary tumors treated with radiation alone, all of whom were excluded from the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a Children's Oncology Group (COG) study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00006734">COG-AEWS0031 [NCT00006734]</ProtocolRef>), patients presenting without metastases were randomly assigned to receive cycles of VDC alternating with cycles of  IE at either 2-week or 3-week intervals.<Reference refidx="24"/><ItemizedList id="_1824" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The administration of cycles of VDC/IE at 2-week intervals achieved superior EFS  (5-year EFS rate, 73%) than did alternating cycles at  3-week intervals (5-year EFS rate, 65%). With longer follow-up, the advantage of interval-compressed chemotherapy was confirmed.<Reference refidx="25"/></ListItem><ListItem> The 10-year EFS rate was 70% using interval-compressed chemotherapy, compared with 61% using standard-timing chemotherapy (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03). The 10-year OS rate was 76% using interval-compressed chemotherapy, compared with 69% using standard-timing chemotherapy (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .04).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The EE2012 trial was an international multicenter phase III study that included two randomized treatments, the European VIDE induction regimen and the North American standard VDC/IE induction regimen.  Patients with both localized and metastatic Ewing sarcoma were eligible for the study.<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_1981" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The hazard ratios (HRs) for EFS (0.71) and OS (0.62) favored VDC/IE over VIDE. The posterior probabilities were 99% for both EFS and OS, which  showed that VDC/IE was superior.</ListItem><ListItem>Rates of febrile neutropenia were higher with the VIDE regimen. There were no other major differences in acute toxicities between the two regimens.</ListItem><ListItem>The benefit of VDC/IE over VIDE was seen across subgroups defined by patient age, sex, stage, tumor volume, or country of residence.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The Brazilian Cooperative Study Group performed a multi-institutional trial that incorporated carboplatin into a risk-adapted intensive regimen in 175 children with localized or metastatic Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_1825" Style="bullet"><ListItem> The investigators found significantly increased toxicity without an improvement in outcome with the addition of carboplatin.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The COG performed a prospective randomized trial in patients with localized Ewing sarcoma.  All patients received cycles of VDC and cycles of IE. Patients were then randomly assigned to receive or not receive additional experimental cycles of vincristine, cyclophosphamide, and topotecan.<Reference refidx="26"/><ItemizedList id="_2017" Style="bullet"><ListItem>  The 5-year EFS rate was 78% (95% confidence interval [CI], 72%–82%) for those treated with experimental therapy and 79% (95% CI, 74%–83%) for patients treated with standard therapy. </ListItem><ListItem>The experimental therapy did not significantly reduce the risk of events (EFS HR for experimental arm vs. standard arm, 0.86; 1-sided <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .19).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><Title>Local Control (Surgery and Radiation Therapy) for Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_326">Treatment approaches for Ewing sarcoma and therapeutic aggressiveness must be adjusted to maximize local control while also minimizing morbidity. </Para><Para id="_457">Surgery is the most commonly used form of local control.<Reference refidx="30"/> Radiation therapy is an effective alternative modality for local control in cases where the functional or cosmetic morbidity of surgery is deemed too high by experienced surgical oncologists. However, in the immature skeleton, radiation therapy can cause subsequent deformities that may be more morbid than deformities from surgery. When complete surgical resection with pathologically negative margins is not anticipated, surgery is not typically performed, and definitive radiation is used instead. When pathologically positive margins are found, then postoperative radiation therapy is indicated. A multidisciplinary discussion between the experienced radiation oncologist and the surgeon is necessary to determine the best treatment options for local control for a given case. For some marginally resectable lesions, a combined approach of preoperative radiation therapy followed by resection can be used.</Para><Para id="_1954">Timing of local control may impact outcome.  A retrospective review from the National Cancer Database identified 1,318 patients with Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="31"/>  Patients who initiated local therapy at 6 to 15 weeks had a 5-year OS rate of 78.7% and a 10-year OS rate of 70.3%, and patients who initiated local therapy after 16 weeks had a 5-year OS rate of 70.4% and a 10-year OS rate of 57.1% (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). The difference in OS according to time to local therapy was more important in patients who received radiation therapy alone.</Para><Para id="_1908">For patients with metastatic Ewing sarcoma, any benefit of combined surgery and radiation therapy compared with either therapy alone for local control is relatively less substantial because the overall prognosis of these patients is much worse than the prognosis of patients who have localized disease.</Para><Para id="_398">Randomized trials that directly compare surgery and radiation therapy do not exist, and their relative roles remain controversial.  Although retrospective institutional series suggest better local control and survival with surgery than with radiation therapy, most of these studies are compromised by selection bias. An analysis using propensity scoring to adjust for clinical features that may influence the preference for surgery only, radiation only, or combined surgery and radiation demonstrated that similar EFS is achieved with each mode of local therapy.<Reference refidx="30"/> Data for patients with pelvic primary Ewing sarcoma from a North American intergroup trial showed no difference in local control or survival based on local-control modality—surgery alone, radiation therapy alone, or surgery plus radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="32"/></Para><Para id="_1953">The <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00020566">EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 (NCT00020566)</ProtocolRef> trial prospectively treated 180 patients with pelvic primary tumors without clinically detectable metastatic disease.<Reference refidx="33"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]  A retrospective analysis of outcomes for these patients showed improved survival for patients whose tumors were treated with combined radiation therapy and surgery.  The study did not prospectively define criteria for the selection of local-control modalities, and the investigators did not have access to information that would allow them to clarify how decisions for local-control modalities were made.  In nonsacral tumors, combined local treatment was associated with a lower local recurrence probability (14% [95% CI, 5%–23%] vs. 33% [95% CI, 19%–47%] at 5 years; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .015) and a higher OS probability (72% [95% CI, 61%–83%] vs. 47% [95% CI, 33%–62%] at 5 years; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .024), compared with surgery alone.  Even in a subgroup of patients with wide surgical margins and a good histological response to induction treatment, the combined local treatment was associated with a higher OS probability (87% [95% CI, 74%–100%] vs. 51% [95% CI, 33%–69%] at 5 years; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .009), compared with surgery alone.  In patients with bone tumors who underwent surgical treatment—after controlling for tumor site in the pelvis, tumor volume, and surgical margin status—those who did not undergo complete   removal of the affected bone (HR, 5.04; 95% CI, 2.07–12.24; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001), those with a poor histological response to induction chemotherapy (HR, 3.72; 95% CI, 1.51–9.21; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .004), and those who did not receive additional radiation therapy (HR, 4.34; 95% CI, 1.71–11.05; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002) had a higher risk of death.</Para><Para id="_172">For patients who undergo gross-total resection with microscopic residual disease, a radiation therapy dose of 50.4 Gy is recommended. For patients treated with primary radiation therapy, the radiation dose is 55.8 Gy (45 Gy to the initial tumor volume and an additional 10.8 Gy to the postchemotherapy volume).<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="34"/></Para><Para id="_399">Evidence (postoperative radiation therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_400" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Investigators from St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital reported 39 patients with localized Ewing sarcoma who received both surgery and radiation.<Reference refidx="14"/><ItemizedList id="_401" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The local failure rate for patients with positive margins was 17%, and the OS rate was 71%.</ListItem><ListItem>The local failure rate for patients with negative margins was 5%, and the OS rate was 94%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a large retrospective Italian study, 45 Gy of adjuvant radiation therapy for patients with inadequate margins did not appear to improve either local control or disease-free survival (DFS).<Reference refidx="15"/><ItemizedList id="_2535" Style="bullet"><ListItem>    These investigators concluded that patients who are anticipated to have suboptimal surgery should be considered for definitive radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00020566">EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 (NCT00020566)</ProtocolRef> study reported the outcomes of 599 patients who presented with localized disease and had surgical resection after initial chemotherapy with at least 90% necrosis of the primary tumor.<Reference refidx="34"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]    The protocol recommended postoperative radiation therapy  for patients with inadequate surgical margins, vertebral primary tumors, or thoracic tumors with pleural effusion, but the decision to use postoperative radiation therapy was left to the institutional investigator.<ItemizedList id="_648" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Patients who received postoperative radiation therapy (n = 142) had a lower risk of failure than patients who did not receive postoperative radiation therapy, even after controlling for known prognostic factors, including age, sex, tumor site, clinical response, quality of resection, and histological necrosis.  Most of the improvement was seen in a decreased risk of local recurrence.  The improvement was greater in patients who had large tumors (&gt;200 mL) and were assessed to have 100% necrosis than in patients who were assessed to have 90% to 100% necrosis.</ListItem><ListItem>There is a clear interaction between systemic therapy and local-control modalities for both local control and DFS.  The induction regimen used in the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study is less intense than the induction regimen used in contemporaneous protocols in the COG, and it is not appropriate to extrapolate the results from the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study to different systemic chemotherapy regimens.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_1922"><Title>Thoracic primary tumors</Title><Para id="_1923">Evidence (surgery):</Para><OrderedList id="_1924" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The treatment and outcomes for 62 patients with thoracic Ewing sarcoma were reported from the Cooperative Weichteilsarkom Studiengruppe CWS-81, -86, -91, -96, and -2002P trials.<Reference refidx="35"/><ItemizedList id="_1909" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year OS rate was 58.7% (95% CI, 52.7%–64.7%), and the EFS rate was 52.8% (95% CI, 46.8%–58.8%).</ListItem><ListItem>Patients with intrathoracic tumors (n = 24) had a worse outcome (EFS rate, 37.5% [95% CI, 27.5%–37.5%]) than patients with chest wall tumors (n = 38; EFS rate, 62.3% [95% CI, 54.3%–70.3%]; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .008).</ListItem><ListItem>Patients aged 10 years and younger (n = 38) had a better survival (EFS rate, 65.7% [95% CI, 57.7%–73.7%]) than patients older than 10 years (EFS rate, 31.3% [95% CI, 21.3%–41.3%]; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01).</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor size of less than or equal to 5 cm (n = 15) was associated with significantly better survival (EFS rate, 93.3% [95% CI, 87.3%–99.3%]), compared with a tumor size greater than  5 cm (n = 47; EFS rate, 40% [95% CI, 33%–47%]; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002).</ListItem><ListItem>Primary resections were carried out in 36 patients, 75% of which were incomplete, resulting in inferior EFS (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006).</ListItem><ListItem>Complete secondary resections were performed in 22 of 40 patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The COG reviewed its results for 98 patients with chest wall tumors who were treated on the INT-0091 and INT-0154 trials from 1988 to 1998 and found the following:<Reference refidx="36"/><ItemizedList id="_1952" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year EFS rate was 56%.</ListItem><ListItem>Negative margins were more common in patients who received initial chemotherapy and then underwent resections (41 of 53 patients, 77%) than in patients who had up-front surgery (10 of 20 patients, 50%).  </ListItem><ListItem>More patients who underwent up-front surgery received radiation therapy (71%) than patients  who started with chemotherapy  (48%).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Para id="_173">In summary, surgery is chosen as definitive local therapy for suitable patients, but radiation therapy is appropriate for patients with unresectable disease or those who would experience functional or cosmetic compromise by definitive surgery. The possibility of impaired function or cosmesis needs to be measured against the possibility of second tumors in the radiation field.  Adjuvant radiation therapy should be considered for patients with residual microscopic disease or inadequate margins.</Para><Para id="_268">When preoperative assessment has suggested a high probability that surgical margins will be close or positive, preoperative radiation therapy has achieved tumor shrinkage and allowed surgical resection with clear margins.<Reference refidx="37"/></Para><Para id="_1826">Multiple analyses have evaluated diagnostic findings, treatment, and outcome of patients with bone lesions at the following anatomical primary sites: </Para><ItemizedList id="_1827" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Pelvis.<Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Femur.<Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Humerus.<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/></ListItem><ListItem>Hand and foot.<Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Chest wall/rib.<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Head and neck.<Reference refidx="50"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Spine/sacrum.<Reference refidx="51"/><Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>High-Dose Chemotherapy With Stem Cell Support for Ewing Sarcoma </Title><Para id="_139">For patients with a high risk of relapse with conventional treatments, some investigators have used high-dose chemotherapy with hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) as consolidation treatment, in an effort to improve outcome.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="55"/><Reference refidx="56"/><Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="59"/><Reference refidx="60"/><Reference refidx="61"/><Reference refidx="62"/><Reference refidx="63"/><Reference refidx="64"/><Reference refidx="65"/><Reference refidx="66"/><Reference refidx="67"/></Para><Para id="_402">Evidence (high-dose therapy with stem cell support):</Para><OrderedList id="_403" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>  In a prospective study, patients with bone and/or bone marrow metastases at diagnosis were treated with aggressive chemotherapy, surgery, and/or radiation therapy and HSCT if a good initial response was achieved.<Reference refidx="60"/> <ItemizedList id="_404" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The study showed no benefit for HSCT compared with historical controls.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A retrospective review using international bone marrow transplant registries compared the outcomes after treatment with either reduced-intensity conditioning or high-intensity conditioning followed by allogeneic HSCT for patients with Ewing sarcoma at high risk of relapse.<Reference refidx="68"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] <ItemizedList id="_405" Style="bullet"><ListItem>There was no difference in outcome, and the authors concluded that this suggested the absence of a clinically relevant graft-versus-tumor effect against Ewing sarcoma tumor cells with current approaches. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The role of high-dose therapy with busulfan-melphalan (BuMel) followed by stem cell rescue was investigated in the prospective randomized <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00020566">EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 (NCT00020566)</ProtocolRef> trial for two distinct groups:<Reference refidx="69"/><OrderedList id="_1876" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>Patients who presented with isolated pulmonary metastases (R2pulm).</ListItem><ListItem>Patients with localized tumors with poor response to initial chemotherapy (&lt;90% necrosis) or with large tumors (&gt;200 mL) (R2loc).<Para id="_1877">   Both study arms were compromised by the potential for selection bias for patients who were eligible for and accepted randomization, which may limit the generalizability of the results. Only 40% of eligible patients were randomized.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1808" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For R2pulm patients, there was no statistically significant difference in EFS or OS between the treatment groups.<Reference refidx="70"/><ItemizedList id="_1970" Style="dash"><ListItem>The EFS rates at 3 years were 50.6% for patients who received VAI plus whole-lung irradiation versus 56.6% for patients who received BuMel. The EFS rates at 8 years were 43.1% for patients who received VAI plus whole-lung irradiation versus 52.9% for patients who received BuMel.</ListItem><ListItem>The OS rates at 3 years were 68.0% for patients who received VAI plus whole-lung irradiation versus 68.2% for patients who received BuMel. The OS rates at 8 years were 54.2% for patients who received VAI plus whole-lung irradiation versus 55.3% for patients who received BuMel.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Among R2loc patients, the 3-year EFS rate was superior with BuMel compared with continued chemotherapy (66.9% vs. 53.1%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .019). The 3-year OS rate was 78.0% with BuMel and 72.2% with continued chemotherapy (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .028).<Reference refidx="69"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1805">The induction regimen employed in the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 trial was VIDE.  This regimen is less dose intensive than the regimen employed in COG studies.  This can be inferred from the intended dose intensity of the agents employed for the 21-week period that preceded randomization in the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1816" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Table 6</SummaryRef>).  The lower dose intensity can also be inferred from the outcome of the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study for patients in the localized disease stratum.  Results from this study include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1884" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Patients assigned to the most favorable risk stratum, R1, were patients with small primary tumors, less than 200 mL in volume.  In addition, patients who had poor response to the initial six cycles of therapy with VIDE, as assessed by pathology or radiology, were removed from the R1 stratum and assigned to the R2 stratum.  As a result, the R1 stratum includes only patients with small primary tumors and favorable response to initial therapy.  The probability for EFS at 3 years for this favorable group was 76%, and the OS rate at 3 years was 85%.<Reference refidx="28"/>  </ListItem><ListItem>For all patients with localized Ewing sarcoma, including patients with large primary tumors and patients with poor response to initial therapy treated on the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01231906">COG-AEWS1031 (NCT01231906)</ProtocolRef> trial, the 5-year probability for EFS was 73%, and the 5-year  OS rate was 88%.<Reference refidx="24"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1881">  The observation that high-dose therapy with autologous stem cell rescue improved outcomes for patients with a poor response to initial therapy in the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study must be interpreted in this context.  The advantage of high-dose therapy as consolidation for patients with a poor response to initial treatment with a less intensive regimen cannot be extrapolated to a population of patients who received a more intensive treatment regimen as initial therapy.</Para><Table id="_1816"><Title>Table 6.  Comparison of the Dose Intensity of the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 Trial Versus COG Interval Dose Compression</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Chemotherapy Agent</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Prescribed Dose Intensity (mg/week)</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>	EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 Trial <Reference refidx="28"/></entry><entry>COG Interval Dose Compression <Reference refidx="24"/></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">COG = Children's Oncology Group.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Vincristine	</entry><entry>0.5 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>	</entry><entry>0.43 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry>Doxorubicin	</entry><entry>17.1 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>	</entry><entry>21.4 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry>Ifosfamide	</entry><entry>3,000 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>	</entry><entry>2,150 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry>Cyclophosphamide</entry><entry>	0	</entry><entry>343 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry>Cyclophosphamide equivalent dose  (= cyclophosphamide dose + ifosfamide dose × 0.244)</entry><entry>732 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry><entry>868 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></ListItem><ListItem>Multiple small studies that report benefit for HSCT have been published but are difficult to interpret because only patients who have a good initial response to standard chemotherapy are considered for HSCT.  </ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><Title>Extraosseous Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_149">Extraosseous Ewing sarcoma is biologically similar to Ewing sarcoma  arising in bone. Historically, most children and young adults with extraosseous Ewing sarcoma were treated on protocols designed for the treatment of rhabdomyosarcoma. This is important because many of the treatment regimens for rhabdomyosarcoma do not include an anthracycline, which is a critical component of  current treatment regimens for Ewing sarcoma.  Currently, patients with extraosseous Ewing sarcoma are eligible for studies that include Ewing sarcoma of bone.</Para><Para id="_1828">Evidence (treatment of extraosseous Ewing sarcoma):</Para><OrderedList id="_1829" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>From 1987 to 2004, 111 patients with nonmetastatic extraosseous Ewing sarcoma were enrolled on the RMS-88 and RMS-96 protocols.<Reference refidx="71"/> Patients with initial complete tumor resection received ifosfamide, vincristine, and actinomycin (IVA) while patients with residual tumor received IVA plus doxorubicin (VAIA) or IVA plus carboplatin, epirubicin, and etoposide (CEVAIE). Seventy-six percent of patients received radiation.<ItemizedList id="_1830" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year EFS rate was 59%, and the OS rate was 69%.</ListItem><ListItem>In a multivariate analysis, independent adverse prognostic factors included axial primary, tumor size greater than 10 cm, Intergroup Rhabdomyosarcoma Studies  Group III, and lack of radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a retrospective French study, patients with extraosseous Ewing sarcoma were treated using a rhabdomyosarcoma regimen (no anthracyclines) or a Ewing sarcoma regimen (includes anthracyclines).<Reference refidx="72"/><Reference refidx="73"/><ItemizedList id="_1832" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Patients who received the anthracycline-containing regimen had a significantly better EFS and OS than patients who did not receive anthracyclines.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Two North American Ewing sarcoma trials included patients with extraosseous Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="74"/>  In a review of data from the POG-9354 (INT-0154) and <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00006734">EWS0031 (NCT00006734)</ProtocolRef> studies, 213 patients with extraosseous Ewing sarcoma and 826 patients with Ewing sarcoma of bone were identified.<Reference refidx="75"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_1833" Style="bullet"><ListItem> The HR for EFS of extraosseous Ewing sarcoma was superior (0.62), and extraosseous Ewing sarcoma was a favorable risk factor, independent of age, race, and primary site.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In addition to the above review, the COG <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01231906">AEWS1031 (NCT01231906)</ProtocolRef> trial subsequently treated patients using a compressed chemotherapy schedule (every 2 weeks). Patients were randomly assigned to receive  standard cycles of vincristine, doxorubicin, and cyclophosphamide, alternating with either ifosfamide and etoposide or vincristine, topotecan and cyclophosphamide every third cycle. There were 116 patients with extraosseous tumors, 114 patients with pelvic bone tumors, and 399 patients with nonpelvic bone tumors.<Reference refidx="26"/><ItemizedList id="_2400" Style="bullet"><ListItem>There were no differences in patient outcomes between the treatment regimens.</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year EFS rates were 75% (95% CI, 65%–82%) for patients with pelvic bone tumors, 78% (95% CI, 73%–81%) for patients with nonpelvic bone tumors, and 85% (95% CI, 76%–90%) for patients with extraosseous primary sites (global <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> value = .124).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The Cooperative Weichteilsarkomstudiengruppe (CWS) performed a retrospective analysis of 243 patients with nonmetastatic extraosseous Ewing sarcoma treated on three consecutive soft tissue sarcoma studies between 1991 and 2008. Several different drug regimens were used, all containing vincristine, doxorubicin, and alkylating agents.<Reference refidx="76"/><ItemizedList id="_2403" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The outcome improved over time, but it was difficult to assign causality to any specific therapy with these historical comparisons.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients with extremity primary tumors (compared with other locations) and patients with smaller tumors had better outcomes.</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year EFS rate varied, from 57% to 79%, with the better outcome seen in the most recent protocol.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_310">Cutaneous Ewing sarcoma is a soft tissue tumor in the skin or subcutaneous tissue that seems to behave as a less-aggressive tumor than primary bone or soft tissue Ewing sarcoma.  Tumors can form throughout the body, although the extremity is the most common site, and they are almost always localized.  </Para><Para id="_1834">Evidence (treatment of cutaneous Ewing sarcoma):</Para><OrderedList id="_1835" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a review of 78 reported cases (some lacking molecular confirmation),  the OS rate was 91%.  Adequate local control, defined as a complete resection  with negative margins, radiation therapy, or a combination, significantly reduced the incidence of relapse. Standard chemotherapy for Ewing sarcoma is often used for these patients because there are no data to suggest which patients could be treated less aggressively.<Reference refidx="77"/><Reference refidx="78"/></ListItem><ListItem>A series of 56 patients with cutaneous or subcutaneous Ewing sarcoma confirmed the excellent outcome with the use of standard systemic therapy and local control. Attempted primary definitive surgery often resulted in the need for either radiation therapy or more function-compromising surgery, supporting the recommendation of biopsy only as initial surgery, rather than up-front unplanned resection.<Reference refidx="79"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="14612626">Fuchs B, Valenzuela RG, Sim FH: Pathologic fracture as a complication in the treatment of Ewing's sarcoma. Clin Orthop  (415): 25-30, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="23660273">Singh VM, Salunga RC, Huang VJ, et al.: Analysis of the effect of various decalcification agents on the quantity and quality of nucleic acid (DNA and RNA) recovered from bone biopsies. Ann Diagn Pathol 17 (4): 322-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8165999">Hoffer FA, Gianturco LE, Fletcher JA, et al.: Percutaneous biopsy of peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumors and Ewing's sarcomas for cytogenetic analysis. AJR Am J Roentgenol 162 (5): 1141-2, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="9817284" MedlineID="99032196">Craft A, Cotterill S, Malcolm A, et al.: Ifosfamide-containing chemotherapy in Ewing's sarcoma: The Second United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group and the Medical Research Council Ewing's Tumor Study. J Clin Oncol 16 (11): 3628-33, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10674016" MedlineID="20138971">Shankar AG, Pinkerton CR, Atra A, et al.: Local therapy and other factors influencing site of relapse in patients with localised Ewing's sarcoma. United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group (UKCCSG). Eur J Cancer 35 (12): 1698-704, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="9743460" MedlineID="98414417">Nilbert M, Saeter G, Elomaa I, et al.: Ewing's sarcoma treatment in Scandinavia 1984-1990--ten-year results of the Scandinavian Sarcoma Group Protocol SSGIV. Acta Oncol 37 (4): 375-8, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9876058" MedlineID="99091286">Ferrari S, Mercuri M, Rosito P, et al.: Ifosfamide and actinomycin-D, added in the induction phase to vincristine, cyclophosphamide and doxorubicin, improve histologic response and prognosis in patients with non metastatic Ewing's sarcoma of the extremity. J Chemother 10 (6): 484-91, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12594313" MedlineID="22482785">Grier HE, Krailo MD, Tarbell NJ, et al.: Addition of ifosfamide and etoposide to standard chemotherapy for Ewing's sarcoma and primitive neuroectodermal tumor of bone. N Engl J Med 348 (8): 694-701, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15877528">Thacker MM, Temple HT, Scully SP: Current treatment for Ewing's sarcoma. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther 5 (2): 319-31, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="16572419">Juergens C, Weston C, Lewis I, et al.: Safety assessment of intensive induction with vincristine, ifosfamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide (VIDE) in the treatment of Ewing tumors in the EURO-E.W.I.N.G. 99 clinical trial. Pediatr Blood Cancer 47 (1): 22-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="15049022">Dunst J, Schuck A: Role of radiotherapy in Ewing tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 42 (5): 465-70, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="15049023">Donaldson SS: Ewing sarcoma: radiation dose and target volume. Pediatr Blood Cancer 42 (5): 471-6, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="14654912">Bacci G, Ferrari S, Longhi A, et al.: Role of surgery in local treatment of Ewing's sarcoma of the extremities in patients undergoing adjuvant and neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Oncol Rep 11 (1): 111-20, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="15266406">Krasin MJ, Rodriguez-Galindo C, Davidoff AM, et al.: Efficacy of combined surgery and irradiation for localized Ewings sarcoma family of tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 43 (3): 229-36, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="16626886">Bacci G, Longhi A, Briccoli A, et al.: The role of surgical margins in treatment of Ewing's sarcoma family tumors: experience of a single institution with 512 patients treated with adjuvant and neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 65 (3): 766-72, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="9602261" MedlineID="98264971">Paulussen M, Ahrens S, Burdach S, et al.: Primary metastatic (stage IV) Ewing tumor: survival analysis of 171 patients from the EICESS studies. European Intergroup Cooperative Ewing Sarcoma Studies. Ann Oncol 9 (3): 275-81, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="11435062" MedlineID="21328958">Pinkerton CR, Bataillard A, Guillo S, et al.: Treatment strategies for metastatic Ewing's sarcoma. Eur J Cancer 37 (11): 1338-44, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="16382125">Bernstein ML, Devidas M, Lafreniere D, et al.: Intensive therapy with growth factor support for patients with Ewing tumor metastatic at diagnosis: Pediatric Oncology Group/Children's Cancer Group Phase II Study 9457--a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 24 (1): 152-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="20547982">Ladenstein R, Pötschger U, Le Deley MC, et al.: Primary disseminated multifocal Ewing sarcoma: results of the Euro-EWING 99 trial. J Clin Oncol 28 (20): 3284-91, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="15254055">Miser JS, Krailo MD, Tarbell NJ, et al.: Treatment of metastatic Ewing's sarcoma or primitive neuroectodermal tumor of bone: evaluation of combination ifosfamide and etoposide--a Children's Cancer Group and Pediatric Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 22 (14): 2873-6, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="17584910">Miser JS, Goldsby RE, Chen Z, et al.: Treatment of metastatic Ewing sarcoma/primitive neuroectodermal tumor of bone: evaluation of increasing the dose intensity of chemotherapy--a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 49 (7): 894-900, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="19924786">Haeusler J, Ranft A, Boelling T, et al.: The value of local treatment in patients with primary, disseminated, multifocal Ewing sarcoma (PDMES). Cancer 116 (2): 443-50, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="18802150">Paulussen M, Craft AW, Lewis I, et al.: Results of the EICESS-92 Study: two randomized trials of Ewing's sarcoma treatment--cyclophosphamide compared with ifosfamide in standard-risk patients and assessment of benefit of etoposide added to standard treatment in high-risk patients. J Clin Oncol 26 (27): 4385-93, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="23091096">Womer RB, West DC, Krailo MD, et al.: Randomized controlled trial of interval-compressed chemotherapy for the treatment of localized Ewing sarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 30 (33): 4148-54, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="37651654">Cash T, Krailo MD, Buxton AB, et al.: Long-Term Outcomes in Patients With Localized Ewing Sarcoma Treated With Interval-Compressed Chemotherapy on Children's Oncology Group Study AEWS0031. J Clin Oncol 41 (30): 4724-4728, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="34652968">Leavey PJ, Laack NN, Krailo MD, et al.: Phase III Trial Adding Vincristine-Topotecan-Cyclophosphamide to the Initial Treatment of Patients With Nonmetastatic Ewing Sarcoma: A Children's Oncology Group Report. J Clin Oncol 39 (36): 4029-4038, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="36522207">Brennan B, Kirton L, Marec-Bérard P, et al.: Comparison of two chemotherapy regimens in patients with newly diagnosed Ewing sarcoma (EE2012): an open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet 400 (10362): 1513-1521, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="24982464">Le Deley MC, Paulussen M, Lewis I, et al.: Cyclophosphamide compared with ifosfamide in consolidation treatment of standard-risk Ewing sarcoma: results of the randomized noninferiority Euro-EWING99-R1 trial. J Clin Oncol 32 (23): 2440-8, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="25917418">Brunetto AL, Castillo LA, Petrilli AS, et al.: Carboplatin in the treatment of Ewing sarcoma: Results of the first Brazilian collaborative study group for Ewing sarcoma family tumors-EWING1. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (10): 1747-53, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="25251206">DuBois SG, Krailo MD, Gebhardt MC, et al.: Comparative evaluation of local control strategies in localized Ewing sarcoma of bone: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Cancer 121 (3): 467-75, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="30593906">Lin TA, Ludmir EB, Liao KP, et al.: Timing of Local Therapy Affects Survival in Ewing Sarcoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 104 (1): 127-136, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="16921035">Yock TI, Krailo M, Fryer CJ, et al.: Local control in pelvic Ewing sarcoma: analysis from INT-0091--a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 24 (24): 3838-43, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="31580267">Andreou D, Ranft A, Gosheger G, et al.: Which Factors Are Associated with Local Control and Survival of Patients with Localized Pelvic Ewing's Sarcoma? A Retrospective Analysis of Data from the Euro-EWING99 Trial. Clin Orthop Relat Res 478 (2): 290-302, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="27176931">Foulon S, Brennan B, Gaspar N, et al.: Can postoperative radiotherapy be omitted in localised standard-risk Ewing sarcoma? An observational study of the Euro-E.W.I.N.G group. Eur J Cancer 61: 128-36, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="30421578">Seitz G, Urla C, Sparber-Sauer M, et al.: Treatment and outcome of patients with thoracic tumors of the Ewing sarcoma family: A report from the Cooperative Weichteilsarkom Studiengruppe CWS-81, -86, -91, -96, and -2002P trials. Pediatr Blood Cancer 66 (3): e27537, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="14530727">Shamberger RC, LaQuaglia MP, Gebhardt MC, et al.: Ewing sarcoma/primitive neuroectodermal tumor of the chest wall: impact of initial versus delayed resection on tumor margins, survival, and use of radiation therapy. Ann Surg 238 (4): 563-7; discussion 567-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="19100921">Wagner TD, Kobayashi W, Dean S, et al.: Combination short-course preoperative irradiation, surgical resection, and reduced-field high-dose postoperative irradiation in the treatment of tumors involving the bone. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 73 (1): 259-66, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="10091764" MedlineID="99190185">Hoffmann C, Ahrens S, Dunst J, et al.: Pelvic Ewing sarcoma: a retrospective analysis of 241 cases. Cancer 85 (4): 869-77, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="10810477" MedlineID="20270774">Sucato DJ, Rougraff B, McGrath BE, et al.: Ewing's sarcoma of the pelvis. Long-term survival and functional outcome. Clin Orthop  (373): 193-201, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="12571462">Bacci G, Ferrari S, Mercuri M, et al.: Multimodal therapy for the treatment of nonmetastatic Ewing sarcoma of pelvis. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 25 (2): 118-24, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="12585587">Bacci G, Ferrari S, Longhi A, et al.: Local and systemic control in Ewing's sarcoma of the femur treated with chemotherapy, and locally by radiotherapy and/or surgery. J Bone Joint Surg Br 85 (1): 107-14, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="9057563" MedlineID="97210490">Ozaki T, Hillmann A, Hoffmann C, et al.: Ewing's sarcoma of the femur. Prognosis in 69 patients treated by the CESS group. Acta Orthop Scand 68 (1): 20-4, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="10872374" MedlineID="20331178">Ayoub KS, Fiorenza F, Grimer RJ, et al.: Extensible endoprostheses of the humerus after resection of bone tumours. J Bone Joint Surg Br 81 (3): 495-500, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="19576648">Bacci G, Palmerini E, Staals EL, et al.: Ewing's sarcoma family tumors of the humerus: outcome of patients treated with radiotherapy, surgery or surgery and adjuvant radiotherapy. Radiother Oncol 93 (2): 383-7, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="15057103">Casadei R, Magnani M, Biagini R, et al.: Prognostic factors in Ewing's sarcoma of the foot. Clin Orthop  (420): 230-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="19091738">Anakwenze OA, Parker WL, Wold LE, et al.: Ewing's sarcoma of the hand. J Hand Surg Eur Vol 34 (1): 35-9, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="10838532" MedlineID="20299060">Shamberger RC, Laquaglia MP, Krailo MD, et al.: Ewing sarcoma of the rib: results of an intergroup study with analysis of outcome by timing of resection. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg 119 (6): 1154-61, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="11872350" MedlineID="21861653">Sirvent N, Kanold J, Levy C, et al.: Non-metastatic Ewing's sarcoma of the ribs: the French Society of Pediatric Oncology Experience. Eur J Cancer 38 (4): 561-7, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="12377336" MedlineID="22265470">Schuck A, Ahrens S, Konarzewska A, et al.: Hemithorax irradiation for Ewing tumors of the chest wall. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 54 (3): 830-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="15274413">Windfuhr JP: Primitive neuroectodermal tumor of the head and neck: incidence, diagnosis, and management. Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol 113 (7): 533-43, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="11466720" MedlineID="21359802">Venkateswaran L, Rodriguez-Galindo C, Merchant TE, et al.: Primary Ewing tumor of the vertebrae: clinical characteristics, prognostic factors, and outcome. Med Pediatr Oncol 37 (1): 30-5, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="15803079">Marco RA, Gentry JB, Rhines LD, et al.: Ewing's sarcoma of the mobile spine. Spine 30 (7): 769-73, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="16137838">Schuck A, Ahrens S, von Schorlemer I, et al.: Radiotherapy in Ewing tumors of the vertebrae: treatment results and local relapse analysis of the CESS 81/86 and EICESS 92 trials. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 63 (5): 1562-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="19277725">Bacci G, Boriani S, Balladelli A, et al.: Treatment of nonmetastatic Ewing's sarcoma family tumors of the spine and sacrum: the experience from a single institution. Eur Spine J 18 (8): 1091-5, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="11157041" MedlineID="21104139">Kushner BH, Meyers PA: How effective is dose-intensive/myeloablative therapy against Ewing's sarcoma/primitive neuroectodermal tumor metastatic to bone or bone marrow? The Memorial Sloan-Kettering experience and a literature review. J Clin Oncol 19 (3): 870-80, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="15781877">Marina N, Meyers PA: High-dose therapy and stem-cell rescue for Ewing's family of tumors in second remission. J Clin Oncol 23 (19): 4262-4, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="15125708">Burdach S: Treatment of advanced Ewing tumors by combined radiochemotherapy and engineered cellular transplants. Pediatr Transplant 8 (Suppl 5): 67-82, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="16782749">McTiernan A, Driver D, Michelagnoli MP, et al.: High dose chemotherapy with bone marrow or peripheral stem cell rescue is an effective treatment option for patients with relapsed or progressive Ewing's sarcoma family of tumours. Ann Oncol 17 (8): 1301-5, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="12915596">Burdach S, Meyer-Bahlburg A, Laws HJ, et al.: High-dose therapy for patients with primary multifocal and early relapsed Ewing's tumors: results of two consecutive regimens assessing the role of total-body irradiation. J Clin Oncol 21 (16): 3072-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="11387352" MedlineID="21281030">Meyers PA, Krailo MD, Ladanyi M, et al.: High-dose melphalan, etoposide, total-body irradiation, and autologous stem-cell reconstitution as consolidation therapy for high-risk Ewing's sarcoma does not improve prognosis. J Clin Oncol 19 (11): 2812-20, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="16921053">Oberlin O, Rey A, Desfachelles AS, et al.: Impact of high-dose busulfan plus melphalan as consolidation in metastatic Ewing tumors: a study by the Société Française des Cancers de l'Enfant. J Clin Oncol 24 (24): 3997-4002, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="10797354" MedlineID="20259935">Hawkins D, Barnett T, Bensinger W, et al.: Busulfan, melphalan, and thiotepa with or without total marrow irradiation with hematopoietic stem cell rescue for poor-risk Ewing-Sarcoma-Family tumors. Med Pediatr Oncol 34 (5): 328-37, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="18587438">Rosenthal J, Bolotin E, Shakhnovits M, et al.: High-dose therapy with hematopoietic stem cell rescue in patients with poor prognosis Ewing family tumors. Bone Marrow Transplant 42 (5): 311-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="19684633">Burdach S, Thiel U, Schöniger M, et al.: Total body MRI-governed involved compartment irradiation combined with high-dose chemotherapy and stem cell rescue improves long-term survival in Ewing tumor patients with multiple primary bone metastases. Bone Marrow Transplant 45 (3): 483-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="22516209">Gaspar N, Rey A, Bérard PM, et al.: Risk adapted chemotherapy for localised Ewing's sarcoma of bone: the French EW93 study. Eur J Cancer 48 (9): 1376-85, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="22609883">Drabko K, Raciborska A, Bilska K, et al.: Consolidation of first-line therapy with busulphan and melphalan, and autologous stem cell rescue in children with Ewing's sarcoma. Bone Marrow Transplant 47 (12): 1530-4, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="26030048">Loschi S, Dufour C, Oberlin O, et al.: Tandem high-dose chemotherapy strategy as first-line treatment of primary disseminated multifocal Ewing sarcomas in children, adolescents and young adults. Bone Marrow Transplant 50 (8): 1083-8, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="21245159">Thiel U, Wawer A, Wolf P, et al.: No improvement of survival with reduced- versus high-intensity conditioning for allogeneic stem cell transplants in Ewing tumor patients. Ann Oncol 22 (7): 1614-21, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="30188789">Whelan J, Le Deley MC, Dirksen U, et al.: High-Dose Chemotherapy and Blood Autologous Stem-Cell Rescue Compared With Standard Chemotherapy in Localized High-Risk Ewing Sarcoma: Results of Euro-E.W.I.N.G.99 and Ewing-2008. J Clin Oncol : JCO2018782516, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="31553693">Dirksen U, Brennan B, Le Deley MC, et al.: High-Dose Chemotherapy Compared With Standard Chemotherapy and Lung Radiation in Ewing Sarcoma With Pulmonary Metastases: Results of the European Ewing Tumour Working Initiative of National Groups, 99 Trial and EWING 2008. J Clin Oncol 37 (34): 3192-3202, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="71">Spiller M, Bisogno G, Ferrari A, et al.: Prognostic factors in localized extraosseus Ewing family tumors. [Abstract] Pediatr Blood Cancer  46 (10) :  A-PD.024, 434, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="17401006">Castex MP, Rubie H, Stevens MC, et al.: Extraosseous localized ewing tumors: improved outcome with anthracyclines--the French society of pediatric oncology and international society of pediatric oncology. J Clin Oncol 25 (10): 1176-82, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="19224858">Dantonello TM, Int-Veen C, Harms D, et al.: Cooperative trial CWS-91 for localized soft tissue sarcoma in children, adolescents, and young adults. J Clin Oncol 27 (9): 1446-55, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="19349548">Granowetter L, Womer R, Devidas M, et al.: Dose-intensified compared with standard chemotherapy for nonmetastatic Ewing sarcoma family of tumors: a Children's Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 27 (15): 2536-41, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="75" PMID="27297500">Cash T, McIlvaine E, Krailo MD, et al.: Comparison of clinical features and outcomes in patients with extraskeletal versus skeletal localized Ewing sarcoma: A report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 63 (10): 1771-9, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="34089219">Koscielniak E, Sparber-Sauer M, Scheer M, et al.: Extraskeletal Ewing sarcoma in children, adolescents, and young adults. An analysis of three prospective studies of the Cooperative Weichteilsarkomstudiengruppe (CWS). Pediatr Blood Cancer 68 (10): e29145, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="22042282">Collier AB, Simpson L, Monteleone P: Cutaneous Ewing sarcoma: report of 2 cases and literature review of presentation, treatment, and outcome of 76 other reported cases. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 33 (8): 631-4, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="18820660">Terrier-Lacombe MJ, Guillou L, Chibon F, et al.: Superficial primitive Ewing's sarcoma: a clinicopathologic and molecular cytogenetic analysis of 14 cases. Mod Pathol 22 (1): 87-94, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="79" PMID="25894676">Di Giannatale A, Frezza AM, Le Deley MC, et al.: Primary cutaneous and subcutaneous Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (9): 1555-61, 2015.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_642"><Title>Special Considerations for the Treatment of Children With Cancer</Title><Para id="_642_md_3">Cancer in children and adolescents is rare, although the overall incidence has slowly increased since 1975.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Children and adolescents with cancer should be referred to medical centers that have a multidisciplinary team of cancer specialists with experience treating the cancers that occur during childhood and adolescence.  This multidisciplinary team approach incorporates the skills
of the following pediatric specialists and others to ensure that children receive treatment, supportive care, and rehabilitation
to achieve optimal survival and quality of life:</Para><ItemizedList id="_642_md_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Primary care physicians.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric surgeons.</ListItem><ListItem>Transplant surgeons.</ListItem><ListItem>Pathologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric radiation
oncologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric medical oncologists and hematologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Ophthalmologists.</ListItem><ListItem> Rehabilitation
specialists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric oncology nurses.</ListItem><ListItem>Social workers.</ListItem><ListItem>Child-life professionals.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Nutritionists.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_642_md_5">For specific information about supportive care for children and adolescents with cancer, see the summaries on <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/supportive-care">Supportive and Palliative Care</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_642_md_6">The American Academy of Pediatrics has outlined guidelines for
pediatric cancer centers and their role in the treatment of children and adolescents
with cancer.<Reference refidx="2"/>  At
these centers, clinical trials are available for most  types of cancer that occur in children and adolescents, and the opportunity
to participate is offered to most patients and their families.  Clinical
trials for children and adolescents diagnosed with cancer are generally
designed to compare potentially better therapy with current standard therapy.  Other types of clinical trials test novel therapies when there is no standard therapy for a cancer diagnosis. Most of the progress in identifying curative
therapies for childhood cancers has been achieved through clinical trials.
Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_2436">  Childhood and adolescent cancer survivors require close monitoring because side effects of cancer therapy may persist or develop months or years after treatment.  For specific information about the incidence, type, and monitoring of late effects in childhood and adolescent cancer survivors, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343584" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-hp-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20404250">Smith MA, Seibel NL, Altekruse SF, et al.: Outcomes for children and adolescents with cancer: challenges for the twenty-first century. J Clin Oncol 28 (15): 2625-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2">American Academy of Pediatrics: Standards for pediatric cancer centers. Pediatrics  134 (2): 410-4, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/134/2/410">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_34"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043411">localized Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Localized Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_407">Standard treatment options for localized Ewing sarcoma include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_408" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_410" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_413" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Local-control measures</SummaryRef>:<ItemizedList id="_409" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_415" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_422" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1811" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">High-dose chemotherapy with autologous stem cell rescue</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_35">Because most patients with apparently localized disease at diagnosis have
occult metastatic disease, multidrug chemotherapy and surgery and/or radiation therapy (to control local disease) is indicated in the treatment of all
patients.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> Patients with localized Ewing sarcoma who receive current treatment regimens achieve event-free survival (EFS) and overall survival (OS) rates of approximately 70% at 5 years after diagnosis.<Reference refidx="9"/> </Para><SummarySection id="_410"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_36">Current standard chemotherapy in the United States includes vincristine,
doxorubicin, and cyclophosphamide (VDC), alternating with ifosfamide and
etoposide (IE) or VDC/IE.<Reference refidx="9"/>; <Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  With the outcome of the EURO EWING 2012 (EE2012) trial, which compared VDC/IE to VIDE (vincristine, ifosfamide, doxorubicin, etoposide), the VDC/IE regimen has become increasingly used internationally as initial therapy over the previous VIDE regimen.<Reference refidx="11"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] For more information about the EE2012 trial, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_134" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy for Ewing Sarcoma</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_411">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_412" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>IE has shown activity in Ewing sarcoma. A large randomized clinical trial and a nonrandomized trial demonstrated that outcome was improved when IE was alternated with VDC.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem>The use of
high-dose VDC has shown promising results in small numbers of patients. A single-institution study of 44 patients treated with high-dose VDC and IE showed a 4-year  EFS rate of 82%.<Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem><ListItem>However, in an intergroup trial of the Pediatric Oncology Group and the Children's Cancer Group, which compared an alkylator dose-intensified VDC/IE regimen with standard alkylator doses of the same VDC/IE regimen, no differences in outcome were observed.<Reference refidx="14"/> Unlike the single-institution trial, this trial did not maintain the dose intensity of cyclophosphamide for the duration of treatment.<Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem><ListItem>In a Children's Oncology Group (COG) trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00006734">COG-AEWS0031 [NCT00006734]</ProtocolRef>), 568  patients with newly diagnosed localized extradural Ewing sarcoma were randomly assigned to receive chemotherapy (VDC/IE) given either every 2 weeks (interval compression) or every 3 weeks (standard).<Reference refidx="10"/><ItemizedList id="_2395" Style="bullet"><ListItem>
Patients randomly assigned to the every-2-week interval of treatment had an improved 5-year EFS rate (73% vs. 65%, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .048). </ListItem><ListItem>There was no increase in toxicity observed with the every-2-week schedule.</ListItem><ListItem>With longer follow-up of 10 years, interval-compressed VDC/IE continued to demonstrate superior EFS. OS was also significantly higher with this regimen than with VDC/IE given every 3 weeks.<Reference refidx="15"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The European Ewing 2008R1 trial evaluated 284 patients with standard-risk Ewing sarcoma, defined as localized disease with favorable histological response to initial chemotherapy and/or an initial tumor volume of less than 200 mL. All patients received VIDE chemotherapy followed by vincristine, dactinomycin, and ifosfamide (VAI) (male) or vincristine, dactinomycin, and cyclophosphamide (VAC) (female) consolidation therapy. During the sixth cycle of consolidation, patients were randomly assigned to therapy with either the addition of zoledronic acid for nine 28-day cycles or no maintenance therapy.<Reference refidx="16"/><ItemizedList id="_2505" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Outcomes were similar between patients who received zoledronic acid and patients who did not receive maintenance therapy (3-year EFS rates, 84.0% vs. 81.7%). </ListItem><ListItem>Patients who received zoledronic acid experienced higher rates of renal, neurological, and gastrointestinal toxicities.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>EE2012 was a European investigator–initiated, open-label, randomized, controlled, phase III trial that took place in ten countries. Between 2014 and 2019, 640 patients were enrolled and were randomly allocated (1:1) to either the European or COG treatment regimens (320 patients in each treatment group). The European treatment  regimen for induction included VIDE, and the consolidation regimen included  vincristine, dactinomycin, with ifosfamide or cyclophosphamide, or busulfan and melphalan (group 1). The COG treatment regimen for induction included interval-compressed VDC/IE, and the consolidation regimen included vincristine and cyclophosphamide, with ifosfamide and etoposide or busulfan and melphalan (group 2).<Reference refidx="11"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_2450" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 3-year EFS rate was 61% for patients in group 1 and 67% for patients in group 2 (adjusted hazard ratio [HR], 0.71; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.55–0.92 in favor of group 2). </ListItem><ListItem>The probability that the true HR for group 2 with interval-compressed VDC/IE was less than 1 was greater than 0.99. </ListItem><ListItem>The investigators concluded that dose-intensive induction chemotherapy with the VDC/IE regimen was more effective, less toxic, and shorter in duration for patients with all stages of newly diagnosed Ewing sarcoma than the VIDE regimen.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_413"><Title>Local-Control Measures</Title><Para id="_414">Local control can be achieved by surgery and/or radiation therapy.  Decisions regarding the optimal modality for local control for an individual patient involve consideration of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1809" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The possibility of complete resection with adequate margins after an initial period of systemic therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>The predicted functional impact of a surgical procedure.</ListItem><ListItem>The predicted morbidity after radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>The possibility of increased risk of second malignant neoplasms after radiation therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1810">An analysis using propensity scoring (a method that adjusts for the inherent selection bias of the location and size of the tumor) to adjust for clinical features that may influence the preference for surgery only, radiation only, or combined surgery and radiation demonstrated that similar EFS rates are achieved with each mode of local therapy after propensity adjustment.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><SummarySection id="_415"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_37">Surgery is
generally the preferred approach if the lesion is resectable.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/>  The
superiority of resection for local control has never been tested in a
prospective randomized trial.  The apparent superiority may represent selection
bias.    </Para><OrderedList id="_416" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In past studies, smaller, more peripheral tumors were more likely to be
treated with surgery, and larger, more central tumors were more likely to be
treated with radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem><ListItem>An Italian retrospective study showed that surgery improved outcome only in extremity tumors, although the number of patients with central axis Ewing sarcoma who achieved adequate margins was small.<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem>In a series of 39 patients who received both surgery and radiation therapy at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital, the 8-year local failure rate was 5% for patients with negative surgical margins and 17% for those with positive margins.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem>Data for patients with pelvic primary Ewing sarcoma from a North American intergroup trial showed no difference in local control or survival based on local-control modality—surgery alone, radiation therapy alone, or radiation plus surgery.<Reference refidx="21"/></ListItem><ListItem>Patients with residual viable tumor in the resected
specimen have a worse outcome than those with complete necrosis.  In a
French Ewing sarcoma study (EW88), the EFS rates were 75% for patients with less than 5%
viable tumor, 48% for patients with 5% to 30% viable tumor, and 20% for patients with more than 30% viable tumor.<Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_421">A single-institution retrospective analysis of 78 patients with Ewing sarcoma suggested that pathological fracture at initial presentation was associated with inferior EFS and OS.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]
 Another study found that pathological fracture at the time of diagnosis did not preclude surgical resection and was not associated with adverse outcome.<Reference refidx="23"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_422"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_1836">Radiation therapy is usually employed in the following cases:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1837" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Patients who do
not have a surgical option that preserves function and cosmesis.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients whose tumors have been excised but with inadequate margins.</ListItem><ListItem>Preoperative radiation therapy if gross-total resection is possible but without adequate margins (and preservation of function and cosmesis).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_38">Radiation therapy is delivered in a setting in which stringent planning
techniques are applied by those experienced in the treatment of  Ewing sarcoma.  Such an approach will result in local control of the tumor with
acceptable morbidity in most patients.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="24"/></Para><Para id="_424">The radiation dose may
be adjusted depending on the extent of residual disease after the initial surgical
procedure.  When no surgical resection is performed, radiation therapy is generally administered in fractionated doses totaling approximately 55.8 Gy to the prechemotherapy tumor volume. A randomized study of 40 patients with Ewing sarcoma using
 55.8 Gy to the prechemotherapy tumor extent with a 2-cm margin compared with the
same total-tumor dose after  39.6 Gy to the entire bone showed no
difference in local control or EFS.<Reference refidx="3"/> Hyperfractionated
radiation therapy   has not been associated with improved local control  or decreased morbidity.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_2426">Preoperative radiation therapy is an approach that can be used when surgical resection is deemed possible but with the likelihood of microscopic residual disease. A panel of international expert clinicians used a three-stage modified Delphi technique to develop consensus statements about local treatment. The panel reached a strong consensus that preoperative radiation therapy may be given when an inadequate (marginal) margin at resection is foreseen on imaging.<Reference refidx="25"/></Para><Para id="_1838">For patients with residual disease after an attempt at surgical resection, the Intergroup Ewing Sarcoma Study (INT-0091) recommended 45 Gy to the original disease site plus a 10.8 Gy boost for patients with gross residual disease and 45 Gy plus a  5.4 Gy
boost for patients with microscopic residual disease.  No radiation therapy was recommended for those who had no evidence of 
microscopic residual disease after surgical resection.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_2433">For patients who are deemed to have unresectable disease after induction chemotherapy, radiation therapy is given, using the same doses as those administered for patients with partially resected disease.<Reference refidx="26"/>  Patients who have  unresectable disease are typically those with extremity tumors that have persistent encasement of the neurovascular bundles and/or morbid surgical excision entailing loss of functionality.  In a phase III randomized controlled clinical trial of patients with unresectable disease, patients were randomly assigned to  receive either standard-dose radiation therapy (55.8 Gy in 1.8 Gy fractions) or escalated-dose radiation therapy (70.2 Gy in 1.8 Gy fractions).<Reference refidx="26"/>  From 2005 to 2015, the study accrued 47 patients who received standard-dose radiation therapy and 48 patients who received escalated-dose radiation therapy (interquartile age, 13–23 years). The median largest tumor dimension was 9.7 cm. At a median follow-up of 67 months, the 5-year local control rate was significantly better in the escalated arm than in the standard arm (76.4% vs. 49.4%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).  The differences in disease-free survival (DFS) and OS at 5 years did not achieve statistical significance (DFS rates, 46.7% vs. 31.8%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .22; OS rates, 58.8% vs. 45.4%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .08), possibly because the rate of metastatic disease was not changed.  A skin toxicity grade of more than 2 was greater in the high-dose arm (10.4% vs. 2.1%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .08).  </Para><Para id="_2509">In a single-institution nonrandomized study, patients who had primary tumors 8 cm or larger were treated with higher-dose radiation therapy (median dose, 64.8 Gy).  The 5-year cumulative incidence of local failure rate was 6.6%, which compares favorably to other published local failure rates in this group of patients.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_318">Comparison of proton-beam radiation therapy and intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) treatment plans has shown that proton-beam radiation therapy can spare more normal tissue adjacent to Ewing sarcoma primary tumors than IMRT.<Reference refidx="28"/> Follow-up remains relatively short, and there are no data to determine whether the reduction in dose to adjacent tissue will result in improved functional outcome or reduce the risk of secondary malignancy. Because patient numbers are small and follow-up is relatively short, it is not possible to determine whether the risk of local recurrence might be increased by reducing radiation dose in tissue adjacent to the primary tumor.</Para><Para id="_75"> Higher rates of local failure are seen in patients older than 14 years who have tumors larger than 8 cm in length.<Reference refidx="29"/> Among patients with pelvic tumors, a larger tumor volume, a periacetabular tumor site, and the use of definitive radiation therapy only (rather than a combined-modality approach) were associated with higher rates of local failure.<Reference refidx="30"/> A retrospective analysis of patients with   Ewing sarcoma of the chest wall compared patients who received hemithorax radiation therapy with those who received radiation therapy to the chest wall only.  Patients with pleural invasion, pleural effusion, or intraoperative contamination were assigned to hemithorax radiation therapy.  EFS was longer for patients who received hemithorax radiation, but the difference was not statistically significant.  In addition, most patients with primary vertebral tumors did not receive hemithorax radiation and had a lower probability for EFS.<Reference refidx="31"/></Para><Para id="_69">Radiation therapy is associated with the development of subsequent neoplasms.  A retrospective
study noted that patients who received  60 Gy or more had an incidence
of second malignancy of 20%.  Patients who received  48 Gy to  60 Gy had an
incidence of 5%, and those who received less than  48 Gy did not develop a
second malignancy.<Reference refidx="32"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1811"><Title>High-Dose Chemotherapy With Autologous Stem Cell Rescue</Title><Para id="_1812">Evidence (high-dose chemotherapy with autologous stem cell rescue):</Para><OrderedList id="_1818" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The role of high-dose therapy with busulfan-melphalan (BuMel) followed by stem cell rescue was investigated in the prospective randomized <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00020566">EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 (NCT00020566)</ProtocolRef> trial for two distinct groups:<Reference refidx="33"/><OrderedList id="_1890" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>Patients who presented with isolated pulmonary metastases (R2pulm).</ListItem><ListItem>Patients with localized tumors with poor response to initial chemotherapy (&lt;90% necrosis) or with large tumors (&gt;200 mL) (R2loc).<Para id="_1891">   Both study arms were compromised by the potential for selection bias for patients who were eligible for and accepted randomization, which may limit the generalizability of the results. Only 40% of eligible patients were randomized. </Para><ItemizedList id="_1892" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For R2pulm patients, there was no statistically significant difference in EFS or OS between the treatment groups.<Reference refidx="34"/><ItemizedList id="_1971" Style="dash"><ListItem>The EFS rates at 3 years were 50.6% for patients who received vincristine, dactinomycin, and ifosfamide (VAI) plus whole-lung irradiation versus 56.6% for patients who received BuMel.</ListItem><ListItem>The EFS rates at 8 years were 43.1% for patients who received VAI plus whole-lung irradiation versus 52.9% for patients who received BuMel.</ListItem><ListItem>The OS rates at 3 years were 68.0% for patients who received VAI plus whole-lung irradiation versus 68.2% for patients who received BuMel.</ListItem><ListItem> The OS rates at 8 years were 54.2% for patients who received VAI plus whole-lung irradiation versus 55.3% for patients who received BuMel.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Among R2loc patients, the 3-year EFS rate was superior with BuMel compared with continued chemotherapy (66.9% vs. 53.1%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .019). The 3-year OS rate was 78.0% with BuMel and 72.2% with continued chemotherapy (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .028).<Reference refidx="33"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1893">The induction regimen employed in the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99  trial included VIDE.  This regimen is less dose intensive than the regimen employed in COG studies.  This can be inferred from the intended dose intensity of the agents employed for the 21-week period that preceded randomization in the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1816" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Table 6</SummaryRef>).  The lower dose intensity can also be inferred from the outcome of the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study for patients in the localized disease stratum.  Results from this study include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_2421" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>Patients assigned to the most favorable risk stratum, R1, were patients with small primary tumors, less than 200 mL in volume.  In addition, patients who had poor response to the initial six cycles of therapy with VIDE, as assessed by pathology or radiology, were removed from the R1 stratum and assigned to the R2 stratum.  As a result, the R1 stratum includes only patients with small primary tumors and favorable response to initial therapy.<Reference refidx="35"/>  <ItemizedList id="_2399" Style="bullet"><ListItem>  The probability for EFS at 3 years for this favorable group was 76%, and the OS rate at 3 years was 85%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>For all patients with localized Ewing sarcoma, including patients with large primary tumors and patients with poor response to initial therapy treated on the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01231906">COG-AEWS1031 (NCT01231906)</ProtocolRef> trial, the 5-year probability for EFS was 73%, and the 5-year OS rate was 88%.<Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1895">  The observation that high-dose therapy with autologous stem cell rescue improved outcomes for patients with a poor response to initial therapy in the EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 study must be interpreted in this context.  The advantage of high-dose therapy as consolidation for patients with a poor response to initial treatment (with a less intensive regimen) cannot be extrapolated to a population of patients who received a more intensive treatment regimen as initial therapy.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_34_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_34_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="7607966" MedlineID="95332097">Dunst J, Jürgens H, Sauer R, et al.: Radiation therapy in Ewing's sarcoma: an update of the CESS 86 trial. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 32 (4): 919-30, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9747829" MedlineID="98418601">Donaldson SS, Torrey M, Link MP, et al.: A multidisciplinary study investigating radiotherapy in Ewing's sarcoma: end results of POG #8346. Pediatric Oncology Group. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 42 (1): 125-35, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9817284" MedlineID="99032196">Craft A, Cotterill S, Malcolm A, et al.: Ifosfamide-containing chemotherapy in Ewing's sarcoma: The Second United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group and the Medical Research Council Ewing's Tumor Study. J Clin Oncol 16 (11): 3628-33, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="9743460" MedlineID="98414417">Nilbert M, Saeter G, Elomaa I, et al.: Ewing's sarcoma treatment in Scandinavia 1984-1990--ten-year results of the Scandinavian Sarcoma Group Protocol SSGIV. Acta Oncol 37 (4): 375-8, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15948159">Krasin MJ, Davidoff AM, Rodriguez-Galindo C, et al.: Definitive surgery and multiagent systemic therapy for patients with localized Ewing sarcoma family of tumors: local outcome and prognostic factors. Cancer 104 (2): 367-73, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="14687792">Bacci G, Forni C, Longhi A, et al.: Long-term outcome for patients with non-metastatic Ewing's sarcoma treated with adjuvant and neoadjuvant chemotherapies. 402 patients treated at Rizzoli between 1972 and 1992. Eur J Cancer 40 (1): 73-83, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="10430250" MedlineID="99357319">Rosito P, Mancini AF, Rondelli R, et al.: Italian Cooperative Study for the treatment of children and young adults with localized Ewing sarcoma of bone: a preliminary report of 6 years of experience. Cancer 86 (3): 421-8, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="16626886">Bacci G, Longhi A, Briccoli A, et al.: The role of surgical margins in treatment of Ewing's sarcoma family tumors: experience of a single institution with 512 patients treated with adjuvant and neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 65 (3): 766-72, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12594313" MedlineID="22482785">Grier HE, Krailo MD, Tarbell NJ, et al.: Addition of ifosfamide and etoposide to standard chemotherapy for Ewing's sarcoma and primitive neuroectodermal tumor of bone. N Engl J Med 348 (8): 694-701, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="23091096">Womer RB, West DC, Krailo MD, et al.: Randomized controlled trial of interval-compressed chemotherapy for the treatment of localized Ewing sarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 30 (33): 4148-54, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="36522207">Brennan B, Kirton L, Marec-Bérard P, et al.: Comparison of two chemotherapy regimens in patients with newly diagnosed Ewing sarcoma (EE2012): an open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet 400 (10362): 1513-1521, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="9876058" MedlineID="99091286">Ferrari S, Mercuri M, Rosito P, et al.: Ifosfamide and actinomycin-D, added in the induction phase to vincristine, cyclophosphamide and doxorubicin, improve histologic response and prognosis in patients with non metastatic Ewing's sarcoma of the extremity. J Chemother 10 (6): 484-91, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="12972518">Kolb EA, Kushner BH, Gorlick R, et al.: Long-term event-free survival after intensive chemotherapy for Ewing's family of tumors in children and young adults. J Clin Oncol 21 (18): 3423-30, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="19349548">Granowetter L, Womer R, Devidas M, et al.: Dose-intensified compared with standard chemotherapy for nonmetastatic Ewing sarcoma family of tumors: a Children's Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 27 (15): 2536-41, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="37651654">Cash T, Krailo MD, Buxton AB, et al.: Long-Term Outcomes in Patients With Localized Ewing Sarcoma Treated With Interval-Compressed Chemotherapy on Children's Oncology Group Study AEWS0031. J Clin Oncol 41 (30): 4724-4728, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="37843857">Koch R, Haveman L, Ladenstein R, et al.: Zoledronic Acid Add-on Therapy for Standard-Risk Ewing Sarcoma Patients in the Ewing 2008R1 Trial. Clin Cancer Res 29 (24): 5057-5068, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="25251206">DuBois SG, Krailo MD, Gebhardt MC, et al.: Comparative evaluation of local control strategies in localized Ewing sarcoma of bone: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Cancer 121 (3): 467-75, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="10091764" MedlineID="99190185">Hoffmann C, Ahrens S, Dunst J, et al.: Pelvic Ewing sarcoma: a retrospective analysis of 241 cases. Cancer 85 (4): 869-77, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="10838532" MedlineID="20299060">Shamberger RC, Laquaglia MP, Krailo MD, et al.: Ewing sarcoma of the rib: results of an intergroup study with analysis of outcome by timing of resection. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg 119 (6): 1154-61, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="11742482" MedlineID="21607627">Oberlin O, Deley MC, Bui BN, et al.: Prognostic factors in localized Ewing's tumours and peripheral neuroectodermal tumours: the third study of the French Society of Paediatric Oncology (EW88 study). Br J Cancer 85 (11): 1646-54, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="16921035">Yock TI, Krailo M, Fryer CJ, et al.: Local control in pelvic Ewing sarcoma: analysis from INT-0091--a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 24 (24): 3838-43, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="29656296">Schlegel M, Zeumer M, Prodinger PM, et al.: Impact of Pathological Fractures on the Prognosis of Primary Malignant Bone Sarcoma in Children and Adults: A Single-Center Retrospective Study of 205 Patients. Oncology 94 (6): 354-362, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="17698347">Bramer JA, Abudu AA, Grimer RJ, et al.: Do pathological fractures influence survival and local recurrence rate in bony sarcomas? Eur J Cancer 43 (13): 1944-51, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="15465200">Krasin MJ, Rodriguez-Galindo C, Billups CA, et al.: Definitive irradiation in multidisciplinary management of localized Ewing sarcoma family of tumors in pediatric patients: outcome and prognostic factors. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 60 (3): 830-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="33292535">Gerrand C, Bate J, Seddon B, et al.: Seeking international consensus on approaches to primary tumour treatment in Ewing sarcoma. Clin Sarcoma Res 10 (1): 21, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="35568246">Laskar S, Sinha S, Chatterjee A, et al.: Radiation Therapy Dose Escalation in Unresectable Ewing Sarcoma: Final Results of a Phase 3 Randomized Controlled Trial. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 113 (5): 996-1002, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="38271232">Kacar M, Nagel MB, Liang J, et al.: Radiation therapy dose escalation achieves high rates of local control with tolerable toxicity profile in pediatric and young adult patients with Ewing sarcoma. Cancer 130 (10): 1836-1843, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="21856094">Rombi B, DeLaney TF, MacDonald SM, et al.: Proton radiotherapy for pediatric Ewing's sarcoma: initial clinical outcomes. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 82 (3): 1142-8, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="14612626">Fuchs B, Valenzuela RG, Sim FH: Pathologic fracture as a complication in the treatment of Ewing's sarcoma. Clin Orthop  (415): 25-30, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="36302496">Ahmed SK, Witten BG, Harmsen WS, et al.: Analysis of Local Control Outcomes and Clinical Prognostic Factors in Localized Pelvic Ewing Sarcoma Patients Treated With Radiation Therapy: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 115 (2): 337-346, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="12377336" MedlineID="22265470">Schuck A, Ahrens S, Konarzewska A, et al.: Hemithorax irradiation for Ewing tumors of the chest wall. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 54 (3): 830-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="8874344" MedlineID="97028330">Kuttesch JF, Wexler LH, Marcus RB, et al.: Second malignancies after Ewing's sarcoma: radiation dose-dependency of secondary sarcomas. J Clin Oncol 14 (10): 2818-25, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="30188789">Whelan J, Le Deley MC, Dirksen U, et al.: High-Dose Chemotherapy and Blood Autologous Stem-Cell Rescue Compared With Standard Chemotherapy in Localized High-Risk Ewing Sarcoma: Results of Euro-E.W.I.N.G.99 and Ewing-2008. J Clin Oncol : JCO2018782516, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="31553693">Dirksen U, Brennan B, Le Deley MC, et al.: High-Dose Chemotherapy Compared With Standard Chemotherapy and Lung Radiation in Ewing Sarcoma With Pulmonary Metastases: Results of the European Ewing Tumour Working Initiative of National Groups, 99 Trial and EWING 2008. J Clin Oncol 37 (34): 3192-3202, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="24982464">Le Deley MC, Paulussen M, Lewis I, et al.: Cyclophosphamide compared with ifosfamide in consolidation treatment of standard-risk Ewing sarcoma: results of the randomized noninferiority Euro-EWING99-R1 trial. J Clin Oncol 32 (23): 2440-8, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043412">metastatic Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_44">Approximately 25% of patients with Ewing sarcoma have metastases at diagnosis.<Reference refidx="1"/> The prognosis is poor for patients with metastatic disease.
With current therapies, patients who present with metastatic disease have a   6-year event-free survival (EFS) rate of approximately  28%  and an overall survival (OS) rate of approximately 30%.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> For patients
with lung/pleural metastases only, the 6-year EFS rate is approximately 40% when using bilateral lung irradiation.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  In contrast, patients with bone/bone marrow metastases have a 4-year EFS rate of approximately 28%, and patients with combined lung and bone/bone
marrow metastases have a 4-year EFS rate of approximately 14%.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> 
</Para><Para id="_425">The following factors independently predict a poor outcome in patients presenting with metastatic disease:<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_426" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Age older than 14 years.</ListItem><ListItem>Primary tumor volume of more than 200 mL.</ListItem><ListItem>More than one bone metastatic site.</ListItem><ListItem>Bone marrow metastases.</ListItem><ListItem>Additional lung metastases.</ListItem><ListItem>Pulmonary metastases lack of complete response to induction chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_427">Standard treatment options for metastatic Ewing sarcoma include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_428" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_430" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_433" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_433" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_430"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_46">For patients with metastatic Ewing sarcoma, standard treatment that uses alternating cycles of vincristine/doxorubicin/cyclophosphamide
and ifosfamide/etoposide (VDC/IE) combined with   adequate local-control measures applied to both primary and metastatic sites often results in complete or
partial responses. However, the overall cure rate is 20%.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> </Para><Para id="_431">The following chemotherapy regimens have <Strong>not</Strong> shown benefit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_432" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In the Intergroup Ewing Sarcoma Study, patients with metastatic disease showed no benefit from the addition of ifosfamide and etoposide to a standard regimen of vincristine, doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, and dactinomycin.<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem>In another Intergroup study, increasing dose intensity of cyclophosphamide, ifosfamide, and doxorubicin did not improve outcome compared with regimens using standard-dose intensity. This regimen increased toxicity and risk of second malignancy without improving EFS or OS.<Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem>Intensification of ifosfamide to 2.8 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> per day for 5 days did not improve outcome when administered with standard chemotherapy in patients with newly diagnosed metastatic Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>A pilot study of low-dose anti-angiogenic therapy with vinblastine and celecoxib added to every-3-week therapy with VDC/IE did not improve outcomes for patients presenting with metastases.<Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Children's Oncology Group performed a prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02306161">AEWS1221 [NCT02306161]</ProtocolRef>) that tested the addition of ganitumab to multiagent chemotherapy.  Patients were randomly assigned (1:1) at enrollment to either the standard arm (interval-compressed VDC/IE) or the experimental arm (ganitumab is given with VDC/IE when the cycle starts and as monotherapy once every 3 weeks for 6 months after conventional therapy).  The study enrolled 298 eligible patients (148 in standard arm; 150 in experimental arm).<Reference refidx="11"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_2452" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 3-year EFS rate estimates were 37.4% (95% confidence interval [CI], 29.3%–45.5%) for patients in the standard arm and 39.1% (95% CI, 31.3%–46.7%) for patients in the experimental arm (stratified EFS-event hazard ratio [HR] for experimental arm, 1.00; 95% CI, 0.76–1.33; 1-sided, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .50).  </ListItem><ListItem>Patients in the experimental arm reported more cases of pneumonitis after radiation therapy involving thoracic fields and nominally higher rates of febrile neutropenia and alanine transaminase elevation.  </ListItem><ListItem>Ganitumab added to interval-compressed chemotherapy did not significantly reduce the risk of an EFS event in patients with newly diagnosed metastatic Ewing sarcoma. The outcomes of these patients were similar to those in previous trials who did not receive IGF-1R inhibition or interval compression. </ListItem><ListItem>The addition of ganitumab may be associated with increased toxicity.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_433"><Title>Surgery and Radiation Therapy</Title><Para id="_47">Systematic use of surgery and radiation therapy for metastatic sites may improve overall outcome in patients with extrapulmonary metastases, although a randomized trial has not been done. </Para><Para id="_434">Evidence (surgery and radiation therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_435" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a retrospective data analysis of 120 patients with multifocal metastatic Ewing sarcoma, patients who received local treatment to both the primary tumor and metastases had better outcomes than patients who received  local treatment to the primary tumor only or with no local treatment (3-year EFS rate, 39% vs. 17% and 14%, respectively; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem>A similar trend for better outcomes with irradiation of all sites of metastatic disease was seen in three retrospective analyses of smaller groups of patients who received radiation therapy to all tumor sites.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Para id="_1839"> These results must be interpreted with caution. The patients who received local-control therapy to all known sites of metastatic disease were selected by the treating investigator, not randomly assigned. Patients with so many metastases that radiation to all sites would result in bone marrow failure were not selected to receive radiation to all sites of metastatic disease. Patients who did not achieve control of the primary tumor did not go on to have local control of all sites of metastatic disease. There was a selection bias. While all patients in these reports had multiple sites of metastatic disease, the patients who had surgery and/or radiation therapy to all sites of clinically detectable metastatic disease had better responses to systemic therapy and fewer sites of metastasis than patients who did not undergo similar therapy of metastatic sites.  </Para></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_330">Radiation therapy, delivered in a setting in which stringent planning techniques are applied by those experienced in the treatment of Ewing sarcoma, should be considered. Such an approach will result in local control of the tumor with acceptable morbidity in most patients.<Reference refidx="16"/> </Para><Para id="_436">The radiation dose depends on the metastatic site of disease:</Para><ItemizedList id="_437" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Bone and soft tissue. </Strong> Stereotactic body radiation therapy  has been used to treat metastatic sites in bone and soft tissue.  The median total curative/definitive stereotactic body radiation therapy dose delivered was 40 Gy in five fractions (range, 30–60 Gy in 3–10 fractions). The median total palliative stereotactic body radiation therapy dose delivered was 40 Gy in five fractions (range, 16–50 Gy in 1–10 fractions).  These short-course regimens with large-dose fractions are biologically equivalent to higher doses delivered with smaller-dose fractions given over longer treatment courses.<Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Pulmonary. </Strong>For all
patients with pulmonary metastases, whole-lung irradiation should be considered, even if
complete resolution of overt pulmonary metastatic disease has been achieved with
chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="18"/>  Radiation doses are modulated based on age, the amount of
lung to be irradiated, and pulmonary function.  Doses between  12 Gy and  15 Gy are generally used if whole
lungs are treated. No randomized trial has been done to prove radiation therapy improves survival in this group of patients. An early trial from the intergroup Ewing sarcoma group in the 1970s showed that radiation to the lung improved survival in patients with nonmetastatic disease when added to vincristine, actinomycin, and cyclophosphamide (VAC) compared with VAC alone.<Reference refidx="19"/> However, the addition of doxorubicin to the therapy produced better EFS than the VAC/radiation therapy regimen.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_438"><Title>Other Therapies</Title><Para id="_48">More intensive therapies, many of which incorporate high-dose chemotherapy with
or without total-body irradiation in conjunction with stem cell support, have
not improved EFS rates for patients with bone
and/or bone marrow metastases.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/>; <Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]  For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_138" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">High-Dose Therapy With Stem Cell Support for Ewing Sarcoma</SummaryRef> section.</Para><ItemizedList id="_439" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>High-dose chemotherapy with stem cell support. </Strong><ItemizedList id="_2404" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00987636">Ewing 2008R3 (NCT00987636)</ProtocolRef> was the first phase III, open-label, multicenter, randomized controlled trial conducted for newly diagnosed patients with disseminated Ewing sarcoma who had metastases to bone and/or other sites.<Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]  The study evaluated the EFS and OS effect of treatment with treosulfan and melphalan high-dose chemotherapy  (TreoMel-HDT) followed by infusion of autologous hematopoietic stem cells.  After six cycles of chemotherapy (vincristine, ifosfamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide), consenting patients were randomly assigned to receive either eight cycles of  consolidation therapy (vincristine, dactinomycin, and cyclophosphamide) or consolidation therapy with TreoMel-HDT followed by autologous stem cell reinfusion. Between 2009 and 2018, 109 patients were randomly assigned,  55 of whom received TreoMel-HDT.  There was no significant difference in  3-year EFS rates between patients who received TreoMel-HDT and patients in the control arm (20.9% vs. 19.2%; median follow-up, 3.3 years).</ListItem><ListItem>One of the largest studies was the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00020566">EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99</ProtocolRef> R3 trial  that enrolled 281 patients with primary disseminated metastatic Ewing sarcoma.  Patients were treated with six cycles of vincristine, ifosfamide, doxorubicin, and etoposide followed by high-dose therapy and autologous stem cell transplant. Patients had a  3-year EFS rate of 27% and an OS rate of 34%.  Identified independent prognostic factors included the presence and number of bone lesions, primary tumor volume  greater than 200 mL, age older than 14 years,  additional pulmonary  metastases, and bone marrow involvement.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>The role of high-dose therapy with busulfan-melphalan (BuMel) followed by stem cell rescue was investigated in the prospective randomized <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00020566">EURO-EWING-INTERGROUP-EE99 (NCT00020566)</ProtocolRef> trial. Among patients with isolated pulmonary metastases, there was no difference in 3-year EFS rates (55.7% with BuMel vs. 50.3% with continued chemotherapy and whole-lung radiation therapy; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .21).<Reference refidx="25"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Melphalan. </Strong> At nonmyeloablative doses, melphalan proved to be an active agent in an up-front window study for patients with metastatic disease at diagnosis. However, the cure rate remained extremely low.<Reference refidx="26"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Irinotecan. </Strong>Irinotecan was administered as a single agent in an up-front window study for patients with newly diagnosed metastatic Ewing sarcoma and showed modest activity (partial response in 5 of 24 patients).<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]  Further investigation is needed to determine irinotecan dosing and combinations with other agents for patients with Ewing sarcoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_43_sid_8"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_43_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18525458">Esiashvili N, Goodman M, Marcus RB: Changes in incidence and survival of Ewing sarcoma patients over the past 3 decades: Surveillance Epidemiology and End Results data. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 30 (6): 425-30, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="17584910">Miser JS, Goldsby RE, Chen Z, et al.: Treatment of metastatic Ewing sarcoma/primitive neuroectodermal tumor of bone: evaluation of increasing the dose intensity of chemotherapy--a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 49 (7): 894-900, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="20547982">Ladenstein R, Pötschger U, Le Deley MC, et al.: Primary disseminated multifocal Ewing sarcoma: results of the Euro-EWING 99 trial. J Clin Oncol 28 (20): 3284-91, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="9738574" MedlineID="98408954">Paulussen M, Ahrens S, Craft AW, et al.: Ewing's tumors with primary lung metastases: survival analysis of 114 (European Intergroup) Cooperative Ewing's Sarcoma Studies patients. J Clin Oncol 16 (9): 3044-52, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="9602261" MedlineID="98264971">Paulussen M, Ahrens S, Burdach S, et al.: Primary metastatic (stage IV) Ewing tumor: survival analysis of 171 patients from the EICESS studies. European Intergroup Cooperative Ewing Sarcoma Studies. Ann Oncol 9 (3): 275-81, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="31944574">Halalsheh H, Kaste SC, Krasin MJ, et al.: Clinical impact of post-induction resolution of pulmonary lesions in metastatic Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 67 (4): e28150, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="11435062" MedlineID="21328958">Pinkerton CR, Bataillard A, Guillo S, et al.: Treatment strategies for metastatic Ewing's sarcoma. Eur J Cancer 37 (11): 1338-44, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="15254055">Miser JS, Krailo MD, Tarbell NJ, et al.: Treatment of metastatic Ewing's sarcoma or primitive neuroectodermal tumor of bone: evaluation of combination ifosfamide and etoposide--a Children's Cancer Group and Pediatric Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 22 (14): 2873-6, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="25630954">Magnan H, Goodbody CM, Riedel E, et al.: Ifosfamide dose-intensification for patients with metastatic Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (4): 594-7, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="23065953">Felgenhauer JL, Nieder ML, Krailo MD, et al.: A pilot study of low-dose anti-angiogenic chemotherapy in combination with standard multiagent chemotherapy for patients with newly diagnosed metastatic Ewing sarcoma family of tumors: A Children's Oncology Group (COG) Phase II study NCT00061893. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (3): 409-14, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="36669140">DuBois SG, Krailo MD, Glade-Bender J, et al.: Randomized Phase III Trial of Ganitumab With Interval-Compressed Chemotherapy for Patients With Newly Diagnosed Metastatic Ewing Sarcoma: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 41 (11): 2098-2107, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="19924786">Haeusler J, Ranft A, Boelling T, et al.: The value of local treatment in patients with primary, disseminated, multifocal Ewing sarcoma (PDMES). Cancer 116 (2): 443-50, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="19684633">Burdach S, Thiel U, Schöniger M, et al.: Total body MRI-governed involved compartment irradiation combined with high-dose chemotherapy and stem cell rescue improves long-term survival in Ewing tumor patients with multiple primary bone metastases. Bone Marrow Transplant 45 (3): 483-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="22547005">Paulino AC, Mai WY, Teh BS: Radiotherapy in metastatic ewing sarcoma. Am J Clin Oncol 36 (3): 283-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="25346208">Casey DL, Wexler LH, Meyers PA, et al.: Radiation for bone metastases in Ewing sarcoma and rhabdomyosarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (3): 445-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="9747829" MedlineID="98418601">Donaldson SS, Torrey M, Link MP, et al.: A multidisciplinary study investigating radiotherapy in Ewing's sarcoma: end results of POG #8346. Pediatric Oncology Group. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 42 (1): 125-35, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="25548538">Brown LC, Lester RA, Grams MP, et al.: Stereotactic body radiotherapy for metastatic and recurrent ewing sarcoma and osteosarcoma. Sarcoma 2014: 418270, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="11216713" MedlineID="21084520">Spunt SL, McCarville MB, Kun LE, et al.: Selective use of whole-lung irradiation for patients with Ewing sarcoma family tumors and pulmonary metastases at the time of diagnosis. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 23 (2): 93-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="7029293">Nesbit ME, Perez CA, Tefft M, et al.: Multimodal therapy for the management of primary, nonmetastatic Ewing's sarcoma of bone: an Intergroup Study. Natl Cancer Inst Monogr  (56): 255-62, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="11387352" MedlineID="21281030">Meyers PA, Krailo MD, Ladanyi M, et al.: High-dose melphalan, etoposide, total-body irradiation, and autologous stem-cell reconstitution as consolidation therapy for high-risk Ewing's sarcoma does not improve prognosis. J Clin Oncol 19 (11): 2812-20, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="12915596">Burdach S, Meyer-Bahlburg A, Laws HJ, et al.: High-dose therapy for patients with primary multifocal and early relapsed Ewing's tumors: results of two consecutive regimens assessing the role of total-body irradiation. J Clin Oncol 21 (16): 3072-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="21245159">Thiel U, Wawer A, Wolf P, et al.: No improvement of survival with reduced- versus high-intensity conditioning for allogeneic stem cell transplants in Ewing tumor patients. Ann Oncol 22 (7): 1614-21, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="26030048">Loschi S, Dufour C, Oberlin O, et al.: Tandem high-dose chemotherapy strategy as first-line treatment of primary disseminated multifocal Ewing sarcomas in children, adolescents and young adults. Bone Marrow Transplant 50 (8): 1083-8, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="35427190">Koch R, Gelderblom H, Haveman L, et al.: High-Dose Treosulfan and Melphalan as Consolidation Therapy Versus Standard Therapy for High-Risk (Metastatic) Ewing Sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 40 (21): 2307-2320, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="30188789">Whelan J, Le Deley MC, Dirksen U, et al.: High-Dose Chemotherapy and Blood Autologous Stem-Cell Rescue Compared With Standard Chemotherapy in Localized High-Risk Ewing Sarcoma: Results of Euro-E.W.I.N.G.99 and Ewing-2008. J Clin Oncol : JCO2018782516, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="17254770">Luksch R, Grignani G, Fagioli F, et al.: Response to melphalan in up-front investigational window therapy for patients with metastatic Ewing's family tumours. Eur J Cancer 43 (5): 885-90, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="24019263">Morland B, Platt K, Whelan JS: A phase II window study of irinotecan (CPT-11) in high risk Ewing sarcoma: a Euro-E.W.I.N.G. study. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (3): 442-5, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_51"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043413">recurrent Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_340"> Recurrence of Ewing sarcoma is most common within 2 years of initial diagnosis (approximately 80%).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> However, late relapses occurring more than 5 years from initial diagnosis are more common in Ewing sarcoma (13%; 95% confidence interval, 9.4%–16.5%) than in other pediatric solid tumors.<Reference refidx="3"/> An analysis of the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program database identified 1,351 patients who survived more than 60 months from diagnosis.<Reference refidx="4"/>  Of these patients, 209 died;  144 of the deaths (69%) were attributed to recurrent, progressive Ewing sarcoma.  Black race, male sex, older age at initial diagnosis, and primary tumors of the pelvis and axial skeleton were associated with a higher risk of late death. This analysis covered the period from 1973 to 2013, and the 1,351 patients represented only 38% of the patients in the original sample, which reflects the inferior treatment outcomes from the earlier era. It is possible that patients who reach the 5-year point after more contemporary treatment may not recapitulate this experience.</Para><Para id="_440">The overall prognosis for patients with recurrent Ewing sarcoma is poor. The 5-year survival rate after recurrence is approximately 10% to 15%.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>; <Reference refidx="1"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]  Patients with relapsed or progressive Ewing sarcoma with measurable disease have a 6-month event-free survival (EFS) rate of 13%.<Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] </Para><Para id="_441">Prognostic factors include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_442" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Time to recurrence. </Strong>Time to recurrence is the most important prognostic factor. Patients whose Ewing sarcoma recurred more than 2 years from initial diagnosis had a 5-year survival rate of 30%, versus 7% for patients whose disease recurred within 2 years.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Local and distant recurrence. </Strong>Patients with both local recurrence and distant metastases have a worse outcome than patients with either isolated local recurrence or metastatic recurrence alone.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Isolated pulmonary recurrence. </Strong>Isolated pulmonary recurrence was not an important prognostic factor in a North American series.<Reference refidx="1"/> In the Italian/Scandinavian experience, younger age, longer disease-free interval, and lung-only recurrence were associated with longer progression-free survival (PFS) after recurrence. In this experience, patients with Ewing sarcoma that recurred after initial therapy, which included high-dose therapy with autologous stem cell rescue, were less likely to achieve a second complete remission.<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_225">The selection of treatment for patients with recurrent disease depends on many
factors, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_443" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Site of recurrence.</ListItem><ListItem>Previous treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Individual patient considerations.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_444">There is no standardized second-line treatment for patients with relapsed or refractory  Ewing sarcoma. Most patients in first relapse are treated with conventional systemic chemotherapy. Patients who demonstrate a response to therapy may undergo local control to sites of recurrence.</Para><Para id="_445">Treatment options for recurrent Ewing sarcoma include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_446" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_447" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1987" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_451" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1854" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">High-dose chemotherapy with stem cell support</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_452" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Other therapies</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_447"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_448">Combinations of chemotherapy, such as cyclophosphamide and topotecan or irinotecan   and temozolomide with or without vincristine, are active in recurrent Ewing sarcoma and can be considered for these patients.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Table id="_1874"><Title>Table  7.  Results from Studies that Used Cyclophosphamide and Topotecan Regimens to Treat Patients With Relapsed and/or Refractory Ewing Sarcoma</Title><TGroup Cols="7"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="7" ColWidth="14.28%"/><THead><Row><entry>Study Reference					</entry><entry>Trial Phase (Total No. of Patients)</entry><entry>Median
Age (Range) (y)	</entry><entry>CR/PR</entry><entry>RR</entry><entry>Cyclophosphamide
(mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>)/Topotecan
(mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) × d</entry><entry>Other
Agents
</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1">II = phase II trial; CR = complete response; PR = partial response; R = retrospective; RR = objective response rate; VCR = vincristine. </entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Saylors et al.<Reference refidx="9"/>



</entry><entry>II (17)</entry><entry>13.8 (1–21)
</entry><entry>1/3
</entry><entry>29%
</entry><entry>250 × 5/0.75 × 5

</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>Hunold et al.<Reference refidx="11"/></entry><entry>
R (54)
</entry><entry>17.4 (3–49)
</entry><entry>0/16
</entry><entry>30%
</entry><entry>250 × 5/0.75 × 5
</entry><entry>
None
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Farhat et al.<Reference refidx="15"/></entry><entry>R (14)
</entry><entry>11 (2–19)
</entry><entry>0/3
</entry><entry>21%
</entry><entry>250 × 5/0.75 × 5
</entry><entry>None
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Kebudi et al.<Reference refidx="16"/></entry><entry>R (14)
</entry><entry>13 (3–16)
</entry><entry>2/5
</entry><entry>50%
</entry><entry>250 × 5/0.75 × 5</entry><entry>VCR
</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1872">These studies were retrospective. Prospective trials with clearly defined eligibility cohorts and intent-to-treat analyses are lacking. When combined, these studies accrued 99 patients and observed 3 complete remissions and 27 partial remissions. The objective response rate was 30%.</Para><Table id="_1875"><Title>Table  8.  Results from Studies that Used Temozolomide and Irinotecan Regimens to Treat Patients With Relapsed and/or Refractory Ewing Sarcoma</Title><TGroup Cols="7"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="15.24%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="12.98%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="12.98%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="8.06%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="8.06%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="21.45%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="7" ColWidth="21.20%"/><THead><Row><entry>Study Reference					</entry><entry>Trial Phase (Total No. of Patients)</entry><entry>Median
Age (Range) (y)	</entry><entry>CR/PR</entry><entry>RR</entry><entry>Temozolomide
(mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>)/Irinotecan
(mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) × d × wk</entry><entry>Other
Agents
</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1">I = phase I trial; II = phase II trial; Acta Onc = Acta Oncologica; An Ped = Annals of Pediatrics; Clin Cancer Res = Clinical Cancer Research; Exp Opin = Expert Opinion Investigational Drugs; Clin Transl Oncol = Clinical and Translational Oncology; BEV = bevacizumab; CR = complete response; IV = intravenous; N/A = not applicable; PBC = Pediatric Blood and Cancer; Ped Hem Onc = Pediatric Hematology and Oncology;  PO = oral; PR = partial response; R = retrospective trial; RR = objective response rate; TMS = temsirolimus; UK = unknown; VCR = vincristine. </entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Wagner et al. (PBC, 2007) <Reference refidx="12"/>



</entry><entry>R (16)	</entry><entry>18 (7–33)	</entry><entry>1/3	</entry><entry>29%	</entry><entry>100 × 5/IV 10–20 × 5 × 2	</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>Casey et al. (PBC, 2009) <Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>R (19)	</entry><entry>19.5 (2–40)	</entry><entry>5/7	</entry><entry>63%	</entry><entry>100 × 5/IV 20 × 5 × 2	</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>Hernandez-Marques et al. (An Ped, 2013) <Reference refidx="17"/></entry><entry>R (8)	</entry><entry>13 (6–18)	</entry><entry>0/3	</entry><entry>37%	</entry><entry>80–100 × 5/IV 10–20 × 5 × 2	</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>Raciborska et al. (PBC, 2013) <Reference refidx="14"/></entry><entry>R (22)	</entry><entry>14.3	</entry><entry>5/7	</entry><entry>54%	</entry><entry>125 × 5/IV 50 × 5	</entry><entry>VCR</entry></Row><Row><entry>McKnall-Knapp et al. (PBC, 2010) <Reference refidx="18"/></entry><entry>I (1)	</entry><entry>N/A	</entry><entry>0/1	</entry><entry>100%	</entry><entry>100 × 5/IV 20 × 5 × 2	</entry><entry>VCR</entry></Row><Row><entry>Wagner et al. (PBC, 2010) <Reference refidx="19"/></entry><entry>I (5)	</entry><entry>(&lt;21)	</entry><entry>1/1	</entry><entry>40%	</entry><entry>100–150 × 5/PO 35–90 × 5	</entry><entry>VCR</entry></Row><Row><entry>Wagner et al. (PBC, 2013) <Reference refidx="20"/></entry><entry>I (2)	</entry><entry>20, 22	</entry><entry>1/1	</entry><entry>100%	</entry><entry>150 × 5/PO 90 × 5	</entry><entry>VCR, BEV</entry></Row><Row><entry>Bagatell et al. (PBC, 2014) <Reference refidx="21"/></entry><entry>I (7)	</entry><entry>(&lt;21)	</entry><entry>0/1	</entry><entry>14%	</entry><entry>100–150 × 5/PO 50–90 × 5	</entry><entry>TMS</entry></Row><Row><entry>Kurucu et al. (Ped Hem Onc, 2015) <Reference refidx="22"/></entry><entry>R (20)	</entry><entry>14 (1–18)	</entry><entry>UK	</entry><entry>55%	</entry><entry>100 × 5/IV 20 × 5 × 2	</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>Anderson et al. (Exp Opin, 2008) <Reference refidx="23"/></entry><entry>R (25)	</entry><entry>15	</entry><entry>7/9	</entry><entry>64%	</entry><entry>100 × 5/IV 10 × 5 × 2	</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>Palmerini et al. (Acta Onc, 2018) <Reference refidx="24"/></entry><entry>R (51)	</entry><entry>21 (3–65)	</entry><entry>5/12	</entry><entry>34%	</entry><entry>100 × 5/IV 40 × 5	</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>Salah et al. (Clin Transl Oncol, 2021) <Reference refidx="25"/></entry><entry>R (53)</entry><entry>20 (5–45)</entry><entry>1/11</entry><entry>28%</entry><entry>100 × 5/IV 40 × 5  in 21 patients; IV 50 × 5 in 24 patients; IV 20 × 5 × 2 in 6 patients</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>Xu et al. (Clin Cancer Res, 2023) <Reference refidx="26"/> 5-day schedule: </entry><entry>II (24) </entry><entry>16.5 ± 7.9</entry><entry>1/4    </entry><entry>20.8%</entry><entry>100 × 5/50 × 5</entry><entry>VCR 1.4 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> day 1 </entry></Row><Row><entry>Xu et al. (Clin Cancer Res, 2023) <Reference refidx="26"/> 10-day schedule: </entry><entry>II (22) </entry><entry>15.2 ± 6.3 </entry><entry>1/11 </entry><entry> 54.5% </entry><entry>100 × 5/20 × 5 × 2</entry><entry>VCR 1.4 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> days 1 and 8 </entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1873">Most of these studies were retrospective, not prospective. There are only four prospective trials with well-defined eligibility cohorts and report by intent to treat.  In addition, there is significant variability among the reports in doses and dose schedules of irinotecan and temozolomide and the use of additional agents. When combined, these studies accrued 275 patients and observed 21 complete remissions and 82 partial remissions. The objective response rate was 37.5%.</Para><Para id="_449">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_450" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>One phase II study of topotecan and cyclophosphamide showed a response in 6 of 17 patients with Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="9"/> In a similar trial in Germany, 16 of 49 patients had a clinical response.<Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem><ListItem>Several retrospective studies have demonstrated the activity of temozolomide and irinotecan in patients with recurrent Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="24"/>   <OrderedList id="_2405" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>In the largest retrospective multicenter study of the combination of temozolomide and irinotecan in patients with recurrent and primary refractory Ewing sarcoma, 51 patients (66% of patients were aged ≥18 years; median age, 21 years) were treated with temozolomide (100 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/day orally) and irinotecan (40 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/day intravenously), on days 1 to 5, every 21 days. Twenty-five percent of the patients were in first relapse/progression, while the remainder of the patients were in second or greater relapse/progression.<Reference refidx="24"/><ItemizedList id="_1853" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Five patients (10%) achieved complete remissions, 12 patients (24%) achieved partial remissions, and 19 patients (37%) had stable disease, with a disease control rate of 71%.</ListItem><ListItem>On univariate analysis, the only two factors predicting  response to temozolomide and irinotecan in PFS were performance score and lactate dehydrogenase levels.</ListItem><ListItem>Two patients were rechallenged with temozolomide and irinotecan after disease remission was induced.  Both patients achieved partial remissions on rechallenge. One patient's remission lasted at least 15 cycles and the other remission lasted 22 cycles.<Reference refidx="24"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial compared two schedules of irinotecan given in combination with vincristine and temozolomide for the treatment of recurrent Ewing sarcoma. One schedule administered irinotecan 50 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> daily for 5 days (d × 5) and the other administered irinotecan 20 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> daily for 5 days for two consecutive weeks (10 doses; d × 5 × 2).<Reference refidx="26"/><ItemizedList id="_2456" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The objective response rate at 12 weeks was lower for the patients treated on the d × 5 schedule (5 of 24; 20.8%) than for patients treated on the d × 5 × 2 schedule (12 of 22; 54.5%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .019).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A retrospective review of published series compared the results of treatment with irinotecan and temozolomide with a 10-day schedule to treatment with a 5-day schedule.<Reference refidx="27"/><ItemizedList id="_2457" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Among 89 patients treated with a 10-day irinotecan schedule, there were 47 objective responses (53%). </ListItem><ListItem>Among 180 patients treated with a 5-day irinotecan schedule, there were 52 responses (29%).  </ListItem><ListItem>The two studies that used the 5-day irinotecan schedule reported median times to progression of 3.0 and 3.9 months, respectively.  </ListItem><ListItem>The four studies that used the 10-day irinotecan schedule reported median times to progression of 4.6, 5.5, 8.3, and 9.5 months, respectively.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem><ListItem>The combination of docetaxel either with gemcitabine or irinotecan has achieved objective responses in patients with relapsed Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>High-dose ifosfamide (3 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> per day for 5 days = 15 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) has shown activity in patients whose Ewing sarcoma recurred after therapy that included standard ifosfamide (1.8 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> per day for 5 days = 9 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>).<Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>European investigators are performing a prospective study to compare four regimens for the treatment of patients with recurrent Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="32"/> The rEECur phase II/III adaptive multiarm trial is the first to compare regimens in a randomized design. Patients aged 4 to 50 years with refractory or recurrent Ewing sarcoma and healthy enough to receive chemotherapy were randomly assigned to receive one of four regimens: topotecan and cyclophosphamide (TC), irinotecan and temozolomide (IT), gemcitabine and docetaxel (GD), or high-dose ifosfamide.<Reference refidx="33"/><ItemizedList id="_2536" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Pairwise comparison showed that GD was the least effective.</ListItem><ListItem>Imaging response and survival outcomes after TC were marginally better than after IT. However, in a phase II comparison, ifosfamide had significantly better PFS and OS than TC. As a result, ifosfamide was the most effective regimen in this setting, although with significant renal and neurological toxicity. </ListItem><ListItem>The study is ongoing and has recruited over 570 patients. The study is now comparing  ifosfamide and lenvatinib with ifosfamide, carboplatin, and etoposide.<Reference refidx="34"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1986"><Title>Local Therapy for Relapsed Disease</Title><SummarySection id="_1987"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_1988">Aggressive surgery (such as amputation or hemipelvectomy) may be considered for patients with nonmetastatic locally recurrent Ewing sarcoma, even if the prognosis is limited.<Reference refidx="35"/></Para><Para id="_1989">The role of pulmonary metastasectomy in patients with relapsed disease and isolated lung metastases is controversial.<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_451"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_287">Radiation therapy may be used (similar to first-line strategies) for patients who relapsed after the beginning of front-line therapy and/or who present only with relapsed pulmonary metastases.<Reference refidx="36"/>; <Reference refidx="38"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] Radiation therapy to bone
lesions may provide palliation, although radical resection may improve outcome.<Reference refidx="2"/> Patients with pulmonary metastases who have not received radiation therapy to the lungs should be considered for whole-lung irradiation and/or treated with stereotactic body radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="39"/>; <Reference refidx="38"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>];  Residual disease in the lung may be surgically
removed.
</Para><Para id="_2492">Palliation of painful lesions in children with recurrent or progressive disease can be achieved using a short course (10 or fewer fractions) of radiation therapy. In a retrospective study of 213 children with various malignancies, who were treated with such short course radiation therapy, 85% of patients had complete or partial pain relief, with low levels of toxicity.<Reference refidx="40"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1854"><Title>High-Dose Chemotherapy With Stem Cell Support</Title><Para id="_1855">Aggressive
attempts to control the disease, including myeloablative regimens, have been used, but there is no evidence at this time to conclude that myeloablative therapy is superior to standard chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/>; <Reference refidx="44"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_1856">Most published reports about the use of high-dose therapy and stem cell support for patients with high-risk Ewing sarcoma have significant flaws in methodology. The most common issue is the comparison of this high-risk group with an inappropriate control group. Patients with Ewing sarcoma at high risk of treatment failure who received high-dose therapy are compared with patients who did not receive high-dose therapy. Patients who undergo high-dose therapy must respond to systemic therapy, remain alive and respond to treatment long enough to reach the time at which stem cell therapy can be applied, be free of comorbid toxicity that precludes high-dose therapy, and have an adequate stem cell collection. Patients who undergo high-dose therapy and stem cell support are a highly selected group. Comparing this patient group with all patients with high-risk Ewing sarcoma is inappropriate and leads to the erroneous conclusion that this strategy improves outcome.</Para><Para id="_1857">Surveys of patients who underwent allogeneic  hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT)  for recurrent Ewing sarcoma did  not  show improved  EFS when compared with patients who underwent autologous HSCT. In addition, allogeneic HSCT was
associated with a higher complication rate.<Reference refidx="41"/>  <Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_452"><Title>Other Therapies</Title><Para id="_453">Other therapies that have been studied in the treatment of recurrent Ewing sarcoma include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_454" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Monoclonal antibody therapy. </Strong>Monoclonal antibodies against the insulin-like growth factor  1 receptor (IGF1R) are reported to produce objective responses in approximately 10% of patients with metastatic recurrent Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] These studies suggested that time-to-progression was prolonged compared with historical controls. Objective responses have been reported in studies combining the mTOR inhibitor temsirolimus with an IGF1R antibody. In a phase II trial of ten patients who were treated with an IGF1R antibody and a CDK4/6 inhibitor, no responses were reported.<Reference refidx="51"/> Stratification by IGF1R expression (detected by immunohistochemistry) in one of the studies did not predict clinical outcome in patients with Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/> Further studies are needed to identify patients who are likely to benefit from IGF1R therapy. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Immunotherapy. </Strong>Immunotherapy with antigen-specific T cells is being studied in patients with Ewing sarcoma because immune-mediated killing attacks the tumor in a different way, unlike conventional therapies (that rely on pathways), which such tumors often resist.  Several potential chimeric antigen receptors target antigens that have been identified for Ewing sarcomas. These include HER2 (human epidermal growth factor receptor 2),<Reference refidx="54"/> GD2,<Reference refidx="55"/> CD99 (MIC2 antigens),<Reference refidx="56"/> and STEAP1 (six-transmembrane epithelial antigens of the prostate).<Reference refidx="57"/>   Some of these therapies are in early-phase testing in patients with sarcomas.<Reference refidx="54"/><Para id="_2537"> Treatment with single-agent and combined immune checkpoint inhibitors has shown no activity in patients with recurrent Ewing sarcoma. There were no responses in five patients with Ewing sarcoma treated on a clinical  trial with single-agent nivolumab or the combination of nivolumab and ipilimumab.<Reference refidx="58"/> A trial of pembrolizumab included 13 patients with  Ewing sarcoma whose cancer did not respond to the treatment.<Reference refidx="59"/> Another trial of nivolumab reported that there were no responses in 11 patients with Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="60"/> The Children's Oncology Group (COG) conducted a phase I/II trial of the combination of nivolumab and ipilimumab in children with recurrent sarcomas.<Reference refidx="61"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] Only 1 of 14 patients with Ewing sarcoma exhibited a sustained partial response.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Multitargeted kinase inhibitors.</Strong> <ItemizedList id="_2481" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Regorafenib:</Strong> A phase II study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02048371">SARC024 [NCT02048371]</ProtocolRef>) evaluated regorafenib monotherapy  in 30 patients with metastatic recurrent Ewing sarcoma and other translocation-positive tumors, including <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> sarcoma.<Reference refidx="62"/> Modest activity was observed, with a 10% objective response rate by response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST). The median PFS was 14.8 weeks.<Para id="_2506">A prospective, randomized, double-blind trial compared regorafenib with placebo in patients with recurrent Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="63"/> Of 36 patients who were evaluable for efficacy, 23 received regorafenib and 13 received placebo. The patients randomly assigned to regorafenib had an 8-week PFS rate of 56%, compared with 7.7% for patients randomly assigned to placebo. The median PFS was 11.4 weeks for patients who received regorafenib and 3.9 weeks for patients who received placebo. The response rate was 13% in patients treated with regorafenib. Ten patients in the placebo group crossed over to receive regorafenib after progression. Although the results were not significant, the authors suggested that this trial provided some evidence of benefit for the use of regorafenib in patients with relapsed Ewing sarcoma.</Para><Para id="_2504">In addition to this single-agent experience, regorafenib was shown to be tolerable on a sequential schedule with vincristine and irinotecan in 21 pediatric patients. Five patients with relapsed Ewing sarcoma were included as part of this phase I trial. Three of five patients had partial responses with this regimen.<Reference refidx="64"/></Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Anlotinib:</Strong> A study completed in China evaluated treatment with anlotinib (an oral receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor targeting vascular endothelial growth factor receptors 1–3, fibroblast growth factors 1–3, platelet-derived growth factor receptors alpha and beta, c-KIT,  and RET) given along with vincristine and irinotecan for patients with relapsed or refractory Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="65"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]  Patients were treated in two cohorts. Cohort A included patients aged 16 years and older, and cohort B included patients younger than 16 years.  At 12 weeks, patients in cohort A demonstrated an objective response rate of 62.5% (14 of 23 patients), and patients in cohort B demonstrated an objective response rate of 83.3% (11 of 12 patients). Anlotinib has not yet received approval from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Cabozantinib:</Strong> A real-world evidence analysis included 16 patients with relapsed or refractory Ewing sarcoma who were treated with cabozantinib. Four patients had objective responses (25% objective response rate).<Reference refidx="66"/> <Para id="_2510">Thirty-nine patients (older than 12 years) with relapsed Ewing sarcoma were assessable for response after cabozantinib monotherapy.<Reference refidx="67"/> Patients younger than 16 years received 40 mg daily, and patients aged 16 years and older received 60 mg daily. Most patients were older than 18 years. Ten patients (26%) had responses (all partial responses).</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Strategies to target fusion proteins.</Strong><ItemizedList id="_2541" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Lurbinectedin:</Strong> Lurbinectedin is structurally related to trabectedin, but it has been more effective in suppressing the activity of the oncogenic transcription factor EWS::FLI in mice in preclinical studies.  In an open-label, single-arm, basket phase II trial,  clinical antitumor activity was seen. In a cohort of 28 adult patients with confirmed Ewing sarcoma and relapsed disease, the objective response rate was 14.3%, the clinical benefit rate (response or disease stabilization for &gt;4 months) was 39.3%, and the disease control rate (response or disease stabilization of any duration) was 57.1%.<Reference refidx="68"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>TK216:</Strong> An agent known as TK216 is thought to interfere with interactions between the EWSR1::FLI1 fusion oncoprotein and key proteins critical for its oncogenic function, although it has also been shown to disrupt microtubules.<Reference refidx="69"/> In a phase I/II trial of TK216 in combination with vincristine in patients with recurrent Ewing sarcoma, three responses were observed. However, the overall response rate was only 3.5% across the whole trial.<Reference refidx="70"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2455">Sequencing of recurrent and refractory Ewing sarcoma tumors from pediatric (n = 79) and young adult patients (n = 25) enrolled in the National Cancer Institute (NCI)-COG Pediatric Molecular Analysis for Therapeutic Choice (MATCH) trial revealed genomic alterations that were considered actionable for treatment on MATCH study arms in 8 of 104 tumors (7.7%), including <GeneName>EZH2</GeneName> variants in 2 of 104 tumors (1.9%).<Reference refidx="71"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_383"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043413">recurrent Ewing sarcoma/peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation for Recurrent Ewing Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_384">Information about NCI-supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_2532">The following is an example of a national and/or institutional clinical trial that is currently being conducted:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2533" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04890093">NCT04890093</ProtocolRef></Strong> (Vincristine and Temozolomide in Combination With PEN-866 for Adolescents and Young Adults With Relapsed or Refractory Solid Tumors)<Strong>:</Strong> PEN-866 is a novel molecule consisting of SN-38 conjugated to a heat shock protein 90 (HSP90) inhibitor that has been shown to have a pharmacokinetic advantage over irinotecan in preclinical models. In preclinical models of Ewing sarcoma, PEN-866 had superior efficacy and pharmacodynamics compared with irinotecan. For the phase I portion of this trial, any patient aged 12 to 39 years with a relapsed or refractory solid tumor is eligible. The phase II portion of this trial will enroll only patients aged 12 to 39 years with relapsed or refractory Ewing sarcoma or rhabdomyosarcoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_383_sid_16"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_383_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18506764">Leavey PJ, Mascarenhas L, Marina N, et al.: Prognostic factors for patients with Ewing sarcoma (EWS) at first recurrence following multi-modality therapy: A report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 51 (3): 334-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21442722">Stahl M, Ranft A, Paulussen M, et al.: Risk of recurrence and survival after relapse in patients with Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 57 (4): 549-53, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19966206">Wasilewski-Masker K, Liu Q, Yasui Y, et al.: Late recurrence in pediatric cancer: a report from the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study. J Natl Cancer Inst 101 (24): 1709-20, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="26891183">Davenport JR, Vo KT, Goldsby R, et al.: Conditional Survival and Predictors of Late Death in Patients With Ewing Sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 63 (6): 1091-5, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15781881">Barker LM, Pendergrass TW, Sanders JE, et al.: Survival after recurrence of Ewing's sarcoma family of tumors. J Clin Oncol 23 (19): 4354-62, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16621429">Bacci G, Longhi A, Ferrari S, et al.: Pattern of relapse in 290 patients with nonmetastatic Ewing's sarcoma family tumors treated at a single institution with adjuvant and neoadjuvant chemotherapy between 1972 and 1999. Eur J Surg Oncol 32 (9): 974-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="34496122">Collier AB, Krailo MD, Dang HM, et al.: Outcome of patients with relapsed or progressive Ewing sarcoma enrolled on cooperative group phase 2 clinical trials: A report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 68 (12): e29333, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25585917">Ferrari S, Luksch R, Hall KS, et al.: Post-relapse survival in patients with Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (6): 994-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11481351" MedlineID="21374152">Saylors RL, Stine KC, Sullivan J, et al.: Cyclophosphamide plus topotecan in children with recurrent or refractory solid tumors: a Pediatric Oncology Group phase II study. J Clin Oncol 19 (15): 3463-9, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="16782749">McTiernan A, Driver D, Michelagnoli MP, et al.: High dose chemotherapy with bone marrow or peripheral stem cell rescue is an effective treatment option for patients with relapsed or progressive Ewing's sarcoma family of tumours. Ann Oncol 17 (8): 1301-5, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="16411206">Hunold A, Weddeling N, Paulussen M, et al.: Topotecan and cyclophosphamide in patients with refractory or relapsed Ewing tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 47 (6): 795-800, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="16317751">Wagner LM, McAllister N, Goldsby RE, et al.: Temozolomide and intravenous irinotecan for treatment of advanced Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 48 (2): 132-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="19637327">Casey DA, Wexler LH, Merchant MS, et al.: Irinotecan and temozolomide for Ewing sarcoma: the Memorial Sloan-Kettering experience. Pediatr Blood Cancer 53 (6): 1029-34, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="23776128">Raciborska A, Bilska K, Drabko K, et al.: Vincristine, irinotecan, and temozolomide in patients with relapsed and refractory Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (10): 1621-5, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="23042020">Farhat R, Raad R, Khoury NJ, et al.: Cyclophosphamide and topotecan as first-line salvage therapy in patients with relapsed ewing sarcoma at a single institution. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 35 (5): 356-60, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="23484903">Kebudi R, Cakir FB, Gorgun O, et al.: A modified protocol with vincristine, topotecan, and cyclophosphamide for recurrent/progressive ewing sarcoma family tumors. Pediatr Hematol Oncol 30 (3): 170-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="23332825">Hernández-Marqués C, Lassaletta-Atienza A, Ruiz Hernández A, et al.: [Irinotecan plus temozolomide in refractory or relapsed pediatric solid tumors]. An Pediatr (Barc) 79 (2): 68-74, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="20405511">McNall-Knapp RY, Williams CN, Reeves EN, et al.: Extended phase I evaluation of vincristine, irinotecan, temozolomide, and antibiotic in children with refractory solid tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 54 (7): 909-15, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="20049936">Wagner LM, Perentesis JP, Reid JM, et al.: Phase I trial of two schedules of vincristine, oral irinotecan, and temozolomide (VOIT) for children with relapsed or refractory solid tumors: a Children's Oncology Group phase I consortium study. Pediatr Blood Cancer 54 (4): 538-45, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="23630159">Wagner L, Turpin B, Nagarajan R, et al.: Pilot study of vincristine, oral irinotecan, and temozolomide (VOIT regimen) combined with bevacizumab in pediatric patients with recurrent solid tumors or brain tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (9): 1447-51, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="24249672">Bagatell R, Norris R, Ingle AM, et al.: Phase 1 trial of temsirolimus in combination with irinotecan and temozolomide in children, adolescents and young adults with relapsed or refractory solid tumors: a Children's Oncology Group Study. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (5): 833-9, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="25252096">Kurucu N, Sari N, Ilhan IE: Irinotecan and temozolamide treatment for relapsed Ewing sarcoma: a single-center experience and review of the literature. Pediatr Hematol Oncol 32 (1): 50-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="18922107">Anderson P, Kopp L, Anderson N, et al.: Novel bone cancer drugs: investigational agents and control paradigms for primary bone sarcomas (Ewing's sarcoma and osteosarcoma). Expert Opin Investig Drugs 17 (11): 1703-15, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="29533113">Palmerini E, Jones RL, Setola E, et al.: Irinotecan and temozolomide in recurrent Ewing sarcoma: an analysis in 51 adult and pediatric patients. Acta Oncol 57 (7): 958-964, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="32761317">Salah S, To YH, Khozouz O, et al.: Irinotecan and temozolomide chemotherapy in paediatric and adult populations with relapsed Ewing Sarcoma. Clin Transl Oncol 23 (4): 757-763, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="36622702">Xu J, Xie L, Sun X, et al.: Longer versus Shorter Schedules of Vincristine, Irinotecan, and Temozolomide (VIT) for Relapsed or Refractory Ewing Sarcoma: A Randomized Controlled Phase 2 Trial. Clin Cancer Res 29 (6): 1040-1046, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="36184748">Slotkin EK, Meyers PA: Irinotecan dose schedule for the treatment of Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 70 (1): e30005, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="22363068">Fox E, Patel S, Wathen JK, et al.: Phase II study of sequential gemcitabine followed by docetaxel for recurrent Ewing sarcoma, osteosarcoma, or unresectable or locally recurrent chondrosarcoma: results of Sarcoma Alliance for Research Through Collaboration Study 003. Oncologist 17 (3): 321, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="19727011">Mora J, Cruz CO, Parareda A, et al.: Treatment of relapsed/refractory pediatric sarcomas with gemcitabine and docetaxel. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 31 (10): 723-9, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="25164234">Yoon JH, Kwon MM, Park HJ, et al.: A study of docetaxel and irinotecan in children and young adults with recurrent or refractory Ewing sarcoma family of tumors. BMC Cancer 14: 622, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="19142994">Ferrari S, del Prever AB, Palmerini E, et al.: Response to high-dose ifosfamide in patients with advanced/recurrent Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 52 (5): 581-4, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="32">McCabe MG, Moroz V, Khan M, et al.: Results of the first interim assessment of rEECur, an international randomized controlled trial of chemotherapy for the treatment of recurrent and primary refractory Ewing sarcoma. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  37 (Suppl 15): A-11007, 2019. <ExternalRef xref="https://ascopubs.org/doi/10.1200/JCO.2019.37.15_suppl.11007">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed June 29, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="33">McCabe MG, Kirton L, Khan M, et al.: Results of the second interim assessment of rEECur, an international randomized controlled trial of chemotherapy for the treatment of recurrent and primary refractory Ewing sarcoma (RR-ES). [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  38 (Suppl 15): A-11502, 2020. <ExternalRef xref="https://ascopubs.org/doi/abs/10.1200/JCO.2020.38.15_suppl.11502">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed June 29, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="38775200">Strauss SJ, Berlanga P, McCabe MG: Emerging therapies in Ewing sarcoma. Curr Opin Oncol 36 (4): 297-304, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="33292535">Gerrand C, Bate J, Seddon B, et al.: Seeking international consensus on approaches to primary tumour treatment in Ewing sarcoma. Clin Sarcoma Res 10 (1): 21, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="11900241" MedlineID="21896914">Rodriguez-Galindo C, Billups CA, Kun LE, et al.: Survival after recurrence of Ewing tumors: the St Jude Children's Research Hospital experience, 1979-1999. Cancer 94 (2): 561-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="14736525">Briccoli A, Rocca M, Ferrari S, et al.: Surgery for lung metastases in Ewing's sarcoma of bone. Eur J Surg Oncol 30 (1): 63-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="30244879">Scobioala S, Ranft A, Wolters H, et al.: Impact of Whole Lung Irradiation on Survival Outcome in Patients With Lung Relapsed Ewing Sarcoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 102 (3): 584-592, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="33305087">Liu KX, Chen YH, Kozono D, et al.: Phase I/II Study of Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy for Pulmonary Metastases in Pediatric Patients. Adv Radiat Oncol 5 (6): 1267-1273, 2020 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="36642970">Sudmeier LJ, Madden N, Zhang C, et al.: Palliative radiotherapy for children: Symptom response and treatment-associated toxicity according to radiation therapy dose and fractionation. Pediatr Blood Cancer 70 (4): e30195, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="11142486" MedlineID="21022095">Burdach S, van Kaick B, Laws HJ, et al.: Allogeneic and autologous stem-cell transplantation in advanced Ewing tumors. An update after long-term follow-up from two centers of the European Intergroup study EICESS. Stem-Cell Transplant Programs at Düsseldorf University Medical Center, Germany and St. Anna Kinderspital, Vienna, Austria. Ann Oncol 11 (11): 1451-62, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="12915596">Burdach S, Meyer-Bahlburg A, Laws HJ, et al.: High-dose therapy for patients with primary multifocal and early relapsed Ewing's tumors: results of two consecutive regimens assessing the role of total-body irradiation. J Clin Oncol 21 (16): 3072-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="33007495">Pawlowska AB, Sun V, Calvert GT, et al.: Long-Term Follow-up of High-Dose Chemotherapy with Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation in Children and Young Adults with Metastatic or Relapsed Ewing Sarcoma: A Single-Institution Experience. Transplant Cell Ther 27 (1): 72.e1-72.e7, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="18246113">Gardner SL, Carreras J, Boudreau C, et al.: Myeloablative therapy with autologous stem cell rescue for patients with Ewing sarcoma. Bone Marrow Transplant 41 (10): 867-72, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="18679365">Gilman AL, Oesterheld J: Myeloablative chemotherapy with autologous stem cell rescue for Ewing sarcoma. Bone Marrow Transplant 42 (11): 761; author reply 763, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="46">Eapen M: Response to Dr Gilman. Bone Marrow Transplant  42 (11): 763, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="22184397">Malempati S, Weigel B, Ingle AM, et al.: Phase I/II trial and pharmacokinetic study of cixutumumab in pediatric patients with refractory solid tumors and Ewing sarcoma: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 30 (3): 256-62, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="22025154">Juergens H, Daw NC, Geoerger B, et al.: Preliminary efficacy of the anti-insulin-like growth factor type 1 receptor antibody figitumumab in patients with refractory Ewing sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 29 (34): 4534-40, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="22025149">Pappo AS, Patel SR, Crowley J, et al.: R1507, a monoclonal antibody to the insulin-like growth factor 1 receptor, in patients with recurrent or refractory Ewing sarcoma family of tumors: results of a phase II Sarcoma Alliance for Research through Collaboration study. J Clin Oncol 29 (34): 4541-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="22508822">Tap WD, Demetri G, Barnette P, et al.: Phase II study of ganitumab, a fully human anti-type-1 insulin-like growth factor receptor antibody, in patients with metastatic Ewing family tumors or desmoplastic small round cell tumors. J Clin Oncol 30 (15): 1849-56, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="37306107">Shulman DS, Merriam P, Choy E, et al.: Phase 2 trial of palbociclib and ganitumab in patients with relapsed Ewing sarcoma. Cancer Med 12 (14): 15207-15216, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="22465830">Naing A, LoRusso P, Fu S, et al.: Insulin growth factor-receptor (IGF-1R) antibody cixutumumab combined with the mTOR inhibitor temsirolimus in patients with refractory Ewing's sarcoma family tumors. Clin Cancer Res 18 (9): 2625-31, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="23477833">Schwartz GK, Tap WD, Qin LX, et al.: Cixutumumab and temsirolimus for patients with bone and soft-tissue sarcoma: a multicentre, open-label, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 14 (4): 371-82, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="25800760">Ahmed N, Brawley VS, Hegde M, et al.: Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor 2 (HER2) -Specific Chimeric Antigen Receptor-Modified T Cells for the Immunotherapy of HER2-Positive Sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 33 (15): 1688-96, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="18978797">Pule MA, Savoldo B, Myers GD, et al.: Virus-specific T cells engineered to coexpress tumor-specific receptors: persistence and antitumor activity in individuals with neuroblastoma. Nat Med 14 (11): 1264-70, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="11016640">Scotlandi K, Baldini N, Cerisano V, et al.: CD99 engagement: an effective therapeutic strategy for Ewing tumors. Cancer Res 60 (18): 5134-42, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="22080479">Grunewald TG, Diebold I, Esposito I, et al.: STEAP1 is associated with the invasive and oxidative stress phenotype of Ewing tumors. Mol Cancer Res 10 (1): 52-65, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="29370992">D'Angelo SP, Mahoney MR, Van Tine BA, et al.: Nivolumab with or without ipilimumab treatment for metastatic sarcoma (Alliance A091401): two open-label, non-comparative, randomised, phase 2 trials. Lancet Oncol 19 (3): 416-426, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="28988646">Tawbi HA, Burgess M, Bolejack V, et al.: Pembrolizumab in advanced soft-tissue sarcoma and bone sarcoma (SARC028): a multicentre, two-cohort, single-arm, open-label, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 18 (11): 1493-1501, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="32192573">Davis KL, Fox E, Merchant MS, et al.: Nivolumab in children and young adults with relapsed or refractory solid tumours or lymphoma (ADVL1412): a multicentre, open-label, single-arm, phase 1-2 trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (4): 541-550, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="36190525">Davis KL, Fox E, Isikwei E, et al.: A Phase I/II Trial of Nivolumab plus Ipilimumab in Children and Young Adults with Relapsed/Refractory Solid Tumors: A Children's Oncology Group Study ADVL1412. Clin Cancer Res 28 (23): 5088-5097, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="35950293">Attia S, Bolejack V, Ganjoo KN, et al.: A phase II trial of regorafenib in patients with advanced Ewing sarcoma and related tumors of soft tissue and bone: SARC024 trial results. Cancer Med 12 (2): 1532-1539, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="37914801">Duffaud F, Blay JY, Le Cesne A, et al.: Regorafenib in patients with advanced Ewing sarcoma: results of a non-comparative, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicentre Phase II study. Br J Cancer 129 (12): 1940-1948, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="37606641">Casanova M, Bautista F, Campbell-Hewson Q, et al.: Regorafenib plus Vincristine and Irinotecan in Pediatric Patients with Recurrent/Refractory Solid Tumors: An Innovative Therapy for Children with Cancer Study. Clin Cancer Res 29 (21): 4341-4351, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="33611805">Xu J, Xie L, Sun X, et al.: Anlotinib, Vincristine, and Irinotecan for Advanced Ewing Sarcoma After Failure of Standard Multimodal Therapy: A Two-Cohort, Phase Ib/II Trial. Oncologist 26 (7): e1256-e1262, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="37724607">Peretz Soroka H, Vora T, Noujaim J, et al.: Real-world experience of tyrosine kinase inhibitors in children, adolescents and adults with relapsed or refractory bone tumours: A Canadian Sarcoma Research and Clinical Collaboration (CanSaRCC) study. Cancer Med 12 (18): 18872-18881, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="32078813">Italiano A, Mir O, Mathoulin-Pelissier S, et al.: Cabozantinib in patients with advanced Ewing sarcoma or osteosarcoma (CABONE): a multicentre, single-arm, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (3): 446-455, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="35486638">Subbiah V, Braña I, Longhi A, et al.: Antitumor Activity of Lurbinectedin, a Selective Inhibitor of Oncogene Transcription, in Patients with Relapsed Ewing Sarcoma: Results of a Basket Phase II Study. Clin Cancer Res 28 (13): 2762-2770, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="35803262">Povedano JM, Li V, Lake KE, et al.: TK216 targets microtubules in Ewing sarcoma cells. Cell Chem Biol 29 (8): 1325-1332.e4, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="38954782">Meyers PA, Federman N, Daw N, et al.: Open-Label, Multicenter, Phase I/II, First-in-Human Trial of TK216: A First-Generation EWS::FLI1 Fusion Protein Antagonist in Ewing Sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 42 (31): 3725-3734, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="35353553">Parsons DW, Janeway KA, Patton DR, et al.: Actionable Tumor Alterations and Treatment Protocol Enrollment of Pediatric and Young Adult Patients With Refractory Cancers in the National Cancer Institute-Children's Oncology Group Pediatric MATCH Trial. J Clin Oncol 40 (20): 2224-2234, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1910"><Title>Undifferentiated Small Round Cell (Ewing-Like) Sarcomas</Title><Para id="_1991">There are undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas of bone and soft tissue that do not have the translocations of the  <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> gene and a gene in the ETS family. These sarcomas appear to be biologically distinctive from Ewing sarcoma with <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> and ETS gene family member translocations. This includes tumors with translocations of the <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene or the <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> gene, as well as tumors with <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName> translocations involving non-ETS gene family members. These groups occur much less frequently than Ewing sarcoma, and descriptions of clinical outcomes for these patients are based on smaller sample sizes and less homogeneous treatment. Therefore, patient outcomes are hard to quantitate with precision. Most of these tumors have been treated with regimens designed for Ewing sarcoma, and there is consensus that they were often included in past clinical trials for the treatment of Ewing sarcoma, sometimes called translocation-negative Ewing sarcoma. There is agreement that these tumors are sufficiently different from Ewing sarcoma; they should be stratified and analyzed separately from Ewing sarcoma with the common translocations, even if they are treated with similar therapy. The summary of these entities are presented below and follows the categorization of the 2020 World Health Organization (WHO) Classification of Tumours: Soft Tissue and Bone Tumours (5th edition).<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><SummarySection id="_1911"><Title>Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas With <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> Genetic Alterations</Title><SummarySection id="_1912"><Title>Clinical presentation</Title><Para id="_1913">Undifferentiated round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName> rearrangements account for about 5% of all <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>-negative rearranged sarcomas and more commonly affects males. More than 70% of cases occur in patients younger than 18 years (median age at diagnosis, 13–15 years).<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] These tumors more commonly arise in the bones of the pelvis and extremities, and metastases are present in approximately 30% of cases.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1994"><Title>Genomic characteristics</Title><Para id="_1995">The most common types of undifferentiated small round cell sarcoma with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> rearrangements are those with the <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName> rearrangement.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="4"/> The <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>MAML3</GeneName> rearrangement is less commonly observed, but tumors with this translocation appear to have biological characteristics that are similar to tumors with the <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName> rearrangement.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_1996"><GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> internal tandem duplications (ITD) involving exon 15 are observed in infantile undifferentiated round cell sarcomas and primitive myxoid mesenchymal tumors of infancy (PMMTI).<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> These two entities have significant histological overlap and similar transcriptional profiles, and they are distinguished by more prominent myxoid stroma in PMMTI. <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> ITD may be occasionally observed in undifferentiated round cell sarcomas arising in older children.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_1997"><GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> ITD have been reported in 90% of cases of clear cell sarcoma of the kidney, with a smaller subset harboring <GeneName>YWHAE</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM2B/E</GeneName> or <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName> gene fusions.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062789#_10" url="/types/kidney/hp/wilms-treatment-pdq">Clear Cell Sarcoma of the Kidney</SummaryRef> section in Wilms Tumor and Other Childhood Kidney Tumors Treatment.</Para><Para id="_1998">The transcriptional profiles induced by <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> gene fusions, <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> ITD, and <GeneName>YWHAE</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM2B/E</GeneName> fusions appear to be similar to each other and distinctive from that of Ewing sarcoma.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> As an example, elevated BCOR expression is observed across all of these entities, which can be useful in distinguishing these entities from other undifferentiated small round cell tumors.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1914"><Title>Treatment of undifferentiated round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> genetic alterations</Title><Para id="_1915">When treated with Ewing sarcoma–like therapies, 75% of patients show significant treatment-associated pathological responses. In one series of 36 cases, the 3-year and 5-year survival rates were  93% and 72%, respectively.<Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] In another series of 26 patients, the 5-year overall survival (OS) rate was  76.5%, and survival was better for patients who received induction therapy using an  Ewing sarcoma–type regimen.<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] Most of the tumors in these series arose in the bone. A retrospective survey of European cancer centers identified 148 patients with undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas who did not have an Ewing sarcoma–related fusion gene.<Reference refidx="13"/> Of the 148 patients, 88 (60%) had <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas (median age, 32 years; range 7–78 years), 33 (22%) had <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas (median age, 17 years; range 5–91 years), and 27 (18%) had unclassified undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas (median age, 37 years; range 4–70 years). Of the 148 patients, 101 (68.2%) presented with localized disease and 47 (31.8%) had metastasis at diagnosis. Male prevalence, younger age, bone primary site, and low rate of synchronous metastases were observed in <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName>-rearranged cases. The local treatment was surgery for 67 patients (45%) and surgery and radiation therapy for 52 patients (35%). Chemotherapy was given to 122 patients (82%). At a median follow-up of 42.7 months, the 3-year OS rate was 92.2% for patients with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas, 39.6% for patients with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas, and 78.7% (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) for patients with unclassified undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas.</Para><Para id="_2490">A multi-institution retrospective analysis of patients aged 0 to 24 years identified 29 patients with sarcomas and <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene fusions and 25 patients with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>-associated sarcomas (18 with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName> gene fusions and 7 with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> ITD).<Reference refidx="14"/> Using a diverse range of treatments, the 3-year event-free survival (EFS) rates were 44.0% (95% confidence interval [CI], 28.7%–67.5%) for patients with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene fusions and 41.2% (95% CI, 25.4%–67.0%) for patients with  <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> alterations (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .97).</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1916"><Title>Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas With <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>  Genetic Alterations</Title><Para id="_2534"><GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas represent the second most common family of round cell sarcomas and are defined by the presence of <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> fusions at the molecular level.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><SummarySection id="_1917"><Title>Clinical presentation</Title><Para id="_1918">Undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> rearrangements most commonly affect young adults, with 50% of cases occurring between  the ages of 21 and 40 years. In a series of 115 cases, the median age at diagnosis was  32 years, and 22% of cases occurred in patients younger than 18 years.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="15"/> This entity more commonly affects males and usually originates from the soft tissues of the trunk and extremities.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1999"><Title>Genomic characteristics</Title><Para id="_2000"><GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas most commonly have a <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene fusion with <GeneName>DUX4</GeneName>, <GeneName>FOXO4</GeneName>, or <GeneName>NUTM1</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/> The <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene fusion with <GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> results from either a t(4;19)(q35;q13) or a t(10;19)(q26;q13) translocation.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="18"/> <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> is located at chromosome 19q13.1 and <GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> is located on either chromosome 4q35 or 10q26.3. Sarcomas with the <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> rearrangement have a transcriptional profile and DNA methylation profile that differs from that of Ewing sarcoma, supporting their characterization as a distinct entity.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> For example, nearly all sarcomas with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> rearrangements express WT1 and ETV4, in contrast to Ewing sarcoma and <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>-rearranged tumors, making immunohistochemistry for these proteins useful in distinguishing between these diagnoses.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="19"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1919"><Title>Treatment of undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> genetic alterations</Title><Para id="_1920">In a series of 115 cases of <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged small round cell sarcomas, 57 patients had adequate follow-up information.<Reference refidx="15"/> Nine patients presented with metastases, and 53% of patients with localized disease experienced a recurrence commonly involving the lung. Patients treated with neoadjuvant chemotherapy had an inferior survival than patients who were treated with up-front surgical resection. However, this difference in survival might have been related to a larger tumor size at presentation in the former group. The 2-year and 5-year survival rates were 53% and 43%, respectively. </Para><Para id="_2483">An international retrospective cohort study further highlighted the poor outcomes for patients with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas. The 3-year OS rate was 39.6%, which was significantly worse than outcomes for patients with other undifferentiated round cell sarcomas.<Reference refidx="13"/> Likewise, these survival rates are significantly lower than the survival rates observed in patients with Ewing sarcoma. Further study is required to identify optimal treatments for this disease.</Para><Para id="_2480">In another series of 79 patients with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged round cell sarcomas, outcomes were likewise poor, with a median OS of 18 months.<Reference refidx="21"/> Patients treated with Ewing sarcoma–based chemotherapy regimens had nominally higher response rates compared with patients treated with soft tissue sarcoma–based regimens. However, OS rates were similar between these two groups.</Para><Para id="_2491">A multi-institution retrospective analysis of patients aged 0 to 24 years identified 29 patients with sarcomas and <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene fusions and 25 patients with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>-associated sarcomas (18 with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName>::<GeneName>CCNB3</GeneName> gene fusions and 7 with <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> ITD).<Reference refidx="14"/> Using a diverse range of treatments, the 3-year EFS rates were 44.0% (95% CI, 28.7%–67.5%) for patients with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene fusions and 41.2% (95% CI, 25.4%–67.0%) for patients with  <GeneName>BCOR</GeneName> alterations (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .97).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1955"><Title>Undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM1</GeneName> rearrangements</Title><Para id="_1956">Undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM1</GeneName> rearrangements occur much less frequently than undifferentiated round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> rearrangements.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/>  These tumors occur in younger patients, with a median age of 6 years, compared with an average age of 21.6 years for patients with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> fusions. The primary tumors occur in the central nervous system (CNS) and in the periphery.  The histological appearance of these tumors is similar to <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>DUX4</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas.  The prognosis of patients with these tumors is reported to be very poor despite treatment with surgery, multiagent chemotherapy, and radiation therapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2430"><Title>Undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas with <GeneName>ATXN1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM2A</GeneName> or <GeneName>ATXN1L</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM2A</GeneName> fusions</Title><Para id="_2431">In one report, three children had tumors with <GeneName>ATXN1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM2A</GeneName> or <GeneName>ATXN1L</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM2A</GeneName> fusions.<Reference refidx="26"/> Two of the patients were infants with CNS lesions, and the third patient was a neonate with skin involvement and multiple masses throughout the peritoneal cavity. The authors suggested that <GeneName>ATXN1</GeneName>- or <GeneName>ATXN1L</GeneName>-associated fusions disrupted their interaction with CIC and decreased the transcription repressor complex, leading to downstream <GeneName>PEA3</GeneName> family gene overexpression.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2001"><Title>Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas With <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::non-ETS Fusions</Title><SummarySection id="_2002"><Title>Sarcomas with <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> and <GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> fusions</Title><Para id="_2003">Sarcomas with <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> and <GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> fusions typically arise in long bones, show a strong male predominance, and are more common in adults than in children.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/> These entities have transcriptional and DNA methylation profiles that distinguish them from Ewing sarcoma and other small round cell sarcomas.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="20"/> Additionally, the transcriptional profiles for <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> and <GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> differ from each other,<Reference refidx="6"/> although the significance of this observation is unclear. The two entities also differ in that amplification of the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> gene fusion is commonly observed, but the <GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> gene fusion is generally not amplified.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="29"/> Sarcomas with <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> and <GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> fusions have metastatic potential and appear to respond poorly to chemotherapy regimens that are commonly used to treat other sarcomas.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/></Para><Para id="_2004"><GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> and <GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> rearrangements are also observed in a substantial proportion of solitary bone cysts (also known as simple bone cysts), a benign condition that typically presents in the metadiaphyses of the long bones of skeletally immature individuals.<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/> Therefore, the presence of either <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> or <GeneName>FUS</GeneName>::<GeneName>NFATC2</GeneName> fusions should not be taken as an indicator of malignancy, but rather needs to be interpreted considering the clinical setting.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2005"><Title>Sarcomas with <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>PATZ1</GeneName> fusions</Title><Para id="_2006">Sarcomas with the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>PATZ1</GeneName> fusion are very uncommon. In the small number of cases described, there appears to be gender balance, a propensity for presentation at truncal primary sites (particularly the chest), and a median age of presentation of between 40 to 50 years, with cases rarely occurring  in the pediatric age range.<Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/> Sarcomas with the <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>PATZ1</GeneName> fusion have gene expression and DNA methylation profiles that distinguish them from other sarcomas,<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="20"/> and <GeneName>CDKN2A</GeneName> deletions appear to commonly occur as secondary genomic alterations.<Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/></Para><Para id="_2018">The <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>PATZ1</GeneName> fusion has been described more commonly in brain tumors. It has been suggested that this fusion may define a novel form of glioblastoma.<Reference refidx="35"/> In a series of 11 cases of <GeneName>EWSR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>PATZ1</GeneName> fusion–associated tumors, 3 were primary brain tumors, 7 were sarcomas, and 1 was classified as a soft tissue sarcoma in the CNS.<Reference refidx="32"/>   Patients were between the ages of 11 and  81 years.  Treatment details were reported for only three adult patients, two of whom had mixed responses to chemotherapy followed by disease progression, and one patient who did not receive chemotherapy.  </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">WHO Classification of Tumours Editorial Board: WHO Classification of Tumours. Volume 3: Soft Tissue and Bone Tumours. 5th ed., IARC Press, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="29300189">Kao YC, Owosho AA, Sung YS, et al.: BCOR-CCNB3 Fusion Positive Sarcomas: A Clinicopathologic and Molecular Analysis of 36 Cases With Comparison to Morphologic Spectrum and Clinical Behavior of Other Round Cell Sarcomas. Am J Surg Pathol 42 (5): 604-615, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27306060">Machado I, Navarro S, Llombart-Bosch A: Ewing sarcoma and the new emerging Ewing-like sarcomas: (CIC and BCOR-rearranged-sarcomas). A systematic review. Histol Histopathol 31 (11): 1169-81, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="22387997">Pierron G, Tirode F, Lucchesi C, et al.: A new subtype of bone sarcoma defined by BCOR-CCNB3 gene fusion. Nat Genet 44 (4): 461-6, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="26752546">Specht K, Zhang L, Sung YS, et al.: Novel BCOR-MAML3 and ZC3H7B-BCOR Gene Fusions in Undifferentiated Small Blue Round Cell Sarcomas. Am J Surg Pathol 40 (4): 433-42, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="29431183">Watson S, Perrin V, Guillemot D, et al.: Transcriptomic definition of molecular subgroups of small round cell sarcomas. J Pathol 245 (1): 29-40, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26945340">Kao YC, Sung YS, Zhang L, et al.: Recurrent BCOR Internal Tandem Duplication and YWHAE-NUTM2B Fusions in Soft Tissue Undifferentiated Round Cell Sarcoma of Infancy: Overlapping Genetic Features With Clear Cell Sarcoma of Kidney. Am J Surg Pathol 40 (8): 1009-20, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="27428733">Kao YC, Sung YS, Zhang L, et al.: BCOR Overexpression Is a Highly Sensitive Marker in Round Cell Sarcomas With BCOR Genetic Abnormalities. Am J Surg Pathol 40 (12): 1670-1678, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="32372022">Antonescu CR, Kao YC, Xu B, et al.: Undifferentiated round cell sarcoma with BCOR internal tandem duplications (ITD) or YWHAE fusions: a clinicopathologic and molecular study. Mod Pathol 33 (9): 1669-1677, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="26098867">Ueno-Yokohata H, Okita H, Nakasato K, et al.: Consistent in-frame internal tandem duplications of BCOR characterize clear cell sarcoma of the kidney. Nat Genet 47 (8): 861-3, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="26573325">Roy A, Kumar V, Zorman B, et al.: Recurrent internal tandem duplications of BCOR in clear cell sarcoma of the kidney. Nat Commun 6: 8891, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="25176412">Cohen-Gogo S, Cellier C, Coindre JM, et al.: Ewing-like sarcomas with BCOR-CCNB3 fusion transcript: a clinical, radiological and pathological retrospective study from the Société Française des Cancers de L'Enfant. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (12): 2191-8, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="36791667">Palmerini E, Gambarotti M, Italiano A, et al.: A global collaboRAtive study of CIC-rearranged, BCOR::CCNB3-rearranged and other ultra-rare unclassified undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas (GRACefUl). Eur J Cancer 183: 11-23, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="37212486">Sparber-Sauer M, Corradini N, Affinita MC, et al.: Clinical characteristics and outcomes for children, adolescents and young adults with "CIC-fused" or "BCOR-rearranged" soft tissue sarcomas: A multi-institutional European retrospective analysis. Cancer Med 12 (13): 14346-14359, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="28346326">Antonescu CR, Owosho AA, Zhang L, et al.: Sarcomas With CIC-rearrangements Are a Distinct Pathologic Entity With Aggressive Outcome: A Clinicopathologic and Molecular Study of 115 Cases. Am J Surg Pathol 41 (7): 941-949, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="22072439">Italiano A, Sung YS, Zhang L, et al.: High prevalence of CIC fusion with double-homeobox (DUX4) transcription factors in EWSR1-negative undifferentiated small blue round cell sarcomas. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 51 (3): 207-18, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="29356724">Dickson BC, Sung YS, Rosenblum MK, et al.: NUTM1 Gene Fusions Characterize a Subset of Undifferentiated Soft Tissue and Visceral Tumors. Am J Surg Pathol 42 (5): 636-645, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="16717057">Kawamura-Saito M, Yamazaki Y, Kaneko K, et al.: Fusion between CIC and DUX4 up-regulates PEA3 family genes in Ewing-like sarcomas with t(4;19)(q35;q13) translocation. Hum Mol Genet 15 (13): 2125-37, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="24723486">Specht K, Sung YS, Zhang L, et al.: Distinct transcriptional signature and immunoprofile of CIC-DUX4 fusion-positive round cell tumors compared to EWSR1-rearranged Ewing sarcomas: further evidence toward distinct pathologic entities. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 53 (7): 622-33, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="30895378">Koelsche C, Kriegsmann M, Kommoss FKF, et al.: DNA methylation profiling distinguishes Ewing-like sarcoma with EWSR1-NFATc2 fusion from Ewing sarcoma. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 145 (5): 1273-1281, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="36537582">Brahmi M, Gaspar N, Gantzer J, et al.: Patterns of care and outcome of CIC-rearranged sarcoma patients: A nationwide study of the French sarcoma group. Cancer Med 12 (7): 7801-7807, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="30407212">Le Loarer F, Pissaloux D, Watson S, et al.: Clinicopathologic Features of CIC-NUTM1 Sarcomas, a New Molecular Variant of the Family of CIC-Fused Sarcomas. Am J Surg Pathol 43 (2): 268-276, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="29901569">Mangray S, Kelly DR, LeGuellec S, et al.: Clinicopathologic Features of a Series of Primary Renal CIC-rearranged Sarcomas With Comprehensive Molecular Analysis. Am J Surg Pathol 42 (10): 1360-1369, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="29700887">Schaefer IM, Dal Cin P, Landry LM, et al.: CIC-NUTM1 fusion: A case which expands the spectrum of NUT-rearranged epithelioid malignancies. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 57 (9): 446-451, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="38851744">Zhao L, He H, Ren J, et al.: CIC::NUTM1 sarcomas occurred in soft tissues of upper limbs : a rare case report and literature review. Diagn Pathol 19 (1): 76, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="35836290">Xu F, Viaene AN, Ruiz J, et al.: Novel ATXN1/ATXN1L::NUTM2A fusions identified in aggressive infant sarcomas with gene expression and methylation patterns similar to CIC-rearranged sarcoma. Acta Neuropathol Commun 10 (1): 102, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="31049020">Bode-Lesniewska B, Fritz C, Exner GU, et al.: EWSR1-NFATC2 and FUS-NFATC2 Gene Fusion-Associated Mesenchymal Tumors: Clinicopathologic Correlation and Literature Review. Sarcoma 2019: 9386390, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="30994538">Wang GY, Thomas DG, Davis JL, et al.: EWSR1-NFATC2 Translocation-associated Sarcoma Clinicopathologic Findings in a Rare Aggressive Primary Bone or Soft Tissue Tumor. Am J Surg Pathol 43 (8): 1112-1122, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="19318479">Szuhai K, Ijszenga M, de Jong D, et al.: The NFATc2 gene is involved in a novel cloned translocation in a Ewing sarcoma variant that couples its function in immunology to oncology. Clin Cancer Res 15 (7): 2259-68, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="32991339">Pižem J, Šekoranja D, Zupan A, et al.: FUS-NFATC2 or EWSR1-NFATC2 Fusions Are Present in a Large Proportion of Simple Bone Cysts. Am J Surg Pathol 44 (12): 1623-1634, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="33316098">Hung YP, Fisch AS, Diaz-Perez JA, et al.: Identification of EWSR1-NFATC2 fusion in simple bone cysts. Histopathology 78 (6): 849-856, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="31189996">Bridge JA, Sumegi J, Druta M, et al.: Clinical, pathological, and genomic features of EWSR1-PATZ1 fusion sarcoma. Mod Pathol 32 (11): 1593-1604, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="33012788">Michal M, Rubin BP, Agaimy A, et al.: EWSR1-PATZ1-rearranged sarcoma: a report of nine cases of spindle and round cell neoplasms with predilection for thoracoabdominal soft tissues and frequent expression of neural and skeletal muscle markers. Mod Pathol 34 (4): 770-785, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="38043789">Dehner CA, Torres-Mora J, Gupta S, et al.: Sarcomas Harboring EWSR1::PATZ1 Fusions: A Clinicopathologic Study of 17 Cases. Mod Pathol 37 (2): 100400, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="29679497">Siegfried A, Rousseau A, Maurage CA, et al.: EWSR1-PATZ1 gene fusion may define a new glioneuronal tumor entity. Brain Pathol 29 (1): 53-62, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/27/2024)</Title><Para id="_73">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_2542"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_51" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Recurrent Ewing Sarcoma</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_2545">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_454" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">strategies to target fusion proteins</SummaryRef> to the list of other therapies that have been studied in the treatment of recurrent Ewing sarcoma.</Para><Para id="_2546">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2541" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that  lurbinectedin is structurally related to trabectedin, but it has been more effective in suppressing the activity of the oncogenic transcription factor EWS::FLI in mice in preclinical studies. Also added text about the results of an open-label, single-arm, basket phase II trial of lurbinectedin (cited Subbiah et al. as reference 68). Added text to state that  an agent known as TK216 is thought to interfere with interactions between the EWSR1::FLI1 fusion oncoprotein and key proteins critical for its oncogenic function, although it has also been shown to disrupt microtubules (cited Povedano et al. as reference 69). Also added text about the results of a phase I/II trial of TK216 in combination with vincristine in patients with recurrent Ewing sarcoma (cited Meyers et al. as reference 70).</Para><Para id="_2543">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2533" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">NCT04890093</SummaryRef> as a treatment option under clinical evaluation for patients with recurrent Ewing sarcoma.</Para><Para id="_2544"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1910" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">Undifferentiated Small Round Cell (Ewing-Like) Sarcomas</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_2547">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2534" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas represent the second most common family of round cell sarcomas and are defined by the presence of <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> fusions at the molecular level.</Para><Para id="_2548">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2000" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>-rearranged sarcomas most commonly have a <GeneName>CIC</GeneName> gene fusion with <GeneName>DUX4</GeneName>, <GeneName>FOXO4</GeneName>, or <GeneName>NUTM1</GeneName> (cited Dickson et al. as reference 17).</Para><Para id="_2549">Added Zhao et al. as <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_1956" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">reference 25</SummaryRef>. Also revised text to state that tumors with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUTM1</GeneName> rearrangements occur in younger patients, with a median age of 6 years, compared with an average age of 21.6 years for patients with <GeneName>CIC</GeneName>::<GeneName>DUX4</GeneName> fusions.</Para><Para id="_2550">Added Dehner et al. as <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_2006" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">reference 34</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062841#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood Ewing sarcoma and undifferentiated small round cell sarcomas of bone and soft tissue. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Ewing Sarcoma and Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas of Bone and Soft Tissue Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Holcombe Edwin Grier, MD</ListItem><ListItem>Andrea A. Hayes-Dixon, MD, FACS, FAAP (Howard University)</ListItem><ListItem>Karen J. Marcus, MD, FACR (Dana-Farber of Boston Children's Cancer Center and Blood Disorders Harvard Medical School)</ListItem><ListItem>William H. Meyer, MD</ListItem><ListItem>Paul A. Meyers, MD (Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Thomas A. Olson, MD (Aflac Cancer and Blood Disorders Center of Children's Healthcare of Atlanta - Egleston Campus)</ListItem><ListItem>Nita Louise Seibel, MD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Malcolm A. Smith, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Ewing Sarcoma and Undifferentiated Small Round Cell Sarcomas of Bone and Soft Tissue Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/bone/hp/ewing-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389480]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-11-27</DateLastModified></Summary>
