<Summary id="CDR0000062854" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatment for children with extracranial germ cell tumors (GCT) may involve surgical resection followed by monitoring or chemotherapy before or after surgery.
Get detailed treatment information for newly diagnosed and recurrent extracranial GCTs in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/extracranial-germ-cell/patient/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043493">childhood extracranial germ cell tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043494">childhood teratoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043496">childhood malignant ovarian germ cell tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043495">childhood malignant testicular germ cell tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_641">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood extracranial germ cell tumors. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_642">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood extracranial germ cell tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood immature teratoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood malignant ovarian germ cell tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood malignant testicular germ cell tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood mature teratoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043493">childhood extracranial germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors (GCTs)</Title><Para id="_433">GCTs arise from primordial germ cells, which migrate during embryogenesis from the yolk sac through the mesentery to the gonads (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1872" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Figure 1</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Childhood extracranial GCTs   can generally be divided into gonadal and extragonadal. These tumors can also be broadly classified as teratomas, malignant GCTs, or mixed GCTs.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000801664" type="image/jpeg" alt="Diagram showing extracranial germ cell development from primordial germ cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1872"><Caption language="en">Figure 1.  Extracranial germ cell development from primordial germ cells. Credit: Thomas Olson, M.D.</Caption></MediaLink><SummarySection id="_442"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_4">Childhood GCTs are rare in children younger than 15
years, accounting for   approximately 3% of cancers in this age
group.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> In the fetal/neonatal age group, most extracranial GCTs are benign teratomas occurring at midline locations, including the head and neck, sacrococcyx, and retroperitoneum.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/>  Despite the small percentage of malignant teratomas that occur in this age group,  perinatal tumors have a high morbidity rate caused by hydrops fetalis and premature delivery.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_443">The incidence of malignant extracranial GCTs increases with the onset of puberty. These tumors   represent approximately 15% of cancers in male adolescents aged 15 to 19 years and 4% of cancers in female adolescents aged 15 to 19 years.<Reference refidx="3"/>  </Para><Para id="_1938"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1940" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Figure 2</SummaryRef>  shows the age-incidence profile by sex for malignant extracranial/extragonadal  GCTs (left panel) and malignant gonadal GCTs (right panel) between  2014 and 2018 for 23 U.S. Cancer registries that represent 66% of all U.S. children, adolescents, and young adults (blue triangles, females; green triangles, males).<Reference refidx="3"/> For males, there is a peak in incidence in children younger than 2 years for both extragonadal and gonadal sites, which is followed by low rates between the ages of 2 and 12 years, and then higher rates throughout adolescence. For females, the peak in young children is present only for extragonadal tumors, with rates increasing after the age of puberty for both extragonadal and gonadal sites. However, the incidence of  each tumor is lower for females during adolescence than for males during adolescence. </Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000809649" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of two graphs showing age-incidence profiles for extracranial, extragonadal germ cell tumors (left graph) and for gonadal germ cell tumors (right graph). The blue triangles represent males, and the green triangles represent females." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1940"><Caption language="en">Figure 2.  Age-incidence profiles for extracranial, extragonadal germ cell tumors (left graph) and for gonadal germ cell tumors (right graph). The blue triangles represent females, and the green triangles represent males. (See text for details.)</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_444">The incidence of extracranial GCTs according to age group, sex, and gonadal versus extragonadal primary site is shown in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1939" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Table id="_1939"><Title>Table 1.  Incidence of Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors by Age Group and Sex<Superscript>a,b</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="7"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColWidth="14.28%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColWidth="14.28%"/><THead><Row><entry>Tumor Site</entry><entry>Sex</entry><entry>Age &lt;1 y</entry><entry>Ages 1–4 y</entry><entry>Ages 5–9 y</entry><entry>Ages 10–14 y</entry><entry>Ages 15–19 y</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Rates are per 1 million children from 2014 to 2018 for NCCR Registries, 23 U.S. Cancer registries that represent 66% of all U.S. children, adolescents, and young adults. </entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Data from National Cancer Institute; National Childhood Cancer Registry: NCCR*Explorer.<Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Extragonadal</entry><entry>Female</entry><entry>17.7</entry><entry>2.1</entry><entry>0.1</entry><entry>0.1</entry><entry>0.7</entry></Row><Row><entry>Male</entry><entry>8.8</entry><entry>0.7</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0.6</entry><entry>2.2</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Gonadal</entry><entry>Female</entry><entry>0.6</entry><entry>0.7</entry><entry>2.1</entry><entry>7.6</entry><entry>8.3</entry></Row><Row><entry>Male</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>2.5</entry><entry>0.1</entry><entry>1.5</entry><entry>36.1</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1825"><Title>Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_1826">Cryptorchidism, the presence of an abdominal undescended testis, has been associated with a 10.8-fold increased risk of developing a GCT.<Reference refidx="11"/> Gonadal dysgenesis, as well as the presence of Y-chromosome material in an abdominal gonad, also increases the risk of developing a gonadal GCT, especially gonadoblastoma. Gonadoblastoma is a rare gonadal tumor consisting of a mixture of germ cells and sex-cord stromal derivatives resembling immature granulosa and Sertoli cells.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_212">There are few data about the potential genetic or environmental risk factors
associated with childhood extragonadal extracranial GCTs.  Patients with
the following syndromes are at an increased risk of extragonadal extracranial GCTs:</Para><ItemizedList id="_459" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Klinefelter syndrome: Increased risk of mediastinal GCTs.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/> <Para id="_1865">Most mediastinal GCTs in adolescents and young adults occur in males, and 22% to 50% have cytogenetic changes consistent with Klinefelter syndrome.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="18"/> The age of  tumor presentation is younger in patients with Klinefelter syndrome, and testing all younger males for Klinefelter syndrome should be considered.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="18"/> </Para><Para id="_1881">Patients with GCTs were identified from the Children's Oncology Group (COG) Childhood Cancer Research Network.  Twenty-nine patients in the study had mediastinal primary tumors, and nine patients (31%) had Klinefelter syndrome. In the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention's large 2013 WONDER database, 3% of patients with GCTs had Klinefelter syndrome  (70% were mediastinal). In comparison, 0.2% of males in the general population have Klinefelter syndrome.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para></ListItem><ListItem>Swyer syndrome: Increased risk of gonadoblastomas and seminomas.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem><ListItem>Turner syndrome: Increased risk of gonadoblastomas and dysgerminomas.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043493">childhood extracranial germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Histological Classification of Childhood Extracranial GCTs</Title><Para id="_14">Childhood extracranial GCTs comprise a variety of histological
diagnoses and can be broadly classified as the following: 
</Para><ItemizedList id="_445" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Teratomas.<ItemizedList id="_673" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_130" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Mature teratoma</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_132" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Immature teratoma</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_134" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Malignant GCTs</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_446">The histological properties of extracranial GCTs are heterogeneous and vary by primary tumor site and the sex and age of the patient.<Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/> Histologically identical GCTs that arise in younger children have different biological characteristics from those that arise in adolescents and young adults.<Reference refidx="25"/></Para><SummarySection id="_130"><Title>Mature teratoma</Title><Para id="_131">Mature teratomas can occur at gonadal or at extragonadal locations. They are the most common histological subtype of childhood GCT.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/>  Mature teratomas usually contain well-differentiated tissues from the ectodermal, mesodermal, and endodermal germ cell layers. Any tissue type may be found within this tumor.  </Para><Para id="_447">Mature teratomas are benign, although some mature teratomas may secrete enzymes or hormones, including insulin, growth hormone, androgens, and prolactin.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_132"><Title>Immature teratoma</Title><Para id="_133">Immature teratomas contain tissues from the ectodermal, mesodermal, and endodermal germ cell layers. Immature tissues, primarily neuroepithelial, are also present.  Immature teratomas are graded from 0 to 3 on the basis of the amount of immature neural tissue found in the tumor specimen.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/> Tumors of higher grade are more likely to have foci of yolk sac tumor.<Reference refidx="33"/> Immature teratomas can exhibit malignant behavior and metastasize. </Para><Para id="_448">Immature teratomas occur primarily in young children at extragonadal sites and in the ovaries of girls near the age of puberty. However, there is no correlation between tumor grade and patient age.<Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/> Some immature teratomas may secrete enzymes or hormones such as vasopressin.<Reference refidx="35"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><Title>Malignant GCTs</Title><Para id="_435">Most childhood extragonadal GCTs arise in midline sites (i.e., head and neck, sacrococcygeal, mediastinal, and retroperitoneal). The midline location may represent aberrant embryonic migration of the primordial germ cells.</Para><Para id="_259">GCTs contain malignant tissues of germ cell origin and, rarely, tissues of somatic origin.  Isolated malignant elements may constitute a small fraction of a predominantly mature or immature teratoma.<Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="36"/> </Para><Para id="_449">Malignant germ cell elements of children, adolescents, and young adults can be grouped broadly by location (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_318" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>).</Para><Table id="_318"><Title>Table 2.  Histology of Malignant Germ Cell Tumors in Children, Adolescents, and Young Adults<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="7.40%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="35.48%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="57.11%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">Malignant Germ Cell Elements</entry><entry>Location</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">E = extragonadal; O = ovarian; T = testicular.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Modified from Perlman et al.<Reference refidx="37"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Seminomatous</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Seminoma</entry><entry>T</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Dysgerminoma</entry><entry>O</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Germinoma</entry><entry>E</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Nonseminomatous</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Yolk sac tumor (endodermal sinus tumor)</entry><entry>E, O, T</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Choriocarcinoma</entry><entry>E, O, T</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Embryonal carcinoma</entry><entry>E, T</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Gonadoblastoma</entry><entry>O</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Mixed Germ Cell Tumors</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Mixed germ cell tumors</entry><entry>E, O, T</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_204"><Title>GCT Biology</Title><Para id="_451">Childhood extracranial GCTs develop at many sites, including testicles, ovaries, mediastinum, retroperitoneum, sacrum, coccyx, and head and neck (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_637" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Figure 3</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="7"/> The clinical features at presentation are specific for each site.</Para><Para id="_636"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000770217" type="image/jpeg" alt="Extracranial germ cell tumor; drawing shows parts of the body where extracranial germ cell tumors may form, including the head and neck, mediastinum (the area between the lungs, shown in blue), retroperitoneum (the area behind the abdominal organs, shown in red), sacrum, coccyx, testicles (in males), and ovaries (in females). Also shown are the heart and peritoneum." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_637"><Caption language="en">Figure 3.  Extracranial germ cell tumors form in parts of the body other than the brain.  This includes the testicles, ovaries, sacrococcyx (usually originating from the coccyx and including the sacrum), mediastinum, and retroperitoneum.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_205">The following biologically distinct subtypes of GCTs are found in children and adolescents:</Para><ItemizedList id="_454" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_206" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Testicular GCTs</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_208" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Ovarian GCTs</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_210" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Extragonadal extracranial GCTs</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_455">Biological distinctions between GCTs in children and GCTs in adults may not be absolute, and biological factors have not been shown to predict risk.<Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/></Para><SummarySection id="_206"><Title>Testicular GCTs</Title><ItemizedList id="_207" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Children (aged &lt;11 years): </Strong>During early childhood, both testicular teratomas and malignant testicular GCTs are identified. The malignant tumors are commonly composed of pure yolk sac tumor (also known as endodermal
sinus tumor) and are generally diploid or tetraploid. Up to approximately 44% of testicular GCTs contain
the isochromosome of the short arm of chromosome 12 (i12p) that characterizes testicular cancer in young adults.<Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/> Deletions of chromosomes 1p, 4q, 
and 6q and gains of chromosomes 1q, 3, and 20q are reported as recurring chromosomal abnormalities for this group
of tumors.<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Adolescents and young adults (aged ≥11 years):</Strong> Testicular GCTs in the adolescent and young adult population almost always possess an i12p chromosomal abnormality <Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/> and are aneuploid.<Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="50"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_208"><Title>Ovarian GCTs</Title><Para id="_209">Ovarian GCTs occur primarily in adolescent and young adult females. While most ovarian GCTs are benign mature teratomas (dermoid cysts), a heterogeneous group of malignant GCTs, including immature teratomas, dysgerminomas, yolk sac tumors, and mixed GCTs, do occur in females.    The malignant ovarian GCT commonly shows increased copies of the short arm of chromosome 12.<Reference refidx="51"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_210"><Title>Extragonadal extracranial GCTs</Title><Para id="_458">Extragonadal extracranial GCTs occur outside of the brain and gonads.</Para><ItemizedList id="_211" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Children (aged &lt;11 years):</Strong> These tumors typically present at birth or during early childhood. Most of these tumors are benign teratomas occurring in the sacrococcygeal region, and thus are not included in Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program data.<Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/> Malignant yolk sac tumor histology occurs in a minority of these tumors; however, they may have cytogenetic abnormalities similar to those observed for tumors occurring in the testes of young males.<Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="46"/> Mediastinal GCTs in children  younger than 8 years share the same genetic gains and losses as do sacrococcygeal and testicular tumors in young children.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="54"/><Reference refidx="55"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Older children, adolescents, and young adults (aged ≥11 years):</Strong> The mediastinum is the most common primary site for extragonadal GCTs in older children and adolescents.<Reference refidx="27"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_584">For information about the treatment of intracranial GCTs, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000712041" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Germ Cell Tumors
Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_452"><Title>Diagnostic and Staging Evaluation</Title><Para id="_592">Diagnostic evaluation of GCTs includes measurement of serum tumor markers and imaging studies. In suspected cases, tumor markers can suggest the diagnosis before surgery and/or biopsy. This information can be used by the multidisciplinary team to make appropriate treatment choices.</Para><SummarySection id="_593"><Title>Tumor markers</Title><Para id="_1887">Tumor markers are measured with each cycle of chemotherapy for all pediatric patients with malignant GCTs. After initial chemotherapy, tumor markers may show a transient  elevation.<Reference refidx="56"/></Para><Para id="_1888">Common tumor markers include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1921" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Alpha-fetoprotein (AFP).</Strong><Para id="_1889"> The fetal liver produces AFP, and during the first year of life, infants have elevated serum  AFP levels, which are not associated with the presence of a GCT. Normal ranges have been described.<Reference refidx="57"/><Reference refidx="58"/> The serum half-life of AFP is 5 to 7 days.</Para><Para id="_1890">Yolk sac tumors produce AFP. Most children with malignant GCTs will have a component of yolk sac tumor and have elevations of AFP levels,<Reference refidx="59"/> <Reference refidx="60"/> which are serially monitored during treatment to help assess response to therapy.<Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="59"/> Benign teratomas and immature teratomas may produce small elevations of AFP and beta-human chorionic gonadotropin  (beta-hCG).</Para><Para id="_1891">A COG study measured AFP levels in children who received chemotherapy for GCTs. AFP decline was defined as automatically satisfactory if AFP normalized after two cycles of chemotherapy and was calculated satisfactory if the AFP half-life decline was less than or equal to 7 days after the start of chemotherapy. Other decline in AFP was defined as unsatisfactory.<Reference refidx="61"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_1922" Style="dash"><ListItem> The cumulative incidence of relapse was 11%  for patients with a satisfactory decline in AFP (n = 117) and 38% for patients with an unsatisfactory decline in AFP (n = 14).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Beta-hCG.</Strong><Para id="_1893"> Beta-hCG is produced by all choriocarcinomas and by some germinomas (seminomas and dysgerminomas) and embryonal carcinomas, resulting in elevated serum levels of these substances. The  serum half-life of beta-hCG is 1 to 2 days.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>MicroRNAs.</Strong><Para id="_1894"> In a prospective multicentric study, the serum level of microRNA-371a-3p was shown to be a sensitive and specific  biomarker for adult testicular GCTs.<Reference refidx="62"/> The study included 616 patients with GCTs of varying histologies and 258 controls without malignant GCTs. Elevation of microRNA-371a-3p levels was noted in all malignant histologies, including seminomas. Normal controls and patients with benign teratomas did not have the biomarker elevation. MicroRNA-371a-3p levels were related to tumor volume, and the levels decreased in response to chemotherapy. More studies about microRNA-371a-3p are needed to assess its use in patients with pediatric GCTs.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_595"><Title>Imaging tests</Title><Para id="_596">Imaging tests may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_597" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Computed tomography (CT) scan of the chest.</ListItem><ListItem>CT or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the primary site.</ListItem><ListItem>Radionuclide bone scan, if clinically indicated.</ListItem><ListItem>MRI of the brain, if clinically indicated.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1895"><Title>Prognostic Factors</Title><Para id="_1896">Prognostic factors for extracranial GCTs depend on many patient and tumor characteristics and include the following (obtained  from historical national GCT trials):<Reference refidx="59"/><Reference refidx="63"/><Reference refidx="64"/><Reference refidx="65"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_1897" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Age (e.g., young children vs. adolescents).</ListItem><ListItem>Stage of disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Primary site of disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Histology (e.g., seminomatous vs. nonseminomatous).</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor marker decline (AFP and beta-hCG) in response to therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Presence of gonadal dysgenesis.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1898">To better identify prognostic factors, data from five U.S. trials and two U.K. trials for malignant extracranial GCTs in children and adolescents were merged by the Malignant Germ Cell Tumor International Collaborative.  The goal was to ascertain the important prognostic factors in 519 young patients who received chemotherapy, incorporating age at diagnosis, stage, and site of primary tumor, along with pretreatment AFP level and histology.<Reference refidx="66"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>] In this age-focused investigation of these factors in young children and adolescents, outcomes included the following (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1902" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Figure 4</SummaryRef>):<Reference refidx="66"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_1899" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Patients aged 11 years and older with stage III or stage IV extragonadal disease or stage IV ovarian disease had a less than 70% likelihood of long-term disease-free survival, ranging from 40% (extragonadal stage IV) to 67% (ovarian stage IV).</ListItem><ListItem>Boys (aged 11 years and older) with International Germ Cell Consensus Classification <Reference refidx="67"/> intermediate-risk or poor-risk features also had inferior outcomes.</ListItem><ListItem>Presence of a yolk sac tumor predicted better outcome, but it did not achieve statistical significance at the .05 level.</ListItem><ListItem>Preoperative AFP levels were not prognostic. Postoperative AFP levels were prognostic in adult men.<Reference refidx="67"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1928">A subsequent study used a database of 11 GCT trials and identified 593 patients with metastatic testicular, mediastinal, or retroperitoneal GCTs. The distribution of patients by age groups included 90 children (aged 0 to &lt;11 years), 109 adolescents (aged 11 to &lt;18 years), and 394 young adults (aged 18 to ≤30 years).<Reference refidx="67"/>; <Reference refidx="68"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_1951" Style="bullet"><ListItem> The 5-year event-free survival (EFS) rate was lower for adolescents (72%; 95% confidence interval [CI], 62%–79%) than it was for children (90%; 95% CI, 81%–95%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003) or young adults (88%; 95% CI, 84%–91%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0002). </ListItem><ListItem>After adjusting for the International Germ Cell Consensus Classification risk group,<Reference refidx="67"/> only the difference in EFS between adolescents and children remained significant (hazard ratio, 0.30; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1900">Although few pediatric data exist, adult studies have shown that an unsatisfactory decline of elevated tumor markers after the first cycle of chemotherapy is a poor prognostic finding.<Reference refidx="69"/><Reference refidx="70"/></Para><Para id="_1901">The presence of gonadal dysgenesis in patients with ovarian nondysgerminomas is associated with worse outcomes. In a report from the COG <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00053352">AGCT0132</ProtocolRef> study, seven patients with gonadal dysgenesis and ovarian nondysgerminomas had  an estimated 3-year EFS rate of 67%, compared with  89% for 100 patients with nondysgerminoma ovarian tumors  who did not have gonadal dysgenesis.<Reference refidx="13"/> These dysgenetic gonads contain Y-chromosome material, and intra-abdominal gonads with Y-chromosome material are at increased risk of tumor development.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="71"/> In contrast to nondysgerminomas, gonadal dysgenesis was identified in 7 of 48 patients  with ovarian dysgerminomas in a report from the French Society of Pediatric Oncology. With a medium follow-up of 14 years, all patients survived.<Reference refidx="72"/></Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000801167" type="image/jpeg" alt="Table showing the predicted fraction of pediatric germ cell tumors cured by site, age, and stage using parameter estimates from Cure model." language="en" placement="image-center-full" id="_1902"><Caption language="en">Figure 4.  Predicted fraction of pediatric germ cell tumors cured by site, age, and stage using parameter estimates from cure model. Reprinted with permission. © 2015 American Society of Clinical Oncology.  All rights reserved. Frazier AL, Hale JP, Rodriguez-Galindo C, et al: Revised risk classification for pediatric extracranial germ cell tumors based on 25 years of clinical trial data from the United Kingdom and United States. J Clin Oncol, Vol. 33 (Issue 2), 2015: 195-201.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_1905">For more information about prognosis and prognostic factors for childhood extragonadal extracranial GCTs, see the sections on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_213" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Mature and Immature Teratomas in Children</SummaryRef>, <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_220" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Malignant Gonadal GCTs in Children</SummaryRef>, and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_75" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Malignant Extragonadal Extracranial GCTs in Children</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_588"><Title>Follow-up After Treatment</Title><Para id="_599">The following tests and procedures may be performed at the physician's discretion for monitoring children with extracranial GCTs:</Para><ItemizedList id="_600" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>AFP and beta-hCG.</Strong> Monitor AFP and beta-hCG levels monthly for 6 months  (period of highest risk) and then every 3 months, for a total of 2 years (3 years for sacrococcygeal teratoma). <Para id="_1906">A COG trial of patients with low-risk and intermediate-risk GCTs reported the following results:<Reference refidx="73"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_1907" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Forty-eight patients with elevated tumor markers at diagnosis relapsed during the surveillance phase.</ListItem><ListItem> At the time of relapse (after central review), 47 of 48 (98%) relapses were detected by tumor marker elevation.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Imaging tests.</Strong><ItemizedList id="_676" Style="dash"><ListItem> MRI/CT may be performed  at the completion of therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Guided imaging of the primary site may be performed every 3 months for the first year and every six months for the second year. Seminomas and dysgerminomas may recur later, so the imaging schedule may need to be extended.</ListItem><ListItem>Chest x-ray annually.</ListItem><ListItem>When tumor markers are normal at diagnosis, ultrasonography or CT/MRI may be performed every 3 months for 2 years and then annually for 5 years for germinomas.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_719">Dramatic improvements in survival have been achieved for children and adolescents with cancer.<Reference refidx="74"/> Between 1975 and 2020, childhood cancer mortality decreased by more than 50%.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="74"/><Reference refidx="75"/> During the period from 2002 to 2010, cancer mortality continued to decrease by 2.4% per year for children and adolescents with gonadal tumors, as compared with the period from 1975 to 1998 (plateauing from 1998 to 2001).<Reference refidx="74"/>  Childhood and adolescent cancer survivors require close monitoring because late effects of cancer therapy may persist or develop months or years after treatment.  For information about the incidence, type, and monitoring of late effects of childhood and adolescent cancer survivors, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343584" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-hp-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="6343221" MedlineID="83211763">Dehner LP: Gonadal and extragonadal germ cell neoplasia of childhood. Hum Pathol 14 (6): 493-511, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="18381640">McIntyre A, Gilbert D, Goddard N, et al.: Genes, chromosomes and the development of testicular germ cell tumors of adolescents and adults. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 47 (7): 547-57, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="3">National Cancer Institute: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://NCCRExplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="20597129">Poynter JN, Amatruda JF, Ross JA: Trends in incidence and survival of pediatric and adolescent patients with germ cell tumors in the United States, 1975 to 2006. Cancer 116 (20): 4882-91, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="25489016">Kaatsch P, Häfner C, Calaminus G, et al.: Pediatric germ cell tumors from 1987 to 2011: incidence rates, time trends, and survival. Pediatrics 135 (1): e136-43, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24488779">Ward E, DeSantis C, Robbins A, et al.: Childhood and adolescent cancer statistics, 2014. CA Cancer J Clin 64 (2): 83-103, 2014 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="29447817">Dharmarajan H, Rouillard-Bazinet N, Chandy BM: Mature and immature pediatric head and neck teratomas: A 15-year review at a large tertiary center. Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol 105: 43-47, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="15213888">Isaacs H: Perinatal (fetal and neonatal) germ cell tumors. J Pediatr Surg 39 (7): 1003-13, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15613854">Heerema-McKenney A, Harrison MR, Bratton B, et al.: Congenital teratoma: a clinicopathologic study of 22 fetal and neonatal tumors. Am J Surg Pathol 29 (1): 29-38, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="26611341">Alexander VR, Manjaly JG, Pepper CM, et al.: Head and neck teratomas in children--A series of 23 cases at Great Ormond Street Hospital. Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol 79 (12): 2008-14, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="19603020">Johnson KJ, Ross JA, Poynter JN, et al.: Paediatric germ cell tumours and congenital abnormalities: a Children's Oncology Group study. Br J Cancer 101 (3): 518-21, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="27862157">Huang H, Wang C, Tian Q: Gonadal tumour risk in 292 phenotypic female patients with disorders of sex development containing Y chromosome or Y-derived sequence. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf) 86 (4): 621-627, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29286555">Dicken BJ, Billmire DF, Krailo M, et al.: Gonadal dysgenesis is associated with worse outcomes in patients with ovarian nondysgerminomatous tumors: A report of the Children's Oncology Group AGCT 0132 study. Pediatr Blood Cancer 65 (4): , 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="2837589" MedlineID="88245450">Dexeus FH, Logothetis CJ, Chong C, et al.: Genetic abnormalities in men with germ cell tumors. J Urol 140 (1): 80-4, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="3040921" MedlineID="87310573">Nichols CR, Heerema NA, Palmer C, et al.: Klinefelter's syndrome associated with mediastinal germ cell neoplasms. J Clin Oncol 5 (8): 1290-4, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="3778123" MedlineID="87048001">Lachman MF, Kim K, Koo BC: Mediastinal teratoma associated with Klinefelter's syndrome. Arch Pathol Lab Med 110 (11): 1067-71, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="30291793">Williams LA, Pankratz N, Lane J, et al.: Klinefelter syndrome in males with germ cell tumors: A report from the Children's Oncology Group. Cancer 124 (19): 3900-3908, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="11921289" MedlineID="21917062">Schneider DT, Schuster AE, Fritsch MK, et al.: Genetic analysis of mediastinal nonseminomatous germ cell tumors in children and adolescents. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 34 (1): 115-25, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="9026505" MedlineID="97161638">Coutin AS, Hamy A, Fondevilla M, et al.: [Pure 46XY gonadal dysgenesis] J Gynecol Obstet Biol Reprod (Paris) 25 (8): 792-6, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="3948114" MedlineID="86133098">Amice V, Amice J, Bercovici JP, et al.: Gonadal tumor and H-Y antigen in 46,XY pure gonadal dysgenesis. Cancer 57 (7): 1313-7, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="7979900">Tanaka Y, Sasaki Y, Tachibana K, et al.: Gonadal mixed germ cell tumor combined with a large hemangiomatous lesion in a patient with Turner's syndrome and 45,X/46,X, +mar karyotype. Arch Pathol Lab Med 118 (11): 1135-8, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="22629515">Kota SK, Gayatri K, Pani JP, et al.: Dysgerminoma in a female with turner syndrome and Y chromosome material: A case-based review of literature. Indian J Endocrinol Metab 16 (3): 436-40, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="9533752">Hawkins EP: Germ cell tumors. Am J Clin Pathol 109 (4 Suppl 1): S82-8, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="14752882">Schneider DT, Calaminus G, Koch S, et al.: Epidemiologic analysis of 1,442 children and adolescents registered in the German germ cell tumor protocols. Pediatr Blood Cancer 42 (2): 169-75, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="17719771">Horton Z, Schlatter M, Schultz S: Pediatric germ cell tumors. Surg Oncol 16 (3): 205-13, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="9607423" MedlineID="98268439">Göbel U, Calaminus G, Engert J, et al.: Teratomas in infancy and childhood. Med Pediatr Oncol 31 (1): 8-15, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="9988869">Rescorla FJ: Pediatric germ cell tumors. Semin Surg Oncol 16 (2): 144-58, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="17080330">Harms D, Zahn S, Göbel U, et al.: Pathology and molecular biology of teratomas in childhood and adolescence. Klin Padiatr 218 (6): 296-302, 2006 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="8979209">Tomlinson MW, Alaverdian AA, Alaverdian V: Testosterone-producing benign cystic teratoma with virilism. A case report. J Reprod Med 41 (12): 924-6, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="1384444">Kallis P, Treasure T, Holmes SJ, et al.: Exocrine pancreatic function in mediastinal teratomata: an aid to preoperative diagnosis? Ann Thorac Surg 54 (4): 741-3, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="1260722" MedlineID="76163013">Norris HJ, Zirkin HJ, Benson WL: Immature (malignant) teratoma of the ovary: a clinical and pathologic study of 58 cases. Cancer 37 (5): 2359-72, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="7814189" MedlineID="95113613">O'Connor DM, Norris HJ: The influence of grade on the outcome of stage I ovarian immature (malignant) teratomas and the reproducibility of grading. Int J Gynecol Pathol 13 (4): 283-9, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="9737245" MedlineID="98407263">Heifetz SA, Cushing B, Giller R, et al.: Immature teratomas in children: pathologic considerations: a report from the combined Pediatric Oncology Group/Children's Cancer Group. Am J Surg Pathol 22 (9): 1115-24, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="10561269" MedlineID="20029998">Marina NM, Cushing B, Giller R, et al.: Complete surgical excision is effective treatment for children with immature teratomas with or without malignant elements: A Pediatric Oncology Group/Children's Cancer Group Intergroup Study. J Clin Oncol 17 (7): 2137-43, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="8775270">Lam SK, Cheung LP: Inappropriate ADH secretion due to immature ovarian teratoma. Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol 36 (1): 104-5, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="17080332">Göbel U, Calaminus G, Schneider DT, et al.: The malignant potential of teratomas in infancy and childhood: the MAKEI experiences in non-testicular teratoma and implications for a new protocol. Klin Padiatr 218 (6): 309-14, 2006 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="10463297">Perlman EJ, Hawkins EP: Pediatric germ cell tumors: protocol update for pathologists. Pediatr Dev Pathol 1 (4): 328-35, 1998 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="17285132">Palmer RD, Foster NA, Vowler SL, et al.: Malignant germ cell tumours of childhood: new associations of genomic imbalance. Br J Cancer 96 (4): 667-76, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="18519683">Palmer RD, Barbosa-Morais NL, Gooding EL, et al.: Pediatric malignant germ cell tumors show characteristic transcriptome profiles. Cancer Res 68 (11): 4239-47, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="22072546">Poynter JN, Hooten AJ, Frazier AL, et al.: Associations between variants in KITLG, SPRY4, BAK1, and DMRT1 and pediatric germ cell tumors. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 51 (3): 266-71, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="2536126" MedlineID="89095727">Oosterhuis JW, Castedo SM, de Jong B, et al.: Ploidy of primary germ cell tumors of the testis. Pathogenetic and clinical relevance. Lab Invest 60 (1): 14-21, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="7892165" MedlineID="95199223">Silver SA, Wiley JM, Perlman EJ: DNA ploidy analysis of pediatric germ cell tumors. Mod Pathol 7 (9): 951-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="7971587" MedlineID="95061743">Perlman EJ, Cushing B, Hawkins E, et al.: Cytogenetic analysis of childhood endodermal sinus tumors: a Pediatric Oncology Group study. Pediatr Pathol 14 (4): 695-708, 1994 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="11528555" MedlineID="21419551">Schneider DT, Schuster AE, Fritsch MK, et al.: Genetic analysis of childhood germ cell tumors with comparative genomic hybridization. Klin Padiatr 213 (4): 204-11, 2001 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="10337997">Bussey KJ, Lawce HJ, Olson SB, et al.: Chromosome abnormalities of eighty-one pediatric germ cell tumors: sex-, age-, site-, and histopathology-related differences--a Children's Cancer Group study. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 25 (2): 134-46, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="9162192" MedlineID="97013657">Perlman EJ, Valentine MB, Griffin CA, et al.: Deletion of 1p36 in childhood endodermal sinus tumors by two-color fluorescence in situ hybridization: a pediatric oncology group study. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 16 (1): 15-20, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="7512366" MedlineID="94206868">Rodriguez E, Houldsworth J, Reuter VE, et al.: Molecular cytogenetic analysis of i(12p)-negative human male germ cell tumors. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 8 (4): 230-6, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="8308927" MedlineID="94141962">Bosl GJ, Ilson DH, Rodriguez E, et al.: Clinical relevance of the i(12p) marker chromosome in germ cell tumors. J Natl Cancer Inst 86 (5): 349-55, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="9632138" MedlineID="98293927">Mostert MC, Verkerk AJ, van de Pol M, et al.: Identification of the critical region of 12p over-representation in testicular germ cell tumors of adolescents and adults. Oncogene 16 (20): 2617-27, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="8527395" MedlineID="96108406">van Echten J, Oosterhuis JW, Looijenga LH, et al.: No recurrent structural abnormalities apart from i(12p) in primary germ cell tumors of the adult testis. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 14 (2): 133-44, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="9679978" MedlineID="98343572">Riopel MA, Spellerberg A, Griffin CA, et al.: Genetic analysis of ovarian germ cell tumors by comparative genomic hybridization. Cancer Res 58 (14): 3105-10, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="2156245" MedlineID="90192504">Malogolowkin MH, Mahour GH, Krailo M, et al.: Germ cell tumors in infancy and childhood: a 45-year experience. Pediatr Pathol 10 (1-2): 231-41, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="6268666" MedlineID="82008224">Marsden HB, Birch JM, Swindell R: Germ cell tumours of childhood: a review of 137 cases. J Clin Pathol 34 (8): 879-83, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="2790759" MedlineID="90002866">Dal Cin P, Drochmans A, Moerman P, et al.: Isochromosome 12p in mediastinal germ cell tumor. Cancer Genet Cytogenet 42 (2): 243-51, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="8174074" MedlineID="94228462">Aly MS, Dal Cin P, Jiskoot P, et al.: Competitive in situ hybridization in a mediastinal germ cell tumor. Cancer Genet Cytogenet 73 (1): 53-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="6181870">Vogelzang NJ, Lange PH, Goldman A, et al.: Acute changes of alpha-fetoprotein and human chorionic gonadotropin during induction chemotherapy of germ cell tumors. Cancer Res 42 (11): 4855-61, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="6163129">Wu JT, Book L, Sudar K: Serum alpha fetoprotein (AFP) levels in normal infants. Pediatr Res 15 (1): 50-2, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="9592840">Blohm ME, Vesterling-Hörner D, Calaminus G, et al.: Alpha 1-fetoprotein (AFP) reference values in infants up to 2 years of age. Pediatr Hematol Oncol 15 (2): 135-42, 1998 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="11078494" MedlineID="20530736">Mann JR, Raafat F, Robinson K, et al.: The United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group's second germ cell tumor study: carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin are effective treatment for children with malignant extracranial germ cell tumors, with acceptable toxicity. J Clin Oncol 18 (22): 3809-18, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="1384951" MedlineID="93046025">Marina N, Fontanesi J, Kun L, et al.: Treatment of childhood germ cell tumors. Review of the St. Jude experience from 1979 to 1988. Cancer 70 (10): 2568-75, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="31355926">O'Neill AF, Xia C, Krailo MD, et al.: α-Fetoprotein as a predictor of outcome for children with germ cell tumors: A report from the Malignant Germ Cell International Consortium. Cancer 125 (20): 3649-3656, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="30875280">Dieckmann KP, Radtke A, Geczi L, et al.: Serum Levels of MicroRNA-371a-3p (M371 Test) as a New Biomarker of Testicular Germ Cell Tumors: Results of a Prospective Multicentric Study. J Clin Oncol 37 (16): 1412-1423, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="15337806">Rogers PC, Olson TA, Cullen JW, et al.: Treatment of children and adolescents with stage II testicular and stages I and II ovarian malignant germ cell tumors: A Pediatric Intergroup Study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9048 and Children's Cancer Group 8891. J Clin Oncol 22 (17): 3563-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="15226336">Cushing B, Giller R, Cullen JW, et al.: Randomized comparison of combination chemotherapy with etoposide, bleomycin, and either high-dose or standard-dose cisplatin in children and adolescents with high-risk malignant germ cell tumors: a pediatric intergroup study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9049 and Children's Cancer Group 8882. J Clin Oncol 22 (13): 2691-700, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="11283126">Göbel U, Schneider DT, Calaminus G, et al.: Multimodal treatment of malignant sacrococcygeal germ cell tumors: a prospective analysis of 66 patients of the German cooperative protocols MAKEI 83/86 and 89. J Clin Oncol 19 (7): 1943-50, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="25452439">Frazier AL, Hale JP, Rodriguez-Galindo C, et al.: Revised risk classification for pediatric extracranial germ cell tumors based on 25 years of clinical trial data from the United Kingdom and United States. J Clin Oncol 33 (2): 195-201, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="9053482" MedlineID="97178749">International Germ Cell Consensus Classification: a prognostic factor-based staging system for metastatic germ cell cancers. International Germ Cell Cancer Collaborative Group. J Clin Oncol 15 (2): 594-603, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="33079404">Shaikh F, Stark D, Fonseca A, et al.: Outcomes of adolescent males with extracranial metastatic germ cell tumors: A report from the Malignant Germ Cell Tumor International Consortium. Cancer 127 (2): 193-202, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="17235042">Motzer RJ, Nichols CJ, Margolin KA, et al.: Phase III randomized trial of conventional-dose chemotherapy with or without high-dose chemotherapy and autologous hematopoietic stem-cell rescue as first-line treatment for patients with poor-prognosis metastatic germ cell tumors. J Clin Oncol 25 (3): 247-56, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="25456363">Fizazi K, Pagliaro L, Laplanche A, et al.: Personalised chemotherapy based on tumour marker decline in poor prognosis germ-cell tumours (GETUG 13): a phase 3, multicentre, randomised trial. Lancet Oncol 15 (13): 1442-50, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="20920735">Thorup J, McLachlan R, Cortes D, et al.: What is new in cryptorchidism and hypospadias--a critical review on the testicular dysgenesis hypothesis. J Pediatr Surg 45 (10): 2074-86, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="29331749">Duhil de Bénazé G, Pacquement H, Faure-Conter C, et al.: Paediatric dysgerminoma: Results of three consecutive French germ cell tumours clinical studies (TGM-85/90/95) with late effects study. Eur J Cancer 91: 30-37, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="30576269">Fonseca A, Xia C, Lorenzo AJ, et al.: Detection of Relapse by Tumor Markers Versus Imaging in Children and Adolescents With Nongerminomatous Malignant Germ Cell Tumors: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 37 (5): 396-402, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="24853691">Smith MA, Altekruse SF, Adamson PC, et al.: Declining childhood and adolescent cancer mortality. Cancer 120 (16): 2497-506, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="75">Surveillance Research Program, National Cancer Institute: SEER*Explorer: An interactive website for SEER cancer statistics. 	Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statistics-network/explorer/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043493">childhood extracranial germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Childhood Extracranial GCTs</Title><Para id="_19">As with other childhood solid tumors, stage of disease at diagnosis directly impacts the outcome of
patients with malignant germ cell tumors (GCTs).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  The most commonly used staging
systems in the United States are as follows:<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_462" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_374" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Testicular GCT Staging (Children's Oncology Group [COG])</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_376" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Ovarian GCT Staging (COG)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_378" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Ovarian GCT Staging (International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics [FIGO])</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_385" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Extragonadal Extracranial GCT Staging (COG)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_374"><Title>Testicular GCT Staging From COG (Patients Aged &lt;11 Years)</Title><Para id="_754"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_731" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 3</SummaryRef> describes the testicular GCT staging for males younger than 11 years from the COG <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 (NCT03067181)</ProtocolRef> trial.</Para><Table id="_731"><Title>Table 3.  Testicular GCT Staging From the  COG AGCT1531 Trial<Superscript>a,b</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="17.54%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="82.45%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage</entry><entry>Extent of Disease</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">COG = Children's Oncology Group; CT = computed tomography; GCT = germ cell tumor.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Males younger than 50 years  are eligible for the AGCT1531 trial.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>COG trials include patients younger than 15 years  with testicular GCT. Although data are scarce, patients between the ages of 11 years and 15 years might be more appropriately staged according to adult testicular guidelines. For more information about the staging of adult testicular GCTs, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062899" url="/types/testicular/hp/testicular-treatment-pdq">Testicular Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="3"><Strong>I</Strong></entry><entry>(1) Tumor limited to testis (testes) with negative microscopic margins, completely resected by high inguinal orchiectomy;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(2) Tumor capsule cannot have been violated by needle biopsy, incisional biopsy, or tumor rupture. Patients who have undergone scrotal orchiectomy without violation of the tumor capsule and with removal of the spermatic cord to the level of the internal ring are stage I. Patients who have undergone excisional biopsy for frozen section analysis with complete orchiectomy and cord excision at the same operation can be designated stage I;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(3) No clinical, radiographic, or histological evidence of disease beyond the testes;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(4) Lymph nodes all &lt;1 cm maximum short-axis diameter on multiplanar imaging. (Note: Nodes 1–2 cm require short-interval follow-up in 4–6 weeks. If nodes are unchanged at 4–6 weeks [1–2 cm], consider biopsy or transfer to chemotherapy arm. If growing, transfer to chemotherapy arm.)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2"><Strong>II</Strong></entry><entry>(1) Complete orchiectomy with violation of the tumor capsule <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> (includes preoperative needle biopsy and incisional biopsy or intraoperative tumor capsule rupture);</entry></Row><Row><entry>(2) Microscopic disease in scrotum or high in spermatic cord (&lt;5 cm from proximal end). Failure of tumor markers to normalize or decrease with an appropriate half-life;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(3) Lymph nodes negative.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"><Strong>III</Strong></entry><entry>(1) Retroperitoneal lymph node involvement, but no visceral or extra-abdominal involvement;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(2) Lymph nodes ≥2 cm or lymph nodes &gt;1 cm but &lt;2 cm on short axis by multiplanar imaging CT that fail to resolve on re-imaging at 4–6 weeks.</entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong>IV</Strong></entry><entry>(1) Distant metastases, including liver, lung, bone, and brain.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_677"><Title>Testicular GCT Staging (Patients Aged ≥11 Years)</Title><Para id="_679">Retroperitoneal lymph node dissection has not been required in pediatric germ cell trials to stage disease in males younger than 15 years.  Data on adolescent males with testicular GCTs are limited.  Retroperitoneal lymph node dissection is used for both staging and treatment in adult testicular GCT trials.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_1861">In males older than 15 years, there are only stage I tumors and metastatic tumors. Metastatic tumors are assigned risk according to the International Germ Cell Consensus Classification.<Reference refidx="6"/> </Para><Para id="_678">For more information about the American Joint Committee on Cancer staging criteria for testicular GCT in males aged 11 years and older, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062899" url="/types/testicular/hp/testicular-treatment-pdq">Testicular Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_376"><Title>Ovarian GCT Staging From COG</Title><Para id="_755"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_732" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 4</SummaryRef> describes the ovarian GCT staging for females younger than 11 years from the COG <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 (NCT03067181)</ProtocolRef> trial.</Para><Table id="_732"><Title>Table 4.  Ovarian GCT Staging From the  COG AGCT1531 Trial<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="13.34%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="3.53%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="83.12%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Extent of Disease</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">COG = Children's Oncology Group; CT = computed tomography; GCT = germ cell tumor.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Bilateral ovarian tumors may be any stage as long as other stage criteria are met. Tumor staged according to ovary with most advanced features.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="4"><Strong>I</Strong></entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(1) Ovarian tumor removed without violation of the tumor capsule;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(2) No evidence of partial or complete capsular penetration;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(3) Peritoneal cytology negative for malignant cells;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(4) Peritoneal surfaces and omentum documented to be free of disease in operative note or biopsied with negative histology if abnormal in appearance;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(5) Lymph nodes all &lt;1 cm by short-axis diameter on multiplanar imaging or biopsy proven negative. (Note: Nodes 1–2 cm require short-interval follow-up in 4–6 weeks. If nodes are unchanged at 4–6 weeks [1–2 cm], consider biopsy or transfer to chemotherapy arm. If growing, transfer to chemotherapy arm.)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4"><Strong>II</Strong></entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">  (1) Ovarian tumor completely removed but with preoperative biopsy, violation of tumor capsule <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis>, or presence of partial or complete capsule penetration at histology;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(2) Tumor &gt;10 cm removed laparoscopically;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(3) Tumor morcellated for removal so that capsule cannot be assessed for penetration;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(4) Peritoneal cytology must be negative  for malignant cells;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(5) Lymph nodes, peritoneal surfaces, and omentum documented to be free of disease in operative note or biopsied with negative histology if abnormal in appearance.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4"><Strong>III</Strong></entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(1) Lymph nodes ≥2 cm or lymph nodes &gt;1 cm but &lt;2 cm on short axis by multiplanar imaging CT that fail to resolve on re-imaging at 4–6 weeks;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(2) Ovarian tumor biopsy or removal with gross residual;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(3) Positive peritoneal fluid cytology for malignant cells, including immature teratoma;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(4) Lymph nodes positive for malignant cells, including immature teratoma;</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(5) Peritoneal implants positive for malignant cells, including immature teratoma.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4"><Strong>III–X</Strong></entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Patients otherwise stage I or II by COG criteria but with the following: </entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>(1) Failure to collect peritoneal cytology;</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>(2) Failure to biopsy lymph nodes &gt;1 cm on short axis by multiplanar imaging;</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>(3) Failure to sample abnormal peritoneal surfaces or omentum; or</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>(4) Delayed completion of surgical staging at a second procedure for patients who had only oophorectomy at first procedure.</entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong>IV</Strong></entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">(1) Metastatic disease to the parenchyma of the liver (surface implants are stage III) or metastases outside the peritoneal cavity to any other viscera (bone, lung, or brain) and pleural fluid with positive cytology.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_378"><Title>Ovarian GCT Staging From FIGO</Title><Para id="_379">Another ovarian GCT staging system used frequently by gynecologic oncologists is the
FIGO staging system, which
is based on adequate surgical staging at the time of diagnosis.<Reference refidx="7"/> This
system has also been used by some pediatric centers,<Reference refidx="2"/> is most applicable to females older than 11 years, and is  described in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_717" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 5</SummaryRef>. For more information about the FIGO staging system, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062935" url="/types/ovarian/hp/ovarian-germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Ovarian Germ Cell Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Table id="_717"><Title>Table 5.  FIGO Staging for Carcinoma of the Ovary<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="7.43%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="14.12%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="78.43%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">Stage</entry><entry>Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Berek et al.<Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1"><Strong>I</Strong></entry><entry><Strong>Tumor confined to the ovary.</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IA</entry><entry>Tumor limited to one ovary (capsule intact); no tumor on surface of the ovary; no malignant cells in the ascites or peritoneal washings.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IB</entry><entry>Tumor limited to both ovaries (capsules intact); no tumor on surface of the ovary; no malignant cells in the ascites or peritoneal washings.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IC</entry><entry>Tumor limited to one or both ovaries, with any of the following:</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IC1</entry><entry>Surgical spill.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IC2</entry><entry>Capsule ruptured before surgery or tumor on the surface of the ovary.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IC3</entry><entry>Malignant cells in the ascites or peritoneal washings.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1"><Strong>II</Strong></entry><entry><Strong>Tumor involves one or both ovaries with pelvic extension (below pelvic brim) or primary peritoneal cancer.</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIA</entry><entry>Extension and/or implants on uterus and/or fallopian tubes.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIB</entry><entry>Extension to other pelvic intraperitoneal tissues.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1"><Strong>III</Strong></entry><entry><Strong>Tumor involves one or both ovaries or primary peritoneal cancer, with cytologically or histologically confirmed spread to the peritoneum outside the pelvis and/or metastasis to the retroperitoneal lymph nodes.</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIA1</entry><entry>Positive retroperitoneal lymph nodes only (cytologically or histologically proven):</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIA1(i)</entry><entry>Lymph nodes ≤10 mm in greatest dimension.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIA1(ii)</entry><entry>Lymph nodes &gt;10 mm in greatest dimension.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIA2</entry><entry>Microscopic extrapelvic (above the pelvic brim) peritoneal involvement with or without positive retroperitoneal lymph nodes.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIB</entry><entry>Macroscopic peritoneal metastasis beyond the pelvis ≤2 cm in greatest dimension, with or without metastasis to the retroperitoneal lymph nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIC</entry><entry>Macroscopic peritoneal metastasis beyond the pelvis &gt;2 cm in greatest dimension, with or without metastasis to the retroperitoneal lymph nodes (includes extension of tumor to capsule of liver and spleen without parenchymal involvement of either organ).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1"><Strong>IV</Strong></entry><entry><Strong>Distant metastasis excluding peritoneal metastases.</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IVA</entry><entry>Pleural effusion with positive cytology.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IVB</entry><entry>Parenchymal metastases and metastases to extra-abdominal organs (including inguinal lymph nodes and lymph nodes outside of the abdominal cavity).</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_757">The ovarian staging systems described above require adherence to specific surgical guidelines. However, in a pediatric intergroup trial, guidelines were followed in only 2 of 131 patients with ovarian tumors.<Reference refidx="9"/>  In a single-institution retrospective study, guidelines were followed in only 2 of 44 patients with ovarian tumors.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_385"><Title>Extragonadal Extracranial GCT Staging From COG</Title><Para id="_756"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_733" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 6</SummaryRef> describes the extragonadal extracranial GCT staging from the COG <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 (NCT03067181)</ProtocolRef> trial.</Para><Table id="_733"><Title>Table 6.  Extragonadal Extracranial GCT Staging From the  COG AGCT1531 Trial</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="17.54%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="82.45%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage</entry><entry>Extent of Disease</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">COG = Children's Oncology Group; CT = computed tomography; GCT = germ cell tumor.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="3"><Strong>I</Strong></entry><entry>(1) Complete resection at any site, including coccygectomy for sacrococcygeal site;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(2) Must have negative tumor margins and intact capsule;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(3) For any tumors involving abdominal cavity or retroperitoneum, peritoneal fluid or washings must be done for cytology and be negative for malignant cells;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(4) Lymph nodes ≤1 cm by imaging of abdomen, pelvis, and chest. (Note: Nodes 1–2 cm require short-interval follow-up in 4–6 weeks. If nodes are unchanged at 4–6 weeks [1–2 cm], consider biopsy or transfer to chemotherapy arm. If growing, transfer to chemotherapy arm. For any tumors involving abdominal cavity or retroperitoneum, peritoneal fluid or washings must be done for cytology and be negative for malignant cells.)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2"><Strong>II</Strong></entry><entry>(1) Microscopic residual disease;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(2) Gross-total resection with preoperative biopsy, intraoperative biopsy, microscopic residual disease, or pathological evidence of capsular disruption;</entry></Row><Row><entry>(3) Lymph nodes negative by abdomen, pelvic, and chest imaging. Peritoneal fluid negative.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"><Strong>III</Strong></entry><entry>(1) Gross residual disease or biopsy only; </entry></Row><Row><entry>(2) Lymph nodes positive with tumor resection. Lymph nodes ≥2 cm or lymph nodes &gt;1 cm but &lt;2 cm on short axis by multiplanar imaging CT that fail to resolve on re-imaging at 4–6 weeks.</entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong>IV</Strong></entry><entry>Distant metastases, including liver, lung, bone, and brain.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1717667" MedlineID="92014151">Ablin AR, Krailo MD, Ramsay NK, et al.: Results of treatment of malignant germ cell tumors in 93 children: a report from the Childrens Cancer Study Group. J Clin Oncol 9 (10): 1782-92, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2467734" MedlineID="89195012">Mann JR, Pearson D, Barrett A, et al.: Results of the United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group's malignant germ cell tumor studies. Cancer 63 (9): 1657-67, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1384951" MedlineID="93046025">Marina N, Fontanesi J, Kun L, et al.: Treatment of childhood germ cell tumors. Review of the St. Jude experience from 1979 to 1988. Cancer 70 (10): 2568-75, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="7284981" MedlineID="82025321">Brodeur GM, Howarth CB, Pratt CB, et al.: Malignant germ cell tumors in 57 children and adolescents. Cancer 48 (8): 1890-8, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="17158533">de Wit R, Fizazi K: Controversies in the management of clinical stage I testis cancer. J Clin Oncol 24 (35): 5482-92, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="9053482" MedlineID="97178749">International Germ Cell Consensus Classification: a prognostic factor-based staging system for metastatic germ cell cancers. International Germ Cell Cancer Collaborative Group. J Clin Oncol 15 (2): 594-603, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="8155119" MedlineID="94019647">Cannistra SA: Cancer of the ovary. N Engl J Med 329 (21): 1550-9, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="34669199">Berek JS, Renz M, Kehoe S, et al.: Cancer of the ovary, fallopian tube, and peritoneum: 2021 update. Int J Gynaecol Obstet 155 (Suppl 1): 61-85, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15017564">Billmire D, Vinocur C, Rescorla F, et al.: Outcome and staging evaluation in malignant germ cell tumors of the ovary in children and adolescents: an intergroup study. J Pediatr Surg 39 (3): 424-9; discussion 424-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="27125730">Madenci AL, Levine BS, Laufer MR, et al.: Poor adherence to staging guidelines for children with malignant ovarian tumors. J Pediatr Surg 51 (9): 1513-7, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_44"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043493">childhood extracranial germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment  Option Overview for Childhood Extracranial  GCTs</Title><Para id="_414">Childhood extracranial germ cell tumors (GCTs) are very heterogenous.</Para><Para id="_467">On the basis of clinical factors and tumor histology, appropriate treatment for extracranial GCTs may involve one of the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_468" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgical resection followed by careful monitoring for disease recurrence.</ListItem><ListItem>Initial surgical resection followed by platinum-based chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Diagnostic tumor biopsy and preoperative platinum-based chemotherapy followed by definitive tumor resection.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_726">To maximize long-term survival while minimizing treatment-related long-term sequelae (e.g., secondary leukemias, infertility, hearing loss, and renal dysfunction), children with extracranial malignant GCTs need to be cared for at pediatric cancer centers with experience treating these rare tumors. </Para><SummarySection id="_683"><Title>Treatment Options for Childhood Extracranial GCTs by Histological Type</Title><Para id="_139"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_718" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 7</SummaryRef> provides an
overview of treatment options for children with extracranial GCTs.  Specific details of treatment by primary site and clinical condition are described in subsequent sections.
</Para><Table id="_718"><Title>Table 7.  Treatment Options for Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors (GCTs)</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="6.57%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="6.90%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="37.30%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="4" ColWidth="49.21%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">Histology 	</entry><entry>Treatment Options </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">BEP = bleomycin (weekly), etoposide, and cisplatin; JEb = carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin;  PEb = cisplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin (bleomycin only on day 1 of each cycle).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Chemotherapy has not been shown to be effective in the treatment of children with stages II–IV immature teratoma. However, the role of chemotherapy in these patients has not been systematically studied. In postpubertal patients, chemotherapy remains the standard treatment, although studies are limited.<Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>In prepubertal females with reported stage I disease, but in whom strict surgical staging guidelines were not followed, chemotherapy (PEb) can be considered standard treatment.<Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>In postpubertal females with stage I disease, the strategy of observation after surgery has not been established. This treatment strategy is under investigation in a clinical trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 [NCT03067181]</ProtocolRef>).</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Mature teratoma</Strong></entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col02">Sacrococcygeal site</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_689" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col02">Nonsacrococcygeal site</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_475" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1" NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Immature teratoma</Strong></entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_604" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation (stage I)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_609" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery  and observation or chemotherapy (stages I–IV)</SummaryRef><Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Malignant gonadal GCTs in children:</Strong> 
 	</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col02">Childhood malignant testicular GCTs: 
</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry MoreRows="1">Malignant testicular GCTs in prepubertal males </entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_532" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation (stage I)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_535" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (PEb) (stages II–IV)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Malignant testicular GCTs in postpubertal males </entry><entry>For information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062899" url="/types/testicular/hp/testicular-treatment-pdq">Testicular Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col02">Childhood malignant ovarian GCTs: </entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry MoreRows="1">Dysgerminomas of the ovary </entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_538" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation (stage I)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_541" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (PEb) (stages II–IV)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry MoreRows="1">Malignant nongerminomatous ovarian GCTs (yolk sac and mixed GCTs) in prepubertal females </entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1809" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation for prepubertal females (stage I following strict surgical staging guidelines)</SummaryRef><Superscript>b</Superscript>. For information about the treatment of ovarian mature teratoma, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_70" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Childhood Malignant Ovarian GCTs</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1813" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (PEb) for prepubertal and postpubertal females (purported stage I and stages II–IV)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Malignant nongerminomatous ovarian GCTs (yolk sac and mixed GCTs) in postpubertal females</entry><entry> <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1813" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (BEP) for prepubertal and postpubertal females  (purported stage I and stages II–IV)</SummaryRef><Superscript>c</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>Malignant nongerminomatous ovarian GCTs (yolk sac and mixed GCTs) that are initially unresectable</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_552" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Biopsy followed by chemotherapy and surgery (initially unresectable ovarian GCT)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs in children:</Strong> </entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry MoreRows="1" NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col02">Malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs in prepubertal children</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_560" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (PEb or JEb) (stages I –IV)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1919" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Biopsy followed by chemotherapy with or without surgery (stages III and IV)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3"/><entry MoreRows="3" NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col02">Malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs in postpubertal children</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_708" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_708" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy (BEP)</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_708" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy followed by surgery to remove residual tumor</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_708" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Enrollment in a clinical trial</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1" NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Recurrent malignant GCTs in children</Strong>  </entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_426" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery 
alone</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_428" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery with neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_397"><Title>GCTs with non-GCT elements (teratoma with malignant transformation)</Title><Para id="_398">The treatment of GCTs with other non-GCT somatic elements is complex, and few data exist to direct treatment.  In adolescents, central primitive neuroectodermal tumors and sarcomas have been found in teratomas.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> The Italian Pediatric Germ Cell Tumor group identified 14 patients with malignant GCTs with a somatic malignancy, such as neuroblastoma or rhabdomyosarcoma, embedded in teratomas (&lt;2% of extracranial GCTs).<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_727">The optimal treatment strategy for GCTs with non-GCT elements  has not been determined. Separate treatments for both malignant GCTs and non-GCT elements may be required.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_415"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_416">Surgery is an essential component of treatment. Specific treatments will be discussed for each tumor type.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_680"><Title>Surgery and Observation</Title><Para id="_681">For patients with completely resected immature teratomas of all grades and at any location, and for patients with localized, completely resected (stage I) seminomatous and nonseminomatous GCTs (testicular and ovarian), additional therapy may not be necessary. However, close monitoring of patients is important.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> The watch-and-wait approach requires scheduled serial physical examination, tumor marker determination, and primary tumor imaging to ensure that a recurrent tumor is detected without delay. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_418"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_286">In the United States, the standard chemotherapy regimen for both adults and children with malignant nonseminomatous GCTs includes cisplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin. Adult patients receive weekly bleomycin throughout treatment (bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin [BEP]).<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> U.S. pediatric trials included patients aged 15 years and younger with testicular GCTs and patients aged 21 years and younger with ovarian and extragonadal GCTs. Patients received bleomycin only on day 1 of each cycle (cisplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin [PEb]).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="13"/>   The combination of carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin (JEb) underwent clinical investigation in the United Kingdom in children younger than 16 years. Treatment with this regimen produced event-free survival (EFS) rates by site and stage similar to those produced using treatment with PEb.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>; <Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] For information about adult BEP and pediatric PEb and JEb chemotherapy dosing schedules, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_156" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 8</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="13"/> In both adult and pediatric trials, the number of adolescent subjects was small. The optimal therapy for adolescents (aged ≥11 years) is not clear.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_736"> The use of JEb appears to be associated with fewer otologic toxic effects and renal toxic effects than does the use of PEb.<Reference refidx="14"/>   In a retrospective meta-analysis of data from the Children’s Oncology Group (COG) and the Children’s Cancer and Leukaemia Group germ cell studies conducted contemporaneously, the multivariate cure model showed no difference in 4-year EFS rates. The 4-year EFS rate was 86% (95% confidence interval [CI], 83%–89%) for patients who received the cisplatin regimen (n = 620) and 86% (95% CI, 79%–90%) for patients who received the carboplatin regimen (n = 163) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .87).<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] However, PEb and JEb have not been compared in a randomized pediatric GCT trial. </Para><Table id="_156"><Title>  Table 8.  Comparison of Adult BEP and Pediatric PEb and JEb Chemotherapy Dosing Schedules</Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="18.34%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="18.34%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="18.34%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="18.34%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="26.63%"/><THead><Row><entry>Regimen</entry><entry>Bleomycin</entry><entry>Etoposide</entry><entry>Cisplatin</entry><entry>Carboplatin</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col1">BEP = bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin; GFR = glomerular filtration rate; JEb = carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin; PEb = cisplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Adult BEP (every 21 days) <Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="19"/></entry><entry>30 units/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, days 1, 8, 15 (maximum 30 units)</entry><entry>100 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, days 1–5</entry><entry>20 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, days 1–5</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Pediatric PEb (every 21 days) <Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>15 units/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, day 1 (maximum 30 units)</entry><entry>100 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, days 1–5</entry><entry>20 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, days 1–5</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Pediatric JEb (every 21–28 days) <Reference refidx="14"/></entry><entry>15 units/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, day  3  (maximum 30 units)</entry><entry>120 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, days 1–3</entry><entry/><entry>600 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> or  GFR-based dosing,  day 2</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_287">Several trials were conducted by the COG (previously the Children's Cancer Group and the Pediatric Oncology Group).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="13"/> These trials explored the use of PEb for the treatment of localized gonadal GCT <Reference refidx="3"/> and intensified regimens for patients with poor-risk features. The strategies included high-dose cisplatin (200 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) 
and cyclophosphamide or the protective agent amifostine.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="20"/> None of these strategies had a significant effect on survival or decreased toxicity. </Para><Para id="_1862">The COG conducted a trial of compressed and reduced PEb chemotherapy (three cycles in 3 days) for patients with low-risk or intermediate-risk malignant GCTs. This study was designed as a noninferior trial with a <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> value of .1. The 4-year EFS rate of 89%  was significantly lower than  the rate for the historical control  model (92%;  <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .08).<Reference refidx="21"/> However, the number of patients in each stratum was small, and further investigation in patients with lower-stage disease may be warranted.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_470"><Title>Radiation Therapy</Title><Para id="_471">Testicular and mediastinal seminomas in males and ovarian dysgerminomas in females are sensitive to radiation, but radiation therapy is rarely recommended because of the known late effects.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="9988869">Rescorla FJ: Pediatric germ cell tumors. Semin Surg Oncol 16 (2): 144-58, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1260722" MedlineID="76163013">Norris HJ, Zirkin HJ, Benson WL: Immature (malignant) teratoma of the ovary: a clinical and pathologic study of 58 cases. Cancer 37 (5): 2359-72, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="15337806">Rogers PC, Olson TA, Cullen JW, et al.: Treatment of children and adolescents with stage II testicular and stages I and II ovarian malignant germ cell tumors: A Pediatric Intergroup Study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9048 and Children's Cancer Group 8891. J Clin Oncol 22 (17): 3563-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="20231305">Ehrlich Y, Beck SD, Ulbright TM, et al.: Outcome analysis of patients with transformed teratoma to primitive neuroectodermal tumor. Ann Oncol 21 (9): 1846-50, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="24952240">Rice KR, Magers MJ, Beck SD, et al.: Management of germ cell tumors with somatic type malignancy: pathological features, prognostic factors and survival outcomes. J Urol 192 (5): 1403-9, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20049928">Terenziani M, D'Angelo P, Bisogno G, et al.: Teratoma with a malignant somatic component in pediatric patients: the Associazione Italiana Ematologia Oncologia Pediatrica (AIEOP) experience. Pediatr Blood Cancer 54 (4): 532-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="10561269" MedlineID="20029998">Marina NM, Cushing B, Giller R, et al.: Complete surgical excision is effective treatment for children with immature teratomas with or without malignant elements: A Pediatric Oncology Group/Children's Cancer Group Intergroup Study. J Clin Oncol 17 (7): 2137-43, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12632342" MedlineID="22519191">Schlatter M, Rescorla F, Giller R, et al.: Excellent outcome in patients with stage I germ cell tumors of the testes: a study of the Children's Cancer Group/Pediatric Oncology Group. J Pediatr Surg 38 (3): 319-24; discussion 319-24, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11250991" MedlineID="21150310">de Wit R, Roberts JT, Wilkinson PM, et al.: Equivalence of three or four cycles of bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin chemotherapy and of a 3- or 5-day schedule in good-prognosis germ cell cancer: a randomized study of the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Genitourinary Tract Cancer Cooperative Group and the Medical Research Council. J Clin Oncol 19 (6): 1629-40, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="1690272" MedlineID="90188473">Gershenson DM, Morris M, Cangir A, et al.: Treatment of malignant germ cell tumors of the ovary with bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin. J Clin Oncol 8 (4): 715-20, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2437455" MedlineID="87201806">Williams SD, Birch R, Einhorn LH, et al.: Treatment of disseminated germ-cell tumors with cisplatin, bleomycin, and either vinblastine or etoposide. N Engl J Med 316 (23): 1435-40, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="9053482" MedlineID="97178749">International Germ Cell Consensus Classification: a prognostic factor-based staging system for metastatic germ cell cancers. International Germ Cell Cancer Collaborative Group. J Clin Oncol 15 (2): 594-603, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="15226336">Cushing B, Giller R, Cullen JW, et al.: Randomized comparison of combination chemotherapy with etoposide, bleomycin, and either high-dose or standard-dose cisplatin in children and adolescents with high-risk malignant germ cell tumors: a pediatric intergroup study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9049 and Children's Cancer Group 8882. J Clin Oncol 22 (13): 2691-700, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="11078494" MedlineID="20530736">Mann JR, Raafat F, Robinson K, et al.: The United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group's second germ cell tumor study: carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin are effective treatment for children with malignant extracranial germ cell tumors, with acceptable toxicity. J Clin Oncol 18 (22): 3809-18, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="12210444" MedlineID="22199335">Stern JW, Bunin N: Prospective study of carboplatin-based chemotherapy for pediatric germ cell tumors. Med Pediatr Oncol 39 (3): 163-7, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="31306943">Depani S, Stoneham S, Krailo M, et al.: Results from the UK Children's Cancer and Leukaemia Group study of extracranial germ cell tumours in children and adolescents (GCIII). Eur J Cancer 118: 49-57, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="25452439">Frazier AL, Hale JP, Rodriguez-Galindo C, et al.: Revised risk classification for pediatric extracranial germ cell tumors based on 25 years of clinical trial data from the United Kingdom and United States. J Clin Oncol 33 (2): 195-201, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="29859339">Frazier AL, Stoneham S, Rodriguez-Galindo C, et al.: Comparison of carboplatin versus cisplatin in the treatment of paediatric extracranial malignant germ cell tumours: A report of the Malignant Germ Cell International Consortium. Eur J Cancer 98: 30-37, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="2465391" MedlineID="89140928">Einhorn LH, Williams SD, Loehrer PJ, et al.: Evaluation of optimal duration of chemotherapy in favorable-prognosis disseminated germ cell tumors: a Southeastern Cancer Study Group protocol. J Clin Oncol 7 (3): 387-91, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="15999362">Marina N, Chang KW, Malogolowkin M, et al.: Amifostine does not protect against the ototoxicity of high-dose cisplatin combined with etoposide and bleomycin in pediatric germ-cell tumors: a Children's Oncology Group study. Cancer 104 (4): 841-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="28240974">Shaikh F, Cullen JW, Olson TA, et al.: Reduced and Compressed Cisplatin-Based Chemotherapy in Children and Adolescents With Intermediate-Risk Extracranial Malignant Germ Cell Tumors: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 35 (11): 1203-1210, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_666"><Title>Special Considerations for the Treatment of Children With Cancer</Title><Para id="_666_md_3">Cancer in children and adolescents is rare, although the overall incidence has slowly increased since 1975.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Children and adolescents with cancer should be referred to medical centers that have a multidisciplinary team of cancer specialists with experience treating the cancers that occur during childhood and adolescence.  This multidisciplinary team approach incorporates the skills
of the following pediatric specialists and others to ensure that children receive treatment, supportive care, and rehabilitation
to achieve optimal survival and quality of life:</Para><ItemizedList id="_666_md_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Primary care physicians.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric surgeons.</ListItem><ListItem>Transplant surgeons.</ListItem><ListItem>Pathologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric radiation
oncologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric medical oncologists and hematologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Ophthalmologists.</ListItem><ListItem> Rehabilitation
specialists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric oncology nurses.</ListItem><ListItem>Social workers.</ListItem><ListItem>Child-life professionals.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Nutritionists.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_666_md_5">For specific information about supportive care for children and adolescents with cancer, see the summaries on <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/supportive-care">Supportive and Palliative Care</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_666_md_6">The American Academy of Pediatrics has outlined guidelines for
pediatric cancer centers and their role in the treatment of children and adolescents
with cancer.<Reference refidx="2"/>  At
these centers, clinical trials are available for most  types of cancer that occur in children and adolescents, and the opportunity
to participate is offered to most patients and their families.  Clinical
trials for children and adolescents diagnosed with cancer are generally
designed to compare potentially better therapy with current standard therapy.  Other types of clinical trials test novel therapies when there is no standard therapy for a cancer diagnosis. Most of the progress in identifying curative
therapies for childhood cancers has been achieved through clinical trials.
Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20404250">Smith MA, Seibel NL, Altekruse SF, et al.: Outcomes for children and adolescents with cancer: challenges for the twenty-first century. J Clin Oncol 28 (15): 2625-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2">American Academy of Pediatrics: Standards for pediatric cancer centers. Pediatrics  134 (2): 410-4, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/134/2/410">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_213"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043494">childhood teratoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Mature and Immature Teratomas in Children</Title><Para id="_387">Mature and immature teratomas arise primarily in the sacrococcygeal region of neonates and young children and in the ovaries of pubescent girls. Less commonly, these tumors are found in the testicular region of boys younger than 4 years, the mediastinum of adolescents, and other sites.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> The primary treatment for teratomas is surgery with complete resection. Surgical options for sacrococcygeal teratomas are complex.</Para><Para id="_1874">Benign head and neck teratomas and immature teratomas can cause morbidity and mortality through obstruction. In preterm infants and neonates, head and neck teratomas and immature teratomas can cause significant airway compromise. In a single-institutional report, airway obstruction was overcome by using the ex utero intrapartum treatment (EXIT) procedure.<Reference refidx="4"/> Complete resection of a teratoma can be achieved.</Para><SummarySection id="_217"><Title>Treatment of Mature Teratomas</Title><SummarySection id="_684"><Title>Standard treatment options for mature teratomas (sacrococcygeal sites)</Title><Para id="_685">The sacrococcygeal region is the primary tumor site for most benign and malignant germ cell tumors (GCTs) diagnosed in neonates, infants, and children younger than 4 years.  These tumors occur more often in girls than in boys; ratios of 3:1 to 4:1 have been reported.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_686">Sacrococcygeal tumors present in the following two clinical patterns related to the child’s age, tumor location, and likelihood of tumor malignancy:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_687" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Neonates: Neonatal tumors present at birth protruding from the sacral site. However, saccrococcygeal tumors may extend into the retroperitoneal space without outward protrusion. They are usually mature or immature teratomas.</ListItem><ListItem>Infants and young children: In infants and young children, tumors present as a palpable mass in the sacro-pelvic region, compressing the bladder or rectum.  These pelvic tumors are more likely to be malignant.  <Para id="_688">The older the child at presentation, the more likely a malignant component is present in addition to the teratoma. An early survey found that the rate of tumor malignancy was 48% for girls and 67% for boys older than 2 months at the time of sacrococcygeal tumor diagnosis, compared with a malignant tumor incidence of 7% for girls and 10% for boys younger than 2 months at the time of diagnosis.<Reference refidx="6"/>  The pelvic primary tumor site has been reported to be an adverse prognostic factor. This could be due to a delayed diagnosis because it was overlooked at birth or incomplete resection at the time of original surgery.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_689">Standard treatment options for mature teratomas in a sacrococcygeal site include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_690" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery and observation.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_691">Surgery is an essential component of treatment. Complete resection of the coccyx is vital to minimize the likelihood of tumor recurrence.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_474"><Title>Standard treatment options for mature teratomas (nonsacrococcygeal sites)</Title><Para id="_475">Standard treatment options for mature teratomas in a nonsacrococcygeal site include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_496" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery and observation.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_218">Children with mature teratomas, including mature teratomas of the mediastinum, can be treated with surgery and observation and have an excellent prognosis.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="10"/> </Para><Para id="_1926">In a review of 153 children with nontesticular mature teratomas, the 6-year relapse-free survival rate was 96% for patients with completely resected disease and 55% for patients with incompletely resected disease.<Reference refidx="2"/> Another series included 57 girls with mature teratomas of the ovary. Two patients experienced tumor recurrences (8 and 12 months after ovarian-sparing surgery), and seven patients developed metachronous tumors (as late as 79 months after initial diagnosis).<Reference refidx="11"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_477">A multidisciplinary team should treat and monitor neonates with head and neck GCTs. Although most head and neck GCTs are benign, they  can be life-threatening and present significant challenges to surgeons, especially in newborns.<Reference refidx="4"/> Some tumors develop malignant elements, which may change the treatment strategy.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_478">Mature teratomas in the prepubertal testis are relatively common benign lesions and may be amenable to testis-sparing surgery.<Reference refidx="14"/>  
 </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_479"><Title>Treatment of Immature Teratomas</Title><SummarySection id="_480"><Title>Treatment options for immature teratomas</Title><Para id="_481">Treatment options for immature teratomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_497" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_604" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation (stage I)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_609" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation or chemotherapy (stages I–IV)</SummaryRef>. The use of chemotherapy is controversial. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_694" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">evidence on the role of chemotherapy for immature teratomas</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_604"><Title>Surgery and observation (stage I)</Title><Para id="_605">Immature teratomas in children are primarily managed with surgery and observation. </Para><Para id="_606">Evidence (surgery and observation for stage I disease):</Para><OrderedList id="_607" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A surgery-alone approach was investigated in a study by the Pediatric Oncology Group and Children's Cancer Group. Surgical resection followed by careful observation was used to treat patients with immature teratomas.<Reference refidx="15"/><ItemizedList id="_608" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery alone was curative for most children and adolescents with resected ovarian immature teratomas of any grade, even when elevated levels of serum alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) or microscopic foci of yolk sac tumor were present.</ListItem><ListItem>The 3-year event-free survival (EFS) rates were  97.8% for patients with ovarian tumors, 100% for patients with testicular tumors, and 80% for patients with extragonadal tumors.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_609"><Title>Surgery and observation or chemotherapy (stages I–IV)</Title><Para id="_658">The use of chemotherapy is controversial in the treatment of immature teratomas. There are no clinical trials supporting the use of chemotherapy in children. In adult women with ovarian tumors, surgery followed by chemotherapy has been the standard treatment approach since 1976.<Reference refidx="16"/> As in children, there are no clinical trials supporting the use of chemotherapy in adults.</Para><Para id="_694">Evidence (role of chemotherapy for immature teratomas):</Para><OrderedList id="_724" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A seminal article published in 1976 reported that most women with ovarian immature teratomas were treated with surgery and chemotherapy. This approach has remained standard practice in postpubertal females.<Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem><ListItem>A report on  pediatric patients aged 15 years and younger in the United Kingdom found that immature teratomas did not respond to chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="17"/></ListItem><ListItem>A report from the Malignant Germ Cell Tumor International Collaborative (MaGIC) analyzed data from 98 pediatric patients and 81 adult patients with ovarian immature teratomas. Ninety pediatric patients underwent surgery alone. All 81 adult patients received adjuvant chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_725" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year EFS rate was 91% for pediatric patients and 98% for adult patients.</ListItem><ListItem>The overall survival (OS) rate was 83% for pediatric patients and 93% for adult patients.</ListItem><ListItem>There were no relapses in patients with grade I tumors. One adult patient with a grade II tumor relapsed after chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>For pediatric patients with grade III, stage I/II tumors, the 5-year EFS rate was 92%. For patients with grade III, stage III tumors, the 5-year EFS rate was 52%. </ListItem><ListItem>For adult patients with grade III, stage I/II tumors, the 5-year EFS rate was 91%. For patients with grade III, stage III/IV tumors, the 5-year EFS rate was 65%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_661">Additional studies on the treatment of ovarian immature teratomas with chemotherapy are needed. For more information about the treatment of ovarian immature teratomas in postpubertal females, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062935" url="/types/ovarian/hp/ovarian-germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Ovarian Germ Cell Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_738"><Title>Treatment options under clinical evaluation for immature teratomas</Title><Para id="_739">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1798">The following is an example of a national and/or institutional clinical trial that is currently being conducted:</Para><OrderedList id="_758" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><Strong><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 (NCT03067181)</ProtocolRef></Strong> (Active Surveillance, Bleomycin, Carboplatin, Etoposide, or Cisplatin in Treating Pediatric and Adult Patients with GCTs)<Strong>:</Strong>
Patients with ovarian pure-cell immature teratomas that are Children's Oncology Group stage I (International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics [FIGO] stage IA and IB), grade 2 or 3, and have an  AFP level of less than 1,000 ng/mL are eligible for surgery and observation on this trial.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1908"><Title>Follow-up After Treatment of Mature and Immature Teratomas</Title><Para id="_692">After successful resection, neonates diagnosed with benign mature and immature teratomas are closely observed with follow-up exams and serial serum AFP determinations. These tests are done for several years to ensure that AFP measurements normalize to expected physiological levels and to facilitate early detection of tumor relapse.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/>  Several oncology groups have reported significant rates of recurrence among these benign tumors, ranging from 10% to 21%. Most relapses occur within 3 years of resection.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_693">While there is no standard follow-up schedule, tumor markers are measured frequently for 3 years in all children. With early detection, recurrent malignant GCTs can be treated successfully with surgery and chemotherapy (OS rate, 92%).<Reference refidx="23"/>  Long-term survivors are monitored for complications of extensive surgery, which include constipation, fecal and urinary incontinence, and psychologically unacceptable cosmetic scars.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_213_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_213_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="9988869">Rescorla FJ: Pediatric germ cell tumors. Semin Surg Oncol 16 (2): 144-58, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9607423" MedlineID="98268439">Göbel U, Calaminus G, Engert J, et al.: Teratomas in infancy and childhood. Med Pediatr Oncol 31 (1): 8-15, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9291812" MedlineID="97437279">Pinkerton CR: Malignant germ cell tumours in childhood. Eur J Cancer 33 (6): 895-901; discussion 901-2, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="29447817">Dharmarajan H, Rouillard-Bazinet N, Chandy BM: Mature and immature pediatric head and neck teratomas: A 15-year review at a large tertiary center. Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol 105: 43-47, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="9498381">Rescorla FJ, Sawin RS, Coran AG, et al.: Long-term outcome for infants and children with sacrococcygeal teratoma: a report from the Childrens Cancer Group. J Pediatr Surg 33 (2): 171-6, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="4843993">Altman RP, Randolph JG, Lilly JR: Sacrococcygeal teratoma: American Academy of Pediatrics Surgical Section Survey-1973. J Pediatr Surg 9 (3): 389-98, 1974.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="1717667" MedlineID="92014151">Ablin AR, Krailo MD, Ramsay NK, et al.: Results of treatment of malignant germ cell tumors in 93 children: a report from the Childrens Cancer Study Group. J Clin Oncol 9 (10): 1782-92, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="1384951" MedlineID="93046025">Marina N, Fontanesi J, Kun L, et al.: Treatment of childhood germ cell tumors. Review of the St. Jude experience from 1979 to 1988. Cancer 70 (10): 2568-75, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="10561181" MedlineID="20029910">Baranzelli MC, Kramar A, Bouffet E, et al.: Prognostic factors in children with localized malignant nonseminomatous germ cell tumors. J Clin Oncol 17 (4): 1212, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="10673525" MedlineID="20139488">Schneider DT, Calaminus G, Reinhard H, et al.: Primary mediastinal germ cell tumors in children and adolescents: results of the German cooperative protocols MAKEI 83/86, 89, and 96. J Clin Oncol 18 (4): 832-9, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="31837839">Braungart S, Craigie RJ, Farrelly P, et al.: Ovarian tumors in children: how common are lesion recurrence and metachronous disease? A UK CCLG Surgeons Cancer Group nationwide study. J Pediatr Surg 55 (10): 2026-2029, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="18937314">Bernbeck B, Schneider DT, Bernbeck B, et al.: Germ cell tumors of the head and neck: report from the MAKEI Study Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 52 (2): 223-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="26611341">Alexander VR, Manjaly JG, Pepper CM, et al.: Head and neck teratomas in children--A series of 23 cases at Great Ormond Street Hospital. Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol 79 (12): 2008-14, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="14634440">Metcalfe PD, Farivar-Mohseni H, Farhat W, et al.: Pediatric testicular tumors: contemporary incidence and efficacy of testicular preserving surgery. J Urol 170 (6 Pt 1): 2412-5; discussion 2415-6, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="10561269" MedlineID="20029998">Marina NM, Cushing B, Giller R, et al.: Complete surgical excision is effective treatment for children with immature teratomas with or without malignant elements: A Pediatric Oncology Group/Children's Cancer Group Intergroup Study. J Clin Oncol 17 (7): 2137-43, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="1260722" MedlineID="76163013">Norris HJ, Zirkin HJ, Benson WL: Immature (malignant) teratoma of the ovary: a clinical and pathologic study of 58 cases. Cancer 37 (5): 2359-72, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="18541896">Mann JR, Gray ES, Thornton C, et al.: Mature and immature extracranial teratomas in children: the UK Children's Cancer Study Group Experience. J Clin Oncol 26 (21): 3590-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="26485622">Pashankar F, Hale JP, Dang H, et al.: Is adjuvant chemotherapy indicated in ovarian immature teratomas? A combined data analysis from the Malignant Germ Cell Tumor International Collaborative. Cancer 122 (2): 230-7, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="12721723">Huddart SN, Mann JR, Robinson K, et al.: Sacrococcygeal teratomas: the UK Children's Cancer Study Group's experience. I. Neonatal. Pediatr Surg Int 19 (1-2): 47-51, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="27786428">Egler RA, Gosiengfiao Y, Russell H, et al.: Is surgical resection and observation sufficient for stage I and II sacrococcygeal germ cell tumors? A case series and review. Pediatr Blood Cancer 64 (5): , 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="580884" MedlineID="78209932">Gonzalez-Crussi F, Winkler RF, Mirkin DL: Sacrococcygeal teratomas in infants and children: relationship of histology and prognosis in 40 cases. Arch Pathol Lab Med 102 (8): 420-5, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="16952583">Gabra HO, Jesudason EC, McDowell HP, et al.: Sacrococcygeal teratoma--a 25-year experience in a UK regional center. J Pediatr Surg 41 (9): 1513-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="22459912">De Corti F, Sarnacki S, Patte C, et al.: Prognosis of malignant sacrococcygeal germ cell tumours according to their natural history and surgical management. Surg Oncol 21 (2): e31-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="17560233">Derikx JP, De Backer A, van de Schoot L, et al.: Long-term functional sequelae of sacrococcygeal teratoma: a national study in The Netherlands. J Pediatr Surg 42 (6): 1122-6, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_220"><Title> Treatment of Malignant Gonadal  GCTs in Children</Title><SummarySection id="_60"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043495">childhood malignant testicular germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Childhood Malignant Testicular GCTs</Title><SummarySection id="_61"><Title>Malignant testicular GCTs in prepubertal males</Title><Para id="_1909">The role of surgery at diagnosis for germ cell tumors (GCTs) depends on patient age and tumor site, and treatment must be individualized. All malignant testicular GCTs should be resected. Resection may be followed by subsequent excision of residual masses after chemotherapy. </Para><Para id="_62">Testicular GCTs in children occur almost exclusively in boys
younger than 5 years.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> The initial surgical approach to evaluate a testicular mass in a young boy is important  because a trans-scrotal biopsy can risk inguinal node metastasis.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Radical inguinal orchiectomy with initial high
ligation of the spermatic cord is the procedure of choice.<Reference refidx="5"/> 
</Para><Para id="_493">Computed tomography or magnetic resonance imaging evaluation, with the additional information provided by elevated tumor markers, appears adequate for staging. Retroperitoneal
dissection of lymph nodes is not beneficial in the staging of testicular GCTs in young boys.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Therefore,  there may be no reason to risk the potential morbidity (e.g., impotence and retrograde ejaculation) associated with lymph node dissection.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_1910">A revised risk stratification was developed by the Malignant Germ Cell Tumor  International Consortium (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1902" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Figure 4</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><SummarySection id="_289"><Title>Standard treatment options for malignant GCTs in prepubertal males</Title><Para id="_494">Standard treatment options for malignant GCTs in prepubertal males (aged &lt;11 years)  include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_495" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_532" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation (stage I)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_535" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (stages II–IV)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_500">The treatment options for malignant GCTs in prepubertal males differ by stage of disease.</Para><SummarySection id="_532"><Title>Surgery and observation (stage I)</Title><Para id="_533">Surgery and close follow-up observation are indicated to document that tumor marker levels normalize after resection.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_501">Evidence (surgery and observation for stage I disease in prepubertal males):</Para><OrderedList id="_534" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A  Children’s Cancer Group (CCG)/Pediatric Oncology Group (POG) clinical
trial evaluated surgery followed by observation for boys aged 10 years or younger with stage I
testicular tumors.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><ItemizedList id="_503" Style="bullet"><ListItem>This  treatment strategy resulted in a 6-year event-free survival (EFS) rate of 82%. </ListItem><ListItem>Boys who developed recurrent disease received salvage therapy with four cycles of standard-dose cisplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin (PEb), with a 6-year survival rate of 100%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A subsequent Children’s Oncology Group (COG) study of 80 boys younger than 15 years with stage I disease included 15 boys aged 11 to 15 years who were treated with surgery and observation.<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_657" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 4-year EFS rate was 80% for the 65 boys younger than 11 years at diagnosis and 48% for the 15 boys aged 11 years and older  (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01). All patients' disease was eventually salvaged, with a 4-year overall survival (OS) rate of 100%.</ListItem><ListItem>Favorable prognostic factors were younger age, presence of pure yolk sac tumor, and lack of lymphovascular invasion by the primary tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Adult testicular staging systems classify patients with lymphovascular invasion as stage IB. In the entire cohort, those with lymphovascular invasion had a lower 4-year EFS rate (62% vs. 84%).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A pooled analysis (from the studies above) provided more complete outcome data on patients with stage I disease who were treated with surgery and observation.<Reference refidx="11"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>] <ItemizedList id="_1949" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Most patients were prepubertal, but 13.2% of patients were adolescents (aged 13–15 years). </ListItem><ListItem>At a median follow-up of 56 months, all patients were alive. </ListItem><ListItem>There were 25 events. </ListItem><ListItem> On multivariate analysis, independent prognostic factors were age younger than 12 years (hazard ratio [HR], 8.87; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) and higher pT stage (pT2: HR, 7.31; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0017 and pT3: HR, 13.5; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0047).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A German study (MAHO 98) of 128 boys younger than 10 years with testicular GCTs, mostly stage I, also evaluated surgery followed by observation.<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_619" Style="bullet"><ListItem>There were  49 patients with yolk sac tumors that  were staged as IA after inguinal orchiectomy. Stage IA includes no evidence of lymphovascular invasion. The 5-year EFS rate was 95%, and the 5-year OS rate was 100% for this group. Two patients relapsed and then were cured after chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>There were 12 patients who initially had trans-scrotal orchiectomy who were pathologically confirmed to have no lymphovascular invasion (would be considered stage IA, if not for surgery). Ten patients were observed who had no adverse events. Two patients relapsed (17%) and remained in continuous remission after chemotherapy. No patients had hemiscrotectomy. A long-standing question has been whether trans-scrotal orchiectomy necessitates chemotherapy or hemiscrotectomy. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_535"><Title>Surgery and chemotherapy (stages II–IV)</Title><Para id="_536">Surgery and chemotherapy with four cycles of standard PEb is a common treatment regimen for prepubertal males with stages II through IV disease. Patients treated with this regimen have OS rates exceeding 90%, suggesting that a reduction in therapy could be considered.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_537">Surgery and treatment with four to six cycles of carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin (JEb) is an alternative treatment regimen.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_504">Evidence (surgery and chemotherapy for stages II–IV disease in prepubertal males):</Para><OrderedList id="_505" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A  CCG/POG clinical
trial evaluated boys younger than 10 years with stage II tumors who were treated with four cycles of PEb after diagnosis.<Reference refidx="13"/> <ItemizedList id="_506" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 6-year EFS and OS rates were 100%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In the same CCG/POG clinical trial, boys and adolescents (aged 14 years and younger) with stage III and stage IV testicular tumors were treated with surgical resection followed by four cycles of standard-dose PEb or high-dose PEb (HD-PEb) therapy.<Reference refidx="14"/>  <ItemizedList id="_507" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 6-year survival rate for males younger than 15 years with stage III and   stage IV tumors was 100%.</ListItem><ListItem>The 6-year  EFS rate for males younger than 15 years was 100% for stage III tumors and 94% for stage IV tumors.</ListItem><ListItem>The use of HD-PEb therapy did not improve the outcome for these boys but did cause increased incidence of otologic toxic effects.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>European investigators have reported excellent outcomes for boys with testicular GCTs using surgery and observation for stage I tumors and JEb and other cisplatin-containing chemotherapy regimens for stage II, stage III, and stage IV tumors.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  </ListItem><ListItem>A phase III, single-arm COG trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00053352">AGCT0132</ProtocolRef> [NCT00053352]) included 210 intermediate-risk patients (stages II–IV testicular, stages II–III ovarian, stages I–II extragonadal, or stage I gonadal tumors with subsequent recurrence). These patients received three, rather than four, cycles of PEb and the schedule was compressed from 5 days to 3 days per cycle. A parametric comparator model specified that the observed EFS rate would not be significantly less than 92%.<Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_696" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 4-year EFS rate was 89% (95% confidence interval, 83%–92%), which was significantly lower than the 92% threshold of the comparison model (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .08).  </ListItem><ListItem>In a post hoc analysis, the EFS rate was compared with similar patients treated with four cycles of PEb in two previous studies. Among 181 newly diagnosed patients, the 4-year EFS rate was 87%, compared with 92% for 92 comparable children in the historical cohort (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .15).</ListItem><ListItem>The 4-year EFS rate was significantly associated with stage (stage I, 100%; stage II, 92%; stage III, 85%; and stage IV, 54%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).</ListItem><ListItem>These data do not support a reduction in the number of cycles of PEb from four to three.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_66"><Title>Malignant testicular GCTs in postpubertal males</Title><Para id="_68">   The
treatment options described for prepubertal males   may not be strictly applicable
to  postpubertal males.
In particular, retroperitoneal lymph node dissection is a treatment option and  may play a crucial role <Reference refidx="16"/> in the initial treatment of patients or in subsequent treatment of patients with  residual disease after chemotherapy for metastatic testicular GCT.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>  A meta-analysis showed that patients older than 11 years were at higher risk of recurrence.<Reference refidx="8"/> The number of males aged 11 to 15 years with GCT is small; it is possible that these patients should be treated according to adult standards. For more information about the treatment of malignant testicular GCTs in postpubertal males, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062899" url="/types/testicular/hp/testicular-treatment-pdq">Testicular Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_510"><Title>Standard treatment options for malignant testicular GCTs in postpubertal males</Title><Para id="_67">For information about the treatment of malignant testicular GCTs in postpubertal males, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062899" url="/types/testicular/hp/testicular-treatment-pdq">Testicular Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_742"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043495">childhood malignant testicular germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment options under clinical evaluation for malignant testicular GCTs</Title><Para id="_743">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1799">The following is an example of a national and/or institutional clinical trial that is currently being conducted:</Para><OrderedList id="_744" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><Strong><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 (NCT03067181)</ProtocolRef></Strong> (Active Surveillance, Bleomycin, Carboplatin, Etoposide, or Cisplatin in Treating Pediatric and Adult Patients with GCTs)<Strong>:</Strong>
The aim of this trial is to reduce toxicity and maintain efficacy of treatment for patients with standard-risk GCTs.  Patients with stage I malignant GCTs (low risk, age 0–50 years) will be treated with surgery and observation.  Patients with intermediate-risk GCTs will be randomly assigned to receive cisplatin or carboplatin and bleomycin and etoposide. Children younger than 11 years will receive bleomycin with each cycle, and those aged 11 years and older will receive weekly bleomycin. Patients with pure seminoma or dysgerminoma are excluded from the trial.</ListItem>  </OrderedList><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_742_sid_4"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_742_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043496">childhood malignant ovarian germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Childhood Malignant Ovarian GCTs</Title><Para id="_144">Most ovarian neoplasms in children and adolescents are of germ cell origin.<Reference refidx="19"/>  Ovarian GCTs are very rare in young girls, but the incidence begins to increase in children aged approximately  8 or 9 years and continues to rise throughout adulthood.<Reference refidx="1"/>  </Para><Para id="_511">Childhood malignant ovarian GCTs can be divided into germinomatous (dysgerminomas) and nongerminomatous malignant GCTs (i.e., yolk sac carcinomas, mixed GCTs, choriocarcinoma, and embryonal carcinomas). </Para><Para id="_513">For more information about childhood mature and immature teratomas arising in the ovary, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_217" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Mature Teratomas</SummaryRef> section. For more information about the treatment of ovarian GCT in postpubertal females, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062935" url="/types/ovarian/hp/ovarian-germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Ovarian Germ Cell Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_423"><Title>Dysgerminomas  of the ovary</Title><SummarySection id="_514"><Title>Standard treatment options for dysgerminomas of the ovary</Title><Para id="_515">Standard treatment options for dysgerminomas of the ovary include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_516" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_538" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation (stage I)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_541" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (stages II–IV)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_517">The treatment options for dysgerminomas of the ovary differ by stage of disease.</Para><SummarySection id="_538"><Title>Surgery and observation (stage I)</Title><Para id="_539">For stage I ovarian dysgerminomas, a cure can usually be achieved by unilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, conserving the uterus and opposite ovary, and close follow-up observation.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/> </Para><Para id="_1911">Evidence (surgery and observation for stage I dysgerminomas):</Para><OrderedList id="_1912" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In three successive French Society of Pediatric Oncology studies (TGM-85, TGM-90, and TGM-95), the following was reported:<Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_1913" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Fifteen patients were identified as stage I, and all patients survived.</ListItem><ListItem>Before 1998, eight patients were treated with adjuvant radiation or chemotherapy. After a practice change in 1998, seven patients underwent surgery and observation.</ListItem><ListItem> One of the seven patients (14%) had a tumor event and responded to treatment with chemotherapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_541"><Title>Surgery and chemotherapy (stages II–IV)</Title><Para id="_542">While advanced-stage ovarian dysgerminomas, like testicular seminomas, are highly curable with surgery and radiation therapy, the effects on growth, fertility, and risk of treatment-induced second malignancy in these young patients <Reference refidx="25"/> <Reference refidx="26"/> make chemotherapy a more attractive adjunct to surgery.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/>  Complete tumor resection is the goal for advanced dysgerminomas. Platinum-based chemotherapy can be given preoperatively to facilitate resection or postoperatively (after debulking surgery) to avoid mutilating surgical procedures.<Reference refidx="23"/>  </Para><Para id="_1875">Evidence (surgery and chemotherapy for stage II–IV dysgerminomas):</Para><OrderedList id="_1876" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a report from the French Society of Pediatric Oncology, 48 girls younger than 19 years (median age, 12.8 years) were registered; 20 patients had localized disease, 28 patients had locoregional disease, and no patients had metastases. Seven patients had positive para-aortic lymph nodes. Forty-seven patients underwent primary surgery. Before 1998, all patients with advanced disease received radiation therapy. After a practice change in 1998, patients were treated with platinum-based chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]  <ItemizedList id="_1877" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year EFS rate was 91%, and the 5-year OS rate was 100%. </ListItem><ListItem>Side effects were not severe, and several patients became pregnant in later years.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem> A meta-analysis of patients with dysgerminoma by the Malignant Germ Cell Tumor International Consortium reported the following:<Reference refidx="29"/><ItemizedList id="_1923" Style="bullet"><ListItem>No difference was seen between  patients who were treated with cisplatin (n = 70)  (5-year EFS rate, 93%; OS rate, 96%) and patients who were treated with carboplatin (n = 56) (5-year EFS rate, 96%; OS rate, 96%).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1878">This approach results in a high rate of cure and the preservation of menstrual function and fertility in most patients with dysgerminomas.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="30"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_424"><Title>Malignant nongerminomatous  ovarian GCTs</Title><Para id="_520">A multidisciplinary approach is essential for treatment of ovarian GCTs.  Various surgical subspecialists and the pediatric oncologist must be involved in clinical decisions. The surgical approach for pediatric ovarian GCTs is often guided by the expectation that reproductive function can be preserved. </Para><Para id="_1914"> The treatment of ovarian malignant GCTs that are not dysgerminomas or immature teratomas generally involves surgical resection and adjuvant chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/>  </Para><Para id="_1915">The role for surgery at diagnosis depends on patient age and tumor site, and treatment must be individualized. The use of laparoscopy in children with ovarian GCTs has not been well studied.</Para><Para id="_1950">The use of intraoperative frozen biopsy in pediatric and adolescent patients to determine the presence of malignancy to allow an ovarian-sparing procedure has been questioned. In a retrospective analysis from the COG <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00053352">AGCT0132 (NCT00053352)</ProtocolRef> study, 60 of 131 eligible patients with ovarian tumors had both intraoperative frozen section and final paraffin section diagnoses available.<Reference refidx="33"/> Intraoperative frozen section biopsy was incorrect 38% of the time (23 patients), and it confirmed the final diagnosis 76% of the time. In addition, central pathological review detected additional germ cell components in 23.7% of patients. </Para><Para id="_1916">Pediatric surgical guidelines to determine stage I disease have been published.<Reference refidx="34"/> Adult surgical guidelines to determine stage are more extensive. For more information about staging of ovarian GCTs in postpubertal females, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062935#_8" url="/types/ovarian/hp/ovarian-germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Stage Information for Ovarian Germ Cell Tumors</SummaryRef> section in Ovarian Germ Cell Tumors Treatment.</Para><Para id="_1917">Strict surgical staging guidelines need to be followed to determine true stage I disease. Historically, in both pediatric and adult studies, comprehensive staging guidelines have not been followed. If strict surgical staging guidelines are not followed, surgery followed by chemotherapy, rather than surgery followed by observation, is the standard treatment.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="35"/> </Para><Para id="_1927">A goal of surgical therapy for pediatric GCTs is to preserve reproductive function. If conservative surgery is the choice, a high rate of cure can be obtained with adjuvant chemotherapy, and adherence to strict surgical guidelines is not necessary.<Reference refidx="36"/></Para><SummarySection id="_521"><Title>Standard treatment options for malignant nongerminomatous ovarian GCTs</Title><Para id="_522">Standard treatment options for malignant nongerminomatous ovarian GCTs in <Strong>prepubertal females</Strong> include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_523" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1809" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation  (stage I following strict surgical staging guidelines)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1813" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (PEb) (purported stage I and stages II–IV)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_699">Standard treatment options for malignant nongerminomatous ovarian GCTs in <Strong>postpubertal females</Strong> include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_721" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1813" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin [BEP]) (purported stage I and stages II–IV)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_701">Standard treatment options for malignant nongerminomatous ovarian GCTs that cannot be resected initially include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_722" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_552" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Biopsy followed by chemotherapy and surgery (initially unresectable tumor)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_1809"><Title>Surgery and observation for prepubertal females (stage I following strict surgical staging guidelines)</Title><Para id="_1810">When strict surgical staging guidelines are followed, surgery followed by observation may be an appropriate treatment choice for prepubertal females with stage I disease.</Para><Para id="_1811">Evidence (surgery and observation for prepubertal females with stage I disease):</Para><OrderedList id="_1812" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a COG trial, 25 girls with stage I ovarian malignant GCTs were treated with surgery and observation.<Reference refidx="34"/><ItemizedList id="_527" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 4-year EFS rate was 52%.</ListItem><ListItem>Relapse was detected in 12 patients by tumor marker elevation (mean time, 2 months). All patients later received salvage therapy with three cycles of PEb. The 4-year OS rate was 96%; one patient's disease was not salvaged.</ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem><ListItem>Similar results have been reported in other international pediatric trials, but the number of patients has been small.<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1813"><Title>Surgery and chemotherapy for prepubertal and postpubertal females (purported stage I and stages II–IV)</Title><Para id="_1864">A revised risk stratification was developed by the Malignant Germ Cell Tumor  International Consortium (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1902" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Figure 4</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_544">Chemotherapy regimens with cisplatin (PEb) or  carboplatin (JEb) have been used successfully in children.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="20"/> BEP is a common regimen in young women with ovarian GCTs.<Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/> BEP differs from PEb with the addition of weekly bleomycin.  This approach results in a high rate of cure and the preservation of menstrual function and fertility in most patients with nondysgerminomas.<Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="35"/> For more information about the dosing schedules for BEP, PEb, and JEb, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_156" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Table 8</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_1814">In <Strong>prepubertal females</Strong> with purported <Strong>stage I ovarian tumors</Strong> (when strict surgical staging guidelines are not followed) surgery followed by chemotherapy (four cycles of PEb) is an appropriate treatment choice and results in EFS and OS rates of 95%.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_1815">In <Strong>postpubertal females</Strong> with purported <Strong>stage I ovarian tumors</Strong>, chemotherapy after resection remains the standard treatment. In postpubertal females, the strategy of observation after surgery has not been established and is under investigation in the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 (NCT03067181)</ProtocolRef> trial.</Para><Para id="_1816">In <Strong>prepubertal and postpubertal females with stages II, III, or IV ovarian tumors</Strong>, surgery and chemotherapy are considered standard treatments. Surgery and chemotherapy with four to six cycles of standard PEb is used to treat younger (prepubertal) girls,<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> and BEP is used to treat postpubertal girls.<Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/> Patients with normalization of tumor markers undergo imaging after four cycles of PEb, and any residual tumor is resected. Patients with residual viable tumor after surgery are considered refractory.</Para><Para id="_1817">Alternatively, surgery and chemotherapy with four to six cycles of JEb is a treatment option (as demonstrated in one study in which all patients were younger than 15 years).<Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_552"><Title>Initially unresectable ovarian GCT</Title><Para id="_553">Primary resection of ovarian GCT is usually attempted. However, in rare instances, primary resection of the ovary is not possible without undue risk of damage to adjacent structures. In these cases, an appropriate strategy is biopsy for diagnosis, followed by chemotherapy and then subsequent surgery for patients who have residual masses after undergoing chemotherapy.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_746"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043496">childhood malignant ovarian germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment options under clinical evaluation for malignant ovarian GCTs</Title><Para id="_747">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1800">The following is an example of a national and/or institutional clinical trial that is currently being conducted:</Para><OrderedList id="_748" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><Strong><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 (NCT03067181)</ProtocolRef></Strong> (Active Surveillance, Bleomycin, Carboplatin, Etoposide, or Cisplatin in Treating Pediatric and Adult Patients with GCTs)<Strong>:</Strong>
The aim of this trial is to reduce toxicity and maintain efficacy of treatment for patients with standard-risk GCTs.  Patients with stage I malignant GCTs (low risk, age 0–50 years) will be treated with surgery and observation.  Patients with intermediate-risk GCTs will be randomly assigned to receive cisplatin or carboplatin and bleomycin and etoposide. Children younger than 11 years will receive bleomycin with each cycle, and those aged 11 years and older will receive weekly bleomycin. Patients with pure seminoma or dysgerminoma are excluded from the trial.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_746_sid_8"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_746_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">National Cancer Institute: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://NCCRExplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16904461">Walsh TJ, Grady RW, Porter MP, et al.: Incidence of testicular germ cell cancers in U.S. children: SEER program experience 1973 to 2000. Urology 68 (2): 402-5; discussion 405, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="12632342" MedlineID="22519191">Schlatter M, Rescorla F, Giller R, et al.: Excellent outcome in patients with stage I germ cell tumors of the testes: a study of the Children's Cancer Group/Pediatric Oncology Group. J Pediatr Surg 38 (3): 319-24; discussion 319-24, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Canning DA: Excellent outcome in patients with stage I germ cell tumors of the testes: a study of the Children's Cancer Group/Pediatric Oncology Group [Editorial Comment on Schlatter]. J Urol  174 (1): 310, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="9988869">Rescorla FJ: Pediatric germ cell tumors. Semin Surg Oncol 16 (2): 144-58, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="7521931" MedlineID="94366361">Haas RJ, Schmidt P, Göbel U, et al.: Treatment of malignant testicular tumors in childhood: results of the German National Study 1982-1992. Med Pediatr Oncol 23 (5): 400-5, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9291812" MedlineID="97437279">Pinkerton CR: Malignant germ cell tumours in childhood. Eur J Cancer 33 (6): 895-901; discussion 901-2, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25452439">Frazier AL, Hale JP, Rodriguez-Galindo C, et al.: Revised risk classification for pediatric extracranial germ cell tumors based on 25 years of clinical trial data from the United Kingdom and United States. J Clin Oncol 33 (2): 195-201, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11078494" MedlineID="20530736">Mann JR, Raafat F, Robinson K, et al.: The United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group's second germ cell tumor study: carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin are effective treatment for children with malignant extracranial germ cell tumors, with acceptable toxicity. J Clin Oncol 18 (22): 3809-18, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="25812445">Rescorla FJ, Ross JH, Billmire DF, et al.: Surveillance after initial surgery for Stage I pediatric and adolescent boys with malignant testicular germ cell tumors: Report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Pediatr Surg 50 (6): 1000-3, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="35606324">Singla N, Wong J, Singla S, et al.: Clinicopathologic predictors of outcomes in children with stage I testicular germ cell tumors: A pooled post hoc analysis of trials from the Children's Oncology Group. J Pediatr Urol 18 (4): 505-511, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="24158884">Göbel U, Haas R, Calaminus G, et al.: Testicular germ cell tumors in boys &lt;10 years: results of the protocol MAHO 98 in respect to surgery and watch &amp; wait strategy. Klin Padiatr 225 (6): 296-302, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="15337806">Rogers PC, Olson TA, Cullen JW, et al.: Treatment of children and adolescents with stage II testicular and stages I and II ovarian malignant germ cell tumors: A Pediatric Intergroup Study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9048 and Children's Cancer Group 8891. J Clin Oncol 22 (17): 3563-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="15226336">Cushing B, Giller R, Cullen JW, et al.: Randomized comparison of combination chemotherapy with etoposide, bleomycin, and either high-dose or standard-dose cisplatin in children and adolescents with high-risk malignant germ cell tumors: a pediatric intergroup study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9049 and Children's Cancer Group 8882. J Clin Oncol 22 (13): 2691-700, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="28240974">Shaikh F, Cullen JW, Olson TA, et al.: Reduced and Compressed Cisplatin-Based Chemotherapy in Children and Adolescents With Intermediate-Risk Extracranial Malignant Germ Cell Tumors: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 35 (11): 1203-1210, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="17158533">de Wit R, Fizazi K: Controversies in the management of clinical stage I testis cancer. J Clin Oncol 24 (35): 5482-92, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="17261854">Carver BS, Shayegan B, Serio A, et al.: Long-term clinical outcome after postchemotherapy retroperitoneal lymph node dissection in men with residual teratoma. J Clin Oncol 25 (9): 1033-7, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="17906201">Carver BS, Shayegan B, Eggener S, et al.: Incidence of metastatic nonseminomatous germ cell tumor outside the boundaries of a modified postchemotherapy retroperitoneal lymph node dissection. J Clin Oncol 25 (28): 4365-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="19">Ries LA, Smith MA, Gurney JG, et al., eds.: Cancer incidence and survival among children and adolescents: United States SEER Program 1975-1995. National Cancer Institute, SEER Program, 1999. NIH Pub.No. 99-4649. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/archive/publications/childhood/">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 22, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="10708940">Baranzelli MC, Bouffet E, Quintana E, et al.: Non-seminomatous ovarian germ cell tumours in children. Eur J Cancer 36 (3): 376-83, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="9053485" MedlineID="97178752">Dark GG, Bower M, Newlands ES, et al.: Surveillance policy for stage I ovarian germ cell tumors. J Clin Oncol 15 (2): 620-4, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="10561269" MedlineID="20029998">Marina NM, Cushing B, Giller R, et al.: Complete surgical excision is effective treatment for children with immature teratomas with or without malignant elements: A Pediatric Oncology Group/Children's Cancer Group Intergroup Study. J Clin Oncol 17 (7): 2137-43, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="8091071" MedlineID="94377822">Gershenson DM: Chemotherapy of ovarian germ cell tumors and sex cord stromal tumors. Semin Surg Oncol 10 (4): 290-8, 1994 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="29331749">Duhil de Bénazé G, Pacquement H, Faure-Conter C, et al.: Paediatric dysgerminoma: Results of three consecutive French germ cell tumours clinical studies (TGM-85/90/95) with late effects study. Eur J Cancer 91: 30-37, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="8177140" MedlineID="94232077">Teinturier C, Gelez J, Flamant F, et al.: Pure dysgerminoma of the ovary in childhood: treatment results and sequelae. Med Pediatr Oncol 23 (1): 1-7, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="1991256" MedlineID="91121372">Mitchell MF, Gershenson DM, Soeters RP, et al.: The long-term effects of radiation therapy on patients with ovarian dysgerminoma. Cancer 67 (4): 1084-90, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="10561340" MedlineID="20030069">Brewer M, Gershenson DM, Herzog CE, et al.: Outcome and reproductive function after chemotherapy for ovarian dysgerminoma. J Clin Oncol 17 (9): 2670-75, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="1719142" MedlineID="92044708">Williams SD, Blessing JA, Hatch KD, et al.: Chemotherapy of advanced dysgerminoma: trials of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 9 (11): 1950-5, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="29884437">Shah R, Xia C, Krailo M, et al.: Is carboplatin-based chemotherapy as effective as cisplatin-based chemotherapy in the treatment of advanced-stage dysgerminoma in children, adolescents and young adults? Gynecol Oncol 150 (2): 253-260, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="2828558" MedlineID="88117650">Gershenson DM: Menstrual and reproductive function after treatment with combination chemotherapy for malignant ovarian germ cell tumors. J Clin Oncol 6 (2): 270-5, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="1690272" MedlineID="90188473">Gershenson DM, Morris M, Cangir A, et al.: Treatment of malignant germ cell tumors of the ovary with bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin. J Clin Oncol 8 (4): 715-20, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="10326703" MedlineID="99256635">Mitchell PL, Al-Nasiri N, A'Hern R, et al.: Treatment of nondysgerminomatous ovarian germ cell tumors: an analysis of 69 cases. Cancer 85 (10): 2232-44, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="35750503">Dicken BJ, Billmire DF, Rich B, et al.: Utility of frozen section in pediatric and adolescent malignant ovarian nonseminomatous germ cell tumors: A report from the children's oncology group. Gynecol Oncol 166 (3): 476-480, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="24395845">Billmire DF, Cullen JW, Rescorla FJ, et al.: Surveillance after initial surgery for pediatric and adolescent girls with stage I ovarian germ cell tumors: report from the Children's Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 465-70, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="18948812">Palenzuela G, Martin E, Meunier A, et al.: Comprehensive staging allows for excellent outcome in patients with localized malignant germ cell tumor of the ovary. Ann Surg 248 (5): 836-41, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="15017564">Billmire D, Vinocur C, Rescorla F, et al.: Outcome and staging evaluation in malignant germ cell tumors of the ovary in children and adolescents: an intergroup study. J Pediatr Surg 39 (3): 424-9; discussion 424-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="9633853">Williams SD: Ovarian germ cell tumors: an update. Semin Oncol 25 (3): 407-13, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="7512129" MedlineID="94201785">Williams S, Blessing JA, Liao SY, et al.: Adjuvant therapy of ovarian germ cell tumors with cisplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin: a trial of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 12 (4): 701-6, 1994.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_75"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043497">childhood extragonadal germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Malignant Extragonadal   Extracranial GCTs in Children</Title><Para id="_76">In initial reports, children with extragonadal 
malignant germ cell tumors (GCTs), particularly those with advanced-stage (stage III or stage IV) disease, had the
highest risk of treatment failure for any GCT presentation.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Subsequently, an analysis of data from 25 years of pediatric GCT studies in the United States and United Kingdom reported that children younger than 11 years with extragonadal stage III and stage IV GCTs had an event-free survival (EFS) rate of 85%, and adolescents with stage III and stage IV extragonadal disease had poorer outcomes (expected EFS rate, &lt;70%).<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para><Para id="_1918">The role of surgery at diagnosis for extragonadal tumors depends on patient age and tumor site, and treatment must be individualized. Depending on the clinical setting, the appropriate surgical approach may be primary resection,  biopsy before chemotherapy, or no surgery (e.g.,  for a mediastinal primary tumor in a patient with a compromised airway and elevated tumor markers). An appropriate strategy may be biopsy at diagnosis followed by chemotherapy and subsequent surgery in selected patients who have residual masses after chemotherapy.</Para><SummarySection id="_555"><Title>Standard Treatment Options for Malignant Extragonadal Extracranial GCTs in Prepubertal Children</Title><Para id="_556">Standard treatment options for malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs in prepubertal children include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_585" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_560" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and chemotherapy (stages I–IV)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1919" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Biopsy followed by chemotherapy with or without surgery (stages III and IV)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_729">The treatment of malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs also depends on the site of disease. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_565" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Site-specific considerations for malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs</SummaryRef> section.</Para><SummarySection id="_560"><Title>Surgery and chemotherapy (stages I–IV)</Title><Para id="_561">Surgery and chemotherapy with four cycles of standard cisplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin (PEb) is one treatment option. Patients with stage I and stage II disease treated with this regimen had an overall survival (OS) rate of 90%, suggesting that a reduction in therapy may be considered.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Patients with stage III and stage IV disease had OS rates of higher than 80%.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para><Para id="_1879">An alternative treatment option is surgery and chemotherapy with carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin (JEb).<Reference refidx="5"/> Stage III and stage IV patients treated with  JEb had an OS rate similar to that with the PEb regimen.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_1880">Two pediatric intergroup trials for patients with high-risk disease investigated the use of high-dose cisplatin (200 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) in a randomized study and a subsequent study that added amifostine to high-dose cisplatin.<Reference refidx="1"/> No benefit in OS was observed, and 75% of patients required hearing aids. A Children's Oncology Group (COG) trial of patients with high-risk disease investigated the addition of cyclophosphamide to standard-dose PEb. The addition of cyclophosphamide was feasible and well tolerated at all dose levels, but there was no evidence that adding cyclophosphamide improved efficacy.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1919"><Title>Biopsy followed by chemotherapy with or without surgery (stages III and IV)</Title><Para id="_558">While outcomes  have improved remarkably since the advent of platinum-based
chemotherapy and the use of a multidisciplinary treatment approach, complete resection before chemotherapy may be possible in some patients without major morbidity.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  </Para><Para id="_1920"> However, for  patients  with
locally advanced sacrococcygeal tumors, mediastinal tumors,  or large pelvic tumors, tumor biopsy followed by preoperative chemotherapy may facilitate subsequent complete tumor resection and improve ultimate patient outcome. No decrease in OS has been noted for patients with malignant extragonadal GCTs who have had delayed resection after receiving chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_565"><Title>Site-specific considerations for malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs</Title><Para id="_703">The treatment of malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs depends in part on the site of disease.</Para><SummarySection id="_704"><Title>Sacrococcygeal site</Title><Para id="_148">Sacrococcygeal GCTs are common extragonadal tumors that occur in very young children, predominantly young females.<Reference refidx="10"/>  The tumors are usually diagnosed at birth, when large external lesions predominate (usually mature or immature teratomas), or later in the first years of life, when presacral lesions with higher malignancy rates predominate.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_569">Malignant sacrococcygeal tumors are usually very advanced at diagnosis. Two-thirds of patients have locoregional disease, and metastases are present in 50% of patients.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Because of their advanced stage at presentation, the management of sacrococcygeal tumors requires a multimodal approach with platinum-based chemotherapy followed by delayed tumor resection.</Para><Para id="_570">Platinum-based therapies, with either cisplatin or carboplatin, are the cornerstone of treatment. The PEb regimen or the JEb regimen produces EFS rates of 85%.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  Surgery may be facilitated by preoperative chemotherapy. In any patient with a sacrococcygeal GCT, resection of the coccyx is mandatory.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_571"> Completeness of surgical resection is an important prognostic factor, as shown in the following circumstances:<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_572" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Resected tumors with negative microscopic margins: EFS rates higher than 90%.</ListItem><ListItem>Resected tumors with microscopic margins: EFS rates of 75% to 85%.</ListItem><ListItem>Resected tumors with macroscopic residual disease: EFS rates lower than 40%. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_705"><Title>Mediastinal site</Title><Para id="_77">Mediastinal GCTs account for 15% to 20% of malignant extragonadal
extracranial GCTs in children.<Reference refidx="5"/> The histology of mediastinal
GCT is dependent on age, with teratomas predominating among
infants and yolk sac tumors predominating among children aged 1
to 4 years.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_573">Prepubertal children with mediastinal malignant teratomas are treated with tumor
resection, which is curative in almost all patients.<Reference refidx="7"/> Children with
stage I to stage III nonmetastatic mediastinal GCTs who receive 
cisplatin-based chemotherapy have 5-year EFS and OS rates of 90%. However, patients with stage IV mediastinal tumors have EFS rates closer to 80%.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="7"/>; <Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_567"><Title>Retroperitoneal site</Title><Para id="_149">Malignant GCTs located in the retroperitoneum or abdomen usually present in children younger than 5 years. Most of these tumors are advanced stage and locally unresectable at diagnosis.<Reference refidx="15"/> A limited biopsy followed by platinum-based chemotherapy to shrink tumor bulk can lead to complete tumor resection in most patients.  Despite the advanced-stage disease in most patients, the 6-year  EFS rate using PEb was 83% in the Pediatric Oncology Group/Children's Cancer Group intergroup study.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_568"><Title>Head and neck site</Title><Para id="_326">Although rare, benign and malignant GCTs can occur in the head and neck region, especially in infants. The airway is often threatened. Surgery for nonmalignant tumors and surgery plus chemotherapy for malignant tumors can be curative.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_706"><Title>Standard Treatment Options for Malignant Extragonadal Extracranial GCTs in Postpubertal Children</Title><Para id="_707">In a study of prognostic factors in pediatric extragonadal malignant GCTs, age older than 12 years was the most important prognostic factor. In a multivariate analysis, children aged 12 years and older with thoracic tumors had six times the risk of death compared with children younger than 12 years with primary nonthoracic tumors.<Reference refidx="17"/> In a subsequent meta-analysis, adolescents with stage III and stage IV extragonadal disease had poor outcomes (expected EFS rate, &lt;70%).<Reference refidx="3"/> Extragonadal disease of any stage is considered a poor risk factor in adolescents and young adults.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_708">Standard treatment options for malignant extragonadal extracranial GCTs in postpubertal children include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_709" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy (four cycles of bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin [BEP]).</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy followed by surgery to remove residual tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>Enrollment in a clinical trial.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1882">As with sacrococcygeal tumors, primary chemotherapy is usually necessary to facilitate surgical resection of mediastinal GCTs, and the completeness of resection is a very important prognostic indicator.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="19"/>  Survival rates for the older adolescent and young adult
population with mediastinal tumors are  generally  lower than 60%.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/>; <Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_711">Patients with a malignant mediastinal primary tumor and extracranial metastases are at the highest risk of developing brain metastases and are monitored closely for signs and symptoms of central nervous system involvement.<Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] For more information about the treatment of adult patients, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062939" url="/types/extragonadal-germ-cell/hp/extragonadal-treatment-pdq">Extragonadal Germ Cell
Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_750"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043497">childhood extragonadal germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation for Malignant Extragonadal Extracranial GCTs</Title><Para id="_751">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1801">The following is an example of a national and/or institutional clinical trial that is currently being conducted:</Para><OrderedList id="_752" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><Strong><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03067181">AGCT1531 (NCT03067181)</ProtocolRef></Strong> (Active Surveillance, Bleomycin, Carboplatin, Etoposide, or Cisplatin in Treating Pediatric and Adult Patients with GCTs)<Strong>:</Strong>
The aim of this trial is to reduce toxicity and maintain efficacy of treatment for patients with standard-risk GCTs.  Patients with stage I malignant GCTs (low risk, age 0–50 years) will be treated with surgery and observation.  Patients with intermediate-risk GCTs will be randomly assigned to receive cisplatin or carboplatin and bleomycin and etoposide. Children younger than 11 years will receive bleomycin with each cycle, and those aged 11 years and older will receive weekly bleomycin. Patients with pure seminoma or dysgerminoma are excluded from the trial.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_750_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_750_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15226336">Cushing B, Giller R, Cullen JW, et al.: Randomized comparison of combination chemotherapy with etoposide, bleomycin, and either high-dose or standard-dose cisplatin in children and adolescents with high-risk malignant germ cell tumors: a pediatric intergroup study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9049 and Children's Cancer Group 8882. J Clin Oncol 22 (13): 2691-700, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10561181" MedlineID="20029910">Baranzelli MC, Kramar A, Bouffet E, et al.: Prognostic factors in children with localized malignant nonseminomatous germ cell tumors. J Clin Oncol 17 (4): 1212, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25452439">Frazier AL, Hale JP, Rodriguez-Galindo C, et al.: Revised risk classification for pediatric extracranial germ cell tumors based on 25 years of clinical trial data from the United Kingdom and United States. J Clin Oncol 33 (2): 195-201, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15337806">Rogers PC, Olson TA, Cullen JW, et al.: Treatment of children and adolescents with stage II testicular and stages I and II ovarian malignant germ cell tumors: A Pediatric Intergroup Study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9048 and Children's Cancer Group 8891. J Clin Oncol 22 (17): 3563-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="11078494" MedlineID="20530736">Mann JR, Raafat F, Robinson K, et al.: The United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group's second germ cell tumor study: carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin are effective treatment for children with malignant extracranial germ cell tumors, with acceptable toxicity. J Clin Oncol 18 (22): 3809-18, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="23703725">Malogolowkin MH, Krailo M, Marina N, et al.: Pilot study of cisplatin, etoposide, bleomycin, and escalating dose cyclophosphamide therapy for children with high risk germ cell tumors: a report of the children's oncology group (COG). Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (10): 1602-5, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="10673525" MedlineID="20139488">Schneider DT, Calaminus G, Reinhard H, et al.: Primary mediastinal germ cell tumors in children and adolescents: results of the German cooperative protocols MAKEI 83/86, 89, and 96. J Clin Oncol 18 (4): 832-9, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11283126">Göbel U, Schneider DT, Calaminus G, et al.: Multimodal treatment of malignant sacrococcygeal germ cell tumors: a prospective analysis of 66 patients of the German cooperative protocols MAKEI 83/86 and 89. J Clin Oncol 19 (7): 1943-50, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11150431" MedlineID="20584362">Rescorla F, Billmire D, Stolar C, et al.: The effect of cisplatin dose and surgical resection in children with malignant germ cell tumors at the sacrococcygeal region: a pediatric intergroup trial (POG 9049/CCG 8882). J Pediatr Surg 36 (1): 12-7, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="4843993">Altman RP, Randolph JG, Lilly JR: Sacrococcygeal teratoma: American Academy of Pediatrics Surgical Section Survey-1973. J Pediatr Surg 9 (3): 389-98, 1974.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="9498381">Rescorla FJ, Sawin RS, Coran AG, et al.: Long-term outcome for infants and children with sacrococcygeal teratoma: a report from the Childrens Cancer Group. J Pediatr Surg 33 (2): 171-6, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="12610174">Calaminus G, Schneider DT, Bökkerink JP, et al.: Prognostic value of tumor size, metastases, extension into bone, and increased tumor marker in children with malignant sacrococcygeal germ cell tumors: a prospective evaluation of 71 patients treated in the German cooperative protocols Maligne Keimzelltumoren (MAKEI) 83/86 and MAKEI 89. J Clin Oncol 21 (5): 781-6, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="27786428">Egler RA, Gosiengfiao Y, Russell H, et al.: Is surgical resection and observation sufficient for stage I and II sacrococcygeal germ cell tumors? A case series and review. Pediatr Blood Cancer 64 (5): , 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="26766550">De Pasquale MD, Crocoli A, Conte M, et al.: Mediastinal Germ Cell Tumors in Pediatric Patients: A Report From the Italian Association of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology. Pediatr Blood Cancer 63 (5): 808-12, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="12632341">Billmire D, Vinocur C, Rescorla F, et al.: Malignant retroperitoneal and abdominal germ cell tumors: an intergroup study. J Pediatr Surg 38 (3): 315-8; discussion 315-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="18937314">Bernbeck B, Schneider DT, Bernbeck B, et al.: Germ cell tumors of the head and neck: report from the MAKEI Study Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 52 (2): 223-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="16735707">Marina N, London WB, Frazier AL, et al.: Prognostic factors in children with extragonadal malignant germ cell tumors: a pediatric intergroup study. J Clin Oncol 24 (16): 2544-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="9053482" MedlineID="97178749">International Germ Cell Consensus Classification: a prognostic factor-based staging system for metastatic germ cell cancers. International Germ Cell Cancer Collaborative Group. J Clin Oncol 15 (2): 594-603, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="11150432" MedlineID="20584363">Billmire D, Vinocur C, Rescorla F, et al.: Malignant mediastinal germ cell tumors: an intergroup study. J Pediatr Surg 36 (1): 18-24, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="11157018" MedlineID="21104116">Vuky J, Bains M, Bacik J, et al.: Role of postchemotherapy adjunctive surgery in the management of patients with nonseminoma arising from the mediastinum. J Clin Oncol 19 (3): 682-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="10699894" MedlineID="20164351">Ganjoo KN, Rieger KM, Kesler KA, et al.: Results of modern therapy for patients with mediastinal nonseminomatous germ cell tumors. Cancer 88 (5): 1051-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="11919246" MedlineID="21917884">Bokemeyer C, Nichols CR, Droz JP, et al.: Extragonadal germ cell tumors of the mediastinum and retroperitoneum: results from an international analysis. J Clin Oncol 20 (7): 1864-73, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="18222229">Kang CH, Kim YT, Jheon SH, et al.: Surgical treatment of malignant mediastinal nonseminomatous germ cell tumor. Ann Thorac Surg 85 (2): 379-84, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="22693072">Göbel U, von Kries R, Teske C, et al.: Brain metastases during follow-up of children and adolescents with extracranial malignant germ cell tumors: risk adapted management decision tree analysis based on data of the MAHO/MAKEI-registry. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (2): 217-23, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043498">recurrent childhood malignant germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Malignant  GCTs in Children</Title><Para id="_150">Only a small number of children and adolescents with extracranial germ cell tumors (GCTs) have a recurrence.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Reports regarding the treatment and outcome of these children are based on small studies.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_425">Treatment options for recurrent pediatric GCTs are modeled after treatment options in adult clinical trials.  Information about ongoing National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_576"><Title>Standard Treatment Options for Recurrent Malignant GCTs in Children</Title><Para id="_426">Standard treatment options for recurrent childhood malignant GCTs include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_586" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery alone.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_428" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery with neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_712">For information about salvage therapy after observation for patients with stage I disease, see the following sections:</Para><ItemizedList id="_720" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_680" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and Observation</SummaryRef> section of the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_44" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview for Childhood Extracranial GCTs</SummaryRef> section.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_532" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation (stage I)</SummaryRef> section of the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_61" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Malignant testicular GCTs in prepubertal males</SummaryRef> section.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_1809" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Surgery and observation for prepubertal females (stage I following strict surgical staging guidelines)</SummaryRef> section of the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_424" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">Malignant nongerminomatous ovarian GCTs</SummaryRef> section.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_428"><Title>Surgery with neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_713">Reports of salvage treatment strategies used in adult recurrent GCTs  include larger numbers of patients, but the differences between children and adults regarding the location of the primary  GCT site, pattern of relapse, and the biology of childhood  GCTs may limit the applicability of adult salvage approaches to children. In adults with recurrent GCTs, several chemotherapy combinations (most include the addition of paclitaxel and ifosfamide to a platinum compound) have achieved relatively good disease-free status.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  A combination of paclitaxel and gemcitabine has demonstrated activity in adults with testicular GCTs who relapsed after high-dose chemotherapy and hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT).<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_714">Among children with benign sacrococcygeal tumors who recur, a malignant component may be present at the primary tumor site. For these children, complete surgical resection of the recurrent tumor and  coccyx (if not done originally) is the basis of salvage treatment. Preoperative chemotherapy with cisplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin (PEb)  may assist the surgical resection. In patients who had a malignant sacrococcygeal tumor that recurred after PEb treatment, surgery and additional chemotherapy may be warranted.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_730">In a phase II Children’s Oncology Group (COG) trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00467051">AGCT0521 [NCT00467051]</ProtocolRef>), 20 patients younger than 21 years who relapsed after PEb therapy received two cycles of paclitaxel, ifosfamide, and carboplatin (TIC). Responses were then assessed by a combination of Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria and marker decline. Eight patients had partial responses, ten patients had stable disease, and two patients had progressive disease. This chemotherapy regimen produced a combined response rate of 44%.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_715"><Title>Nonstandard Treatment Options for Recurrent Malignant GCTs in Children</Title><SummarySection id="_613"><Title>High-dose (HD) chemotherapy and hematopoietic stem cell rescue</Title><Para id="_616">The role of HD chemotherapy and hematopoietic stem cell rescue for recurrent pediatric GCTs is not established, despite anecdotal reports. In one European series, 10 of 23 children with relapsed extragonadal GCTs achieved long-term disease-free survival (median follow-up, 66 months) after receiving HD chemotherapy with stem cell support.<Reference refidx="12"/>  Additional study in children and adolescents is needed. For more information about transplant, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000805686" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/autologous">Pediatric Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000700000" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant">Pediatric Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant and Cellular Therapy for Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_614">HD chemotherapy with autologous stem cell rescue has been explored as a treatment for adults with recurrent testicular GCTs. HD chemotherapy plus hematopoietic stem cell rescue has been reported to cure adult patients with relapsed testicular GCTs, even as third-line therapy and in cisplatin-refractory patients.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> A small study also demonstrated efficacy in adolescents and women with ovarian GCTs.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]   While some studies support this approach,<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/> others do not.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> Salvage attempts using HD chemotherapy regimens may be of little benefit if the patient is not clinically disease free at the time of HSCT.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="21"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_580"><Title>Radiation therapy followed by surgery (for brain metastases)</Title><Para id="_581"> In a very small pediatric study, patients with nongerminomatous brain metastases responded to radiation therapy. In the German Maligne Keimzelltümoren (MAKEI) studies, radiation therapy and surgery for patients with brain metastases provided palliation and occasional long-term survival.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] A meta-analysis showed that radiation therapy did not improve outcome compared with surgery and radiation. However, the number of patients treated with radiation therapy was too small to accurately assess outcome.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_431"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043498">recurrent childhood malignant germ cell tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation for Recurrent Malignant GCTs in Children and Adolescents</Title><Para id="_582">Information about NCI-supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_431_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_431_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11078494" MedlineID="20530736">Mann JR, Raafat F, Robinson K, et al.: The United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group's second germ cell tumor study: carboplatin, etoposide, and bleomycin are effective treatment for children with malignant extracranial germ cell tumors, with acceptable toxicity. J Clin Oncol 18 (22): 3809-18, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15226336">Cushing B, Giller R, Cullen JW, et al.: Randomized comparison of combination chemotherapy with etoposide, bleomycin, and either high-dose or standard-dose cisplatin in children and adolescents with high-risk malignant germ cell tumors: a pediatric intergroup study--Pediatric Oncology Group 9049 and Children's Cancer Group 8882. J Clin Oncol 22 (13): 2691-700, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11283127">Schneider DT, Wessalowski R, Calaminus G, et al.: Treatment of recurrent malignant sacrococcygeal germ cell tumors: analysis of 22 patients registered in the German protocols MAKEI 83/86, 89, and 96. J Clin Oncol 19 (7): 1951-60, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="9667270" MedlineID="98329844">Loehrer PJ, Gonin R, Nichols CR, et al.: Vinblastine plus ifosfamide plus cisplatin as initial salvage therapy in recurrent germ cell tumor. J Clin Oncol 16 (7): 2500-4, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10856101">Motzer RJ, Sheinfeld J, Mazumdar M, et al.: Paclitaxel, ifosfamide, and cisplatin second-line therapy for patients with relapsed testicular germ cell cancer. J Clin Oncol 18 (12): 2413-8, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11250992">Hartmann JT, Einhorn L, Nichols CR, et al.: Second-line chemotherapy in patients with relapsed extragonadal nonseminomatous germ cell tumors: results of an international multicenter analysis. J Clin Oncol 19 (6): 1641-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="17194908">Kondagunta GV, Bacik J, Sheinfeld J, et al.: Paclitaxel plus Ifosfamide followed by high-dose carboplatin plus etoposide in previously treated germ cell tumors. J Clin Oncol 25 (1): 85-90, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="14568987">Schmoll HJ, Kollmannsberger C, Metzner B, et al.: Long-term results of first-line sequential high-dose etoposide, ifosfamide, and cisplatin chemotherapy plus autologous stem cell support for patients with advanced metastatic germ cell cancer: an extended phase I/II study of the German Testicular Cancer Study Group. J Clin Oncol 21 (22): 4083-91, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="16361627">Kondagunta GV, Bacik J, Bajorin D, et al.: Etoposide and cisplatin chemotherapy for metastatic good-risk germ cell tumors. J Clin Oncol 23 (36): 9290-4, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="17290059">Einhorn LH, Brames MJ, Juliar B, et al.: Phase II study of paclitaxel plus gemcitabine salvage chemotherapy for germ cell tumors after progression following high-dose chemotherapy with tandem transplant. J Clin Oncol 25 (5): 513-6, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="29697191">Pashankar F, Frazier AL, Krailo M, et al.: Treatment of refractory germ cell tumors in children with paclitaxel, ifosfamide, and carboplatin: A report from the Children's Oncology Group AGCT0521 study. Pediatr Blood Cancer 65 (8): e27111, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="16106248">De Giorgi U, Rosti G, Slavin S, et al.: Salvage high-dose chemotherapy for children with extragonadal germ-cell tumours. Br J Cancer 93 (4): 412-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="17652649">Einhorn LH, Williams SD, Chamness A, et al.: High-dose chemotherapy and stem-cell rescue for metastatic germ-cell tumors. N Engl J Med 357 (4): 340-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="10715285" MedlineID="20181879">Motzer RJ, Mazumdar M, Sheinfeld J, et al.: Sequential dose-intensive paclitaxel, ifosfamide, carboplatin, and etoposide salvage therapy for germ cell tumor patients. J Clin Oncol 18 (6): 1173-80, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="11134198">Rick O, Bokemeyer C, Beyer J, et al.: Salvage treatment with paclitaxel, ifosfamide, and cisplatin plus high-dose carboplatin, etoposide, and thiotepa followed by autologous stem-cell rescue in patients with relapsed or refractory germ cell cancer. J Clin Oncol 19 (1): 81-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="26115974">Meisel JL, Woo KM, Sudarsan N, et al.: Development of a risk stratification system to guide treatment for female germ cell tumors. Gynecol Oncol 138 (3): 566-72, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="11013274" MedlineID="20469575">Bhatia S, Abonour R, Porcu P, et al.: High-dose chemotherapy as initial salvage chemotherapy in patients with relapsed testicular cancer. J Clin Oncol 18 (19): 3346-51, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="20194867">Feldman DR, Sheinfeld J, Bajorin DF, et al.: TI-CE high-dose chemotherapy for patients with previously treated germ cell tumors: results and prognostic factor analysis. J Clin Oncol 28 (10): 1706-13, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="11374323">Beyer J, Rick O, Siegert W, et al.: Salvage chemotherapy in relapsed germ cell tumors. World J Urol 19 (2): 90-3, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="8874322" MedlineID="97028308">Beyer J, Kramar A, Mandanas R, et al.: High-dose chemotherapy as salvage treatment in germ cell tumors: a multivariate analysis of prognostic variables. J Clin Oncol 14 (10): 2638-45, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="15365067">Rick O, Bokemeyer C, Weinknecht S, et al.: Residual tumor resection after high-dose chemotherapy in patients with relapsed or refractory germ cell cancer. J Clin Oncol 22 (18): 3713-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="22693072">Göbel U, von Kries R, Teske C, et al.: Brain metastases during follow-up of children and adolescents with extracranial malignant germ cell tumors: risk adapted management decision tree analysis based on data of the MAHO/MAKEI-registry. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (2): 217-23, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="20514616">Göbel U, Schneider DT, Teske C, et al.: Brain metastases in children and adolescents with extracranial germ cell tumor - data of the MAHO/MAKEI-registry. Klin Padiatr 222 (3): 140-4, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="26460295">Feldman DR, Lorch A, Kramar A, et al.: Brain Metastases in Patients With Germ Cell Tumors: Prognostic Factors and Treatment Options--An Analysis From the Global Germ Cell Cancer Group. J Clin Oncol 34 (4): 345-51, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_112"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/05/2024)</Title><Para id="_662">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_1952">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062854#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood extracranial germ cell tumors. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Thomas A. Olson, MD (Aflac Cancer and Blood Disorders Center of Children's Healthcare of Atlanta - Egleston Campus)</ListItem><ListItem>D. Williams Parsons, MD, PhD (Texas Children's Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Stephen J. Shochat, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Extracranial Germ Cell Tumors Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/extracranial-germ-cell/hp/germ-cell-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389316]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-11-05</DateLastModified></Summary>
