<Summary id="CDR0000062864" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) treatment options include chemotherapy, radiation therapy, stem cell transplant, and targeted therapy. Get detailed information about the molecular genetics, prognosis, and treatment of ALL in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037837">adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_248">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_249">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037837">adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL)</Title><Para id="_193">ALL (also called acute lymphocytic leukemia) is an aggressive type of leukemia characterized by the presence of too many lymphoblasts or lymphocytes in the bone marrow and peripheral blood. It can spread to the lymph nodes, spleen, liver, central nervous system (CNS), testicles, and other organs. Without treatment, ALL usually progresses quickly.</Para><Para id="_194">Signs and symptoms of ALL may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_195" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Weakness or fatigue.</ListItem><ListItem>Fever or night sweats.</ListItem><ListItem>Bruises or bleeds easily (i.e., bleeding gums, purplish patches in the skin, or petechiae [flat, pinpoint spots under the skin]).</ListItem><ListItem>Shortness of breath.</ListItem><ListItem>Unexpected weight loss or anorexia.</ListItem><ListItem>Pain in the bones or joints.</ListItem><ListItem>Swollen lymph nodes, particularly lymph nodes in the neck, armpit, or groin,  which are usually painless.</ListItem><ListItem>Swelling or discomfort in the abdomen.</ListItem><ListItem>Frequent infections.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_196">ALL occurs in both children and adults. It is the most common type of cancer in children, and treatment results in a good chance for a cure. For adults, the prognosis is not as optimistic. This summary discusses ALL in adults. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062923" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-all-treatment-pdq">Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_14"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_228">Estimated new cases and deaths from ALL in the United States in 2025:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_16" Style="bullet"><ListItem>New cases: 6,100.</ListItem><ListItem>Deaths: 1,400.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_44"><Title>Anatomy</Title><Para id="_214">ALL presumably arises from malignant transformation of B- or T-cell progenitor cells.<Reference refidx="2"/> It is more commonly seen in children but can occur at any age.  The disease is characterized by the accumulation of lymphoblasts in the marrow or in various extramedullary sites, frequently accompanied by suppression of normal hematopoiesis.  B- and T-cell lymphoblastic leukemia cells express surface antigens that parallel their respective lineage developments.  Precursor B-cell ALL cells typically express CD10, CD19, and CD34 on their surface, along with nuclear terminal deoxynucleotide transferase (TdT), while precursor T-cell ALL cells commonly express CD2, CD3, CD7, CD34, and TdT.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526538" type="image/jpeg" alt="Blood cell development; drawing shows the steps a blood stem cell goes through to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell. A myeloid stem cell becomes a red blood cell, a platelet, or a myeloblast, which then becomes a granulocyte (the types of granulocytes are eosinophils, basophils, and neutrophils). A lymphoid stem cell becomes a lymphoblast and then becomes a B-lymphocyte, T-lymphocyte, or natural killer cell." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_199"><Caption language="en">Blood cell development. A blood stem cell goes through several steps to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell.   </Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><Title>Molecular Genetics</Title><Para id="_21">Some patients presenting with acute
leukemia may have a cytogenetic abnormality that is cytogenetically
indistinguishable from the Philadelphia chromosome (Ph).<Reference refidx="3"/> The Ph occurs in only 1% to 2% of patients with acute myeloid leukemia (AML), but it occurs in about 20% of
adults and a small percentage of children with ALL.<Reference refidx="4"/> In most
children and in more than one-half of adults with Ph-positive
ALL, the molecular abnormality is different from that in Ph-positive chronic
myeloid leukemia (CML).
</Para><Para id="_22">  Many patients who
have molecular evidence of the <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> fusion gene, which characterizes the Ph, have no evidence of the abnormal chromosome by cytogenetics.  
   The <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> fusion gene may be detectable only by fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization (FISH) or reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) because many patients have a different fusion protein from the one found in
CML (p190 vs. p210).  These tests should be performed, whenever
possible, in patients with ALL, especially in  those with B-cell lineage disease.</Para><Para id="_23">L3 ALL is associated with a variety of translocations that
involve the <GeneName>MYC</GeneName>  proto-oncogene and the immunoglobulin gene
locus t(2;8), t(8;12), and t(8;22).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Diagnosis</Title><Para id="_215">Patients with ALL may present with a variety of hematologic abnormalities ranging from pancytopenia to hyperleukocytosis.  In addition to a history and physical examination, the initial workup should include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_216" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Complete blood count with differential.</ListItem><ListItem>A chemistry panel (including uric acid, creatinine, blood urea nitrogen, potassium, phosphate, calcium, bilirubin, and hepatic transaminases).</ListItem><ListItem>Fibrinogen and tests of coagulation as a screen for disseminated intravascular coagulation.</ListItem><ListItem>A careful screen for evidence of active infection.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_217">A bone marrow biopsy and aspirate are routinely performed even in T-cell ALL to determine the extent of marrow involvement.  Malignant cells should be sent for conventional cytogenetic studies, as detection of the Ph t(9;22), <GeneName>MYC</GeneName> gene rearrangements (in Burkitt leukemia), and <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> gene rearrangements add important prognostic information. Flow cytometry should be performed to characterize expression of lineage-defining antigens and determine the specific ALL subtype.  In addition, for B-cell disease, the malignant cells should be analyzed using RT-PCR and FISH for evidence of the <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> fusion gene.  This last point is of utmost importance, as timely diagnosis of Ph ALL will significantly change the therapeutic approach.</Para><Para id="_32">Diagnostic
confusion with  AML, hairy cell leukemia, and
malignant lymphoma is not uncommon.  Proper diagnosis is crucial because of the
difference in prognosis and treatment of ALL and AML.  Immunophenotypic
analysis is essential because leukemias that do not express myeloperoxidase
include M0 AML,  M7 AML,  and ALL.
</Para><Para id="_33">The examination of bone marrow
aspirates and/or biopsy specimens should be done by an experienced oncologist,
hematologist, hematopathologist, or general pathologist who is capable of
interpreting conventional and specially stained specimens.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_34"><Title>Prognosis and Survival</Title><Para id="_155">Factors associated with prognosis in patients with ALL include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_156" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Age:</Strong> Age, a significant factor in
childhood ALL and  AML, may  be an important prognostic factor in adult
ALL.  In one study, the overall prognosis was better in patients younger than
25 years; another study found a better prognosis in  patients younger than 35
years.  These findings may, in part, be related to the increased incidence of
the  Ph in older patients with ALL, a subgroup associated
with poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>CNS involvement:</Strong> As in childhood ALL, adult patients with ALL are at risk of developing CNS involvement during the course of their disease. This is particularly true for patients with L3  (Burkitt) morphology.<Reference refidx="7"/> This complication influences both treatment and
prognosis. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Cellular morphology:</Strong> Patients with L3 morphology showed improved outcomes, as evidenced in a completed Cancer and Leukemia Group B study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00002494">CLB-9251</ProtocolRef> [NCT00002494]), when treated according to
specific treatment algorithms.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  This study found  that L3 leukemia can be cured with aggressive, rapidly cycling, lymphoma-like
chemotherapy regimens.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Chromosomal abnormalities:</Strong> Chromosomal
abnormalities, including aneuploidy and translocations, have been described and
may correlate with prognosis.<Reference refidx="12"/> In particular, patients with Ph-positive t(9;22) ALL have a
poor prognosis and represent more than 30% of adult cases. Patients with leukemia and a <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> fusion gene who do not
demonstrate the classical Ph carry a poor prognosis similar
to those who are Ph positive.  Patients with Ph-positive ALL are rarely cured with chemotherapy, although long-term survival is now routinely reported when such patients are treated with combinations of chemotherapy and BCR::ABL1 tyrosine kinase inhibitors. <Para id="_41">Two other chromosomal abnormalities associated with a poor prognosis are t(4;11), which is characterized by rearrangements of the <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> gene and may be rearranged despite normal cytogenetics, and t(9;22). In addition to t(4;11) and t(9;22), compared with patients with a normal karyotype, patients
with deletion of chromosome 7 or trisomy 8 have been reported to have a lower
probability of survival at 5 years.<Reference refidx="13"/> In a multivariate analysis, karyotype was the most important
predictor of disease-free survival.<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><Title> Late Effects of Treatment for ALL</Title><Para id="_43">Long-term follow-up of 30 patients with ALL in remission for at least 10 years has demonstrated ten cases of secondary malignancies.  Of 31 long-term female survivors of ALL or AML younger than 40 years, 26 resumed normal menstruation following completion of therapy.      Among 36 live offspring of survivors, two congenital problems occurred.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="17268486">Pui CH, Jeha S: New therapeutic strategies for the treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukaemia. Nat Rev Drug Discov 6 (2): 149-65, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Peterson LC, Bloomfield CD, Brunning RD: Blast crisis as an initial or terminal manifestation of chronic myeloid leukemia: a study of 28 patients. Am J Med  60(2): 209-220, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="3165301" MedlineID="88294342">Secker-Walker LM, Cooke HM, Browett PJ, et al.: Variable Philadelphia breakpoints and potential lineage restriction of bcr rearrangement in acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 72 (2): 784-91, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3163722" MedlineID="88229801">Gaynor J, Chapman D, Little C, et al.: A cause-specific hazard rate analysis of prognostic factors among 199 adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: the Memorial Hospital experience since 1969. J Clin Oncol 6 (6): 1014-30, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="3422030" MedlineID="88078354">Hoelzer D, Thiel E, Löffler H, et al.: Prognostic factors in a multicenter study for treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia in adults. Blood 71 (1): 123-31, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3052630" MedlineID="89027115">Kantarjian HM, Walters RS, Smith TL, et al.: Identification of risk groups for development of central nervous system leukemia in adults with acute lymphocytic leukemia. Blood 72 (5): 1784-9, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11600602" MedlineID="21486642">Lee EJ, Petroni GR, Schiffer CA, et al.: Brief-duration high-intensity chemotherapy for patients with small noncleaved-cell lymphoma or FAB L3 acute lymphocytic leukemia: results of cancer and leukemia group B study 9251. J Clin Oncol 19 (20): 4014-22, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="8555471" MedlineID="96141069">Hoelzer D, Ludwig WD, Thiel E, et al.: Improved outcome in adult B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 87 (2): 495-508, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="2930722" MedlineID="89194116">Fenaux P, Lai JL, Miaux O, et al.: Burkitt cell acute leukaemia (L3 ALL) in adults: a report of 18 cases. Br J Haematol 71 (3): 371-6, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="1421370" MedlineID="93043292">Reiter A, Schrappe M, Ludwig WD, et al.: Favorable outcome of B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia in childhood: a report of three consecutive studies of the BFM group. Blood 80 (10): 2471-8, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="6571719" MedlineID="83076922">Chromosomal abnormalities and their clinical significance in acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Third International Workshop on Chromosomes in Leukemia. Cancer Res 43 (2): 868-73, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="10339508" MedlineID="99272444">Wetzler M, Dodge RK, Mrózek K, et al.: Prospective karyotype analysis in adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia: the cancer and leukemia Group B experience. Blood 93 (11): 3983-93, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="11380414" MedlineID="21275148">Micallef IN, Rohatiner AZ, Carter M, et al.: Long-term outcome of patients surviving for more than ten years following treatment for acute leukaemia. Br J Haematol 113 (2): 443-5, 2001.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037837">adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular Classification of ALL</Title><Para id="_50">The following leukemic cell characteristics are important: </Para><ItemizedList id="_51" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Morphological features.</ListItem><ListItem>Cytogenetic characteristics. </ListItem><ListItem>Immunologic cell surface and biochemical markers. </ListItem><ListItem>Cytochemistry.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_52">In adults, French-American-British (FAB) L1 morphology (more mature-appearing lymphoblasts) is present in fewer than 50% of patients, and L2
 morphology (more immature and pleomorphic) predominates.<Reference refidx="1"/> L3 (Burkitt) acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) is much less common than the other two FAB subtypes.  It is characterized by blasts with cytoplasmic vacuolizations and surface expression of immunoglobulin, and the bone marrow often has an appearance described as a <Emphasis>starry sky</Emphasis> owing to the presence of numerous apoptotic cells.  L3 ALL is associated with a variety of translocations that
involve the <GeneName>MYC</GeneName>  proto-oncogene and the immunoglobulin gene
locus t(2;8), t(8;12), and t(8;22).</Para><Para id="_163">Some patients presenting with acute
leukemia may have a cytogenetic abnormality that is morphologically
indistinguishable from the Philadelphia chromosome (Ph).<Reference refidx="2"/>  The Ph occurs in only 1% to 2% of patients with acute myeloid leukemia (AML), but it occurs in about 20% of
adults and a small percentage of children with ALL.<Reference refidx="3"/>  In most
children and in more than one-half of adults with Ph-positive
ALL, the molecular abnormality is different from that in Ph-positive chronic
myeloid leukemia (CML).
</Para><Para id="_164">  Many patients who
have molecular evidence of the <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> fusion gene, which characterizes the Ph, have no evidence of the abnormal chromosome by cytogenetics.  
  The <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> fusion gene may be detectable only by pulsed-field gel electrophoresis or reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction because many patients have a different fusion protein from the one found in
CML (p190 vs. p210).   </Para><Para id="_54">Using heteroantisera and monoclonal antibodies, ALL cells can be divided into several subtypes (see Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_222" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Table id="_222"><Title>Table 1.   Frequency of Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) Cell Subtypes</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Cell Subtype</entry><entry Align="Center">Approximate Frequency</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry>Early B-cell lineage</entry><entry>80% </entry></Row><Row><entry>T cells</entry><entry>10%–15%</entry></Row><Row><entry>B cells with surface immunoglobulins</entry><entry>&lt;5%</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_56">About 95% of all types of ALL (except Burkitt, which usually has an L3 morphology by the FAB classification) have elevated terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (TdT) expression. This elevation is extremely useful in diagnosis; if concentrations of the enzyme are not elevated, the diagnosis of ALL is suspect. However, 20% of cases of AML may express TdT; therefore, its usefulness as a lineage marker is limited. Because Burkitt leukemias are managed  according to different treatment algorithms, it is important to specifically identify these cases prospectively by their L3 morphology, absence of TdT, and expression of surface immunoglobulin. Patients with Burkitt leukemias  will typically have one of  the following three chromosomal translocations: </Para><ItemizedList id="_57" Style="bullet"><ListItem>t(8;14).</ListItem><ListItem>t(2;8).</ListItem><ListItem>t(8;22).</ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="291508" MedlineID="80046818">Brearley RL, Johnson SA, Lister TA: Acute lymphoblastic leukaemia in adults: clinicopathological correlations with the French-American-British (FAB) co-operative group classification. Eur J Cancer 15 (6): 909-14, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Peterson LC, Bloomfield CD, Brunning RD: Blast crisis as an initial or terminal manifestation of chronic myeloid leukemia: a study of 28 patients. Am J Med  60(2): 209-220, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="3165301" MedlineID="88294342">Secker-Walker LM, Cooke HM, Browett PJ, et al.: Variable Philadelphia breakpoints and potential lineage restriction of bcr rearrangement in acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 72 (2): 784-91, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="3422030" MedlineID="88078354">Hoelzer D, Thiel E, Löffler H, et al.: Prognostic factors in a multicenter study for treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia in adults. Blood 71 (1): 123-31, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3855666" MedlineID="85123225">Sobol RE, Royston I, LeBien TW, et al.: Adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia phenotypes defined by monoclonal antibodies. Blood 65 (3): 730-5, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="6969097" MedlineID="81063459">Foon KA, Billing RJ, Terasaki PI, et al.: Immunologic classification of acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Implications for normal lymphoid differentiation. Blood 56 (6): 1120-6, 1980.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_58"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037837">adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for ALL</Title><Para id="_59">There is no distinct staging system for acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL). This disease is classified as untreated, in remission, or recurrent. </Para><SummarySection id="_60"><Title>Untreated ALL</Title><Para id="_61">For a newly diagnosed patient with no prior treatment, untreated  ALL is defined by:</Para><ItemizedList id="_62" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Abnormal white blood cell count
and differential.</ListItem><ListItem>Abnormal hematocrit/hemoglobin and platelet counts.</ListItem><ListItem>Abnormal
bone marrow with more than 5% blasts.</ListItem><ListItem>Signs and symptoms of the disease.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_63"><Title>ALL in Remission</Title><Para id="_64">A patient who has received remission-induction treatment of ALL is in remission if all of the following criteria are met:</Para><ItemizedList id="_65" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Bone marrow is normocellular with no more than 5% blasts.</ListItem><ListItem>There are no
signs or symptoms of the disease.</ListItem><ListItem>There are no signs or symptoms of central nervous
system leukemia or other extramedullary infiltration.</ListItem><ListItem>All of the following
laboratory values are within the reference ranges:<ItemizedList id="_66" Style="dash"><ListItem>White blood cell count and
differential.</ListItem><ListItem>Hematocrit/hemoglobin level.</ListItem><ListItem>Platelet count.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_69"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037837">adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for ALL</Title><Para id="_70">Successful treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) consists of the
control of bone marrow and systemic disease and  the treatment (or
prevention) of sanctuary-site disease, particularly the central nervous system
(CNS).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> The cornerstone of this strategy includes systemically
administered combination chemotherapy with CNS preventive therapy.  CNS
prophylaxis is achieved with chemotherapy (intrathecal and/or high-dose
systemic therapy) and, in some cases, cranial radiation therapy.
 </Para><Para id="_71">Treatment is divided into three phases:</Para><ItemizedList id="_72" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Remission induction.</ListItem><ListItem>CNS prophylaxis.</ListItem><ListItem>Consolidation (also called remission continuation or maintenance).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_73">The average length of treatment for ALL
ranges from 1.5 to 3 years in the effort to eradicate the leukemic cell
population.  Younger adults with ALL may be eligible for selected clinical trials for childhood ALL. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062923#_1161" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-all-treatment-pdq">Adolescents and Young Adults With ALL</SummaryRef> section in Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Treatment.</Para><Para id="_168">Entry into a clinical trial is highly desirable to ensure adequate patient treatment and maximal information retrieval from the treatment of this highly responsive, but usually fatal, disease. </Para><Table id="_167"><Title>Table 2.  Treatment Options for Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL)</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="24.27%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="75.72%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_58" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Disease Status</SummaryRef></entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Options</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">BMT = bone marrow transplant; CNS = central nervous system.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Untreated ALL</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_87" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Remission induction therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_101" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">CNS prophylaxis therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">ALL in remission</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_111" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Consolidation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_130" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">CNS prophylaxis therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Recurrent ALL</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_139" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Reinduction chemotherapy</SummaryRef> followed by allogeneic BMT</entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_279" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Blinatumomab</SummaryRef> followed by allogeneic BMT</entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_271" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Inotuzumab ozogamicin</SummaryRef> followed by allogeneic BMT</entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_141" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Palliative radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_143" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Dasatinib</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_362" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Revumenib</SummaryRef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3513984" MedlineID="86162033">Clarkson BD, Gee T, Arlin ZA, et al.: Current status of treatment of acute leukemia in adults: an overview of the Memorial experience and review of literature. Crit Rev Oncol Hematol 4 (3): 221-48, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="3547671" MedlineID="87149134">Hoelzer D, Gale RP: Acute lymphoblastic leukemia in adults: recent progress, future directions. Semin Hematol 24 (1): 27-39, 1987.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_81"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039077">untreated adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Untreated ALL</Title><SummarySection id="_82"><Title>Treatment Options for Untreated ALL</Title><Para id="_83">Treatment options for untreated acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) include:</Para><OrderedList id="_84" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_87" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Remission induction therapy</SummaryRef>, including:<ItemizedList id="_206" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Combination chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Imatinib mesylate (for patients with Philadelphia chromosome [Ph]–positive ALL).</ListItem><ListItem>Imatinib mesylate combined with combination chemotherapy (for patients with Ph-positive ALL).</ListItem><ListItem>Supportive care.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_101" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Central nervous system (CNS) prophylaxis therapy</SummaryRef>, including:<ItemizedList id="_207" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Cranial radiation therapy plus intrathecal (IT) methotrexate.</ListItem><ListItem>High-dose systemic methotrexate and IT methotrexate without cranial radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>IT chemotherapy alone. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_87"><Title>Remission induction therapy</Title><Para id="_218">Sixty percent to 80% of adults with ALL usually achieve a  complete remission after appropriate induction therapy.  Appropriate initial treatment, usually consisting of a regimen that includes the combination of vincristine, prednisone, and an anthracycline, with or without asparaginase, results in a complete response  rate of up to 80%.   In patients with Ph-positive ALL, the remission rate is generally greater than 90% when standard induction regimens are combined with BCR::ABL1 tyrosine kinase inhibitors.   In the largest study published to date of Ph-positive ALL patients, 1,913 adult patients with ALL had a 5-year overall survival (OS) rate of 39%.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_219">Patients who experience a
relapse after remission  usually die within 1 year, even if a
second complete remission is achieved.   If there are appropriate available
donors and if the patient is younger than 55 years, bone marrow
transplant may be considered.<Reference refidx="2"/> Transplant centers performing five or fewer transplants annually usually have
poorer results than larger centers.<Reference refidx="3"/> If allogeneic transplant is considered,
it is recommended to avoid transfusions with blood products from a potential donor.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><SummarySection id="_169"><Title>Combination chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_88">Most current induction regimens for patients with adult ALL
include combination chemotherapy with prednisone, vincristine, and an anthracycline.  Some regimens, including those used in a Cancer and Leukemia Group B   (CALGB) study (CLB-8811), also add
other drugs, such as asparaginase or cyclophosphamide.  Current multiagent
induction regimens result in complete response rates that range from 60% to
90%.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_170"><Title>Imatinib mesylate </Title><Para id="_171">Imatinib mesylate is often incorporated into the therapeutic plan for patients with Ph-positive ALL. Imatinib mesylate, an orally available inhibitor of the BCR::ABL1  tyrosine kinase, has shown clinical activity as a single agent in Ph-positive ALL.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] More commonly, particularly in younger patients, imatinib is incorporated into combination chemotherapy regimens.  There are several published single-arm studies in which the complete response rate and survival rate are compared with historical controls.</Para><Para id="_172">Evidence (imatinib mesylate):</Para><Para id="_173">Several studies have suggested that the addition of imatinib  to conventional combination chemotherapy induction regimens results in complete response rates, event-free survival rates, and OS rates that are higher than those in historical controls.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/>  <Reference refidx="17"/> At the present time, no conclusions can be drawn regarding the optimal imatinib dose or schedule.</Para><OrderedList id="_174" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a study of imatinib combined with chemotherapy from the Northern Italy Leukemia Group, patients with newly diagnosed, untreated Ph-positive ALL were treated with an induction regimen containing idarubicin, vincristine, prednisone, and L-asparaginase.<Reference refidx="18"/>  After accrual of an initial cohort, the study was modified to include the use of imatinib (600 mg qd from days 15 to 21).  In consolidation, patients received imatinib (600 mg qd for 7 days) beginning 3 days before the start of each course of chemotherapy. <ItemizedList id="_223" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For all patients who achieved remission, the intent was to proceed to allogeneic transplant when and if an HLA-matched donor could be identified.  Patients lacking a donor received an autologous transplant.  After completion of chemotherapy and transplant, all patients were to receive maintenance imatinib for as long as tolerated.  After 20 patients had accrued to the imatinib arm, L-asparaginase was omitted from the induction regimen from both arms because of toxicity.  </ListItem><ListItem>Outcomes for the first cohort of 35 patients who did not receive imatinib were compared with those of the subsequent cohort of 59 imatinib-treated patients.  For patients treated with imatinib, the OS probability was 38% at 5 years (median, 3.1 years) versus 23% in the imatinib-free group (median, 1.1 year; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .009).<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]  </ListItem><ListItem>The drawbacks of this nonrandomized study were the small sample size (94 total patients) and the change in the treatment regimen (omission of L-asparaginase) midway through the study.  However, the results suggested that inclusion of imatinib into a relatively standard chemotherapy regimen for newly diagnosed adult patients with Ph-positive ALL may provide a significant survival advantage.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In another study, ten patients with Ph-positive ALL and ten patients with chronic myeloid leukemia in lymphoid blast crisis were treated with doses of imatinib ranging from 300 mg to 1,000 mg per day.<Reference refidx="13"/> <ItemizedList id="_371" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Of these 20 patients, four had complete hematologic remission and ten had marrow responses.</ListItem><ListItem>  Responses were short lived, with most of these patients experiencing disease relapse at a median of 58 days after the start of therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In another study, 48 patients with Ph-positive ALL were treated with 400 mg to 800 mg of imatinib per day.<Reference refidx="14"/><ItemizedList id="_372" Style="bullet"><ListItem> The overall response rate was 60%, with 9 out of 48 patients (19%) achieving a complete remission.  </ListItem><ListItem>The responses again were short, with a median duration of 2.2 months.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_208">In each of these studies, common toxicities were nausea and liver enzyme abnormalities, which necessitated interruption and/or dose reduction of imatinib.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> Subsequent allogeneic transplant does not appear to be adversely affected by the addition of imatinib to the treatment regimen. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062747" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">Nausea and Vomiting Related to Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_175">Imatinib is generally incorporated into the treatment of patients with Ph-positive ALL because of the responses observed in monotherapy trials. If a suitable donor is available,
allogeneic bone marrow transplant should be considered because remissions
are generally short with conventional ALL chemotherapy clinical trials.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_176"><Title>Supportive care</Title><Para id="_177">Since myelosuppression is an anticipated consequence of both leukemia and
its treatment with chemotherapy, patients must be closely monitored during
remission induction treatment.  Facilities must be available for hematologic
support and  for the treatment of infectious complications.
</Para><Para id="_178">Supportive care during remission induction treatment should routinely include
red blood cell and platelet transfusions, when appropriate.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_179">Evidence (supportive care):</Para><OrderedList id="_96" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Randomized
clinical trials have shown similar outcomes for patients who received prophylactic
platelet transfusions at a level of 10,000/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript> rather than at a level of
20,000/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript>.<Reference refidx="21"/> </ListItem><ListItem>The incidence of platelet alloimmunization was
similar among groups randomly assigned to receive one of the following from random donors:<Reference refidx="22"/><ItemizedList id="_200" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Pooled platelet concentrates.</ListItem><ListItem>Filtered, pooled platelet concentrates.</ListItem><ListItem>Ultraviolet B-irradiated, pooled platelet concentrates.</ListItem><ListItem>Filtered platelets obtained by apheresis.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_98">Empiric broad-spectrum antimicrobial therapy is an absolute necessity for
febrile patients who are profoundly neutropenic.<Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/> Careful instruction in
personal hygiene and dental care and in recognizing early signs of infection are
appropriate for all  patients.  Elaborate isolation facilities, including
filtered air, sterile food, and gut flora sterilization, are not routinely
indicated but may benefit patients undergoing transplants.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/> </Para><Para id="_180">Rapid marrow ablation
with consequent earlier marrow regeneration decreases morbidity and mortality. 
White blood cell transfusions can be beneficial in selected patients with
aplastic marrow and serious infections that are not responding to
antibiotics.<Reference refidx="27"/> Prophylactic oral antibiotics may be appropriate in patients
with expected prolonged, profound granulocytopenia (&lt;100/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript> for 2 weeks), although further studies are necessary.<Reference refidx="28"/> Serial surveillance cultures may be helpful in  detecting the presence or acquisition of resistant organisms in these patients.</Para><Para id="_100">As suggested in a CALGB study (CLB-9111), the use of myeloid growth factors during
remission-induction therapy appears to decrease the time to hematopoietic
reconstitution.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_101"><Title>CNS prophylaxis therapy</Title><Para id="_102">The early institution of CNS prophylaxis is critical to achieve control of
sanctuary disease.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_181"><Title>Special Considerations for B-Cell and T-Cell ALL</Title><Para id="_80">Two additional subtypes of ALL require special consideration.  B-cell ALL, which
expresses surface immunoglobulin and cytogenetic abnormalities such as t(8;14),
t(2;8), and t(8;22), is not usually cured with typical ALL regimens. 
Aggressive, brief-duration, high-intensity regimens, including those previously used in <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00002494">CLB-9251</ProtocolRef> (NCT00002494), that are similar to those used in aggressive non-Hodgkin lymphoma have shown high response rates and cure rates
(75% complete response rate; 40% failure-free survival rate).<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/> Similarly,  T-cell ALL,
including lymphoblastic lymphoma,  has shown high cure rates when
treated with cyclophosphamide-containing regimens.<Reference refidx="4"/> </Para><Para id="_182">Whenever possible, patients with B-cell or T-cell ALL should enroll in clinical trials designed to improve the outcomes
in these subsets. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_81_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_81_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18048644">Goldstone AH, Richards SM, Lazarus HM, et al.: In adults with standard-risk acute lymphoblastic leukemia, the greatest benefit is achieved from a matched sibling allogeneic transplantation in first complete remission, and an autologous transplantation is less effective than conventional consolidation/maintenance chemotherapy in all patients: final results of the International ALL Trial (MRC UKALL XII/ECOG E2993). Blood 111 (4): 1827-33, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1321298" MedlineID="92333727">Bortin MM, Horowitz MM, Gale RP, et al.: Changing trends in allogeneic bone marrow transplantation for leukemia in the 1980s. JAMA 268 (5): 607-12, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1586723" MedlineID="92265935">Horowitz MM, Przepiorka D, Champlin RE, et al.: Should HLA-identical sibling bone marrow transplants for leukemia be restricted to large centers? Blood 79 (10): 2771-4, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="7718875" MedlineID="95235024">Larson RA, Dodge RK, Burns CP, et al.: A five-drug remission induction regimen with intensive consolidation for adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: cancer and leukemia group B study 8811. Blood 85 (8): 2025-37, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="1835410" MedlineID="92063004">Linker CA, Levitt LJ, O'Donnell M, et al.: Treatment of adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia with intensive cyclical chemotherapy: a follow-up report. Blood 78 (11): 2814-22, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2665858" MedlineID="89323442">Barrett AJ, Horowitz MM, Gale RP, et al.: Marrow transplantation for acute lymphoblastic leukemia: factors affecting relapse and survival. Blood 74 (2): 862-71, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="6347274" MedlineID="83257783">Dinsmore R, Kirkpatrick D, Flomenberg N, et al.: Allogeneic bone marrow transplantation for patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 62 (2): 381-8, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="6092951" MedlineID="85036490">Jacobs AD, Gale RP: Recent advances in the biology and treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia in adults. N Engl J Med 311 (19): 1219-31, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="3332183" MedlineID="89001434">Doney K, Buckner CD, Kopecky KJ, et al.: Marrow transplantation for patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia in first marrow remission. Bone Marrow Transplant 2 (4): 355-63, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="3276822" MedlineID="88117645">Vernant JP, Marit G, Maraninchi D, et al.: Allogeneic bone marrow transplantation in adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia in first complete remission. J Clin Oncol 6 (2): 227-31, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="3422030" MedlineID="88078354">Hoelzer D, Thiel E, Löffler H, et al.: Prognostic factors in a multicenter study for treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia in adults. Blood 71 (1): 123-31, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="15481055">Kantarjian H, Thomas D, O'Brien S, et al.: Long-term follow-up results of hyperfractionated cyclophosphamide, vincristine, doxorubicin, and dexamethasone (Hyper-CVAD), a dose-intensive regimen, in adult acute lymphocytic leukemia. Cancer 101 (12): 2788-801, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="11287973" MedlineID="21166353">Druker BJ, Sawyers CL, Kantarjian H, et al.: Activity of a specific inhibitor of the BCR-ABL tyrosine kinase in the blast crisis of chronic myeloid leukemia and acute lymphoblastic leukemia with the Philadelphia chromosome. N Engl J Med 344 (14): 1038-42, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="12200353">Ottmann OG, Druker BJ, Sawyers CL, et al.: A phase 2 study of imatinib in patients with relapsed or refractory Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphoid leukemias. Blood 100 (6): 1965-71, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="14551133">Thomas DA, Faderl S, Cortes J, et al.: Treatment of Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphocytic leukemia with hyper-CVAD and imatinib mesylate. Blood 103 (12): 4396-407, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="16344315">Yanada M, Takeuchi J, Sugiura I, et al.: High complete remission rate and promising outcome by combination of imatinib and chemotherapy for newly diagnosed BCR-ABL-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a phase II study by the Japan Adult Leukemia Study Group. J Clin Oncol 24 (3): 460-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="16638934">Wassmann B, Pfeifer H, Goekbuget N, et al.: Alternating versus concurrent schedules of imatinib and chemotherapy as front-line therapy for Philadelphia-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (Ph+ ALL). Blood 108 (5): 1469-77, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="20606084">Bassan R, Rossi G, Pogliani EM, et al.: Chemotherapy-phased imatinib pulses improve long-term outcome of adult patients with Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia: Northern Italy Leukemia Group protocol 09/00. J Clin Oncol 28 (22): 3644-52, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="6994626" MedlineID="80240734">Slichter SJ: Controversies in platelet transfusion therapy. Annu Rev Med 31: 509-40, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="3954967" MedlineID="86159603">Murphy MF, Metcalfe P, Thomas H, et al.: Use of leucocyte-poor blood components and HLA-matched-platelet donors to prevent HLA alloimmunization. Br J Haematol 62 (3): 529-34, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="9407153" MedlineID="98057267">Rebulla P, Finazzi G, Marangoni F, et al.: The threshold for prophylactic platelet transfusions in adults with acute myeloid leukemia. Gruppo Italiano Malattie Ematologiche Maligne dell'Adulto. N Engl J Med 337 (26): 1870-5, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="9417523" MedlineID="98057266">Leukocyte reduction and ultraviolet B irradiation of platelets to prevent alloimmunization and refractoriness to platelet transfusions. The Trial to Reduce Alloimmunization to Platelets Study Group. N Engl J Med 337 (26): 1861-9, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="2179420" MedlineID="90187947">Hughes WT, Armstrong D, Bodey GP, et al.: From the Infectious Diseases Society of America. Guidelines for the use of antimicrobial agents in neutropenic patients with unexplained fever. J Infect Dis 161 (3): 381-96, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="3132310" MedlineID="88241420">Rubin M, Hathorn JW, Pizzo PA: Controversies in the management of febrile neutropenic cancer patients. Cancer Invest 6 (2): 167-84, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="6424468" MedlineID="84176054">Armstrong D: Symposium on infectious complications of neoplastic disease (Part II). Protected environments are discomforting and expensive and do not offer meaningful protection. Am J Med 76 (4): 685-9, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="3314494" MedlineID="88046838">Sherertz RJ, Belani A, Kramer BS, et al.: Impact of air filtration on nosocomial Aspergillus infections. Unique risk of bone marrow transplant recipients. Am J Med 83 (4): 709-18, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="2134613" MedlineID="92200070">Schiffer CA: Granulocyte transfusions: an overlooked therapeutic modality. Transfus Med Rev 4 (1): 2-7, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="6782486" MedlineID="81148760">Wade JC, Schimpff SC, Hargadon MT, et al.: A comparison of trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole plus nystatin with gentamicin plus nystatin in the prevention of infections in acute leukemia. N Engl J Med 304 (18): 1057-62, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="7686404" MedlineID="93305771">Scherrer R, Geissler K, Kyrle PA, et al.: Granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) as an adjunct to induction chemotherapy of adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL). Ann Hematol 66 (6): 283-9, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="9716583" MedlineID="98384218">Larson RA, Dodge RK, Linker CA, et al.: A randomized controlled trial of filgrastim during remission induction and consolidation chemotherapy for adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: CALGB study 9111. Blood 92 (5): 1556-64, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="8555471" MedlineID="96141069">Hoelzer D, Ludwig WD, Thiel E, et al.: Improved outcome in adult B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 87 (2): 495-508, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="11600602" MedlineID="21486642">Lee EJ, Petroni GR, Schiffer CA, et al.: Brief-duration high-intensity chemotherapy for patients with small noncleaved-cell lymphoma or FAB L3 acute lymphocytic leukemia: results of cancer and leukemia group B study 9251. J Clin Oncol 19 (20): 4014-22, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="10561310" MedlineID="20030039">Thomas DA, Cortes J, O'Brien S, et al.: Hyper-CVAD program in Burkitt's-type adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia. J Clin Oncol 17 (8): 2461-70, 1999.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039084">adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia in remission</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of ALL in Remission</Title><SummarySection id="_107"><Title>Treatment Options for ALL in Remission</Title><Para id="_108">Treatment options for acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) in remission include:</Para><OrderedList id="_109" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_111" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Consolidation therapy</SummaryRef>, including: <ItemizedList id="_209" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>	Ongoing treatment with a BCR::ABL1 tyrosine kinase inhibitor,  such as imatinib, nilotinib, or dasatinib.</ListItem><ListItem>Autologous or allogeneic bone marrow transplant (BMT).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_130" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Central nervous system (CNS) prophylaxis therapy</SummaryRef>, including:<ItemizedList id="_210" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Cranial radiation therapy plus intrathecal (IT) methotrexate.</ListItem><ListItem>High-dose systemic methotrexate and IT methotrexate without cranial  
radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>IT chemotherapy alone.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_111"><Title>Consolidation therapy</Title><Para id="_112">Current approaches to consolidation therapy for ALL include short-term, relatively intensive chemotherapy followed by:</Para><ItemizedList id="_113" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Longer-term therapy at lower doses (maintenance therapy).</ListItem><ListItem>Allogeneic BMT.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_134">Because the optimal consolidation therapy for patients with ALL is still
unclear, patients should consider participating in clinical trials.  For more information, see the
<SummaryRef href="CDR0000816140#_1925" url="/types/lymphoma/hp/aggressive-b-cell-lymphoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Diffuse Small Noncleaved-Cell/Burkitt Lymphoma</SummaryRef> section in Aggressive B-Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma
Treatment.
</Para><Para id="_114">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_116" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Several
trials, including studies from the Cancer and Leukemia Group B (CLB-8811) and the completed European Cooperative Oncology Group (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00002514">ECOG-2993</ProtocolRef> [NCT00002514]), of aggressive consolidation chemotherapy for ALL have confirmed a
long-term disease-free survival (DFS) rate of approximately 40%.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>   <ItemizedList id="_201" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In 
two series,<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> especially good prognoses were found for patients with T-cell lineage
ALL, with DFS rates of 50% to 70% for patients receiving
consolidation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>These series represent a significant improvement in
DFS rates over previous, less intensive chemotherapeutic
approaches.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In contrast, poor cure rates were demonstrated in patients with
Philadelphia chromosome (Ph)–positive ALL, B-cell lineage ALL with an L3
phenotype (surface immunoglobulin positive), and B-cell lineage ALL
characterized by t(4;11). </ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_202">Administration of the newer dose-intensive schedules can be difficult and should be performed by physicians experienced in   these regimens at centers equipped to deal with potential complications. In studies that eliminated continuation or maintenance chemotherapy, patients had outcomes
inferior to those of patients in studies with extended treatment durations.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> Imatinib has been incorporated into maintenance regimens in patients with Ph-positive ALL.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/>  <Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_119">Evidence (allogeneic and  autologous BMT):</Para><Para id="_203">Allogeneic BMT results in the lowest incidence of leukemic relapse, even when compared
with a BMT from an identical twin (syngeneic BMT).  This
finding has led to the concept of an immunologic graft-versus-leukemia effect
similar to graft-versus-host disease (GVHD). The improvement in DFS in patients undergoing allogeneic  BMT as primary consolidation therapy is
offset, in part, by the increased morbidity and mortality from GVHD,
veno-occlusive disease of the liver, and interstitial pneumonitis.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><OrderedList id="_120" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The results of a series of retrospective and prospective studies published between 1987 and 1994 suggest that allogeneic  BMT or autologous BMT as consolidation therapy offer no survival advantage over intensive chemotherapy, except perhaps for patients with high-risk or Ph-positive ALL.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/> This was confirmed in the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01505699">ECOG-2993</ProtocolRef> study (NCT01505699).<Reference refidx="7"/><ItemizedList id="_211" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The use of allogeneic BMT as primary consolidation therapy is limited by both the need for an HLA-matched sibling donor and the increased mortality from allogeneic  BMT in patients in their fifth or sixth decade.</ListItem><ListItem>The mortality from allogeneic  BMT using an HLA-matched sibling donor in these studies ranged from 20% to 40%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Following on the results of  earlier  studies, the International ALL Trial (ECOG-2993) was launched to examine the role of transplant as consolidation therapy for ALL more definitively. Patients were accrued from 1993 to 2006.<Reference refidx="7"/> Patients with Ph-negative ALL between the ages of 15 years and 59 years received identical multiagent induction therapy resembling previously published regimens.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  Patients in remission were then eligible for HLA typing; patients with a fully matched sibling donor underwent allogeneic  BMT as consolidation therapy.  Patients without a donor were randomly assigned to receive either an autologous BMT or maintenance chemotherapy.  The primary outcome measured was overall survival (OS). Event-free survival, relapse rate, and nonrelapse mortality were secondary outcomes. A total of 1,929 patients were registered and stratified according to age, white blood cell (WBC) count, and time to remission. High-risk patients were defined as those having a high WBC count at presentation or those older than 35 years.<OrderedList id="_122" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>Ninety percent of patients in this study achieved remission after induction therapy.  Of these patients, 443 had  an HLA-identical sibling, 310 of whom underwent an allogeneic BMT.   For the 456 patients in remission who were eligible for transplant but lacked a donor, 227 received chemotherapy alone, while 229 underwent an autologous BMT.</ListItem><ListItem>  By donor-to-no-donor analysis, standard-risk ALL patients with an HLA-identical sibling had a 5-year OS rate of 53%, compared with 45% for patients lacking a donor (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01).  </ListItem><ListItem>In a subgroup analysis, the advantage for patients with  standard-risk ALL who had donors remained significant  (OS rate, 62% vs. 52%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).  <ItemizedList id="_212" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For patients with high-risk disease (older than 35 years or high WBC count), the difference in OS was 41% versus 35% (donor vs. no donor) but was not significant (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .2).</ListItem><ListItem>Relapse rates were significantly lower (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .00005) for both standard- and high-risk patients with HLA-matched donors.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In contrast to allogeneic BMT, autologous BMT was less effective than maintenance chemotherapy as consolidation treatment (5-year OS rate, 46% for chemotherapy vs. 37% for autologous BMT; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03).</ListItem><ListItem>The results of this trial suggest the existence of a graft-versus-leukemia effect for adult Ph-negative ALL and support the use of sibling donor allogeneic BMT as the consolidation therapy providing the greatest chance for long-term survival for patients with standard-risk adult ALL in first remission.<Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The results also suggest that in the absence of a sibling donor, maintenance chemotherapy is preferable to autologous BMT as consolidation therapy.<Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]</ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_125">The use of matched unrelated donors for allogeneic BMT is
currently under evaluation. However, because of its current high treatment-related
morbidity and mortality, allogeneic BMT is reserved for patients in second remission or
beyond. The dose of total-body radiation therapy administered is associated with the
incidence of acute and chronic GVHD and may be an independent predictor of
leukemia-free survival.<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]
   </Para><Para id="_127">Evidence (B-cell ALL):</Para><Para id="_204">Aggressive cyclophosphamide-based regimens similar to those used in aggressive
non-Hodgkin lymphoma have shown improved outcome of prolonged DFS for patients with B-cell ALL (L3 morphology, surface immunoglobulin
positive).<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><OrderedList id="_128" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>One group of investigators retrospectively reviewed three sequential cooperative group trials
from Germany and found the following results:<Reference refidx="19"/><ItemizedList id="_213" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A marked improvement in survival,
from zero survivors in a 1981 study that used standard pediatric therapy and
lasted 2.5 years, to a 50% survival rate in two subsequent trials that used
rapidly alternating lymphoma-like chemotherapy and were completed within 6
months.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_130"><Title>CNS prophylaxis therapy</Title><Para id="_131">The early institution of CNS prophylaxis is critical to achieve control of
sanctuary disease.  Some authors have suggested that there is a subgroup of
patients at low risk of CNS relapse for whom CNS prophylaxis may not be
necessary.  However, this concept has not been tested prospectively.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_132">Aggressive CNS prophylaxis remains a prominent component of treatment.<Reference refidx="19"/> 
This report, which requires confirmation in other cooperative group settings,
is encouraging for patients with L3 ALL.  Patients with surface immunoglobulin
and  L1 or L2 morphology did not benefit from this regimen.  Similarly, patients
with L3 morphology and immunophenotype, but unusual cytogenetic features, were
not cured with this approach.  A WBC count of less than 50,000 per
microliter predicted improved leukemia-free survival in a univariate analysis.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_106_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_106_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3163722" MedlineID="88229801">Gaynor J, Chapman D, Little C, et al.: A cause-specific hazard rate analysis of prognostic factors among 199 adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: the Memorial Hospital experience since 1969. J Clin Oncol 6 (6): 1014-30, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="3422030" MedlineID="88078354">Hoelzer D, Thiel E, Löffler H, et al.: Prognostic factors in a multicenter study for treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia in adults. Blood 71 (1): 123-31, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1835410" MedlineID="92063004">Linker CA, Levitt LJ, O'Donnell M, et al.: Treatment of adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia with intensive cyclical chemotherapy: a follow-up report. Blood 78 (11): 2814-22, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="7639442" MedlineID="95366679">Zhang MJ, Hoelzer D, Horowitz MM, et al.: Long-term follow-up of adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia in first remission treated with chemotherapy or bone marrow transplantation. The Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Working Committee. Ann Intern Med 123 (6): 428-31, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7718875" MedlineID="95235024">Larson RA, Dodge RK, Burns CP, et al.: A five-drug remission induction regimen with intensive consolidation for adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: cancer and leukemia group B study 8811. Blood 85 (8): 2025-37, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15481055">Kantarjian H, Thomas D, O'Brien S, et al.: Long-term follow-up results of hyperfractionated cyclophosphamide, vincristine, doxorubicin, and dexamethasone (Hyper-CVAD), a dose-intensive regimen, in adult acute lymphocytic leukemia. Cancer 101 (12): 2788-801, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="18048644">Goldstone AH, Richards SM, Lazarus HM, et al.: In adults with standard-risk acute lymphoblastic leukemia, the greatest benefit is achieved from a matched sibling allogeneic transplantation in first complete remission, and an autologous transplantation is less effective than conventional consolidation/maintenance chemotherapy in all patients: final results of the International ALL Trial (MRC UKALL XII/ECOG E2993). Blood 111 (4): 1827-33, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="2033963" MedlineID="91238226">Cuttner J, Mick R, Budman DR, et al.: Phase III trial of brief intensive treatment of adult acute lymphocytic leukemia comparing daunorubicin and mitoxantrone: a CALGB Study. Leukemia 5 (5): 425-31, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9053468" MedlineID="97178735">Dekker AW, van't Veer MB, Sizoo W, et al.: Intensive postremission chemotherapy without maintenance therapy in adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Dutch Hemato-Oncology Research Group. J Clin Oncol 15 (2): 476-82, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="14551133">Thomas DA, Faderl S, Cortes J, et al.: Treatment of Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphocytic leukemia with hyper-CVAD and imatinib mesylate. Blood 103 (12): 4396-407, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="16344315">Yanada M, Takeuchi J, Sugiura I, et al.: High complete remission rate and promising outcome by combination of imatinib and chemotherapy for newly diagnosed BCR-ABL-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a phase II study by the Japan Adult Leukemia Study Group. J Clin Oncol 24 (3): 460-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="16638934">Wassmann B, Pfeifer H, Goekbuget N, et al.: Alternating versus concurrent schedules of imatinib and chemotherapy as front-line therapy for Philadelphia-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (Ph+ ALL). Blood 108 (5): 1469-77, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="10073558" MedlineID="99171566">Finiewicz KJ, Larson RA: Dose-intensive therapy for adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Semin Oncol 26 (1): 6-20, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="2048858" MedlineID="91264418">Horowitz MM, Messerer D, Hoelzer D, et al.: Chemotherapy compared with bone marrow transplantation for adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia in first remission. Ann Intern Med 115 (1): 13-8, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="7989932" MedlineID="95081796">Sebban C, Lepage E, Vernant JP, et al.: Allogeneic bone marrow transplantation in adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia in first complete remission: a comparative study. French Group of Therapy of Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia. J Clin Oncol 12 (12): 2580-7, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="3300815" MedlineID="87272081">Forman SJ, O'Donnell MR, Nademanee AP, et al.: Bone marrow transplantation for patients with Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 70 (2): 587-8, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="8410124" MedlineID="94015220">Fière D, Lepage E, Sebban C, et al.: Adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a multicentric randomized trial testing bone marrow transplantation as postremission therapy. The French Group on Therapy for Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia. J Clin Oncol 11 (10): 1990-2001, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="10078628" MedlineID="99176514">Corvò R, Paoli G, Barra S, et al.: Total body irradiation correlates with chronic graft versus host disease and affects prognosis of patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia receiving an HLA identical allogeneic bone marrow transplant. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 43 (3): 497-503, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="8555471" MedlineID="96141069">Hoelzer D, Ludwig WD, Thiel E, et al.: Improved outcome in adult B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 87 (2): 495-508, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="3052630" MedlineID="89027115">Kantarjian HM, Walters RS, Smith TL, et al.: Identification of risk groups for development of central nervous system leukemia in adults with acute lymphocytic leukemia. Blood 72 (5): 1784-9, 1988.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_135"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038716">recurrent adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent ALL</Title><SummarySection id="_136"><Title>Treatment Options for Recurrent ALL</Title><Para id="_137">Treatment options for recurrent acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) include:</Para><OrderedList id="_138" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_139" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Reinduction chemotherapy </SummaryRef> followed by allogeneic bone marrow transplant (BMT).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_279" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Blinatumomab</SummaryRef> followed by allogeneic BMT.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_271" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Inotuzumab ozogamicin</SummaryRef> followed by allogeneic BMT.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_141" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Palliative radiation therapy</SummaryRef> (for patients with symptomatic recurrence).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_143" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Dasatinib</SummaryRef> (for patients with Philadelphia chromosome [Ph]–positive ALL).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_362" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Revumenib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients who do not have an HLA-matched donor are excellent candidates for enrollment in clinical trials that are
studying:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><ItemizedList id="_361" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Autologous transplant.</ListItem><ListItem>Immunomodulation.</ListItem><ListItem>Chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T-cell therapy.<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem>Novel
chemotherapeutic or biological agents.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_139"><Title>Reinduction chemotherapy followed by allogeneic BMT</Title><Para id="_140">Patients with ALL who experience a relapse after chemotherapy and maintenance
therapy are unlikely to be cured by further chemotherapy alone.  These patients
should be considered for reinduction chemotherapy followed by  allogeneic BMT.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_279"><Title>Blinatumomab followed by allogeneic BMT</Title><Para id="_280">Blinatumomab is a bispecific antibody targeting CD19 and CD3. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved blinatumomab for use in patients with relapsed or refractory B-cell ALL. </Para><Para id="_281">Evidence (blinatumomab):</Para><OrderedList id="_282" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A randomized phase III study of blinatumomab versus one of four standard reinduction regimens was conducted in patients with primary refractory disease,  which was refractory to salvage, with a first relapse lasting fewer than 12 months, a second or greater relapse, or any relapse after allogeneic transplant.<Reference refidx="9"/> The four regimens included the following: fludarabine, high-dose cytosine arabinoside, and
granulocyte colony-stimulating factor with or without
anthracycline; a high-dose cytosine arabinoside–based regimen; a high-dose methotrexate-based regimen; or a clofarabine-based regimen. <ItemizedList id="_283" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Remission rates  were 43.9% for the blinatumomab-treated group versus 24.6% in the standard-treatment group (odds ratio, 2.40; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.51–3.80).  </ListItem><ListItem>Overall survival (OS) was superior in the blinatumomab-treated group (7.7 months vs. 4.0 months in the standard-treatment group), with a hazard ratio (HR) of .71 (95% CI, 0.55–0.93), favoring blinatumomab.  </ListItem><ListItem>Adverse events occurred at similar rates in both groups, and  the only unique side effect of blinatumomab was cytokine-release syndrome, which was seen in 4.9% of patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_284">Blinatumomab should be considered as an option for reinduction therapy for patients with primary refractory disease, which is refractory to salvage, with a first relapse lasting fewer than 12 months, a second or greater relapse, or any relapse after allogeneic transplant.<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_271"><Title>Inotuzumab ozogamicin followed by allogeneic BMT</Title><Para id="_272">Inotuzumab ozogamicin is an antibody-drug conjugate targeting CD22, which contains a conjugated toxin, calicheamicin. The FDA has approved inotuzumab ozogamicin for use in patients with relapsed or refractory B-cell ALL with CD22 expression. </Para><Para id="_273">Evidence (inotuzumab ozogamicin):</Para><OrderedList id="_274" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	A randomized phase III study compared inotuzumab ozogamicin with one of three standard reinduction regimens. The trial enrolled 218 patients, aged 18 years or older, who had relapsed or refractory disease and  were to receive their first or second salvage regimen.<Reference refidx="10"/> The three standard regimens consisted of fludarabine, cytarabine, and granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (FLAG), cytarabine and mitoxantrone, or high-dose cytarabine.   <ItemizedList id="_275" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Complete remission or complete remission with incomplete count recovery rates were 80.7% (95% CI, 72.1%–87.7%) in the inotuzumab group versus 29.4% (95% CI, 21.0%–38.8%) in the standard-treatment group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).</ListItem><ListItem>	Progression-free survival was superior in the inotuzumab-treated group (5.0 months vs. 1.8 months in the standard-treatment group) with an HR of 0.45 (97.5 CI, 0.34–0.61; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).  </ListItem><ListItem>Duration of remission was short in both groups; duration in the inotuzumab group was 4.6 months (95% CI, 3.9–5.4) and duration in the standard chemotherapy group was 3.1 months (95% CI, 1.4–4.9). </ListItem><ListItem> Of the 48 patients in the inotuzumab arm who proceeded to transplant after therapy, 10 developed veno-occlusive disease. Of the 20 patients who proceeded to transplant after remission on the standard chemotherapy arm, 1 developed veno-occlusive disease.</ListItem><ListItem>	OS was not statistically prolonged in the inotuzumab group (7.7 months in the  inotuzumab group vs. 6.7 months in the standard-treatment group) (HR, 0.77; 97.5% CI, 0.58–1.03; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .04) because of a failure to meet a study-prespecified boundary of <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0208.</ListItem><ListItem>	Grade 3 or higher adverse events were more common in the inotuzumab group.  Veno-occlusive disease of the liver occurred in 11% of patients in the inotuzumab group and 1% of patients in the standard-treatment group. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_276">Inotuzumab ozogamicin may be an option for reinduction for patients with relapsed or refractory CD22-positive ALL.<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_141"><Title>Palliative radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_142">Low-dose palliative radiation
therapy may be considered in patients with symptomatic recurrence either within
or outside the central nervous system.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_143"><Title>Dasatinib</Title><Para id="_144">Patients with Ph-positive ALL are often taking imatinib at the time of relapse and thus have imatinib-resistant disease.  Dasatinib is a novel tyrosine kinase inhibitor with efficacy against several different imatinib-resistant <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> fusion gene  variants. Dasatinib has been approved for use in  patients with Ph-positive ALL who are resistant to, or intolerant of, imatinib. The approval was based on a series of trials involving patients with chronic myeloid leukemia, one of which included small numbers of patients with lymphoid blast crisis or Ph-positive ALL.</Para><Para id="_145">Evidence (dasatinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_146" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In one study, ten  patients were treated with dose-escalated dasatinib.<Reference refidx="12"/> Seven of these patients had a complete hematologic response (&lt;5% marrow blasts with normal peripheral blood cell counts), three of whom had a complete cytogenetic response.<ItemizedList id="_205" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The common toxicities were reversible myelosuppression (89%) and pleural effusions (21%).</ListItem><ListItem>Virtually all of these patients relapsed within 6 months of the start of treatment with dasatinib.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_362"><Title>Revumenib</Title><Para id="_363">Revumenib is an oral menin inhibitor that is approved by the FDA for the treatment of relapsed or refractory acute leukemia with a <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> translocation in adult and pediatric patients aged 1 year and older.</Para><OrderedList id="_364" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>In the phase I/II <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04065399">AUGMENT-101</ProtocolRef> study (NCT04065399), 104 patients with relapsed or refractory acute leukemia with a <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> rearrangement received revumenib. 	Patients had to have a corrected QT interval (QTc) using Fridericia's formula of less than 450 milliseconds at baseline.<Reference refidx="13"/><ItemizedList id="_365" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>	The overall rate of complete remission (CR) plus CRh (complete remission with partial hematologic recovery) was 21.2% (95% CI, 13.8%–30.3%). The median duration of CR plus CRh was 6.4 months (95% CI, 2.7–not reached).<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>	Of the 83 patients who were dependent on red blood cell and/or platelet transfusions, 14% became independent of transfusions during a 56-day postbaseline period. </ListItem><ListItem>	Revumenib has a <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2024/218944s000lbl.pdf">boxed warning</ExternalRef> for differentiation syndrome, which was observed in 29% of patients. Grade 3 or 4 differentiation syndrome was observed in 13% of patients, and one patient died (0.7%). </ListItem><ListItem>	Grade 3 or higher QTc prolongation was observed in 12% of patients. </ListItem><ListItem>Because revumenib is metabolized by CYP3A4, the dose must be reduced in patients receiving strong CYP3A4 inhibitors. The standard dose for patients who weigh more than 40 kg is 270 mg orally twice daily, with a dose reduction to 160 mg orally twice daily for patients receiving a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor. Furthermore, the dose is adjusted according to body surface area in patients who weigh less than 40 kg.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_135_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_135_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2882192" MedlineID="87171766">Herzig RH, Bortin MM, Barrett AJ, et al.: Bone-marrow transplantation in high-risk acute lymphoblastic leukaemia in first and second remission. Lancet 1 (8536): 786-9, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="6354306" MedlineID="84025045">Thomas ED, Sanders JE, Flournoy N, et al.: Marrow transplantation for patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a long-term follow-up. Blood 62 (5): 1139-41, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2665858" MedlineID="89323442">Barrett AJ, Horowitz MM, Gale RP, et al.: Marrow transplantation for acute lymphoblastic leukemia: factors affecting relapse and survival. Blood 74 (2): 862-71, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6347274" MedlineID="83257783">Dinsmore R, Kirkpatrick D, Flomenberg N, et al.: Allogeneic bone marrow transplantation for patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 62 (2): 381-8, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2809677" MedlineID="90039438">Sallan SE, Niemeyer CM, Billett AL, et al.: Autologous bone marrow transplantation for acute lymphoblastic leukemia. J Clin Oncol 7 (11): 1594-601, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="3476201" MedlineID="87301481">Paciucci PA, Keaveney C, Cuttner J, et al.: Mitoxantrone, vincristine, and prednisone in adults with relapsed or primarily refractory acute lymphocytic leukemia and terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase positive blastic phase chronic myelocytic leukemia. Cancer Res 47 (19): 5234-7, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="1498326" MedlineID="92360858">Biggs JC, Horowitz MM, Gale RP, et al.: Bone marrow transplants may cure patients with acute leukemia never achieving remission with chemotherapy. Blood 80 (4): 1090-3, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25317870">Maude SL, Frey N, Shaw PA, et al.: Chimeric antigen receptor T cells for sustained remissions in leukemia. N Engl J Med 371 (16): 1507-17, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="28249141">Kantarjian H, Stein A, Gökbuget N, et al.: Blinatumomab versus Chemotherapy for Advanced Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia. N Engl J Med 376 (9): 836-847, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="27292104">Kantarjian HM, DeAngelo DJ, Stelljes M, et al.: Inotuzumab Ozogamicin versus Standard Therapy for Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia. N Engl J Med 375 (8): 740-53, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2394621" MedlineID="90368431">Gray JR, Wallner KE: Reversal of cranial nerve dysfunction with radiation therapy in adults with lymphoma and leukemia. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 19 (2): 439-44, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="16775234">Talpaz M, Shah NP, Kantarjian H, et al.: Dasatinib in imatinib-resistant Philadelphia chromosome-positive leukemias. N Engl J Med 354 (24): 2531-41, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="39121437">Issa GC, Aldoss I, Thirman MJ, et al.: Menin Inhibition With Revumenib for KMT2A-Rearranged Relapsed or Refractory Acute Leukemia (AUGMENT-101). J Clin Oncol 43 (1): 75-84, 2025.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_151"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (03/17/2025)</Title><Para id="_197">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_366"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_69" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview for Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL)</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_367">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_167" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>, Treatment Options for Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL), to include revumenib as a treatment option for recurrent ALL.</Para><Para id="_368"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_135" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Recurrent ALL</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_370">Revised the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_137" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">list</SummaryRef> of treatment options for recurrent ALL to include revumenib.</Para><Para id="_369">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_362" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">Revumenib</SummaryRef> as a new subsection.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062864#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewer for Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Treatment is:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Aaron Gerds, MD (Cleveland Clinic Taussig Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/adult-all-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389171]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-03-17</DateLastModified></Summary>
