<Summary id="CDR0000062866" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Plasma cell neoplasms (including multiple myeloma) treatment include observation, chemotherapy, radiation, stem cell rescue, targeted, and supportive therapies. Corticosteroids and immunomodulatory drugs may be used. Get detailed treatment information in this summary for clinicians.  </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Plasma Cell Neoplasms (including Multiple Myeloma)  (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/myeloma/patient/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Plasma Cell Neoplasms (including Multiple Myeloma)  (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037974">multiple myeloma and other plasma cell neoplasms</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_508">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about treatment of plasma cell neoplasms (including multiple myeloma). It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_509">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>multiple myeloma and other plasma cell neoplasms</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Plasma Cell Neoplasms (Including Multiple Myeloma) Treatment  (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Plasma Cell Neoplasms  (Including Multiple Myeloma) Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Plasma Cell Neoplasms  (Including Multiple Myeloma) Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037974">multiple myeloma and other plasma cell neoplasms</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Plasma Cell Neoplasms</Title><Para id="_3">There are several types of plasma cell neoplasms. These diseases are all associated with a monoclonal (or myeloma) protein (M protein). They include monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS), isolated plasmacytoma of the bone, extramedullary plasmacytoma, and multiple myeloma.</Para><Para id="_1337">For information about immunoglobulin (Ig) M monoclonal antibody–associated lymphoma, see the   <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811546#_28" url="/types/lymphoma/hp/indolent-b-cell-lymphoma-treatment-pdq">Lymphoplasmacytic Lymphoma (Waldenström Macroglobulinemia)</SummaryRef> section in Indolent B-Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment.</Para><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_5">Estimated new cases and deaths from multiple myeloma in the United States in 2025:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_230" Style="bullet"><ListItem>New cases: 36,110.</ListItem><ListItem>Deaths:  12,030.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>Clinical Presentation and Evaluation</Title><Table id="_8"><Title>Table 1.  Clinical Presentation of Plasma Cell Neoplasms</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Plasma Cell Neoplasm</entry><entry Align="Center">M Protein Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Pathology</entry><entry Align="Center">Clinical Presentation</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">Ig = immunoglobulin; MGUS = monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance. </entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>MGUS</entry><entry>IgG kappa or lambda; 

or

IgA kappa or lambda
</entry><entry>&lt;10% plasma cells in bone marrow</entry><entry>Asymptomatic, with minimal evidence of disease (aside from the presence of an M protein) <Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Isolated plasmacytoma of bone</entry><entry>IgG kappa or lambda; or

IgA kappa or gamma
</entry><entry>Solitary lesion of bone; &lt;10% plasma cells in marrow of uninvolved site</entry><entry>Asymptomatic or symptomatic </entry></Row><Row><entry>Extramedullary plasmacytoma</entry><entry>IgG kappa or lambda; 

or

IgA kappa or gamma</entry><entry>Solitary lesion of soft tissue; most commonly occurs in the nasopharynx, tonsils,  or paranasal sinuses <Reference refidx="3"/></entry><entry>Asymptomatic or symptomatic</entry></Row><Row><entry>Multiple myeloma</entry><entry>IgG kappa or lambda; or IgA kappa or gamma</entry><entry>Often, multiple lesions of bone</entry><entry>Symptomatic</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Evaluation of patients with monoclonal (or myeloma) protein (M protein)</Title><Para id="_10">Idiotypic myeloma cells can be found in the blood of patients with myeloma in all
stages of the disease.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> For this reason, when treatment is indicated,
systemic treatment must be considered for all patients with symptomatic
plasma cell neoplasms.  Patients with MGUS or asymptomatic smoldering myeloma do not require
immediate treatment but must be followed carefully for signs of disease
progression.
</Para><Para id="_231">The major challenge is
to separate the stable asymptomatic group of patients who do not require
treatment from patients with progressive, symptomatic myeloma who  may need to be
treated immediately.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_11">Patients with an M protein in the serum and/or urine are evaluated by some of the following criteria:
</Para><ItemizedList id="_232" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Measure and follow the serum M protein by serum electrophoresis or by specific Ig assays; however, specific Ig quantification always overestimates the M protein because normal
Ig are included in the result.  For this reason, the preference is often that  baseline and
follow-up measurements of the M protein  be done by the same method.<Reference refidx="9"/>
Quantitative serum free light chains (FLC) may be helpful to follow response when an M protein is not apparent.</ListItem><ListItem>Measure and follow the amount of M protein light chains excreted in the
urine over 24 hours.  Measure the total amount of protein excreted over 24
hours and multiply this value by the percentage of urine protein that is
M protein, as determined by electrophoresis of concentrated urine protein. An easier, but less accurate, method uses a spot-urine protein electrophoresis.</ListItem><ListItem>Identify the heavy and light chain of the M protein by immunofixation electrophoresis.</ListItem><ListItem>Measure the hemoglobin, leukocyte, platelet, and differential counts.</ListItem><ListItem>Determine the percentage of marrow plasma cells.  Be aware that marrow plasma-cell distribution may vary in different sites. Bone marrow is often   sent for cytogenetics and fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization testing for genetic markers of high-risk disease.  For more information, see the  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_53" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Genetic factors and risk groups</SummaryRef> section.</ListItem><ListItem>Measure serum free kappa and lambda light chains. This is especially useful in cases of oligosecretory plasma-cell dyscrasia or for following cases of light-chain amyloidosis.<Reference refidx="10"/> The FLC ratio  of over 100 can predict a greater than  70% progression within 2 years in patients with smoldering myeloma.<Reference refidx="11"/> </ListItem><ListItem>If clinically warranted, obtain needle aspirates of a solitary lytic bone lesion, extramedullary
tumor(s), or enlarged lymph node(s) to determine whether these are
plasmacytomas.</ListItem><ListItem>Evaluate renal function with serum creatinine and a creatinine clearance.</ListItem><ListItem>Electrophoresis of concentrated urine protein is very helpful in
differentiating glomerular lesions from tubular lesions.  Glomerular lesions,
such as those resulting from glomerular deposits of amyloid or light-chain
deposition disease, result in the nonselective leakage of all serum proteins
into the urine; the electrophoresis pattern of this urine resembles the serum
pattern with a preponderance of albumin.<Para id="_233">In most patients with myeloma, the glomeruli function normally allows only the small molecular weight proteins, such as light chains, to
filter into the urine.  The concentration of protein in the tubules increases
as water is reabsorbed.  This leads to precipitation of proteins and the
formation of tubular casts, which may injure the tubular cells.  With tubular
lesions, the typical electrophoresis pattern shows a small albumin peak and a
larger light-chain peak in the globulin region; this tubular pattern is the
usual pattern found in patients with myeloma.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>Measure serum levels of calcium, alkaline phosphatase, lactic
dehydrogenase, and, when indicated by clinical symptoms, cryoglobulins and
serum viscosity.</ListItem><ListItem>Obtain radiographs of the skull, ribs, vertebrae, pelvis, shoulder girdle,
and long bones.
</ListItem><ListItem>Obtain a spinal magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan (or spinal computed tomography [CT] or positron emission tomography [PET]–CT scan depending on availability) if the skeletal survey is negative.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> At diagnosis, whole-body  PET scan or MRI of the total spine and pelvis appears to be equally efficacious in the detection of bone lesions.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem><ListItem>If amyloidosis is suspected, perform a needle aspiration of subcutaneous
abdominal fat and stain the bone marrow biopsy for amyloid as the easiest and
safest way to confirm the diagnosis.<Reference refidx="17"/></ListItem><ListItem>Measure serum albumin and beta-2-microglobulin as independent
prognostic factors.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem><ListItem>The presence of circulating myeloma cells is considered a poor prognostic
factor.<Reference refidx="20"/> Primary plasma cell leukemia has a particularly poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_14">These initial studies are often compared with subsequent values at a later
time, when it is necessary to decide whether the disease is stable or
progressive, responding to treatment, or getting worse.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Monoclonal Gammopathy of Undetermined Significance (MGUS)</Title><Para id="_17">Patients with MGUS have an M protein in the serum without findings of multiple
myeloma, macroglobulinemia, amyloidosis, or lymphoma and have fewer than 10%
 of plasma cells in the bone marrow.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/> Patients with smoldering myeloma have similar characteristics but may have more  than  10% of plasma cells in the bone marrow.  </Para><Para id="_18">These types of patients are asymptomatic and do  not need to be treated.  However, patients with MGUS and risk factors for disease progression must be followed carefully because they are more likely to develop myeloma (most commonly), amyloidosis, lymphoplasmacytic lymphoma, or chronic lymphocytic leukemia. These patients may
then require therapy.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_19">Virtually all cases of multiple myeloma are preceded by a gradually rising level of MGUS.<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/> The annual risk of progression of MGUS to a lymphoid or plasma cell malignancy ranges from 0.5% to 1.0% in population-based cohorts.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/> This risk ranges from 2% to more than 20% in higher-risk patients.</Para><Para id="_20">The following risk factors predict disease progression:</Para><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet"><ListItem>An abnormal serum FLC ratio.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="33"/></ListItem><ListItem>Non-IgG class MGUS.</ListItem><ListItem>A high level of serum M protein (≥1.5 g/dL).<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="33"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_449">	A Swedish cohort study confirmed that an abnormal serum FLC ratio and a high level of serum monoclonal protein are high-risk factors.<Reference refidx="32"/> The study described the additional risk factor of immunoparesis, which is defined as the reciprocal depression of the other Ig classes (i.e., if a patient has an IgG kappa M protein, the IgM and IgA would be below normal levels with immunoparesis). Incorporation of gene-expression profiles to better assess risk is under clinical evaluation.<Reference refidx="34"/> </Para><Para id="_450">Monoclonal gammopathies that cause organ damage, particularly to the kidney, heart, or peripheral nerves, require immediate therapy with the same strategies applied for the conventional plasma-cell dyscrasias.<Reference refidx="35"/> A monoclonal gammopathy causing renal dysfunction—by direct antibody deposition or amyloidosis—is referred to as monoclonal gammopathy of renal significance.<Reference refidx="36"/> Rising serum creatinine, dropping glomerular filtration rates, and increasing urinary–albumin excretion are all parameters that may signify renal damage and are assessed prospectively for high-risk MGUS patients. Although the N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide is a very sensitive marker for amyloid involvement in the heart, the low specificity must be noted. These extra tests are included with the M-protein level, FLC levels, and FLC  ratio when following patients with MGUS.<Reference refidx="37"/> </Para><Para id="_663">In a retrospective review of 6,399 patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma, 44 patients were found to have a biclonal IgG or IgA MGUS. The overall response rate of the myeloma clone to induction therapy was 93%, compared with 64% for the separate-clone MGUS (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001).<Reference refidx="38"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] Many MGUS plasma cell clones were unresponsive to available myeloma therapy; this result highlights the need to lower expectations for response in situations in which an MGUS may require therapy because of end-organ damage.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Isolated Plasmacytoma of Bone</Title><Para id="_32">The patient has an isolated plasmacytoma of the bone if the following are found:</Para><ItemizedList id="_33" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A solitary lytic lesion of plasma cells on skeletal survey in an
otherwise asymptomatic patient.</ListItem><ListItem>A bone marrow examination from an uninvolved
site contains less than  10% plasma cells.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/> The absence of plasma cells on flow cytometry of the bone marrow suggests a low (&lt;10%) risk of recurrence after radiation therapy of the isolated bone plasmacytoma.<Reference refidx="42"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_34">MRI  may reveal
unsuspected bony lesions that were undetected on standard radiographs.  MRI scans of the
total spine and pelvis may identify other bony lesions.<Reference refidx="43"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Extramedullary Plasmacytoma</Title><Para id="_36">A patient has extramedullary plasmacytoma if the following are found: </Para><ItemizedList id="_37" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Isolated plasma-cell tumors of soft tissues, most commonly
occurring in the tonsils, nasopharynx, or paranasal sinuses.</ListItem><ListItem>Negative findings on skeletal x-rays and bone marrow biopsy.<Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><Title>Multiple Myeloma</Title><Para id="_39">Multiple myeloma is a systemic malignancy of plasma cells that typically involves multiple sites within the bone marrow and secretes all or part of a monoclonal antibody. </Para><SummarySection id="_40"><Title>Prognosis</Title><Para id="_42">Multiple myeloma is highly treatable but rarely curable. The median
survival in the prechemotherapy era was about 7 months.  After the introduction
of chemotherapy, prognosis improved significantly with a median survival of 24  to
30 months and a 10-year survival rate of 3%.  Even further improvements in prognosis have occurred because of the introduction of newer biological therapies and better salvage options, with median survivals now exceeding 10 years.<Reference refidx="47"/> Patients with plasma cell leukemia or with soft tissue plasmacytomas (often with plasmablastic morphology) in association with multiple myeloma have poor outcomes.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="48"/> Racial disparities because of socioeconomic factors, genetics, differences in risk factor exposure, and structural racism are under evaluation.<Reference refidx="49"/> </Para><Para id="_41">Multiple myeloma is potentially curable when it presents as a
solitary plasmacytoma of bone or as an extramedullary plasmacytoma. For more information, see the sections on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_31" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Isolated Plasmacytoma of Bone</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_35" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Extramedullary Plasmacytoma</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><Title>Amyloidosis Associated With Plasma Cell Neoplasms </Title><Para id="_44">Multiple myeloma and other plasma cell neoplasms may cause a condition called amyloidosis. Primary amyloidosis can result in severe organ dysfunction, especially in the kidney, heart, or peripheral nerves.<Reference refidx="50"/> Clinical symptoms and signs include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_371" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Fatigue.</ListItem><ListItem>Purpura.</ListItem><ListItem>Enlarged tongue.</ListItem><ListItem>Diarrhea.</ListItem><ListItem>Edema.</ListItem><ListItem>Lower-extremity paresthesia.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_511">Accurate diagnosis of amyloidosis requires histological evidence of amyloid deposits and characterization of the amyloidogenic protein using immunoelectron microscopy.<Reference refidx="51"/> In one series of 745 consecutive patients, 20% of patients with nonamyloid light chain amyloidosis (usually transthyretin) had an <Emphasis>innocent</Emphasis> monoclonal gammopathy, indicating the  significant risk of misdiagnosis.<Reference refidx="51"/></Para><Para id="_372">Elevated serum levels of cardiac troponins, amino-terminal fragment brain-type natriuretic peptide, and serum FLC are poor prognostic factors.<Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="53"/> Proposed staging systems for primary systemic amyloidosis based on these serum levels require independent and prospective confirmation.<Reference refidx="52"/><Reference refidx="54"/>
        An increase in levels of serum FLC over many years can precede the clinical diagnosis of amyloid light chain amyloidosis.<Reference refidx="55"/> Amyloidosis associated with an IgM monoclonal gammopathy is a rare, but distinct, clinical entity with more frequent neuropathy and adenopathy and less cardiac involvement.<Reference refidx="56"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_512"><Title>POEMS Syndrome </Title><Para id="_513">POEMS (polyneuropathy, organomegaly, endocrinopathy, monoclonal gammopathy, and skin changes) syndrome is a rare paraneoplastic condition associated with a plasma cell dyscrasia of early or late stage. The acronym describes a constellation of findings often marked by polyneuropathy, organomegaly (usually splenomegaly), endocrinopathy, monoclonal plasma cell dyscrasia, and skin changes.<Reference refidx="57"/> Both sclerotic or lytic bone lesions and lymphadenopathy (with possible Castleman histology)  may be identified. Anecdotal reports suggest remissions have been achieved using myeloma-directed therapy.<Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="59"/><Reference refidx="60"/><Reference refidx="61"/><Reference refidx="62"/> </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="18021088">Kyle RA, Rajkumar SV: Monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance and smouldering multiple myeloma: emphasis on risk factors for progression. Br J Haematol 139 (5): 730-43, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="6668499" MedlineID="84137802">Knowling MA, Harwood AR, Bergsagel DE: Comparison of extramedullary plasmacytomas with solitary and multiple plasma cell tumors of bone. J Clin Oncol 1 (4): 255-62, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="7812210" MedlineID="95111363">Zandecki M, Facon T, Preudhomme C, et al.: Significance of circulating plasma cells in multiple myeloma. Leuk Lymphoma 14 (5-6): 491-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="8704185" MedlineID="96290435">Billadeau D, Van Ness B, Kimlinger T, et al.: Clonal circulating cells are common in plasma cell proliferative disorders: a comparison of monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance, smoldering multiple myeloma, and active myeloma. Blood 88 (1): 289-96, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12535504" MedlineID="22422929">He Y, Wheatley K, Clark O, et al.: Early versus deferred treatment for early stage multiple myeloma. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (1): CD004023, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="17582068">Kyle RA, Remstein ED, Therneau TM, et al.: Clinical course and prognosis of smoldering (asymptomatic) multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 356 (25): 2582-90, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="35576526">Vaxman I, Gertz MA: How I approach smoldering multiple myeloma. Blood 140 (8): 828-838, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="1872571" MedlineID="91336648">Riches PG, Sheldon J, Smith AM, et al.: Overestimation of monoclonal immunoglobulin by immunochemical methods. Ann Clin Biochem 28 ( Pt 3): 253-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="19020545">Dispenzieri A, Kyle R, Merlini G, et al.: International Myeloma Working Group guidelines for serum-free light chain analysis in multiple myeloma and related disorders. Leukemia 23 (2): 215-24, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="23183428">Larsen JT, Kumar SK, Dispenzieri A, et al.: Serum free light chain ratio as a biomarker for high-risk smoldering multiple myeloma. Leukemia 27 (4): 941-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="17330855">Horger M, Kanz L, Denecke B, et al.: The benefit of using whole-body, low-dose, nonenhanced, multidetector computed tomography for follow-up and therapy response monitoring in patients with multiple myeloma. Cancer 109 (8): 1617-26, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="17296972">Walker R, Barlogie B, Haessler J, et al.: Magnetic resonance imaging in multiple myeloma: diagnostic and clinical implications. J Clin Oncol 25 (9): 1121-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="20410922">Kyle RA, Durie BG, Rajkumar SV, et al.: Monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS) and smoldering (asymptomatic) multiple myeloma: IMWG consensus perspectives risk factors for progression and guidelines for monitoring and management. Leukemia 24 (6): 1121-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="28686535">Moreau P, Attal M, Caillot D, et al.: Prospective Evaluation of Magnetic Resonance Imaging and [18F]Fluorodeoxyglucose Positron Emission Tomography-Computed Tomography at Diagnosis and Before Maintenance Therapy in Symptomatic Patients With Multiple Myeloma Included in the IFM/DFCI 2009 Trial: Results of the IMAJEM Study. J Clin Oncol 35 (25): 2911-2918, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="30587527">Zamagni E, Tacchetti P, Cavo M: Imaging in multiple myeloma: How? When? Blood 133 (7): 644-651, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="2451487" MedlineID="88182554">Gertz MA, Li CY, Shirahama T, et al.: Utility of subcutaneous fat aspiration for the diagnosis of systemic amyloidosis (immunoglobulin light chain). Arch Intern Med 148 (4): 929-33, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="1509293" MedlineID="92376595">Greipp PR: Advances in the diagnosis and management of myeloma. Semin Hematol 29 (3 Suppl 2): 24-45, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="2405920" MedlineID="90149148">Durie BG, Stock-Novack D, Salmon SE, et al.: Prognostic value of pretreatment serum beta 2 microglobulin in myeloma: a Southwest Oncology Group Study. Blood 75 (4): 823-30, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="35666958">Garcés JJ, Cedena MT, Puig N, et al.: Circulating Tumor Cells for the Staging of Patients With Newly Diagnosed Transplant-Eligible Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 40 (27): 3151-3161, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="21252060">Pagano L, Valentini CG, De Stefano V, et al.: Primary plasma cell leukemia: a retrospective multicenter study of 73 patients. Ann Oncol 22 (7): 1628-35, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="27114594">Royer B, Minvielle S, Diouf M, et al.: Bortezomib, Doxorubicin, Cyclophosphamide, Dexamethasone Induction Followed by Stem Cell Transplantation for Primary Plasma Cell Leukemia: A Prospective Phase II Study of the Intergroupe Francophone du Myélome. J Clin Oncol 34 (18): 2125-32, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="16571879">Kyle RA, Therneau TM, Rajkumar SV, et al.: Prevalence of monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance. N Engl J Med 354 (13): 1362-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="12780789">International Myeloma Working Group: Criteria for the classification of monoclonal gammopathies, multiple myeloma and related disorders: a report of the International Myeloma Working Group. Br J Haematol 121 (5): 749-57, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="19673884">Bird J, Behrens J, Westin J, et al.: UK Myeloma Forum (UKMF) and Nordic Myeloma Study Group (NMSG): guidelines for the investigation of newly detected M-proteins and the management of monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS). Br J Haematol 147 (1): 22-42, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="8649495" MedlineID="96266359">Attal M, Harousseau JL, Stoppa AM, et al.: A prospective, randomized trial of autologous bone marrow transplantation and chemotherapy in multiple myeloma. Intergroupe Français du Myélome. N Engl J Med 335 (2): 91-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="11856795" MedlineID="21846746">Kyle RA, Therneau TM, Rajkumar SV, et al.: A long-term study of prognosis in monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance. N Engl J Med 346 (8): 564-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="19234139">Weiss BM, Abadie J, Verma P, et al.: A monoclonal gammopathy precedes multiple myeloma in most patients. Blood 113 (22): 5418-22, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="19179464">Landgren O, Kyle RA, Pfeiffer RM, et al.: Monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS) consistently precedes multiple myeloma: a prospective study. Blood 113 (22): 5412-7, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="19478048">Bladé J, Rosiñol L, Cibeira MT: Are all myelomas preceded by MGUS? Blood 113 (22): 5370, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="15855274">Rajkumar SV, Kyle RA, Therneau TM, et al.: Serum free light chain ratio is an independent risk factor for progression in monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance. Blood 106 (3): 812-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="24222331">Turesson I, Kovalchik SA, Pfeiffer RM, et al.: Monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance and risk of lymphoid and myeloid malignancies: 728 cases followed up to 30 years in Sweden. Blood 123 (3): 338-45, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="29342381">Kyle RA, Larson DR, Therneau TM, et al.: Long-Term Follow-up of Monoclonal Gammopathy of Undetermined Significance. N Engl J Med 378 (3): 241-249, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="24144643">Dhodapkar MV, Sexton R, Waheed S, et al.: Clinical, genomic, and imaging predictors of myeloma progression from asymptomatic monoclonal gammopathies (SWOG S0120). Blood 123 (1): 78-85, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="30012636">Fermand JP, Bridoux F, Dispenzieri A, et al.: Monoclonal gammopathy of clinical significance: a novel concept with therapeutic implications. Blood 132 (14): 1478-1485, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="34010532">Leung N, Bridoux F, Nasr SH: Monoclonal Gammopathy of Renal Significance. N Engl J Med 384 (20): 1931-1941, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="24434993">Merlini G: Determining the significance of MGUS. Blood 123 (3): 305-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="29146225">Campbell JP, Heaney JLJ, Pandya S, et al.: Response comparison of multiple myeloma and monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance to the same anti-myeloma therapy: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet Haematol 4 (12): e584-e594, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="16229966">Ozsahin M, Tsang RW, Poortmans P, et al.: Outcomes and patterns of failure in solitary plasmacytoma: a multicenter Rare Cancer Network study of 258 patients. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 64 (1): 210-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="10979944" MedlineID="20435328">Dimopoulos MA, Moulopoulos LA, Maniatis A, et al.: Solitary plasmacytoma of bone and asymptomatic multiple myeloma. Blood 96 (6): 2037-44, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="12057071">Dimopoulos MA, Hamilos G: Solitary bone plasmacytoma and extramedullary plasmacytoma. Curr Treat Options Oncol 3 (3): 255-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="24876564">Paiva B, Chandia M, Vidriales MB, et al.: Multiparameter flow cytometry for staging of solitary bone plasmacytoma: new criteria for risk of progression to myeloma. Blood 124 (8): 1300-3, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="9719116" MedlineID="98383598">Liebross RH, Ha CS, Cox JD, et al.: Solitary bone plasmacytoma: outcome and prognostic factors following radiotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 41 (5): 1063-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="16343803">Tournier-Rangeard L, Lapeyre M, Graff-Caillaud P, et al.: Radiotherapy for solitary extramedullary plasmacytoma in the head-and-neck region: A dose greater than 45 Gy to the target volume improves the local control. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 64 (4): 1013-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="14512335">Michalaki VJ, Hall J, Henk JM, et al.: Definitive radiotherapy for extramedullary plasmacytomas of the head and neck. Br J Radiol 76 (910): 738-41, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="10357398" MedlineID="99284290">Alexiou C, Kau RJ, Dietzfelbinger H, et al.: Extramedullary plasmacytoma: tumor occurrence and therapeutic concepts. Cancer 85 (11): 2305-14, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="32298201">Joseph NS, Kaufman JL, Dhodapkar MV, et al.: Long-Term Follow-Up Results of Lenalidomide, Bortezomib, and Dexamethasone Induction Therapy and Risk-Adapted Maintenance Approach in Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 38 (17): 1928-1937, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="21900099">Bladé J, Fernández de Larrea C, Rosiñol L, et al.: Soft-tissue plasmacytomas in multiple myeloma: incidence, mechanisms of extramedullary spread, and treatment approach. J Clin Oncol 29 (28): 3805-12, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="32066732">Marinac CR, Ghobrial IM, Birmann BM, et al.: Dissecting racial disparities in multiple myeloma. Blood Cancer J 10 (2): 19, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="32633805">Gertz MA, Dispenzieri A: Systemic Amyloidosis Recognition, Prognosis, and Therapy: A Systematic Review. JAMA 324 (1): 79-89, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="25636337">Fernández de Larrea C, Verga L, Morbini P, et al.: A practical approach to the diagnosis of systemic amyloidoses. Blood 125 (14): 2239-44, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="22331953">Kumar S, Dispenzieri A, Lacy MQ, et al.: Revised prognostic staging system for light chain amyloidosis incorporating cardiac biomarkers and serum free light chain measurements. J Clin Oncol 30 (9): 989-95, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="21220614">Pinney JH, Lachmann HJ, Bansi L, et al.: Outcome in renal Al amyloidosis after chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol 29 (6): 674-81, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="30333122">Lilleness B, Ruberg FL, Mussinelli R, et al.: Development and validation of a survival staging system incorporating BNP in patients with light chain amyloidosis. Blood 133 (3): 215-223, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="25024082">Weiss BM, Hebreo J, Cordaro DV, et al.: Increased serum free light chains precede the presentation of immunoglobulin light chain amyloidosis. J Clin Oncol 32 (25): 2699-704, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="27114592">Sachchithanantham S, Roussel M, Palladini G, et al.: European Collaborative Study Defining Clinical Profile Outcomes and Novel Prognostic Criteria in Monoclonal Immunoglobulin M-Related Light Chain Amyloidosis. J Clin Oncol 34 (17): 2037-45, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="21681783">Dispenzieri A: POEMS syndrome: 2011 update on diagnosis, risk-stratification, and management. Am J Hematol 86 (7): 591-601, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="23699599">Humeniuk MS, Gertz MA, Lacy MQ, et al.: Outcomes of patients with POEMS syndrome treated initially with radiation. Blood 122 (1): 68-73, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="21393478">Li J, Zhang W, Jiao L, et al.: Combination of melphalan and dexamethasone for patients with newly diagnosed POEMS syndrome. Blood 117 (24): 6445-9, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="23335406">Royer B, Merlusca L, Abraham J, et al.: Efficacy of lenalidomide in POEMS syndrome: a retrospective study of 20 patients. Am J Hematol 88 (3): 207-12, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="27496680">Misawa S, Sato Y, Katayama K, et al.: Safety and efficacy of thalidomide in patients with POEMS syndrome: a multicentre, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet Neurol 15 (11): 1129-37, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="30700844">Zhao H, Huang XF, Gao XM, et al.: What is the best first-line treatment for POEMS syndrome: autologous transplantation, melphalan and dexamethasone, or lenalidomide and dexamethasone? Leukemia 33 (4): 1023-1029, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037974">multiple myeloma and other plasma cell neoplasms</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Plasma Cell Neoplasms</Title><Para id="_46">No generally accepted staging system exists for monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance, isolated plasmacytoma of bone, or extramedullary plasmacytoma.  Of the plasma cell neoplasms, a staging system exists only for multiple myeloma.</Para><SummarySection id="_234"><Title>Multiple Myeloma</Title><Para id="_47">Multiple myeloma is staged by estimating the myeloma tumor cell mass based on the amount of monoclonal (or myeloma) protein (M protein) in the serum and/or urine, along with various clinical parameters, such as hemoglobin and serum calcium concentrations, the number of lytic bone lesions, and the presence or absence of renal failure. Impaired renal function worsens prognosis regardless of stage.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_48">The stage of the disease at presentation is a strong determinant of survival, but it has little influence on the choice of therapy because almost all patients, except for rare patients with solitary bone tumors or extramedullary plasmacytomas, have generalized disease.</Para><SummarySection id="_49"><Title>International staging system</Title><Para id="_50">The International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) studied 11,171 patients, 2,901 of whom received high-dose therapy and 8,270 of whom received only standard-dose therapy.<Reference refidx="2"/> The IMWG  evaluated 4,445 patients to create a   Revised International Staging System (R-ISS) incorporating lactate dehydrogenase levels and interphase fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization (I-FISH) results.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_51">An International Staging System (ISS) was derived and is shown below in Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_52" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">2</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Table id="_52"><Title>Table 2.  The International Staging System (ISS) for Multiple Myeloma</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">Criteria</entry><entry Align="Center">Median Survival (mo)</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">I-FISH = interphase fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization;  LDH =  lactate dehydrogenase; R-ISS = Revised International Staging System.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>I</entry><entry>Beta-2-microglobulin &lt;3.5 mg/L and albumin ≥3.5 g/dL</entry><entry>Not reached</entry></Row><Row><entry>II</entry><entry>Not R-ISS I or III</entry><entry>83</entry></Row><Row><entry>III</entry><entry>Beta-2-microglobulin ≥5.5 mg/L and either high LDH or high-risk chromosomal abnormalities by I-FISH (defined as presence of del(17p) and/or translocation t(4;14) and/or translocation t(14;16))</entry><entry>43</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><Title>Genetic factors and risk groups
</Title><Para id="_55">Newer clinical investigations are stratifying patients with multiple myeloma into so-called good-risk, intermediate-risk, and high-risk groups, based on genetic aberrations detected by  I-FISH.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> (See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_442" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">3</SummaryRef> below.) This stratification, based on cytogenetic findings, has been derived from retrospective analyses and requires prospective validation.<Reference refidx="4"/> Bone marrow samples are sent for cytogenetic and FISH analysis.<Reference refidx="6"/> Plasma cell leukemia (&gt;2%–5% circulating plasma cells) has a particularly poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> The otherwise favorable prognosis of hyperploidy is trumped by coexistent adverse cytogenetics.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Table id="_442"><Title>Table 3.  Risk Groups for Multiple Myeloma</Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="18.76%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="18.76%"/><ColSpec ColName="col03" ColNum="3" ColWidth="24.95%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="18.76%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="18.76%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Risk Group</entry><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col03" NameSt="col2">Cytogenetic Findings</entry><entry Align="Center">Disease Characteristics</entry><entry Align="Center">Median Survival (y)</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">FISH = fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ </Emphasis>hybridization; Ig = immunoglobulin.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Good risk</entry><entry NameEnd="col03" NameSt="col2">Has any of the following cytogenetic findings:</entry><entry MoreRows="4">These patients most often have  disease that expresses IgG kappa monoclonal gammopathies, and lytic bone lesions.</entry><entry MoreRows="4">10–12 <Reference refidx="15"/></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>No adverse FISH or cytogenetics</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Hyperdiploidy</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>t(11;14) by FISH</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>t(6;14) by FISH</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Intermediate risk</entry><entry NameEnd="col03" NameSt="col2">Has one of the following formerly deleterious criteria that have been abrogated by standard triplet or quadruplet regimens:<Reference refidx="16"/></entry><entry MoreRows="2">These patients often have IgA lambda monoclonal gammopathies and less bone disease.</entry><entry MoreRows="2">5–10 </entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>t(4;14)</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>t(14;16)</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="8">High risk</entry><entry NameEnd="col03" NameSt="col2">Has any of the following cytogenetic findings:</entry><entry MoreRows="8">These patients have disease that expresses IgA lambda monoclonal gammopathies (often) and skeletal-related complications (less often).</entry><entry MoreRows="8">&lt;5 for high-risk;  &lt;3 for ultra-high risk <Reference refidx="15"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>del 17p by FISH</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>t(14;16) by FISH</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>t(4;14)</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>t(14;20)</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>del 13</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Biallelic del <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> (ultra-high risk)</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>1q gain (3 copies), 1 q amp (4 copies, ultra-high risk), monoallelic del (1p32),<Reference refidx="17"/> biallelic del (1p32)<Reference refidx="17"/></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Plasma cell leukemia</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="32160635">Royal V, Leung N, Troyanov S, et al.: Clinicopathologic predictors of renal outcomes in light chain cast nephropathy: a multicenter retrospective study. Blood 135 (21): 1833-1846, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15809451">Greipp PR, San Miguel J, Durie BG, et al.: International staging system for multiple myeloma. J Clin Oncol 23 (15): 3412-20, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="26240224">Palumbo A, Avet-Loiseau H, Oliva S, et al.: Revised International Staging System for Multiple Myeloma: A Report From International Myeloma Working Group. J Clin Oncol 33 (26): 2863-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19955246">Kumar SK, Mikhael JR, Buadi FK, et al.: Management of newly diagnosed symptomatic multiple myeloma: updated Mayo Stratification of Myeloma and Risk-Adapted Therapy (mSMART) consensus guidelines. Mayo Clin Proc 84 (12): 1095-110, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="22547600">Avet-Loiseau H, Attal M, Campion L, et al.: Long-term analysis of the IFM 99 trials for myeloma: cytogenetic abnormalities [t(4;14), del(17p), 1q gains] play a major role in defining long-term survival. J Clin Oncol 30 (16): 1949-52, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="27002115">Sonneveld P, Avet-Loiseau H, Lonial S, et al.: Treatment of multiple myeloma with high-risk cytogenetics: a consensus of the International Myeloma Working Group. Blood 127 (24): 2955-62, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="19877113">Ramsingh G, Mehan P, Luo J, et al.: Primary plasma cell leukemia: a Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results database analysis between 1973 and 2004. Cancer 115 (24): 5734-9, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="23288300">Fernández de Larrea C, Kyle RA, Durie BG, et al.: Plasma cell leukemia: consensus statement on diagnostic requirements, response criteria and treatment recommendations by the International Myeloma Working Group. Leukemia 27 (4): 780-91, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="28255016">Granell M, Calvo X, Garcia-Guiñón A, et al.: Prognostic impact of circulating plasma cells in patients with multiple myeloma: implications for plasma cell leukemia definition. Haematologica 102 (6): 1099-1104, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="30332496">Mina R, Joseph NS, Kaufman JL, et al.: Survival outcomes of patients with primary plasma cell leukemia (pPCL) treated with novel agents. Cancer 125 (3): 416-423, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="27114594">Royer B, Minvielle S, Diouf M, et al.: Bortezomib, Doxorubicin, Cyclophosphamide, Dexamethasone Induction Followed by Stem Cell Transplantation for Primary Plasma Cell Leukemia: A Prospective Phase II Study of the Intergroupe Francophone du Myélome. J Clin Oncol 34 (18): 2125-32, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="24957143">Gonsalves WI, Rajkumar SV, Go RS, et al.: Trends in survival of patients with primary plasma cell leukemia: a population-based analysis. Blood 124 (6): 907-12, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="36315921">Jelinek T, Bezdekova R, Zihala D, et al.: More Than 2% of Circulating Tumor Plasma Cells Defines Plasma Cell Leukemia-Like Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 41 (7): 1383-1392, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="25428216">Pawlyn C, Melchor L, Murison A, et al.: Coexistent hyperdiploidy does not abrogate poor prognosis in myeloma with adverse cytogenetics and may precede IGH translocations. Blood 125 (5): 831-40, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="35653112">Davies FE, Pawlyn C, Usmani SZ, et al.: Perspectives on the Risk-Stratified Treatment of Multiple Myeloma. Blood Cancer Discov 3 (4): 273-284, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="36929439">Khot A: Del(1p32): prime time in (ultra) high-risk myeloma. Blood 141 (11): 1241-1243, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="36375118">Schavgoulidze A, Talbot A, Perrot A, et al.: Biallelic deletion of 1p32 defines ultra-high-risk myeloma, but monoallelic del(1p32) remains a strong prognostic factor. Blood 141 (11): 1308-1315, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037974">multiple myeloma and other plasma cell neoplasms</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Plasma Cell Neoplasms </Title><Para id="_58">The major challenge in treating plasma cell neoplasms is separating the stable asymptomatic patients who do not require immediate treatment from patients with progressive symptomatic myeloma who  may need to be treated immediately.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance or smoldering myeloma must
be distinguished from progressive myeloma.</Para><SummarySection id="_59"><Title>Asymptomatic Plasma Cell Neoplasms (Smoldering Multiple Myeloma) </Title><Para id="_60">Asymptomatic patients with multiple myeloma who have no lytic bone lesions and normal renal function may be initially observed safely outside the context of a clinical trial.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Increasing anemia is the most reliable indicator of progression.<Reference refidx="5"/> The following criteria represent the new definition for smoldering myeloma:<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_455" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Serum monoclonal protein immunoglobulin (Ig) G or IgA of at least  30 g/L or urinary monoclonal protein of at least 500 mg per 24 hours.</ListItem><ListItem>Clonal bone marrow plasma cells 10% to 60% (&gt;60% represents overt myeloma).</ListItem><ListItem>Absence of amyloidosis or myeloma-defining events as follows:<ItemizedList id="_456" Style="dash"><ListItem>Hypercalcemia greater than 1 mg/dL higher than reference range.</ListItem><ListItem>Creatinine greater than 2 mg/dL or creatinine clearance less than 40 mL/min. </ListItem><ListItem>Anemia with hemoglobin less than 10.0 g/dL. </ListItem><ListItem>Bone lesions (one or more) on skeletal radiography, computed tomography (CT)  or positron emission tomography (PET)-CT.</ListItem><ListItem>Clonal plasma cell percentage in marrow at 60% or more.</ListItem><ListItem>Involved:uninvolved serum free light chain (FLC) ratio of 100 or more.</ListItem><ListItem>More than one focal lesion of at least  5 mm on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the spine.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1325">The International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) 2/20/20 rule measures four adverse risk factors for patients with smoldering myeloma. The presence of three or four of the following adverse factors predicts a greater than 50% chance of progression to myeloma within 2 years:<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_1326" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Serum monoclonal (or myeloma) protein (M protein)  greater than 2 g/dL.</ListItem><ListItem>Involved:uninvolved serum FLC ratio of more than 20.</ListItem><ListItem>Bone marrow plasma cell infiltration of more than 20%.</ListItem><ListItem>t(4;14), t(14;16), 1q gain, or del13q/monosomy 13 chromosomal abnormality. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1327">Clinical trials evaluating smoldering myeloma need to exclude patients at high risk of progression to myeloma because those patients should consider induction therapy for symptomatic patients. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_61" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Symptomatic Plasma Cell Neoplasms</SummaryRef> section.</Para><OrderedList id="_1328" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial of 390 patients with smoldering myeloma, patients were eligible if the marrow plasmacytosis was 10% to 49% and one of the following criteria was met:<ItemizedList id="_1329" Style="bullet"><ListItem>M protein of at least 3 g/dL.</ListItem><ListItem>Immunoparesis of two Ig classes.</ListItem><ListItem>Involved:uninvolved serum FLC ratio of 8 to 99.</ListItem><ListItem>IgA monoclonal protein.</ListItem><ListItem>Marrow plasmacytosis of 50% to 59%.</ListItem></ItemizedList> These patients received daratumumab (the anti-CD38 monoclonal antibody) or no therapy.<Reference refidx="7"/><ItemizedList id="_1330" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 65.2 months, the 5-year progression-free survival rate was 63.1% for patients in the daratumumab arm and 40.8% for patients in the watchful waiting arm (hazard ratio [HR], 0.49; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.36–0.67; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The median time to progression was 44.1 months for patients in the daratumumab arm and 17.8 months for patients in the watchful waiting arm (HR, 0.51; 95% CI, 0.40–0.66; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year overall survival (OS) rate was 93% for patients in the daratumumab arm and 86% for patients in the watchful waiting arm (HR, 0.52; 95% CI, 0.27–0.98).</ListItem><ListItem>Three quality-of-life assessments showed no difference between the arms.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1331"><Strong>Summary:</Strong> This trial did not show a significant improvement in OS or quality of life. However, the significant and clinically relevant delay in progression may particularly benefit older, less fit patients with myeloma. Early use of daratumumab did not result in a shortened OS after the subsequent initiation of full-dose induction therapy.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><Title>Symptomatic Plasma Cell Neoplasms </Title><Para id="_62">Patients with symptomatic advanced disease require treatment.</Para><Para id="_63">Treatment most often is   directed at
reducing the tumor cell burden and reversing any complications of disease, such
as renal failure, infection, hyperviscosity, or hypercalcemia, with appropriate
medical management. The IMWG has published new criteria for identifying patients with active myeloma who require therapy:<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_457" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Amyloidosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Hypercalcemia greater than 1 mg/dL higher than reference range.</ListItem><ListItem>Creatinine greater than 2 mg/dL or creatinine clearance less than 40 mL/min. Myeloma can cause renal dysfunction via hypercalcemia, amyloidosis, or light chain deposition disease.<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem>Anemia with hemoglobin less than 10.0 g/dL. </ListItem><ListItem>Bone lesions (one or more) on skeletal radiography, whole-body MRI or spine and pelvis MRI, or PET-CT scans.<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem>Clonal plasma cell percentage in marrow at 60% or more.</ListItem><ListItem>Involved:uninvolved serum FLC ratio of 100 or more.</ListItem><ListItem>More than one focal lesion of at least  5 mm on skeletal bone survey, or if negative, total-body MRI, or MRI of the spine and pelvis, or PET-CT scan.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_64">Response criteria have been developed for patients on clinical trials by the IMWG.<Reference refidx="10"/> A very good partial response (VGPR) is defined as a reduction of 90% or more in the serum monoclonal protein and a 24-hour urine monoclonal protein of less than 100 mg. Although not incorporated in the IMWG criteria, many trials report near complete response when patients have less than 5% bone marrow plasma cells and unmeasurable serum monoclonal proteins but still have positive serum and/or urine immunofixation. Note that these near complete response patients are incorporated into the VGPR group by the IMWG. Patients who achieve a complete response by IMWG criteria (with a negative immunofixation along with the clear marrow and unmeasurable serum monoclonal proteins) are often said to have attained a stringent complete response if their free kappa/lambda light–chain levels and ratio return to reference ranges. The clinical utility of these various categories must be validated in clinical trials. </Para><Para id="_65">Therapy options for patients with symptomatic myeloma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_66" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Induction therapies.</ListItem><ListItem>Consolidation therapies, which are less applicable for patients of advanced age.</ListItem><ListItem>Maintenance therapies.</ListItem><ListItem>Supportive care, such as bisphosphonates. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062738#_58" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-hp-pdq">Pharmacological Therapies for Pain Control</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Infection prevention, which includes vaccination, antimicrobial prophylaxis, and immunoglobulin replacement (in a small subset of patients), per consensus guidelines from the IMWG.<Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12535504" MedlineID="22422929">He Y, Wheatley K, Clark O, et al.: Early versus deferred treatment for early stage multiple myeloma. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (1): CD004023, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="17582068">Kyle RA, Remstein ED, Therneau TM, et al.: Clinical course and prognosis of smoldering (asymptomatic) multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 356 (25): 2582-90, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25439696">Rajkumar SV, Dimopoulos MA, Palumbo A, et al.: International Myeloma Working Group updated criteria for the diagnosis of multiple myeloma. Lancet Oncol 15 (12): e538-48, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10755397" MedlineID="20216173">Riccardi A, Mora O, Tinelli C, et al.: Long-term survival of stage I multiple myeloma given chemotherapy just after diagnosis or at progression of the disease: a multicentre randomized study. Cooperative Group of Study and Treatment of Multiple Myeloma. Br J Cancer 82 (7): 1254-60, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="20026810">Bladé J, Dimopoulos M, Rosiñol L, et al.: Smoldering (asymptomatic) multiple myeloma: current diagnostic criteria, new predictors of outcome, and follow-up recommendations. J Clin Oncol 28 (4): 690-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="33067414">Mateos MV, Kumar S, Dimopoulos MA, et al.: International Myeloma Working Group risk stratification model for smoldering multiple myeloma (SMM). Blood Cancer J 10 (10): 102, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="39652675">Dimopoulos MA, Voorhees PM, Schjesvold F, et al.: Daratumumab or Active Monitoring for High-Risk Smoldering Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 392 (18): 1777-1788, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="26392598">Sayed RH, Wechalekar AD, Gilbertson JA, et al.: Natural history and outcome of light chain deposition disease. Blood 126 (26): 2805-10, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="25605835">Dimopoulos MA, Hillengass J, Usmani S, et al.: Role of magnetic resonance imaging in the management of patients with multiple myeloma: a consensus statement. J Clin Oncol 33 (6): 657-64, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="16855634">Durie BG, Harousseau JL, Miguel JS, et al.: International uniform response criteria for multiple myeloma. Leukemia 20 (9): 1467-73, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="35114152">Raje NS, Anaissie E, Kumar SK, et al.: Consensus guidelines and recommendations for infection prevention in multiple myeloma: a report from the International Myeloma Working Group. Lancet Haematol 9 (2): e143-e161, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041926">primary systemic amyloidosis</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Amyloidosis Associated With Plasma Cell Neoplasms</Title><SummarySection id="_68"><Title>Treatment Options for Amyloidosis Associated With Plasma Cell Neoplasms </Title><Para id="_514">Treatment depends on assessing the extent of systemic damage from the amyloidosis and  the underlying plasma cell dyscrasia.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> A rising and elevated level of N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide (NT-proBNP) may predict impending cardiac failure in cases of cardiac amyloidosis, and early treatment should be considered for these patients.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_69">Treatment options for amyloidosis associated with plasma cell neoplasms include:</Para><OrderedList id="_70" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_71" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Induction therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_74" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Stem cell rescue</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1123" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Monoclonal antibody targeting of amyloid deposits</SummaryRef> (under clinical evaluation).</ListItem> </OrderedList><SummarySection id="_71"><Title>Induction therapy</Title><Para id="_73">As is true for all plasma cell dyscrasias, responses have been reported for patients treated with all the same regimens active in multiple myeloma.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Lower doses of lenalidomide or pomalidomide must be used in patients with renal dysfunction.<Reference refidx="13"/> Patients with amyloidosis respond to treatment with daratumumab, with or without other active agents. Daratumumab is usually combined with other agents used for myeloma.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> Rapid responses to induction therapy may result in improvement of renal or cardiac function.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_1119">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_1120" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03201965">NCT03201965</ProtocolRef>) included 388 previously untreated patients with immunoglobulin light-chain amyloidosis (excluding symptomatic myeloma). Patients were randomly assigned to receive bortezomib, cyclophosphamide, and dexamethasone with or without subcutaneous daratumumab.<Reference refidx="23"/><ItemizedList id="_1121" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 11.4 months, the hematologic complete response rate was 53% for patients in the daratumumab group and 18.1% for patients in the control group (relative risk, 2.9; 95% confidence interval [CI], 2.1–4.1; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). A landmark analysis at 6 months was also performed.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Survival free from organ deterioration, hematologic progression, or death favored the daratumumab arm (hazard ratio, 0.58; 95% CI, 0.36–0.93; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).</ListItem><ListItem>The cardiac and renal responses were doubled for patients in the daratumumab group, but no statistical analysis was provided.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1122">Daratumumab combined with bortezomib, cyclophosphamide, and dexamethasone is considered a standard regimen for previously untreated patients who are eligible to receive this regimen. When using daratumumab induction therapy, the fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization–detected cytogenetic abnormality of t(11;14) no longer confers an adverse prognostic impact. However, the presence of 1q gain continues to be associated with a lower response rate and hematologic event-free survival during treatment of amyloid light chain amyloidosis.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_74"><Title>Stem cell rescue</Title><Para id="_76">A prospective randomized study of 100 patients with immunoglobulin light-chain amyloidosis compared melphalan plus high-dose dexamethasone with high-dose melphalan plus autologous stem cell rescue.<Reference refidx="25"/> After a median follow-up of 3 years, median overall survival (OS) favored the nontransplant arm (56.9 months  vs. 22.2 months;  <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .04).<Reference refidx="25"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]   The 24% transplant-related mortality in this series and others reflects the difficulties involved with high-dose chemotherapy in older patients with organ dysfunction.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/> Between 2007 and 2012, the International Blood and Marrow Transplant Research Program identified 800 patients with amyloidosis who underwent autologous stem cell transplant (SCT); the 5-year OS rate was 77% and the transplant-related mortality rate was 5%, suggesting better selection of patients for transplant.<Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] Similarly, in a retrospective review of 672 consecutive patients with amyloidosis who underwent autologous SCT over 20 years, the treatment-related mortality rate declined to 2.4% between 2010 and 2016, compared with rates of 8.6% between 2003 and 2009 and 14.5% between 1996 and 2002.<Reference refidx="32"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>] A randomized trial confirming the benefit of autologous SCT is not anticipated.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="33"/></Para><Para id="_77">An anecdotal series described full-intensity and reduced-intensity allogeneic SCT.<Reference refidx="34"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1123"><Title>Monoclonal antibody targeting of amyloid deposits</Title><Para id="_1124">The monoclonal antibody anselamimab binds to immunoglobulin-associated amyloid in an effort to promote phagocytosis and clearance of the amyloid deposits.</Para><OrderedList id="_1150" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a phase I study (NCT02245867), 27 patients with deep hematologic responses to myeloma therapy, but persistent organ involvement, received anselamimab.<Reference refidx="35"/><ItemizedList id="_1151" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Fifteen of 24 patients (63%) manifested cardiac, renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, or soft tissue response by serum biomarkers (such as NT-proBNP), renal function, cardiac function, or imaging studies.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1152">This treatment is not approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration and is under clinical evaluation.<Reference refidx="35"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_67_sid_4"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_67_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="32633805">Gertz MA, Dispenzieri A: Systemic Amyloidosis Recognition, Prognosis, and Therapy: A Systematic Review. JAMA 324 (1): 79-89, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="34517412">Palladini G, Merlini G: How I treat AL amyloidosis. Blood 139 (19): 2918-2930, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23670179">Merlini G, Wechalekar AD, Palladini G: Systemic light chain amyloidosis: an update for treating physicians. Blood 121 (26): 5124-30, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="22504925">Kumar SK, Hayman SR, Buadi FK, et al.: Lenalidomide, cyclophosphamide, and dexamethasone (CRd) for light-chain amyloidosis: long-term results from a phase 2 trial. Blood 119 (21): 4860-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="22331187">Venner CP, Lane T, Foard D, et al.: Cyclophosphamide, bortezomib, and dexamethasone therapy in AL amyloidosis is associated with high clonal response rates and prolonged progression-free survival. Blood 119 (19): 4387-90, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="23479568">Wechalekar AD, Schonland SO, Kastritis E, et al.: A European collaborative study of treatment outcomes in 346 patients with cardiac stage III AL amyloidosis. Blood 121 (17): 3420-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="27381904">Sanchorawala V, Shelton AC, Lo S, et al.: Pomalidomide and dexamethasone in the treatment of AL amyloidosis: results of a phase 1 and 2 trial. Blood 128 (8): 1059-62, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="29101236">Palladini G, Milani P, Foli A, et al.: Presentation and outcome with second-line treatment in AL amyloidosis previously sensitive to nontransplant therapies. Blood 131 (5): 525-532, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="31578202">Manwani R, Cohen O, Sharpley F, et al.: A prospective observational study of 915 patients with systemic AL amyloidosis treated with upfront bortezomib. Blood 134 (25): 2271-2280, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="32730181">Kastritis E, Leleu X, Arnulf B, et al.: Bortezomib, Melphalan, and Dexamethasone for Light-Chain Amyloidosis. J Clin Oncol 38 (28): 3252-3260, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="32083996">Lentzsch S, Lagos GG, Comenzo RL, et al.: Bendamustine With Dexamethasone in Relapsed/Refractory Systemic Light-Chain Amyloidosis: Results of a Phase II Study. J Clin Oncol 38 (13): 1455-1462, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="34168284">Dispenzieri A, Kastritis E, Wechalekar AD, et al.: A randomized phase 3 study of ixazomib-dexamethasone versus physician's choice in relapsed or refractory AL amyloidosis. Leukemia 36 (1): 225-235, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="30190454">Mikhael J, Manola J, Dueck AC, et al.: Lenalidomide and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma and impaired renal function: PrE1003, a PrECOG study. Blood Cancer J 8 (9): 86, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="32244252">Palladini G, Kastritis E, Maurer MS, et al.: Daratumumab plus CyBorD for patients with newly diagnosed AL amyloidosis: safety run-in results of ANDROMEDA. Blood 136 (1): 71-80, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="31978210">Sanchorawala V, Sarosiek S, Schulman A, et al.: Safety, tolerability, and response rates of daratumumab in relapsed AL amyloidosis: results of a phase 2 study. Blood 135 (18): 1541-1547, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="30951198">Nooka AK, Kaufman JL, Hofmeister CC, et al.: Daratumumab in multiple myeloma. Cancer 125 (14): 2364-2382, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="32353125">Dispenzieri A: AL patients don't dare go without dara. Blood 135 (18): 1509-1510, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="32108228">Roussel M, Merlini G, Chevret S, et al.: A prospective phase 2 trial of daratumumab in patients with previously treated systemic light-chain amyloidosis. Blood 135 (18): 1531-1540, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="32107537">Kimmich CR, Terzer T, Benner A, et al.: Daratumumab for systemic AL amyloidosis: prognostic factors and adverse outcome with nephrotic-range albuminuria. Blood 135 (18): 1517-1530, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="32160635">Royal V, Leung N, Troyanov S, et al.: Clinicopathologic predictors of renal outcomes in light chain cast nephropathy: a multicenter retrospective study. Blood 135 (21): 1833-1846, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="35772003">Basset M, Milani P, Foli A, et al.: Early cardiac response is possible in stage IIIb cardiac AL amyloidosis and is associated with prolonged survival. Blood 140 (18): 1964-1971, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="36215675">Muchtar E, Dispenzieri A, Wisniowski B, et al.: Graded Cardiac Response Criteria for Patients With Systemic Light Chain Amyloidosis. J Clin Oncol 41 (7): 1393-1403, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="34192431">Kastritis E, Palladini G, Minnema MC, et al.: Daratumumab-Based Treatment for Immunoglobulin Light-Chain Amyloidosis. N Engl J Med 385 (1): 46-58, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="39197073">Chakraborty R, Zanwar S, Hegenbart U, et al.: Prognostic impact of cytogenetic abnormalities detected by FISH in AL amyloidosis with daratumumab-based frontline therapy. Blood 144 (25): 2613-2624, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="17855669">Jaccard A, Moreau P, Leblond V, et al.: High-dose melphalan versus melphalan plus dexamethasone for AL amyloidosis. N Engl J Med 357 (11): 1083-93, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="14739213">Dispenzieri A, Kyle RA, Lacy MQ, et al.: Superior survival in primary systemic amyloidosis patients undergoing peripheral blood stem cell transplantation: a case-control study. Blood 103 (10): 3960-3, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="14734330">Skinner M, Sanchorawala V, Seldin DC, et al.: High-dose melphalan and autologous stem-cell transplantation in patients with AL amyloidosis: an 8-year study. Ann Intern Med 140 (2): 85-93, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="16037390">Leung N, Leung TR, Cha SS, et al.: Excessive fluid accumulation during stem cell mobilization: a novel prognostic factor of first-year survival after stem cell transplantation in AL amyloidosis patients. Blood 106 (10): 3353-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="22147893">Madan S, Kumar SK, Dispenzieri A, et al.: High-dose melphalan and peripheral blood stem cell transplantation for light-chain amyloidosis with cardiac involvement. Blood 119 (5): 1117-22, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="21828140">Cibeira MT, Sanchorawala V, Seldin DC, et al.: Outcome of AL amyloidosis after high-dose melphalan and autologous stem cell transplantation: long-term results in a series of 421 patients. Blood 118 (16): 4346-52, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="26371138">D'Souza A, Dispenzieri A, Wirk B, et al.: Improved Outcomes After Autologous Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation for Light Chain Amyloidosis: A Center for International Blood and Marrow Transplant Research Study. J Clin Oncol 33 (32): 3741-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="29558277">Sidiqi MH, Aljama MA, Buadi FK, et al.: Stem Cell Transplantation for Light Chain Amyloidosis: Decreased Early Mortality Over Time. J Clin Oncol 36 (13): 1323-1329, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="33">Mehta  J, Gerta MA, Dispenzieri A: High-dose therapy for amyloidosis: the end of the beginning? Blood  103 (10): 3612-3, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="16293611">Schönland SO, Lokhorst H, Buzyn A, et al.: Allogeneic and syngeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation in patients with amyloid light-chain amyloidosis: a report from the European Group for Blood and Marrow Transplantation. Blood 107 (6): 2578-84, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="34521113">Edwards CV, Rao N, Bhutani D, et al.: Phase 1a/b study of monoclonal antibody CAEL-101 (11-1F4) in patients with AL amyloidosis. Blood 138 (25): 2632-2641, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_78"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040134">monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Monoclonal Gammopathy of Undetermined Significance</Title><SummarySection id="_79"><Title>Treatment Options for Monoclonal Gammopathy of Undetermined Significance (MGUS)</Title><Para id="_80">Treatment options for MGUS include:</Para><OrderedList id="_81" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_82" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Watchful waiting</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_82"><Title>Watchful waiting</Title><Para id="_83">Multiple myeloma, other plasma cell dyscrasia,
or lymphoma will develop in 12% of patients by 10 years, 25% of patients by 20 years, and 30%
of patients by 25 years. </Para><Para id="_84">All
patients with MGUS are generally  observed to detect increases in
monoclonal (M) protein levels and development of a plasma cell dyscrasia. Higher levels of initial M protein levels may  correlate with increased risk of progression to multiple myeloma.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> In a large retrospective report, the risk of progression at 20 years was 14% for an initial M protein level of 0.5 g/dL or less, 25% for a level of 1.5 g/dL, 41% for a level of 2.0 g/dL, 49% for a level of 2.5 g/dL, and 64% for a level of 3.0 g/dL.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_85">Treatment
is delayed until the disease progresses to the stage that symptoms or signs
appear.</Para><Para id="_86">Patients with MGUS or smoldering myeloma do not respond more
frequently,  achieve longer remissions, or have improved survival if chemotherapy is
started early while they are still asymptomatic as opposed to waiting for
progression before treatment is initiated.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> Newer therapies have not been proven to prevent or delay the progression of MGUS to a plasma cell dyscrasia.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_78_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_78_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11856795" MedlineID="21846746">Kyle RA, Therneau TM, Rajkumar SV, et al.: A long-term study of prognosis in monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance. N Engl J Med 346 (8): 564-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="19673884">Bird J, Behrens J, Westin J, et al.: UK Myeloma Forum (UKMF) and Nordic Myeloma Study Group (NMSG): guidelines for the investigation of newly detected M-proteins and the management of monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS). Br J Haematol 147 (1): 22-42, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="20026810">Bladé J, Dimopoulos M, Rosiñol L, et al.: Smoldering (asymptomatic) multiple myeloma: current diagnostic criteria, new predictors of outcome, and follow-up recommendations. J Clin Oncol 28 (4): 690-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12535504" MedlineID="22422929">He Y, Wheatley K, Clark O, et al.: Early versus deferred treatment for early stage multiple myeloma. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (1): CD004023, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10755397" MedlineID="20216173">Riccardi A, Mora O, Tinelli C, et al.: Long-term survival of stage I multiple myeloma given chemotherapy just after diagnosis or at progression of the disease: a multicentre randomized study. Cooperative Group of Study and Treatment of Multiple Myeloma. Br J Cancer 82 (7): 1254-60, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="17582068">Kyle RA, Remstein ED, Therneau TM, et al.: Clinical course and prognosis of smoldering (asymptomatic) multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 356 (25): 2582-90, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_87"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037790">Waldenström macroglobulinemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Waldenström Macroglobulinemia (Lymphoplasmacytic Lymphoma)</Title><Para id="_88">For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811546#_28" url="/types/lymphoma/hp/indolent-b-cell-lymphoma-treatment-pdq">Lymphoplasmacytic Lymphoma (Waldenström Macroglobulinemia)</SummaryRef> section in Indolent B-Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_89"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041558">solitary osseous plasmacytoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Isolated Plasmacytoma of Bone</Title><SummarySection id="_90"><Title>Treatment Options for Isolated Plasmacytoma of Bone</Title><Para id="_91">Treatment options for isolated plasmacytoma of bone include:</Para><OrderedList id="_92" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_93" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef> to the lesion.
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_96" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef> (if monoclonal [or myeloma] protein [M protein] increases and other evidence of symptomatic multiple
myeloma occurs).</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_93"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_94">About 25% of patients have serum and/or urine M protein present. Generally, this disappears after adequate radiation therapy to the lytic lesion. </Para><Para id="_95">The survival rate of patients with
isolated plasmacytoma of bone treated with radiation therapy to the lesion is greater than 50%
at 10 years, which is more favorable than the survival rate of patients with disseminated multiple
myeloma.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_96"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_97">Most patients eventually develop disseminated disease and
require chemotherapy. Almost 50% of patients do so within 2 years of
diagnosis.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> However, patients with serum paraprotein or Bence Jones
protein, who have complete disappearance of these proteins after radiation
therapy, may remain free of disease for prolonged periods.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Patients with a negative flow cytometry on bone marrow examination for plasma cell infiltration are also unlikely to relapse.<Reference refidx="5"/> Patients with progression to multiple myeloma often have good responses to
chemotherapy, with a median survival of 63 months after progression.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_89_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_89_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11316553" MedlineID="21216612">Tsang RW, Gospodarowicz MK, Pintilie M, et al.: Solitary plasmacytoma treated with radiotherapy: impact of tumor size on outcome. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 50 (1): 113-20, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9719116" MedlineID="98383598">Liebross RH, Ha CS, Cox JD, et al.: Solitary bone plasmacytoma: outcome and prognostic factors following radiotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 41 (5): 1063-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10979944" MedlineID="20435328">Dimopoulos MA, Moulopoulos LA, Maniatis A, et al.: Solitary plasmacytoma of bone and asymptomatic multiple myeloma. Blood 96 (6): 2037-44, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1548521" MedlineID="92193968">Dimopoulos MA, Goldstein J, Fuller L, et al.: Curability of solitary bone plasmacytoma. J Clin Oncol 10 (4): 587-90, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="24876564">Paiva B, Chandia M, Vidriales MB, et al.: Multiparameter flow cytometry for staging of solitary bone plasmacytoma: new criteria for risk of progression to myeloma. Blood 124 (8): 1300-3, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_100"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041865">extramedullary plasmacytoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Extramedullary Plasmacytoma</Title><SummarySection id="_101"><Title>Treatment Options for Extramedullary Plasmacytoma</Title><Para id="_102">Treatment options for extramedullary plasmacytoma include:</Para><OrderedList id="_103" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Radiation therapy to the isolated lesion with fields that cover
the regional lymph nodes, if possible.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem>In some cases, surgical resection may be considered, but it is usually
followed by radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="2"/>
</ListItem><ListItem>If the presence of monoclonal (or myeloma) protein (M protein) persists or reappears, the patient may need further
radiation therapy.  In some patients, the plasmacytoma may shrink, but not disappear, and
the M protein persists.  Close follow-up is generally warranted for these patients.   Surgery
is often performed if the plasmacytoma is in a site where it can be removed
easily (e.g., in the tonsil); the M protein may disappear from the blood or
urine.
In other cases, persistence or an increasing M protein may herald progression to multiple myeloma.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy is required if the disease progresses and causes symptoms.
</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_104">Patients with isolated plasma cell tumors of soft tissues, most commonly
occurring in the tonsils, nasopharynx, or paranasal sinuses,  may need to  have
skeletal x-rays and bone marrow biopsy (both of which are most often  negative) and
evaluation for M protein in serum and urine.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_105">About 25% of patients have serum and/or urine M protein; this frequently  disappears after adequate radiation. </Para><Para id="_106">Extramedullary plasmacytoma  is a highly curable disease. Progression-free survival rates range from 70% to 87% at 10 to 14 years after treatment with radiation therapy  (with or without previous resection).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_100_sid_8"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_100_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11316553" MedlineID="21216612">Tsang RW, Gospodarowicz MK, Pintilie M, et al.: Solitary plasmacytoma treated with radiotherapy: impact of tumor size on outcome. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 50 (1): 113-20, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10357398" MedlineID="99284290">Alexiou C, Kau RJ, Dietzfelbinger H, et al.: Extramedullary plasmacytoma: tumor occurrence and therapeutic concepts. Cancer 85 (11): 2305-14, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="3102035" MedlineID="87130620">Meis JM, Butler JJ, Osborne BM, et al.: Solitary plasmacytomas of bone and extramedullary plasmacytomas. A clinicopathologic and immunohistochemical study. Cancer 59 (8): 1475-85, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1606070" MedlineID="92297509">Soesan M, Paccagnella A, Chiarion-Sileni V, et al.: Extramedullary plasmacytoma: clinical behaviour and response to treatment. Ann Oncol 3 (1): 51-7, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="12062614" MedlineID="22058041">Strojan P, Soba E, Lamovec J, et al.: Extramedullary plasmacytoma: clinical and histopathologic study. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 53 (3): 692-701, 2002.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_107"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042947">multiple myeloma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Multiple Myeloma</Title><SummarySection id="_108"><Title>Initial Evaluation</Title><Para id="_109">The initial approach to the patient is to evaluate the following parameters:</Para><OrderedList id="_110" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Detection and quantification of a monoclonal (or myeloma) protein (M protein) in the serum or urine, and possible immunoparesis (suppression of the other uninvolved immunoglobulins [Ig]).<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem> Detection of more than 10% of plasma cells on a bone marrow examination, along with flow cytometry, cytogenetics, and fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization  testing.</ListItem><ListItem>Detection of lytic bone lesions or generalized osteoporosis in skeletal
x-rays, or whole-body or spinal and pelvic magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans, or focal bone lesions on positron emission tomography-computed tomography (CT) scan.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem>Presence of soft tissue plasmacytomas.</ListItem><ListItem>Serum albumin and beta-2-microglobulin levels.</ListItem><ListItem>Detection of free kappa and free lambda serum Ig light chain, with calculation of the serum free light chain ratio.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem><ListItem>Presence of hypercalcemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Detection of renal dysfunction attributable to the plasma cell dyscrasia (induced by gammopathy or amyloidosis).</ListItem><ListItem>Presence of anemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Presence of circulating plasma cells.</ListItem><ListItem>Presence of hyperviscosity. Asymptomatic patients usually respond to myeloma therapy; plasma exchange is indicated with hemorrhagic or central nervous system manifestations.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_111">Treatment selection is influenced by
the age and general health of the patient, previous therapy, and the presence of
disease complications.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_460"><Title>Therapeutic Overview</Title><Para id="_461">Despite the introduction of many new therapeutic agents over the past two decades, there is still no confirmed curative approach.  </Para><SummarySection id="_664"><Title>Indolent myeloma (smoldering multiple myeloma)</Title><Para id="_1332">For information on watchful waiting versus immediate therapy for patients with asymptomatic smoldering myeloma, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_59" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Asymptomatic Plasma Cell Neoplasms (Smoldering Multiple Myeloma)</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_666"><Title>Symptomatic myeloma</Title><Para id="_667">Newly diagnosed patients who require therapy fall into two categories: (1) patients in good or well-controlled health (previously referred to as the fit, transplant-eligible patient) or (2) the less-fit patient with significant comorbidities or advanced age (previously referred to as not transplant eligible). Comorbidities and performance status are important determinants to help decide about fitness of patients at all ages, especially those between the ages of 70 years and 80 years. Nomograms exist for geriatric patients to define life expectancy independent of the myeloma diagnosis.<Reference refidx="7"/> Age, organ dysfunction, and risk of cardiovascular and thrombotic complications influence the choice of induction therapies. These factors are also important when considering consolidation therapies, such as chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy, bispecific antibody therapy, and autologous stem cell transplant (SCT) consolidation. Most patients also receive a bisphosphonate or RANKL inhibitor to prevent skeletal-related complications.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> </Para><Para id="_817">The International Myeloma Working Group has issued guidance for the diagnosis and management of patients with renal impairment.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><SummarySection id="_668"><Title>Fit patients in good or well-controlled health</Title><Para id="_669">Patients in good or well-controlled health may receive induction chemotherapy with a four-drug (quadruplet) or three-drug (triplet) approach that includes bortezomib in the absence of a clinical trial. The most commonly used regimens include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_670" Style="bullet"><ListItem>D-VRd: daratumumab + bortezomib + lenalidomide + dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem>I-VRd: isatuximab + bortezomib + lenalidomide + dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem>D-CVRd: daratumumab + cyclophosphamide + bortezomib + lenalidomide + dexamethasone.</ListItem><ListItem>VRd: bortezomib + lenalidomide + dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/></ListItem><ListItem>CyBorD: cyclophosphamide + bortezomib + dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> This regimen is preferred in the presence of significant renal dysfunction (creatinine clearance less than 45 cc/min). If the renal function recovers rapidly, some clinicians switch to VRd.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_672">After 4 to 8 months of therapy, patients with disease response may undergo autologous SCT consolidation.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="21"/> The previously standard autologous SCT consolidation has been questioned because a large, prospective, randomized trial failed to demonstrate an overall survival (OS) benefit.<Reference refidx="22"/> Maintenance therapy is then implemented until the time of relapse.<Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/> At relapse, subsequent therapies are given sequentially by using previously successful drugs (if the interval of time since previous exposure is &gt;1 year) or newer drugs not previously tried.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_673"><Title>Less-fit patients with significant comorbidities or advanced age (aged ≥80 years) </Title><Para id="_674">The less-fit patient may receive induction chemotherapy with a triplet or quadruplet regimen (as described for the patient in good or well-controlled health, but with dosage adjustments) including the CD38-directed monoclonal antibodies daratumumab or isatuximab, or with a doublet regimen including daratumumab or isatuximab, which might be better tolerated.<Reference refidx="26"/> Therapy is continued until maximal response, and then maintenance therapy is given until relapse.<Reference refidx="27"/> At relapse, subsequent therapies are given sequentially (as described for the patient in good or well-controlled health). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_675"><Title>High risk versus standard risk</Title><Para id="_677">Patients with newly diagnosed or relapsing myeloma can be identified as having standard-risk or high-risk disease. This determination is made based on cytogenetics, genetic aberrations detected by fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization, and possibly the genetic expression profile analyses that are in the process of standardization.<Reference refidx="28"/> Plasma cell leukemia at presentation, or as a leukemic evolution of refractory myeloma, is a particularly high-risk, poor-prognosis entity.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/> Plasma cell leukemia with an ultra-high poor prognosis is defined by the presence of more than 2% circulating tumor plasma cells by flow cytometry.<Reference refidx="34"/> Higher-risk patients are candidates for clinical trials using newer agents upfront or newer combination therapies currently used for relapsed disease at the discretion of the clinician.<Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/> Beyond induction therapy, high-risk disease can warrant more aggressive strategies, such as tandem transplant or consideration of allogeneic SCT. More intensive maintenance therapies may also be given for high-risk disease; instead of using lenalidomide alone, lenalidomide plus bortezomib has been chosen based on prior trials using thalidomide.<Reference refidx="38"/> These more aggressive strategies have been implemented because of poor responsiveness to standard regimens and the worse prognosis of high-risk patients. Ultimately, prospective randomized trials are needed to establish improved outcomes with these newer approaches for high-risk patients.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1196"><Title>Measurable Residual Disease</Title><Para id="_1197">The assessment of measurable residual disease (MRD) in the bone marrow is mandatory for the assessment of efficacy in clinical trials.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/> Does MRD testing outside of the trial setting yield meaningful clinical improvement in patient outcomes by informing selection or duration of therapy? Achievement of MRD negativity after induction therapy (with or without consolidation therapy) is associated with improved progression-free survival (PFS) and improved OS.<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/><Reference refidx="52"/> While MRD negativity may be useful for the design of clinical trials, there are no data suggesting that this interim marker improves outcomes by altering subsequent therapy. Similarly, there are no data to suggest that sustained MRD negativity can allow deintensification or discontinuation of maintenance therapy.<Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/> Using peripheral blood to assess for MRD appears feasible with next-generation flow and mass spectroscopy. This approach is less-invasive than using bone marrow.<Reference refidx="55"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_112"><Title>Induction Therapy</Title><Para id="_679">Patients with myeloma who are symptomatic or require therapy because of progression or adverse laboratory findings require induction therapy. Ideally, induction therapy should reduce tumor burden, provide symptomatic relief, and prevent further end-organ damage.</Para><SummarySection id="_680"><Title>Fit patients in good or well-controlled health</Title><Para id="_681">Two prospective  randomized trials evaluated induction therapy with the D-VRd regimen (which includes daratumumab, an anti-CD38 monoclonal antibody)  in fit patients in good or well-controlled health. Another prospective randomized trial evaluated I-VRd (which includes isatuximab, another anti-CD38 monoclonal antibody) as an alternative induction therapy.</Para><OrderedList id="_682" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective trial included 709 transplant-eligible patients with newly diagnosed myeloma. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either D-VRd or VRd. All patients received an autologous SCT and subsequent lenalidomide maintenance therapy.<Reference refidx="56"/><ItemizedList id="_1262" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 47.5 months, the 4-year PFS rate was 84.3% in the D-VRd group and 67.7% in the VRd group (hazard ratio [HR], 0.42; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.30–0.59; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="56"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The complete response rate was 87.9% in the  D-VRd group and 70.1% in the VRd group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). The percentage of patients who achieved MRD-negative status favored D-VRd (75.2% vs. 47.5%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).</ListItem><ListItem>The most common grade 3 or 4 adverse event was neutropenia, which occurred in 62% of patients who received D-VRd and 51% of patients who received VRd.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The phase II <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02874742">GRIFFIN</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT02874742) enrolled 207 patients with newly diagnosed transplant-eligible multiple myeloma. Patients were randomly assigned to receive induction therapy with either D-VRd or VRd. Patients then received an autologous SCT, two more cycles of the induction regimen, and 2 years of maintenance therapy with Dara-R (daratumumab and lenalidomide) or lenalidomide alone depending on the original randomization.<Reference refidx="57"/> <ItemizedList id="_1263" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 49.6 months, the percentage of patients with a stringent complete response was 67% in the D-VRd group and 48% in the VRd group (odds ratio [OR], 2.18; 95% CI, 1.22–3.89; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0079).<Reference refidx="57"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]  </ListItem><ListItem>The 4-year PFS rate was 87.2% in the  D-VRd group and 70.0% in the VRd  group (HR, 0.45; 95% CI, 0.21–0.95; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .032).<Reference refidx="57"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The median OS was not reached in either group (HR, 0.90; 95% CI, 0.31–2.56; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .84).</ListItem><ListItem>A Markov model using MRD status to predict PFS suggested improved quality of life and lower cost over 10 years with the use of daratumumab in the first-line setting.<Reference refidx="58"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective trial, reported in abstract form, included 662 transplant-eligible patients with newly diagnosed myeloma. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either I-VRd or VRd. All patients received an autologous SCT and subsequent lenalidomide maintenance therapy.<Reference refidx="13"/><ItemizedList id="_1333" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 47.0 months, the 3-year PFS rate was 83% in the I-VRd group and 75% in the VRd group (HR, 0.70; 95% CI, 0.52–0.94; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Isatuximab is given intravenously (IV), unlike daratumumab, which is given subcutaneously.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1161">A more intensive regimen of induction therapy, consolidation therapy, and maintenance therapy was investigated in patients with high-risk cytogenetic abnormalities.</Para><OrderedList id="_1162" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In the multicenter phase II <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03188172">OPTIMUM</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT03188172), 412 newly diagnosed patients were screened to identify 103 patients with ultra–high-risk (UHR) myeloma or plasma cell leukemia.<Reference refidx="59"/> UHR myeloma was defined by the presence of at least two specified genetic risk markers (t(4;14), t(14;16), t(14;20), del (1p), 1q gain, and del 17p)) and/or <GeneName>SKY92</GeneName> gene expression risk signature. All patients were treated with D-CVRd induction for six cycles (or until maximum response), autologous SCT consolidation, and D-VRd consolidation followed by Dara-R maintenance.<Reference refidx="60"/><ItemizedList id="_1163" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 41.2 months, the 30-month PFS rate was 77% (95% CI, 69%–81%) for patients who  received the study treatment  versus 40% (95% CI, 31%–49%) for an historical control group who received KCRD (carfilzomib, cyclophosphamide, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone).<Reference refidx="59"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>] The 30-month OS rate was 84% (95% CI, 76%–91%) for patients who received the OPTIMUM regimen and 74% (95% CI, 66%–82%) for the historical control KCRD regimen.<Reference refidx="59"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The study design did not prove that D-CVRd is the preferred regimen for patients with UHR myeloma, but it is a feasible regimen for further randomized trials in this patient population.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_686">In transplant-eligible patients, alkylators such as melphalan are avoided upfront to prevent stem cell toxicity with subsequent risks for cytopenias, secondary malignancies, or poor stem cell harvesting.<Reference refidx="61"/> Bortezomib is given subcutaneously, which helps to avoid the neuropathies that were much more severe with IV administration.<Reference refidx="62"/><Reference refidx="63"/><Reference refidx="64"/> Bortezomib is also preferred for patients with renal impairment.<Reference refidx="65"/> Patients receiving a bortezomib-containing regimen need prophylaxis for herpes zoster (usually with valacyclovir or acyclovir). Lenalidomide is given orally and can cause an increased risk of deep venous thrombosis (DVT) or pulmonary embolism, requiring additional prophylactic medication.<Reference refidx="66"/><Reference refidx="67"/> Because lenalidomide is metabolized erratically in patients with renal failure, clinicians may choose the CyBorD regimen,<Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> but this selection is empiric and not based on randomized trial results. For patients without extra risk factors for DVT, aspirin (81 mg daily) suffices, but stronger anticoagulants should be considered for patients with multiple risk factors who receive lenalidomide (or other similar immunomodulating agents such as pomalidomide or thalidomide). Lower doses of lenalidomide must be used for patients with renal dysfunction.<Reference refidx="68"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_809"><Title>Less-fit patients with significant comorbidities or advanced age (aged ≥80 years) </Title><Para id="_810">Triplet or quadruplet therapies such as VRd and CyBorD with daratumumab or isatuximab can be used in patients with adequate fitness and minimal comorbidities. When triplets are deemed too difficult, doublets with Vd (bortezomib plus dexamethasone) or Rd (lenalidomide plus dexamethasone) can be used, or even a triplet such as VMP (bortezomib, melphalan, and prednisone).<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="26"/> Therapeutic options have changed with the advent of daratumumab and isatuximab, the CD38-directed monoclonal antibodies. </Para><OrderedList id="_811" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial, reported in abstract form, included 395 patients with newly diagnosed myeloma who were aged 70 years or older or ineligible for autologous SCT with medical comorbidities. Patients received D-VRd or VRd.<Reference refidx="69"/><ItemizedList id="_1334" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 58.7 months, the 2-year MRD negativity (10<Superscript>-6</Superscript>) was 32.0% for patients who received D-VRd and 15.7% for patients who received VRd (HR, 0.40; 95% CI, 0.24–0.64; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001).<Reference refidx="69"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03319667">NCT03319667</ProtocolRef>) was conducted in 446 patients with newly diagnosed myeloma who were ineligible for transplant. Patients were randomly assigned in a 3:2 ratio to receive either I-VRd or VRd alone.<Reference refidx="14"/><ItemizedList id="_1335" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 59.7 months, the 5-year PFS rate was 63.2% for patients who received I-VRd versus 45.2% for patients who received VRd alone (HR, 0.60; 98.5% CI, 0.41–0.88; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Isatuximab is given IV, unlike daratumumab, which is given subcutaneously (with significantly less side effects than the IV formulation).</ListItem><ListItem>Serious adverse events were similar in the two groups.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02252172">NCT02252172</ProtocolRef>) of 737 patients with newly diagnosed myeloma who were ineligible for transplant, daratumumab plus lenalidomide and dexamethasone was compared with Rd alone.<Reference refidx="70"/><ItemizedList id="_818" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 56.2 months, the 60-month OS rate was 66.3% (95% CI, 60.8%–71.3%) for patients who received daratumumab and 53.1% (95% CI, 47.2%–58.6%) for patients who received Rd alone (HR, 0.68; 95% CI, 0.53–0.86; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0013).<Reference refidx="70"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 56.2 months, the 60-month PFS rate was 52.5% for patients who received daratumumab (95% CI, 46.7%−58.0%) and 28.7% for patients who received Rd alone (95% CI, 23.1%−34.6%) (HR, 0.53; 95% CI, 0.43−0.66; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis>  &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="70"/></ListItem><ListItem>Results for the percentage of patients falling below the threshold for MRD (&lt;1 tumor cell per 10<Superscript>5</Superscript> white cells) favored the daratumumab combination, 24.2% versus 7.3% (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).</ListItem><ListItem>The daratumumab combination resulted in significant and sustained reductions of pain scores and improved quality of life in the EuroQOL 5-dimensional descriptive visual system.<Reference refidx="71"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810021" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial of 706 patients with newly diagnosed myeloma who were ineligible for transplant, daratumumab plus VMP was compared with VMP alone.<Reference refidx="72"/><ItemizedList id="_812" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 40.1 months, the 3-year OS rate favored the daratumumab combination group at 78% (95% CI, 73.2%−83.0%) versus 67.9% in the VMP-alone group (95% CI, 62.6%−72.6%) (HR, 0.60; 95% CI, 0.46−0.80; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003).<Reference refidx="72"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 40.1 months, the 3-year PFS rate favored the daratumumab combination group at  50.7% (95% CI, 45.1%−55.9%) versus 18.5% in the VMP-alone group (95% CI, 14.4%−23.1%) (HR, 0.42; 95% CI, 0.34−0.51; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="72"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>In the daratumumab combination group,  22.3% of patients were MRD negative (at a threshold of one tumor cell per 10<Superscript>5</Superscript> white cells); in the VMP-alone group, 6.2% of patients were MRD negative (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_813">Immunological reaction to the initial dose of daratumumab can be modulated by splitting the first infusion over 2 days or using the subcutaneous version (this dosing schedule is not approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration).</Para></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04751877">NCT04751877</ProtocolRef>), 270 patients with newly diagnosed myeloma who were transplant ineligible and aged 65 to 79 years received either I-VRd or  isatuximab plus Rd.<Reference refidx="73"/><ItemizedList id="_1284" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 23.5 months, the MRD negativity rates (at 10<Superscript>-5</Superscript>)  at 18 months were 53% for the I-VRd group and 26% for the isatuximab-Rd group (OR, 3.16; 95% CI, 1.89–5.28; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="73"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Isatuximab is given IV, unlike daratumumab, which is given subcutaneously (with significantly less side effects than the IV formulation).</ListItem><ListItem>Serious adverse events were similar in the two groups.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial, 955 patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma who were ineligible for transplant received either carfilzomib plus melphalan and prednisone or VMP.<Reference refidx="74"/><ItemizedList id="_819" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 23 months, there was no difference in median PFS (22.3 vs. 22.1 months; HR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.75−1.10; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .159) or in median OS (HR, 1.1; 95% CI, 0.82−1.4).<Reference refidx="74"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective trial, 1,087 patients with standard-risk or intermediate-risk myeloma who deferred transplant for induction therapy were randomly assigned to receive carfilzomib plus lenalidomide and dexamethasone or bortezomib plus lenalidomide and dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="75"/> <ItemizedList id="_1062" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 26 months, there was no difference in median PFS (34.6 vs. 34.4 months; HR, 1.04; 95% CI, 0.83−1.31; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .742) or in median OS (HR, 0.98; 95% CI, 0.71−1.36; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .923).<Reference refidx="75"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Many other phase II and phase III trials, published in preliminary abstract form, show results similar to the trial that combined daratumumab with melphalan and prednisone, and used daratumumab with other triplets and doublets in both previously untreated and previously treated patients.<Reference refidx="76"/><Reference refidx="77"/> Further follow-up is required to establish OS benefits. Mature OS data are required to better assess the cost-effectiveness of daratumumab in the first-line setting.<Reference refidx="78"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_171"><Title>Consolidation Therapy</Title><SummarySection id="_172"><Title>Autologous bone marrow or peripheral stem cell transplant</Title><Para id="_173">Evidence (autologous bone marrow or peripheral SCT):</Para><Para id="_174">The failure of conventional therapy to cure myeloma has led
investigators to test the effectiveness of much higher doses of drugs such as
melphalan.  The development of techniques for harvesting hematopoietic stem
cells, from marrow aspirates or the peripheral blood of the patient, and
infusing these cells to promote hematopoietic recovery made it possible for
investigators to test very large doses of chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_175">Based on the experience of treating
thousands of patients  in this way, it is possible to draw a few
conclusions:</Para><ItemizedList id="_176" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The risk of early death caused by  treatment-related toxic effects has been
reduced to less than 3% in highly selected populations.<Reference refidx="79"/></ListItem><ListItem>Extensive prior chemotherapy, especially with alkylating agents,
compromises marrow hemopoiesis and may make the harvesting of adequate numbers
of hematopoietic stem cells impossible.<Reference refidx="61"/></ListItem><ListItem>Younger patients in good health tolerate high-dose therapy better than
older patients with a poor performance status.<Reference refidx="80"/><Reference refidx="81"/><Reference refidx="82"/> However, fit patients older than 70 to 75 years can receive autologous SCT consolidation.<Reference refidx="83"/><Reference refidx="84"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_177"><Title>Single autologous bone marrow or peripheral stem cell transplant</Title><Para id="_178">Evidence (single autologous bone marrow or peripheral SCT):</Para><OrderedList id="_652" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>While some prospective randomized trials showed improved survival for patients who received autologous peripheral stem cell or bone marrow transplant after induction chemotherapy compared with chemotherapy alone,<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="85"/><Reference refidx="86"/><Reference refidx="87"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  other trials have not shown any survival advantage.<Reference refidx="88"/><Reference refidx="89"/><Reference refidx="90"/><Reference refidx="91"/><Reference refidx="92"/><Reference refidx="93"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01208662">NCT01208662</ProtocolRef>), 722 patients aged 65 years or younger with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma received either VRd for three cycles followed by autologous SCT consolidation and two more cycles of VRd or VRd alone for eight cycles. Both groups received maintenance lenalidomide given continuously in the absence of disease relapse or unacceptable side effects.<Reference refidx="94"/> At relapse, patients who received VRd only (without autologous SCT) were re-induced and offered transplant if they were still responding.<ItemizedList id="_1127" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 76.0 months, the median PFS was shorter for patients in the nontransplant arm (42.0 months)  than for patients in the transplant arm (67.5 months) (HR, 1.53; 95% CI, 1.23–1.91; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="94"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year OS rate was not significantly different: 79.2% for patients in the nontransplant arm versus 80.7% for patients in the transplant arm (HR, 1.10; 95% CI, 0.73–1.65; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &gt; 0.99).</ListItem><ListItem>Rates of grade 3 or 4 hematologic adverse events were significantly higher in the transplant arm (41.9%) than in the nontransplant arm (26.1%) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). Acute myeloid leukemia  (AML) or myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS) were only reported in the transplant arm (10 cases).</ListItem><ListItem>Only 28% of patients who received VRd originally received autologous SCT at any time after the end of study treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Three meta-analyses of almost 3,000 patients showed no survival advantage.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="95"/><Reference refidx="96"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>A meta-analysis was performed for all randomized clinical trials conducted between 2000 and 2021 that compared up-front autologous SCT with standard-dose therapy/consolidation. A total of  3,307 citations were screened: six trials were selected for PFS analysis and four trials were selected for OS analysis (2,959 patients).<Reference refidx="97"/><ItemizedList id="_1198" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 3.1 to 7.8 years, patients with high-risk cytogenetics (t(4;14), t(14;16), and/or del(17p)) had a significant OS benefit from autologous SCT versus standard-dose therapy (HR, 0.66; 95% CI, 0.45–0.97; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03).<Reference refidx="97"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810019" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A2</LOERef>] No survival benefit was seen for patients with standard-risk cytogenetics.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients with high-risk disease (approximately 20% of the total) showed a significant PFS benefit from autologous SCT versus standard-dose therapy (HR, 0.52; 95% CI, 0.33–0.83). Patients with standard-risk disease also showed a PFS benefit from autologous SCT (HR, 0.65; 95% CI, 0.56–0.76).<Reference refidx="97"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_181">Even the trials suggesting improved survival showed no signs of a slowing in the relapse rate or a plateau to suggest that any of these patients had been cured.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="85"/><Reference refidx="86"/><Reference refidx="87"/><Reference refidx="98"/> The role of autologous SCT has changed, from a mandated standard consolidation for those patients healthy enough to undergo it toward a therapeutic option, like any other, that offers approximately 2 years of increased PFS on average with defined toxicities. Incorporating, eliminating, delaying, or even replacing autologous SCT in the future (perhaps with chimeric antigen receptor T cells or bispecific antibodies) will be the subject of ongoing and upcoming clinical trials. Subgroups of patients may have a particular benefit from autologous SCT. Patients with a t(11;14) translocation may show differential benefit, as found in a retrospective review of 3,538 total patients in a dataset from the Center of International Blood and Marrow Transplant Research.<Reference refidx="99"/> One meta-analysis of only four randomized clinical trials suggested an OS benefit for up-front autologous SCT in patients with high-risk cytogenetics.<Reference refidx="97"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_182"><Title>Tandem autologous bone marrow or peripheral stem cell transplant followed by autologous or allogeneic transplant</Title><Para id="_183">Another approach to high-dose therapy has been the use of two sequential infusions
of high-dose therapy with stem cell support (tandem transplants).<Reference refidx="100"/><Reference refidx="101"/><Reference refidx="102"/><Reference refidx="103"/><Reference refidx="104"/></Para><Para id="_184">Evidence (tandem autologous bone marrow or peripheral SCT):</Para><OrderedList id="_185" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A meta-analysis of six randomized clinical trials enrolling 1,803 patients compared single autologous hematopoietic cell transplant  with tandem autologous hematopoietic cell transplant.<ItemizedList id="_186" Style="bullet"><ListItem>There was no difference in OS (HR, 0.94; 95% CI, 0.77–1.14) or in event-free survival (EFS) (HR, 0.86; 95% CI, 0.70–1.05).<Reference refidx="105"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810019" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A2</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial of 758 patients who completed induction therapy in less than 12 months compared autologous SCT plus lenalidomide maintenance, tandem autologous SCT, and autologous SCT plus VRd maintenance.<Reference refidx="106"/><ItemizedList id="_871" Style="bullet"><ListItem>There was no difference in 38-month PFS (53.9%−58.5%) and OS (81.8%−85.4%) rates among these three randomized groups.<Reference refidx="106"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Five different groups have compared single or tandem autologous transplants with one autologous transplant followed by a reduced-intensity conditioning allograft from a HLA-identical sibling; treatment assignment was based on the presence or absence of an HLA-identical sibling. The results have been discordant for survival in these nonrandomized trials.<Reference refidx="107"/><Reference refidx="108"/><Reference refidx="109"/><Reference refidx="110"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Six clinical trials compared the outcomes of patients receiving tandem autologous transplant with those of patients receiving a reduced-intensity allogeneic SCT after autologous transplant.  Patients were assigned to the latter treatments based on the availability of an HLA-matched donor.  Two meta-analyses of these data showed that although the complete remission rate was higher in patients undergoing reduced-intensity allogeneic SCT, OS was comparable because of an increased incidence of nonrelapse mortality with allogeneic transplant.<Reference refidx="111"/><Reference refidx="112"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_405">A Cochrane review of 14 controlled studies found none of the trials helpful for contemporary treatment decisions regarding single versus tandem transplants.<Reference refidx="113"/> None of the trials used bortezomib or lenalidomide, and the sharp decrease in compliance with a second transplant complicated sample-size calculations for sufficient statistical power.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_193"><Title>Allogeneic bone marrow or peripheral stem cell transplant</Title><Para id="_194">Evidence (allogeneic bone marrow or peripheral SCT):</Para><Para id="_361">Many patients are not young enough or healthy enough to
undergo these intensive approaches.  A definite graft-versus-myeloma effect has
been demonstrated, including regression of myeloma relapses after the
infusion of donor lymphocytes.<Reference refidx="114"/></Para><Para id="_196">Favorable prognostic features included:</Para><ItemizedList id="_197" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Low tumor burden.</ListItem><ListItem>Responsive disease before transplant.</ListItem><ListItem>Application of transplant after
first-line therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_199">Myeloablative allogeneic SCT  has significant toxic effects (15%–40% mortality), but the possibility of a potent and
possibly curative graft-versus-myeloma effect  in a minority of patients may offset the high transplant-related mortality.<Reference refidx="114"/><Reference refidx="115"/><Reference refidx="116"/> In one anecdotal series of 60 patients who underwent allogeneic SCT, six of the patients relapsed between 6 and 12 years, suggesting that late relapses still occur with this type of consolidation.<Reference refidx="117"/></Para><Para id="_200"> The lower transplant-related mortality from nonmyeloablative approaches has been accompanied by a greater risk of relapse.<Reference refidx="116"/> Since the introduction of lenalidomide and bortezomib, a trial exploring donor versus no donor comparison of autologous SCT versus autologous SCT and nonmyeloablative allogeneic SCT in 260 untreated patients showed no difference in PFS or OS.<Reference refidx="118"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] This result contrasted with two older trials (before introduction of lenalidomide and bortezomib), which suggested improvement of PFS and OS with a sibling donor.<Reference refidx="109"/><Reference refidx="119"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] </Para><Para id="_446">	Six clinical trials compared the outcomes of patients receiving tandem autologous transplant with those of patients receiving a reduced-intensity  autologous SCT after autologous transplant.  Patients were assigned to the latter treatments based on the availability of an HLA-matched donor.  Two meta-analyses of these data showed that although the complete remission rate was higher in patients undergoing reduced-intensity autologous SCT, OS was comparable because of an increased incidence of nonrelapse mortality with allogeneic transplant.<Reference refidx="111"/><Reference refidx="112"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] Anecdotal long-term survivals have been reported for patients with therapy-related MDS, AML, acute lymphoblastic leukemia, or chronic myelomonocytic leukemia treated with allogeneic SCT.<Reference refidx="120"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_660"><Title>Salvage autologous bone marrow or peripheral stem cell transplant after relapse from first transplant</Title><Para id="_661">After relapsing more than 24 months after autologous SCT, 174 patients received reinduction therapy and were then randomly assigned to receive either high-dose melphalan and salvage autologous SCT or oral weekly cyclophosphamide.<Reference refidx="121"/> With a median follow-up of 52 months, the median OS was superior for salvage autologous SCT: 67 months (95% CI, 55–not estimable) versus 52 months (42–60) (HR, 0.56; 0.35–0.90; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .017).<Reference refidx="121"/><Reference refidx="122"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_820">In a retrospective review of 233 patients with refractory myeloma or relapsed and refractory myeloma who underwent a salvage autologous SCT, 81% of patients achieved a partial response (PR) or better.<Reference refidx="123"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_201"><Title>Maintenance Therapy </Title><Para id="_202">Myeloma patients who respond to treatment show a progressive fall in the
M protein until a plateau is reached; subsequent treatment with conventional
doses does not result in any further improvement.  This has led investigators
to question how long treatment should be continued. No clinical trial has directly compared a consolidation approach with a maintenance approach to assess which is better in prolonging remission and, ultimately, survival.<Reference refidx="124"/> Most clinical trials employ one or both.<Reference refidx="125"/><Reference refidx="126"/>  Maintenance trials with glucocorticosteroids <Reference refidx="127"/><Reference refidx="128"/> and with interferon <Reference refidx="129"/> showed very minor improvements in remission duration and survival but with toxicities that outweighed the benefits.  The efficacy and tolerability of thalidomide, lenalidomide, bortezomib, and ixazomib in the induction and relapse settings has made these agents attractive options in maintenance trials.<Reference refidx="124"/></Para><SummarySection id="_408"><Title>Maintenance therapy (lenalidomide, ixazomib, and daratumumab alone or in combination)</Title><Para id="_828">Evidence (maintenance therapy [lenalidomide, ixazomib, and daratumumab alone or in combination]):</Para><OrderedList id="_829" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The prospective randomized <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03901963">AURIGA</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT03901963) included 200 patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma who achieved a very good or better partial response, were MRD-positive on bone marrow (10<Superscript>-5</Superscript>), and who had not received daratumumab (or isatuximab) anti-CD38 therapy during induction therapy.<Reference refidx="130"/> Patients were randomly assigned to receive either Dara-R or lenalidomide alone.<ItemizedList id="_1354" Style="bullet"><ListItem>At a median follow-up of 32.3 months, the 30-month PFS rate was 82.7% for patients who received Dara-R and 66.4% for patients who received lenalidomide alone (HR, 0.53; 95% CI, 0.29–0.97; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .036).<Reference refidx="130"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>The MRD-negative (10<Superscript>-6</Superscript>) conversion rate was 23.2% for patients who received Dara-R and 5.0% for patients who received lenalidomide alone (OR, 5.97; 95% CI, 2.15–16.58; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0002).</ListItem><ListItem>Grade 3 or 4 cytopenias occurred in 54.2% of patients who received Dara-R versus 46.9% of patients who received lenalidomide alone. Infections occurred in 18.8% of patients who received Dara-R  versus 13.3% of patients who received lenalidomide alone.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial of 460 patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma who had completed induction therapy and autologous SCT compared lenalidomide maintenance with placebo.<Reference refidx="131"/><ItemizedList id="_872" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 91 months, the median OS for the lenalidomide maintenance group was 113.8 months (95% CI, 100.4−not reached) versus 84.1 months for the placebo group (range, 73.8−106.0 months; HR, 0.61; 95% CI, 0.46−0.80; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0004).<Reference refidx="131"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>This translated to a 5-year OS rate of 76% (95% CI, 70%−81%) for the lenalidomide group versus 64% (95% CI, 58%−70%) for the placebo group.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial evaluated lenalidomide maintenance in 1,917 patients newly diagnosed with or without transplant.<Reference refidx="132"/> <ItemizedList id="_830" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 31 months, lenalidomide showed improved median PFS, 39 months (95% CI, 36−42) versus 20 months (range, 18−22) (HR, 0.46; 95% CI, 0.41−0.53; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001), but lenalidomide failed to significantly improve the 3-year OS rate, 78.6% (95% CI, 75.6%−81.6%) versus 75.8% (72.4%−79.2%) (HR, 0.87; 95% CI, 0.73−1.05; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .15).<Reference refidx="132"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A meta-analysis included 1,208 patients with newly diagnosed disease who underwent an autologous SCT.<Reference refidx="133"/><ItemizedList id="_831" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 79.5 months, OS was not reached for the lenalidomide maintenance group versus 86 months for the placebo or observation group (HR, 0.75; 95% CI, 0.63‒0.90; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001).<Reference refidx="133"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810019" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A2</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A meta-analysis of 7,730 patients in randomized clinical trials investigated lenalidomide or thalidomide maintenance in patients with newly diagnosed myeloma, with or without transplant.<Reference refidx="134"/><ItemizedList id="_832" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The immunomodulatory maintenance therapy significantly improved PFS (HR, 0.62; 95% CI, 0.57−0.67; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001), but failed to significantly improve OS (HR, 0.93; 95% CI, 0.85−1.01; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .082).<Reference refidx="134"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A meta-analysis of 5,073 patients in randomized clinical trials investigated maintenance therapy in patients with newly diagnosed myeloma.<Reference refidx="135"/><ItemizedList id="_833" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lenalidomide (with or without prednisone) significantly improved PFS (HR, 0.47; 95% CI, 0.39−0.55), but also failed to significantly improve OS (HR, 0.76; 95% CI, 0.51−1.16).<Reference refidx="135"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial of lenalidomide maintenance versus no maintenance after induction with melphalan and prednisone or melphalan, prednisone, and lenalidomide included patients aged 65 years and older who were not eligible for transplant.<Reference refidx="27"/><ItemizedList id="_834" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The results showed a 66% reduction in the rate of progression (HR, 0.34; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001), which translated to an EFS of 31 months versus 14 months in favor of maintenance lenalidomide.<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02541383">CASSIOPEIA</ProtocolRef> [NCT02541383]) evaluated daratumumab maintenance versus no maintenance for patients with newly diagnosed myeloma. Patients had already received bortezomib, thalidomide, and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab as induction before autologous SCT.<Reference refidx="136"/><ItemizedList id="_1118" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 35.4 months after maintenance randomization, the median PFS was not reached in the daratumumab arm and was 46.7 months (40.0–not evaluable) with observation only (HR, 0.53; 95% CI, 0.42–0.68; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="136"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial evaluated ixazomib maintenance versus no maintenance for patients with newly diagnosed myeloma who were not undergoing autologous SCT after induction therapy.<Reference refidx="137"/><ItemizedList id="_1089" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 41 months, the median PFS favored ixazomib maintenance at 17.4 months versus 9.4 months (HR, 0.66; 95% CI, 0.54–0.80; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="137"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02659293">NCT02659293</ProtocolRef>) evaluated maintenance therapy in patients with newly diagnosed melanoma who had received induction therapy and autologous SCT. Patients were randomly assigned to receive maintenance therapy with either 3 years of carfilzomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone or lenalidomide alone.<Reference refidx="138"/><ItemizedList id="_1164" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 33.8 months, the median PFS was 59.1 months for patients who received the triplet maintenance therapy and  41.4 months for patients who received lenalidomide alone (HR, 0.51; 95% CI, 0.31–0.86; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .012).<Reference refidx="138"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Toxicity and efficacy data are not mature.<Reference refidx="138"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_835">All the trials and meta-analyses of lenalidomide maintenance showed a significant improvement in PFS, while OS was improved in one trial and one meta-analysis, both after autologous SCT. All of these trials showed an increase in myelodysplasia or acute leukemia from 3% to 7% for lenalidomide, consistent with other studies of lenalidomide.  This increased risk is mostly seen in patients with previous exposure to alkylating agents. Doses of 5 mg to 15 mg a day have been used either continuously or with 1 week off every month. </Para><Para id="_1355">One prospective trial found improved benefit in PFS for Dara-R compared with lenalidomide alone in a population that had undergone transplant and was naïve to anti-CD38 therapy.<Reference refidx="130"/> One trial establishing the D-VRd regimen for newly diagnosed patients  included Dara-R maintenance (for 2 to 3 years or longer) in the D-VRd induction arm.<Reference refidx="57"/> The incremental impact of Dara-R maintenance therapy in patients who received daratumumab induction therapy has not been established. It is also unclear if patients with MRD-negative (10<Superscript>-5</Superscript>) disease after induction therapy and transplant would benefit similarly since they were also not studied.<Reference refidx="139"/></Para><Para id="_1356">Among 556 patients in the <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01554852">Myeloma XI</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT01554852), those with del(1p), del(17p), and t(4;14) had a median PFS of 57.3 months with lenalidomide maintenance and 10.9 months with observation.<Reference refidx="140"/> For patients unable to receive lenalidomide maintenance, ixazomib is a reasonable alternative. Although maintenance therapy with carfilzomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone resulted in improved PFS when compared with lenalidomide alone, the preliminary toxicity and efficacy results must mature before implementing this regimen.<Reference refidx="138"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_410"><Title>Proteasome inhibitor maintenance therapy</Title><Para id="_836">Evidence (proteasome inhibitor maintenance therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_837" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial of 656 newly diagnosed patients with at least a PR after standard induction therapy followed by autologous SCT, ixazomib (the oral proteasome inhibitor) was compared with placebo.<Reference refidx="141"/><ItemizedList id="_838" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 31 months, the ixazomib maintenance improved medial PFS, 26.5 months (95% CI, 23.7−33.8) versus 21.3 months (95% CI, 18.0−24.7) (HR, 0.72; 95% CI, 0.58−0.89; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0023).<Reference refidx="141"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] There was no increase in second malignancies with the proteasome inhibitor (3% for both groups).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In 511 previously untreated patients not eligible for transplant and aged  65 years or older, a randomized comparison of bortezomib, melphalan, prednisone, thalidomide and subsequent maintenance using bortezomib plus thalidomide versus VMP (with no maintenance) showed superiority of the arm with thalidomide and bortezomib during induction and maintenance.<ItemizedList id="_839" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 47 months, the 3-year PFS rate was 55% versus 33% (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01), and the 5-year OS rate was 59% versus 46% (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .04).<Reference refidx="142"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>Because of trial design, it is unclear whether the improved results were caused by  the addition of thalidomide during the induction or by the use of maintenance therapy with bortezomib and thalidomide.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_687"><Strong>Summary:</Strong> After autologous SCT, patients are offered lenalidomide maintenance therapy based on the consistent PFS and occasional OS benefits previously described. But short-term and long-term toxicities, and financial toxicities, may prevent implementation.<Reference refidx="143"/><Reference refidx="144"/> High-risk patients, especially those with del(17p) or t(14;16), may require bortezomib maintenance (with or without lenalidomide), but this approach is not evidence-based and confirmatory clinical trials are required.<Reference refidx="145"/><Reference refidx="146"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_300"><Title>Management and Prevention of Myeloma Bone Disease</Title><Para id="_688">Myeloma bone disease is a consequence of increased osteoclastic activity, and agents that inhibit osteoclasts are an important component of myeloma therapy.<Reference refidx="9"/> The bisphosphonates pamidronate and zoledronate are used most often, via IV infusion, but the RANKL monoclonal antibody inhibitor denosumab, given subcutaneously, is also effective, especially when renal dysfunction precludes the use of bisphosphonates.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><SummarySection id="_689"><Title>Zoledronate (bisphosphonate)</Title><Para id="_690">Evidence (zoledronate):</Para><OrderedList id="_691" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial of 1,970 patients compared IV zoledronate with oral clodronate in newly diagnosed patients receiving induction chemotherapy with or without consolidation.<Reference refidx="147"/><ItemizedList id="_1259" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 3.7 years, zoledronate improved median OS from 44.5 months  to 50.0 months (HR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.74–0.96; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0118).<Reference refidx="147"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>In this trial, both bisphosphonates were continued until time of relapse.  As expected, skeletal-related events were also reduced in the zoledronate group (27% vs. 35%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .004).<Reference refidx="148"/><Reference refidx="149"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The improvement of median OS with zoledronate was confirmed in a Cochrane network meta-analysis.<Reference refidx="150"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810019" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A2</LOERef>] This meta-analysis also showed that 6 to 15 patients need treatment with bisphosphonates to prevent one skeletal-related event.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of zoledronate given once a month compared with zoledronate given every 12 weeks showed noninferiority for the 12-week regimen in 1,822 patients with bone metastases from breast cancer, prostate cancer, or multiple myeloma.<Reference refidx="151"/> However, this study included only 278 patients with myeloma, and evaluation of this subgroup was insufficiently powered to establish noninferiority for the 12-week regimen. Nonetheless, this trial is used as justification for implementing a 12-week schedule at the start of therapy or as soon as maximal response has been reached.</ListItem><ListItem> Bisphosphonates are associated with infrequent long-term complications (in 3%–5% of patients), including osteonecrosis of the jaw and avascular necrosis of the hip.<Reference refidx="152"/><Reference refidx="153"/> For more information about osteonecrosis of the jaw, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies</SummaryRef>. These side effects must be balanced against the potential benefits of bisphosphonates when bone metastases are evident.<Reference refidx="154"/> Bisphosphonates are usually given IV on a monthly basis for 2 years and then extended at the same schedule or at a reduced schedule (i.e., once every 3–4 months), if there is evidence of active myeloma bone disease.<Reference refidx="155"/><Reference refidx="156"/> On the aforementioned randomized trial,<Reference refidx="148"/> which showed OS advantage, patients received bisphosphonates monthly until time of relapse.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_692"><Title>Pamidronate (bisphosphonate)</Title><Para id="_693">Evidence (pamidronate):</Para><OrderedList id="_694" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A randomized, double-blind study of patients with stage III myeloma showed that
monthly IV pamidronate significantly reduced pathological fractures,
bone pain, spinal cord compression, and the need for bone radiation therapy (38% skeletal-related events were reported in the treatment group vs. 51% in the placebo
group after 21 months of therapy; <Emphasis>P </Emphasis>= .015).<Reference refidx="157"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] For more information about bisphosphonate therapy, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062738#_58" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-hp-pdq">Pharmacological Therapies for Pain Control</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Pain.</ListItem><ListItem>A double-blind, randomized, controlled trial of 504 patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma compared 30 mg of pamidronate to 90 mg of pamidronate. The study found  that there was no difference in skeletal-related events, but there was less osteonecrosis (2 events vs. 8 events) seen in the low-dose group.<Reference refidx="158"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>A randomized comparison of pamidronate versus zoledronic acid in 518 patients with multiple myeloma showed equivalent efficacy in regard to skeletal-related complications (both were given for 2 years).<Reference refidx="159"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]  </ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_695"><Title>Denosumab (RANKL inhibitor)</Title><Para id="_696">Evidence (denosumab):</Para><OrderedList id="_697" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a prospective randomized double-blind trial, 1,718 patients with newly diagnosed myeloma and at least one documented lytic bone lesion received either zoledronate or denosumab.<Reference refidx="8"/><ItemizedList id="_698" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The study met its primary end point of noninferiority for denosumab compared with zoledronate (HR, 0.98; 95% CI, 0.85‒1.14; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01 for noninferiority).<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem>Denosumab is significantly more expensive than the bisphosphonates, which are available in generic form.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_827">Unlike bisphosphonates, the reversible mechanism of action for denosumab may result in rebound fractures if it is discontinued, although this theoretical concern for patients with myeloma may be mitigated by continuous maintenance therapy.<Reference refidx="160"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_304"><Title>Radiation therapy for bone lesions</Title><Para id="_305">Lytic lesions of the spine  generally require radiation if any of the following are true:</Para><OrderedList id="_306" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>They are associated with an
extramedullary (paraspinal) plasmacytoma.</ListItem><ListItem>A painful destruction of a
vertebral body occurred.</ListItem><ListItem>CT or MRI scans present evidence of spinal
cord compression.<Reference refidx="161"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_307">Back pain caused by osteoporosis and small compression fractures of the
vertebrae responds best to chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_308">Extensive radiation of the spine or
long bones for diffuse osteoporosis may lead to prolonged suppression of
hemopoiesis and is rarely indicated.<Reference refidx="162"/></Para><Para id="_309">Bisphosphonates are useful for
slowing or reversing the osteopenia that is common in patients with myeloma.<Reference refidx="157"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_107_sid_9"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_107_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25838344">Rajkumar SV, Landgren O, Mateos MV: Smoldering multiple myeloma. Blood 125 (20): 3069-75, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25605835">Dimopoulos MA, Hillengass J, Usmani S, et al.: Role of magnetic resonance imaging in the management of patients with multiple myeloma: a consensus statement. J Clin Oncol 33 (6): 657-64, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="28686535">Moreau P, Attal M, Caillot D, et al.: Prospective Evaluation of Magnetic Resonance Imaging and [18F]Fluorodeoxyglucose Positron Emission Tomography-Computed Tomography at Diagnosis and Before Maintenance Therapy in Symptomatic Patients With Multiple Myeloma Included in the IFM/DFCI 2009 Trial: Results of the IMAJEM Study. J Clin Oncol 35 (25): 2911-2918, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19020545">Dispenzieri A, Kyle R, Merlini G, et al.: International Myeloma Working Group guidelines for serum-free light chain analysis in multiple myeloma and related disorders. Leukemia 23 (2): 215-24, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="30104220">Gertz MA: Acute hyperviscosity: syndromes and management. Blood 132 (13): 1379-1385, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="19541364">Raab MS, Podar K, Breitkreutz I, et al.: Multiple myeloma. Lancet 374 (9686): 324-39, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="22235089">Yourman LC, Lee SJ, Schonberg MA, et al.: Prognostic indices for older adults: a systematic review. JAMA 307 (2): 182-92, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="29429912">Raje N, Terpos E, Willenbacher W, et al.: Denosumab versus zoledronic acid in bone disease treatment of newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: an international, double-blind, double-dummy, randomised, controlled, phase 3 study. Lancet Oncol 19 (3): 370-381, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="29341831">Anderson K, Ismaila N, Flynn PJ, et al.: Role of Bone-Modifying Agents in Multiple Myeloma: American Society of Clinical Oncology Clinical Practice Guideline Update. J Clin Oncol 36 (8): 812-818, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="26976420">Dimopoulos MA, Sonneveld P, Leung N, et al.: International Myeloma Working Group Recommendations for the Diagnosis and Management of Myeloma-Related Renal Impairment. J Clin Oncol 34 (13): 1544-57, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="32325490">Voorhees PM, Kaufman JL, Laubach J, et al.: Daratumumab, lenalidomide, bortezomib, and dexamethasone for transplant-eligible newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: the GRIFFIN trial. Blood 136 (8): 936-945, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="33606004">Voorhees PM, Rodriguez C, Reeves B, et al.: Daratumumab plus RVd for newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: final analysis of the safety run-in cohort of GRIFFIN. Blood Adv 5 (4): 1092-1096, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Goldschmidt H, Bertsch U, Pozek E, et al.: Isatuximab, lenalidomide, bortezomib and dexamethasone induction therapy for transplant-eligible patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: final progression-free survival analysis of part 1 of an open-label, multicenter, randomized, phase 3 trial (GMMG-HD7). [Abstract] Blood  144 (Suppl 1): A-769, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="38832972">Facon T, Dimopoulos MA, Leleu XP, et al.: Isatuximab, Bortezomib, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 391 (17): 1597-1609, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="23233713">San Miguel JF, Schlag R, Khuageva NK, et al.: Persistent overall survival benefit and no increased risk of second malignancies with bortezomib-melphalan-prednisone versus melphalan-prednisone in patients with previously untreated multiple myeloma. J Clin Oncol 31 (4): 448-55, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="28379796">Attal M, Lauwers-Cances V, Hulin C, et al.: Lenalidomide, Bortezomib, and Dexamethasone with Transplantation for Myeloma. N Engl J Med 376 (14): 1311-1320, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="31484647">Rosiñol L, Oriol A, Rios R, et al.: Bortezomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone as induction therapy prior to autologous transplant in multiple myeloma. Blood 134 (16): 1337-1345, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="31765002">Piechotta V, Jakob T, Langer P, et al.: Multiple drug combinations of bortezomib, lenalidomide, and thalidomide for first-line treatment in adults with transplant-ineligible multiple myeloma: a network meta-analysis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2019 (11): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="18645194">Reece DE, Rodriguez GP, Chen C, et al.: Phase I-II trial of bortezomib plus oral cyclophosphamide and prednisone in relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma. J Clin Oncol 26 (29): 4777-83, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="20">Knop S, Liebisch H, Wandt H, et al.: Bortezomib, IV cyclophosphamide, and dexamethasone (VelCD) as induction therapy in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: results of an interim analysis of the German DSMM Xia trial. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  27 (Suppl 15): A-8516, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="20085933">Barlogie B, Attal M, Crowley J, et al.: Long-term follow-up of autotransplantation trials for multiple myeloma: update of protocols conducted by the intergroupe francophone du myelome, southwest oncology group, and university of arkansas for medical sciences. J Clin Oncol 28 (7): 1209-14, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="17241924">Koreth J, Cutler CS, Djulbegovic B, et al.: High-dose therapy with single autologous transplantation versus chemotherapy for newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 13 (2): 183-96, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="22571201">McCarthy PL, Owzar K, Hofmeister CC, et al.: Lenalidomide after stem-cell transplantation for multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 366 (19): 1770-81, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="22571202">Attal M, Lauwers-Cances V, Marit G, et al.: Lenalidomide maintenance after stem-cell transplantation for multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 366 (19): 1782-91, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="25184862">Palumbo A, Cavallo F, Gay F, et al.: Autologous transplantation and maintenance therapy in multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 371 (10): 895-905, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="29150421">Facon T, Dimopoulos MA, Dispenzieri A, et al.: Final analysis of survival outcomes in the phase 3 FIRST trial of up-front treatment for multiple myeloma. Blood 131 (3): 301-310, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="22571200">Palumbo A, Hajek R, Delforge M, et al.: Continuous lenalidomide treatment for newly diagnosed multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 366 (19): 1759-69, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="27002115">Sonneveld P, Avet-Loiseau H, Lonial S, et al.: Treatment of multiple myeloma with high-risk cytogenetics: a consensus of the International Myeloma Working Group. Blood 127 (24): 2955-62, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="30332496">Mina R, Joseph NS, Kaufman JL, et al.: Survival outcomes of patients with primary plasma cell leukemia (pPCL) treated with novel agents. Cancer 125 (3): 416-423, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="23288300">Fernández de Larrea C, Kyle RA, Durie BG, et al.: Plasma cell leukemia: consensus statement on diagnostic requirements, response criteria and treatment recommendations by the International Myeloma Working Group. Leukemia 27 (4): 780-91, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="28255016">Granell M, Calvo X, Garcia-Guiñón A, et al.: Prognostic impact of circulating plasma cells in patients with multiple myeloma: implications for plasma cell leukemia definition. Haematologica 102 (6): 1099-1104, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="27114594">Royer B, Minvielle S, Diouf M, et al.: Bortezomib, Doxorubicin, Cyclophosphamide, Dexamethasone Induction Followed by Stem Cell Transplantation for Primary Plasma Cell Leukemia: A Prospective Phase II Study of the Intergroupe Francophone du Myélome. J Clin Oncol 34 (18): 2125-32, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="24957143">Gonsalves WI, Rajkumar SV, Go RS, et al.: Trends in survival of patients with primary plasma cell leukemia: a population-based analysis. Blood 124 (6): 907-12, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="36315921">Jelinek T, Bezdekova R, Zihala D, et al.: More Than 2% of Circulating Tumor Plasma Cells Defines Plasma Cell Leukemia-Like Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 41 (7): 1383-1392, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="33856405">Landgren O, Hultcrantz M, Diamond B, et al.: Safety and Effectiveness of Weekly Carfilzomib, Lenalidomide, Dexamethasone, and Daratumumab Combination Therapy for Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma: The MANHATTAN Nonrandomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Oncol 7 (6): 862-868, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="33024991">Corre J, Munshi NC, Avet-Loiseau H: Risk factors in multiple myeloma: is it time for a revision? Blood 137 (1): 16-19, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="34383000">Al Hadidi S, Yellapragada S: Treatment Options for Relapsed and Refractory Multiple Myeloma: A Luxury or a Challenge? JAMA Oncol 7 (10): 1449-1450, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="22889759">Mateos MV, Oriol A, Martínez-López J, et al.: Maintenance therapy with bortezomib plus thalidomide or bortezomib plus prednisone in elderly multiple myeloma patients included in the GEM2005MAS65 trial. Blood 120 (13): 2581-8, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="27511158">Kumar S, Paiva B, Anderson KC, et al.: International Myeloma Working Group consensus criteria for response and minimal residual disease assessment in multiple myeloma. Lancet Oncol 17 (8): e328-e346, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="28498784">Lahuerta JJ, Paiva B, Vidriales MB, et al.: Depth of Response in Multiple Myeloma: A Pooled Analysis of Three PETHEMA/GEM Clinical Trials. J Clin Oncol 35 (25): 2900-2910, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="30561775">Gambella M, Omedé P, Spada S, et al.: Minimal residual disease by flow cytometry and allelic-specific oligonucleotide real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction in patients with myeloma receiving lenalidomide maintenance: A pooled analysis. Cancer 125 (5): 750-760, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="31770060">Paiva B, Puig N, Cedena MT, et al.: Measurable Residual Disease by Next-Generation Flow Cytometry in Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 38 (8): 784-792, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="27632282">Munshi NC, Avet-Loiseau H, Rawstron AC, et al.: Association of Minimal Residual Disease With Superior Survival Outcomes in Patients With Multiple Myeloma: A Meta-analysis. JAMA Oncol 3 (1): 28-35, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="27632052">Gormley NJ, Farrell AT, Pazdur R: Minimal Residual Disease as a Potential Surrogate End Point-Lingering Questions. JAMA Oncol 3 (1): 18-20, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="30249784">Perrot A, Lauwers-Cances V, Corre J, et al.: Minimal residual disease negativity using deep sequencing is a major prognostic factor in multiple myeloma. Blood 132 (23): 2456-2464, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="34269818">San-Miguel J, Avet-Loiseau H, Paiva B, et al.: Sustained minimal residual disease negativity in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma and the impact of daratumumab in MAIA and ALCYONE. Blood 139 (4): 492-501, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="33513030">Avet-Loiseau H, San-Miguel J, Casneuf T, et al.: Evaluation of Sustained Minimal Residual Disease Negativity With Daratumumab-Combination Regimens in Relapsed and/or Refractory Multiple Myeloma: Analysis of POLLUX and CASTOR. J Clin Oncol 39 (10): 1139-1149, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="35377708">de Tute RM, Pawlyn C, Cairns DA, et al.: Minimal Residual Disease After Autologous Stem-Cell Transplant for Patients With Myeloma: Prognostic Significance and the Impact of Lenalidomide Maintenance and Molecular Risk. J Clin Oncol 40 (25): 2889-2900, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="36130300">Paiva B, Manrique I, Dimopoulos MA, et al.: MRD dynamics during maintenance for improved prognostication of 1280 patients with myeloma in the TOURMALINE-MM3 and -MM4 trials. Blood 141 (6): 579-591, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="32693406">Goicoechea I, Puig N, Cedena MT, et al.: Deep MRD profiling defines outcome and unveils different modes of treatment resistance in standard- and high-risk myeloma. Blood 137 (1): 49-60, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="34289038">Cavo M, San-Miguel J, Usmani SZ, et al.: Prognostic value of minimal residual disease negativity in myeloma: combined analysis of POLLUX, CASTOR, ALCYONE, and MAIA. Blood 139 (6): 835-844, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="38701390">Pasquini MC, Wallace PK, Logan B, et al.: Minimal Residual Disease Status in Multiple Myeloma 1 Year After Autologous Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation and Lenalidomide Maintenance Are Associated With Long-Term Overall Survival. J Clin Oncol 42 (23): 2757-2768, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="35084473">Bianchi G: Sustained minimal residual disease in myeloma. Blood 139 (4): 469-471, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="34898239">Costa LJ, Chhabra S, Medvedova E, et al.: Daratumumab, Carfilzomib, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone With Minimal Residual Disease Response-Adapted Therapy in Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 40 (25): 2901-2912, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="39353166">Lasa M, Notarfranchi L, Agullo C, et al.: Minimally Invasive Assessment of Peripheral Residual Disease During Maintenance or Observation in Transplant-Eligible Patients With Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 43 (2): 125-132, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="38084760">Sonneveld P, Dimopoulos MA, Boccadoro M, et al.: Daratumumab, Bortezomib, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 390 (4): 301-313, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="37708911">Voorhees PM, Sborov DW, Laubach J, et al.: Addition of daratumumab to lenalidomide, bortezomib, and dexamethasone for transplantation-eligible patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (GRIFFIN): final analysis of an open-label, randomised, phase 2 trial. Lancet Haematol 10 (10): e825-e837, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="35580269">Yamamoto C, Minakata D, Koyama S, et al.: Daratumumab in first-line therapy is cost-effective in transplant-eligible patients with newly diagnosed myeloma. Blood 140 (6): 594-607, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="37315268">Kaiser MF, Hall A, Walker K, et al.: Daratumumab, Cyclophosphamide, Bortezomib, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone as Induction and Extended Consolidation Improves Outcome in Ultra-High-Risk Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 41 (23): 3945-3955, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="33762245">Brown S, Sherratt D, Hinsley S, et al.: MUKnine OPTIMUM protocol: a screening study to identify high-risk patients with multiple myeloma suitable for novel treatment approaches combined with a phase II study evaluating optimised combination of biological therapy in newly diagnosed high-risk multiple myeloma and plasma cell leukaemia. BMJ Open 11 (3): e046225, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="9332333">Goldschmidt H, Hegenbart U, Wallmeier M, et al.: Factors influencing collection of peripheral blood progenitor cells following high-dose cyclophosphamide and granulocyte colony-stimulating factor in patients with multiple myeloma. Br J Haematol 98 (3): 736-44, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="20368561">Mateos MV, Richardson PG, Schlag R, et al.: Bortezomib plus melphalan and prednisone compared with melphalan and prednisone in previously untreated multiple myeloma: updated follow-up and impact of subsequent therapy in the phase III VISTA trial. J Clin Oncol 28 (13): 2259-66, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="17690257">Richardson PG, Sonneveld P, Schuster M, et al.: Extended follow-up of a phase 3 trial in relapsed multiple myeloma: final time-to-event results of the APEX trial. Blood 110 (10): 3557-60, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="16754936">Richardson PG, Briemberg H, Jagannath S, et al.: Frequency, characteristics, and reversibility of peripheral neuropathy during treatment of advanced multiple myeloma with bortezomib. J Clin Oncol 24 (19): 3113-20, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="18200040">San-Miguel JF, Richardson PG, Sonneveld P, et al.: Efficacy and safety of bortezomib in patients with renal impairment: results from the APEX phase 3 study. Leukemia 22 (4): 842-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="19853510">Rajkumar SV, Jacobus S, Callander NS, et al.: Lenalidomide plus high-dose dexamethasone versus lenalidomide plus low-dose dexamethasone as initial therapy for newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: an open-label randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 11 (1): 29-37, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="32438407">Bradbury CA, Craig Z, Cook G, et al.: Thrombosis in patients with myeloma treated in the Myeloma IX and Myeloma XI phase 3 randomized controlled trials. Blood 136 (9): 1091-1104, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="30190454">Mikhael J, Manola J, Dueck AC, et al.: Lenalidomide and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma and impaired renal function: PrE1003, a PrECOG study. Blood Cancer J 8 (9): 86, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="69">Zweegman S, Facon T, Hungria V, et al.: Phase 3 randomized study of daratumumab (DARA) + bortezomib, lenalidomide and dexamethasone (VRd) versus alone in patients with transplant-ineligible newly diagnosed multiple myeloma or for whom transplant is not planned as initial therapy: analysis of minimal residual disease in the Cepheus trial. [Abstract] Blood  144 (Suppl 1): A-362, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="34655533">Facon T, Kumar SK, Plesner T, et al.: Daratumumab, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone versus lenalidomide and dexamethasone alone in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (MAIA): overall survival results from a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 22 (11): 1582-1596, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="33326255">Perrot A, Facon T, Plesner T, et al.: Health-Related Quality of Life in Transplant-Ineligible Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma: Findings From the Phase III MAIA Trial. J Clin Oncol 39 (3): 227-237, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="31836199">Mateos MV, Cavo M, Blade J, et al.: Overall survival with daratumumab, bortezomib, melphalan, and prednisone in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (ALCYONE): a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet 395 (10218): 132-141, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="38830994">Leleu X, Hulin C, Lambert J, et al.: Isatuximab, lenalidomide, dexamethasone and bortezomib in transplant-ineligible multiple myeloma: the randomized phase 3 BENEFIT trial. Nat Med 30 (8): 2235-2241, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="30819926">Facon T, Lee JH, Moreau P, et al.: Carfilzomib or bortezomib with melphalan-prednisone for transplant-ineligible patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma. Blood 133 (18): 1953-1963, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="75" PMID="32866432">Kumar SK, Jacobus SJ, Cohen AD, et al.: Carfilzomib or bortezomib in combination with lenalidomide and dexamethasone for patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma without intention for immediate autologous stem-cell transplantation (ENDURANCE): a multicentre, open-label, phase 3, randomised, controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (10): 1317-1330, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="36413710">Sonneveld P, Chanan-Khan A, Weisel K, et al.: Overall Survival With Daratumumab, Bortezomib, and Dexamethasone in Previously Treated Multiple Myeloma (CASTOR): A Randomized, Open-Label, Phase III Trial. J Clin Oncol 41 (8): 1600-1609, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="27705267">Dimopoulos MA, Oriol A, Nahi H, et al.: Daratumumab, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 375 (14): 1319-1331, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="33411586">Patel KK, Giri S, Parker TL, et al.: Cost-Effectiveness of First-Line Versus Second-Line Use of Daratumumab in Older, Transplant-Ineligible Patients With Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 39 (10): 1119-1128, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="79" PMID="12893762">Bladé J, Vesole DH, Gertz Morie: High-dose therapy in multiple myeloma. Blood 102 (10): 3469-70, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="80" PMID="9864145">Siegel DS, Desikan KR, Mehta J, et al.: Age is not a prognostic variable with autotransplants for multiple myeloma. Blood 93 (1): 51-4, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="81" PMID="11552985">Badros A, Barlogie B, Siegel E, et al.: Autologous stem cell transplantation in elderly multiple myeloma patients over the age of 70 years. Br J Haematol 114 (3): 600-7, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="82" PMID="16643445">Lenhoff S, Hjorth M, Westin J, et al.: Impact of age on survival after intensive therapy for multiple myeloma: a population-based study by the Nordic Myeloma Study Group. Br J Haematol 133 (4): 389-96, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="83" PMID="32965680">Munshi PN, Vesole D, Jurczyszyn A, et al.: Age no bar: A CIBMTR analysis of elderly patients undergoing autologous hematopoietic cell transplantation for multiple myeloma. Cancer 126 (23): 5077-5087, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="84" PMID="34374445">Munshi PN, Vesole DH, St Martin A, et al.: Outcomes of upfront autologous hematopoietic cell transplantation in patients with multiple myeloma who are 75 years old or older. Cancer 127 (22): 4233-4239, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="85" PMID="8649495" MedlineID="96266359">Attal M, Harousseau JL, Stoppa AM, et al.: A prospective, randomized trial of autologous bone marrow transplantation and chemotherapy in multiple myeloma. Intergroupe Français du Myélome. N Engl J Med 335 (2): 91-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="86" PMID="12736280" MedlineID="22621947">Child JA, Morgan GJ, Davies FE, et al.: High-dose chemotherapy with hematopoietic stem-cell rescue for multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 348 (19): 1875-83, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="87" PMID="15265788">Palumbo A, Bringhen S, Petrucci MT, et al.: Intermediate-dose melphalan improves survival of myeloma patients aged 50 to 70: results of a randomized controlled trial. Blood 104 (10): 3052-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="88" PMID="12456509" MedlineID="22496794">Segeren CM, Sonneveld P, van der Holt B, et al.: Overall and event-free survival are not improved by the use of myeloablative therapy following intensified chemotherapy in previously untreated patients with multiple myeloma: a prospective randomized phase 3 study. Blood 101 (6): 2144-51, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="89" PMID="16275936">Fermand JP, Katsahian S, Divine M, et al.: High-dose therapy and autologous blood stem-cell transplantation compared with conventional treatment in myeloma patients aged 55 to 65 years: long-term results of a randomized control trial from the Group Myelome-Autogreffe. J Clin Oncol 23 (36): 9227-33, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="90" PMID="16105975">Bladé J, Rosiñol L, Sureda A, et al.: High-dose therapy intensification compared with continued standard chemotherapy in multiple myeloma patients responding to the initial chemotherapy: long-term results from a prospective randomized trial from the Spanish cooperative group PETHEMA. Blood 106 (12): 3755-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="91" PMID="16432076">Barlogie B, Kyle RA, Anderson KC, et al.: Standard chemotherapy compared with high-dose chemoradiotherapy for multiple myeloma: final results of phase III US Intergroup Trial S9321. J Clin Oncol 24 (6): 929-36, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="92" PMID="24948586">Cook G, Williams C, Brown JM, et al.: High-dose chemotherapy plus autologous stem-cell transplantation as consolidation therapy in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma after previous autologous stem-cell transplantation (NCRI Myeloma X Relapse [Intensive trial]): a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 15 (8): 874-85, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="93" PMID="26596670">Gay F, Oliva S, Petrucci MT, et al.: Chemotherapy plus lenalidomide versus autologous transplantation, followed by lenalidomide plus prednisone versus lenalidomide maintenance, in patients with multiple myeloma: a randomised, multicentre, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 16 (16): 1617-29, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="94" PMID="35660812">Richardson PG, Jacobus SJ, Weller EA, et al.: Triplet Therapy, Transplantation, and Maintenance until Progression in Myeloma. N Engl J Med 387 (2): 132-147, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="95" PMID="16010209">Lévy V, Katsahian S, Fermand JP, et al.: A meta-analysis on data from 575 patients with multiple myeloma randomly assigned to either high-dose therapy or conventional therapy. Medicine (Baltimore) 84 (4): 250-60, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="96" PMID="29302684">Dhakal B, Szabo A, Chhabra S, et al.: Autologous Transplantation for Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma in the Era of Novel Agent Induction: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. JAMA Oncol 4 (3): 343-350, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="97" PMID="35377484">Chakraborty R, Siddiqi R, Willson G, et al.: Impact of autologous transplantation on survival in patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma who have high-risk cytogenetics: A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Cancer 128 (12): 2288-2297, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="98" PMID="18300230">Pineda-Roman M, Barlogie B, Anaissie E, et al.: High-dose melphalan-based autotransplants for multiple myeloma: the Arkansas experience since 1989 in 3077 patients. Cancer 112 (8): 1754-64, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="99" PMID="32966625">Badar T, Hari P, Dávila O, et al.: African Americans with translocation t(11;14) have superior survival after autologous hematopoietic cell transplantation for multiple myeloma in comparison with Whites in the United States. Cancer 127 (1): 82-92, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="100" PMID="16939489">Barlogie B, Tricot GJ, van Rhee F, et al.: Long-term outcome results of the first tandem autotransplant trial for multiple myeloma. Br J Haematol 135 (2): 158-64, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="101" PMID="16322468">Barlogie B, Tricot G, Rasmussen E, et al.: Total therapy 2 without thalidomide in comparison with total therapy 1: role of intensified induction and posttransplantation consolidation therapies. Blood 107 (7): 2633-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="102" PMID="16796777">Barlogie B, Zangari M, Bolejack V, et al.: Superior 12-year survival after at least 4-year continuous remission with tandem transplantations for multiple myeloma. Clin Lymphoma Myeloma 6 (6): 469-74, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="103" PMID="19064724">Bruno B, Rotta M, Patriarca F, et al.: Nonmyeloablative allografting for newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: the experience of the Gruppo Italiano Trapianti di Midollo. Blood 113 (14): 3375-82, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="104" PMID="19015394">Rotta M, Storer BE, Sahebi F, et al.: Long-term outcome of patients with multiple myeloma after autologous hematopoietic cell transplantation and nonmyeloablative allografting. Blood 113 (14): 3383-91, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="105" PMID="19141779">Kumar A, Kharfan-Dabaja MA, Glasmacher A, et al.: Tandem versus single autologous hematopoietic cell transplantation for the treatment of multiple myeloma: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Natl Cancer Inst 101 (2): 100-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="106" PMID="30653422">Stadtmauer EA, Pasquini MC, Blackwell B, et al.: Autologous Transplantation, Consolidation, and Maintenance Therapy in Multiple Myeloma: Results of the BMT CTN 0702 Trial. J Clin Oncol 37 (7): 589-597, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="107" PMID="18948589">Moreau P, Garban F, Attal M, et al.: Long-term follow-up results of IFM99-03 and IFM99-04 trials comparing nonmyeloablative allotransplantation with autologous transplantation in high-risk de novo multiple myeloma. Blood 112 (9): 3914-5, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="108" PMID="17360989">Bruno B, Rotta M, Patriarca F, et al.: A comparison of allografting with autografting for newly diagnosed myeloma. N Engl J Med 356 (11): 1110-20, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="109" PMID="23482933">Gahrton G, Iacobelli S, Björkstrand B, et al.: Autologous/reduced-intensity allogeneic stem cell transplantation vs autologous transplantation in multiple myeloma: long-term results of the EBMT-NMAM2000 study. Blood 121 (25): 5055-63, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="110" PMID="18612103">Rosiñol L, Pérez-Simón JA, Sureda A, et al.: A prospective PETHEMA study of tandem autologous transplantation versus autograft followed by reduced-intensity conditioning allogeneic transplantation in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma. Blood 112 (9): 3591-3, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="111" PMID="22964593">Armeson KE, Hill EG, Costa LJ: Tandem autologous vs autologous plus reduced intensity allogeneic transplantation in the upfront management of multiple myeloma: meta-analysis of trials with biological assignment. Bone Marrow Transplant 48 (4): 562-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="112" PMID="23289975">Kharfan-Dabaja MA, Hamadani M, Reljic T, et al.: Comparative efficacy of tandem autologous versus autologous followed by allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation in patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. J Hematol Oncol 6: 2, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="113" PMID="23076906">Naumann-Winter F, Greb A, Borchmann P, et al.: First-line tandem high-dose chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplantation versus single high-dose chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplantation in multiple myeloma, a systematic review of controlled studies. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 10: CD004626, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="114" PMID="11477436" MedlineID="21369446">Reynolds C, Ratanatharathorn V, Adams P, et al.: Allogeneic stem cell transplantation reduces disease progression compared to autologous transplantation in patients with multiple myeloma. Bone Marrow Transplant 27 (8): 801-7, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="115" PMID="15834435">Arora M, McGlave PB, Burns LJ, et al.: Results of autologous and allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplant therapy for multiple myeloma. Bone Marrow Transplant 35 (12): 1133-40, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="116" PMID="20697091">Lokhorst H, Einsele H, Vesole D, et al.: International Myeloma Working Group consensus statement regarding the current status of allogeneic stem-cell transplantation for multiple myeloma. J Clin Oncol 28 (29): 4521-30, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="117" PMID="23151215">Sahebi F, Shen Y, Thomas SH, et al.: Late relapses following reduced intensity allogeneic transplantation in patients with multiple myeloma: a long-term follow-up study. Br J Haematol 160 (2): 199-206, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="118" PMID="22442350">Lokhorst HM, van der Holt B, Cornelissen JJ, et al.: Donor versus no-donor comparison of newly diagnosed myeloma patients included in the HOVON-50 multiple myeloma study. Blood 119 (26): 6219-25; quiz 6399, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="119" PMID="21490341">Giaccone L, Storer B, Patriarca F, et al.: Long-term follow-up of a comparison of nonmyeloablative allografting with autografting for newly diagnosed myeloma. Blood 117 (24): 6721-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="120" PMID="35100661">Vasudevan Nampoothiri R, Pasic I, Law AD, et al.: Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in patients with therapy-related hematologic malignancies developing after multiple myeloma. Eur J Haematol 108 (5): 430-436, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="121" PMID="27374467">Cook G, Ashcroft AJ, Cairns DA, et al.: The effect of salvage autologous stem-cell transplantation on overall survival in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma (final results from BSBMT/UKMF Myeloma X Relapse [Intensive]): a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Haematol 3 (7): e340-51, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="122" PMID="30969846">Ahmedzai SH, Snowden JA, Ashcroft AJ, et al.: Patient-Reported Outcome Results From the Open-Label, Randomized Phase III Myeloma X Trial Evaluating Salvage Autologous Stem-Cell Transplantation in Relapsed Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 37 (19): 1617-1628, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="123" PMID="28513828">Veltri LW, Milton DR, Delgado R, et al.: Outcome of autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in refractory multiple myeloma. Cancer 123 (18): 3568-3575, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="124" PMID="22271445">Ludwig H, Durie BG, McCarthy P, et al.: IMWG consensus on maintenance therapy in multiple myeloma. Blood 119 (13): 3003-15, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="125" PMID="25184863">Benboubker L, Dimopoulos MA, Dispenzieri A, et al.: Lenalidomide and dexamethasone in transplant-ineligible patients with myeloma. N Engl J Med 371 (10): 906-17, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="126" PMID="26282661">Palumbo A, Gay F, Cavallo F, et al.: Continuous Therapy Versus Fixed Duration of Therapy in Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 33 (30): 3459-66, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="127" PMID="17233817">Shustik C, Belch A, Robinson S, et al.: A randomised comparison of melphalan with prednisone or dexamethasone as induction therapy and dexamethasone or observation as maintenance therapy in multiple myeloma: NCIC CTG MY.7. Br J Haematol 136 (2): 203-11, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="128" PMID="11964279" MedlineID="21961531">Berenson JR, Crowley JJ, Grogan TM, et al.: Maintenance therapy with alternate-day prednisone improves survival in multiple myeloma patients. Blood 99 (9): 3163-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="129" PMID="11442498" MedlineID="21335951">The Myeloma Trialists' Collaborative Group: Interferon as therapy for multiple myeloma: an individual patient data overview of 24 randomized trials and 4012 patients. Br J Haematol 113 (4): 1020-34, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="130" PMID="39331724">Badros A, Foster L, Anderson LD, et al.: Daratumumab with lenalidomide as maintenance after transplant in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: the AURIGA study. Blood 145 (3): 300-310, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="131" PMID="28826616">Holstein SA, Jung SH, Richardson PG, et al.: Updated analysis of CALGB (Alliance) 100104 assessing lenalidomide versus placebo maintenance after single autologous stem-cell transplantation for multiple myeloma: a randomised, double-blind, phase 3 trial. Lancet Haematol 4 (9): e431-e442, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="132" PMID="30559051">Jackson GH, Davies FE, Pawlyn C, et al.: Lenalidomide maintenance versus observation for patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (Myeloma XI): a multicentre, open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 20 (1): 57-73, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="133" PMID="28742454">McCarthy PL, Holstein SA, Petrucci MT, et al.: Lenalidomide Maintenance After Autologous Stem-Cell Transplantation in Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma: A Meta-Analysis. J Clin Oncol 35 (29): 3279-3289, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="134" PMID="26582244">Wang Y, Yang F, Shen Y, et al.: Maintenance Therapy With Immunomodulatory Drugs in Multiple Myeloma: A Meta-Analysis and Systematic Review. J Natl Cancer Inst 108 (3): , 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="135" PMID="30098165">Gay F, Jackson G, Rosiñol L, et al.: Maintenance Treatment and Survival in Patients With Myeloma: A Systematic Review and Network Meta-analysis. JAMA Oncol 4 (10): 1389-1397, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="136" PMID="34529931">Moreau P, Hulin C, Perrot A, et al.: Maintenance with daratumumab or observation following treatment with bortezomib, thalidomide, and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab and autologous stem-cell transplant in patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (CASSIOPEIA): an open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 22 (10): 1378-1390, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="137" PMID="33021870">Dimopoulos MA, Špička I, Quach H, et al.: Ixazomib as Postinduction Maintenance for Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma Not Undergoing Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation: The Phase III TOURMALINE-MM4 Trial. J Clin Oncol 38 (34): 4030-4041, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="138" PMID="36642080">Dytfeld D, Wróbel T, Jamroziak K, et al.: Carfilzomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone or lenalidomide alone as maintenance therapy after autologous stem-cell transplantation in patients with multiple myeloma (ATLAS): interim analysis of a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 24 (2): 139-150, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="139" PMID="39820980">Touzeau C, Perrot A: Daratumumab for maintenance in myeloma. Blood 145 (3): 251-252, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="140" PMID="36564045">Panopoulou A, Cairns DA, Holroyd A, et al.: Optimizing the value of lenalidomide maintenance by extended genetic profiling: an analysis of 556 patients in the Myeloma XI trial. Blood 141 (14): 1666-1674, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="141" PMID="30545780">Dimopoulos MA, Gay F, Schjesvold F, et al.: Oral ixazomib maintenance following autologous stem cell transplantation (TOURMALINE-MM3): a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled phase 3 trial. Lancet 393 (10168): 253-264, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="142">Palumbo A, Bringhen S, Rossi D, et al.: Overall survival benefit for bortezomib-melphalan-prednisone-thalidomide followed by maintenance with bortezomib-thalidomide (VMPT-VT) versus bortezomib-melphalan-prednisone (VMP) in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma patients. [Abstract] Blood  120 (21): A-200, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="143" PMID="28541791">Olszewski AJ, Dusetzina SB, Eaton CB, et al.: Subsidies for Oral Chemotherapy and Use of Immunomodulatory Drugs Among Medicare Beneficiaries With Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 35 (29): 3306-3314, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="144" PMID="30113885">Olszewski AJ, Dusetzina SB, Trivedi AN, et al.: Prescription Drug Coverage and Outcomes of Myeloma Therapy Among Medicare Beneficiaries. J Clin Oncol 36 (28): 2879-2886, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="145" PMID="28834440">Mikhael JR: Maintenance Lenalidomide After Transplantation in Multiple Myeloma Prolongs Survival-In Most. J Clin Oncol 35 (29): 3269-3271, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="146" PMID="30545778">van de Donk NWCJ, Yong K: Oral proteasome inhibitor maintenance for multiple myeloma. Lancet 393 (10168): 204-205, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="147" PMID="21131037">Morgan GJ, Davies FE, Gregory WM, et al.: First-line treatment with zoledronic acid as compared with clodronic acid in multiple myeloma (MRC Myeloma IX): a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 376 (9757): 1989-99, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="148" PMID="21771568">Morgan GJ, Child JA, Gregory WM, et al.: Effects of zoledronic acid versus clodronic acid on skeletal morbidity in patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (MRC Myeloma IX): secondary outcomes from a randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 12 (8): 743-52, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="149" PMID="22498739">Morgan GJ, Davies FE, Gregory WM, et al.: Effects of induction and maintenance plus long-term bisphosphonates on bone disease in patients with multiple myeloma: the Medical Research Council Myeloma IX Trial. Blood 119 (23): 5374-83, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="150" PMID="20238320">Mhaskar R, Redzepovic J, Wheatley K, et al.: Bisphosphonates in multiple myeloma. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (3): CD003188, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="151" PMID="28030702">Himelstein AL, Foster JC, Khatcheressian JL, et al.: Effect of Longer-Interval vs Standard Dosing of Zoledronic Acid on Skeletal Events in Patients With Bone Metastases: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 317 (1): 48-58, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="152" PMID="16484704">Badros A, Weikel D, Salama A, et al.: Osteonecrosis of the jaw in multiple myeloma patients: clinical features and risk factors. J Clin Oncol 24 (6): 945-52, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="153" PMID="16901034">Kademani D, Koka S, Lacy MQ, et al.: Primary surgical therapy for osteonecrosis of the jaw secondary to bisphosphonate therapy. Mayo Clin Proc 81 (8): 1100-3, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="154" PMID="16901028">Lacy MQ, Dispenzieri A, Gertz MA, et al.: Mayo clinic consensus statement for the use of bisphosphonates in multiple myeloma. Mayo Clin Proc 81 (8): 1047-53, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="155" PMID="19738129">Jakubowiak AJ, Kendall T, Al-Zoubi A, et al.: Phase II trial of combination therapy with bortezomib, pegylated liposomal doxorubicin, and dexamethasone in patients with newly diagnosed myeloma. J Clin Oncol 27 (30): 5015-22, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="156" PMID="19465418">Terpos E, Sezer O, Croucher PI, et al.: The use of bisphosphonates in multiple myeloma: recommendations of an expert panel on behalf of the European Myeloma Network. Ann Oncol 20 (8): 1303-17, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="157" PMID="9469347" MedlineID="98129249">Berenson JR, Lichtenstein A, Porter L, et al.: Long-term pamidronate treatment of advanced multiple myeloma patients reduces skeletal events. Myeloma Aredia Study Group. J Clin Oncol 16 (2): 593-602, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="158" PMID="20863761">Gimsing P, Carlson K, Turesson I, et al.: Effect of pamidronate 30 mg versus 90 mg on physical function in patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (Nordic Myeloma Study Group): a double-blind, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 11 (10): 973-82, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="159" PMID="14534891">Rosen LS, Gordon D, Kaminski M, et al.: Long-term efficacy and safety of zoledronic acid compared with pamidronate disodium in the treatment of skeletal complications in patients with advanced multiple myeloma or breast carcinoma: a randomized, double-blind, multicenter, comparative trial. Cancer 98 (8): 1735-44, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="160" PMID="31246229">Chakraborty R, Majhail NS, Anwer F: Denosumab vs Zoledronic Acid for Bone-Targeted Therapy in Multiple Myeloma: What Are the Unanswered Questions? JAMA Oncol 5 (8): 1095-1096, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="161" PMID="16413695">Rades D, Hoskin PJ, Stalpers LJ, et al.: Short-course radiotherapy is not optimal for spinal cord compression due to myeloma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 64 (5): 1452-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="162" PMID="9422566" MedlineID="98083029">Catell D, Kogen Z, Donahue B, et al.: Multiple myeloma of an extremity: must the entire bone be treated? Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 40 (1): 117-9, 1998.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_219"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041876">refractory multiple myeloma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</Title><SummarySection id="_945"><Title>Treatment Options for Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</Title><Para id="_946">Relapses occur for almost all patients after induction therapy, consolidation with autologous stem cell transplant (SCT),  and maintenance therapy. During initial therapy, some patients have poor disease response, or their disease progresses. The general strategy is to give new therapies sequentially as required. In fit patients, reinduction therapy with response may be consolidated with an autologous SCT or allogeneic SCT in some cases. Sometimes, when relapse occurs 1 year or more after initial therapy, the same drugs can be administered a second time.</Para><Para id="_947">A
subgroup of patients who do not achieve a response to induction chemotherapy have stable disease and a survival prognosis that
is as good as that for responding patients.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> When the stable nature of the
disease becomes established, these patients can discontinue therapy until the
myeloma begins to progress again.  Other patients with primary refractory myeloma and
progressive disease require a change in therapy. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_107" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Multiple Myeloma</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_948">For patients with disease response to initial therapy, the myeloma growth rate, as
measured by the monoclonal (or myeloma) protein-doubling time, increases progressively with each
subsequent relapse, and remission durations become shorter and shorter.  Marrow
function becomes increasingly compromised as patients develop pancytopenia and
enter a refractory phase; occasionally, the myeloma cells dedifferentiate and
extramedullary plasmacytomas develop.  The myeloma cells may still be sensitive
to chemotherapy, but the regrowth rate during relapse is so rapid that
progressive improvement is not observed.</Para><Para id="_949">Combinations of drugs or single agents may be given sequentially as required. The goal is to avoid symptoms and adverse consequences of relapsing disease. However, the onset of therapy may be delayed because of slow disease progression and good performance status. </Para><Para id="_950">Treatment options for relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma include:</Para><OrderedList id="_951" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_955" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Monoclonal antibodies</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_952" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_956" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Daratumumab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_964" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Elotuzumab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1111" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Isatuximab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_970" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Proteasome inhibitors</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_953" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1050" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Bortezomib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_971" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Carfilzomib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_978" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Ixazomib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1207" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T-cell therapy</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_1285" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1287" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Ciltacabtagene autoleucel (cilta-cel)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1306" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Idecabtagene vicleucel (ide-cel)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1212" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Bispecific antibody therapy</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_1278" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1214" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Teclistamab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1264" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Talquetamab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1219" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Elranatamab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_990" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Immunomodulatory agents</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_954" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_991" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Pomalidomide</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_998" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Lenalidomide</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1006" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Thalidomide</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1294" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">B-cell maturation antigen (BCMA)-targeting antibody-drug conjugates</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_1286" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1295" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Belantamab mafodotin</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1012" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy (cytotoxic agents)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1020" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Selinexor</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1026" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Venetoclax</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1205" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">BRAF/MEK inhibitors</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1035" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Corticosteroids</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_955"><Title>Monoclonal antibodies</Title><SummarySection id="_956"><Title>Daratumumab</Title><Para id="_957">Daratumumab is a monoclonal antibody targeting CD38 that can be given on its own but is usually given in combination with other drugs. Although it is given as an infusion, the subcutaneous formulation has equivalent efficacy and fewer adverse events.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_958">Evidence (daratumumab):</Para><OrderedList id="_959" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In the prospective <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02136134">CASTOR</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT02136134), 498 previously treated patients were randomly assigned to receive either daratumumab, bortezomib, and dexamethasone (DVd) or bortezomib and dexamethasone (Vd).<Reference refidx="4"/><ItemizedList id="_960" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 72.6 months, the median overall survival (OS) was 49.6 months for patients in the DVd group and 38.5 months for patients in the Vd group (hazard ratio [HR], 0.74; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.59–0.92; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0075).<Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In the prospective <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02076009">POLLUX</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT02076009), 569 previously treated patients were randomly assigned to receive either daratumumab, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone (DRd) or lenalidomide and dexamethasone (Rd).<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><ItemizedList id="_961" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 79.7 months, the median OS was 67.6 months for patients in the DRd group and 51.8 months for patients in the Rd group (HR, 0.73; 95% CI, 0.58–0.91; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0044).<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03158688">NCT03158688</ProtocolRef>), 466 previously treated patients were randomly assigned in a 2:1 ratio to receive either daratumumab, carfilzomib, and dexamethasone or carfilzomib and dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="7"/><ItemizedList id="_1087" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 27.8 months, the median progression-free survival (PFS) was 28.6 months (95%  CI, 25.6–29.5) in the daratumumab group and 15.2 months (11.1–19.9) in the control arm (log-rank <Emphasis>P</Emphasis>  &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial, 1,304 previously treated patients received either daratumumab plus pomalidomide and dexamethasone (DPd) or pomalidomide and dexamethasone (Pd) alone.<Reference refidx="9"/><ItemizedList id="_1156" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 16.9 months, the median PFS was 12.4 months (95% CI, 8.3–19.3) for patients who received DPd and 6.9 months (95% CI, 5.5–9.3) for patients who received Pd (HR, 0.63; 95% CI, 0.47–0.85; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0018).<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem>  </ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Several phase I and phase II trials evaluated daratumumab as a single agent for relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><ItemizedList id="_962" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 12 to 17 months, the overall response rate was 31% and 36%, with minimal  response or stable disease in about 40% of patients.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1088">In every prospective randomized trial to date, adding daratumumab to other active myeloma combination therapies improved responses and PFS when compared with  the combination therapies alone.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_964"><Title>Elotuzumab</Title><Para id="_965">Elotuzumab is a monoclonal antibody directed at SLAMF7 (signaling lymphocytic activation molecule F7).</Para><Para id="_966">Evidence (elotuzumab):</Para><OrderedList id="_967" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02654132">ELOQUENT-3</ProtocolRef> [NCT02654132]) included 117 patients with relapsed or refractory disease after both lenalidomide and a proteasome inhibitor. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either elotuzumab, pomalidomide, and dexamethasone (EPd) or Pd.<Reference refidx="13"/><ItemizedList id="_968" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 45 months, the median OS was 29.8 months (22.9–45.7) for patients who received EPd compared with 17.4 months (13.8–27.7) for patients who received Pd (HR, 0.59; 95% CI, 0.37–0.93; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0217).<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01239797">ELOQUENT-2</ProtocolRef> [NCT01239797]) of 646 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma, elotuzumab was combined with lenalidomide and dexamethasone and compared with Rd alone.<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_969" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 70.6 months, the 5-year PFS rate was 17%  in the elotuzumab group and 11% in the Rd group (HR, 0.73; 95% CI, 0.60–0.89; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0014). The 5-year OS rate was 40% in the elotuzumab group and 33% in the Rd group (HR, 0.82; 95.4% CI, 0.68–1.00; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0408).<Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1111"><Title>Isatuximab</Title><Para id="_1112">Isatuximab is a monoclonal antibody directed against CD38.</Para><Para id="_1126">Evidence (isatuximab):</Para><OrderedList id="_1113" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial of 387 patients with relapsed or refractory disease, Pd was given with or without isatuximab.<Reference refidx="15"/><ItemizedList id="_1158" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 35.3 months, the median OS was 24.6 months (95% CI, 20.3–31.3) for patients who received isatuximab plus PD and 17.7 months (95% CI, 14.4–26.2) for patients who received Pd alone (HR, 0.76; 95% CI, 0.57–1.01; 2-sided <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .056).</ListItem><ListItem>Similarly, the median PFS was 17.5 months (95% CI, 14.9–19.2) for the isatuximab group and 12.9 months (95% CI, 10.1–16.6) for the Pd group (HR, 0.76; 95% CI, 0.58–0.99; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .020).<Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial of 302 patients with relapsed or refractory disease, the combination of carfilzomib and dexamethasone was given with or without isatuximab.<ItemizedList id="_1159" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 20.7 months, the 2-year PFS rate was 68.9% (95% CI, 60.7%–75.8%) for patients who received isatuximab group and 45.7% (95% CI, 35.2%–55.6%) for patients who received carfilzomib and dexamethasone alone (HR, 0.53; 99% CI, 0.32–0.89; 2-sided <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0014).<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1160">There are no data comparing isatuximab with daratumumab, both of which target CD38. There are no data proving that isatuximab has efficacy in patients with disease that is resistant to daratumumab.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_970"><Title>Proteasome inhibitors</Title><SummarySection id="_1050"><Title>Bortezomib</Title><Para id="_1051">Bortezomib is the first-in-class proteasome inhibitor that is given subcutaneously on a weekly basis for 3 of every 4 weeks; the subcutaneous route is preferred to the intravenous (IV) route because it causes significantly less neuropathy and no loss of responsiveness.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/> Bortezomib is metabolized and cleared by the liver, and it appears to be active and well tolerated in patients with renal impairment.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/> More than 6 months after completion of bortezomib induction therapy, bortezomib can be given again with a 40% overall response rate, according to a meta-analysis of 23 phase II studies.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </Para><Para id="_1052">Evidence (bortezomib):</Para><OrderedList id="_1053" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized study of 669 patients with relapsed myeloma compared bortezomib given by IV with high-dose oral dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="23"/><ItemizedList id="_1054" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 22 months, the median OS was 29.8 months for bortezomib versus 23.7 months for dexamethasone (HR, 0.77; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .027) even though the trial allowed crossover after relapse.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00103506">NCT00103506</ProtocolRef>) of 646 previously treated patients compared bortezomib plus pegylated liposomal doxorubicin with bortezomib alone.<Reference refidx="24"/><ItemizedList id="_1055" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 7.0 months, 1-year OS rates were better in patients who received the combination (82% vs. 75%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .05).<Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial of 260 newly diagnosed patients aged 65 years and older compared bortezomib, melphalan, and prednisone (VMP) with bortezomib, thalidomide, and prednisone (VTP).<Reference refidx="25"/><ItemizedList id="_1056" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 72 months, the median OS favored the VMP arm, 63 months versus 43 months for the VTP group (HR, 0.67; 95% CI, 0.49–0.91; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01).<Reference refidx="25"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_971"><Title>Carfilzomib</Title><Para id="_972">Carfilzomib is a second-generation proteasome inhibitor that is given by IV (unlike the subcutaneous route for bortezomib). Most studies have used twice-weekly administration, but once-weekly administration appears at least equally efficacious and safe.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para><Para id="_973">Evidence (carfilzomib):</Para><OrderedList id="_974" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial included 578 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma.<Reference refidx="26"/><ItemizedList id="_975" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The median PFS of patients who received carfilzomib once a week was significantly better  (11.2 months; 95% CI, 8.6‒13.0) than twice a week (7.6 months; 95% CI, 5.8‒9.2) (HR, 0.69; 95% CI, 0.54‒0.83; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0029).<Reference refidx="26"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial of 792 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma, the combination of carfilzomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone was compared with Rd.<Reference refidx="27"/><ItemizedList id="_976" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 67.1 months, median OS in the carfilzomib arm was 48.3 months (95% CI, 42.4‒52.8) versus 40.4 months (95% CI, 33.6‒44.4) (HR, 0.79; 95% CI, 0.67‒0.95; one-sided <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .009).<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>In a preplanned subgroup analysis, patients with high-risk cytogenetics (i.e., t(4;14), t(14;16), del(17p)) also had improved PFS with the triplet regimen (23 months vs. 14 months; HR, 0.70; 95% CI, 0.43−1.16; one-sided <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .083). Response rates were also improved, but the carfilzomib combination did not abrogate the worse prognosis.<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01568866">NCT01568866</ProtocolRef>) of 929 patients compared carfilzomib and dexamethasone with bortezomib and dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="29"/><ItemizedList id="_977" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 37 months, the median OS was 47.6 months (95% CI, 42.5–not evaluable) for the carfilzomib combination compared with  40.0 months (95% CI, 32.6–42.3) for the bortezomib combination (HR, 0.79; 95% CI,  0.65–0.96; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .020).<Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Cardiovascular adverse events such as heart failure, chest pain, and acute coronary syndrome (grade 3 or higher) occurred in 25% of patients, especially in the first 3 months of therapy.<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/></ListItem><ListItem>A systematic review and meta-analysis demonstrated that renal adverse events occurred in 21% of patients of patients who received carfilzomib, and 8.3% had grade 3 to 5 toxicities. Acute kidney injury was the most common renal toxicity.<Reference refidx="32"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_978"><Title>Ixazomib</Title><Para id="_979">Ixazomib is a second-generation proteasome inhibitor that is given orally on a weekly basis for 3 of every 4 weeks.</Para><Para id="_980">Evidence (ixazomib):</Para><OrderedList id="_981" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a prospective randomized trial involving 722 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma, ixazomib combined with lenalidomide and dexamethasone was compared with a placebo combined with lenalidomide and dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><ItemizedList id="_982" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 2 years, the median PFS was 20.6 months in the ixazomib group versus 14.7 months for the placebo group (HR, 0.66; 95% CI, 0.47–0.93; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .016).<Reference refidx="33"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Improved PFS was also seen for high-risk patients (defined by fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization and cytogenetics).<Reference refidx="34"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>No grade 3 or 4 neuropathy was seen in any patient treated with ixazomib.</ListItem><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 85 months, there was little difference in the median OS at 53.6 months for the ixazomib group and 51.6 months for the placebo group (HR, 0.939; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .49).<Reference refidx="35"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef> based on PFS, as noted above]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01850524">NCT01850524</ProtocolRef>) included 705 patients with newly diagnosed, transplant-eligible multiple myeloma. The study compared ixazomib combined with lenalidomide and dexamethasone with a placebo combined with lenalidomide and dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="36"/><ItemizedList id="_1116" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 53.3 to 55.8 months for each arm, the median PFS was 35.3 months in the ixazomib group versus 21.8 months in the placebo group (HR, 0.830; 95% CI, 0.676–1.018; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .073).<Reference refidx="36"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] This difference did not meet statistical significance for PFS.</ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial of patients with relapsed myeloma undergoing a second autologous SCT compared consolidation and maintenance therapy with ixazomib versus observation alone.<Reference refidx="37"/><ItemizedList id="_1336" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 27 months, the median PFS was 20 months in the consolidation and maintenance therapy group and 13 months in the observation group (HR, 0.55; 95% CI, 0.39–0.78; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0006).<Reference refidx="37"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1207"><Title>CAR T-cell therapy</Title><Para id="_1208">CAR T-cell therapy is a cellular therapy for refractory and/or multiply relapsed  myeloma. This therapy consists of autologous anti-BCMA transduced T cells. This therapy  has shown a 50% to 65% complete remission rate and a median PFS of 18 to 20 months in patients from highly selected nonrandomized series.<Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] Based on the durable responses in these nonrandomized series, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved the BCMA-directed CAR T-cell products idecabtagene vicleucel (ide-cel) and ciltacabtagene autoleucel (cilta-cel) for patients with relapsed or refractory disease. A review of the management of moderate-to-severe immune-related adverse events suggests immediate use of corticosteroids and supportive hospital care.<Reference refidx="41"/> Other molecular targets and expanded clinical approaches are being investigated.<Reference refidx="42"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><SummarySection id="_1287"><Title>Ciltacabtagene autoleucel</Title><Para id="_1302">Evidence (cilta-cel):</Para><OrderedList id="_1303" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04181827">NCT04181827</ProtocolRef>) included 419 patients with relapsed myeloma after one to three prior lines of treatment who also had lenalidomide-refractory disease. Patients received either CAR T-cell therapy with cilta-cel or the standard of care at the discretion of physicians.<Reference refidx="43"/><ItemizedList id="_1304" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 15.9 months, the 12-month PFS rate was 75.9% (95% CI, 69.4%–81.1%) in the cilta-cel group and 48.6% (95% CI, 41.5%–55.3%) in the standard-of-care group (HR, 0.26; 95% CI, 0.18–0.38; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="43"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>No difference in OS was reported. Grade 3 or higher  cytokine-release syndrome occurred in 1.1% of  patients in the CAR T-cell therapy group, and no patients had grade 3 or higher neurotoxicity.</ListItem><ListItem>Two patients developed a T-cell lymphoma on the skin at 5 and 16 months after cilta-cell infusion, and the T cells had detectable CAR transgenic expression and integration.<Reference refidx="44"/> Both patients attained a complete response with lymphoma-directed therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>A quality-of-life evaluation showed significant improvement in global health status and visual analogue scale responses for patients who received cilta-cel.<Reference refidx="45"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810021" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1311">Based on this trial, the FDA approved cilta-cel for patients with (1) relapsed or refractory myeloma after at least one line of therapy including a proteosome inhibitor (such as bortezomib) and an immunomodulatory agent (such as lenalidomide) AND (2) lenalidomide-refractory disease.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1306"><Title>Idecabtagene vicleucel (ide-cel)</Title><Para id="_1307">Evidence (ide-cel):</Para><OrderedList id="_1308" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03651128">NCT03651128</ProtocolRef>) included 386 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma after two to four prior lines of  treatment who also had lenalidomide-refractory disease. Patients received either CAR T-cell therapy with ide-cel or one of five standard alternative regimens.<Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="47"/><ItemizedList id="_1309" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 30.9 months, the median PFS was 13.8 months in the ide-cel group versus 4.4 months in the standard-regimen group (HR, 0.49; 95% CI, 0.38–0.63; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="47"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The overall and complete response rates were higher in patients who received ide-cel (71% and 39%, respectively) than in patients who received the standard regimens (42% and 5%, respectively).</ListItem><ListItem>Grade 3 or 4 adverse events occurred in 93% of patients who received ide-cel and 75% who received a standard regimen. Ide-cel was associated with cytokine-release syndrome in 88% of patients (grade 3 or higher in 5% of patients) and with neurological symptoms in 15% of patients (grade 3 or higher in 3% of patients).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1310">Based on this  trial, the FDA approved ide-cel for patients with (1) relapsed or refractory myeloma after at least two lines of therapy AND (2) lenalidomide-refractory disease.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1212"><Title>Bispecific antibody therapy</Title><Para id="_1213">Bispecific antibodies target both CD3, which is on the surface of T cells, and either BCMA or GPRC5D (G protein–coupled receptor family C group 5 member D), both of which concentrate on the surface of myeloma cells.<Reference refidx="48"/><Reference refidx="49"/></Para><SummarySection id="_1214"><Title>Teclistamab</Title><Para id="_1215">Teclistamab is a T-cell-redirecting bispecific antibody. </Para><Para id="_1216">Evidence (teclistamab):</Para><OrderedList id="_1217" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a phase I/II study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03145181">NCT03145181</ProtocolRef> and <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04557098">NCT04557098</ProtocolRef>), teclistamab was given to 165 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma who received at last four prior systemic treatments.<Reference refidx="50"/><ItemizedList id="_1218" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 14.1 months, the overall response rate was 63.0%, with a complete response rate of 39.4%. The median PFS was 11.3 months (95% CI, 8.8–17.1).<Reference refidx="50"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Side effects included cytokine release syndrome in 72% of patients (grade 3 or 4 in only one patient) and hematologic toxicity (grade 3 or 4) in 61% of patients, including febrile neutropenia (44.8%).</ListItem><ListItem>Of the 165 patients, 40 patients who had received prior anti-BCMA therapy (an antibody-drug conjugate or CAR T-cell therapy) were assessed at a median follow-up of 28.0 months.<Reference refidx="51"/> The overall response rate was 52.5%. A total of 47.5% of patients had a very good partial response or better, and 30.0% of patients had a complete response or better. The median duration of response was 14.8 months.<Reference refidx="51"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1350">Patients receiving teclistamab can be given replacement immunoglobulin G IV or subcutaneously every 2 to 4 weeks to reduce the risk of infection.<Reference refidx="52"/> Replacement of immunoglobulin G may be applicable for patients receiving other bispecific antibodies.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1264"><Title>Talquetamab</Title><Para id="_1265">Talquetamab is a T-cell-redirecting bispecific antibody that targets GPRC5D, a receptor highly expressed on plasma cells, along with CD3.</Para><Para id="_1266">Evidence (talquetamab):</Para><OrderedList id="_1267" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a phase II study, talquetamab was given to 232 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma who had received at least four prior systemic treatments.<Reference refidx="53"/><ItemizedList id="_1268" Style="bullet"><ListItem>At a median follow-up of 11.7 months, the overall response rate was 73.6% (95% CI, 63%–82.4%). Approximately 85% of responders were still in remission by 9 months.<Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Cytokine release syndrome occurred in up to 89% patients and was grade 1 or 2 in all but one case. Skin-related events and dysgeusia occurred in 60% to 70% of patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1219"><Title>Elranatamab</Title><Para id="_1220">Elranatamab is a T-cell directing bispecific antibody targeting BCMA and CD3.</Para><Para id="_1221">Evidence (elranatamab):</Para><OrderedList id="_1222" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Elranatamab was given to 187 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma who received at least four prior lines of therapy.<Reference refidx="55"/><ItemizedList id="_1223" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 14.7 months, the objective response rate was 61% (95% CI, 51.8%–69.6%), and 35% of patients achieved a complete response. The 15-month PFS rate was 50.9% (95% CI,         40.9%–60.0%).<Reference refidx="55"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Para id="_1232"><Strong>Summary: </Strong>Patients with myeloma who have received one to four prior  lines of therapy, are refractory to proteosome inhibitors and immunomodulatory agents, and are also experiencing a slow relapse are often referred for CAR T-cell therapy. This is because delays in production of the CAR T-cell agent are less problematic, and because time receiving therapy is fixed and short-term, allowing a long duration therapy-free time after a response.<Reference refidx="49"/> Patients who experience a quick relapse may benefit from an "off-the-shelf" bispecific antibody that results in similar response rates and durability of response, but this approach comes with the downside of required continual therapy.<Reference refidx="49"/> The choice of bispecific antibody cannot be made based on any clinical evidence because of the lack of comparative trials. In heavily pretreated patients, bispecific antibodies impair humoral immunity, but this can be ameliorated using IV or subcutaneous immunoglobulin and antimicrobial prophylaxis.<Reference refidx="49"/> Current logic supports using products with different targets sequentially.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_990"><Title>Immunomodulatory agents</Title><SummarySection id="_991"><Title>Pomalidomide</Title><Para id="_992">Pomalidomide is a third-generation immunomodulatory agent. Pomalidomide is associated with some myelosuppression and an increased incidence of thromboembolic events, as noted with lenalidomide and thalidomide (requiring thromboprophylaxis with aspirin at least), but very little peripheral neuropathy compared with other agents.</Para><Para id="_993">Evidence (pomalidomide):</Para><OrderedList id="_994" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02654132">ELOQUENT-3</ProtocolRef> [NCT02654132]) included 117 patients who had relapsed or refractory disease after both lenalidomide and a proteasome inhibitor. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either EPd or Pd.<Reference refidx="13"/><ItemizedList id="_995" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 45 months, the median OS was 29.8 months (95% CI, 22.9–45.7) for patients who received EPd compared with 17.4 months (95% CI, 13.8–27.7) for patients who received Pd (HR, 0.59; 95% CI, 0.37–0.93; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0217).<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective trial of 559 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma and previous treatment with lenalidomide, patients were randomly assigned to receive either pomalidomide plus bortezomib and dexamethasone or Vd.<Reference refidx="56"/><ItemizedList id="_996" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 15.9 months, the median PFS was 11.2 months (95% CI, 9.7−13.7) in the pomalidomide combination group and 7.1 months (95% CI, 5.9−8.9) in the Vd group (HR, 0.61; 95% CI, 0.49−0.77; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="56"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>For 302 patients with relapsed or refractory disease, Pd (40 mg weekly) was compared with a higher-dose dexamethasone regimen   (40 mg daily for 4 days every 8 days).<Reference refidx="57"/><ItemizedList id="_997" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 10.0 months, the PFS was superior for the pomalidomide arm, at 4.0 months versus 1.9 months (HR, 0.48; 95% CI, 0.39–0.60; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001)<Reference refidx="57"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_998"><Title>Lenalidomide</Title><Para id="_999">Lenalidomide is a second-generation immunomodulatory agent. Lenalidomide is associated with increased incidence of thromboembolic events, as noted with pomalidomide and thalidomide (requiring thromboprophylaxis with aspirin at least), myelosuppression (more than pomalidomide), and neuropathy (less than thalidomide, but more than pomalidomide).<Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="59"/><Reference refidx="60"/><Reference refidx="61"/><Reference refidx="62"/></Para><Para id="_1000">A meta-analysis of 3,254 patients from seven randomized trials showed that lenalidomide was associated with an increased risk of hematologic second primary malignancies (3.1% in patients who received lenalidomide vs. 1.4% in those who did not; HR, 3.8; 95% CI, 1.15–12.62; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .029).<Reference refidx="63"/> This risk was confined to the combination of lenalidomide and melphalan (HR, 4.86; 95% CI, 2.79–8.46; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0001) but was not higher for lenalidomide with either cyclophosphamide or dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="63"/> A retrospective review of almost 4,000 patients with relapsed or refractory disease who received lenalidomide in 11 clinical trials suggested an increased incidence of nonmelanoma skin cancers.<Reference refidx="64"/></Para><Para id="_1001">As a result of  predominant renal clearance, lenalidomide doses need to be reduced for patients with impaired renal function (creatinine clearance, 30–50: 10 mg every day; creatinine clearance, &lt;30: 15 mg every other day; dialysis, 15 mg on day after dialysis).<Reference refidx="65"/> Uncontrolled trials have added clarithromycin (500 mg twice a day) to lenalidomide and dexamethasone, with reports of increased response rates.<Reference refidx="66"/> Controlled studies are required to establish the value of this approach.</Para><Para id="_1002">Evidence (lenalidomide):</Para><OrderedList id="_1003" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Two prospective randomized and placebo-controlled studies of 351 and 353 patients with relapsed myeloma compared lenalidomide plus high-dose dexamethasone versus high-dose dexamethasone alone.<Reference refidx="67"/><Reference refidx="68"/><ItemizedList id="_1004" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 16 to 26 months, the median OS was 29.6 months or more (not reached in one trial) versus 20.2 months to 20.6 months in the control group (HR, 0.66; 95% CI, 0.45‒0.96; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03 in one study <Reference refidx="67"/> and <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt;  .001 in the other study).<Reference refidx="68"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized study of 1,623 patients with transplant-ineligible, previously untreated myeloma compared lenalidomide and dexamethasone given until disease  progression with a 72-week induction regimen with melphalan, prednisone, and thalidomide (MPT) for 72 weeks.<Reference refidx="59"/><ItemizedList id="_1005" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 46 months, there was  improved OS for the  lenalidomide group, with 4-year OS rates of 52% versus 38% (HR, 0.72; 95% CI, 0.54–0.96; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).<Reference refidx="59"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1006"><Title>Thalidomide</Title><Para id="_1007">Thalidomide is a first-generation immunomodulatory agent that is not often used because of its sedative and constipating effects, its significant and potentially debilitating neuropathy, and its thrombogenic effect (thromboprophylaxis is required).<Reference refidx="69"/><Reference refidx="70"/> Very little myelosuppression is seen with this agent.</Para><Para id="_1008">Late in the disease course, when all other options have failed, thalidomide can be employed, sometimes with durable responses.<Reference refidx="71"/>  By using a low dose (50 mg by mouth every day), significant sedation, constipation, and neuropathy may be avoided. Thromboprophylaxis with aspirin, warfarin, or low-molecular-weight heparin is required; the choice of therapy depends on preexisting risk factors.<Reference refidx="62"/></Para><Para id="_1009">Evidence (thalidomide):</Para><OrderedList id="_1010" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A meta-analysis of 1,685 previously untreated patients considered six prospective randomized trials comparing thalidomide, melphalan, and prednisone versus melphalan and prednisone alone.<Reference refidx="72"/><ItemizedList id="_1011" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The addition of thalidomide improved median OS from 32.7 months to 39.3 months (HR, 0.83; 95% CI, 0.73–0.94; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .004).<Reference refidx="72"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1294"><Title>BCMA-targeting antibody-drug conjugates</Title><SummarySection id="_1295"><Title>Belantamab mafodotin</Title><Para id="_1296">Belantamab mafodotin is an antibody-drug conjugate composed of an anti-BCMA monoclonal antibody attached to monomethyl auristatin, which inhibits microtubule formation. In 2020, the FDA approved this antibody-drug conjugate for patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma. However, this approval was withdrawn in 2023 based on findings from a prospective randomized trial in 325 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma, which compared belantamab mafodotin with pomalidomide plus dexamethasone and showed no significant difference in median PFS.<Reference refidx="73"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] Since then, the results of several European clinical trials may revive interest in seeking FDA approval in the United States.</Para><Para id="_1297">Evidence (belantamab mafodotin):</Para><OrderedList id="_1298" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04246047">NCT04246047</ProtocolRef>) included 494 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma. Patients received either belantamab mafodotin plus Vd or DVd.<Reference refidx="74"/><Reference refidx="75"/><ItemizedList id="_1299" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 28.2 months, the 3-year OS rate was 74% for the belantamab-Vd group and 60% for the  DVd group (HR, 0.58; 95% CI, 0.43–0.79; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .00023).<Reference refidx="75"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The median PFS was 36.6 months for the belantamab mafodotin-Vd group and 13.4 months for the DVd group (HR, 0.41; 95% CI, 0.31–0.53; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="74"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Belantamab mafodotin is known to cause ocular toxicity (mostly in the cornea) which was noted in 79% of patients who received the drug  in this trial. Monthly corneal examinations allowed for dose modification, and 98% of patients regained normal vision from 20/50 or worse.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04484623">NCT04484623</ProtocolRef>) included 302 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma. Patients received either belantamab mafodotin plus Pd (BPd) or PVd (pomalidomide, bortezomib, and dexamethasone).<Reference refidx="76"/><ItemizedList id="_1300" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With  a median follow-up of 21.8 months, the 1-year PFS rate was 71% for the BPd group and 51% for the PVd group (HR, 0.52; 95% CI, 0.37–0.73; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="76"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Belantamab mafodotin is known to cause ocular toxicity (usually in the cornea). Grade 3 or 4 ocular toxicity occurred in 43% of patients who received the drug in this trial (all-grades toxicity occurred in 89% of patients). Monthly corneal examinations allowed for dose modification, and 9% of patients in the BPd group required early treatment discontinuation.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1301"><Strong>Summary:</Strong> The use of BCMA-targeted therapy in the second- or third-line of therapy appears better than the usual standard of care. FDA approval may occur after review of these European trials. The use of belantamab mafodotin may affect the subsequent efficacy of other BCMA-directed therapies that have already been approved by the FDA, including the CAR T-cell therapies, cilta-cel and ide-cel, and the bispecific BCMA T-cell enhancers, teclistamab and elranatamab. Clinical trials must establish the correct sequencing of BCMA-directed therapies. In the meantime, belantamab mafodotin has not been approved by the FDA.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1012"><Title>Chemotherapy (cytotoxic agents)</Title><Para id="_1013">Regimens:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1014" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Melphalan and prednisone.<Reference refidx="77"/><Reference refidx="78"/></ListItem><ListItem>Vincristine + doxorubicin (infusion) + dexamethasone (VAD).<Reference refidx="79"/><Reference refidx="80"/></ListItem><ListItem>Cyclophosphamide (+ bortezomib + dexamethasone in the CyBorD regimen).<Reference refidx="81"/><Reference refidx="82"/></ListItem><ListItem>Pegylated liposomal doxorubicin (in a modified VAD regimen) <Reference refidx="83"/><Reference refidx="84"/> or combined with bortezomib and dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="85"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1015">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_1016" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A meta-analysis of prospective randomized trials compared  melphalan and prednisone with combinations of other cytotoxic agents. No differences were noted in PFS or OS.<Reference refidx="78"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The VAD regimen has shown activity in previously untreated patients and in relapsed patients, with response rates ranging from 60% to 80%.<Reference refidx="79"/><Reference refidx="80"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] Because of logistics problems delivering a 96-hour infusion of doxorubicin, substitution with pegylated liposomal doxorubicin provides comparable response rates.<Reference refidx="83"/><Reference refidx="84"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1017">Chemotherapy alone has been used to obtain a clinical remission after exhausting most of the new regimens, allowing improvement in performance status that may permit subsequent use of clinical trials investigating alternative therapies.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1020"><Title>Selinexor</Title><Para id="_1021">Selinexor is a selective inhibitor of nuclear export compounds that blocks exportin 1 (which activates tumor suppressor proteins), inhibits nuclear factor κB, and reduces oncoprotein mRNA translation.</Para><Para id="_1022">Selinexor (evidence):</Para><OrderedList id="_1023" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial included 402 patients with relapsed or refractory disease. Patients received either selinexor plus bortezomib and dexamethasone (SVd) or Vd.<Reference refidx="86"/><ItemizedList id="_1155" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 13.2 months (SVd) or 16.5 months (Vd), the median PFS was 13.9 months (95% CI, 11.7–not evaluable) for patients who received SVd and 9.5 months (95% CI, 8.1–10.8) for patients who received Vd (HR, 0.70; 95% CI, 0.53–0.93; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0075).<Reference refidx="86"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>Patients who received the selinexor combination had more thrombocytopenia (39% vs. 17%) and fatigue (13% vs. 1%).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a phase IIB multicenter study, 122 patients with multiply resistant myeloma refractory to a proteasome inhibitor, an  immunomodulatory agent, and daratumumab received oral selinexor and dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="87"/> High-risk cytogenetics were present in 53% of patients. Patients had received a median of seven previous regimens.<ItemizedList id="_1024" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A partial response or better was observed in 26% of patients (95% CI, 19%−35%), with a median duration of response of 4.4 months. The median PFS was 3.7 months; median OS was 8.6 months.<Reference refidx="87"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a phase II study of 42 patients with relapsed or refractory disease, patients received SVd.<Reference refidx="88"/><ItemizedList id="_1025" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A partial response or better was observed in 63% of patients, with a median PFS of 9.0 months.<Reference refidx="88"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1085">Selinexor has significant side effects, including nausea, vomiting, fatigue, diarrhea, weight loss, poor appetite, and cytopenias. A descriptive retrospective study of 437 patients enrolled in clinical trials focused on aggressive medical support for these side effects.<Reference refidx="89"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1026"><Title>Venetoclax</Title><Para id="_1027">Venetoclax is a selective BCL-2 inhibitor that induces apoptosis in myeloma cells, particularly in those with t(11;14), which expresses high levels of bcl2.</Para><Para id="_1028">Evidence (venetoclax):</Para><OrderedList id="_1029" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a phase I study of 66 heavily pretreated patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma, 30 patients harbored a t(11;14) translocation.<Reference refidx="90"/><ItemizedList id="_1030" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Among all 66 patients, the overall response rate was 21%, and 15% of patients achieved very good partial response or better. For those with t(11;14), the overall response rate was 40%, with 27% achieving a very good partial response or better.<Reference refidx="90"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a prospective trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02755597">BELLINI</ProtocolRef> [NCT02755597]), 291 patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma were randomly assigned to receive venetoclax plus bortezomib and dexamethasone versus placebo plus bortezomib and dexamethasone.<Reference refidx="91"/><ItemizedList id="_1086" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 18.7 months, the median PFS was 22.4 months for patients on the venetoclax arm versus 11.5 months for patients on the placebo arm (HR, 0.63; 95% CI, 0.44–0.90; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .01). </ListItem><ListItem>OS favored the placebo arm because of treatment-related sepsis (HR, 2.03; 95% CI, 1.04–3.95; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .034).<Reference refidx="91"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>A prespecified analysis of 35 patients with t(11;14) translocation (20 patients who received venetoclax and 15 patients who received placebo) resulted in the median PFS not being reached for patients on the venetoclax arm versus 9.5 months for patients on the placebo arm (HR, 0.11; 95% CI, 0.02–0.56; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .004).<Reference refidx="91"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1205"><Title>BRAF/MEK inhibitors</Title><Para id="_1206">Although activating <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> variants are rarely found in patients with newly diagnosed myeloma, these variants appear in multiple-relapsing disease. Twelve such patients with a <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> V600E variant who received encorafenib and binimetinib had an overall response rate of 83.3%, a median PFS of 5.6 months, and an OS rate of 55% at 24 months.<Reference refidx="92"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1035"><Title>Corticosteroids</Title><Para id="_1036">Dexamethasone dosage has been evaluated in two prospective randomized trials.</Para><OrderedList id="_1037" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A prospective randomized study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00098475">ECOG-E4A03</ProtocolRef>) of 445 previously untreated patients with myeloma compared lenalidomide and high-dose dexamethasone (40 mg on days 1–4, 9–12, and 17–20, every 28 days) with lenalidomide and low-dose dexamethasone (40 mg on days 1, 8, 15, and 22, every 28 days).<Reference refidx="58"/><ItemizedList id="_1038" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 36 months, the 2-year OS rate favored the low-dose dexamethasone arm (87% vs. 75%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006), despite no difference in PFS.<Reference refidx="58"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The increased deaths on the high-dose dexamethasone arm were attributed to cardiopulmonary toxicity.  </ListItem><ListItem>Deep venous thromboses (DVTs) were also more frequent in the high-dose arm (25% vs. 9%).  Patients in the low-dose dexamethasone arm with lenalidomide experienced less than 5% DVT with aspirin alone.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A prospective randomized trial of melphalan and prednisone versus melphalan and high-dose dexamethasone showed no difference in PFS or OS, but there was an increase in infection in the high-dose dexamethasone arm.<Reference refidx="93"/></ListItem><ListItem>A retrospective review of 541 patients in pooled myeloma studies from the Southwest Oncology Group found frequent dosage reductions of dexamethasone because of toxicity. These dose reductions did not appear to impact PFS or OS.<Reference refidx="94"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1358"><Strong>Summary:</Strong> Although prospective randomized trials are needed to clarify the role of corticosteroids or their dose, it is doubtful that those studies will ever be performed.</Para><Para id="_1039">Based on these trials, all ongoing trials and regimens use the low-dose dexamethasone schedule in combination with other therapeutic agents: 40 mg dexamethasone (oral or IV) weekly in fit patients, or 20 mg (oral or IV) in less-fit patients at higher risk for complications.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_219_sid_10"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_219_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12504655" MedlineID="22393043">Riccardi A, Mora O, Tinelli C, et al.: Response to first-line chemotherapy and long-term survival in patients with multiple myeloma: results of the MM87 prospective randomised protocol. Eur J Cancer 39 (1): 31-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15111617">Durie BG, Jacobson J, Barlogie B, et al.: Magnitude of response with myeloma frontline therapy does not predict outcome: importance of time to progression in southwest oncology group chemotherapy trials. J Clin Oncol 22 (10): 1857-63, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="31270103">Usmani SZ, Nahi H, Mateos MV, et al.: Subcutaneous delivery of daratumumab in relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Blood 134 (8): 668-677, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="36413710">Sonneveld P, Chanan-Khan A, Weisel K, et al.: Overall Survival With Daratumumab, Bortezomib, and Dexamethasone in Previously Treated Multiple Myeloma (CASTOR): A Randomized, Open-Label, Phase III Trial. J Clin Oncol 41 (8): 1600-1609, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="27705267">Dimopoulos MA, Oriol A, Nahi H, et al.: Daratumumab, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 375 (14): 1319-1331, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="36599114">Dimopoulos MA, Oriol A, Nahi H, et al.: Overall Survival With Daratumumab, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone in Previously Treated Multiple Myeloma (POLLUX): A Randomized, Open-Label, Phase III Trial. J Clin Oncol 41 (8): 1590-1599, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="34871550">Usmani SZ, Quach H, Mateos MV, et al.: Carfilzomib, dexamethasone, and daratumumab versus carfilzomib and dexamethasone for patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma (CANDOR): updated outcomes from a randomised, multicentre, open-label, phase 3 study. Lancet Oncol 23 (1): 65-76, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="32682484">Dimopoulos M, Quach H, Mateos MV, et al.: Carfilzomib, dexamethasone, and daratumumab versus carfilzomib and dexamethasone for patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma (CANDOR): results from a randomised, multicentre, open-label, phase 3 study. Lancet 396 (10245): 186-197, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="34087126">Dimopoulos MA, Terpos E, Boccadoro M, et al.: Daratumumab plus pomalidomide and dexamethasone versus pomalidomide and dexamethasone alone in previously treated multiple myeloma (APOLLO): an open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 22 (6): 801-812, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="27216216">Usmani SZ, Weiss BM, Plesner T, et al.: Clinical efficacy of daratumumab monotherapy in patients with heavily pretreated relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Blood 128 (1): 37-44, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="26308596">Lokhorst HM, Plesner T, Laubach JP, et al.: Targeting CD38 with Daratumumab Monotherapy in Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 373 (13): 1207-19, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="27531679">Plesner T, Arkenau HT, Gimsing P, et al.: Phase 1/2 study of daratumumab, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone for relapsed multiple myeloma. Blood 128 (14): 1821-1828, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="35960908">Dimopoulos MA, Dytfeld D, Grosicki S, et al.: Elotuzumab Plus Pomalidomide and Dexamethasone for Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma: Final Overall Survival Analysis From the Randomized Phase II ELOQUENT-3 Trial. J Clin Oncol 41 (3): 568-578, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="32887873">Dimopoulos MA, Lonial S, White D, et al.: Elotuzumab, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone in RRMM: final overall survival results from the phase 3 randomized ELOQUENT-2 study. Blood Cancer J 10 (9): 91, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="35151415">Richardson PG, Perrot A, San-Miguel J, et al.: Isatuximab plus pomalidomide and low-dose dexamethasone versus pomalidomide and low-dose dexamethasone in patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma (ICARIA-MM): follow-up analysis of a randomised, phase 3 study. Lancet Oncol 23 (3): 416-427, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="34097854">Moreau P, Dimopoulos MA, Mikhael J, et al.: Isatuximab, carfilzomib, and dexamethasone in relapsed multiple myeloma (IKEMA): a multicentre, open-label, randomised phase 3 trial. Lancet 397 (10292): 2361-2371, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="20807892">Bringhen S, Larocca A, Rossi D, et al.: Efficacy and safety of once-weekly bortezomib in multiple myeloma patients. Blood 116 (23): 4745-53, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="20739218">Mateos MV, Oriol A, Martínez-López J, et al.: Bortezomib, melphalan, and prednisone versus bortezomib, thalidomide, and prednisone as induction therapy followed by maintenance treatment with bortezomib and thalidomide versus bortezomib and prednisone in elderly patients with untreated multiple myeloma: a randomised trial. Lancet Oncol 11 (10): 934-41, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="21507715">Moreau P, Pylypenko H, Grosicki S, et al.: Subcutaneous versus intravenous administration of bortezomib in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma: a randomised, phase 3, non-inferiority study. Lancet Oncol 12 (5): 431-40, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="18200040">San-Miguel JF, Richardson PG, Sonneveld P, et al.: Efficacy and safety of bortezomib in patients with renal impairment: results from the APEX phase 3 study. Leukemia 22 (4): 842-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="20956629">Dimopoulos MA, Terpos E, Chanan-Khan A, et al.: Renal impairment in patients with multiple myeloma: a consensus statement on behalf of the International Myeloma Working Group. J Clin Oncol 28 (33): 4976-84, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="25023616">Knopf KB, Duh MS, Lafeuille MH, et al.: Meta-analysis of the efficacy and safety of bortezomib re-treatment in patients with multiple myeloma. Clin Lymphoma Myeloma Leuk 14 (5): 380-8, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="17690257">Richardson PG, Sonneveld P, Schuster M, et al.: Extended follow-up of a phase 3 trial in relapsed multiple myeloma: final time-to-event results of the APEX trial. Blood 110 (10): 3557-60, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="17679727">Orlowski RZ, Nagler A, Sonneveld P, et al.: Randomized phase III study of pegylated liposomal doxorubicin plus bortezomib compared with bortezomib alone in relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma: combination therapy improves time to progression. J Clin Oncol 25 (25): 3892-901, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="25102853">Mateos MV, Oriol A, Martínez-López J, et al.: GEM2005 trial update comparing VMP/VTP as induction in elderly multiple myeloma patients: do we still need alkylators? Blood 124 (12): 1887-93, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="29866475">Moreau P, Mateos MV, Berenson JR, et al.: Once weekly versus twice weekly carfilzomib dosing in patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma (A.R.R.O.W.): interim analysis results of a randomised, phase 3 study. Lancet Oncol 19 (7): 953-964, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="29341834">Siegel DS, Dimopoulos MA, Ludwig H, et al.: Improvement in Overall Survival With Carfilzomib, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 36 (8): 728-734, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="27439911">Avet-Loiseau H, Fonseca R, Siegel D, et al.: Carfilzomib significantly improves the progression-free survival of high-risk patients in multiple myeloma. Blood 128 (9): 1174-80, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="28843768">Dimopoulos MA, Goldschmidt H, Niesvizky R, et al.: Carfilzomib or bortezomib in relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma (ENDEAVOR): an interim overall survival analysis of an open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 18 (10): 1327-1337, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="31188726">Cornell RF, Ky B, Weiss BM, et al.: Prospective Study of Cardiac Events During Proteasome Inhibitor Therapy for Relapsed Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 37 (22): 1946-1955, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="29285538">Waxman AJ, Clasen S, Hwang WT, et al.: Carfilzomib-Associated Cardiovascular Adverse Events: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. JAMA Oncol 4 (3): e174519, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="32382772">Ball S, Behera TR, Anwer F, et al.: Risk of kidney toxicity with carfilzomib in multiple myeloma: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Ann Hematol 99 (6): 1265-1271, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="27119237">Moreau P, Masszi T, Grzasko N, et al.: Oral Ixazomib, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 374 (17): 1621-34, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="29054911">Avet-Loiseau H, Bahlis NJ, Chng WJ, et al.: Ixazomib significantly prolongs progression-free survival in high-risk relapsed/refractory myeloma patients. Blood 130 (24): 2610-2618, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="34111952">Richardson PG, Kumar SK, Masszi T, et al.: Final Overall Survival Analysis of the TOURMALINE-MM1 Phase III Trial of Ixazomib, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 39 (22): 2430-2442, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="33763699">Facon T, Venner CP, Bahlis NJ, et al.: Oral ixazomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone for transplant-ineligible patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma. Blood 137 (26): 3616-3628, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="39250926">Cook G, Ashcroft AJ, Senior E, et al.: Ixazomib as consolidation and maintenance versus observation in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma eligible for salvage autologous stem-cell transplantation (Myeloma XII [ACCoRD]): interim analysis of a multicentre, open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet Haematol 11 (11): e816-e829, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="35333600">Wang Y, Cao J, Gu W, et al.: Long-Term Follow-Up of Combination of B-Cell Maturation Antigen and CD19 Chimeric Antigen Receptor T Cells in Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol 40 (20): 2246-2256, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="33626253">Munshi NC, Anderson LD, Shah N, et al.: Idecabtagene Vicleucel in Relapsed and Refractory Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 384 (8): 705-716, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="35658469">Martin T, Usmani SZ, Berdeja JG, et al.: Ciltacabtagene Autoleucel, an Anti-B-cell Maturation Antigen Chimeric Antigen Receptor T-Cell Therapy, for Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma: CARTITUDE-1 2-Year Follow-Up. J Clin Oncol 41 (6): 1265-1274, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="34724386">Santomasso BD, Nastoupil LJ, Adkins S, et al.: Management of Immune-Related Adverse Events in Patients Treated With Chimeric Antigen Receptor T-Cell Therapy: ASCO Guideline. J Clin Oncol 39 (35): 3978-3992, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="36170501">Mailankody S, Devlin SM, Landa J, et al.: GPRC5D-Targeted CAR T Cells for Myeloma. N Engl J Med 387 (13): 1196-1206, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="37272512">San-Miguel J, Dhakal B, Yong K, et al.: Cilta-cel or Standard Care in Lenalidomide-Refractory Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 389 (4): 335-347, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="39938094">Harrison SJ, Touzeau C, Kint N, et al.: CAR+ T-Cell Lymphoma after Cilta-cel Therapy for Relapsed or Refractory Myeloma. N Engl J Med 392 (7): 677-685, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="39756844">Mina R, Mylin AK, Yokoyama H, et al.: Patient-reported outcomes following ciltacabtagene autoleucel or standard of care in patients with lenalidomide-refractory multiple myeloma (CARTITUDE-4): results from a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Haematol 12 (1): e45-e56, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="36762851">Rodriguez-Otero P, Ailawadhi S, Arnulf B, et al.: Ide-cel or Standard Regimens in Relapsed and Refractory Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 388 (11): 1002-1014, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="39197072">Ailawadhi S, Arnulf B, Patel K, et al.: Ide-cel vs standard regimens in triple-class-exposed relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma: updated KarMMa-3 analyses. Blood 144 (23): 2389-2401, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="35404996">Moreau P, Touzeau C: T-cell-redirecting bispecific antibodies in multiple myeloma: a revolution? Blood 139 (26): 3681-3687, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="37471687">Holstein SA, Grant SJ, Wildes TM: Chimeric Antigen Receptor T-Cell and Bispecific Antibody Therapy in Multiple Myeloma: Moving Into the Future. J Clin Oncol 41 (27): 4416-4429, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="35661166">Moreau P, Garfall AL, van de Donk NWCJ, et al.: Teclistamab in Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 387 (6): 495-505, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="39172760">Touzeau C, Krishnan AY, Moreau P, et al.: Efficacy and safety of teclistamab in patients with relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma after BCMA-targeting therapies. Blood 144 (23): 2375-2388, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="52">Cheruvalath H, Clennon A, Shrestha A, et al.: Effects of intravenous immunoglobulin supplementation (IVIG) on infections in recipients of teclistamab therapy for multiple myeloma (MM): a multi-institutional study. [Abstract] Blood  144 (Suppl 1): A-256, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="36507686">Chari A, Minnema MC, Berdeja JG, et al.: Talquetamab, a T-Cell-Redirecting GPRC5D Bispecific Antibody for Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 387 (24): 2232-2244, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="54">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: FDA grants accelerated approval to talquetamab-tgvs for relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/resources-information-approved-drugs/fda-grants-accelerated-approval-talquetamab-tgvs-relapsed-or-refractory-multiple-myeloma">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed April 23, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="37582952">Lesokhin AM, Tomasson MH, Arnulf B, et al.: Elranatamab in relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma: phase 2 MagnetisMM-3 trial results. Nat Med 29 (9): 2259-2267, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="31097405">Richardson PG, Oriol A, Beksac M, et al.: Pomalidomide, bortezomib, and dexamethasone for patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma previously treated with lenalidomide (OPTIMISMM): a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 20 (6): 781-794, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="24007748">San Miguel J, Weisel K, Moreau P, et al.: Pomalidomide plus low-dose dexamethasone versus high-dose dexamethasone alone for patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma (MM-003): a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 14 (11): 1055-66, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="19853510">Rajkumar SV, Jacobus S, Callander NS, et al.: Lenalidomide plus high-dose dexamethasone versus lenalidomide plus low-dose dexamethasone as initial therapy for newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: an open-label randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 11 (1): 29-37, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="27325857">Hulin C, Belch A, Shustik C, et al.: Updated Outcomes and Impact of Age With Lenalidomide and Low-Dose Dexamethasone or Melphalan, Prednisone, and Thalidomide in the Randomized, Phase III FIRST Trial. J Clin Oncol 34 (30): 3609-3617, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="19901114">Zangari M, Tricot G, Polavaram L, et al.: Survival effect of venous thromboembolism in patients with multiple myeloma treated with lenalidomide and high-dose dexamethasone. J Clin Oncol 28 (1): 132-5, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="21835953">Larocca A, Cavallo F, Bringhen S, et al.: Aspirin or enoxaparin thromboprophylaxis for patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma treated with lenalidomide. Blood 119 (4): 933-9; quiz 1093, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="32438407">Bradbury CA, Craig Z, Cook G, et al.: Thrombosis in patients with myeloma treated in the Myeloma IX and Myeloma XI phase 3 randomized controlled trials. Blood 136 (9): 1091-1104, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="24525202">Palumbo A, Bringhen S, Kumar SK, et al.: Second primary malignancies with lenalidomide therapy for newly diagnosed myeloma: a meta-analysis of individual patient data. Lancet Oncol 15 (3): 333-42, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="22323483">Dimopoulos MA, Richardson PG, Brandenburg N, et al.: A review of second primary malignancy in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma treated with lenalidomide. Blood 119 (12): 2764-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="20192988">Dimopoulos MA, Christoulas D, Roussou M, et al.: Lenalidomide and dexamethasone for the treatment of refractory/relapsed multiple myeloma: dosing of lenalidomide according to renal function and effect on renal impairment. Eur J Haematol 85 (1): 1-5, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="23299315">Rossi A, Mark T, Jayabalan D, et al.: BiRd (clarithromycin, lenalidomide, dexamethasone): an update on long-term lenalidomide therapy in previously untreated patients with multiple myeloma. Blood 121 (11): 1982-5, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="18032762">Dimopoulos M, Spencer A, Attal M, et al.: Lenalidomide plus dexamethasone for relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med 357 (21): 2123-32, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="18032763">Weber DM, Chen C, Niesvizky R, et al.: Lenalidomide plus dexamethasone for relapsed multiple myeloma in North America. N Engl J Med 357 (21): 2133-42, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="21282540">Palumbo A, Cavo M, Bringhen S, et al.: Aspirin, warfarin, or enoxaparin thromboprophylaxis in patients with multiple myeloma treated with thalidomide: a phase III, open-label, randomized trial. J Clin Oncol 29 (8): 986-93, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="20932799">Delforge M, Bladé J, Dimopoulos MA, et al.: Treatment-related peripheral neuropathy in multiple myeloma: the challenge continues. Lancet Oncol 11 (11): 1086-95, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="18245666">Palumbo A, Facon T, Sonneveld P, et al.: Thalidomide for treatment of multiple myeloma: 10 years later. Blood 111 (8): 3968-77, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="21670471">Fayers PM, Palumbo A, Hulin C, et al.: Thalidomide for previously untreated elderly patients with multiple myeloma: meta-analysis of 1685 individual patient data from 6 randomized clinical trials. Blood 118 (5): 1239-47, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="37793771">Dimopoulos MA, Hungria VTM, Radinoff A, et al.: Efficacy and safety of single-agent belantamab mafodotin versus pomalidomide plus low-dose dexamethasone in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma (DREAMM-3): a phase 3, open-label, randomised study. Lancet Haematol 10 (10): e801-e812, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="38828933">Hungria V, Robak P, Hus M, et al.: Belantamab Mafodotin, Bortezomib, and Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 391 (5): 393-407, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="75">Hungria V, Robak P, Hus M, et al.: Belantamab mafodotin, bortezomib, and dexamethasone vs daratumumab, bortezomib, and dexamethasone in relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma: overall survival analysis and updated efficacy outcomes of the phase 3 Dreamm-7 trial. [Abstract] Blood  144 (Suppl 1): A-772, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="38828951">Dimopoulos MA, Beksac M, Pour L, et al.: Belantamab Mafodotin, Pomalidomide, and Dexamethasone in Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 391 (5): 408-421, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="1531068" MedlineID="92121948">Gregory WM, Richards MA, Malpas JS: Combination chemotherapy versus melphalan and prednisolone in the treatment of multiple myeloma: an overview of published trials. J Clin Oncol 10 (2): 334-42, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="9850028" MedlineID="99065280">Combination chemotherapy versus melphalan plus prednisone as treatment for multiple myeloma: an overview of 6,633 patients from 27 randomized trials. Myeloma Trialists' Collaborative Group. J Clin Oncol 16 (12): 3832-42, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="79" PMID="10233375" MedlineID="99250515">Segeren CM, Sonneveld P, van der Holt B, et al.: Vincristine, doxorubicin and dexamethasone (VAD) administered as rapid intravenous infusion for first-line treatment in untreated multiple myeloma. Br J Haematol 105 (1): 127-30, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="80" PMID="7841049">Anderson H, Scarffe JH, Ranson M, et al.: VAD chemotherapy as remission induction for multiple myeloma. Br J Cancer 71 (2): 326-30, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="81" PMID="18645194">Reece DE, Rodriguez GP, Chen C, et al.: Phase I-II trial of bortezomib plus oral cyclophosphamide and prednisone in relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma. J Clin Oncol 26 (29): 4777-83, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="82">Knop S, Liebisch H, Wandt H, et al.: Bortezomib, IV cyclophosphamide, and dexamethasone (VelCD) as induction therapy in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: results of an interim analysis of the German DSMM Xia trial. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  27 (Suppl 15): A-8516, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="83" PMID="12853344">Dimopoulos MA, Pouli A, Zervas K, et al.: Prospective randomized comparison of vincristine, doxorubicin and dexamethasone (VAD) administered as intravenous bolus injection and VAD with liposomal doxorubicin as first-line treatment in multiple myeloma. Ann Oncol 14 (7): 1039-44, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="84" PMID="16404741">Rifkin RM, Gregory SA, Mohrbacher A, et al.: Pegylated liposomal doxorubicin, vincristine, and dexamethasone provide significant reduction in toxicity compared with doxorubicin, vincristine, and dexamethasone in patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: a Phase III multicenter randomized trial. Cancer 106 (4): 848-58, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="85" PMID="19738129">Jakubowiak AJ, Kendall T, Al-Zoubi A, et al.: Phase II trial of combination therapy with bortezomib, pegylated liposomal doxorubicin, and dexamethasone in patients with newly diagnosed myeloma. J Clin Oncol 27 (30): 5015-22, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="86" PMID="33189178">Grosicki S, Simonova M, Spicka I, et al.: Once-per-week selinexor, bortezomib, and dexamethasone versus twice-per-week bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with multiple myeloma (BOSTON): a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet 396 (10262): 1563-1573, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="87" PMID="31433920">Chari A, Vogl DT, Gavriatopoulou M, et al.: Oral Selinexor-Dexamethasone for Triple-Class Refractory Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 381 (8): 727-738, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="88" PMID="30352784">Bahlis NJ, Sutherland H, White D, et al.: Selinexor plus low-dose bortezomib and dexamethasone for patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Blood 132 (24): 2546-2554, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="89" PMID="32094461">Gavriatopoulou M, Chari A, Chen C, et al.: Integrated safety profile of selinexor in multiple myeloma: experience from 437 patients enrolled in clinical trials. Leukemia 34 (9): 2430-2440, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="90" PMID="29018077">Kumar S, Kaufman JL, Gasparetto C, et al.: Efficacy of venetoclax as targeted therapy for relapsed/refractory t(11;14) multiple myeloma. Blood 130 (22): 2401-2409, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="91" PMID="33129376">Kumar SK, Harrison SJ, Cavo M, et al.: Venetoclax or placebo in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma (BELLINI): a randomised, double-blind, multicentre, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (12): 1630-1642, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="92" PMID="36608320">Giesen N, Chatterjee M, Scheid C, et al.: A phase 2 clinical trial of combined BRAF/MEK inhibition for BRAFV600E-mutated multiple myeloma. Blood 141 (14): 1685-1690, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="93" PMID="17233817">Shustik C, Belch A, Robinson S, et al.: A randomised comparison of melphalan with prednisone or dexamethasone as induction therapy and dexamethasone or observation as maintenance therapy in multiple myeloma: NCIC CTG MY.7. Br J Haematol 136 (2): 203-11, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="94" PMID="39321347">Banerjee R, Sexton R, Cowan AJ, et al.: Dexamethasone dose intensity does not impact outcomes in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma: a secondary SWOG analysis. Blood 145 (1): 75-84, 2025.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_589"><Title>Key References for Plasma Cell Neoplasms  (Including Multiple Myeloma)</Title><Para id="_590">These references have been identified by members of the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef> as significant in the field of plasma cell neoplasms  and multiple myeloma treatment.  This list is provided to inform users of important studies that have helped shape the current understanding of and treatment options for plasma cell neoplasms  and multiple myeloma. Listed after each reference are the sections within this summary where the reference is cited.</Para><ItemizedList id="_591" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Facon T, Kumar SK, Plesner T, et al.: Daratumumab, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone versus lenalidomide and dexamethasone alone in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (MAIA): overall survival results from a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 22 (11): 1582-1596, 2021. <ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34655533/">[PUBMED Abstract]</ExternalRef><Para id="_1153">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1154" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_107" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Multiple Myeloma</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Moreau P, Masszi T, Grzasko N, et al.: Oral Ixazomib, Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma. N Engl J Med 374 (17): 1621-34, 2016. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27119237">[PUBMED Abstract]</ExternalRef><Para id="_594">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_595" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_219" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Morgan GJ, Davies FE, Gregory WM, et al.: First-line treatment with zoledronic acid as compared with clodronic acid in multiple myeloma (MRC Myeloma IX): a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 376 (9757): 1989-99, 2010. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21131037">[PUBMED Abstract]</ExternalRef><Para id="_596">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_597" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_107" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Multiple Myeloma</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Palumbo A, Avet-Loiseau H, Oliva S, et al.: Revised International Staging System for Multiple Myeloma: A Report From International Myeloma Working Group. J Clin Oncol 33 (26): 2863-9, 2015. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26240224">[PUBMED Abstract]</ExternalRef><Para id="_598">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_599" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_45" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Stage Information for Plasma Cell Neoplasms</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Sonneveld P, Chanan-Khan A, Weisel K, et al.: Overall Survival With Daratumumab, Bortezomib, and Dexamethasone in Previously Treated Multiple Myeloma (CASTOR): A Randomized, Open-Label, Phase III Trial. J Clin Oncol 41 (8): 1600-1609, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36413710/">[PUBMED Abstract]</ExternalRef> <Para id="_631">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_632" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_107" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Multiple Myeloma</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_219" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Rajkumar SV, Dimopoulos MA, Palumbo A, et al.: International Myeloma Working Group updated criteria for the diagnosis of multiple myeloma. Lancet Oncol 15 (12): e538-48, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25439696">[PUBMED Abstract]</ExternalRef><Para id="_600">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_601" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">General Information About Plasma Cell Neoplasms</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_57" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview for Plasma Cell Neoplasms</SummaryRef> </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_224"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (04/25/2025)</Title><Para id="_225">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_1359"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_67" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Amyloidosis Associated With Plasma Cell Neoplasms</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_1360">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1122" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that when daratumumab is used for induction therapy, the fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization–detected cytogenetic abnormality of t(11;14) no longer confers an adverse prognostic impact. However, the presence of 1q gain continues to be associated with a lower response rate and hematologic event-free survival during treatment of amyloid light chain amyloidosis (cited Chakraborty et al. as reference 24).</Para><Para id="_1361"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_107" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Multiple Myeloma</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_1362">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1197" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that using peripheral blood to assess for measurable residual disease (MRD) appears feasible with next-generation flow and mass spectroscopy. This approach is  less invasive than using bone marrow (cited Lasa et al. as reference 55).</Para><Para id="_1363">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_829" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> about a prospective randomized trial of 200 patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma who achieved a very good or better partial response, were MRD-positive on bone marrow, and who had not received daratumumab (or isatuximab) anti-CD38 therapy during induction. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either daratumumab and lenalidomide (Dara-R) or lenalidomide alone (cited Badros et al. as reference 130 and level of evidence B1).</Para><Para id="_1364">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1355" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that one prospective trial found improved progression-free survival (PFS) for Dara-R compared with lenalidomide alone in a population that had undergone transplant and was naïve to anti-CD38 therapy. One trial establishing the daratumumab, bortezomib, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone (D-VRd) regimen for newly diagnosed patients included Dara-R maintenance in the D-VRd induction arm. The incremental impact of Dara-R maintenance therapy in patients who received daratumumab induction therapy has not been established. It is also unclear if patients with MRD-negative disease after induction therapy and transplant would benefit similarly since they were also not studied (cited Touzeau et al. as reference 139).</Para><Para id="_1365"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_219" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_1366">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1303" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> about the results of a prospective randomized trial that included 419 patients with relapsed myeloma after one to three prior lines of treatment who also had lenalidomide-refractory disease. Patients received either ciltacabtagene autoleucel or the standard of care at the discretion of physicians (cited Harrison et al. as reference 44, and Mina et al. as reference 45, level of evidence A3).</Para><Para id="_1367">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_1036" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> about a retrospective review of 541 patients in pooled myeloma studies from the Southwest Oncology Group. The review found frequent dosage reductions of dexamethasone because of toxicity. These dose reductions did not appear to impact PFS or overall survival (cited Banerjee et al. as reference 94 and level of evidence C3). Also added text to state that although prospective randomized trials are needed to clarify the role of corticosteroids or their dose, it is doubtful that those studies will ever be performed.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062866#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about treatment of plasma cell neoplasms (including multiple myeloma). It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewer for Plasma Cell Neoplasms (Including Multiple Myeloma) Treatment is:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Eric J. Seifter, MD (Johns Hopkins University)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Plasma Cell Neoplasms (Including Multiple Myeloma) Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/myeloma/hp/myeloma-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389362]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-04-25</DateLastModified></Summary>
