<Summary id="CDR0000062869" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Acute myeloid (myelogenous) leukemia (AML) treatment options include chemotherapy, radiation therapy, stem cell transplant, and other medications. Cytogenetic analysis helps predict treatment outcomes. Get detailed information about AML in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037885">adult acute myeloid leukemia</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_445">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of acute myeloid leukemia. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_446">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adult acute myeloid leukemia</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037885">adult acute myeloid leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML)</Title><Para id="_448">AML is also called
acute myelogenous leukemia and acute nonlymphocytic leukemia.</Para><SummarySection id="_359"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_258">Estimated new cases and deaths from AML  in the United States in 2025:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_259" Style="bullet"><ListItem>New cases: 22,010.</ListItem><ListItem>Deaths: 11,090.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_577">Based on Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program data from 2014 to 2020, 31.9% of patients with AML were alive 5 years after diagnosis.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_449"><Title>Anatomy</Title><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526538" type="image/jpeg" alt="Blood cell development; drawing shows the steps a blood stem cell goes through to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell. A myeloid stem cell becomes a red blood cell, a platelet, or a myeloblast, which then becomes a granulocyte (the types of granulocytes are eosinophils, basophils, and neutrophils). A lymphoid stem cell becomes a lymphoblast and then becomes a B-lymphocyte, T-lymphocyte, or natural killer cell." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_568"><Caption language="en">Blood cell development. A blood stem cell goes through several steps to become a red blood cell, platelet, or white blood cell.   </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_578">AML  is a heterogenous group of blood cancers that  result from clonal expansion of myeloid hematopoietic precursors in the bone marrow. Not only are circulating leukemia cells (also called blasts) seen in the peripheral blood, but granulocytopenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia are also common as proliferating leukemia cells interfere with normal hematopoiesis.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_450"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_579">The diagnosis of AML is uncommon before age 45 years; the median age at diagnosis is 69 years.<Reference refidx="2"/> Patients may present with symptoms that include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_580" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Weakness.</ListItem><ListItem>Fever.</ListItem><ListItem>Infection.</ListItem><ListItem>Pallor. </ListItem><ListItem>Bleeding. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_581">The hampered production of normal blood cells due to leukemic infiltration of the bone marrow can also cause other symptoms and complications. Less commonly, patients have signs or symptoms related to the collection of leukemia cells in certain anatomical locations, such as central nervous system (CNS) or testicular involvement, or the presence of a myeloid sarcoma (also called chloroma). The symptoms of acute leukemia often arise over a 4- to 6-week period before diagnosis.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_451"><Title>Diagnostic Evaluation</Title><Para id="_8">The differentiation of AML from other forms of leukemia, in particular chronic myeloid leukemia and acute lymphocytic leukemia, has vital
therapeutic implications.  The primary diagnostic tool in this determination is flow cytometry to evaluate surface antigens on the leukemia cells. Simple morphology is not adequate in determining lineage and, at a minimum, special histochemical stains are needed. While a diagnosis can be made by evaluating peripheral blood, a bone marrow biopsy is used to evaluate morphology and cell surface markers, as well as provide material for cytogenetic and molecular analysis. A peripheral blood or bone marrow blast count of 20% or greater is required to make the diagnosis, except for cases with certain chromosomal abnormalities (i.e., t(15;17), t(8;21), inv(16), or t(16;16)).<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_393"><Title>Prognosis and Prognostic Factors</Title><Para id="_2">While the rates of new cases of AML have not changed significantly over the last decade, age-adjusted death rates have dropped.<Reference refidx="2"/>   Treatment should be sufficiently aggressive to
achieve complete remission (CR) because partial remission offers no substantial
survival benefit.  Approximately 60% to 70% of adults with AML can be expected
to attain CR status after appropriate induction therapy. 
More than 25% of adults with AML (about 45% of those who attain CR) can be expected to survive 3 or more years and may be cured.</Para><Para id="_452">Approximately half of patients with AML will harbor chromosomal abnormalities; therefore, conventional cytogenetic analysis remains mandatory in the evaluation of suspected AML.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> With the routine use of molecular diagnostics, the identification of recurrent somatic pathogenic variants in <GeneName>NPM1</GeneName>, <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>, <GeneName>CEPBA</GeneName>, <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>, and other genes has become a routine part of determining prognosis. Cytogenetic and molecular analyses provide the strongest prognostic information
available,  predicting outcome of both remission induction and consolidation
therapy.<Reference refidx="7"/> Cytogenic and molecular information has been combined to form distinct prognostic groups.</Para><Para id="_453">Additional adverse prognostic factors for AML include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_454" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Age at diagnosis. Remission rates in adult AML are inversely related to age, with an expected
remission rate of more than 65% for those younger than 60 years. 
Data suggest that once attained, duration of remission may be shorter in older
patients.  Increased morbidity and mortality during induction appear to be
directly related to age.</ListItem><ListItem>  CNS involvement with leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Systemic infection at diagnosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Elevated white blood cell count (&gt;100,000/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript>) at diagnosis.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_139" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Therapy-related myeloid neoplasms</SummaryRef>, resulting from alkylating agents and radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>History of myelodysplastic syndrome or another antecedent hematologic disorder.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_459"><Title>Long-Term Effects of Cancer Treatment</Title><Para id="_582">The risk of developing any long-term effects depends on the type and dose of treatment that was used and the age at which the patient underwent treatment.</Para><Para id="_105">A study of 30 patients who had AML that was in remission for at least 10 years demonstrated a 13% incidence of secondary malignancies.<Reference refidx="8"/> Of 31 female long-term survivors of AML or acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) diagnosed before age 40 years, 26 resumed normal menstruation after completion of therapy. Among 36 live offspring of survivors, two congenital problems occurred.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_583">Most patients with AML who undergo intensive therapy are treated with an anthracycline. Anthracyclines have been associated with increased risk of congestive heart failure (CHF).<Reference refidx="9"/> Anthracycline cardiotoxicity is dose-dependent. In one study, doxorubicin-related CHF was 5% at a lifetime cumulative dose of 400 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, rising to 26% at a cumulative dose of 550 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>.<Reference refidx="10"/> In many cases, heart failure can manifest as a late effect.<Reference refidx="11"/> In an analysis of children who underwent  treatment for acute leukemia, the cumulative incidence of CHF at 10 years was 1.7% in ALL and 7.5% in AML.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_584">Patients who undergo allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant can experience a large number of long-term or late side effects of  treatment as a result of high-dose chemotherapy and/or radiation, and as an effect of chronic graft-versus-host disease and immunosuppression. These side effects may include chronic fatigue, thyroid and gonadal dysfunction, infertility, chronic infection, accelerated coronary heart disease, osteopenia, cataracts, iron overload, adverse psychological outcomes, and second cancers.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> </Para><Para id="_656">In the Bone Marrow Transplant Survivor Study, hematopoietic cell transplant survivors had accelerated aging and were 8.4 times more likely to be frail than their siblings (95% confidence interval [CI], 2.0−34.5; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003). In a multivariable analysis, frailty was associated with a 2.76-fold increase in the risk of death, compared with a nonfrail state (95% CI, 1.7−4.4; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="16"/> </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results Program: Cancer Stat Facts: Leukemia — Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML). Bethesda, Md: National Cancer Institute, DCCPS, Surveillance Research Program, 2020. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/amyl.html">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 24, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="26111473">Sekeres MA, Gerds AT: Mitigating Fear and Loathing in Managing Acute Myeloid Leukemia. Semin Hematol 52 (3): 249-55, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Swerdlow SH, Campo E, Harris  NL, et al., eds.: WHO Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. 4th rev. ed. International Agency for Research on Cancer, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="11110676" MedlineID="20563921">Slovak ML, Kopecky KJ, Cassileth PA, et al.: Karyotypic analysis predicts outcome of preremission and postremission therapy in adult acute myeloid leukemia: a Southwest Oncology Group/Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Study. Blood 96 (13): 4075-83, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11520776" MedlineID="21411443">Grimwade D, Walker H, Harrison G, et al.: The predictive value of hierarchical cytogenetic classification in older adults with acute myeloid leukemia (AML): analysis of 1065 patients entered into the United Kingdom Medical Research Council AML11 trial. Blood 98 (5): 1312-20, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="27895058">Döhner H, Estey E, Grimwade D, et al.: Diagnosis and management of AML in adults: 2017 ELN recommendations from an international expert panel. Blood 129 (4): 424-447, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11380414" MedlineID="21275148">Micallef IN, Rohatiner AZ, Carter M, et al.: Long-term outcome of patients surviving for more than ten years following treatment for acute leukaemia. Br J Haematol 113 (2): 443-5, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="1886191">Steinherz LJ, Steinherz PG, Tan CT, et al.: Cardiac toxicity 4 to 20 years after completing anthracycline therapy. JAMA 266 (12): 1672-7, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="12767102">Swain SM, Whaley FS, Ewer MS: Congestive heart failure in patients treated with doxorubicin: a retrospective analysis of three trials. Cancer 97 (11): 2869-79, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="15143078">Hequet O, Le QH, Moullet I, et al.: Subclinical late cardiomyopathy after doxorubicin therapy for lymphoma in adults. J Clin Oncol 22 (10): 1864-71, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="29966479">Chellapandian D, Pole JD, Nathan PC, et al.: Congestive heart failure among children with acute leukemia: a population-based matched cohort study. Leuk Lymphoma 60 (2): 385-394, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="28232372">Inamoto Y, Lee SJ: Late effects of blood and marrow transplantation. Haematologica 102 (4): 614-625, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="21821714">Sun CL, Francisco L, Baker KS, et al.: Adverse psychological outcomes in long-term survivors of hematopoietic cell transplantation: a report from the Bone Marrow Transplant Survivor Study (BMTSS). Blood 118 (17): 4723-31, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="21652685">Armenian SH, Sun CL, Kawashima T, et al.: Long-term health-related outcomes in survivors of childhood cancer treated with HSCT versus conventional therapy: a report from the Bone Marrow Transplant Survivor Study (BMTSS) and Childhood Cancer Survivor Study (CCSS). Blood 118 (5): 1413-20, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="27254472">Arora M, Sun CL, Ness KK, et al.: Physiologic Frailty in Nonelderly Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation Patients: Results From the Bone Marrow Transplant Survivor Study. JAMA Oncol 2 (10): 1277-1286, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037885">adult acute myeloid leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Classification of AML</Title><SummarySection id="_460"><Title>World Health Organization (WHO) Classification</Title><Para id="_4">The classification of acute myeloid leukemia (AML) has been revised by a group of pathologists and clinicians under the auspices of the WHO.<Reference refidx="1"/>  While elements of the French-American-British (FAB) classification have been retained (i.e., morphology, immunophenotype, cytogenetics, and clinical features),<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> the WHO classification incorporates and interrelates morphology, cytogenetics, molecular genetics, and immunologic markers, which construct a classification that is universally applicable and has prognostic and therapeutic relevance.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  Each criterion has prognostic and treatment implications but, for practical purposes, initial antileukemic
therapy is similar for all subtypes.</Para><Para id="_461">In 2001, the WHO proposed a new classification system that incorporated diagnostic cytogenetic information and  that more reliably correlated with outcome.  This classification system also decreased the bone marrow percentage of leukemic blast requirement for the diagnosis of AML from 30% to 20%. An additional clarification was made so patients with recurrent cytogenetic abnormalities did not need to meet the minimum blast requirement to be considered  as having an AML diagnosis.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_462">In 2008, the WHO expanded the number of cytogenetic abnormalities linked to AML classification and, for the first time, included specific pathogenic variants (<GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> and <GeneName>NPM</GeneName>) in its classification system.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="8"/> With the addition of these gene variants, FAB subclassification no longer provided prognostic information for patients with a diagnosis of AML, not otherwise specified (NOS).<Reference refidx="9"/>  </Para><Para id="_585">In 2016, the WHO classification underwent revisions to incorporate the expanding knowledge of leukemia biomarkers that are significantly important to the diagnosis, prognosis, and treatment of leukemia.<Reference refidx="10"/>   With emerging technologies aimed at genetic, epigenetic, proteomic, and immunophenotypic classification, AML classification will continue to evolve and provide informative prognostic and biological guidelines to clinicians and researchers.</Para><SummarySection id="_463"><Title>2016 WHO classification of AML and related neoplasms</Title><ItemizedList id="_464" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_119" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with recurrent genetic abnormalities</SummaryRef>:<ItemizedList id="_465" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_121" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with t(8;21)(q22;q22), <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>::<GeneName>RUNX1T1</GeneName></SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_124" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with inv(16)(p13.1;q22) or t(16;16)(p13.1;q22), <GeneName>CBFB</GeneName>::<GeneName>MYH11</GeneName></SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_127" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Acute promyelocytic leukemia (APL) with <GeneName>PML</GeneName>::<GeneName>RARA</GeneName></SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_131" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with t(9;11)(p21.3;q23.3), <GeneName>MLLT3</GeneName>::<GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName></SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_468" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with t(6;9)(p23;q34.1), <GeneName>DEK</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUP214</GeneName></SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_469" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with inv(3)(q21.3;q26.2) or t(3;3)(q21.3;q26.2),  <GeneName>GATA2, MECOM</GeneName></SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_470" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML (megakaryoblastic) with t(1;22)(p13.3;q13.3), <GeneName>RBM15</GeneName>::<GeneName>MKL1</GeneName></SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_471" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> (provisional entity)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_472" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with <GeneName>NPM1</GeneName> pathogenic variants</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_473" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with biallelic <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_474" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> pathogenic variants (provisional entity)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_134" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML with myelodysplasia-related features</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_139" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Therapy-related myeloid neoplasms</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_147" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">AML, NOS</SummaryRef>:<ItemizedList id="_466" Style="bullet"><ListItem>AML with minimal differentiation (FAB classification M0).</ListItem><ListItem>AML without maturation (FAB classification M1).</ListItem><ListItem>AML with maturation (FAB classification M2).</ListItem><ListItem>Acute myelomonocytic leukemia (FAB classification M4).</ListItem><ListItem>Acute monoblastic/monocytic leukemia (FAB classification M5a and M5b).</ListItem><ListItem>Pure erythroid leukemia (FAB classification M6a and M6b).</ListItem><ListItem>Acute megakaryoblastic leukemia (FAB classification M7).</ListItem><ListItem>Acute basophilic leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Acute panmyelosis with myelofibrosis.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_485" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Myeloid sarcoma</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_486" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Myeloid proliferations related to Down syndrome</SummaryRef>:<ItemizedList id="_467" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Transient abnormal myelopoiesis (TAM).</ListItem><ListItem>Myeloid leukemia associated with Down syndrome.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_119"><Title>AML With Recurrent Genetic Abnormalities</Title><Para id="_120">AML with well-defined genetic abnormalities is characterized by recurrent genetic abnormalities.<Reference refidx="10"/>  The reciprocal translocations t(8;21), inv(16) or t(16;16), t(15;17), and translocations involving the 11q23 breakpoint are the most commonly identified chromosomal abnormalities. These structural chromosome rearrangements result in the formation of fusion genes that encode chimeric proteins that may contribute to the initiation or progression of leukemogenesis.  Many of these translocations are detected by either reverse transcriptase–polymerase chain reaction (RT–PCR) or fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization (FISH), which has a higher sensitivity than metaphase cytogenetics.  Other recurring cytogenetic abnormalities are less common.</Para><Para id="_586">Molecular diagnostic platforms such as next-generation sequencing along with RT-PCR are used to identify recurrent molecular abnormalities in AML, helping to further refine diagnostic categories in the 2016 WHO classification system.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_121"><Strong>AML with t(8;21)(q22;q22), <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-<GeneName>RUNX1T1</GeneName></Strong></Para><Para id="_122">The translocation t(8;21)(q22;q22) is one  of the most common chromosomal aberrations in AML and accounts for 5% to 12% of cases.<Reference refidx="11"/>  Myeloid sarcomas (chloromas) may be present and may be associated with a bone marrow blast percentage of less than 20%.  </Para><Para id="_248">Common morphological features include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_249" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Large blasts with abundant basophilic cytoplasm, often containing numerous azurophilic granules. </ListItem><ListItem>A few blasts in some cases show very large granules (pseudo Chediak-Higashi granules).</ListItem><ListItem>Auer rods, 
which may be detected in mature neutrophils. </ListItem><ListItem>Smaller blasts, predominantly in the peripheral blood.</ListItem><ListItem>Promyelocytes, myelocytes, and mature neutrophils with variable dysplasia in the bone marrow.</ListItem><ListItem>Abnormal nuclear segmentation (pseudo Pelger-Huët nuclei) and/or cytoplasmic staining abnormalities.</ListItem><ListItem>Increased eosinophil precursors.</ListItem><ListItem>Reduced or absent monocytes. </ListItem><ListItem>Normal erythroblasts and megakaryocytes.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_250">Rarely, AML with this translocation presents with a bone marrow blast percentage of less than 20%.<Reference refidx="5"/> Along with inv(16)(p13;q22) or t(16;16)(p13;q22), AML with t(8;21) makes up a category known as core binding factor AML. This category of AML is associated with long-term survival when treated with high-dose cytarabine.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_123">The translocation t(8;21)(q22;q22) involves the <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> gene, which encodes CBF-alpha, and the <GeneName>RUNX1T1</GeneName> (8;21) gene.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="16"/>  The <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>::<GeneName>RUNX1T1</GeneName> fusion transcript is consistently detected in patients with t(8;21) AML. This translocation is usually associated with a good response to chemotherapy and a high complete remission (CR) rate with long-term survival when treated with high-dose cytarabine in the consolidation phase, as demonstrated in the Cancer and Leukemia Group B (CLB-9022 and CLB-8525) trials.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>  Additional chromosome abnormalities are common, for example, loss of a sex chromosome and del(9)(q22).  Leukocytosis (i.e., white blood count &gt;25 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L) is associated with an inferior outcome,<Reference refidx="17"/> as is the presence of a <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="18"/>   </Para><Para id="_124"><Strong>AML with inv(16)(p13.1;q22) or t(16;16)(p13.1;q22), <GeneName>CBFB</GeneName>::<GeneName>MYH11</GeneName></Strong></Para><Para id="_125">The inv(16)(p13;q22) abnormality or t(16;16)(p13;q22) translocation is found in approximately 10% to 12% of all cases of AML, predominantly in younger patients.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="19"/>  Myeloid sarcomas may be present at initial diagnosis or at relapse.  </Para><Para id="_192">Common morphological features include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_193" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Monocytic and granulocytic differentiation.</ListItem><ListItem>A characteristically abnormal eosinophil component with immature purple-violet eosinophil granules that may obscure cell morphology if present in great numbers.</ListItem><ListItem>Auer rods in myeloblasts.</ListItem><ListItem>Decreased neutrophils in bone marrow.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_194">As is found in rare cases of AML with t(8;21), the bone marrow blast percentage in this AML is occasionally less than 20%.</Para><Para id="_126">Both inv(16)(p13;q22) and t(16;16)(p13;q22) result in the fusion of the <GeneName>CBFB</GeneName> gene at 16q22 to the smooth muscle <GeneName>MYH11</GeneName> gene at 16p13, thereby forming the <GeneName>CBFB</GeneName>::<GeneName>MYH11</GeneName> fusion gene .<Reference refidx="11"/>  The use of FISH and RT–PCR methods is sometimes necessary to document this fusion gene because its presence is not always documented by traditional cytogenetics banding techniques.<Reference refidx="20"/>   Similar to AML with t(8;21), patients with the <GeneName>CBFB</GeneName>::<GeneName>MYH11</GeneName> fusion gene achieve higher CR rates and long-term survival when treated with high-dose cytarabine in the consolidation setting.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="15"/> Unlike AML with t(8;21), the prognostic relevance of <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> pathogenic variants is unclear.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_127"><Strong>APL with <GeneName>PML</GeneName>::<GeneName>RARA</GeneName></Strong></Para><Para id="_128">APL is defined by the presence of the PML::RARA fusion protein, typically a result of  t(15;17)(q22;q12), but can be cryptic or result from complex cytogenetic rearrangements other than t(15;17)(q22;q12). It is also an  AML in which promyelocytes are the dominant leukemic cell type.  APL exists as two subtypes, hypergranular or typical APL and microgranular or hypogranular APL.  APL comprises 5% to 8% of cases of AML and occurs predominately in adults in midlife.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Both typical and microgranular APL are commonly associated with disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC).<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/>  In microgranular APL, unlike typical APL, the leukocyte count can be very high with a rapid doubling time.<Reference refidx="5"/>   </Para><Para id="_195">Common morphological features of typical APL include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_196" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Kidney-shaped or bilobed nuclei.</ListItem><ListItem>Cytoplasm densely packed with large granules (bright pink, red, or purple in Romanowsky stains).</ListItem><ListItem>Bundles of Auer rods within the cytoplasm (faggot cells).</ListItem><ListItem>Larger Auer rods than in other types of AML.</ListItem><ListItem>Strongly positive myeloperoxidase (MPO) reaction in all leukemic promyelocytes.</ListItem><ListItem>Only occasional leukemic promyelocytes in the 
blood.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_197">Common morphological features of microgranular APL include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_198" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Bilobed nuclear shape.</ListItem><ListItem>Apparent scarce or absent granules (submicroscopic azurophilic granules).</ListItem><ListItem>Small number of abnormal promyelocytes with visible granules and/or bundles of Auer rods (faggot cells).</ListItem><ListItem>High leukocyte count in the peripheral blood.</ListItem><ListItem>Strongly positive MPO reaction in all leukemic promyelocytes.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_129">In APL, the <GeneName>RARA</GeneName> gene on 17q12 fuses with a nuclear regulatory factor on 15q22 (<GeneName>PML</GeneName> gene) resulting in a <GeneName>PML</GeneName>::<GeneName>RARA</GeneName> gene fusion transcript.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/>  Rare cases of cryptic or masked t(15;17) lack typical cytogenetic findings and involve complex variant translocations or submicroscopic insertion of the <GeneName>RARA</GeneName> gene into the <GeneName>PML</GeneName> gene, leading to the expression of the <GeneName>PML</GeneName>::<GeneName>RARA</GeneName> fusion transcript.<Reference refidx="5"/>  FISH and/or RT–PCR methods may be required to unmask these cryptic genetic rearrangements.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/>  In approximately 1% of the patients with APL, variant chromosomal aberrations may be found in which the <GeneName>RARA</GeneName> gene is fused with other genes.<Reference refidx="29"/>  Variant translocations involving the <GeneName>RARA</GeneName> gene include t(11;17)(q23;q21), t(5;17)(q32;q12), and t(11;17)(q13;q21).<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_130">APL has a specific sensitivity to treatment with all-<ScientificName>trans</ScientificName> retinoic acid (ATRA, tretinoin), which acts as a differentiating agent.<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/>  High CR rates and long-term disease-free survival in APL may be obtained by combining ATRA treatment with chemotherapy,<Reference refidx="33"/> or in a chemotherapy-free regimen with arsenic trioxide.<Reference refidx="34"/> </Para><Para id="_131"><Strong>AML with t(9;11)(p21.3;q23.3), <GeneName>MLLT3</GeneName>::<GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName></Strong></Para><Para id="_132">AML with 11q23 abnormalities comprises 5% to 6% of cases of AML and is typically associated with monocytic features.  This type of AML is more common in children.  Two clinical subgroups who have a high frequency of AML with 11q23 abnormalities are infants with AML and patients with therapy-related AML, usually occurring after treatment with DNA topoisomerase inhibitors.  Patients may present with DIC and extramedullary monocytic sarcomas and/or tissue infiltration (gingiva, skin).<Reference refidx="5"/>  </Para><Para id="_199">Common morphological features include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_200" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Monoblasts and promonocytes predominate in the bone marrow.</ListItem><ListItem>Monoblasts and promonocytes with strong, positive nonspecific-esterase reactions.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_133">The <GeneName>MLLT3</GeneName> gene on 11q23, an epigenetic regulator, is involved in translocations with approximately 135 different rearrangements that have been identified.<Reference refidx="35"/>  Genes other than <GeneName>MLLT3</GeneName> may be involved in 11q23 abnormalities.<Reference refidx="36"/>  FISH may be required to detect genetic abnormalities involving the <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> gene (also known as <GeneName>MLL</GeneName>).<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/>  In general, risk categories and prognoses for individual 11q23 translocations are difficult to determine  because of the lack of studies involving significant numbers of patients; however, patients with t(11;19)(q23;p13.1) have been reported to have poor outcomes.<Reference refidx="13"/> </Para><SummarySection id="_468"><Title>AML with t(6;9)(p23;q34.1), <GeneName>DEK</GeneName>::<GeneName>NUP214</GeneName></Title><Para id="_587">The t(6;9) translocation leads to the formation of a leukemia-associated DEK::NUP214 fusion protein and accounts for approximately 1% of AML cases.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/> NUP214 is a component of the nuclear pore complex. This subgroup of AML has been associated with a poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_469"><Title>AML with inv(3)(q21.3;q26.2) or t(3;3)(q21.3;q26.2),  <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MECOM</GeneName></Title><Para id="_588">The inv(3) abnormality or t(3;3) translocation occur infrequently and account for approximately 1% of all AML cases.<Reference refidx="41"/> <GeneName>MECOM</GeneName> at chromosome 3q26 codes for two proteins, EVI1 and MDS1-EVI1, both of which are transcription regulators. The inv(3) and t(3;3) abnormalities do not lead to a fusion gene, rather they reposition the  distal GATA2 enhancer, resulting in overexpression of EVI1, and simultaneously confer GATA2 haploinsufficiency.<Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/>  These abnormalities are associated with poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="46"/><Reference refidx="47"/> Abnormalities involving MECOM can be detected in some AML cases with other 3q abnormalities and are also associated with poor prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_470"><Title>AML (megakaryoblastic) with t(1;22)(p13.3;q13.3), <GeneName>RBM15</GeneName>::<GeneName>MKL1</GeneName></Title><Para id="_589">The t(1;22)(p13;q13) translocation that produces the <GeneName>RBM15</GeneName>::<GeneName>MKL1</GeneName> fusion gene is an uncommon driver of pediatric AML (&lt;1% of pediatric AML) and is restricted to acute megakaryocytic leukemia. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062896" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq">Childhood Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_471"><Title>AML with <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> (provisional entity)</Title><Para id="_590">This provisional entity was added by the WHO in 2016 in an effort to recognize that patients with the BCR::ABL1 fusion protein should be treated with a tyrosine kinase inhibitor.<Reference refidx="10"/> However, this entity is very difficult to distinguish from chronic myeloid leukemia (CML) in blast phase (BP-CML). Loss of IKZF1 and/or CDKN2A may help distinguish true cases of AML with <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> from BP-CML.<Reference refidx="48"/> For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062876" url="/types/leukemia/hp/cml-treatment-pdq">Chronic Myeloid Leukemia Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_472"><Title>AML with <GeneName>NPM1</GeneName> pathogenic variants</Title><Para id="_591">NPM1 is a protein that has been linked to ribosomal protein assembly and transport and is also a molecular chaperone involved in preventing protein aggregation in the nucleolus. Immunohistochemical methods can be used to accurately identify patients with <GeneName>NPM1</GeneName> pathogenic variants by the demonstration of cytoplasmic localization of NPM.<Reference refidx="49"/> Abnormal NPM1 protein diminishes its nuclear localization and lead to impaired hematopoietic differentiation. They are primarily associated with a normal karyotype (50%), and less commonly seen in conjunction with an abnormal karyotype (&lt;10%), or complex karyotype (&lt;3%).<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/><Reference refidx="52"/> An <GeneName>NPM1</GeneName> pathogenic variant confers improved prognosis in the absence of <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>–internal tandem duplication (ITD) variants.<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_473"><Title>AML with biallelic <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants</Title><Para id="_592">In adults younger than 60 years, 10% to 15% of cytogenetically normal AML cases have  <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="55"/>  The <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> gene is located on chromosome 19 and encodes a transcription factor that coordinates myeloid differentiation and cellular growth arrest.<Reference refidx="56"/> </Para><Para id="_593">

Outcomes for patients with AML and <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants are relatively favorable and similar to that of patients with core-binding factor leukemias.<Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="57"/> Studies have demonstrated that AML with biallelic <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> variants  is independently associated with a favorable prognosis, while AML with monoallelic <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> variants is not.<Reference refidx="55"/><Reference refidx="58"/><Reference refidx="59"/><Reference refidx="60"/> These findings led to the WHO 2016 revision of this subtype definition to require biallelic variants.<Reference refidx="10"/>
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_474"><Title>AML with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> pathogenic variants (provisional entity)</Title><Para id="_594">AML with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> pathogenic variants, which is a provisional entity in the 2016 WHO classification of AML and related neoplasms, denotes a distinct population of de novo AML without myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)-related features.<Reference refidx="61"/> Variants in <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> are associated with a high risk of treatment failure.<Reference refidx="62"/><Reference refidx="63"/><Reference refidx="64"/> </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><Title>AML With Myelodysplasia-Related Features</Title><Para id="_136">AML with myelodysplasia-related features is characterized by 20% or more blasts in the blood or bone marrow and dysplasia in two or more myeloid cell lines, generally 
including megakaryocytes.<Reference refidx="5"/>   To make the diagnosis, dysplasia must be present in 50% or more of the cells of at least two lineages and must be present in a pretreatment bone marrow specimen or must have the presence of an MDS-related cytogenetic abnormality.<Reference refidx="5"/>  AML with myelodysplasia-related features may occur de novo or after MDS  or a myelodysplastic/myeloproliferative neoplasm overlap. The diagnostic terminology <Emphasis>AML with myelodysplasia-related features evolving from a myelodysplastic syndrome</Emphasis> should be used when an MDS precedes AML.<Reference refidx="5"/> When <GeneName>NPM1</GeneName> variants or biallelic  <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> variants are present, multilineage dysplasia alone will not classify a case as AML with myelodysplasia-related changes.<Reference refidx="5"/> For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062929" url="/types/myeloproliferative/hp/myelodysplastic-treatment-pdq">Myelodysplastic Syndromes Treatment</SummaryRef> and   <SummaryRef href="CDR0000334473" url="/types/myeloproliferative/hp/mds-mpd-treatment-pdq">Myelodysplastic/Myeloproliferative Neoplasms Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_137">AML with myelodysplasia-related features occurs primarily in older patients.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Patients with AML with myelodysplasia-related features frequently present with severe pancytopenia.  </Para><Para id="_203">Common morphological features include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_204" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Multilineage dysplasia in the blood or bone marrow.</ListItem><ListItem>Dysplasia in 50% or more of the cells of two or more cell lines.</ListItem><ListItem>Dysgranulopoiesis (neutrophils with hypogranular cytoplasm, hyposegmented nuclei or bizarrely segmented nuclei).</ListItem><ListItem>Dyserythropoiesis (megaloblastic nuclei, karyorrhexis, or multinucleation of erythroid precursors and ringed sideroblasts).</ListItem><ListItem>Dysmegakaryopoiesis (micromegakaryocytes and normal size or large megakaryocytes with monolobed or multiple separated nuclei).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_138">Chromosome abnormalities observed in AML with myelodysplasia-related features are similar to those found in MDS and frequently involve gain or loss of major segments of certain chromosomes, predominately chromosomes 5 and/or 7. The probability of achieving a CR has been reported to be affected adversely by a diagnosis of AML with myelodysplasia-related features.<Reference refidx="65"/><Reference refidx="66"/><Reference refidx="67"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><Title>Therapy-Related Myeloid Neoplasms</Title><Para id="_140">Therapy-related myeloid neoplasms (t-MN) include AML (t-AML) and MDS (t-MDS) that arise secondary to cytotoxic chemotherapy and/or radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="5"/>  The therapy-related (or secondary) MDS are included because of  their close clinicopathological relationships to therapy-related AML.  Although these therapy-related disorders can be distinguished by the specific mutagenic agents involved, this distinction may be difficult to make because of the frequent overlapping use of multiple potentially mutagenic agents in treating cancer.<Reference refidx="68"/>    Because the associated cytogenetic abnormality, not the mutagenetic agent, determines prognosis and treatment it should be noted in the diagnosis.<Reference refidx="10"/> </Para><Para id="_595">Since t-MN have been associated with germline pathogenic variants in cancer susceptibility genes, considering germline genetic testing or genetic counseling is warranted in those with strong family histories of cancer.<Reference refidx="69"/> </Para><Para id="_141"><Strong>Alkylating agent-related t-MN</Strong></Para><Para id="_142">The alkylating agent/radiation-related acute leukemias and myelodysplastic syndromes typically occur 5 to 6 years after exposure to the mutagenic agent, with a reported range of approximately 10 to 192 months.<Reference refidx="70"/><Reference refidx="71"/>  The risk of occurrence is related to both the total cumulative dose of the alkylating agent and the age of the patient.</Para><Para id="_143">Cytogenetic abnormalities have been observed in more than 90% of cases of t-MN and commonly include chromosomes 5 and/or 7.<Reference refidx="70"/><Reference refidx="72"/><Reference refidx="73"/>  Complex chromosomal abnormalities (≥3 distinct abnormalities) are the most common finding.<Reference refidx="68"/><Reference refidx="72"/><Reference refidx="73"/><Reference refidx="74"/>  </Para><Para id="_144"><Strong>Topoisomerase II inhibitor-related t-MN</Strong></Para><Para id="_145">Topoisomerase II inhibitor-related t-MN occurs in patients treated with topoisomerase II inhibitors.  The agents implicated are the epipodophyllotoxins etoposide and teniposide and the anthracyclines doxorubicin and 4-epi-doxorubicin.<Reference refidx="70"/> The mean latency period from the time of institution of the causative therapy to the development of t-MN is approximately 2 years.<Reference refidx="75"/> </Para><Para id="_146">As with alkylating agent/radiation-related t-MN, the cytogenetic abnormalities are often complex.<Reference refidx="68"/><Reference refidx="72"/><Reference refidx="73"/><Reference refidx="74"/> The predominant cytogenetic finding involves chromosome 11q23 abnormalities and <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="68"/><Reference refidx="76"/>  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_147"><Title>AML, Not Otherwise Specified (NOS)</Title><Para id="_148">Cases of AML that do not fulfill the criteria for AML with recurrent genetic abnormalities, AML with myelodysplasia-related features, or t-MN fall within the category of AML, NOS.<Reference refidx="10"/> As mentioned before, the subcategories of AML, NOS lack prognostic significance when it is unclear if <GeneName>NPM1</GeneName> and <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants are present.<Reference refidx="9"/>  Classification in this subset of AML is based on leukemic cell features of morphology, cytochemistry, and maturation (i.e., the FAB classification system) and include:<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_596" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	AML with minimal differentiation.</ListItem><ListItem>	AML without maturation.</ListItem><ListItem>	AML with maturation.</ListItem><ListItem>	Acute myelomonocytic leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Acute monoblastic/monocytic leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>	Pure erythroid leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>	Acute megakaryoblastic leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>	Acute basophilic leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>	Acute panmyelosis with myelofibrosis.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_485"><Title>Myeloid Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_181">Myeloid sarcoma (also known as extramedullary myeloid tumor, granulocytic sarcoma, and chloroma) is a tumor mass that consists of myeloblasts or immature myeloid cells, occurring in an extramedullary site.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Development of myeloid sarcoma has been reported  in 2% to 8% of patients with AML.<Reference refidx="77"/>  Clinical features include occurrence common in subperiosteal bone structures of the skull, paranasal sinuses, sternum, ribs, vertebrae, and pelvis; lymph nodes, skin, mediastinum, small intestine, and the epidural space; and occurrence de novo or concomitant with AML or a myeloproliferative disorder.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="77"/><Reference refidx="78"/></Para><Para id="_242">  Morphological and cytochemical features include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_243" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Granulocytic sarcoma composed of myeloblasts, neutrophils, and neutrophil precursors with three subtypes based on degree of maturation (i.e., blastic, immature, and differentiated).</ListItem><ListItem>Monoblastic sarcoma preceding or occurring simultaneously with acute monoblastic leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumors with trilineage hematopoiesis occurring with transformation of chronic myeloproliferative disorders.</ListItem><ListItem>Myeloblasts and neutrophils that are positive for MPO.</ListItem><ListItem>Neutrophils that are positive for naphthol ASD chloroacetate esterase.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_244">Immunophenotyping with antibodies to MPO, lysozyme, and chloroacetate is critical to the diagnosis of these lesions.<Reference refidx="5"/>  The myeloblasts in granulocytic sarcomas express myeloid-associated antigens (CD13, CD33, CD117, and MPO). The monoblasts in monoblastic sarcomas express acute monoblastic leukemia antigens (CD14, CD116, and CD11c) and usually react with antibodies to lysozyme and CD68.  The main differential diagnosis includes non-Hodgkin lymphoma of the lymphoblastic type, Burkitt lymphoma, large-cell lymphoma, and small, round-cell tumors, especially in children (e.g., neuroblastoma, rhabdomyosarcoma, Ewing/primitive neuroectodermal tumors, and medulloblastoma). When able, FISH for common chromosomal abnormalities should be completed, as well as molecular studies to refine diagnosis and aid in prognosis.</Para><Para id="_182">No unique chromosomal abnormalities are associated with myeloid sarcoma.<Reference refidx="77"/><Reference refidx="79"/>  The presence of myeloid sarcoma in patients with the otherwise good-risk t(8;21) AML may be associated with a lower CR rate and decreased remission duration.<Reference refidx="80"/>  Myeloid sarcoma occurring in the setting of MDS or myeloproliferative disorder is equivalent to blast transformation (progression to AML).  In the case of AML, the prognosis is that of the underlying leukemia.<Reference refidx="10"/>  Although the initial presentation of myeloid sarcoma may appear to be isolated, it is a partial manifestation of a systemic disease and should be treated with intensive chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="77"/><Reference refidx="78"/><Reference refidx="81"/><Reference refidx="82"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_486"><Title>Myeloid Proliferations Related to Down Syndrome</Title><Para id="_487">For more information about TAM and myeloid leukemia associated with Down syndrome, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810726" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-proliferations-down-syndrome-treatment-pdq">Childhood Myeloid Proliferations Associated With Down Syndrome Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_183"><Title>Acute Leukemias of Ambiguous Lineage</Title><Para id="_184">Acute leukemias of ambiguous lineage are rare types of acute leukemia in which the morphological, cytochemical, and immunophenotypic features of the blast population do not allow classification in myeloid or lymphoid categories; or the types  have morphological 
and/or 
immunophenotypic features of both myeloid and lymphoid cells or both B and T lineages (i.e., acute bilineal leukemia and acute biphenotypic leukemia).<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="83"/><Reference refidx="84"/>  </Para><Para id="_597">They include the following subcategories:<Reference refidx="5"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_598" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Acute undifferentiated leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Mixed phenotype acute leukemia (MPAL) with t(9;22)(q34.1;q11.2); <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName>. </ListItem><ListItem>MPAL with t(v;11q23.3); <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> rearranged. </ListItem><ListItem>MPAL, B/myeloid, NOS. </ListItem><ListItem>MPAL, T/myeloid, NOS.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_599">The diagnosis of MPAL is made in leukemias with expression of antigens of more than one  lineage:<Reference refidx="5"/> </Para><Table id="_642"><Title>Table 1.  Mixed Phenotype Acute Leukemia Diagnostic Criteria</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.83%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="74.16%"/><THead><Row><entry>Diagnosis</entry><entry>Criteria</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">MPO = myeloperoxidase.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Myeloid Lineage</entry><entry>MPO (flow cytometry, immunohistochemistry, or cytochemistry) or monocytic differentiation (≥	2 of the following: nonspecific esterase cytochemistry, CD11c, CD14, CD64, lysozyme).</entry></Row><Row><entry>T-cell Lineage</entry><entry>Strong cytoplasmic CD3 (with antibodies to CD3 epsilon chain) or surface CD3.</entry></Row><Row><entry>B-cell Lineage</entry><entry>Strong CD19 with ≥1 of the following strongly expressed: cytoplasmic CD79a, cCD22, or CD10; or weak CD19 with at least two of the following strongly expressed: CD79a, cCD22, or CD10.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_185">Cytogenetic abnormalities are observed in a high percentage of acute leukemias of ambiguous lineage.<Reference refidx="85"/><Reference refidx="86"/><Reference refidx="87"/><Reference refidx="88"/>  Approximately 33% of cases have the Philadelphia chromosome, and some cases are associated with t(4;11)(q21;q23) or other 11q23 abnormalities.  In general, the prognosis appears to be unfavorable. The occurrence of 11q23 abnormalities or <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName>  are especially unfavorable prognostic indicators;<Reference refidx="86"/><Reference refidx="89"/><Reference refidx="90"/> however, preliminary results indicate that tyrosine kinase inhibitors can be used successfully.<Reference refidx="91"/><Reference refidx="92"/> </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Brunning RD, Matutes E, Harris NL, et al.: Acute myeloid leukaemia: introduction. In: Jaffe ES, Harris NL, Stein H, et al., eds.: Pathology and Genetics of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. IARC Press, 2001. World Health Organization Classification of Tumours, 3, pp 77-80.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="3862359" MedlineID="85305214">Bennett JM, Catovsky D, Daniel MT, et al.: Proposed revised criteria for the classification of acute myeloid leukemia. A report of the French-American-British Cooperative Group. Ann Intern Med 103 (4): 620-5, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2185339" MedlineID="90237835">Cheson BD, Cassileth PA, Head DR, et al.: Report of the National Cancer Institute-sponsored workshop on definitions of diagnosis and response in acute myeloid leukemia. J Clin Oncol 8 (5): 813-9, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="188440" MedlineID="77087611">Bennett JM, Catovsky D, Daniel MT, et al.: Proposals for the classification of the acute leukaemias. French-American-British (FAB) co-operative group. Br J Haematol 33 (4): 451-8, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Swerdlow SH, Campo E, Harris  NL, et al., eds.: WHO Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. 4th rev. ed. International Agency for Research on Cancer, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Jaffe ES, Harris NL, Stein H, et al., eds.: Pathology and Genetics of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. IARC Press, 2001. World Health Organization Classification of Tumours, 3.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="12592323" MedlineID="22479947">Hasle H, Niemeyer CM, Chessells JM, et al.: A pediatric approach to the WHO classification of myelodysplastic and myeloproliferative diseases. Leukemia 17 (2): 277-82, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="8">Arber DA, Vardiman JW, Brunning RD: Acute myeloid leukaemia with recurrent genetic abnormalities. In: Swerdlow SH, Campo E, Harris NL, et al., eds.: WHO Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. 4th ed. International Agency for Research on Cancer, 2008, pp 110-23.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="23325837">Walter RB, Othus M, Burnett AK, et al.: Significance of FAB subclassification of "acute myeloid leukemia, NOS" in the 2008 WHO classification: analysis of 5848 newly diagnosed patients. Blood 121 (13): 2424-31, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="27069254">Arber DA, Orazi A, Hasserjian R, et al.: The 2016 revision to the World Health Organization classification of myeloid neoplasms and acute leukemia. Blood 127 (20): 2391-405, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="9045303">Caligiuri MA, Strout MP, Gilliland DG: Molecular biology of acute myeloid leukemia. Semin Oncol 24 (1): 32-44, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="9751631">Bloomfield CD, Lawrence D, Byrd JC, et al.: Frequency of prolonged remission duration after high-dose cytarabine intensification in acute myeloid leukemia varies by cytogenetic subtype. Cancer Res 58 (18): 4173-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="12393746" MedlineID="22340753">Byrd JC, Mrózek K, Dodge RK, et al.: Pretreatment cytogenetic abnormalities are predictive of induction success, cumulative incidence of relapse, and overall survival in adult patients with de novo acute myeloid leukemia: results from Cancer and Leukemia Group B (CALGB 8461). Blood 100 (13): 4325-36, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="12007501">Palmieri S, Sebastio L, Mele G, et al.: High-dose cytarabine as consolidation treatment for patients with acute myeloid leukemia with t(8;21). Leuk Res 26 (6): 539-43, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="9746770" MedlineID="98421375">Grimwade D, Walker H, Oliver F, et al.: The importance of diagnostic cytogenetics on outcome in AML: analysis of 1,612 patients entered into the MRC AML 10 trial. The Medical Research Council Adult and Children's Leukaemia Working Parties. Blood 92 (7): 2322-33, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="10460585">Downing JR: The AML1-ETO chimaeric transcription factor in acute myeloid leukaemia: biology and clinical significance. Br J Haematol 106 (2): 296-308, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="15289486">Schlenk RF, Benner A, Krauter J, et al.: Individual patient data-based meta-analysis of patients aged 16 to 60 years with core binding factor acute myeloid leukemia: a survey of the German Acute Myeloid Leukemia Intergroup. J Clin Oncol 22 (18): 3741-50, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="26980726">Duployez N, Marceau-Renaut A, Boissel N, et al.: Comprehensive mutational profiling of core binding factor acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 127 (20): 2451-9, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="7596186">Marlton P, Keating M, Kantarjian H, et al.: Cytogenetic and clinical correlates in AML patients with abnormalities of chromosome 16. Leukemia 9 (6): 965-71, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="7858261">Poirel H, Radford-Weiss I, Rack K, et al.: Detection of the chromosome 16 CBF beta-MYH11 fusion transcript in myelomonocytic leukemias. Blood 85 (5): 1313-22, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="25696832">Döhner K, Paschka P: Intermediate-risk acute myeloid leukemia therapy: current and future. Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program 2014 (1): 34-43, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="11921015">Kwaan HC, Wang J, Boggio LN: Abnormalities in hemostasis in acute promyelocytic leukemia. Hematol Oncol 20 (1): 33-41, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="11740683">Barbui T, Falanga A: Disseminated intravascular coagulation in acute leukemia. Semin Thromb Hemost 27 (6): 593-604, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="2170850">de Thé H, Chomienne C, Lanotte M, et al.: The t(15;17) translocation of acute promyelocytic leukaemia fuses the retinoic acid receptor alpha gene to a novel transcribed locus. Nature 347 (6293): 558-61, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="10233871" MedlineID="99252073">Melnick A, Licht JD: Deconstructing a disease: RARalpha, its fusion partners, and their roles in the pathogenesis of acute promyelocytic leukemia. Blood 93 (10): 3167-215, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="29743722">Kayser S, Schlenk RF, Platzbecker U: Management of patients with acute promyelocytic leukemia. Leukemia 32 (6): 1277-1294, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="10381493">Lo Coco F, Diverio D, Falini B, et al.: Genetic diagnosis and molecular monitoring in the management of acute promyelocytic leukemia. Blood 94 (1): 12-22, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="12505266">Zaccaria A, Valenti A, Toschi M, et al.: Cryptic translocation of PML/RARA on 17q. A rare event in acute promyelocytic leukemia. Cancer Genet Cytogenet 138 (2): 169-73, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="11172538">Jansen JH, Löwenberg B: Acute promyelocytic leukemia with a PLZF-RARalpha fusion protein. Semin Hematol 38 (1): 37-41, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="2224119" MedlineID="91028230">Castaigne S, Chomienne C, Daniel MT, et al.: All-trans retinoic acid as a differentiation therapy for acute promyelocytic leukemia. I. Clinical results. Blood 76 (9): 1704-9, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="9321529" MedlineID="97449069">Tallman MS, Andersen JW, Schiffer CA, et al.: All-trans-retinoic acid in acute promyelocytic leukemia. N Engl J Med 337 (15): 1021-8, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="12393590" MedlineID="22340729">Tallman MS, Andersen JW, Schiffer CA, et al.: All-trans retinoic acid in acute promyelocytic leukemia: long-term outcome and prognostic factor analysis from the North American Intergroup protocol. Blood 100 (13): 4298-302, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="10438706" MedlineID="99369665">Fenaux P, Chastang C, Chevret S, et al.: A randomized comparison of all transretinoic acid (ATRA) followed by chemotherapy and ATRA plus chemotherapy and the role of maintenance therapy in newly diagnosed acute promyelocytic leukemia. The European APL Group. Blood 94 (4): 1192-200, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="23841729">Lo-Coco F, Avvisati G, Vignetti M, et al.: Retinoic acid and arsenic trioxide for acute promyelocytic leukemia. N Engl J Med 369 (2): 111-21, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="28701730">Meyer C, Burmeister T, Gröger D, et al.: The MLL recombinome of acute leukemias in 2017. Leukemia 32 (2): 273-284, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="12368154">Giugliano E, Rege-Cambrin G, Scaravaglio P, et al.: Two new translocations involving the 11q23 region map outside the MLL locus in myeloid leukemias. Haematologica 87 (10): 1014-20, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="11886378">König M, Reichel M, Marschalek R, et al.: A highly specific and sensitive fluorescence in situ hybridization assay for the detection of t(4;11)(q21;q23) and concurrent submicroscopic deletions in acute leukaemias. Br J Haematol 116 (4): 758-64, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="12472570">Kim HJ, Cho HI, Kim EC, et al.: A study on 289 consecutive Korean patients with acute leukaemias revealed fluorescence in situ hybridization detects the MLL translocation without cytogenetic evidence both initially and during follow-up. Br J Haematol 119 (4): 930-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="18181180">Ageberg M, Drott K, Olofsson T, et al.: Identification of a novel and myeloid specific role of the leukemia-associated fusion protein DEK-NUP214 leading to increased protein synthesis. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 47 (4): 276-87, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="23630019">Shiba N, Ichikawa H, Taki T, et al.: NUP98-NSD1 gene fusion and its related gene expression signature are strongly associated with a poor prognosis in pediatric acute myeloid leukemia. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 52 (7): 683-93, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="27895058">Döhner H, Estey E, Grimwade D, et al.: Diagnosis and management of AML in adults: 2017 ELN recommendations from an international expert panel. Blood 129 (4): 424-447, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="16628187">Slovak ML, Gundacker H, Bloomfield CD, et al.: A retrospective study of 69 patients with t(6;9)(p23;q34) AML emphasizes the need for a prospective, multicenter initiative for rare 'poor prognosis' myeloid malignancies. Leukemia 20 (7): 1295-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="9124211">Alsabeh R, Brynes RK, Slovak ML, et al.: Acute myeloid leukemia with t(6;9) (p23;q34): association with myelodysplasia, basophilia, and initial CD34 negative immunophenotype. Am J Clin Pathol 107 (4): 430-7, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="24703711">Gröschel S, Sanders MA, Hoogenboezem R, et al.: A single oncogenic enhancer rearrangement causes concomitant EVI1 and GATA2 deregulation in leukemia. Cell 157 (2): 369-81, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="24703906">Yamazaki H, Suzuki M, Otsuki A, et al.: A remote GATA2 hematopoietic enhancer drives leukemogenesis in inv(3)(q21;q26) by activating EVI1 expression. Cancer Cell 25 (4): 415-27, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="15010150">Mrózek K, Heerema NA, Bloomfield CD: Cytogenetics in acute leukemia. Blood Rev 18 (2): 115-36, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="20660833">Lugthart S, Gröschel S, Beverloo HB, et al.: Clinical, molecular, and prognostic significance of WHO type inv(3)(q21q26.2)/t(3;3)(q21;q26.2) and various other 3q abnormalities in acute myeloid leukemia. J Clin Oncol 28 (24): 3890-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="23521501">Nacheva EP, Grace CD, Brazma D, et al.: Does BCR/ABL1 positive acute myeloid leukaemia exist? Br J Haematol 161 (4): 541-50, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="16720834">Falini B, Martelli MP, Bolli N, et al.: Immunohistochemistry predicts nucleophosmin (NPM) mutations in acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 108 (6): 1999-2005, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="15659725">Falini B, Mecucci C, Tiacci E, et al.: Cytoplasmic nucleophosmin in acute myelogenous leukemia with a normal karyotype. N Engl J Med 352 (3): 254-66, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="17008539">Falini B, Nicoletti I, Martelli MF, et al.: Acute myeloid leukemia carrying cytoplasmic/mutated nucleophosmin (NPMc+ AML): biologic and clinical features. Blood 109 (3): 874-85, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="21030560">Falini B, Martelli MP, Bolli N, et al.: Acute myeloid leukemia with mutated nucleophosmin (NPM1): is it a distinct entity? Blood 117 (4): 1109-20, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="18450602">Schlenk RF, Döhner K, Krauter J, et al.: Mutations and treatment outcome in cytogenetically normal acute myeloid leukemia. N Engl J Med 358 (18): 1909-18, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="17957027">Gale RE, Green C, Allen C, et al.: The impact of FLT3 internal tandem duplication mutant level, number, size, and interaction with NPM1 mutations in a large cohort of young adult patients with acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 111 (5): 2776-84, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="21177436">Taskesen E, Bullinger L, Corbacioglu A, et al.: Prognostic impact, concurrent genetic mutations, and gene expression features of AML with CEBPA mutations in a cohort of 1182 cytogenetically normal AML patients: further evidence for CEBPA double mutant AML as a distinctive disease entity. Blood 117 (8): 2469-75, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="15122210">Nerlov C: C/EBPalpha mutations in acute myeloid leukaemias. Nat Rev Cancer 4 (5): 394-400, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="18809607">Marcucci G, Maharry K, Radmacher MD, et al.: Prognostic significance of, and gene and microRNA expression signatures associated with, CEBPA mutations in cytogenetically normal acute myeloid leukemia with high-risk molecular features: a Cancer and Leukemia Group B Study. J Clin Oncol 26 (31): 5078-87, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="19171880">Wouters BJ, Löwenberg B, Erpelinck-Verschueren CA, et al.: Double CEBPA mutations, but not single CEBPA mutations, define a subgroup of acute myeloid leukemia with a distinctive gene expression profile that is uniquely associated with a favorable outcome. Blood 113 (13): 3088-91, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="20038735">Dufour A, Schneider F, Metzeler KH, et al.: Acute myeloid leukemia with biallelic CEBPA gene mutations and normal karyotype represents a distinct genetic entity associated with a favorable clinical outcome. J Clin Oncol 28 (4): 570-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="60" PMID="24056881">Fasan A, Haferlach C, Alpermann T, et al.: The role of different genetic subtypes of CEBPA mutated AML. Leukemia 28 (4): 794-803, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="21148331">Schnittger S, Dicker F, Kern W, et al.: RUNX1 mutations are frequent in de novo AML with noncomplex karyotype and confer an unfavorable prognosis. Blood 117 (8): 2348-57, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="19808697">Tang JL, Hou HA, Chen CY, et al.: AML1/RUNX1 mutations in 470 adult patients with de novo acute myeloid leukemia: prognostic implication and interaction with other gene alterations. Blood 114 (26): 5352-61, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="22753902">Mendler JH, Maharry K, Radmacher MD, et al.: RUNX1 mutations are associated with poor outcome in younger and older patients with cytogenetically normal acute myeloid leukemia and with distinct gene and MicroRNA expression signatures. J Clin Oncol 30 (25): 3109-18, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="21343560">Gaidzik VI, Bullinger L, Schlenk RF, et al.: RUNX1 mutations in acute myeloid leukemia: results from a comprehensive genetic and clinical analysis from the AML study group. J Clin Oncol 29 (10): 1364-72, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="65" PMID="21183700">Díaz-Beyá M, Rozman M, Pratcorona M, et al.: The prognostic value of multilineage dysplasia in de novo acute myeloid leukemia patients with intermediate-risk cytogenetics is dependent on NPM1 mutational status. Blood 116 (26): 6147-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="24824767">Rozman M, Navarro JT, Arenillas L, et al.: Multilineage dysplasia is associated with a poorer prognosis in patients with de novo acute myeloid leukemia with intermediate-risk cytogenetics and wild-type NPM1. Ann Hematol 93 (10): 1695-703, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="19131546">Weinberg OK, Seetharam M, Ren L, et al.: Clinical characterization of acute myeloid leukemia with myelodysplasia-related changes as defined by the 2008 WHO classification system. Blood 113 (9): 1906-8, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="68" PMID="12623843">Smith SM, Le Beau MM, Huo D, et al.: Clinical-cytogenetic associations in 306 patients with therapy-related myelodysplasia and myeloid leukemia: the University of Chicago series. Blood 102 (1): 43-52, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="26641009">Churpek JE, Marquez R, Neistadt B, et al.: Inherited mutations in cancer susceptibility genes are common among survivors of breast cancer who develop therapy-related leukemia. Cancer 122 (2): 304-11, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="70">Brunning RD, Matutes E, Flandrin G, et al.: Acute myeloid leukaemias and myelodysplastic syndromes, therapy related. In: Jaffe ES, Harris NL, Stein H, et al., eds.: Pathology and Genetics of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. IARC Press, 2001. World Health Organization Classification of Tumours, 3, pp 89-91.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="8220158">Ellis M, Ravid M, Lishner M: A comparative analysis of alkylating agent and epipodophyllotoxin-related leukemias. Leuk Lymphoma 11 (1-2): 9-13, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="11921275">Olney HJ, Mitelman F, Johansson B, et al.: Unique balanced chromosome abnormalities in treatment-related myelodysplastic syndromes and acute myeloid leukemia: report from an international workshop. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 33 (4): 413-23, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="12454741">Mauritzson N, Albin M, Rylander L, et al.: Pooled analysis of clinical and cytogenetic features in treatment-related and de novo adult acute myeloid leukemia and myelodysplastic syndromes based on a consecutive series of 761 patients analyzed 1976-1993 and on 5098 unselected cases reported in the literature 1974-2001. Leukemia 16 (12): 2366-78, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="74" PMID="11877259">Pedersen-Bjergaard J, Andersen MK, Christiansen DH, et al.: Genetic pathways in therapy-related myelodysplasia and acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 99 (6): 1909-12, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="75" PMID="11378539">Leone G, Voso MT, Sica S, et al.: Therapy related leukemias: susceptibility, prevention and treatment. Leuk Lymphoma 41 (3-4): 255-76, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="11921271">Bloomfield CD, Archer KJ, Mrózek K, et al.: 11q23 balanced chromosome aberrations in treatment-related myelodysplastic syndromes and acute leukemia: report from an international workshop. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 33 (4): 362-78, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="11920536">Yamauchi K, Yasuda M: Comparison in treatments of nonleukemic granulocytic sarcoma: report of two cases and a review of 72 cases in the literature. Cancer 94 (6): 1739-46, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="24396704">Yilmaz AF, Saydam G, Sahin F, et al.: Granulocytic sarcoma: a systematic review. Am J Blood Res 3 (4): 265-70, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="79">Brunning RD, Matutes E, Flandrin G, et al.: Acute myeloid leukaemia not otherwise categorised. In: Jaffe ES, Harris NL, Stein H, et al., eds.: Pathology and Genetics of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. IARC Press, 2001. World Health Organization Classification of Tumours, 3, pp 91-105.</Citation><Citation idx="80" PMID="9053467" MedlineID="97178734">Byrd JC, Weiss RB, Arthur DC, et al.: Extramedullary leukemia adversely affects hematologic complete remission rate and overall survival in patients with t(8;21)(q22;q22): results from Cancer and Leukemia Group B 8461. J Clin Oncol 15 (2): 466-75, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="81" PMID="9737707">Hayashi T, Kimura M, Satoh S, et al.: Early detection of AML1/MTG8 fusion mRNA by RT-PCR in the bone marrow cells from a patient with isolated granulocytic sarcoma. Leukemia 12 (9): 1501-3, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="82" PMID="7625623" MedlineID="95351570">Imrie KR, Kovacs MJ, Selby D, et al.: Isolated chloroma: the effect of early antileukemic therapy. Ann Intern Med 123 (5): 351-3, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="83" PMID="21228332">Matutes E, Pickl WF, Van't Veer M, et al.: Mixed-phenotype acute leukemia: clinical and laboratory features and outcome in 100 patients defined according to the WHO 2008 classification. Blood 117 (11): 3163-71, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="84" PMID="20485373">van den Ancker W, Terwijn M, Westers TM, et al.: Acute leukemias of ambiguous lineage: diagnostic consequences of the WHO2008 classification. Leukemia 24 (7): 1392-6, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="85" PMID="7687860">Hanson CA, Abaza M, Sheldon S, et al.: Acute biphenotypic leukaemia: immunophenotypic and cytogenetic analysis. Br J Haematol 84 (1): 49-60, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="86" PMID="9450804">Legrand O, Perrot JY, Simonin G, et al.: Adult biphenotypic acute leukaemia: an entity with poor prognosis which is related to unfavourable cytogenetics and P-glycoprotein over-expression. Br J Haematol 100 (1): 147-55, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="87" PMID="8709632">Carbonell F, Swansbury J, Min T, et al.: Cytogenetic findings in acute biphenotypic leukaemia. Leukemia 10 (8): 1283-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="88" PMID="8618457">Pane F, Frigeri F, Camera A, et al.: Complete phenotypic and genotypic lineage switch in a Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Leukemia 10 (4): 741-5, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="89">Brunning RD, Matutes E, Borowitz M: Acute leukaemias of ambiguous lineage. In: Jaffe ES, Harris NL, Stein H, et al., eds.: Pathology and Genetics of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. IARC Press, 2001. World Health Organization Classification of Tumours, 3, pp 106-7.</Citation><Citation idx="90" PMID="10457405">Killick S, Matutes E, Powles RL, et al.: Outcome of biphenotypic acute leukemia. Haematologica 84 (8): 699-706, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="91" PMID="24532437">Kawajiri C, Tanaka H, Hashimoto S, et al.: Successful treatment of Philadelphia chromosome-positive mixed phenotype acute leukemia by appropriate alternation of second-generation tyrosine kinase inhibitors according to BCR-ABL1 mutation status. Int J Hematol 99 (4): 513-8, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="92" PMID="24750307">Shimizu H, Yokohama A, Hatsumi N, et al.: Philadelphia chromosome-positive mixed phenotype acute leukemia in the imatinib era. Eur J Haematol 93 (4): 297-301, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_46"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037885">adult acute myeloid leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for AML</Title><SummarySection id="_660"><Title>Phases of Therapy</Title><Para id="_331">The treatment of patients with acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is based on whether the disease is newly diagnosed (previously untreated), in remission, or recurrent. Also, the intensity of the treatment and the patient's overall health status are considered when choosing a treatment approach. Successful treatment of AML requires the control of
bone marrow and systemic disease, and specific treatment of central nervous
system (CNS) disease, if present.  The cornerstone of this strategy includes
systemically administered combination chemotherapy.  Because only 5% or fewer of
patients with AML develop CNS disease, prophylactic treatment is not
indicated.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_657" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Newly diagnosed (untreated):</Strong> Untreated AML is defined as newly diagnosed leukemia that has not been previously treated. The initial treatment for patients with newly diagnosed AML is often induction therapy that aims to induce a remission. In patients with AML, a complete remission (CR) is defined as a normal peripheral blood cell count (absolute neutrophil count &gt;1,000/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript> and platelet count &gt;100,000/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript>)  and normocellular marrow with less than 5% blasts in the marrow and no signs or symptoms of the disease. In addition, no signs or symptoms are evident of CNS leukemia or other extramedullary infiltration.<Reference refidx="3"/> <Para id="_601">Modifications to the definition of CR have been proposed because some responses are deeper than a CR, and others may not meet all the criteria for a complete response. In addition, most AML patients meeting the criteria for CR have residual leukemia.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Table id="_658"><Title>Table 2. Treatment Response Categories for Newly Diagnosed Acute Myeloid Leukemia</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Response Category</entry><entry>Definition</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">ANC = absolute neutrophil count; CR = complete remission; CRh = CR with partial hematologic recovery; CRi = CR with incomplete hematologic recovery;  CR<Subscript>MRD−</Subscript> = CR without measurable residual disease; MLFS = morphological leukemia-free state; PR = partial remission; RT–qPCR = reverse transcription–quantitative polymerase chain reaction.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>CR<Subscript>MRD−</Subscript></entry><entry>If studied pretreatment, CR with negativity for a genetic marker by RT–qPCR, or CR with negativity by multicolor flow cytometry.</entry></Row><Row><entry>CR</entry><entry>Bone marrow blasts &lt;5%; absence of circulating blasts and blasts with Auer rods; absence of extramedullary disease; ANC ≥1.0 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L (1,000/microL); platelet count ≥100 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L (100,000/microL).</entry></Row><Row><entry>CRh</entry><entry>ANC ≥0.5 x 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L (500/microL) and platelet count ≥50 x 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L (100,000/microL); otherwise all other CR criteria met.<Reference refidx="4"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>CRi</entry><entry>All CR criteria except for residual neutropenia (&lt;1.0 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L [1,000/microL]) or thrombocytopenia (&lt;100 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L [100,000/microL]).</entry></Row><Row><entry>MLFS</entry><entry>Bone marrow blasts &lt;5%; absence of blasts with Auer rods; absence of extramedullary disease; no hematologic recovery required.</entry></Row><Row><entry>PR</entry><entry>All hematologic criteria of CR; decrease of bone marrow blast percentage to 5 to 25%; and decrease of pretreatment bone marrow blast percentage by at least 50%.</entry></Row><Row><entry>No response</entry><entry>Patients evaluable for response but not meeting criteria for CR, CRh, CRi, MLFS, or PR are categorized as having no response prior to the response landmark. Patients failing to achieve response by the designated landmark are designated as having refractory disease.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ItemizedList id="_488" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>In remission: </Strong>When patients are in a remission after induction chemotherapy, consolidation chemotherapy is given, with the aim of deepening the response and consolidating the remission. Maintenance therapy is not included in most current
treatment protocols and clinical trials.  Consolidation therapy appears to be effective
when given immediately after remission is achieved.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Persistent/recurrent disease:</Strong> Despite intensive chemotherapy, some patients with newly diagnosed AML will not go into remission and have primary refractory disease. Also, some patients who are in a remission after induction and consolidation chemotherapy may have a return of their disease.<Reference refidx="3"/> The rates of primary refractory disease and relapse vary with the age of the patient, genomic variants seen in the leukemia cells, and initial treatment given. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Table id="_643"><Title>Table 3. Treatment Response Categories for Persistent/Recurrent Acute Myeloid Leukemia</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="21.87%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="6.41%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="71.71%"/><THead><Row><entry>Response Category</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Definition</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">CR = complete remission; CRh = CR with partial hematologic recovery; CRhMRD-LL =  CR with partial hematologic recovery and measurable residual disease at a low level; CRi = CR with incomplete hematologic recovery; CRiMRD-LL =  CR with incomplete hematologic recovery and measurable residual disease at a low level; CRMRD- = CR without measurable residual disease; CRMRD-LL = CR with measurable residual disease detection at a low level; MRD = measurable residual disease; MRD- = absence of measurable residual disease; MRD+ = presence of measurable residual disease; MLFS  = morphological leukemia-free state; PR = partial response; RT–qPCR = reverse transcription–quantitative polymerase chain reaction. </entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Primary refractory disease</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">No CR, CRh, or CRi at the response landmark (i.e., after two courses of intensive induction treatment) or a defined landmark (e.g., 180 days after commencing less-intensive therapy).</entry></Row><Row><entry>Relapsed disease (after CR, CRh, or CRi)</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Bone marrow blasts ≥5%; or reappearance of blasts in the blood in at least two peripheral blood samples obtained at least 1 week apart; or development of extramedullary disease.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">MRD relapse (after CR, CRh, or CRi without MRD-)</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Defined by one of the following:</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Conversion from MRD- to MRD+, independent of method; <Strong>or</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Increase of MRD copy numbers ≥1 log<Subscript>10</Subscript> between any two positive samples in patients with CRMRD-LL, CRhMRD-LL, or CRiMRD-LL by qPCR.
</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Either result should be rapidly confirmed in a second consecutive sample from the same tissue source.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Stable disease</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Absence of CRMRD-, CR, CRi, PR, MLFS; and criteria for progressive disease not met.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Progressive disease</entry><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">Evidence for an increase in bone marrow blast percentage and/or increase of absolute blast counts in the blood:
</entry></Row><Row><entry> </entry><entry>&gt;50% increase in marrow blasts; <Strong>or</Strong>
</entry></Row><Row><entry>	</entry><entry>&gt;50% increase in peripheral blasts in the absence of differentiation syndrome; or
</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>New extramedullary disease.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_493"><Title>Supportive Care During Therapy</Title><Para id="_50">Because myelosuppression is an anticipated consequence of both the leukemia and
its treatment with chemotherapy, patients must be closely monitored during
therapy.  Facilities must be available for hematologic support with multiple
blood fractions, including platelet transfusions, and for the treatment
of related infectious complications.<Reference refidx="6"/>  </Para><SummarySection id="_571"><Title>Transfusion therapy</Title><Para id="_495">Supportive care during remission induction treatment should routinely include
red blood cell and platelet transfusions, when appropriate.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/>  Rapid marrow ablation
with consequent earlier marrow regeneration decreases morbidity and mortality.  
Randomized trials have shown similar
outcomes for patients who received prophylactic platelet transfusions at a
level of 10,000/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript> rather than 20,000/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript>.<Reference refidx="9"/>  The incidence of platelet alloimmunization was similar among
groups randomly assigned to receive pooled platelet concentrates from random
donors; filtered, pooled platelet concentrates from random donors; ultraviolet
B-irradiated, pooled platelet concentrates from random donors; or filtered
platelets obtained by apheresis from single random donors.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_602">No good evidence exists to support granulocyte transfusions in the treatment of AML. A multicenter randomized trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00627393">RING</ProtocolRef> [NCT00627393]) was conducted to address the utility of granulocyte transfusions in the setting of infections.<Reference refidx="11"/> There was no difference between the granulocyte and control arms for the composite primary end point of survival plus microbial response at 42 days after randomization. However, the power to detect a true beneficial effect was low because enrollment was half that of the planned study size.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_572"><Title>Growth factors</Title><Para id="_644">The following growth factors have been studied in the treatment of AML:</Para><ItemizedList id="_603" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Colony-stimulating factors:</Strong> Granulocyte colony–stimulating factor and granulocyte-macrophage colony–stimulating factor have been
studied in an effort to shorten the period of granulocytopenia associated with
leukemia treatment.<Reference refidx="12"/>  If used, these agents are administered after administration
of chemotherapy.  Although the use of growth factors decreases the time to neutrophil recovery by 2 to 5 days, and decreases rates of febrile neutropenia and duration of hospitalization, randomized clinical trials have not shown an impact of growth factors on overall survival and their cost-effectiveness has been inconsistently reported.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> Use of growth factors is not routinely recommended in the remission induction setting.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>	Erythropoiesis-stimulating agents:</Strong> Anemia associated with the diagnosis of AML and induction chemotherapy is managed primarily with red blood transfusions. Unlike myelodysplastic syndromes, there is no role for the use of erythropoiesis stimulating agents (e.g., epoetin alfa and darbepoetin) during the treatment of AML.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Thrombopoietin mimetics:</Strong> Clinical trials have assessed the use of thrombopoietin mimetics in the treatment of AML. Eltrombopag as a single agent was tested in a multicenter, randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, phase I/II trial of 98 patients with platelet counts less than 30 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L as a result of AML or MDS. No significant  improvements  in  platelet counts  were  recorded. Significant hemorrhage was reported in ten (16%) patients given eltrombopag and nine (26%) patients given placebo. No difference in disease progression or overall survival was observed.<Reference refidx="15"/><Para id="_604">Eltrombopag appeared to hasten platelet recovery and reduce the number of platelet transfusions needed when added in an unblinded fashion to induction chemotherapy in older <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-negative AML patients.<Reference refidx="16"/> However, in a separate, randomized double-blind study of 148 patients, eltrombopag or placebo was added to high-dose induction chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="17"/> The results of this study did not indicate any clinical benefit of eltrombopag over placebo. Given the minimal efficacy signal at this point, eltrombopag is not routinely recommended in the supportive care or remission induction setting.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_573"><Title>Antimicrobial therapy</Title><Para id="_58">Empiric
broad spectrum antimicrobial therapy is an absolute necessity for febrile
patients who are profoundly neutropenic.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/>  Careful instruction in
personal hand hygiene, dental care, and recognition of early signs of infection are
appropriate in all patients.  Elaborate isolation facilities (including
filtered air, sterile food, and gut flora sterilization) are not indicated.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/>  Likewise, there are no advantages to eating a cooked neutropenic diet, as demonstrated in randomized trials.<Reference refidx="22"/>  </Para><Para id="_605">Antibiotic prophylaxis with a fluoroquinolone and antifungal prophylaxis with an oral triazole or parenteral echinocandin is appropriate for patients with expected prolonged, profound neutropenia (&lt;100/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript> for 2 weeks for profound neutropenia lasting &gt;7 days).<Reference refidx="23"/> Unlike patients undergoing treatment for acute lymphoblastic lymphoma, <Emphasis>Pneumocystis jirovecii</Emphasis> prophylaxis is not routinely employed.</Para><Para id="_606">Nucleoside analog-based antiviral prophylaxis, such as acyclovir, is appropriate  for patients who are seropositive for herpes simplex virus undergoing induction chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="23"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25110819">Rozovski U, Ohanian M, Ravandi F, et al.: Incidence of and risk factors for involvement of the central nervous system in acute myeloid leukemia. Leuk Lymphoma 56 (5): 1392-7, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="28435324">Alakel N, Stölzel F, Mohr B, et al.: Symptomatic central nervous system involvement in adult patients with acute myeloid leukemia. Cancer Manag Res 9: 97-102, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19880497">Döhner H, Estey EH, Amadori S, et al.: Diagnosis and management of acute myeloid leukemia in adults: recommendations from an international expert panel, on behalf of the European LeukemiaNet. Blood 115 (3): 453-74, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="35797463">Döhner H, Wei AH, Appelbaum FR, et al.: Diagnosis and management of AML in adults: 2022 recommendations from an international expert panel on behalf of the ELN. Blood 140 (12): 1345-1377, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="1562720" MedlineID="92223369">Cassileth PA, Lynch E, Hines JD, et al.: Varying intensity of postremission therapy in acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 79 (8): 1924-30, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Supportive Care. In: Wiernik PH, Canellos GP, Dutcher JP, et al., eds.: Neoplastic Diseases of the Blood. 3rd ed. Churchill Livingstone, 1996, pp 779-967.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="6994626" MedlineID="80240734">Slichter SJ: Controversies in platelet transfusion therapy. Annu Rev Med 31: 509-40, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="3954967" MedlineID="86159603">Murphy MF, Metcalfe P, Thomas H, et al.: Use of leucocyte-poor blood components and HLA-matched-platelet donors to prevent HLA alloimmunization. Br J Haematol 62 (3): 529-34, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9407153" MedlineID="98057267">Rebulla P, Finazzi G, Marangoni F, et al.: The threshold for prophylactic platelet transfusions in adults with acute myeloid leukemia. Gruppo Italiano Malattie Ematologiche Maligne dell'Adulto. N Engl J Med 337 (26): 1870-5, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="9417523" MedlineID="98057266">Leukocyte reduction and ultraviolet B irradiation of platelets to prevent alloimmunization and refractoriness to platelet transfusions. The Trial to Reduce Alloimmunization to Platelets Study Group. N Engl J Med 337 (26): 1861-9, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="26333778">Price TH, Boeckh M, Harrison RW, et al.: Efficacy of transfusion with granulocytes from G-CSF/dexamethasone-treated donors in neutropenic patients with infection. Blood 126 (18): 2153-61, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="8648396" MedlineID="96243105">Geller RB: Use of cytokines in the treatment of acute myelocytic leukemia: a critical review. J Clin Oncol 14 (4): 1371-82, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="7605984" MedlineID="95329701">Rowe JM, Andersen JW, Mazza JJ, et al.: A randomized placebo-controlled phase III study of granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor in adult patients (&gt; 55 to 70 years of age) with acute myelogenous leukemia: a study of the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (E1490). Blood 86 (2): 457-62, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="7760868" MedlineID="95280976">Stone RM, Berg DT, George SL, et al.: Granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor after initial chemotherapy for elderly patients with primary acute myelogenous leukemia. Cancer and Leukemia Group B. N Engl J Med 332 (25): 1671-7, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="26686043">Platzbecker U, Wong RS, Verma A, et al.: Safety and tolerability of eltrombopag versus placebo for treatment of thrombocytopenia in patients with advanced myelodysplastic syndromes or acute myeloid leukaemia: a multicentre, randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind, phase 1/2 trial. Lancet Haematol 2 (10): e417-26, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="16">Mukherjee S, Li H, Hobbs BP: A single arm, phase II study of eltrombopag to enhance platelet count recovery in older patients with acute myeloid leukemia (AML) undergoing remission induction therapy. [Abstract] Blood  134 (Suppl 1): 2595, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="30704923">Frey N, Jang JH, Szer J, et al.: Eltrombopag treatment during induction chemotherapy for acute myeloid leukaemia: a randomised, double-blind, phase 2 study. Lancet Haematol 6 (3): e122-e131, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="2179420" MedlineID="90187947">Hughes WT, Armstrong D, Bodey GP, et al.: From the Infectious Diseases Society of America. Guidelines for the use of antimicrobial agents in neutropenic patients with unexplained fever. J Infect Dis 161 (3): 381-96, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="3132310" MedlineID="88241420">Rubin M, Hathorn JW, Pizzo PA: Controversies in the management of febrile neutropenic cancer patients. Cancer Invest 6 (2): 167-84, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="6424468" MedlineID="84176054">Armstrong D: Symposium on infectious complications of neoplastic disease (Part II). Protected environments are discomforting and expensive and do not offer meaningful protection. Am J Med 76 (4): 685-9, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="3314494" MedlineID="88046838">Sherertz RJ, Belani A, Kramer BS, et al.: Impact of air filtration on nosocomial Aspergillus infections. Unique risk of bone marrow transplant recipients. Am J Med 83 (4): 709-18, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="18955453">Gardner A, Mattiuzzi G, Faderl S, et al.: Randomized comparison of cooked and noncooked diets in patients undergoing remission induction therapy for acute myeloid leukemia. J Clin Oncol 26 (35): 5684-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="30179565">Taplitz RA, Kennedy EB, Bow EJ, et al.: Antimicrobial Prophylaxis for Adult Patients With Cancer-Related Immunosuppression: ASCO and IDSA Clinical Practice Guideline Update. J Clin Oncol 36 (30): 3043-3054, 2018.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039078">untreated adult acute myeloid leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Newly Diagnosed AML</Title><SummarySection id="_628"><Title>Treatment Options for Newly Diagnosed (Untreated; Remission Induction) AML</Title><Para id="_629">Treatment options for newly diagnosed (untreated; remission induction) acute myeloid leukemia (AML) include:</Para><OrderedList id="_630" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_550" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_550"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_607">Chemotherapy for AML is divided into the following two general categories:</Para><OrderedList id="_608" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	Intensive remission-induction chemotherapy. </ListItem><ListItem>	Nonintensive chemotherapy. </ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_510">One of the following combination chemotherapy regimens may be used as intensive remission induction therapy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_401" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Cytarabine plus daunorubicin.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Cytarabine plus idarubicin.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Cytarabine plus mitoxantrone.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem><ListItem>Cytarabine plus anthracycline plus midostaurin.<Reference refidx="8"/> </ListItem><ListItem>	Cytarabine plus anthracycline plus gemtuzumab ozogamicin.<Reference refidx="9"/> </ListItem><ListItem>	Liposomal daunorubicin-cytarabine (CPX-351).<Reference refidx="10"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Intrathecal cytarabine or methotrexate may be used to treat central nervous system (CNS) leukemia, if present.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_55">The two-drug regimen of cytarabine given as a continuous infusion for 7 days and a 3-day course of anthracycline  (the so-called 7 + 3 induction therapy) results in a complete response rate of approximately 65%.  In most instances, there is no further clinical benefit when adding potentially non-cross−resistant drugs (such as fludarabine, topoisomerase inhibitors, thioguanine, mitoxantrone, histone deacetylases inhibitors, or clofarabine) to a 7 + 3 regimen. Cladribine, when added to 7 + 3 induction chemotherapy, showed improved remission rates <Reference refidx="11"/> and survival rates <Reference refidx="12"/> across two randomized controlled trials, but this regimen has not been widely adopted in the absence of confirmatory trials. The addition of midostaurin and gemtuzumab ozogamicin to intensive induction chemotherapy is discussed below.</Para><Para id="_504">The choice of anthracycline and the dose-intensity of anthracycline may influence the survival of patients with AML. Idarubicin appeared to be more effective than
daunorubicin, particularly in younger adults, although the doses of idarubicin and daunorubicin may not have
been equivalent.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  No significant survival difference between daunorubicin and
mitoxantrone has been reported.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><SummarySection id="_651"><Title>Selection of an anthracycline</Title><Para id="_631"> At present, there is no conclusive evidence to recommend one anthracycline over another. </Para><Para id="_645">Evidence (anthracyclines):</Para><OrderedList id="_609" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a systematic review and meta-analysis, 18 randomized controlled trials that included 6,755 patients assessed the use of idarubicin versus daunorubicin as part of induction chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="14"/> <ItemizedList id="_610" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The use of idarubicin led to improved outcomes, including overall survival (OS), when compared with daunorubicin (12 studies, 5,976 patients; hazard ratio [HR], 0.90; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.84−0.96; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0008). However, there was an increased risk of death during induction (14 studies, 6,349 patients; relative risk [RR], 1.18; 95% CI, 1.01−1.36; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03) and mucositis (five studies, 2,000 patients; RR, 1.22; 95% CI, 1.04−1.44; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02) with idarubicin as compared with daunorubicin. Moreover, the survival benefit for idarubicin was no longer present if a daunorubicin dose of at least 180 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> was used (four studies, 2,867 patients; HR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.82−1.00; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .06).</ListItem><ListItem>In patients aged 60 years and younger, outcomes for those who received daunorubicin (90 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/dose, total induction dosing at 270 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) were superior to those who received more traditional dosing (45 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/dose; total dose = 135 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>). The complete remission (CR) rate was 71% versus 57% (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001), and the median survival was 24 months versus 16 months (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003).<Reference refidx="15"/></ListItem><ListItem>No randomized comparison data between daunorubicin at 270 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> and daunorubicin at 180 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>, or between daunorubicin at 270 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> and idarubicin, are available.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_652"><Title>Addition of an FLT3 inhibitor</Title><Para id="_632">Variants in the tyrosine kinase domain (TKD) and internal tandem duplications (ITD) of the <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName> gene are frequent in AML and are often associated with an inferior outcome.</Para><SummarySection id="_802"><Title>Midostaurin</Title><Para id="_804">Evidence (midostaurin):</Para><OrderedList id="_805" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A multicenter, randomized, phase III trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00651261">NCT00651261</ProtocolRef>) included patients with <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-altered AML. Patients received either the FLT3/multikinase inhibitor, midostaurin, or placebo in addition to cytarabine and daunorubicin induction chemotherapy. The addition of midostaurin led to improved survival (median, 75 vs. 26 months; HR for death, 0.78; one-sided <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .009).<Reference refidx="8"/><ItemizedList id="_806" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The event-free survival (defined as the time from randomization to relapse, death from any cause, or failure to achieve protocol-specified CR) was improved for patients in the midostaurin arm (HR for event or death, 0.78; one-sided <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002), and the survival benefit was consistent across all <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName> variant subtypes. The rates of CR (59% vs. 54%) and time to neutrophil count recovery were similar between the two arms.<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_807">The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved midostaurin in combination with induction therapy for patients with AML and any <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName> variant.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_808"><Title>Quizartinib</Title><Para id="_809">Evidence (quizartinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_810" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A multicenter, randomized, phase III trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02668653">NCT02668653</ProtocolRef>) included patients with <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-ITD–altered AML. Patients received either the selective ITD-specific FLT3 inhibitor, quizartinib, or placebo in addition to cytarabine and daunorubicin induction chemotherapy. The addition of quizartinib  led to improved survival (median, 31.9 vs. 15.1 months; HR for death, 0.78; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .032).<Reference refidx="16"/><ItemizedList id="_811" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	The EFS (defined as the time from randomization to lack of CR within 42 days from the start of the last induction cycle, relapse, or death from any cause, whichever occurred first) was similar for patients in the quizartinib and placebo arms (HR for event or death, 0.92; 95% CI, 0.75–1.11; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .24). The rates of CR and time to neutrophil count recovery were similar between the two arms.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_817">	The FDA approved quizartinib in combination with induction therapy for patients with AML and an <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-ITD variant but not for patients with other <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName> variants, such as <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-TKD.</Para></SummarySection><Para id="_812">The addition of an FLT3 inhibitor to induction chemotherapy is the standard of care for patients with <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-altered AML who are eligible for intensive chemotherapy. An ongoing study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03836209">NCT03836209</ProtocolRef>) is evaluating which FLT3 inhibitor is best for patients with <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-ITD AML receiving up-front chemotherapy. Additional studies are evaluating FLT3 inhibitors in combination with hypomethylating agents and venetoclax in patients who are not candidates for intensive therapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_653"><Title>Addition of gemtuzumab ozogamicin</Title><Para id="_635"/><Para id="_647">Evidence (gemtuzumab ozogamicin):</Para><OrderedList id="_636" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a meta-analysis of more than 3,000 patients, the addition of the CD33-directed immunotoxin gemtuzumab ozogamicin to cytarabine plus anthracycline or clofarabine plus anthracycline led to a small increase in the OS rate at 5 years (30.7% vs. 34.6%; HR, 0.90; 95% CI, 0.82−0.98; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis>  = .01).<Reference refidx="9"/>  <ItemizedList id="_637" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The improvement in the 5-year OS rate was seen across all ages, but this effect was greatest in patients with favorable-risk cytogenetics (55.2% vs. 76.3%; HR, 0.47; 95% CI, 0.31−0.73; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0005), and to a lesser extent with intermediate-risk cytogenetics (34.1% vs. 39.4%; HR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.75−0.95; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .007). It was not seen in patients with an adverse-risk karyotype.<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>In contrast, gemtuzumab ozogamicin did not improve the 1-year survival rate of older patients who received low-dose cytarabine, although the CR rate increased from 17% to 30% (odds ratio [OR], 0.48; 95% CI, 0.32–0.73; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006).<Reference refidx="17"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_638">The FDA  label for gemtuzumab ozogamicin includes a boxed warning about the risk of hepatotoxicity, including severe or fatal hepatic sinusoidal obstruction syndrome.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_654"><Title>Liposomal daunorubicin-cytarabine (CPX-351)</Title><Para id="_648">CPX-351 is a two-drug liposomal encapsulation that delivers cytarabine and daunorubicin at a fixed 5:1 synergistic molar ratio.</Para><Para id="_649">Evidence (CPX-351):</Para><OrderedList id="_640" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A multicenter trial investigated CPX-351 in patients aged 60 to 75 years with therapy-related AML, AML with a history of myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS), or AML with myelodysplasia-related changes.<Reference refidx="10"/> <ItemizedList id="_641" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Compared with 7 + 3 induction chemotherapy, CPX-351 resulted in a better overall remission rate (47.7% vs. 33.3%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .016), and improved median OS (9.56 vs. 5.95 months; HR, 0.69; 95% CI, 0.52−0.90; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003).<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>The rates of early mortality and toxicities were similar between the two arms. However, the median time to recovery of neutrophils and platelets was longer for CPX-351 (35.0 and 36.5 days, respectively) as compared with 7 + 3 induction chemotherapy (29 and 29 days, respectively).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_655"><Title>Older adults or adults with significant comorbid conditions</Title><Para id="_613">Some patients may decline or be too frail for intensive induction chemotherapy. Low-dose cytarabine, decitabine, azacitidine, or best supportive care can be considered equivalently effective treatment approaches for older patients with AML who decline traditional 7 + 3 induction chemotherapy. Unlike a succinct course of 7 + 3 induction, these less-intensive therapies are continued indefinitely, as long as the patient is deriving benefit (i.e., until disease progression or significant toxicity occurs). </Para><Para id="_614">One of the following chemotherapy regimens may be used as less-intensive therapy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_615" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	Hypomethylating agents (azacitidine and decitabine).</ListItem><ListItem>	Low-dose cytarabine.</ListItem><ListItem>	Venetoclax plus hypomethylating agents or low-dose cytarabine.</ListItem><ListItem>	Glasdegib plus low-dose cytarabine.</ListItem><ListItem>	Ivosidenib with or without azacitidine.</ListItem><ListItem>	Enasidenib.</ListItem><ListItem>	Intrathecal cytarabine or methotrexate may be used to treat CNS leukemia, if present.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_511">Evidence (chemotherapy for patients who decline intensive remission induction therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_512" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><Strong>Hypomethylating agents: </Strong>The hypomethylating agents azacitidine and decitabine are used commonly in this population of older patients, particularly in the United States. Although approval of the drugs by the FDA is for an MDS  indication, the registration studies leading to approval included patients with 20% to 30% myeloblasts, or what would now be considered oligoblastic AML.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><OrderedList id="_616" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem><Strong>	Azacitidine:</Strong> An international phase III trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01074047">NCT01074047</ProtocolRef>) randomly assigned patients  with AML who were 65 years or older to receive either azacitidine or conventional regimens (7 + 3 induction, low-dose cytarabine, or best supportive care alone).<Reference refidx="20"/> <ItemizedList id="_620" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Azacitidine led to a median OS of 10.4 months (95% CI, 8.0−12.7) as compared with 6.5 months (95% CI, 5.0−8.6) with conventional regimens (HR, 0.85; 95% CI, 0.69−1.03; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .1009).<Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Decitabine: </Strong>One phase III trial randomly assigned 485 patients with AML who were older than 65 years to receive either decitabine (n = 242) or their preferred choice (n = 243) of either supportive care (n = 28) or low-dose cytarabine (n = 215).<Reference refidx="21"/><ItemizedList id="_617" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Although rates of CR + CRp (CR with incomplete platelet recovery) were more than double in the decitabine arm (17.8%) compared with the treatment-choice arm (7.8%) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001), median OS was not significantly improved for patients receiving decitabine (7.7 months) compared with the treatment of choice (5.0 months) (HR for death for decitabine, 0.85; 95% CI, .69–1.04; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .11).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_618">Compared with treatment for 5 consecutive days, treatment for 10 consecutive days may lead to higher response rates, particularly in those with <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants and/or unfavorable cytogenetic features.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Low-dose cytarabine: </Strong> Older adults who decline intensive remission-induction therapy or are considered ineligible for intensive remission-induction therapy may derive benefit from low-dose cytarabine, administered  twice daily for 10 days in cycles repeated every 4 to 6 weeks.<Reference refidx="23"/> <ItemizedList id="_513" Style="bullet"><ListItem>  The CR rate using this regimen was 18% compared with 1% for patients treated with hydroxyurea (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006).</ListItem><ListItem>Survival with low-dose cytarabine was better than was survival with hydroxyurea (OR, 0.60; 95% CI, 0.44–0.81; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .009).<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong>Venetoclax plus hypomethylating agents or low-dose cytarabine:</Strong> The FDA approved venetoclax, an inhibitor of the anti-apoptotic protein BCL2, in combination with low-dose cytarabine or a hypomethylating agent for the treatment of AML in patients aged 75 years or older, and those who cannot undergo 7 + 3 induction chemotherapy because of comorbidities. Approval was granted based on the results of two studies.<OrderedList id="_621" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>The first study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02203773">NCT02203773</ProtocolRef>) was a nonrandomized, open-label, phase Ib clinical trial of venetoclax in combination with azacitidine or decitabine.<Reference refidx="24"/> <ItemizedList id="_622" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In this study, 35 (61%; 95% CI, 47.6%−74.0%) of 57 patients had CR or CR with incomplete hematologic recovery (CRi). The median duration of response for all patients with a response (CR + CRi + partial remission [PR]) was 8.4 months (range, 4.7−11.7; n = 36).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	The second study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02287233">NCT02287233</ProtocolRef>) was a phase I/IIb study of venetoclax in combination with low-dose cytarabine in 82 patients with newly diagnosed AML, including patients with previous exposure to a hypomethylating agent for an antecedent hematologic disorder such as MDS.<Reference refidx="25"/> <ItemizedList id="_623" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In the 82 patients enrolled in the study, the CR/CRi rate was 54% (95% CI, 42%−65%), with a median duration of remission of 8.1 months (95% CI, 5.3−14.9 months). The median OS for all patients, irrespective of response, was 10.1 months (95% CI, 5.7−14.2 months). </ListItem><ListItem>The most common adverse events with venetoclax combinations are gastrointestinal symptoms and myelosuppression, which may require delays between cycles, growth factor support, or decreased duration of venetoclax administration per cycle. Additionally, appropriate prophylactic measures are typically taken to prevent tumor lysis syndrome.<Reference refidx="25"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong>Glasdegib plus low-dose cytarabine:</Strong> Glasdegib, an oral inhibitor of the hedgehog pathway, combined with low-dose cytarabine was compared with low-dose cytarabine alone in a randomized, phase II open-label study that included 116 patients with AML who were aged 75 years or older or who had severe comorbid conditions (cardiac disease, renal impairment, or Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status 2).<Reference refidx="26"/> <ItemizedList id="_624" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Of the 78 patients with AML who received glasdegib plus low-dose cytarabine, 24% (n = 19) of patients had a CR or  CRi compared with 5%  (2 of 38) of patients who received low-dose cytarabine alone. The median OS was 8.3 months (80%; CI, 6.6–9.5) for patients who received glasdegib/low-dose cytarabine and 4.3 months (80%; CI, 2.9–4.9) for patients who received low-dose cytarabine alone in patients with AML (HR, 0.46; 80% CI, 0.35–0.62; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0002).<Reference refidx="26"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_625">Similar to venetoclax, the FDA approved glasdegib  in combination with low-dose cytarabine for the treatment of AML in patients aged 75 years or older or who are unable to receive intensive induction chemotherapy.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>	Ivosidenib:</Strong> For older or frail patients with AML and <GeneName>IDH1</GeneName> variants, the IDH1 inhibitor ivosidenib is an option. The FDA approved ivosidenib alone or in combination with azacitidine for the treatment of AML that has a susceptible <GeneName>IDH1</GeneName> variant (detected by an FDA-approved diagnostic test) in adults aged 75 years or older with newly diagnosed AML or who have comorbidities that preclude the use of intensive induction chemotherapy. Within the context of a phase I study, 34 patients with newly diagnosed <GeneName>IDH1</GeneName>-altered AML who were not candidates for intensive induction chemotherapy were treated with single-agent ivosidenib.<Reference refidx="27"/><ItemizedList id="_626" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Differentiation syndrome was reported in 6 patients (18%), but did not require treatment discontinuation. </ListItem><ListItem>The rate of CR plus CRi was 42.4% (95% CI, 25.5%−60.8%), with a median duration of response that was not reached (lower bound of the 95% CI was 4.6 months). </ListItem><ListItem>For all 34 patients on the study, the median OS was 12.6 months (95% CI, 4.5−25.7).<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_794">The combination of azacitidine and ivosidenib was evaluated in a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, phase III trial in patients with newly diagnosed AML who were not eligible for intensive induction chemotherapy. The intention-to-treat analysis included 72 patients treated with azacitidine and ivosidenib and 74 patients treated with azacitidine and placebo. A supplemental new drug application for ivosidenib in combination with azacitidine for patients with untreated <GeneName>IDH1</GeneName>-altered AML is under priority review with the FDA.<Reference refidx="28"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_795" Style="bullet"><ListItem>At a median follow-up of 12.4 months, the primary end point of EFS was improved in patients who received azacitidine and ivosidenib, compared with patients who received azacitidine and placebo (HR, 0.33; 95% CI, 0.16–0.69).</ListItem><ListItem>	The median OS was 24 months for patients who received azacitidine and ivosidenib and 7.9 months for patients who received azacitidine and placebo (HR for death, 0.44; 95% CI, 0.27–0.73).</ListItem><ListItem>	Differentiation syndrome occurred in 14% of patients who received azacitidine and ivosidenib and 8% of patients who received azacitidine and placebo. The incidence of bleeding events was 41% with azacitidine and ivosidenib and 29% with azacitidine and placebo. Infection of any grade was seen in 28% of patients who received azacitidine and ivosidenib and 49% of patients who received azacitidine and placebo. For more information about differentiation syndrome, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_690" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Newly Diagnosed Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia</SummaryRef> section.<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong>Enasidenib:</Strong> For patients with AML and <GeneName>IDH2</GeneName> variants, the IDH2 inhibitor enasidenib is an option for older or frail patients. Although it does not have approval in this setting, enasidenib monotherapy was evaluated in a phase I/II trial in patients with newly diagnosed AML who were not eligible for standard chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="29"/> <ItemizedList id="_627" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Of the 39 patients enrolled, seven (18%) had CR, one (3%) had CRi, and two (5%) had a PR. </ListItem><ListItem>Median OS for all patients was 11.3 months (95% CI, 5.7−15.1), and was not reached for patients who had a response.<Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_53_sid_4"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_53_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="6953986" MedlineID="82232555">Yates J, Glidewell O, Wiernik P, et al.: Cytosine arabinoside with daunorubicin or adriamycin for therapy of acute myelocytic leukemia: a CALGB study. Blood 60 (2): 454-62, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1824249" MedlineID="92399729">Dillman RO, Davis RB, Green MR, et al.: A comparative study of two different doses of cytarabine for acute myeloid leukemia: a phase III trial of Cancer and Leukemia Group B. Blood 78 (10): 2520-6, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1730080" MedlineID="92110562">Wiernik PH, Banks PL, Case DC, et al.: Cytarabine plus idarubicin or daunorubicin as induction and consolidation therapy for previously untreated adult patients with acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 79 (2): 313-9, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1607916" MedlineID="92300413">Vogler WR, Velez-Garcia E, Weiner RS, et al.: A phase III trial comparing idarubicin and daunorubicin in combination with cytarabine in acute myelogenous leukemia: a Southeastern Cancer Study Group Study. J Clin Oncol 10 (7): 1103-11, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2015395" MedlineID="91198495">Berman E, Heller G, Santorsa J, et al.: Results of a randomized trial comparing idarubicin and cytosine arabinoside with daunorubicin and cytosine arabinoside in adult patients with newly diagnosed acute myelogenous leukemia. Blood 77 (8): 1666-74, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="1829918" MedlineID="91299389">Mandelli F, Petti MC, Ardia A, et al.: A randomised clinical trial comparing idarubicin and cytarabine to daunorubicin and cytarabine in the treatment of acute non-lymphoid leukaemia. A multicentric study from the Italian Co-operative Group GIMEMA. Eur J Cancer 27 (6): 750-5, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9508168">Löwenberg B, Suciu S, Archimbaud E, et al.: Mitoxantrone versus daunorubicin in induction-consolidation chemotherapy--the value of low-dose cytarabine for maintenance of remission, and an assessment of prognostic factors in acute myeloid leukemia in the elderly: final report. European Organization for the Research and Treatment of Cancer and the Dutch-Belgian Hemato-Oncology Cooperative Hovon Group. J Clin Oncol 16 (3): 872-81, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28644114">Stone RM, Mandrekar SJ, Sanford BL, et al.: Midostaurin plus Chemotherapy for Acute Myeloid Leukemia with a FLT3 Mutation. N Engl J Med 377 (5): 454-464, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="25008258">Hills RK, Castaigne S, Appelbaum FR, et al.: Addition of gemtuzumab ozogamicin to induction chemotherapy in adult patients with acute myeloid leukaemia: a meta-analysis of individual patient data from randomised controlled trials. Lancet Oncol 15 (9): 986-96, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="30024784">Lancet JE, Uy GL, Cortes JE, et al.: CPX-351 (cytarabine and daunorubicin) Liposome for Injection Versus Conventional Cytarabine Plus Daunorubicin in Older Patients With Newly Diagnosed Secondary Acute Myeloid Leukemia. J Clin Oncol 36 (26): 2684-2692, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="14999298">Holowiecki J, Grosicki S, Robak T, et al.: Addition of cladribine to daunorubicin and cytarabine increases complete remission rate after a single course of induction treatment in acute myeloid leukemia. Multicenter, phase III study. Leukemia 18 (5): 989-97, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="22508825">Holowiecki J, Grosicki S, Giebel S, et al.: Cladribine, but not fludarabine, added to daunorubicin and cytarabine during induction prolongs survival of patients with acute myeloid leukemia: a multicenter, randomized phase III study. J Clin Oncol 30 (20): 2441-8, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="2179638" MedlineID="90189945">Arlin Z, Case DC, Moore J, et al.: Randomized multicenter trial of cytosine arabinoside with mitoxantrone or daunorubicin in previously untreated adult patients with acute nonlymphocytic leukemia (ANLL). Lederle Cooperative Group. Leukemia 4 (3): 177-83, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="26037486">Li X, Xu S, Tan Y, et al.: The effects of idarubicin versus other anthracyclines for induction therapy of patients with newly diagnosed leukaemia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (6): CD010432, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="19776406">Fernandez HF, Sun Z, Yao X, et al.: Anthracycline dose intensification in acute myeloid leukemia. N Engl J Med 361 (13): 1249-59, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="37116523">Erba HP, Montesinos P, Kim HJ, et al.: Quizartinib plus chemotherapy in newly diagnosed patients with FLT3-internal-tandem-duplication-positive acute myeloid leukaemia (QuANTUM-First): a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet 401 (10388): 1571-1583, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="22964882">Burnett AK, Hills RK, Hunter AE, et al.: The addition of gemtuzumab ozogamicin to low-dose Ara-C improves remission rate but does not significantly prolong survival in older patients with acute myeloid leukaemia: results from the LRF AML14 and NCRI AML16 pick-a-winner comparison. Leukemia 27 (1): 75-81, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="12011120" MedlineID="22007249">Silverman LR, Demakos EP, Peterson BL, et al.: Randomized controlled trial of azacitidine in patients with the myelodysplastic syndrome: a study of the cancer and leukemia group B. J Clin Oncol 20 (10): 2429-40, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="16435386">Kantarjian H, O'brien S, Cortes J, et al.: Results of intensive chemotherapy in 998 patients age 65 years or older with acute myeloid leukemia or high-risk myelodysplastic syndrome: predictive prognostic models for outcome. Cancer 106 (5): 1090-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="25987659">Dombret H, Seymour JF, Butrym A, et al.: International phase 3 study of azacitidine vs conventional care regimens in older patients with newly diagnosed AML with &gt;30% blasts. Blood 126 (3): 291-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="22689805">Kantarjian HM, Thomas XG, Dmoszynska A, et al.: Multicenter, randomized, open-label, phase III trial of decitabine versus patient choice, with physician advice, of either supportive care or low-dose cytarabine for the treatment of older patients with newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia. J Clin Oncol 30 (21): 2670-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="27959731">Welch JS, Petti AA, Miller CA, et al.: TP53 and Decitabine in Acute Myeloid Leukemia and Myelodysplastic Syndromes. N Engl J Med 375 (21): 2023-2036, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="17315155">Burnett AK, Milligan D, Prentice AG, et al.: A comparison of low-dose cytarabine and hydroxyurea with or without all-trans retinoic acid for acute myeloid leukemia and high-risk myelodysplastic syndrome in patients not considered fit for intensive treatment. Cancer 109 (6): 1114-24, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="29339097">DiNardo CD, Pratz KW, Letai A, et al.: Safety and preliminary efficacy of venetoclax with decitabine or azacitidine in elderly patients with previously untreated acute myeloid leukaemia: a non-randomised, open-label, phase 1b study. Lancet Oncol 19 (2): 216-228, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="30892988">Wei AH, Strickland SA, Hou JZ, et al.: Venetoclax Combined With Low-Dose Cytarabine for Previously Untreated Patients With Acute Myeloid Leukemia: Results From a Phase Ib/II Study. J Clin Oncol 37 (15): 1277-1284, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="30555165">Cortes JE, Heidel FH, Hellmann A, et al.: Randomized comparison of low dose cytarabine with or without glasdegib in patients with newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia or high-risk myelodysplastic syndrome. Leukemia 33 (2): 379-389, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="31841594">Roboz GJ, DiNardo CD, Stein EM, et al.: Ivosidenib induces deep durable remissions in patients with newly diagnosed IDH1-mutant acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 135 (7): 463-471, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="35443108">Montesinos P, Recher C, Vives S, et al.: Ivosidenib and Azacitidine in IDH1-Mutated Acute Myeloid Leukemia. N Engl J Med 386 (16): 1519-1531, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="30967620">Pollyea DA, Tallman MS, de Botton S, et al.: Enasidenib, an inhibitor of mutant IDH2 proteins, induces durable remissions in older patients with newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia. Leukemia 33 (11): 2575-2584, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039083">adult acute myeloid leukemia in remission</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of AML in Remission</Title><Para id="_69">Although individual patients with acute myeloid leukemia (AML) have been reported to have long disease-free
survival  (DFS) or cure with a single cycle of chemotherapy,<Reference refidx="1"/> consolidation therapy
is always indicated in therapy that is planned with curative intent.  In a
small randomized study conducted by the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group, all
patients who did not receive consolidation therapy experienced a relapse after
a short median complete remission (CR) duration.<Reference refidx="2"/>  
</Para><Para id="_526">Treatment options for AML in remission (consolidation phase) include:</Para><OrderedList id="_527" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_529" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef> with short-term (3−4 cycles), relatively intensive chemotherapy
with cytarabine-based regimens similar to standard induction clinical trials
(consolidation chemotherapy) and consolidation chemotherapy with more
dose-intensive cytarabine-based treatment.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_705" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">	Maintenance therapy</SummaryRef> (longer-term therapy at lower doses) has not been shown to benefit AML patients in a number of studies, but two strategies have shown a benefit:<ItemizedList id="_659" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_662" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Midostaurin</SummaryRef> in patients with <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-altered AML. </ListItem><ListItem>	<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_668" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Oral azacitidine</SummaryRef>.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_532" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Hematopoietic cell (bone marrow or stem cell) transplant</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_575" Style="bullet"><ListItem>High-dose chemotherapy with autologous peripheral blood stem cell rescue.</ListItem><ListItem>High-dose
marrow-ablative or reduced-intensity therapy followed by allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplant (HCT).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_529"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_70">Nontransplant consolidation therapy using cytarabine-containing regimens has
treatment-related death rates that are usually less than 10% to 20% and has
reported long-term DFS rates from 20% to 50%.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  The optimal doses,
schedules, and duration of consolidation chemotherapy have not been determined.</Para><Para id="_576">The standard consolidation therapy for AML patients in remission is high-dose cytarabine; however, there exists some controversy about whether it benefits all younger AML patients in first complete response versus selected subgroups, such as those with core-binding factor abnormalities.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/>  The duration of consolidation therapy has
ranged from one cycle <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/> to four or more cycles.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_530">Evidence (chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_531" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A large,
randomized trial  that compared three different cytarabine-containing
consolidation therapy regimens showed a clear benefit in survival to patients younger
than 60 years who received high-dose cytarabine.<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem>Intensification of
cytarabine dose or duration of consolidation chemotherapy with conventionally dosed cytarabine did not improve DFS or overall survival (OS) in patients aged 60 years or older, as evidenced in the Medical Research Council (MRC-LEUK-AML11) trial.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_71">Dose-intensive cytarabine-based chemotherapy can be complicated by severe
neurological <Reference refidx="14"/> and/or pulmonary toxic effects <Reference refidx="15"/> and should be administered
by physicians experienced in these regimens at centers that are equipped to
treat potential complications.  In a retrospective analysis of 256 patients
who received high-dose bolus cytarabine at a single institution, the most
powerful predictor of cytarabine neurotoxicity was renal insufficiency.  The
incidence of neurotoxicity was significantly greater in patients treated with
twice daily doses of 3 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/dose when compared with 2
g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>/dose.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_705"><Title>Maintenance Therapy</Title><Para id="_661">While a number of older studies have included longer-term therapy at lower doses (maintenance), there has been no convincing evidence that maintenance therapy provides prolonged DFS or OS. However, maintenance therapy with midostaurin or oral azacitidine may improve outcomes.</Para><SummarySection id="_662"><Title>Midostaurin</Title><Para id="_663">Evidence (midostaurin):</Para><Para id="_664">Variants in the tyrosine kinase domain and internal tandem duplications of the <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName> gene are frequent in AML and are often associated with an inferior outcome.</Para><OrderedList id="_665" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In the multicenter, randomized, phase III <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00651261">RATIFY</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT00651261), the FLT3/multikinase inhibitor midostaurin plus cytarabine and daunorubicin induction chemotherapy was compared with placebo in patients with <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName>-altered AML.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_666" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	The addition of the FLT3/multikinase inhibitor midostaurin to cytarabine and daunorubicin induction chemotherapy led to improved survival (median, 75 vs. 26 months; hazard ratio [HR] for death, 0.78; one-sided <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .009).</ListItem><ListItem>Patients who remained in remission after completion of consolidation therapy entered a maintenance phase in which they received midostaurin or placebo, administered at a dose of 50 mg orally twice daily, for twelve 28-day cycles. A maintenance regimen was administered for the full 12 cycles in 120 patients (69 in the midostaurin group, and 51 in the placebo group). </ListItem><ListItem>An ad-hoc landmark analysis from the end of maintenance revealed no difference in DFS between the two arms. Moreover, from the start of maintenance therapy there was no difference in OS between the two arms.<Reference refidx="17"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_667">While maintenance was well tolerated in the RATIFY study, only a small subset of patients tolerated midostaurin as maintenance therapy after chemotherapy or transplant in a separate phase II study.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para></ListItem><ListItem>	In the multicenter, randomized phase II <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01883362">RADIUS</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT01883362), the addition of midostaurin to standard of care was compared with standard of care alone after allogeneic HCT.<Reference refidx="19"/> Similar to the RATIFY trial, midostaurin was administered at a dose of 50 mg orally twice daily, for twelve 28-day cycles. Thirty patients were enrolled in each arm, but only half were able to complete the entire 12 cycles of therapy. <ItemizedList id="_672" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The estimated 18-month relapse-free survival (RFS) rate was 89% in the midostaurin arm and 76% in the standard of care arm (HR, 0.46; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.12−1.86; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = 0.27). The predicted relative reduction in the risk of relapse with the addition of midostaurin was 54%.<Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_668"><Title>Oral azacitidine</Title><Para id="_669">Evidence (oral azacitidine): </Para><OrderedList id="_670" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase III <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01757535">QUAZAR AML-001</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT01757535) provided the basis for regulatory approval of oral azacitidine as maintenance therapy for AML.<Reference refidx="20"/> The study included 472 patients with AML who were aged 55 years or older, were within 4 months of first CR or CR with incomplete hematologic recovery after induction chemotherapy with or without consolidation treatment, and were not candidates for allogeneic HCT. Oral azacitidine or placebo was administered at 300 mg daily for 14 days every 28 days. Treatment was continued until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. <ItemizedList id="_671" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For patients who received azacitidine, the median OS from randomization was 24.7 months (95% CI, 18.7−30.5) compared with 14.8 months (95% CI, 11.7−17.6) for patients receiving placebo (HR, 0.69; 95% CI, 0.55−0.86; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0009).<Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_532"><Title>Hematopoietic Cell (Bone Marrow or Stem Cell) Transplant</Title><SummarySection id="_533"><Title>Allogeneic HCT</Title><Para id="_72">Allogeneic HCT, even with minimal conditioning chemotherapy, results in the lowest incidence of
leukemic relapse, even when compared with HCT from an
identical twin (syngeneic HCT).  This finding led to the
concept of an immunologic graft-versus-leukemia effect, similar to (and related
to) graft-versus-host disease.  The improvement in freedom from relapse using
allogeneic HCT as the primary consolidation therapy is
offset, at least in part, by the increased morbidity and mortality caused by
graft-versus-host disease, veno-occlusive disease of the liver, and
infection.  The DFS  rates using allogeneic
transplant in first complete remission have ranged from 45% to 60%.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/> 
</Para><Para id="_534">The use of allogeneic HCT in adults requires either a HLA-matched
sibling donor, an HLA-matched unrelated donor, a haploidentical donor (“half HLA-matched”), or two well-matched umbilical cord blood units.  Including patients who underwent HCT from 2007 to 2017, the 3-year probabilities of survival after HLA-matched sibling transplant were 59% (±1%) for patients with early disease, 53% (±1%) for patients with intermediate disease, and 29% (±1%) for patients with advanced disease, according to the Center for International Blood and Marrow Transplant Research registry.<Reference refidx="24"/> The probabilities of survival after an unrelated donor transplant were 53% (±1%) for patients with early disease, 50% (±1%) for intermediate disease, and 27% (±1%)  for patients with advanced disease. [<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_78">Because HCT can cure more than 30% of patients who
experience relapse after chemotherapy, some investigators suggested that
allogeneic bone marrow transplant (BMT) can be reserved for early first relapse
or second CR without compromising the number of patients who
are ultimately cured.<Reference refidx="25"/>  Clinical and cytogenetic information can
define certain subsets of patients with predictable better or worse prognoses
according to favorable- and adverse-risk factors in those using consolidation chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="26"/>  </Para><ItemizedList id="_543" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Favorable-risk AML:</Strong> Favorable-risk factors include t(8;21),
inv(16), normal karyotype with an <GeneName>NPM1</GeneName> variant (in absence of an <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName> variant), and normal karyotype with double cytosine-cytosine-adenosine-adenosine-thymidine (CCAAT)-enhancer binding protein (C/EBP)-alpha variants. Patients in the favorable-risk group have a reasonable chance of cure with intensive
consolidation chemotherapy, and it may be reasonable to defer transplant in that group
until early first relapse.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Adverse-risk AML:</Strong> Adverse-risk factors include deletion of 5q, 7q, 17p, inversion of 3 or t(3;3), abnormality of (17p), trisomy 8, t(6;9),
t(9;22), most translocations involving chromosome 11q23, <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> variants,  a complex or monosomal karyotype, a history of myelodysplasia or antecedent hematologic disorder, <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants, <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> variants, <GeneName>ASXL1</GeneName> variants, and normal karyotype with <GeneName>FLT3</GeneName> variants. 
The adverse-risk group is highly unlikely to be cured with
consolidation chemotherapy, and allogeneic BMT in first CR is a reasonable option for patients.  However, even with allogeneic stem cell transplant, the
outcome for patients with high-risk AML is poor (5-year DFS
rate of 8% to 30% for patients with treatment-related leukemia or
myelodysplasia).<Reference refidx="27"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Normal cytogenetics:</Strong> Patients with normal cytogenetics are in an intermediate-risk
group, and consolidation management should be individualized based on additional molecular markers, patient comorbid factors, and patient preference or, preferably, managed according to a clinical trial.
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_342">A common clinical trial design used to evaluate the benefit of allogeneic transplant as consolidation therapy for AML in first remission is the so-called <Emphasis>donor-no donor</Emphasis> comparison.  In this design, newly diagnosed AML patients who achieve a CR are deemed medically eligible for allogeneic transplant and undergo HLA typing.  If a matched sibling or matched unrelated donor is identified, the patient is allocated to the transplant arm.  Analysis of outcome is by intention to treat; that is, patients assigned to the donor arm who do not receive a transplant are grouped in the analysis with the patients who did actually receive a transplant.  RFS is the usual end point for this type of trial.  OS from the time of diagnosis is less frequently reported in these trials.  </Para><Para id="_341">  Investigators attempted to address this issue with a meta-analysis using data from 18 separate prospective trials of AML patients using the <Emphasis>donor-no donor</Emphasis> design, with data from an additional six trials included for sensitivity analysis.<Reference refidx="28"/>   The trials included in this meta-analysis enrolled adult patients aged 60 years and younger from 1982 to 2006.  Median follow-up ranged from 42 months to 142 months.  Preparative regimens were similar among the different trials.  Allogeneic transplant was compared with autologous transplant (six trials) or with a variety of consolidation chemotherapy regimens, with high-dose cytarabine being the most common.</Para><ItemizedList id="_535" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Treatment-related mortality ranged from 5% to 42% in the donor groups compared with 3% to 27% in the no-donor group.</ListItem><ListItem>Of 18 trials reporting RFS across all cytogenetic risk groups, the combined HR for overall RFS benefit with allogeneic transplant was 0.80, indicating a statistically significant reduction in death or relapse in a first CR.</ListItem><ListItem>Of the 15 trials reporting OS across all cytogenetic risk groups, the combined HR for OS was 0.90, again indicating a statistically significant reduction in death or relapse in a first CR.</ListItem><ListItem>In subgroup analysis according to cytogenetic risk , there was no RFS or OS benefit of allogeneic transplant for patients with favorable-risk AML (RFS: HR, 1.07; 95% CI,  0.83–1.38; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .59; OS: HR, 1.06; 95% CI, 0.64–1.76; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .81).  However, a transplant benefit was seen for patients with intermediate (RFS: HR, 0.83; 95% CI, 0.74–0.93; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01; OS: HR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.71–0.99; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03) or adverse-risk  cytogenetics (RFS: HR, 0.73; 95% CI, 0.59–0.90; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01; OS: HR, 0.60; 95% CI, 0.40–0.90; <Emphasis>P </Emphasis>= .01).<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] The conclusion from this meta-analysis was that allogeneic transplant from a sibling donor in a first CR is justified on the basis of improved RFS and OS for patients with intermediate- or adverse-risk, but not favorable-risk, cytogenetics.<Para id="_536">An important caveat to this analysis is that induction and consolidation strategies for AML among studies included in the meta-analysis were not uniform; nor were definitions of cytogenetic risk groups uniform. This may have resulted in inferior survival rates among chemotherapy-only treated patients. </Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_537">Most physicians who treat patients with leukemia agree that transplant should be offered to AML patients in first CR in the setting of adverse-risk cytogenetics  and should not be offered to patients in first CR with favorable-risk cytogenetics.<Reference refidx="26"/> However, older patients with favorable-risk AML who are unlikely to tolerate intensive cytarabine-based consolidation therapy can be considered for allogeneic HCT as consolidation therapy.<Reference refidx="29"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_538"><Title>Autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplant</Title><Para id="_73">The role of autologous transplant for AML patients has diminished over time because of the improvements in the nonrelapse mortality associated with allogeneic HCT,  as well as the advent of haploidentical and umbilical cord transplant expanding the potential donor pool so that nearly every patient has a donor.<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/>  Autologous HCT can yield DFS rates
between 35% and 50% in patients with AML in first remission.  Autologous HCT has also cured a smaller proportion of patients in second
remission.<Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/>  Treatment-related mortality rates of patients who have had
autologous peripheral blood or marrow transplant range from 10% to 20%. 
</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_67_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_67_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="6942904" MedlineID="81258235">Vaughan WP, Karp JE, Burke PJ: Long chemotherapy-free remissions after single-cycle timed-sequential chemotherapy for acute myelocytic leukemia. Cancer 45 (5): 859-65, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="3282032" MedlineID="88187737">Cassileth PA, Harrington DP, Hines JD, et al.: Maintenance chemotherapy prolongs remission duration in adult acute nonlymphocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol 6 (4): 583-7, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8078551" MedlineID="94359569">Mayer RJ, Davis RB, Schiffer CA, et al.: Intensive postremission chemotherapy in adults with acute myeloid leukemia. Cancer and Leukemia Group B. N Engl J Med 331 (14): 896-903, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1694236" MedlineID="90293807">Champlin R, Gajewski J, Nimer S, et al.: Postremission chemotherapy for adults with acute myelogenous leukemia: improved survival with high-dose cytarabine and daunorubicin consolidation treatment. J Clin Oncol 8 (7): 1199-206, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3422261" MedlineID="88117644">Rohatiner AZ, Gregory WM, Bassan R, et al.: Short-term therapy for acute myelogenous leukemia. J Clin Oncol 6 (2): 218-26, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2676014" MedlineID="90001527">Geller RB, Burke PJ, Karp JE, et al.: A two-step timed sequential treatment for acute myelocytic leukemia. Blood 74 (5): 1499-506, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="23287624">Löwenberg B: Sense and nonsense of high-dose cytarabine for acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 121 (1): 26-8, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8874180" MedlineID="97028165">Weick JK, Kopecky KJ, Appelbaum FR, et al.: A randomized investigation of high-dose versus standard-dose cytosine arabinoside with daunorubicin in patients with previously untreated acute myeloid leukemia: a Southwest Oncology Group study. Blood 88 (8): 2841-51, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="21410371">Löwenberg B, Pabst T, Vellenga E, et al.: Cytarabine dose for acute myeloid leukemia. N Engl J Med 364 (11): 1027-36, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="21606413">Schaich M, Röllig C, Soucek S, et al.: Cytarabine dose of 36 g/m² compared with 12 g/m² within first consolidation in acute myeloid leukemia: results of patients enrolled onto the prospective randomized AML96 study. J Clin Oncol 29 (19): 2696-702, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="21190996">Miyawaki S, Ohtake S, Fujisawa S, et al.: A randomized comparison of 4 courses of standard-dose multiagent chemotherapy versus 3 courses of high-dose cytarabine alone in postremission therapy for acute myeloid leukemia in adults: the JALSG AML201 Study. Blood 117 (8): 2366-72, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11468148" MedlineID="21361148">Stone RM, Berg DT, George SL, et al.: Postremission therapy in older patients with de novo acute myeloid leukemia: a randomized trial comparing mitoxantrone and intermediate-dose cytarabine with standard-dose cytarabine. Blood 98 (3): 548-53, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="11520775" MedlineID="21411442">Goldstone AH, Burnett AK, Wheatley K, et al.: Attempts to improve treatment outcomes in acute myeloid leukemia (AML) in older patients: the results of the United Kingdom Medical Research Council AML11 trial. Blood 98 (5): 1302-11, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="1648599" MedlineID="91294839">Baker WJ, Royer GL, Weiss RB: Cytarabine and neurologic toxicity. J Clin Oncol 9 (4): 679-93, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="7468613" MedlineID="81130839">Haupt HM, Hutchins GM, Moore GW: Ara-C lung: noncardiogenic pulmonary edema complicating cytosine arabinoside therapy of leukemia. Am J Med 70 (2): 256-61, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="28644114">Stone RM, Mandrekar SJ, Sanford BL, et al.: Midostaurin plus Chemotherapy for Acute Myeloid Leukemia with a FLT3 Mutation. N Engl J Med 377 (5): 454-464, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="17">Larson RA, Mandrekar SJ, Sanford BL: An Analysis of Maintenance Therapy and Post-Midostaurin Outcomes in the International Prospective Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Trial (CALGB 10603/RATIFY [Alliance]) for Newly Diagnosed Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) Patients with FLT3 Mutations. [Abstract] Blood  130 (Suppl 1):145, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="30563875">Schlenk RF, Weber D, Fiedler W, et al.: Midostaurin added to chemotherapy and continued single-agent maintenance therapy in acute myeloid leukemia with FLT3-ITD. Blood 133 (8): 840-851, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="33288862">Maziarz RT, Levis M, Patnaik MM, et al.: Midostaurin after allogeneic stem cell transplant in patients with FLT3-internal tandem duplication-positive acute myeloid leukemia. Bone Marrow Transplant 56 (5): 1180-1189, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="33369355">Wei AH, Döhner H, Pocock C, et al.: Oral Azacitidine Maintenance Therapy for Acute Myeloid Leukemia in First Remission. N Engl J Med 383 (26): 2526-2537, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="3332174" MedlineID="89001421">Clift RA, Buckner CD, Thomas ED, et al.: The treatment of acute non-lymphoblastic leukemia by allogeneic marrow transplantation. Bone Marrow Transplant 2 (3): 243-58, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="2660902" MedlineID="89287311">Reiffers J, Gaspard MH, Maraninchi D, et al.: Comparison of allogeneic or autologous bone marrow transplantation and chemotherapy in patients with acute myeloid leukaemia in first remission: a prospective controlled trial. Br J Haematol 72 (1): 57-63, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="3888309" MedlineID="85200264">Bostrom B, Brunning RD, McGlave P, et al.: Bone marrow transplantation for acute nonlymphocytic leukemia in first remission: analysis of prognostic factors. Blood 65 (5): 1191-6, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="32438042">D'Souza A, Fretham C, Lee SJ, et al.: Current Use of and Trends in Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation in the United States. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 26 (8): e177-e182, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="1727924" MedlineID="92092067">Schiller GJ, Nimer SD, Territo MC, et al.: Bone marrow transplantation versus high-dose cytarabine-based consolidation chemotherapy for acute myelogenous leukemia in first remission. J Clin Oncol 10 (1): 41-6, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="27895058">Döhner H, Estey E, Grimwade D, et al.: Diagnosis and management of AML in adults: 2017 ELN recommendations from an international expert panel. Blood 129 (4): 424-447, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="11304765" MedlineID="21201273">Witherspoon RP, Deeg HJ, Storer B, et al.: Hematopoietic stem-cell transplantation for treatment-related leukemia or myelodysplasia. J Clin Oncol 19 (8): 2134-41, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="19509382">Koreth J, Schlenk R, Kopecky KJ, et al.: Allogeneic stem cell transplantation for acute myeloid leukemia in first complete remission: systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective clinical trials. JAMA 301 (22): 2349-61, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="31200351">Tallman MS, Wang ES, Altman JK, et al.: Acute Myeloid Leukemia, Version 3.2019, NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 17 (6): 721-749, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="23187771">Gerds AT, Appelbaum FR: To transplant or not to transplant for adult acute myeloid leukemia: an ever-evolving decision. Clin Adv Hematol Oncol 10 (10): 655-62, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="21105791">Gooley TA, Chien JW, Pergam SA, et al.: Reduced mortality after allogeneic hematopoietic-cell transplantation. N Engl J Med 363 (22): 2091-101, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="26130705">Ciurea SO, Zhang MJ, Bacigalupo AA, et al.: Haploidentical transplant with posttransplant cyclophosphamide vs matched unrelated donor transplant for acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 126 (8): 1033-40, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="26766286">Ballen KK, Lazarus H: Cord blood transplant for acute myeloid leukaemia. Br J Haematol 173 (1): 25-36, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="8422458" MedlineID="93136415">Chao NJ, Stein AS, Long GD, et al.: Busulfan/etoposide--initial experience with a new preparatory regimen for autologous bone marrow transplantation in patients with acute nonlymphoblastic leukemia. Blood 81 (2): 319-23, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="8422457" MedlineID="93136414">Linker CA, Ries CA, Damon LE, et al.: Autologous bone marrow transplantation for acute myeloid leukemia using busulfan plus etoposide as a preparative regimen. Blood 81 (2): 311-8, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="8102640" MedlineID="93359913">Sanz MA, de la Rubia J, Sanz GF, et al.: Busulfan plus cyclophosphamide followed by autologous blood stem-cell transplantation for patients with acute myeloblastic leukemia in first complete remission: a report from a single institution. J Clin Oncol 11 (9): 1661-7, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="8426209" MedlineID="93147864">Cassileth PA, Andersen J, Lazarus HM, et al.: Autologous bone marrow transplant in acute myeloid leukemia in first remission. J Clin Oncol 11 (2): 314-9, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="38">Jones RJ, Santos GW: Autologous bone marrow transplantation with 4-hydroperoxycyclophosphamide purging. In: Gale RP, ed.: Acute Myelogenous Leukemia: Progress and Controversies: Proceedings of a Wyeth-Ayerst-UCLA Symposia Western Workshop Held at Lake Lanier, Georgia, November 28-December 1, 1989. Wiley-Liss, 1990, pp 411-419.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="2328313" MedlineID="90227228">Gorin NC, Aegerter P, Auvert B, et al.: Autologous bone marrow transplantation for acute myelocytic leukemia in first remission: a European survey of the role of marrow purging. Blood 75 (8): 1606-14, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="1571539" MedlineID="92239875">Robertson MJ, Soiffer RJ, Freedman AS, et al.: Human bone marrow depleted of CD33-positive cells mediates delayed but durable reconstitution of hematopoiesis: clinical trial of MY9 monoclonal antibody-purged autografts for the treatment of acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 79 (9): 2229-36, 1992.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_80"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038678">recurrent adult acute myeloid leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Refractory or Recurrent AML</Title><Para id="_263">No standard treatment regimen exists for patients with refractory or recurrent acute myeloid leukemia (AML).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_552">Treatment options for refractory or recurrent AML include:</Para><OrderedList id="_553" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_554" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_702" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_784" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Intensive salvage chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_785" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Reduced-intensity therapy, including targeted therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_560" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplant (HCT)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_554"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><SummarySection id="_784"><Title>Intensive salvage chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_82">A number of intensive salvage chemotherapy regimens have  demonstrated efficacy in recurrent AML, including:</Para><SummarySection id="_725"><Title>Fludarabine, cytarabine, and filgrastim (FLAG)</Title><Para id="_737">FLAG has shown antileukemic activity in patients with relapsed and refractory AML.</Para><Para id="_738">Evidence (FLAG):</Para><OrderedList id="_739" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A multicenter phase II study included 83 patients with relapsed or refractory AML or de novo refractory anemia with excess blasts in transformation. The primary end point was the rate of complete remission (CR) achieved after one or two courses of FLAG induction chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="3"/> <ItemizedList id="_740" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In patients with relapsed leukemia whose first remission lasted for 6 months or more, the CR rate was 81% (17 of 21 patients). </ListItem><ListItem>In patients with AML whose first remission lasted less than 6 months, or in patients with primary refractory disease, the CR rate was 30% (13 of 44 patients).<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Myelosuppression and mucositis were common therapy-related toxicities.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_741">Idarubicin has been added to this regimen as well (FLAG-Ida).<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_727"><Title>Mitoxantrone, etoposide, and cytarabine (MEC)</Title><Para id="_742">Evidence (MEC):</Para><OrderedList id="_743" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A study evaluated  one course of MEC chemotherapy in 74 patients with AML and a poor prognosis. The population included 30 patients with relapsed AML, 28 patients with primary refractory AML, and 16 patients with secondary AML.<Reference refidx="5"/><ItemizedList id="_744" Style="bullet"><ListItem> MEC demonstrated a CR induction rate of 55%.<Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A phase III randomized Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) trial (E-2995) assessed 129 patients with one of the following disease statuses: relapsed AML less than 6 months after first CR; relapsed AML after allogeneic or autologous bone marrow transplant;  second or greater AML relapse; primary induction failure; secondary AML; or high-risk myelodysplastic syndromes. Patients were randomly assigned to receive MEC with or without valspodar, a multidrug resistance modulator.<ItemizedList id="_745" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The  complete response rate was only 17% to 25% in both arms.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_729"><Title>Standard or high-dose cytarabine and mitoxantrone</Title><Para id="_748">Evidence (standard or high-dose cytarabine and mitoxantrone):</Para><OrderedList id="_749" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A study of cytarabine and mitoxantrone included 49 patients with relapsed or refractory AML.<Reference refidx="7"/><ItemizedList id="_750" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Treatment was successful in 50% to 60% of patients who
experienced relapse after initially obtaining a CR, with 62.5% of patients with AML in first relapse achieving M1 marrow.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_731"><Title>High-dose etoposide and cyclophosphamide</Title><Para id="_751">Evidence (high-dose etoposide and cyclophosphamide):</Para><OrderedList id="_752" Style="Arabic"><ListItem> Reported results have been similar to those for the combination of cytarabine and mitoxantrone.<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_733"><Title>Idarubicin and cytarabine</Title><Para id="_753">Evidence (idarubicin and cytarabine):</Para><OrderedList id="_790" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem> Reported results have been similar to those for the combination of cytarabine and mitoxantrone.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_735"><Title>Other intensive regimens</Title><ItemizedList id="_736" Style="bullet"><ListItem>High-dose cytarabine.<Reference refidx="12"/>  </ListItem><ListItem>Cytarabine, daunorubicin, and etoposide (ADE).<Reference refidx="13"/>  </ListItem><ListItem>Clofarabine plus cytarabine with or without filgrastim (CLAG).<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_785"><Title>Reduced-intensity therapy, including targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_557">Patients who are unable or unwilling to undergo intensive therapy can be treated with reduced-intensity therapies.</Para><SummarySection id="_746"><Title>Gilteritinib</Title><Para id="_747">Gilteritinib is an oral FLT3 inhibitor with activity in both internal tandem duplication (ITD) and tyrosine kinase domain (TKD) subtypes.  </Para><Para id="_754">Evidence (gilteritinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_755" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a phase III trial, 371 patients were randomly assigned in a 2:1 ratio to receive either gilteritinib or preselected salvage chemotherapy (MEC, FLAG-Ida, azacitidine, or low-dose cytarabine).<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><ItemizedList id="_756" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 37.1 months, the median overall survival (OS) was 9.3 months for patients who received gilteritinib versus 5.6 months for patients who received chemotherapy (hazard ratio [HR] for death, 0.665; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.52–0.85). The estimated OS rate at 2 years was 20.6% (95% CI, 15.8%–26.0%) for patients who received gilteritinib and 14.2% (95% CI, 8.3%–21.6%) for patients who received chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="16"/> Among those treated with gilteritinib, the median duration of complete response or complete response with partial hematologic recovery was 10 months (interquartile range [IQR], 2.08–not evaluable), and 23 months (IQR, 4.9–not evaluable) for just those achieving a complete response.<Reference refidx="17"/> </ListItem><ListItem>The rates of complete response and complete response with partial hematologic recovery were higher in patients who received gilteritinib than in patients who received chemotherapy (34% vs. 15.3%; HR, 18.6; 95% CI, 9.8–27.4). </ListItem><ListItem>Adverse events of grade 3 or higher were less common in patients who received gilteritinib when adjusted for exposure time.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] The most common adverse event of interest was increased liver transaminases for patients who received gilteritinib therapy. If liver transaminase levels (considered related to treatment) increase to more than 5 times the upper limit of normal, gilteritinib therapy is paused. When the enzymes return to less than 2.5 times the upper limit of normal, therapy can resume at a reduced dose of 80 mg once daily.<Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_757"><Title>Enasidenib</Title><Para id="_758">Enasidenib is an oral small molecule inhibitor with activity against the altered IDH2 enzyme.</Para><Para id="_759">Evidence (enasidenib):</Para><OrderedList id="_760" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a phase I/II study, 214 patients with relapsed or refractory AML were treated with enasidenib.<Reference refidx="18"/><ItemizedList id="_761" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The overall response rate was 40.3% (95% CI, 33.0%–48.0%), with a median response duration of 5.8 months. </ListItem><ListItem>This included 46 patients (26.1%) with a CR or a CR with incomplete hematologic recovery (CRi). </ListItem><ListItem>Grade 3 or 4 treatment-related adverse events included indirect hyperbilirubinemia (12%) and differentiation syndrome (7%). As a result, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) added a <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2017/209606s000lbl.pdf">boxed warning</ExternalRef> to enasidenib, which alerts prescribers that differentiation syndrome can occur.<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_762"><Title>Ivosidenib</Title><Para id="_763">Ivosidenib is an oral small molecule inhibitor with activity against the altered IDH1 enzyme.</Para><Para id="_764">Evidence (ivosidenib):</Para><OrderedList id="_765" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a phase I/II study, 179 patients with relapsed or refractory AML were treated with ivosidenib.<Reference refidx="19"/><ItemizedList id="_766" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The overall response rate was 39.1% (95% CI, 31.9%–46.7%) with a median duration response of 6.5 months (range, 4.6–9.3). This included 54 patients (30.2%) with a CR or a CRi.</ListItem><ListItem>Over one-third of patients who initially required transfusions became transfusion independent. </ListItem><ListItem>Grade 3 or higher prolongation of the QT interval was seen in 14 patients (7.8%), and grade 3 or higher differentiation was seen in 7 patients (3.9%). The FDA added a <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2019/211192s001lbl.pdf">boxed warning</ExternalRef> to ivosidenib, which alerts prescribers that differentiation syndrome can occur.<Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_829"><Title>Revumenib</Title><Para id="_830">Revumenib is an oral menin inhibitor that is approved by the FDA for the treatment of relapsed or refractory acute leukemia with a <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> translocation in adult and pediatric patients aged 1 year and older.</Para><OrderedList id="_831" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	In the phase I/II <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04065399">AUGMENT-101</ProtocolRef> study (NCT04065399), 104 patients with relapsed or refractory acute leukemia with a <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> rearrangement received revumenib. 	Patients had to have a corrected QT interval (QTc) using Fridericia's formula of less than 450 milliseconds at baseline.<Reference refidx="20"/><ItemizedList id="_832" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	The overall rate of CR plus CRh (complete remission with partial hematologic recovery) was 21.2% (95% CI, 13.8%–30.3%). The median duration of CR plus CRh was 6.4 months (95% CI, 2.7–not reached).<Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>	Of the 83 patients who were dependent on red blood cell and/or platelet transfusions, 14% became independent of transfusions during a 56-day postbaseline period. </ListItem><ListItem>	Revumenib has a <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2024/218944s000lbl.pdf">boxed warning</ExternalRef> for differentiation syndrome, which was observed in 29% of patients. Grade 3 or 4 differentiation syndrome was observed in 13% of patients, and one patient died (0.7%). </ListItem><ListItem>	Grade 3 or higher QTc prolongation was observed in 12% of patients. </ListItem><ListItem>Because revumenib is metabolized by CYP3A4, the dose must be reduced in patients receiving strong CYP3A4 inhibitors. The standard dose for patients who weigh more than 40 kg is 270 mg orally twice daily, with a dose reduction to 160 mg orally twice daily for patients receiving a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor. Furthermore, the dose is adjusted according to body surface area in patients who weigh less than 40 kg.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_767"><Title>Hypomethylating agents</Title><Para id="_768">Evidence (hypomethylating agents):</Para><OrderedList id="_769" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a retrospective analysis, 655 patients with relapsed or primary treatment-refractory AML received either azacitidine (57%) or decitabine (43%).<Reference refidx="21"/><ItemizedList id="_770" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Overall, 16% of patients achieved a CR or a CRi and experienced a median OS of 21 months.<Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_771"><Title>Gemtuzumab ozogamicin</Title><Para id="_783">The antibody-targeted chemotherapy agent gemtuzumab ozogamicin has been evaluated in patients who had relapsed AML and expressed CD33.  </Para><Para id="_772">Evidence (gemtuzumab ozogamicin):</Para><OrderedList id="_774" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A pooled analysis of three open-label, single-arm, phase II studies included 277 patients.<Reference refidx="22"/><ItemizedList id="_775" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The overall response rate was 26%.  Thirty-five patients (13%) achieved a CR and 36 patients (13%) achieved a CR without platelet recovery.  It is unclear whether the inadequate platelet
recovery was the result of  megakaryocyte toxic effects of gemtuzumab or subclinical
residual leukemia.  <Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_776">The long-term outcomes of patients who receive gemtuzumab and achieve CR without platelet recovery
are unclear.  Gemtuzumab induces profound bone
marrow aplasia similar to leukemia induction chemotherapy and also has
substantial hepatic toxic effects, including hepatic veno-occlusive
disease.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_777"><Title>Clofarabine with or without cytarabine</Title><Para id="_778">Evidence (clofarabine with or without cytarabine):</Para><OrderedList id="_779" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Clofarabine, a purine nucleoside analogue, was studied as a single agent in 62 patients with relapsed or refractory AML.<Reference refidx="23"/><ItemizedList id="_780" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Eight of 19 patients who received treatment for their first relapse experienced a complete response.</ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem><ListItem>Clofarabine was administered in combination with intermediate-dose cytarabine in patients with relapsed or refractory AML.<Reference refidx="24"/><ItemizedList id="_781" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Seven of 29 patients with AML or myelodysplastic syndrome who received treatment for their first relapse had a CR.<Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_560"><Title>Allogeneic Hematopoietic Cell Transplant</Title><Para id="_84">When patients with relapsed disease are treated aggressively, they may have extended
disease-free survival (DFS); however, patients with relapsed disease can only be cured with HCT.<Reference refidx="25"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]  Allogeneic HCT for patients in their second
CR provides better DFS rates than transplant for patients in relapse.<Reference refidx="26"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]   </Para><Para id="_561">Evidence (allogeneic HCT):</Para><OrderedList id="_562" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	Current transplant outcomes are reported by the Center for International Blood and Marrow Transplantation Registry. The group reported the following outcomes for transplants done in the United States between 2008 and 2018:<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_716" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	The 3-year survival rate was 53% for patients with AML in second or subsequent CR versus 31% for patients with relapsed disease (or never in a CR) who underwent a matched sibling donor transplant.</ListItem><ListItem>The 3-year survival rate was 50% for patients with AML in second or subsequent CR versus 30% for patients with relapsed disease (or who never achieved CR) who underwent a matched unrelated donor transplant.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_85">Allogeneic HCT can
be effective salvage therapy in some patients whose disease fails to go into remission with intensive
chemotherapy (primary refractory leukemia).  A number of retrospective studies have demonstrated the ability of allogeneic HCT to induce remission in primary refractory disease.<Reference refidx="28"/></Para><Para id="_721">Evidence (allogeneic HCT to induce remission):</Para><OrderedList id="_722" Style="Arabic"><ListItem> In one retrospective analysis of 168 patients with AML and primary refractory disease who underwent allogeneic HCT, the 5-year OS rate was 22%.<Reference refidx="29"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Another analysis was conducted among patients enrolled in a prospective cooperative group trial, <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00085709">SWOG S0106</ProtocolRef> (NCT00085709).<Reference refidx="30"/> <ItemizedList id="_723" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Of the 589 patients treated in the cooperative group trial, 150 (25%) had primary refractory disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Among the 64 patients with primary refractory disease who received an allogeneic HCT, the 4-year survival rate was 48% compared with 4% among the 86 patients who did not undergo transplant.<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_724">Randomized trials testing the efficacy of this approach are not available.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_80_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_80_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="27895058">Döhner H, Estey E, Grimwade D, et al.: Diagnosis and management of AML in adults: 2017 ELN recommendations from an international expert panel. Blood 129 (4): 424-447, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="32761235">Sekeres MA, Guyatt G, Abel G, et al.: American Society of Hematology 2020 guidelines for treating newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia in older adults. Blood Adv 4 (15): 3528-3549, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11167793">Jackson G, Taylor P, Smith GM, et al.: A multicentre, open, non-comparative phase II study of a combination of fludarabine phosphate, cytarabine and granulocyte colony-stimulating factor in relapsed and refractory acute myeloid leukaemia and de novo refractory anaemia with excess of blasts in transformation. Br J Haematol 112 (1): 127-37, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12707726">Pastore D, Specchia G, Carluccio P, et al.: FLAG-IDA in the treatment of refractory/relapsed acute myeloid leukemia: single-center experience. Ann Hematol 82 (4): 231-5, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="8464233">Spadea A, Petti MC, Fazi P, et al.: Mitoxantrone, etoposide and intermediate-dose Ara-C (MEC): an effective regimen for poor risk acute myeloid leukemia. Leukemia 7 (4): 549-52, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15020609">Greenberg PL, Lee SJ, Advani R, et al.: Mitoxantrone, etoposide, and cytarabine with or without valspodar in patients with relapsed or refractory acute myeloid leukemia and high-risk myelodysplastic syndrome: a phase III trial (E2995). J Clin Oncol 22 (6): 1078-86, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3478540" MedlineID="88037534">Paciucci PA, Dutcher JP, Cuttner J, et al.: Mitoxantrone and ara-C in previously treated patients with acute myelogenous leukemia. Leukemia 1 (7): 565-7, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="3469002" MedlineID="87129353">Hiddemann W, Kreutzmann H, Straif K, et al.: High-dose cytosine arabinoside and mitoxantrone: a highly effective regimen in refractory acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 69 (3): 744-9, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="2378980" MedlineID="90335431">Brown RA, Herzig RH, Wolff SN, et al.: High-dose etoposide and cyclophosphamide without bone marrow transplantation for resistant hematologic malignancy. Blood 76 (3): 473-9, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="3478198" MedlineID="88029591">Lambertenghi-Deliliers G, Maiolo AT, Annaloro C, et al.: Idarubicin in sequential combination with cytosine arabinoside in the treatment of relapsed and refractory patients with acute non-lymphoblastic leukemia. Eur J Cancer Clin Oncol 23 (7): 1041-5, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2642539" MedlineID="89080803">Harousseau JL, Reiffers J, Hurteloup P, et al.: Treatment of relapsed acute myeloid leukemia with idarubicin and intermediate-dose cytarabine. J Clin Oncol 7 (1): 45-9, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="3894588">Herzig RH, Lazarus HM, Wolff SN, et al.: High-dose cytosine arabinoside therapy with and without anthracycline antibiotics for remission reinduction of acute nonlymphoblastic leukemia. J Clin Oncol 3 (7): 992-7, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="11380463">Liu Yin JA, Wheatley K, Rees JK, et al.: Comparison of 'sequential' versus 'standard' chemotherapy as re-induction treatment, with or without cyclosporine, in refractory/relapsed acute myeloid leukaemia (AML): results of the UK Medical Research Council AML-R trial. Br J Haematol 113 (3): 713-26, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="21848522">Becker PS, Kantarjian HM, Appelbaum FR, et al.: Clofarabine with high dose cytarabine and granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) priming for relapsed and refractory acute myeloid leukaemia. Br J Haematol 155 (2): 182-9, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="23151979">Scappini B, Gianfaldoni G, Caracciolo F, et al.: Cytarabine and clofarabine after high-dose cytarabine in relapsed or refractory AML patients. Am J Hematol 87 (12): 1047-51, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="31665578">Perl AE, Martinelli G, Cortes JE, et al.: Gilteritinib or Chemotherapy for Relapsed or Refractory FLT3-Mutated AML. N Engl J Med 381 (18): 1728-1740, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="35081255">Perl AE, Larson RA, Podoltsev NA, et al.: Follow-up of patients with R/R FLT3-mutation-positive AML treated with gilteritinib in the phase 3 ADMIRAL trial. Blood 139 (23): 3366-3375, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="28588020">Stein EM, DiNardo CD, Pollyea DA, et al.: Enasidenib in mutant IDH2 relapsed or refractory acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 130 (6): 722-731, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="29860938">DiNardo CD, Stein EM, de Botton S, et al.: Durable Remissions with Ivosidenib in IDH1-Mutated Relapsed or Refractory AML. N Engl J Med 378 (25): 2386-2398, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="39121437">Issa GC, Aldoss I, Thirman MJ, et al.: Menin Inhibition With Revumenib for KMT2A-Rearranged Relapsed or Refractory Acute Leukemia (AUGMENT-101). J Clin Oncol 43 (1): 75-84, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="29685952">Stahl M, DeVeaux M, Montesinos P, et al.: Hypomethylating agents in relapsed and refractory AML: outcomes and their predictors in a large international patient cohort. Blood Adv 2 (8): 923-932, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="16116598">Larson RA, Sievers EL, Stadtmauer EA, et al.: Final report of the efficacy and safety of gemtuzumab ozogamicin (Mylotarg) in patients with CD33-positive acute myeloid leukemia in first recurrence. Cancer 104 (7): 1442-52, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="12791647">Kantarjian H, Gandhi V, Cortes J, et al.: Phase 2 clinical and pharmacologic study of clofarabine in patients with refractory or relapsed acute leukemia. Blood 102 (7): 2379-86, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="15486072">Faderl S, Gandhi V, O'Brien S, et al.: Results of a phase 1-2 study of clofarabine in combination with cytarabine (ara-C) in relapsed and refractory acute leukemias. Blood 105 (3): 940-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="1875218" MedlineID="91341522">Forman SJ, Schmidt GM, Nademanee AP, et al.: Allogeneic bone marrow transplantation as therapy for primary induction failure for patients with acute leukemia. J Clin Oncol 9 (9): 1570-4, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="3332174" MedlineID="89001421">Clift RA, Buckner CD, Thomas ED, et al.: The treatment of acute non-lymphoblastic leukemia by allogeneic marrow transplantation. Bone Marrow Transplant 2 (3): 243-58, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="27">Phelan R, Arora M, Chen M: The US Summary Slides - HCT Trends and Survival Data. Center for International Blood and Marrow Transplant Research, 2020. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cibmtr.org/ReferenceCenter/SlidesReports/SummarySlides/pages/index.aspx">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 24, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="28244979">Gyurkocza B, Lazarus HM, Giralt S: Allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation in patients with AML not achieving remission: potentially curative therapy. Bone Marrow Transplant 52 (8): 1083-1090, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="21339758">Craddock C, Labopin M, Pillai S, et al.: Factors predicting outcome after unrelated donor stem cell transplantation in primary refractory acute myeloid leukaemia. Leukemia 25 (5): 808-13, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="25536215">Othus M, Appelbaum FR, Petersdorf SH, et al.: Fate of patients with newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia who fail primary induction therapy. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 21 (3): 559-64, 2015.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_355"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039910">adult acute promyelocytic leukemia (M3)</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by cell type</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia (APL)</Title><Para id="_518">Special consideration must be given to induction therapy for APL.  Treatment is centered around the use of differentiating agents to clear the leukemic cells. Early mortality is related to bleeding, differentiation syndrome, or infection. High complete remission (CR) rates are very common across treatment regimens, and persistent disease or relapse is rare.</Para><SummarySection id="_690"><Title>Treatment of Newly Diagnosed APL</Title><Para id="_691">Treatment options for newly diagnosed APL include:</Para><OrderedList id="_408" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_673" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">All-trans retinoic acid (ATRA) plus arsenic trioxide (ATO) for low- to intermediate-risk disease</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_682" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">	ATRA plus chemotherapy, followed by ATO-based consolidation therapy for high-risk disease</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_519">ATRA induces terminal differentiation of the
leukemic cells followed by restoration of nonclonal hematopoiesis. 
Administration of ATRA leads to rapid resolution of coagulopathy in most patients, and heparin administration is not required in patients
receiving ATRA.  However, randomized trials have not shown a reduction in
morbidity and mortality during ATRA induction when compared with chemotherapy. 
ATRA administration may result in the following conditions:</Para><ItemizedList id="_520" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Differentiation syndrome:</Strong> Administration of ATRA can lead to a syndrome of
respiratory distress, known as differentiation syndrome.  Prompt
recognition of the syndrome and aggressive administration of steroids can
prevent severe respiratory distress.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Hyperleukocytosis:</Strong> The optimal management of
ATRA-induced hyperleukocytosis has not been established. Hyperleukocytosis in APL is typically treated with the addition of cytotoxic chemotherapy. Leukopheresis is not recommended because of an increased risk of complications such as bleeding events and disseminated intravascular coagulation.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_403">Studies performed in the 1990s demonstrated that overall survival (OS) rates improved in patients receiving ATRA in addition to chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> ATO, an agent with both differentiation-inducing and apoptosis-inducing
properties against APL cells, is also used in the treatment of APL. Induction remission therapy for APL is determined by disease risk. Low- to intermediate-risk APL (white blood cell [WBC] count ≤10 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L) is treated without chemotherapy (ATRA and ATO), and high-risk is treated with a combination of ATRA and ATO plus chemotherapy.</Para><SummarySection id="_673"><Title>ATRA plus ATO for low- to intermediate-risk disease</Title><Para id="_674">Evidence (ATRA plus ATO for low- to intermediate-risk disease):</Para><OrderedList id="_680" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	In a phase III, randomized controlled, multicenter trial in patients with APL classified as low-to-intermediate risk (WBC count, ≤10 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L) ATRA plus chemotherapy was compared with ATRA plus ATO.<Reference refidx="4"/> <ItemizedList id="_681" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	CR rates were equally high for both groups. CR occurred in all 77 patients (100%) who could be evaluated in the ATRA plus ATO group and in 75 of 79 patients (95%) in the ATRA plus chemotherapy group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .12).</ListItem><ListItem>	With a median follow-up of 34.4 months, the 2-year OS rate was 99% (95% confidence interval [CI], 96%−100%) in the ATRA plus ATO group, and 91% (95% CI, 85%−97%) in the ATRA plus chemotherapy group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).</ListItem><ListItem>	The 2-year cumulative incidence of relapse was similarly low in both groups, 1% (95% CI, 0%−4%) in the ATRA plus ATO group and 6% (95% CI, 0%−11%) in the ATRA plus chemotherapy group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .24).</ListItem><ListItem>	The primary end point was event-free survival (EFS) (defined as no achievement of hematologic CR after induction therapy, no achievement of molecular CR after three consolidation courses, molecular relapse, hematologic relapse, or death). The 2-year EFS rate was 97% for the ATRA plus ATO group and 85% in the ATRA plus chemotherapy group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001 for noninferiority).</ListItem>	</ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The results of this chemotherapy-free regimen for low- to intermediate-risk APL were confirmed in a second, phase III, randomized controlled trial.<Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_682"><Title>ATRA plus chemotherapy, followed by ATO-based consolidation therapy for high-risk disease</Title><Para id="_683">Remission induction with a combination of anthracycline and ATRA is used for remission induction in patients with high-risk disease (WBC count, &gt;10 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L).</Para><Para id="_684">Evidence (ATRA plus chemotherapy, followed by ATO-based consolidation therapy for high-risk disease):</Para><OrderedList id="_685" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00180128">AIDA-2000</ProtocolRef> study (NCT00180128)  combined oral ATRA until CR or for a maximum of 45 days and four doses of intravenous idarubicin (12 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) on days 2, 4, 6, and 8. Consolidation was then risk stratified so low- to intermediate-risk patients received additional cycles of anthracycline and ATRA, and high-risk patients also received cytarabine, etoposide, 6-thioguanine, and CHT chemotherapy (6-mercaptopurine plus methotrexate) as consolidation.<Reference refidx="6"/><ItemizedList id="_686" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	After induction, 420 of 445 patients (94.4%) treated on the AIDA-2000 protocol were in CR. The 6-year OS rate was 87.4% and the cumulative incidence of relapse rate was 10.7%.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]	</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	In the phase II APML4 study, ATO was added to the ATRA-and-idarubicin remission−induction backbone.<Reference refidx="7"/>  <ItemizedList id="_687" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	Of the 124 patients who could be evaluated, there were 4 (3.2%) early deaths and 118 (95%) hematologic CRs.</ListItem><ListItem>	The 2-year freedom-from-relapse rate was 97.5% (95% CI, 90.4%−99.4%),  the failure-free survival rate was 88.1% (95% CI, 80.7%−92.8%), and the OS rate was 93.2% (95% CI, 85.8%−96.8%).<Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_688">An ATO-based regimen, which includes  gemtuzumab ozogamicin as the only cytotoxic drug, has been developed.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>In a single-institution study, patients received ATRA plus ATO induction. They also received a dose of gemtuzumab ozogamicin (or idarubicin) if the WBC was greater than 10 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L on presentation or rose to more than 30 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L during induction.<Reference refidx="8"/> Patients in remission received ATO and ATRA in alternating months for a total of seven cycles as consolidation; gemtuzumab ozogamicin was substituted if either ATO or ATRA were discontinued because of toxicity. <ItemizedList id="_689" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	Of the 54 patients with high-risk disease treated on the protocol, one patient received both gemtuzumab ozogamicin and idarubicin (12 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> daily for 3 days) because of persistent leukocytosis despite receiving gemtuzumab ozogamicin.</ListItem><ListItem>The CR rate was 96%, and five (9%) patients relapsed.</ListItem><ListItem>	The 5-year rates were  81% for EFS, 89% for disease-free survival (DFS), and 86% for OS, indicating that the responses are durable.</ListItem><ListItem>	Across the entire study population, the 5-year OS rate was similar among the 45 high-risk patients who received gemtuzumab ozogamicin (84%) compared with the seven patients who received a dose of idarubicin (100%, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .453).<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_692">Long-term follow up from this study has been published.<Reference refidx="9"/> </Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Para id="_679">It is important to note that most current regimens for the treatment of APL include some form of maintenance therapy.  A meta-analysis of randomized trials  has indicated that maintenance clearly improves DFS but not OS; however, these trials did not include ATO-containing regimens.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_693"><Title>Treatment of Recurrent APL</Title><Para id="_694">Treatment options for recurrent APL include:</Para><OrderedList id="_695" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_696" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">ATO with or without chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_699" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Hematopoietic cell transplant (HCT)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_696"><Title>ATO with or without chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_86">ATO has high rates of second remission in patients with relapsed APL.<Reference refidx="10"/> As a single agent, ATO can lead to complete response rates of 80% to 90% in patients with hematologic relapse, and 70% to 80% in patients with molecular remission.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> The choice of salvage therapy is based on the previous  therapy and interval of time between first remission and relapse. </Para><ItemizedList id="_697" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	In patients with early relapse less than 6 months after ATRA and ATO, anthracycline-based regimens and ATRA as given for initial remission induction for high-risk disease should be considered.</ListItem><ListItem>	In patients who relapse less than 6 months after ATRA and anthracycline-based regimens (no previous ATO exposure), ATO-based regimens should be considered.</ListItem><ListItem>	In all patients with late relapse (&gt;6 months), ATO-based regimens with or without anthracycline or gemtuzumab ozogamicin should be considered.
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_698">For patients receiving ATO as salvage therapy, a small randomized trial suggested that the addition of ATRA does not confer any benefit over ATO alone in patients who previously received ATRA.<Reference refidx="14"/> In this 20-patient study, the complete response rate after one cycle of ATO with or without ATRA was 80%.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_699"><Title>HCT</Title><Para id="_700">Some patients in second remission with ATO have experienced long-term DFS after autologous stem cell transplant,<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/> and it can be considered in patients who are in molecular remission (negative quantitative polymerase chain reaction [PCR] on a marrow sample). Patients who do not go into remission or have evidence of measurable residual disease by quantitative PCR on a marrow sample after salvage therapy are considered for an allogeneic HCT.<Reference refidx="17"/> A registry study reported a 3-year OS rate after transplant in second CR of 80% compared with 59% in patients without transplant (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03).<Reference refidx="10"/> </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_355_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_355_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1637024" MedlineID="92344155">Frankel SR, Eardley A, Lauwers G, et al.: The "retinoic acid syndrome" in acute promyelocytic leukemia. Ann Intern Med 117 (4): 292-6, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="20018913">Adès L, Guerci A, Raffoux E, et al.: Very long-term outcome of acute promyelocytic leukemia after treatment with all-trans retinoic acid and chemotherapy: the European APL Group experience. Blood 115 (9): 1690-6, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="18664623">Sanz MA, Montesinos P, Vellenga E, et al.: Risk-adapted treatment of acute promyelocytic leukemia with all-trans retinoic acid and anthracycline monochemotherapy: long-term outcome of the LPA 99 multicenter study by the PETHEMA Group. Blood 112 (8): 3130-4, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="23841729">Lo-Coco F, Avvisati G, Vignetti M, et al.: Retinoic acid and arsenic trioxide for acute promyelocytic leukemia. N Engl J Med 369 (2): 111-21, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="26384238">Burnett AK, Russell NH, Hills RK, et al.: Arsenic trioxide and all-trans retinoic acid treatment for acute promyelocytic leukaemia in all risk groups (AML17): results of a randomised, controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 16 (13): 1295-305, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20644121">Lo-Coco F, Avvisati G, Vignetti M, et al.: Front-line treatment of acute promyelocytic leukemia with AIDA induction followed by risk-adapted consolidation for adults younger than 61 years: results of the AIDA-2000 trial of the GIMEMA Group. Blood 116 (17): 3171-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="22715121">Iland HJ, Bradstock K, Supple SG, et al.: All-trans-retinoic acid, idarubicin, and IV arsenic trioxide as initial therapy in acute promyelocytic leukemia (APML4). Blood 120 (8): 1570-80; quiz 1752, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="19075265">Ravandi F, Estey E, Jones D, et al.: Effective treatment of acute promyelocytic leukemia with all-trans-retinoic acid, arsenic trioxide, and gemtuzumab ozogamicin. J Clin Oncol 27 (4): 504-10, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="28003274">Abaza Y, Kantarjian H, Garcia-Manero G, et al.: Long-term outcome of acute promyelocytic leukemia treated with all-trans-retinoic acid, arsenic trioxide, and gemtuzumab. Blood 129 (10): 1275-1283, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="25627637">Lengfelder E, Lo-Coco F, Ades L, et al.: Arsenic trioxide-based therapy of relapsed acute promyelocytic leukemia: registry results from the European LeukemiaNet. Leukemia 29 (5): 1084-91, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="12010661">Leoni F, Gianfaldoni G, Annunziata M, et al.: Arsenic trioxide therapy for relapsed acute promyelocytic leukemia: a bridge to transplantation. Haematologica 87 (5): 485-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11559723" MedlineID="21443827">Soignet SL, Frankel SR, Douer D, et al.: United States multicenter study of arsenic trioxide in relapsed acute promyelocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol 19 (18): 3852-60, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="19822309">Thirugnanam R, George B, Chendamarai E, et al.: Comparison of clinical outcomes of patients with relapsed acute promyelocytic leukemia induced with arsenic trioxide and consolidated with either an autologous stem cell transplant or an arsenic trioxide-based regimen. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 15 (11): 1479-84, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="12805334">Raffoux E, Rousselot P, Poupon J, et al.: Combined treatment with arsenic trioxide and all-trans-retinoic acid in patients with relapsed acute promyelocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol 21 (12): 2326-34, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="23412094">Yanada M, Tsuzuki M, Fujita H, et al.: Phase 2 study of arsenic trioxide followed by autologous hematopoietic cell transplantation for relapsed acute promyelocytic leukemia. Blood 121 (16): 3095-102, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="24691221">Holter Chakrabarty JL, Rubinger M, Le-Rademacher J, et al.: Autologous is superior to allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation for acute promyelocytic leukemia in second complete remission. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 20 (7): 1021-5, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="15534358">de Botton S, Fawaz A, Chevret S, et al.: Autologous and allogeneic stem-cell transplantation as salvage treatment of acute promyelocytic leukemia initially treated with all-trans-retinoic acid: a retrospective analysis of the European acute promyelocytic leukemia group. J Clin Oncol 23 (1): 120-6, 2005.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (03/14/2025)</Title><Para id="_434">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.
</Para><Para id="_833"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_46" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview for Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML)</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_837">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_658" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>, Treatment Response Categories for Newly Diagnosed Acute Myeloid Leukemia.</Para><Para id="_834">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_643" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Table 3</SummaryRef>, Treatment Response Categories for Persistent/Recurrent Acute Myeloid Leukemia.</Para><Para id="_835"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_80" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Refractory or Recurrent AML</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_836">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_829" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">Revumenib</SummaryRef> as a new subsection.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062869#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of acute myeloid leukemia. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Alexander  Ambinder, MD, MPH (Johns Hopkins University )</ListItem><ListItem>Aaron Gerds, MD (Cleveland Clinic Taussig Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/adult-aml-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389432]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-03-14</DateLastModified></Summary>
