<Summary id="CDR0000062870" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Oral complications of cancer therapies are common and should be considered and addressed before, during, and after treatment. Get detailed information about mucositis, orofacial pain, infection, medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw, and other issues in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-pdq">Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038050">oral complications of radiation therapy</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000530108">xerostomia</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000775884">bone necrosis</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_881">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the pathophysiology and treatment of oral complications of cancer therapies. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_882">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bone necrosis</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>oral complications of radiation therapy</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>xerostomia</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Oral Complications (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Oral Complications</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_883"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_884">The field of oral complications caused by cancer therapies continues to evolve for a number of reasons, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_935" Style="bullet"><ListItem>High-quality basic, translational, and clinical research.</ListItem><ListItem>Translation of selected clinical interventions into systematic reviews and clinical practice guidelines based on this research.</ListItem><ListItem>Advances in cancer treatment via precision medicine technology.</ListItem><ListItem>Increased understanding of the value of integration of tumor treatment with evidence-based supportive care.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_885">The oral cavity represents a unique anatomic and functional site.  Clinical prevention and management of oral complications in patients with cancer should be based on state-of-the-science and implemented in an interprofessional practice setting.  The interprofessional team includes, but is not limited to, oncologists, oncology nurses and nurse navigators, dental generalists and specialists, dental hygienists, social workers, and dieticians.</Para><Para id="_936">The type and severity of oral complications vary by classification, intensity, and duration of cancer therapy.  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1424" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef> shows examples of these oral complications.</Para><Table id="_1424"><Title>Table 1.  Medically Necessary Oral Interventions, by Type of Cancer Therapy</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Cancer Therapy</entry><entry>Before Cancer Therapy</entry><entry>During Cancer Therapy</entry><entry>After Cancer Therapy</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">GVHD = graft versus host disease; HPV = human papillomavirus; HSCT = hematopoietic stem cell transplant; WBC = white blood cell.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Chemotherapy, high dose
(e.g., &lt;1,000 WBC/µL for more than 5 days)
and chemotherapy, moderate to low dose (e.g., nadir of 2,500 WBC/µL)</entry><entry>Advanced dental caries, with potential for pulpal involvement</entry><entry MoreRows="3">Maintain effective oral hygiene</entry><entry MoreRows="10">Implement preventive and treatment protocols to optimize oral health</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dentition with moderate/severe periodontal disease</entry></Row><Row><entry>Periapical lesions secondary to dental pulpal infection that have been symptomatic within the past 90 days </entry></Row><Row><entry>Dental appliances (e.g., dentures, orthodontic appliances) that may traumatize oral mucosa</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Patient education</entry><entry>Assess for possible acute infection of oral origin</entry></Row><Row><entry>Manage oral mucositis, including oral hygiene and pain management</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">HSCT, reduced intensity chemotherapy (e.g., nadir of 2,500 WBC/µL) and HSCT, myeloablative chemotherapy (e.g., &lt;1,000 WBC/µL for more than 5 days)</entry><entry>Advanced dental caries, with potential for pulpal involvement</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Maintain effective oral hygiene</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dentition with moderate/severe periodontal disease</entry></Row><Row><entry>Periapical lesions secondary to dental pulpal infection that have been symptomatic within the past 90 days </entry><entry MoreRows="1">Assess for possible acute infection of oral origin</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dental appliances (e.g., dentures, orthodontic appliances) that may traumatize oral mucosa</entry></Row><Row><entry>Patient education</entry><entry>Manage oral mucositis, including oral hygiene and pain management</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">HSCT, GVHD</entry><entry>Determine likelihood of developing acute and/or chronic GVHD, depending on type of transplant</entry><entry>Differentiate oral mucosal injury caused by chemotherapy and acute oral GVHD</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Monitor for emergence of chronic oral GVHD, potentially malignant mucosal disease, and/or oral squamous cell carcinoma</entry></Row><Row><entry>Patient education</entry><entry>Provide supportive care, including oral hygiene and pain control</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="6">Head and neck radiation, high dose</entry><entry>Determine need for medically necessary dental extractions and potential change in occlusal vertical dimension, based on the following:

 
</entry><entry MoreRows="4">Maintain oral hygiene and nutritional support</entry><entry MoreRows="5">Implement preventive and treatment protocols to optimize oral health</entry></Row><Row><entry>•	Advanced dental caries, with potential for pulpal involvement
</entry></Row><Row><entry>•	Dentition involved with moderate/severe periodontal disease</entry></Row><Row><entry>•	Periapical lesions secondary to dental pulpal infection that have been symptomatic within the past 90 days</entry></Row><Row><entry>•	Dental appliances (e.g., dentures, orthodontic appliances) that may traumatize oral mucosa

</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Patient education</entry><entry>Manage oral mucositis, including oral hygiene and pain management</entry></Row><Row><entry>Prescribe jaw opening and closing exercises to reduce risk of trismus</entry><entry>Monitor for risk of osteoradionecrosis, recurrent or new oral mucosal malignancy </entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Head and neck radiation, deintensification (HPV + oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma)</entry><entry>Same as high-dose head and neck radiation; risk for late effects appears to be reduced</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Same as high-dose head and neck radiation</entry><entry>Same as high dose head and neck radiation; risk for late effects appears to be reduced</entry></Row><Row><entry>Patient education</entry><entry>Patient education</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Immunotherapy and targeted cancer therapies</entry><entry>Document baseline oral mucosal status

</entry><entry>Assess number and severity of oral mucosal lesions clinically documented to be caused by immunotherapy/targeted therapy</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Monitor for possible late adverse oral effects</entry></Row><Row><entry>Patient education</entry><entry>Provide topical, intralesional, or systemic steroid treatment if oral pain is sufficiently severe</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Bone-stabilizing agents</entry><entry>Eliminate advanced dental caries that approaches the dental pulp</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Perform periodic systematic dental evaluations for compliance with oral hygiene and assessment of dentition, periodontium, and oral mucosa</entry><entry MoreRows="3">Perform periodic systematic dental evaluations for compliance with oral hygiene and assessment of dentition, periodontium, and oral mucosa
 
</entry></Row><Row><entry>Extract teeth with poor long-term prognosis due to periodontal disease and/or dental caries</entry></Row><Row><entry>Correct ill-fitting, removable dental prostheses that cause or could cause mucosal trauma and potential bone exposure</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Patient education</entry><entry MoreRows="1"/></Row><Row><entry/></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_937">Clinicians may consider many factors about oral interventions, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_938" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Patient’s immune status.</ListItem><ListItem>Pending time to initiation of cancer therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Intensity and duration of cancer therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_939">Many of the oral complications that develop in oncology patients are characterized by considerable biological and clinical complexity.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="31425594">Mougeot JC, Stevens CB, Morton DS, et al.: Oral Microbiome and Cancer Therapy-Induced Oral Mucositis. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="31425601">Lalla RV, Brennan MT, Gordon SM, et al.: Oral Mucositis Due to High-Dose Chemotherapy and/or Head and Neck Radiation Therapy. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="31425592">Keefe DMK, Bateman EH: Potential Successes and Challenges of Targeted Cancer Therapies. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="31425602">Carrozzo M, Eriksen JG, Bensadoun RJ, et al.: Oral Mucosal Injury Caused by Targeted Cancer Therapies. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31425595">Epstein JB, Miaskowski C: Oral Pain in the Cancer Patient. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="31425593">Fall-Dickson JM, Pavletic SZ, Mays JW, et al.: Oral Complications of Chronic Graft-Versus-Host Disease. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="31425591">Deng J, Wulff-Burchfield EM, Murphy BA: Late Soft Tissue Complications of Head and Neck Cancer Therapy: Lymphedema and Fibrosis. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="31425597">Murphy BA, Wulff-Burchfield E, Ghiam M, et al.: Chronic Systemic Symptoms in Head and Neck Cancer Patients. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="31425599">Spijkervet FKL, Brennan MT, Peterson DE, et al.: Research Frontiers in Oral Toxicities of Cancer Therapies: Osteoradionecrosis of the Jaws. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="31425600">Jensen SB, Vissink A, Limesand KH, et al.: Salivary Gland Hypofunction and Xerostomia in Head and Neck Radiation Patients. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="31425596">Migliorati CA, Brennan MT, Peterson DE: Medication-Related Osteonecrosis of the Jaws. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="31425598">Elting LS, Chang YC: Costs of Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies: Estimates and a Blueprint for Future Study. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_886"><Title>Oral Management of Patients Receiving Chemotherapy</Title><SummarySection id="_940"><Title>Before Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_941">Oral evaluation and management of patients scheduled to undergo myeloablative
chemotherapy should occur as early as possible before initiation of
therapy (see the list in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_942" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Oral Disease Stabilization Before Chemotherapy and/or Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant [HSCT]</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1424" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>).  The overall goal is to complete a comprehensive oral care plan that eliminates or stabilizes oral disease that could otherwise produce complications during or after chemotherapy. To maximize positive outcomes, the oncology team should inform the dentist about the patient’s medical status and oncology treatment
plan.  In turn, the dental team should delineate and communicate a plan for oral disease management before, during, and after  chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_942" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Oral Disease Stabilization Before Chemotherapy and/or Hematopoietic
          Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT)</ListTitle><ListItem>Data provided by the oncology team to dental providers includes the following:<ItemizedList id="_943" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Underlying disease:<ItemizedList id="_944" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Cancer type, stage, and prognosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Hematologic status and metabolic panel.</ListItem><ListItem>Additional data based on clinical status.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Type of chemotherapy:<ItemizedList id="_945" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>High/moderate/low dose (without HSCT).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Type of transplant:<ItemizedList id="_1330" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Autologous.</ListItem><ListItem>Allogeneic donor types:<ItemizedList id="_1331" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Matched related and unrelated.</ListItem><ListItem>Mismatched related.</ListItem><ListItem>Mismatched unrelated.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Syngeneic.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Hematopoietic stem cell source:<ItemizedList id="_1332" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Bone marrow.</ListItem><ListItem>Peripheral stem cells.</ListItem><ListItem>Cord blood stem cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Conditioning regimen:<ItemizedList id="_1333" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Myeloablative.</ListItem><ListItem>Reduced-intensity conditioning (including nonmyeloablative regimens).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Planned date of transplant.</ListItem><ListItem>Conditioning regimen:<ItemizedList id="_1334" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Total-body irradiation.</ListItem><ListItem>Radioactive antibodies.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Current hematologic and immunologic status.

</ListItem><ListItem>Current medications.</ListItem><ListItem>Other medical considerations:<ItemizedList id="_1335" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Cardiac disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Pulmonary disease.</ListItem><ListItem>
  Indwelling venous access line.</ListItem><ListItem>Coagulation status.</ListItem><ListItem>Splenectomy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem><ListItem>Data provided by dental 
                           providers to the oncology team includes the following: <ItemizedList id="_954" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Dental caries (number of teeth and severity, including number of teeth that should be treated before cancer treatment begins).</ListItem><ListItem>Endodontic disease:<ItemizedList id="_955" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Teeth with pulpal infection.</ListItem><ListItem>Teeth with periapical infection.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Periodontal disease status.</ListItem><ListItem>Number of teeth requiring
                                              extraction, as well as anticipated degree of surgical complexity.

                                       </ListItem><ListItem>Other urgent care required.</ListItem><ListItem>Time necessary to complete
                                  stabilization of oral disease.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_960">The three categories of dental evaluation and treatment protocols before cancer therapy include the following:<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><OrderedList id="_961" Style="LRoman"><ListItem>Complete protocols:<ItemizedList id="_962" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>All dental pathologies are treated before antineoplastic chemotherapy and HSCT are initiated.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Partial protocols: <ItemizedList id="_963" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Teeth with apical periodontitis are managed only if they are symptomatic and if size of the periapical lesion is 5 mm or more.</ListItem><ListItem>Teeth are extracted only if they have severe periodontitis (probing depth of ≥8 mm) and/or Miller's Class III mobility, they are expected to exfoliate within a few weeks, or if partially erupted third molars are symptomatic and with purulence.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Minimal protocols:<ItemizedList id="_964" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Patients are treated only if they are symptomatic.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_965">Partial dental evaluation/treatment protocols may be appropriate when there is insufficient time for complete dental evaluation/treatment protocols.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_966">Periodontal therapy before and maintenance after cancer therapy (both head and neck radiation and antineoplastic chemotherapy) are  suggested for general good oral health.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_968"><Title>During Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_969">Oral complications during chemotherapy are common. Dentists play an important role on the cancer treatment team by evaluating patients before chemotherapy, with the goal of optimizing their oral health status, minimizing complications, and educating patients to maintain optimal oral hygiene. Routine, systematic oral hygiene is important to reduce incidence and severity of oral sequelae of cancer therapy. The patient must be informed of the rationale for the oral hygiene program, as well as the potential side effects of cancer chemotherapy. Effective oral hygiene is important during cancer treatment, with an emphasis on oral hygiene management before treatment starts.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_970">Management of patients undergoing either high-dose chemotherapy or upper-mantle radiation share selected common principles. These principles are based on baseline oral care and reduction of physical trauma to oral mucosa (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1420" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Guidelines for the Management of Dentures and Orthodontic Appliances in Patients Receiving High-Dose Cancer Therapy</SummaryRef>).</Para><Para id="_984">Variation exists across institutions relative to specific nonmedicated approaches to baseline oral care, given limited published evidence. Most nonmedicated oral care protocols use topical, frequent (every 4–6 hours) rinsing with 0.9% saline. Additional interventions include dental brushing with toothpaste, dental flossing, ice chips, and sodium bicarbonate rinses. Patient compliance with these agents can be maximized  with monitoring by the health care team.<Reference refidx="1"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_1420" Style="simple"><ListTitle>Guidelines for the Management of Dentures and Orthodontic Appliances in Patients Receiving High-Dose Cancer Therapy</ListTitle><ListItem>Minimize denture use during first 3 weeks posttransplant.<Reference refidx="4"/><ItemizedList id="_1421" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Wear dentures only when eating.</ListItem><ListItem>Discontinue use at all other times.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Clean twice a day with a soft brush and rinse well.</ListItem><ListItem>Soak in antimicrobial solutions when not being worn. 
</ListItem><ListItem>Perform routine oral mucosal care procedures 3 to 4 times a day with the oral appliances out of the mouth.</ListItem><ListItem>Leave appliances out of the mouth when sleeping and during periods of significant
mouth soreness.</ListItem><ListItem>Dentures may be used to hold  medications needed for oral care (e.g.,
antifungals).</ListItem><ListItem>Discontinue use of removable appliances until oral mucositis has healed.</ListItem><ListItem>Remove orthodontic appliances (e.g., brackets, wires, retainers) before conditioning.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_986">Dental brushing and flossing are simple, cost-effective approaches to
control of bacterial dental plaque.  This strategy is designed to reduce the risk of
oral soft tissue infection during myeloablation.  For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_901" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Infection</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_990">Patients skilled at flossing without traumatizing gingival tissues may continue
to floss throughout chemotherapy administration.  Flossing allows for
interproximal removal of dental bacterial plaque and promotes gingival
health.</Para><Para id="_991">The oral cavity should be cleaned after meals, as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_992" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>If dry mouth is present,
plaque and food debris may accumulate secondary to reduced salivary function,
and more frequent hygiene may be necessary.</ListItem><ListItem>Dentures need to be cleaned with
denture cleanser every day and brushed and rinsed after meals.</ListItem><ListItem>Rinsing the oral cavity may not be sufficient for thorough cleansing of the
oral tissues; mechanical plaque removal is often necessary.</ListItem><ListItem>Care must be
taken in using  mechanical hygiene aids; dental floss, interproximal brushes, and wooden wedges
can injure oral tissues rendered fragile by chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Toothettes have
limited ability to cleanse the dentition; however, they may be useful for
cleaning maxillary/mandibular alveolar ridges of edentulous areas, palate, and
tongue.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_993">Preventing dry lips  to reduce the risk of tissue injury is important.  Mouth breathing and/or xerostomia secondary to anticholinergic
medications used for nausea management can induce the condition. Graft-versus-host disease can also contribute to dry lips in allogeneic transplant patients.  Lip care
products containing petroleum-based oils and waxes can be useful. 
Lanolin-based creams and ointments may be more effective in
moisturizing/lubricating the lips and protecting against trauma.</Para><SummarySection id="_994"><Title>Oral mucositis (high-dose chemotherapy, HSCT, head and  neck radiation)</Title><Para id="_995">Oral mucositis is one of the most common side effects of cytotoxic cancer regimens. The terms <Emphasis>oral mucositis</Emphasis> and <Emphasis>stomatitis</Emphasis> are often used interchangeably at
the clinical level, but they do not reflect identical processes.</Para><ItemizedList id="_996" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Oral Mucositis:</ListTitle><ListItem>Inflammation of oral mucosa resulting from chemotherapeutic agents or
ionizing radiation.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem>Manifests as erythema or ulcerations.</ListItem><ListItem>May be exacerbated by local factors.</ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_997" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Stomatitis:</ListTitle><ListItem>Any inflammatory
condition of oral tissue, including mucosa, dentition/periapices, and
periodontium.</ListItem><ListItem>Includes infections of oral tissues as well as
mucositis.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_998">The current model of oral mucositis involves a complex five-step trajectory of molecular, cellular, and tissue-based changes involving the oral microbiome.<Reference refidx="7"/> <Reference refidx="5"/> </Para><Para id="_999">Patients receiving cycled chemotherapy or conditioning regimens before HSCT develop the first signs of mucositis 3 to 4 days after infusion. Oral ulcer formation begins during the second week of treatment—with the highest severity between days 7 and 14—and then resolves spontaneously in the week after cessation of cytotoxic chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="8"/> Clinicians need to be alert to the potential for increased toxicity with escalating dose or treatment duration in clinical trials that demonstrate gastrointestinal mucosal toxicity.</Para><Para id="_1347">Several health professional organizations have produced evidence-based guidelines for oral mucositis, including the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1348" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer/International Society of Oral Oncology (MASCC/ISOO).<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>National Comprehensive Cancer Network.<Reference refidx="12"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Cochrane Collaboration.<Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1349">Many recommendations are similar across the organizations. The Cochrane Collaboration, however, uses a meta-analysis approach that provides a unique context for purposes of guideline construction.</Para><SummarySection id="_1002"><Title>Management  of oral mucositis</Title><Para id="_1013">Oral care protocols include atraumatically cleansing the oral mucosa, maintaining lubrication of the lips and oral tissues, and relieving pain and inflammation. Oral mucositis is minimized with the use of mild-flavored fluoridated toothpaste. Avoidance of spicy, acidic, hard, and hot foods and beverages will also decrease oral mucositis.</Para><Para id="_1350">Management of oral mucositis via topical approaches
should address efficacy, patient acceptance, and appropriate dosing.  A
stepped approach is typically used, with progression from one level to
the next.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1351" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Bland rinses:<ItemizedList id="_1352" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>0.9% saline solution.</ListItem><ListItem>Sodium bicarbonate solution.</ListItem><ListItem>0.9% saline/sodium bicarbonate solution.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Topical anesthetics:<ItemizedList id="_1353" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Lidocaine:  viscous, ointments, sprays.</ListItem><ListItem>Benzocaine:  sprays, gels.</ListItem><ListItem>0.5% or 1.0% dyclonine hydrochloride (HCl).</ListItem><ListItem>Diphenhydramine solution.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Mucosal coating agents:<ItemizedList id="_1354" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Amphojel.</ListItem><ListItem>Kaopectate.</ListItem><ListItem>Hydroxypropyl methylcellulose film-forming agents (e.g., Zilactin).</ListItem><ListItem>Gelclair (approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration as a device).</ListItem><ListItem>Caphosol.</ListItem><ListItem>Episil.</ListItem><ListItem>MuGard.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Analgesics:<ItemizedList id="_1355" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Opioid drugs: oral, intravenous (e.g., bolus, continuous infusion, patient-controlled analgesia), patches, transmucosal. Morphine may be used to treat pain caused by oral mucositis in patients undergoing HSCT. Morphine mouthwash (0.2%) may be used in patients receiving chemoradiation for head and neck cancer. Transdermal fentanyl may be given to patients receiving conventional or high-dose chemotherapy, with or without total body irradiation.<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Growth factor (keratinocyte growth factor-1):<ItemizedList id="_1356" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Palifermin for patients receiving high-dose chemotherapy and total body irradiation, followed by autologous stem cell transplant, for a hematological malignancy.<Reference refidx="15"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Cryotherapy in patients receiving bolus fluorouracil chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem><ListItem>Low-level laser therapy to prevent oral mucositis in patients receiving HSCT conditioned with high-dose chemotherapy, with or without total body irradiation.<Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Zinc supplements administered orally in oral cancer patients receiving radiation therapy or chemoradiation.<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1025">A soft toothbrush that is replaced regularly should be used to maintain oral hygiene.<Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>] Foam-swab brushes
do not effectively clean teeth and should not be considered a routine
substitute for a soft, nylon-bristled toothbrush. Additionally, the rough sponge surface may irritate and damage the mucosal surfaces opposite the tooth surfaces being brushed.</Para><Para id="_1031">Irrigation should be performed before topical medication is applied because removal of
debris and saliva allows for better coating of oral tissues and prevents
material from accumulating.  Frequent rinsing cleans and lubricates tissues,
prevents crusting, and palliates painful gingiva and mucosa. </Para><Para id="_1032">Systemic analgesics are administered when topical anesthetic strategies
are not sufficient for clinical relief.  Nonsteroidal
anti-inflammatory drugs that affect platelet adhesion and damage gastric mucosa
are contraindicated, especially if thrombocytopenia is present.</Para><Para id="_1339">MASCC/ISOO recommendations against specific practices include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1340" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>No PTA (polymyxin, tobramycin, amphotericin B) and BCoG (bacitracin, clotrimazole, gentamicin) for oral mucositis in patients receiving radiation therapy for head and neck cancer.<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>No iseganan antimicrobial mouthwash.<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>No sucralfate mouthwash.<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>No intravenous glutamine.<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Table id="_1425"><Title>Table 2.  Oral Mucositis Scales</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Grade</entry><entry>World Health Organization</entry><entry>National Cancer Institute<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>RTOG</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">N/A = not applicable; RTOG = Radiation Therapy Oncology Group.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 5.<Reference refidx="20"/>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>0</entry><entry>No findings</entry><entry>No findings</entry><entry>No findings</entry></Row><Row><entry>1</entry><entry>Erythema and soreness</entry><entry>Asymptomatic or mild symptoms; intervention not indicated</entry><entry>Painless ulcers, erythema, or mild soreness</entry></Row><Row><entry>2</entry><entry>Oral erythema, ulcers; solid diet tolerated</entry><entry>Moderate pain does not interfere with oral intake, but modified diet indicated</entry><entry>Painful erythema, edema, or ulcers but can eat</entry></Row><Row><entry>3</entry><entry>Ulcers requiring liquid diet</entry><entry>Severe pain interfering with oral intake</entry><entry>Painful erythema, edema, or ulcers and cannot eat</entry></Row><Row><entry>4</entry><entry>Ulcers and not able to tolerate a solid or liquid diet</entry><entry>Life-threatening consequence; urgent intervention indicated</entry><entry>Requires parenteral or enteral support</entry></Row><Row><entry>5</entry><entry>N/A</entry><entry>Death</entry><entry>N/A</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1033"><Title>Xerostomia and salivary hypofunction caused by antiemetics</Title><Para id="_1034">Xerostomia is defined as the subjective feeling of oral dryness and can be accompanied by salivary gland hypofunction.  Xerostomia is likely to occur when the salivary ﬂow rate is less than the rate of ﬂuid absorption across the oral mucosa plus the rate of ﬂuid evaporation from the oral cavity.<Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>] (See <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1426" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Table 3</SummaryRef>.)</Para><Table id="_1426"><Title>Table 3.  Definitions of Xerostomia, Hyposalivation, and Salivary Gland Hypofunction and Dysfunction</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Term</entry><entry>Definition</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry>Xerostomia</entry><entry>Subjective feeling of oral dryness</entry></Row><Row><entry>Dry mouth</entry><entry>Xerostomia and/or salivary gland hypofunction  </entry></Row><Row><entry>Hyposalivation</entry><entry>Decreased salivary output (whole saliva ﬂow rate of ≤0.1 mL/min of unstimulated saliva and &lt;0.7 mL/min of stimulated saliva)</entry></Row><Row><entry>Salivary gland hypofunction</entry><entry>Decreased salivary output </entry></Row><Row><entry>Salivary gland dysfunction</entry><entry>Changes in quantity and/or quality of saliva</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1035">Administration of antiemetic agents for the management of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting is related to  several toxicities, including gastrointestinal, renal, hepatic, and cardiovascular adverse events.<Reference refidx="22"/> Some of these agents are reported to induce xerostomia or salivary gland hypofunction. (See <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1427" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Table 4</SummaryRef>.)</Para><Table id="_1427"><Title>Table 4.  Antiemetic Agents Associated With Xerostomia or Salivary Gland Hypofunction</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Pharmacological Class</entry><entry>Mechanism</entry><entry>Agents</entry><entry>References</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0">5-HT3 = 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor 3; GABA = gamma-aminobutyric acid; NK-1 = neurokinin-1.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">5-HT3 receptor antagonists</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Serotonin reuptake inhibitor<Reference refidx="22"/> </entry><entry>Granisetron</entry><entry><Reference refidx="23"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Ondansetron </entry><entry><Reference refidx="24"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Dopamine antagonists</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Blocks dopamine receptors</entry><entry>Prochlorperazine</entry><entry><Reference refidx="25"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Metoclopramide</entry><entry><Reference refidx="25"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Atypical antipsychotics</entry><entry>Antagonist to dopamine, 5-HT, histamine, muscarinics, and alpha-1 adrenergic receptors<Reference refidx="26"/></entry><entry>Olanzapine</entry><entry><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/>   <Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/> <Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry>Cannabinoids</entry><entry>Stimulates receptors within the endocannabinoid system</entry><entry>Nabilone</entry><entry><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Benzodiazepines</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Serotonin reuptake inhibitor, GABA agonist<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="26"/></entry><entry>Alprazolam</entry><entry><Reference refidx="42"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Lorazepam</entry><entry><Reference refidx="43"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>NK-1 receptor antagonists</entry><entry>Substance P binding inhibitor<Reference refidx="22"/></entry><entry>Rolapitant</entry><entry><Reference refidx="44"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1037">For information about  antiemetic therapy, and nausea and vomiting related to chemotherapy and radiation therapy, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062747" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nausea/nausea-hp-pdq">Nausea and Vomiting Related to Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1038"><Title>Oral and Dental Management After Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_1039">After cancer therapy, routine systematic oral hygiene is also important for reducing incidence and severity of oral sequelae, restoring functional and aesthetic impairments, and removing the remaining foci of infection.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Schubert MM, Correa MEP, Peterson DE: Oral complications of hematopoietic cell transplantation. In: Forman SJ, Negrin RS, Antin JH, et al., eds.: Thomas’ Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation: Stem Cell Transplantation. 5th ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, 2016, pp 1242-56.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="29910997">Decker AM, Taichman LS, D'Silva NJ, et al.: Periodontal Treatment in Cancer Patients: An Interdisciplinary Approach. Curr Oral Health Rep 5 (1): 7-12, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="28735355">Hong CHL, Hu S, Haverman T, et al.: A systematic review of dental disease management in cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 26 (1): 155-174, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="31286232">Hong CHL, Gueiros LA, Fulton JS, et al.: Systematic review of basic oral care for the management of oral mucositis in cancer patients and clinical practice guidelines. Support Care Cancer 27 (10): 3949-3967, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31286231">Bowen J, Al-Dasooqi N, Bossi P, et al.: The pathogenesis of mucositis: updated perspectives and emerging targets. Support Care Cancer 27 (10): 4023-4033, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="31425601">Lalla RV, Brennan MT, Gordon SM, et al.: Oral Mucositis Due to High-Dose Chemotherapy and/or Head and Neck Radiation Therapy. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="31425594">Mougeot JC, Stevens CB, Morton DS, et al.: Oral Microbiome and Cancer Therapy-Induced Oral Mucositis. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="23714511">Sonis ST: Oral mucositis in head and neck cancer: risk, biology, and management. Am Soc Clin Oncol Educ Book : , 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="31286226">Elad S: The MASCC/ISOO Mucositis Guidelines 2019 Update: introduction to the first set of articles. Support Care Cancer 27 (10): 3929-3931, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="32052136">Elad S: The MASCC/ISOO mucositis guidelines 2019: the second set of articles and future directions. Support Care Cancer 28 (5): 2445-2447, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="24615748">Lalla RV, Bowen J, Barasch A, et al.: MASCC/ISOO clinical practice guidelines for the management of mucositis secondary to cancer therapy. Cancer 120 (10): 1453-61, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="18289497">Bensinger W, Schubert M, Ang KK, et al.: NCCN Task Force Report. prevention and management of mucositis in cancer care. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 6 (Suppl 1): S1-21; quiz S22-4, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29181845">Riley P, Glenny AM, Worthington HV, et al.: Interventions for preventing oral mucositis in patients with cancer receiving treatment: cytokines and growth factors. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 11: CD011990, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="23832272">Saunders DP, Epstein JB, Elad S, et al.: Systematic review of antimicrobials, mucosal coating agents, anesthetics, and analgesics for the management of oral mucositis in cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 21 (11): 3191-207, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="32080767">Logan RM, Al-Azri AR, Bossi P, et al.: Systematic review of growth factors and cytokines for the management of oral mucositis in cancer patients and clinical practice guidelines. Support Care Cancer 28 (5): 2485-2498, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="26695736">Riley P, Glenny AM, Worthington HV, et al.: Interventions for preventing oral mucositis in patients with cancer receiving treatment: oral cryotherapy. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2015 (12): CD011552, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="31286228">Zadik Y, Arany PR, Fregnani ER, et al.: Systematic review of photobiomodulation for the management of oral mucositis in cancer patients and clinical practice guidelines. Support Care Cancer 27 (10): 3969-3983, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="31286229">Yarom N, Hovan A, Bossi P, et al.: Systematic review of natural and miscellaneous agents for the management of oral mucositis in cancer patients and clinical practice guidelines-part 1: vitamins, minerals, and nutritional supplements. Support Care Cancer 27 (10): 3997-4010, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="17236223">Keefe DM, Schubert MM, Elting LS, et al.: Updated clinical practice guidelines for the prevention and treatment of mucositis. Cancer 109 (5): 820-31, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="20">National Cancer Institute: Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 5.0. Bethesda, Md: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, National Institutes of Health, 2017. <ExternalRef xref="https://ctep.cancer.gov/protocolDevelopment/electronic_applications/docs/CTCAE_v5_Quick_Reference_8.5x11.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed Dec. 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="26602059">Villa A, Wolff A, Narayana N, et al.: World Workshop on Oral Medicine VI: a systematic review of medication-induced salivary gland dysfunction. Oral Dis 22 (5): 365-82, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="28978206">Adel N: Overview of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting and evidence-based therapies. Am J Manag Care 23 (14 Suppl): S259-S265, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="15838618">Moreno J, Sahade M, del Giglio A: Low-dose granisetron for prophylaxis of acute chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting: a pilot study. Support Care Cancer 13 (10): 850-3, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="24807340">Abas MN, Tan PC, Azmi N, et al.: Ondansetron compared with metoclopramide for hyperemesis gravidarum: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol 123 (6): 1272-1279, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="1409258">Zuccato E, Bertolo C, Salomoni M, et al.: The effects of S(-) and R(+) sulpiride, metoclopramide, cisapride and domperidone on the small intestine suggest DA2-receptors are involved in the control of small intestinal transit time in rats. Pharmacol Res 26 (2): 179-85, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="27853957">Wolff A, Joshi RK, Ekström J, et al.: A Guide to Medications Inducing Salivary Gland Dysfunction, Xerostomia, and Subjective Sialorrhea: A Systematic Review Sponsored by the World Workshop on Oral Medicine VI. Drugs R D 17 (1): 1-28, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="22458406">Godoy T, Riva A, Ekström J: Atypical antipsychotics--effects of amisulpride on salivary secretion and on clozapine-induced sialorrhea. Oral Dis 18 (7): 680-91, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="23731177">Ekström J, Godoy T, Loy F, et al.: Parasympathetic vasoactive intestinal peptide (VIP): a likely contributor to clozapine-induced sialorrhoea. Oral Dis 20 (3): e90-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="11163780">Tollefson GD, Birkett MA, Kiesler GM, et al.: Double-blind comparison of olanzapine versus clozapine in schizophrenic patients clinically eligible for treatment with clozapine. Biol Psychiatry 49 (1): 52-63, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="18439263">Johnsen E, Jørgensen HA: Effectiveness of second generation antipsychotics: a systematic review of randomized trials. BMC Psychiatry 8: 31, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="20664822">Kumar A, Gupta M, Jiloha RC, et al.: Efficacy of olanzapine and sodium valproate given alone or as add-on therapy in acute mania. A comparative study. Methods Find Exp Clin Pharmacol 32 (5): 319-24, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="19832806">McIntyre RS, Cohen M, Zhao J, et al.: Asenapine versus olanzapine in acute mania: a double-blind extension study. Bipolar Disord 11 (8): 815-26, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="15147609">Bridle C, Palmer S, Bagnall AM, et al.: A rapid and systematic review and economic evaluation of the clinical and cost-effectiveness of newer drugs for treatment of mania associated with bipolar affective disorder. Health Technol Assess 8 (19): iii-iv, 1-187, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="11379844">Budman CL, Gayer A, Lesser M, et al.: An open-label study of the treatment efficacy of olanzapine for Tourette's disorder. J Clin Psychiatry 62 (4): 290-4, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="10811240">Conley RR, Meltzer HY: Adverse events related to olanzapine. J Clin Psychiatry 61 (Suppl 8): 26-9; discussion 30, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="9028746">Fulton B, Goa KL: Olanzapine. A review of its pharmacological properties and therapeutic efficacy in the management of schizophrenia and related psychoses. Drugs 53 (2): 281-98, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="21047395">Stauffer VL, Sniadecki JL, Piezer KW, et al.: Impact of race on efficacy and safety during treatment with olanzapine in schizophrenia, schizophreniform or schizoaffective disorder. BMC Psychiatry 10: 89, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="38">Jain T, Bhandari A, Ram V: Drug interactions and adverse drug reactions in hospitalized psychiatric patients: A critical element in providing safe medication use. German Journal of Psychiatry, 14: 26-34, 2011. <ExternalRef xref="https://web.archive.org/web/20180409223706id_/http://www.gjpsy.uni-goettingen.de/gjp-article-jain2.pdf">Also available online</ExternalRef>.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="16533193">Berlach DM, Shir Y, Ware MA: Experience with the synthetic cannabinoid nabilone in chronic noncancer pain. Pain Med 7 (1): 25-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="17974490">Skrabek RQ, Galimova L, Ethans K, et al.: Nabilone for the treatment of pain in fibromyalgia. J Pain 9 (2): 164-73, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="20007734">Ware MA, Fitzcharles MA, Joseph L, et al.: The effects of nabilone on sleep in fibromyalgia: results of a randomized controlled trial. Anesth Analg 110 (2): 604-10, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="3340287">Huber SJ, Paulson GW: Efficacy of alprazolam for essential tremor. Neurology 38 (2): 241-3, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="9448744">Yamagishi H, Kawaguchi M: Characterization of central- and peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptors in rat salivary glands. Biochem Pharmacol 55 (2): 209-14, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="29905976">Wang X, Zhang ZY, Wang J, et al.: Pharmacokinetics, Safety, and Tolerability of Rolapitant Administered Intravenously Following Single Ascending and Multiple Ascending Doses in Healthy Subjects. Clin Pharmacol Drug Dev 8 (2): 160-171, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_889"><Title>Oral Management of Patients Receiving Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</Title><Para id="_1270">Hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) is a complex immune-based cellular therapy used to manage a wide range of malignant and nonmalignant conditions, including the following:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_1040" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Blood cancers.</ListItem><ListItem>Childhood immunodeficiency and metabolic disorders.</ListItem><ListItem>Hemoglobinopathies.</ListItem><ListItem>Autoimmune diseases.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_891">Autologous transplant uses an individual’s own isolated hematopoietic cells as a “graft” to reconstitute bone marrow function after an intensive chemotherapy regimen that would otherwise cause irreversible marrow toxicity. While recipients of autologous HSCT are at risk of anticipated toxicities of high-dose chemotherapy (e.g., neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, mucositis, and nausea and vomiting), they are not at risk of developing the immune-related complications frequently associated with allogeneic HSCT. Allogeneic HSCT similarly functions by engraftment and restoration of bone marrow function, but in the case of hematologic malignancies the graft also provides a graft-versus-tumor sustained immunological response. This response is important for maintaining long-term remission but is also associated with development of graft-versus-host disease (GVHD).</Para><Para id="_1042">Recipients of HSCT have unique oral health needs and considerations that span from pre-HSCT workup through survivorship.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> Management requires coordinated multidisciplinary care. See <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1424" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef> for management before, during, and after HSCT.</Para><SummarySection id="_1043"><Title>Pretransplant Dental Evaluation</Title><Para id="_1044">Patients undergoing HSCT experience long-term myelosuppression and immunosuppression. The oral cavity may be a potential source of local as well as systemic inflammation and infection. To reduce risk, patients should undergo a comprehensive dental evaluation by an experienced dentist before undergoing  HSCT.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_1045">The dental evaluation consists of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1343" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>A thorough dental screening (caries, defective restorations, mobile teeth, teeth with deep pocketing, third molars, periapical pathology).</ListItem><ListItem>A soft tissue examination.</ListItem><ListItem>A full mouth series of intraoral radiographs (an orthopantomogram of the maxilla and mandible may be sufficient, and additional intraoral radiographs may be ordered, if necessary). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1047">For children, oral care instructions and dental management are similar to those for adults.<Reference refidx="3"/> When primary teeth with pulpal infection are involved, many clinicians choose to provide a more definitive treatment in the form of extraction. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_928" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Special Considerations in Pediatric Populations</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_1049">A dental evaluation is scheduled as early as possible to allow sufficient time to complete any necessary treatment and for tissues to heal after dental extractions and professional periodontal care. Patients who are thrombocytopenic and require invasive procedures, such as dental extractions, may require coordinated platelet transfusion support.</Para><Table id="_1431"><Title>Table 5.  Pretransplant Dental Evaluation</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Finding</entry><entry>Management</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry>Dental caries</entry><entry>Treat caries, provide endodontic therapy, or extract nonvital/abscessed teeth</entry></Row><Row><entry>Faulty or missing restorations</entry><entry>Replace restoration, eliminate sharp edges</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Periapical pathology</entry><entry>Pulpitis: Provide endodontic treatment</entry></Row><Row><entry>Periapical periodontitis &gt;5 mm: Provide endodontic therapy or extraction</entry></Row><Row><entry>No treatment necessary for previously endodontically treated teeth with persistent periapical pathology without evidence of infection</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Periodontal disease</entry><entry>Perform scaling and root planing</entry></Row><Row><entry>Extract symptomatic teeth, teeth with advanced mobility, teeth with probings &gt;8 mm</entry></Row><Row><entry>Pericoronitis</entry><entry>Extract associated third molar</entry></Row><Row><entry>Prosthetic treatment</entry><entry>Ensure adequate fit and function</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1050"><Title>Oral Care During Transplant</Title><Para id="_1051">Maintenance of good oral hygiene is essential to reduce the risk of infection.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Gingival inflammation caused by oral bacteria increases the risk of gingival bleeding and bacteremia. Oral hygiene aims to remove plaque from all surfaces of the teeth. A dental/oral self-examination should be performed daily. Patients need to brush their teeth two to three times a day to reduce dental plaque, using a soft manual or electric toothbrush and a fluoride toothpaste. If possible, the patient’s teeth should be gently flossed daily. Removable dental prostheses are cleaned in a similar manner as teeth. Dentures are then placed in a cleaning solution overnight.</Para><Para id="_1052">Bland oral rinses (0.9% saline and/or 0.5% sodium bicarbonate solution) can help remove debris and maintain moist and healthy mucosa, but they are not a substitute for mechanical cleaning. Chlorhexidine rinses are often prescribed for the duration of neutropenia. The nonalcoholic chlorhexidine digluconate (0.12%–0.2%) solution is easier to tolerate for patients with sensitive oral mucosa.</Para><SummarySection id="_1055"><Title>Mucositis</Title><Para id="_1056">Oral mucositis is one of the most debilitating toxicities of stem cell transplant and requires a multidisciplinary approach.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_994" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Oral mucositis (high-dose chemotherapy, HSCT, head and  neck radiation)</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1062"><Title>Oral infections</Title><Para id="_1063">Infections are a frequent complication of HSCT during neutropenic periods. Infections may be fungal, viral, or bacterial. Coexistent oral conditions such as oral mucositis and GVHD often complicate prompt diagnosis of infections. For more information, see the  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_901" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Infection</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1064"><Title>Other common noninfectious oral findings</Title><Para id="_1065">Hairy tongue is characterized by marked accumulation of keratin on the dorsum of the tongue, resulting in a hair-like appearance. This occurs largely because of limited oral intake, soft/liquid diet, and xerostomia. Similar hyperkeratosis (although not hair-like) may be observed on the hard palate and gingiva. Thrombocytopenia predisposes the oral mucosa to development of asymptomatic petechiae and ecchymoses and sometimes hematomas. The lesions may appear at the buccal mucosa, lateral tongue, and soft palate, secondary to chewing and swallowing, and resolve with the restoration of platelet count.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1066"><Title>Oral Health After Transplant</Title><SummarySection id="_1067"><Title>Mouth care and dental care</Title><Para id="_1068">Following hospital discharge after HSCT, patients are instructed to continue daily routine mouth care and see a dentist for a routine follow-up examination and dental prophylaxis approximately 6 months after a HSCT and every 6 months thereafter.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1069"><Title>GVHD</Title><Para id="_1070">GVHD can be broadly classified as acute or chronic, with defining features being largely clinical rather than by time frame of onset.<Reference refidx="9"/> (See <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1429" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Table 6</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Table 7</SummaryRef>.)</Para><Table id="_1429"><Title>Table 6.  Graft-Versus-Host Disease Classification</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Category (Acute and Chronic)</entry><entry>Timing of Onset After HSCT or DLI</entry><entry>Presence of Acute GVHD Features</entry><entry>Presence of Chronic GVHD Features</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0">DLI = donor lymphocyte infusion; GVHD = graft-versus-host disease; HSCT = hematopoietic stem cell transplant.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Classic acute GVHD</entry><entry>≤100 days</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>No</entry></Row><Row><entry>Late-onset acute GVHD</entry><entry>&gt;100 days</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>No</entry></Row><Row><entry>Classic chronic GVHD</entry><entry>No time limit</entry><entry>No</entry><entry>Yes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Overlap syndrome</entry><entry>No time limit</entry><entry>Yes</entry><entry>Yes</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_1430"><Title>Table 7.  Clinical Features of Graft-Versus-Host Disease (GVHD)</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>System/Organ</entry><entry>Acute GVHD</entry><entry>Chronic GVHD</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry>Eyes</entry><entry/><entry>Xerophthalmia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Mouth</entry><entry>Mucositis (nonspecific erythema multiforme–like), lip crusting</entry><entry>Lichen planus-like changes, xerostomia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Skin</entry><entry>Maculopapular rash, erythroderma with or without bulla</entry><entry>Poikiloderma, lichen planus-like changes, scleroderma, nail dystrophy</entry></Row><Row><entry>Gastrointestinal</entry><entry>Nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, anorexia</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Liver</entry><entry>Elevated bilirubin levels</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Lung</entry><entry/><entry>Bronchiolitis obliterans</entry></Row><Row><entry>Genital</entry><entry/><entry>Lichen planus-like changes</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_1071"><Title>Acute GVHD</Title><Para id="_1072">Acute GVHD typically occurs within the first 100 days and classically presents with skin, liver, and gastrointestinal tract involvement. Infrequently, the mouth can be affected, presenting with erythema multiforme-like features, including lip crusting and diffuse intraoral erythema and ulcerations.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1073"><Title>Chronic GVHD</Title><Para id="_1074">Chronic GVHD, which affects 50% to 80% of allogeneic HSCT recipients, is an autoimmune-like condition characterized by chronic inflammation, fibrosis, disability, and diminished quality of life.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="11"/> The oral cavity is commonly affected and is often the initial site of involvement. GVHD can persist in the oral cavity after it has resolved in other affected areas.</Para><SummarySection id="_1075"><Title>Clinical features of oral chronic GVHD</Title><Para id="_1076">Oral mucosal involvement resembles oral lichen planus, with characteristic lacy white striations, erythema, and ulcerations.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> Lesions can present on all oral mucosal surfaces but most frequently affect the buccal mucosa and tongue. Lip involvement can also be prominent, ranging from hyperkeratosis and dryness to extensive ulceration. Superficial mucoceles—characterized by small, transient, clear-fluid–filled vesicles—are particularly common on the palate, which has a high concentration of minor salivary gland tissue. While oral mucosal chronic GVHD can be painful at rest, the most common symptom is <Strong>sensitivity,</Strong> defined as oral discomfort with stimulation, typically with acidic, spicy, or strongly flavored items (e.g., mint, chocolate), as well as hard and crusty foods. </Para><Para id="_1077">Chronic GVHD affecting the salivary glands resembles Sjögren syndrome, and affected patients frequently have concurrent involvement of the lacrimal glands and associated ocular chronic GVHD. In addition to experiencing symptoms of xerostomia, patients are at increased risk of developing dental caries and recurrent oral candidiasis. Oral mucosal sensitivity, even in the absence of mucosal lichenoid changes, is common.</Para><Para id="_1078">Sclerodermatous chronic GVHD affecting the oral cavity is uncommon but can be debilitating. Patients with cutaneous, sclerodermatous chronic GVHD may have extension to the perioral tissues, leading to limited mouth opening, as seen in patients with progressive systemic sclerosis. Intraoral fibrosis can also occur, typically in patients with long-standing oral mucosal chronic GVHD. This condition presents with tight bands in the buccal mucosa. In addition to experiencing pain and disability, patients can have difficulty maintaining oral hygiene, and provision of dental care can be challenging.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1079"><Title>Diagnosis and management of oral chronic GVHD</Title><Para id="_1080">The presence of lacy white changes in the oral cavity is diagnostic for chronic GVHD, according to  the National Institutes of Health Consensus.<Reference refidx="11"/> Biopsy is rarely necessary for diagnosis. Ancillary management  of oral mucosal chronic GVHD includes topical steroids and topical tacrolimus. Patients often avoid bothersome foods and drinks.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Table id="_1432"><Title>Table 8.  Management of Oral Chronic Graft-Versus-Host Disease<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Oral Complications</entry><entry>Management Considerations</entry><entry>Long-Term Follow-Up Considerations</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Rizzo et al.<Reference refidx="13"/> and Carpenter et al.2014,<Reference refidx="12"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Mucosal lichenoid changes</entry><entry>Topical corticosteroids</entry><entry MoreRows="5">Increased risk of oral squamous cell carcinoma; cancer screening</entry></Row><Row><entry>Intralesional corticosteroid therapy</entry></Row><Row><entry>Topical tacrolimus</entry></Row><Row><entry>Topical analgesics</entry></Row><Row><entry>Children’s toothpaste</entry></Row><Row><entry>Avoidance of spicy, acidic, and hard/crunchy foods and drinks</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Salivary gland hypofunction</entry><entry>Topical fluoride</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Dental follow-up at least annually (risk of dental caries); monitoring of tooth development in children</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sialogogue therapy</entry></Row><Row><entry>Over-the-counter dry mouth products</entry><entry MoreRows="4"/></Row><Row><entry>Sugar-free gum/candy</entry></Row><Row><entry>Education regarding preventive practices</entry></Row><Row><entry>Management of recurrent candidiasis</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sclerodermatous chronic graft-versus-host disease</entry><entry>Physical therapy</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1357"><Title>Other associated lesions </Title><Para id="_1358">A wide range of oral mucosal lesions frequently arises in the context of chronic GVHD. These lesions include both benign (infectious and noninfectious) and malignant conditions.</Para><SummarySection id="_1359"><Title>Benign lesions</Title><Para id="_1361">Herpes simplex virus and oral candidiasis can occur in the context of oral chronic GVHD owing to several factors, including generalized immunosuppression, salivary gland hypofunction, and the use of topical steroids. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_901" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Infection</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1365"><Title>Malignant lesions</Title><Para id="_1366">Recipients of allogeneic HSCT are at increased risk of various cancers. Posttransplant lymphoproliferative disease can present with oral features similar to those seen in other presentations of lymphoma (mass, ulceration), typically in the early posttransplant period. Patients with chronic GVHD are at increased risk of developing oral squamous cell carcinoma, with this risk increasing with time since HSCT. Cancerous and precancerous oral lesions can be difficult to distinguish from those of chronic GVHD.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1091"><Title>Long-term follow-up</Title><Para id="_1092">Recipients of HSCT (in particular, allogeneic HSCT) are encouraged to maintain good oral health and receive long-term oral health care.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="13"/> Patients are instructed to brush and floss daily, and to visit a dentist at least every 6 months. Patients with GVHD and salivary hypofunction are at risk of developing dental caries and experiencing tooth loss. Children, especially those who were younger than 6 years  at HSCT, are at risk of developmental abnormalities affecting the skeleton and teeth. There is a significantly increased risk of oral squamous cell carcinoma in allogeneic HSCT recipients, especially in those with a history of oral chronic GVHD.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><Table id="_1428"><Title>Table 9.  Diseases Commonly Treated With Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Indications</entry><entry>Autologous Transplant</entry><entry>Allogeneic Transplant</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Copelan et al.<Reference refidx="14"/>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="8">Malignant indications </entry><entry>Multiple myeloma</entry><entry>Acute myeloid leukemia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Non-Hodgkin lymphoma</entry><entry>Acute lymphoblastic leukemia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Hodgkin disease</entry><entry>Chronic myeloid leukemia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Neuroblastoma</entry><entry>Myelodysplastic syndromes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Ovarian cancer</entry><entry>Myeloproliferative disorders</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Germ cell tumors</entry><entry>Non-Hodgkin lymphoma</entry></Row><Row><entry>Hodgkin disease</entry></Row><Row><entry>Chronic lymphocytic leukemia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Multiple myeloma</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="8">Nonmalignant indications</entry><entry>Autoimmune diseases</entry><entry>Aplastic anemia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Amyloidosis</entry><entry>Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="6"/><entry>Fanconi anemia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Diamond-Blackfan anemia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Thalassemia major</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sickle cell anemia</entry></Row><Row><entry>Severe combined immunodeficiency</entry></Row><Row><entry>Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome</entry></Row><Row><entry>Inborn errors of metabolism</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26256941">Majhail NS, Farnia SH, Carpenter PA, et al.: Indications for Autologous and Allogeneic Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation: Guidelines from the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 21 (11): 1863-1869, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25189149">Elad S, Raber-Durlacher JE, Brennan MT, et al.: Basic oral care for hematology-oncology patients and hematopoietic stem cell transplantation recipients: a position paper from the joint task force of the Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer/International Society of Oral Oncology (MASCC/ISOO) and the European Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation (EBMT). Support Care Cancer 23 (1): 223-36, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27931474">Guideline on Dental Management of Pediatric Patients Receiving Chemotherapy, Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation, and/or Radiation Therapy. Pediatr Dent 38 (6): 334-342, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28194493">Bogusławska-Kapała A, Hałaburda K, Rusyan E, et al.: Oral health of adult patients undergoing hematopoietic cell transplantation. Pre-transplant assessment and care. Ann Hematol 96 (7): 1135-1145, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="29509233">Bollero P, Passarelli PC, D'Addona A, et al.: Oral management of adult patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci 22 (4): 876-887, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24615748">Lalla RV, Bowen J, Barasch A, et al.: MASCC/ISOO clinical practice guidelines for the management of mucositis secondary to cancer therapy. Cancer 120 (10): 1453-61, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="25818385">Sung L, Robinson P, Treister N, et al.: Guideline for the prevention of oral and oropharyngeal mucositis in children receiving treatment for cancer or undergoing haematopoietic stem cell transplantation. BMJ Support Palliat Care 7 (1): 7-16, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28642709">Cinausero M, Aprile G, Ermacora P, et al.: New Frontiers in the Pathobiology and Treatment of Cancer Regimen-Related Mucosal Injury. Front Pharmacol 8: 354, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="27821503">Lee SJ: Classification systems for chronic graft-versus-host disease. Blood 129 (1): 30-37, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="24979731">Ion D, Stevenson K, Woo SB, et al.: Characterization of oral involvement in acute graft-versus-host disease. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 20 (11): 1717-21, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="25529383">Jagasia MH, Greinix HT, Arora M, et al.: National Institutes of Health Consensus Development Project on Criteria for Clinical Trials in Chronic Graft-versus-Host Disease: I. The 2014 Diagnosis and Staging Working Group report. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 21 (3): 389-401.e1, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="25838185">Carpenter PA, Kitko CL, Elad S, et al.: National Institutes of Health Consensus Development Project on Criteria for Clinical Trials in Chronic Graft-versus-Host Disease: V. The 2014 Ancillary Therapy and Supportive Care Working Group Report. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 21 (7): 1167-87, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16435004">Rizzo JD, Wingard JR, Tichelli A, et al.: Recommended screening and preventive practices for long-term survivors after hematopoietic cell transplantation: joint recommendations of the European Group for Blood and Marrow Transplantation, Center for International Blood and Marrow Transplant Research, and the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation (EBMT/CIBMTR/ASBMT). Bone Marrow Transplant 37 (3): 249-61, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="16641398">Copelan EA: Hematopoietic stem-cell transplantation. N Engl J Med 354 (17): 1813-26, 2006.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_895"><Title>Oral Management of Patients Receiving Targeted Therapy/Cancer Immunotherapy</Title><SummarySection id="_1093"><Title>Targeted Therapy</Title><Para id="_1094">Targeted therapy acts either directly on specific tissues, cells, and/or genes or indirectly on growth-related tissues and the nutrition of cancer cells.  Antiangiogenesis therapies can suppress the formation of new blood vessels that nourish cancer tissue, preventing its growth.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Table id="_1433"><Title>Table 10.  Oral Management of Patients Receiving Targeted Cancer Therapy or Immunotherapy</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Before Cancer Therapy</entry><entry>During Cancer Therapy</entry><entry>After Cancer Therapy</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry>Document baseline oral mucosal status</entry><entry>Assess number and severity of oral mucosal lesions clinically documented to be caused by targeted therapy/immunotherapy</entry><entry>Monitor for possible late adverse oral effects</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Provide patient education</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Provide topical, intralesional, or systemic steroid treatment if oral pain is severe</entry><entry>Targeted therapy: Monitor for and treat gingival bleeding, necrotizing ulcerative gingivitis, stomatitis, aphthous-like ulcers, hyperkeratosis </entry></Row><Row><entry>Immunotherapy: Monitor for and treat lichenoid reactions (ulcerative or reticular), benign membrane pemphigoid, xerostomia, taste changes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Oral lesions are common for both classes of medications; consider in differential diagnosis of candidiasis and herpes simplex infections, medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1097">As with other cancer therapy modalities, targeted therapy has toxicities inherent to the drug group. Among the most significant side effects are the cutaneous adverse effects.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>] The oral side effects are seen in more than 20% of patients. In severe cases, there is an indication of dose reduction or permanent treatment discontinuation.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><Table id="_1434"><Title>Table 11.  Oral Toxicities of Cancer Drugs</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry> Cancer Drug</entry><entry>Oral Side Effects</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col1" NameSt="col0">EGFR = epidermal growth factor receptor; MRONJ = medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw; mTOR = mechanistic target of rapamycin; PDGF = platelet-derived growth factor; VEGF = vascular endothelial growth factor.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>mTOR <Reference refidx="6"/> <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry>Stomatitis, gingival bleeding, gingivitis, periodontal abscess, MRONJ, benign migratory glossitis, dysgeusia, xerostomia</entry></Row><Row><entry>EGFR <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="8"/></entry><entry>Mucositis, dysgeusia, xerostomia</entry></Row><Row><entry>VEGF <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="10"/></entry><entry>Gingival bleeding, MRONJ, mucositis, benign migratory glossitis</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sunitinib-VEGF receptors <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> </entry><entry>Gingival bleeding, painful soft tissue necrosis, MRONJ, altered taste, dry mouth, mucosal sensitivity, oral pain, oral mucositis/stomatitis, benign migratory glossitis, xerostomia</entry></Row><Row><entry>PDGF receptors <Reference refidx="6"/> <Reference refidx="7"/></entry><entry>Associated with MRONJ, liquenoid lesions, and necrosis</entry></Row><Row><entry>BRAF inhibitors <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></entry><entry>MRONJ, hyperkeratotic lesions</entry></Row><Row><entry>Imatinib <Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="8"/></entry><entry>MRONJ, erythema and atrophy of tissue, pigmentary changes and lichenoid reaction, mucositis, dysgeusia</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_1098"><Title>Cancer Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_1099">Immunotherapies have a different profile than targeted therapies and a new spectrum of toxicities compared with cytotoxic agents.  The mechanism of action of immune checkpoint inhibitors involves triggering cytotoxic T-cell activation and inducing a specific toxicity profile that is primarily of immunologic origin. The most commonly reported immune-related systemic adverse events include the following:<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_1100" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Dermatitis.</ListItem><ListItem>Enterocolitis.</ListItem><ListItem>Liver toxicities.</ListItem><ListItem>Endocrinopathies.</ListItem><ListItem>Pneumonitis.</ListItem><ListItem>Renal toxicity and other less common toxicities.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1101">Reports of oral complications related to immunotherapies are sparse in the literature and most often include xerostomia, dysgeusia, and lichenoid reactions.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="13"/> Other side effects are bullous skin eruptions. Two cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome with severe hemorrhagic cheilitis and erosions have been reported.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Table id="_1435"><Title>Table 12.  Systemic and Oral Toxicities of Cancer Immunotherapy</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Side Effects</entry><entry>Systemic Toxicities</entry><entry>Oral Toxicities</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Acute side effects</entry><entry>Dermatitis</entry><entry MoreRows="5">Lichenoid reactions; other immune-related lesions; xerostomia; taste changes; infections such as candidiasis and herpes simplex; osteonecrosis of the jaw</entry></Row><Row><entry>Lichenoid lesions</entry></Row><Row><entry>Bullous eruptions</entry></Row><Row><entry>Stevens-Johnson syndrome</entry></Row><Row><entry>Enterocolitis clinical expressed as diarrhea, liver toxicity</entry></Row><Row><entry>Endocrinopathies such as hypophysitis, thyroiditis, uveitis, pneumonitis, renal toxicity, infections, neurological events</entry></Row><Row><entry>Delayed events</entry><entry>Pneumonitis</entry><entry/></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1102">The largest reported series of oral immune-related lichenoid reactions   included ten cases.<Reference refidx="17"/> Four patients also showed skin, nail, or genital lesions. Tenderness and/or irritation and xerostomia were present in three patients. The lesions were self-limited and low grade, did not lead to discontinuation or interruption in oncologic treatment, and improved after several weeks of topical corticosteroid treatment.  The authors reported that oral lichenoid reactions were common in their clinical practice.</Para><Para id="_1103">Exacerbations of preexisting autoimmune disease have been reported and necessitated systemic treatment. A detailed history of preexisting autoimmune disease and vigilant clinical monitoring are important for these patients.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_1104">Osteonecrosis related to immunotherapy alone has rarely  been reported.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="22"/> However, with the increasing use of combinations of medications, clinicians should remain alert for these complications.</Para><Para id="_1369">Cancer immunotherapy can cause other side effects, which may be acute or delayed.</Para><Para id="_1283">Consequences of cancer immunotherapy oral side effects and toxicities include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1284" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Therapy dose modifications or discontinuation.</ListItem><ListItem>Inadequate food intake and diet changes.</ListItem><ListItem>Poor oral health.<ItemizedList id="_1285" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Risk of oral infections.</ListItem><ListItem>Increased dental caries.</ListItem><ListItem>Need for dental extractions.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Weight loss.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1105">Clinicians should be aware of immune-related oral adverse events. Routine evaluation of the oral cavity should be incorporated into the care of all patients, particularly those who are already at risk of oral complications—for example, patients with head and neck cancer who receive radiation therapy and patients who receive bone-targeting agents, targeted therapies (mainly inhibitors of angiogenesis), and other drugs.</Para><SummarySection id="_1106"><Title>Before targeted therapy/cancer immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_1107">A patient's medical history report will disclose any preexisting autoimmune oral disease. 
As in any cancer therapy, oral and dental examination and stabilization are  mandatory. Patient education on the importance of good oral health and oral hygiene is needed.<Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1109"><Title>During targeted therapy/cancer immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_1110">Oral management during targeted therapy follows the same guidelines as those  used for chronic graft-versus-host disease  in patients with hematological conditions after bone marrow transplant.<Reference refidx="23"/> Patients are encouraged to maintain good oral hygiene and to report any symptoms. If an oral lesion is suspected or diagnosed, the dentist will  refer the patient to an oral oncology clinic and communicate this information to the treating oncologist.  Early intervention and continued monitoring are required to limit exacerbation of the oral changes. Mucosal changes may be managed with topical anti-inflammatory agents. Severe cases may require systemic steroids. Dysplasia in lichenoid lesions is possible. If mucosal pain is present, topical analgesics may be considered. Dry mouth may include treatment with mouth-wetting agents and management of dental caries risk in the presence of hyposalivation, as well as prevention and management of oral candidiasis, herpes simplex, or other oral infections.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1111"><Title>After targeted therapy/cancer immunotherapy </Title><Para id="_1112">Follow-up after targeted therapy or immunotherapy is important, as late adverse events may develop. The increased use of combination treatment may disclose new adverse events that have not yet been recognized.</Para><Para id="_1113">Having an oral specialist on the oncology team greatly helps in the description, identification, early diagnosis, and timely and successful management of oral side effects related to immunotherapies alone or combined with other biological therapies.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">National Cancer Institute: Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer. Bethesda, Md: National Institutes of Health, 2022. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies/targeted-therapies-fact-sheet">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed Feb. 14, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="26648656">Carrington C: Oral targeted therapy for cancer. Aust Prescr 38 (5): 171-6, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="30353228">Nicolatou-Galitis O, Kouri M, Papadopoulou E, et al.: Osteonecrosis of the jaw related to non-antiresorptive medications: a systematic review. Support Care Cancer 27 (2): 383-394, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28224235">Vigarios E, Epstein JB, Sibaud V: Oral mucosal changes induced by anticancer targeted therapies and immune checkpoint inhibitors. Support Care Cancer 25 (5): 1713-1739, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="30374901">Lacouture M, Sibaud V: Toxic Side Effects of Targeted Therapies and Immunotherapies Affecting the Skin, Oral Mucosa, Hair, and Nails. Am J Clin Dermatol 19 (Suppl 1): 31-39, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="22206873">Gomez-Fernandez C, Garden BC, Wu S, et al.: The risk of skin rash and stomatitis with the mammalian target of rapamycin inhibitor temsirolimus: a systematic review of the literature and meta-analysis. Eur J Cancer 48 (3): 340-6, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="22207567">Boers-Doets CB, Epstein JB, Raber-Durlacher JE, et al.: Oral adverse events associated with tyrosine kinase and mammalian target of rapamycin inhibitors in renal cell carcinoma: a structured literature review. Oncologist 17 (1): 135-44, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="21514211">Watters AL, Epstein JB, Agulnik M: Oral complications of targeted cancer therapies: a narrative literature review. Oral Oncol 47 (6): 441-8, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="23312237">Martins F, de Oliveira MA, Wang Q, et al.: A review of oral toxicity associated with mTOR inhibitor therapy in cancer patients. Oral Oncol 49 (4): 293-8, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="22669112">Nicolatou-Galitis O, Migkou M, Psyrri A, et al.: Gingival bleeding and jaw bone necrosis in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma receiving sunitinib: report of 2 cases with clinical implications. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol 113 (2): 234-8, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="26765102">Michot JM, Bigenwald C, Champiat S, et al.: Immune-related adverse events with immune checkpoint blockade: a comprehensive review. Eur J Cancer 54: 139-148, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="29093678">Wang PF, Chen Y, Song SY, et al.: Immune-Related Adverse Events Associated with Anti-PD-1/PD-L1 Treatment for Malignancies: A Meta-Analysis. Front Pharmacol 8: 730, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="30919155">Nikolaou V, Voudouri D, Tsironis G, et al.: Cutaneous toxicities of antineoplastic agents: data from a large cohort of Greek patients. Support Care Cancer 27 (12): 4535-4542, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="27086658">Jour G, Glitza IC, Ellis RM, et al.: Autoimmune dermatologic toxicities from immune checkpoint blockade with anti-PD-1 antibody therapy: a report on bullous skin eruptions. J Cutan Pathol 43 (8): 688-96, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="28438440">Saw S, Lee HY, Ng QS: Pembrolizumab-induced Stevens-Johnson syndrome in non-melanoma patients. Eur J Cancer 81: 237-239, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="29045532">Salati M, Pifferi M, Baldessari C, et al.: Stevens-Johnson syndrome during nivolumab treatment of NSCLC. Ann Oncol 29 (1): 283-284, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="28419570">Sibaud V, Eid C, Belum VR, et al.: Oral lichenoid reactions associated with anti-PD-1/PD-L1 therapies: clinicopathological findings. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol 31 (10): e464-e469, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="26633184">Johnson DB, Sullivan RJ, Ott PA, et al.: Ipilimumab Therapy in Patients With Advanced Melanoma and Preexisting Autoimmune Disorders. JAMA Oncol 2 (2): 234-40, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="29331748">Danlos FX, Voisin AL, Dyevre V, et al.: Safety and efficacy of anti-programmed death 1 antibodies in patients with cancer and pre-existing autoimmune or inflammatory disease. Eur J Cancer 91: 21-29, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="30195074">Ijaz A, Khan AY, Malik SU, et al.: Significant Risk of Graft-versus-Host Disease with Exposure to Checkpoint Inhibitors before and after Allogeneic Transplantation. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 25 (1): 94-99, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="32144002">Economopoulou P, Nicolatou-Galitis O, Kotsantis I, et al.: Nivolumab-related lichen planus of the lip in a patient with head and neck cancer. Oral Oncol 104: 104623, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="30847290">Nifosì AF, Zuccarello M, Nifosì L, et al.: Osteonecrosis of the jaw in the era of targeted therapy and immunotherapy in oncology. J Korean Assoc Oral Maxillofac Surg 45 (1): 3-8, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="26820877">Epstein JB, Smutzer G, Doty RL: Understanding the impact of taste changes in oncology care. Support Care Cancer 24 (4): 1917-31, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="25417041">Elad S, Jensen SB, Raber-Durlacher JE, et al.: Clinical approach in the management of oral chronic graft-versus-host disease (cGVHD) in a series of specialized medical centers. Support Care Cancer 23 (6): 1615-22, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="25189149">Elad S, Raber-Durlacher JE, Brennan MT, et al.: Basic oral care for hematology-oncology patients and hematopoietic stem cell transplantation recipients: a position paper from the joint task force of the Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer/International Society of Oral Oncology (MASCC/ISOO) and the European Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation (EBMT). Support Care Cancer 23 (1): 223-36, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="28707167">Rapoport BL, van Eeden R, Sibaud V, et al.: Supportive care for patients undergoing immunotherapy. Support Care Cancer 25 (10): 3017-3030, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_898"><Title>Orofacial Pain in Patients With Cancer</Title><Para id="_1387">Orofacial pain may be present throughout the cancer continuum. In patients with head and neck cancer (HNC), orofacial pain has been reported to be as high as 85% at the time of cancer diagnosis.<Reference refidx="1"/>;<Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_1388">Orofacial pain is frequently associated with locoregional cancer, but it can also be a sign of systemic and distant cancers. It may arise from the onset of the disease and develops as the disease progresses. Orofacial pain is also highly associated with acute-treatment side effects and may continue after treatment ends due to persistence, recurrence, or metastasis of the primary cancer or acute and chronic toxicities of cancer therapy.<Reference refidx="4"/>
 It is important to recognize not only the diverse symptoms of orofacial pain in patients with cancer, but also pain's significant impact on their quality of life.</Para><Para id="_1376">The management of head and neck pain and oral and oropharyngeal pain may be particularly challenging because the area is a highly innervated sensory region, and eating, speech, swallowing, and other motor functions of the head and neck and oropharynx are constant pain triggers. Classification of head and neck pain can assist in management.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_1377">For more information on pain in patients with cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062738" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-hp-pdq">Cancer Pain</SummaryRef>. </Para><SummarySection id="_1121"><Title>Orofacial Pain Caused by Cancer Persistence, Recurrence, or Metastasis  </Title><SummarySection id="_1389"><Title>Etiology and epidemiology</Title><Para id="_1390">Pain caused by cancer is often low intensity, but it typically becomes more frequent and increasingly severe with advancing disease. Cancer pain may be caused by local tumor effects via direct invasion of adjacent structures, leading to pressure, ulceration, tissue necrosis, and perineural invasion.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_1391">Pain may also be aggravated by distant tumors or systemic cancer activity (e.g., blood and lymphatic cancers) due to nociceptive, inflammatory, and neuropathic mechanisms. For instance, oral manifestations of blood cancers such as leukemia, lymphoma, and multiple myeloma may cause pain and loss of function by infiltrating pain-sensitive structures <Reference refidx="5"/> or inducing secondary oral infections due to a compromised immune system.<Reference refidx="8"/> Furthermore, intracranial malignancies may give rise to orofacial pain and headaches due to pressure or infiltration of specific brain centers and structures.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1393"><Title>Signs and symptoms</Title><Para id="_1394">
  In the orofacial region, pain may present similarly to classic trigeminal neuralgia/neuropathic pain or musculoskeletal temporomandibular disorders. Symptoms range from acute, localized, sharp shooting episodes to chronic, diffuse, pressing, and aching pain.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_1396">Patients with nasopharyngeal and oropharyngeal cancer may report pain in the temporomandibular joint region with limited mouth opening; ear blockage, ringing, or pain; headaches; facial numbness; and masticatory muscle stiffness. These signs and symptoms may result from direct tumor invasion or represent a pattern of referred pain that can masquerade as a temporomandibular joint disorder.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_1397">Paraneoplastic neuropathies may present in cancer patients, particularly those with lung cancer or lymphoma.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>] This effect may manifest as difficulty swallowing, slurred speech, disturbed vision, seizures, facial muscle weakness, stiffness, or unusual involuntary contractions.<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1398"><Title>Diagnosis and management strategies</Title><Para id="_1399"> Meticulous clinical examination is a critical step in reporting orofacial pain or dysfunction. Pain can be reported in any structure of the craniofacial region, such as a toothache or pain in the gingiva, tongue, face, neck, ear, and pharynx.<Reference refidx="6"/> Management relies mainly on treating the malignancy. Since pain caused by cancer therapy is common, further pharmacotherapeutics and supportive treatment regimens may be needed. For more information on pharmacotherapeutic interventions and supportive regimens, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1413" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Diagnostic investigations and management strategies</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1132"><Title>Orofacial Pain Caused by Cancer Management</Title><SummarySection id="_1400"><Title>Etiology and epidemiology</Title><Para id="_1401">While surgical resection provides near complete relief of HNC-related pain, some patients require adjuvant therapies such as chemotherapy (i.e., cytotoxic agents and targeted biological agents) and/or radiation therapy to further combat the disease.<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>] Other cancer patients may be restricted to nonsurgical interventions because of the type or extent of their cancers. Stem cell transplant, another approach for managing hematologic malignancies, can involve   chemotherapy and/or total body radiation as part of the management regimen. These surgical and nonsurgical interventions, especially concomitant chemoradiotherapy, are tied to short- and long-lasting painful complications that may affect patient well-being and quality of life.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_1402">More than 70% of patients with HNC report variable forms of pain during and after their cancer therapy.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1403"><Title>Signs and symptoms</Title><SummarySection id="_1404"><Title>Pain associated with surgical interventions</Title><Para id="_1405">For patients with HNC undergoing surgical interventions, acute nociceptive regional orofacial pain, scar formation, and sensory impairment are inevitable. These complications increase dramatically with concomitant procedures, such as neck dissection, and may evolve to long-term, painful, postsurgical fibrosis and neuropathy.<Reference refidx="5"/> Fifty  percent to 90% of patients who undergo mandibulectomy or maxillectomy have regional hyperalgesia and allodynia. Pain scores following HNC surgery are the highest for the oral cavity, followed by the larynx, oropharynx, and nasopharynx. The most common locations for orofacial pain complaints are the oral cavity, followed by the temporomandibular joint, face, neck, and shoulders.<Reference refidx="5"/> Musculoskeletal syndromes, including temporomandibular disorders associated with muscular fibrosis and limited jaw opening, lead to significant pain and loss of orofacial function. The persistence of these complications may severely impact cancer survivors’ quality of life and  well-being.<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="15"/><LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1406"><Title>Pain associated with chemotherapy and radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_1407">Orofacial pain as a result of cancer chemotherapy and radiation therapy is a well-recognized complication that may longitudinally affect cancer survivors’ quality of life.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>
 Generally, 60% to 80% of cancer patients experience pain during these interventions, with a significant number continuing to struggle from long-term, persistent pain complaints after the completion of therapy.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_1408">Severe peripheral neurotoxicity leads to neuropathic orofacial pain, changes in taste, and loss of sensory perception and motor coordination. Localized oral burning pain, comparable to burning mouth syndrome, can also occur. Cytotoxic effects of chemotherapy and radiation therapy may cause oral mucositis. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_994" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Oral mucositis (high-dose chemotherapy, HSCT, head and  neck radiation)</SummaryRef> section. Oral ulcerations due to neutropenia or oral bacterial, fungal, and viral infections are other examples of common, acute, painful complications encountered during and after anticancer therapy.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="19"/> In addition, compromised immune function may lead to reactivation of dormant herpes viruses, causing painful oral and para-oral lesions. Postherpetic neuralgia, if emerged, can cause chronic dysesthesias in the affected area that may persist for years.<Reference refidx="20"/> Moreover, hyposalivation, especially in those receiving head and neck radiation, may enhance susceptibility to oral candidiasis and rampant caries.<Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_1409">Several targeted biological agents, such as tyrosine-kinase inhibitors and immune checkpoint inhibitors, have proven efficacy in managing patients with cancer. In the orofacial pain region, these therapies may cause taste alterations, aphthous-like ulceration, and mucosal lichenoid reactions.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="23"/>
	Combinations of multiple agents may result in increasingly complex mucosal changes and related symptoms.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="22"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1109" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Oral management during targeted therapy/cancer immunotherapy</SummaryRef> section. </Para><Para id="_1410">When they occur during cancer therapy, these complications can negatively affect patients’ nutritional status and lead to undesired interruption or reduction of the dose or frequency of the cancer treatment regimen.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="24"/>
 Furthermore, the long-term impact of anticancer therapy may significantly compromise the physical, psychological, and financial well-being of cancer survivors.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1411"><Title>Pain associated with stem cell transplant therapy</Title><Para id="_1412">Graft-versus-host disease is a common complication of allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant, occurring in 25% to 70% of patients and  presenting in both acute and chronic forms. Head and neck involvement is manifested as mucosal striation/ulceration, superficial mucocele, and temporomandibular joint arthritic dysfunction that are often painful.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="28"/> Additionally, increased thermal sensitivity has been observed in patients being treated with cyclosporine after their hematopoietic stem cell transplants.<Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1383"><Title>Oral mucositis</Title><Para id="_1386">For  information on oral mucositis, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_994" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Oral mucositis (high-dose chemotherapy, HSCT, head and neck radiation)</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1413"><Title>Diagnostic investigations and management strategies</Title><Para id="_1414">As cancer pain is mixed in nature and presentation, specific screening and assessment questionnaires are useful in differentiating nociceptive and neuropathic pain and help to better manage orofacial pain.  In the oncology setting, it is important that a thorough health history and oral physical examination be performed when oral pain is present. The role of routine high-maintenance levels of oral hygiene cannot be understated. Radiographic imaging and vitality testing of the dental pulp are typically necessary.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_1415">Persistent neuropathies are a common complication after HNC surgical interventions and radiation therapies.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="30"/> Selected classes of chemotherapy, such as vinca alkaloids, vincristine, vinblastine, platinum-based drugs, taxanes, and targeted biological agents, can also cause direct neurotoxicity.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="31"/> Additionally, drugs such as thalidomide and lenalidomide are associated with peripheral neuropathies that can affect the orofacial region. Deeply-seated mandibular pain may be of dental etiology as a consequence of pulpal neurotoxicity or necrosis.</Para><Para id="_1416">Management of neuropathic orofacial pain is complex and challenging, often involving centrally and peripherally acting pharmacotherapeutic agents. Topical and systemic gabapentinoids, membrane stabilizers, small doses of tricyclic antidepressants, selective serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors, vanilloid receptor inhibitors, and cannabinoids are often prescribed.<Reference refidx="32"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="33"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/> Supportive approaches such as counseling, acupuncture, photobiomodulation, and neurosensory stents may also be considered. Preventive measures such as physical shielding and cryotherapy should  be considered before and during anticancer therapy to reduce cytotoxic and neurotoxic outcomes.<Reference refidx="36"/></Para><Para id="_1417">Dental hypersensitivity may occasionally arise in the weeks or months after the discontinuation of chemotherapy and/or radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="13"/> Topical application of fluorides and desensitizing agents may ameliorate dental discomfort.<Reference refidx="13"/>  In most instances, thermal sensitivity observed in patients who received hematopoietic stem cell transplant is self-resolving after discontinuation of cyclosporine.<Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_1418">Patients may also experience musculoskeletal pain and dysfunction involving muscles of mastication, the neck, and/or the temporomandibular joints.<Reference refidx="37"/> These conditions may be  further aggravated by stress, sleep disturbance, and parafunctional habits (i.e., bruxism and clenching) after treatment of HNC.<Reference refidx="38"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>] Physical management of orofacial pain, including cold compresses or moist heat combined with physical therapy, custom occlusal splints, and masticatory/neck muscle exercises, help significantly. Judicious use of muscle relaxants or anxiolytic agents can be considered. Acupuncture, transcutaneous nerve stimulation, low-level laser use, and massage therapy are adjuvant modalities to alleviate pain in patients with cancer.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="41"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]
	
For more information, see  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000445441" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/acupuncture-pdq">Acupuncture</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_1419">Additionally, psychological approaches such as counseling, distraction, relaxation techniques, biofeedback, group therapy, self-hypnosis, imagery, and cognitive behavioral training programs have shown promising results in randomized clinical trials.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="42"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="43"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663069" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: I</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="30698098">Holländer-Mieritz C, Johansen J, Johansen C, et al.: Comparing the patients' subjective experiences of acute side effects during radiotherapy for head and neck cancer with four different patient-reported outcomes questionnaires. Acta Oncol 58 (5): 603-609, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="29161981">Carpén T, Sjöblom A, Lundberg M, et al.: Presenting symptoms and clinical findings in HPV-positive and HPV-negative oropharyngeal cancer patients. Acta Otolaryngol 138 (5): 513-518, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23832272">Saunders DP, Epstein JB, Elad S, et al.: Systematic review of antimicrobials, mucosal coating agents, anesthetics, and analgesics for the management of oral mucositis in cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 21 (11): 3191-207, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="32052137">Saunders DP, Rouleau T, Cheng K, et al.: Systematic review of antimicrobials, mucosal coating agents, anesthetics, and analgesics for the management of oral mucositis in cancer patients and clinical practice guidelines. Support Care Cancer 28 (5): 2473-2484, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31425595">Epstein JB, Miaskowski C: Oral Pain in the Cancer Patient. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="26088459">Romero-Reyes M, Teruel A, Ye Y: Cancer and Referred Facial Pain. Curr Pain Headache Rep 19 (8): 37, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26608142">Schmidt BL: The Neurobiology of Cancer Pain. J Oral Maxillofac Surg 73 (12 Suppl): S132-5, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="27594910">Silva TD, Ferreira CB, Leite GB, et al.: Oral manifestations of lymphoma: a systematic review. Ecancermedicalscience 10: 665, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Jamal Zohaib, Anjum Fatima: Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma. In: StatPearls [Internet]. StatPearls Publishing, 2024, Treasure Island, FL: StatsPearls [Internet], 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK563268/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed October 10, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Shah Abdul B., Nagalli Shivaraj: Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma. In: StatPearls [Internet]. StatPearls Publishing, 2024, Treasure Island, FL: StatPearls [Internet], 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK554588/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed October 10, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="28682959">Antoine JC, Camdessanché JP: Paraneoplastic neuropathies. Curr Opin Neurol 30 (5): 513-520, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="34659082">Zoccarato M, Grisold W, Grisold A, et al.: Paraneoplastic Neuropathies: What's New Since the 2004 Recommended Diagnostic Criteria. Front Neurol 12: 706169, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29071801">Sroussi HY, Epstein JB, Bensadoun RJ, et al.: Common oral complications of head and neck cancer radiation therapy: mucositis, infections, saliva change, fibrosis, sensory dysfunctions, dental caries, periodontal disease, and osteoradionecrosis. Cancer Med 6 (12): 2918-2931, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="31313400">Pauli N, Mejersjö C, Fagerberg-Mohlin B, et al.: Temporomandibular disorder in head and neck cancer patients undergoing radiotherapy: Clinical findings and patient-reported symptoms. Head Neck 41 (10): 3570-3576, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="32151696">Nicot R, Raoul G, Ferri J, et al.: Temporomandibular disorders in head and neck cancers: Overview of specific mechanisms and management. J Stomatol Oral Maxillofac Surg 121 (5): 563-568, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="29443582">Schmitd LB, Scanlon CS, D'Silva NJ: Perineural Invasion in Head and Neck Cancer. J Dent Res 97 (7): 742-750, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="35717462">Jones JA, Chavarri-Guerra Y, Corrêa LBC, et al.: MASCC/ISOO expert opinion on the management of oral problems in patients with advanced cancer. Support Care Cancer 30 (11): 8761-8773, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="26712589">Mirabile A, Airoldi M, Ripamonti C, et al.: Pain management in head and neck cancer patients undergoing chemo-radiotherapy: Clinical practical recommendations. Crit Rev Oncol Hematol 99: 100-6, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="25108356">Binczak M, Navez M, Perrichon C, et al.: Management of somatic pain induced by head-and-neck cancer treatment: definition and assessment. Guidelines of the French Oto-Rhino-Laryngology- Head and Neck Surgery Society (SFORL). Eur Ann Otorhinolaryngol Head Neck Dis 131 (4): 243-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="24855388">Vickers ER, Karsten E, Flood J, et al.: A preliminary report on stem cell therapy for neuropathic pain in humans. J Pain Res 7: 255-63, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="35231809">Lin A, Helgeson ES, Treister NS, et al.: The impact of head and neck radiotherapy on salivary flow and quality of life: Results of the ORARAD study. Oral Oncol 127: 105783, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="31642136">Shazib MA, Woo SB, Sroussi H, et al.: Oral immune-related adverse events associated with PD-1 inhibitor therapy: A case series. Oral Dis 26 (2): 325-333, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="31425602">Carrozzo M, Eriksen JG, Bensadoun RJ, et al.: Oral Mucosal Injury Caused by Targeted Cancer Therapies. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="34542427">Hunter M, Kellett J, Toohey K, et al.: Toxicities Caused by Head and Neck Cancer Treatments and Their Influence on the Development of Malnutrition: Review of the Literature. Eur J Investig Health Psychol Educ 10 (4): 935-949, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="31941708">Han X, Zhao J, Zheng Z, et al.: Medical Financial Hardship Intensity and Financial Sacrifice Associated with Cancer in the United States. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 29 (2): 308-317, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="31804869">Yabroff KR, Bradley C, Shih YT: Understanding Financial Hardship Among Cancer Survivors in the United States: Strategies for Prevention and Mitigation. J Clin Oncol 38 (4): 292-301, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="35430188">Utley M, Adeyanju T, Bernardo B, et al.: The association between mental health, social support and physical health outcomes among older female cancer survivors. J Geriatr Oncol 13 (6): 834-838, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="31425593">Fall-Dickson JM, Pavletic SZ, Mays JW, et al.: Oral Complications of Chronic Graft-Versus-Host Disease. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr 2019 (53): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="32666212">Epstein JB, Raber-Durlacher JE, Epstein GL, et al.: Chronic oral graft-versus-host disease: induction and maintenance therapy with photobiomodulation therapy. Support Care Cancer 29 (3): 1387-1394, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="33545258">Van den Bosch L, van der Schaaf A, van der Laan HP, et al.: Comprehensive toxicity risk profiling in radiation therapy for head and neck cancer: A new concept for individually optimised treatment. Radiother Oncol 157: 147-154, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="33685809">Brook I: Early side effects of radiation treatment for head and neck cancer. Cancer Radiother 25 (5): 507-513, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="32770612">Smith DK, Cmelak A, Niermann K, et al.: Preventive use of gabapentin to decrease pain and systemic symptoms in patients with head and neck cancer undergoing chemoradiation. Head Neck 42 (12): 3497-3505, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="30074291">Häuser W, Finn DP, Kalso E, et al.: European Pain Federation (EFIC) position paper on appropriate use of cannabis-based medicines and medical cannabis for chronic pain management. Eur J Pain 22 (9): 1547-1564, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="29847473">Häuser W, Finnerup NB, Moore RA: Systematic reviews with meta-analysis on cannabis-based medicines for chronic pain: a methodological and political minefield. Pain 159 (10): 1906-1907, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="29513392">Mücke M, Phillips T, Radbruch L, et al.: Cannabis-based medicines for chronic neuropathic pain in adults. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 3 (3): CD012182, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="31264186">de Pauli Paglioni M, Alves CGB, Fontes EK, et al.: Is photobiomodulation therapy effective in reducing pain caused by toxicities related to head and neck cancer treatment? A systematic review. Support Care Cancer 27 (11): 4043-4054, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="33012151">Brook I: Late side effects of radiation treatment for head and neck cancer. Radiat Oncol J 38 (2): 84-92, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="27061883">Buglione M, Cavagnini R, Di Rosario F, et al.: Oral toxicity management in head and neck cancer patients treated with chemotherapy and radiation: Xerostomia and trismus (Part 2). Literature review and consensus statement. Crit Rev Oncol Hematol 102: 47-54, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="30480345">Bennett MI, Eisenberg E, Ahmedzai SH, et al.: Standards for the management of cancer-related pain across Europe-A position paper from the EFIC Task Force on Cancer Pain. Eur J Pain 23 (4): 660-668, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="35089187">Wan Q, Chen H, Wang X, et al.: Effectiveness of different acupuncture therapies for chronic cancer pain: A protocol for systematic review and Bayesian network meta-analysis. Medicine (Baltimore) 101 (4): e27965, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="33799949">Dymackova R, Selingerova I, Kazda T, et al.: Effect of Acupuncture in Pain Management of Head and Neck Cancer Radiotherapy: Prospective Randomized Unicentric Study. J Clin Med 10 (5): , 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="35351037">Abbas Q, Arooj N, Baig KB, et al.: A clinical trial of cognitive behavior therapy for psychiatric comorbidity and quality of life with Cancer Patients during Chemotherapy (CPdC). BMC Psychiatry 22 (1): 222, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="28453966">Okuyama T, Akechi T, Mackenzie L, et al.: Psychotherapy for depression among advanced, incurable cancer patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Cancer Treat Rev 56: 16-27, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_901"><Title>Infection</Title><Para id="_1271">The intactness of skin and mucosa are physical barriers to infection. The epithelium of the oral mucosa impedes the attachment of pathogenic organisms by shedding dead cells and pathogens. This process limits the  penetration of many compounds into the epithelium by maintaining a chemical barrier of antimicrobial molecules.  These molecules are part of salivary protection and saliva, which are also responsible for protectively cleaning the teeth and mucosa and maintaining neutral pH, and lubrication.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_903">Oral infections in cancer patients could be caused by  a preexisting acute oral infection before the therapy is administered; therefore, control and elimination of these infections play a crucial role.<Reference refidx="2"/> Other infections typically arise in the setting of the immunocompromised host response during therapy.</Para><Para id="_1161">Oral mucositis is a common complication of cancer therapy. In addition to causing severe pain and nutritional impairment, there is an increased risk of local and systemic infections.<Reference refidx="3"/> Oral mucositis can be complicated by infection in immunocompromised patients. Importantly, disruption of the oral mucosa provides a major route of entry for pathological microorganisms. This situation can lead to various infections, including fatal septicemia.<Reference refidx="4"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_994" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">Oral mucositis (high-dose chemotherapy, HSCT, head and  neck radiation) </SummaryRef>section.</Para><Para id="_1282">Both indigenous oral flora and hospital-acquired pathogens have been associated with bacteremias and systemic infection. As the absolute neutrophil count falls below 1,000/µL, the incidence and severity of infection rise. Patients with prolonged neutropenia are at higher risk of developing serious infectious complications. The rate and severity of these infections mostly depend on prolonged periods of neutropenia (more than 7 days).<Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>] Compromised salivary function  and  poor oral hygiene alter oral microbial flora and increase oral microbial load, making patients susceptible to opportunistic bacterial, viral, and fungal infections. Patients have a higher risk of developing odontogenic infections if they do not receive prompt care for any dental or periodontal disorder.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_1162">Other oral sites, including the dentition, periapices, and periodontium, can also become acutely infected during myelosuppression secondary to high-dose chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="2"/> </Para><Para id="_1422">A literature search was conducted in the MEDLINE/PubMed and EMBASE databases for articles published between 2009 and 2016. Dental-related infections and abscesses during cancer therapy (primarily antineoplastic chemotherapy) were reported in six studies. The mean weighted prevalence was 5.4% (standard of error, 1.16; 95% confidence interval, 3.14–7.7).<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_1163">Dental management undertaken before  cytoreductive therapy  can substantially reduce the risk of infectious complications.<Reference refidx="2"/> Researchers have shifted toward the idea that if there is a close relationship between the dental and oncology team, clearance of only acute infection before cancer therapy has similar results as completed dental management regarding oral infection during myelosuppression.<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para><SummarySection id="_1164"><Title>Bacterial Infections</Title><Para id="_1165">Changes in infection profiles in patients with cancer-related myelosuppression have occurred
over the past three decades.  Multiple factors have caused this evolving epidemiology, including the use of prophylactic and therapeutic antimicrobial
regimens and decreased depth and duration of myelosuppression.<Reference refidx="10"/>  Gram-positive organisms, including 
<ScientificName>Viridans streptococci</ScientificName> and <ScientificName>Enterococci</ScientificName> species, are associated with systemic
infection of oral origin.  In addition, gram-negative pathogens, including
<ScientificName>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</ScientificName>, <ScientificName>Neisseria</ScientificName> species, and <ScientificName>Escherichia coli</ScientificName>, remain a
concern.</Para><Para id="_1166">Myeloablated cancer patients with chronic periodontal disease may develop acute
periodontal infections, with associated systemic sequelae.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/>  </Para><Para id="_1168">Pulpal/periapical infections of dental origin can cause complications for the
chemotherapy patient and need to be resolved before chemotherapy begins.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>     </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1172"><Title>Fungal Infections</Title><SummarySection id="_1173"><Title>Candidiasis</Title><Para id="_1174">Candidiasis is typically caused by opportunistic overgrowth of <ScientificName>Candida
albicans</ScientificName>, a normal inhabitant of the oral cavity in many individuals. Several variables contribute to its clinical expression, including drug- or disease-induced immunosuppression, mucosal injury, and salivary compromise. In addition, the use of antibiotics may alter the oral flora, creating a favorable environment for fungal overgrowth.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_1175">The weighted mean prevalence of clinical oral fungal infection during chemotherapy or head and neck radiation therapy was found to be 31% in a retrospective multicenter study.<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>] The appearance of erythematous candidiasis is relatively nonspecific, and laboratory testing may be needed to confirm the diagnosis. It may be accompanied by a burning sensation of the affected tissues.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_1177">Although topical agents may be helpful for superficial oral candidiasis, systemic agents are used for persistent fungal infections and in patients with significant immunosuppression. Systemic fluconazole is highly effective for prophylaxis and treatment of oral fungal infections in the oncology population.<Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1178"><Title>Noncandidal fungal infections</Title><Para id="_1179">Although most oral fungal infections involve <Emphasis>Candida</Emphasis>, there are occasional case reports of other oral fungal infections in immunosuppressed populations, including cancer patients. For example, a few cases of oral mucormycosis have been reported in patients with hematologic malignancies who receive a bone marrow transplant.<Reference refidx="21"/> Such noncandidal oral fungal infections carry a high risk of fungemia and mortality in immunocompromised patients; systemic antifungal therapy must be promptly initiated.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1180"><Title>Viral Infections</Title><SummarySection id="_1181"><Title>Herpes virus</Title><Para id="_1182">Herpes group viral infections, including those caused by oral lesions, can cause a variety of diseases that range from mild to serious in patients undergoing treatment for cancer.   The severity and impact of these lesions and systemic sequelae are directly related to the patient's extent of immunocompromise.  Comorbid oral conditions such as mucositis or graft-versus-host disease can dramatically increase the severity of oral lesions and significantly increase the difficulty of diagnosis.</Para><Para id="_1184">A systematic review was conducted by the Mucositis Study Group of the Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer/International Society of Oral Oncology.<Reference refidx="22"/> Eighteen of 41 studies focused on outcome measures in preventing oral viral infection. This review reported  findings to confirm the use of acyclovir and valacyclovir in preventing and treating oral herpetic infections.</Para><Para id="_1188">Early diagnosis and prompt therapy remain hallmarks of management.  As with
other infections, the risk of systemic dissemination and morbidity/mortality
increases with the degree and duration of immunocompromise.  The infections can be
fatal, depending on the degree of immunosuppression.</Para><SummarySection id="_1189"><Title>Herpes simplex
virus (HSV)</Title><Para id="_1190">Oral herpetic lesions can range from routine herpes labialis to severe stomatitis causing large, painful ulcerations throughout the mouth.  Lesion severity increases with  higher  degrees of immunosuppression.  </Para><Para id="_1191">The introduction of valacyclovir appears to have reduced the incidence of breakthrough oral HSV infections. Topical therapy alone is generally not efficacious in patients who are
immunocompromised.</Para><Para id="_1192">In patients who are not receiving antiviral prophylaxis, oral lesions typically emerge concurrent with chemotherapy or chemoradiation therapy during the period of most significant immunosuppression (white blood cell nadir).  Typically, in patients receiving a hematopoietic stem cell transplant, this represents the period  a few days pretransplant through day 35 posttransplant.  The risk of HSV reactivation remains higher than normal until immune reconstitution occurs.  Similar patterns of risk are noted in patients receiving high-dose (immunosuppressive) chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_1193">Recurrent oral HSV infections occurring simultaneously with cancer therapy–induced oral mucositis can result in the development of extensive, confluent mucosal ulcerations clinically similar to primary herpetic stomatitis.    Thus, HSV stomatitis can be
confused with cancer therapy–induced ulcerative mucositis.  Viral cultures from lesions in HSV-seropositive patients are
essential for accurate diagnoses.  Assays that produce more rapid results,
including direct immunofluorescence, shell vial testing, and specific immunoassays for HSV antigen and/or biopsy, may also be useful.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1195"><Title>Varicella-zoster virus (VZV)</Title><Para id="_1196">VZV infection classically distributes via dermatomes, although the clinical manifestations can be altered in
immunocompromised patients,  and multiple dermatomes or more widespread distribution of lesions can be seen.  In patients who are receiving high-dose chemotherapy, orofacial VZV lesions are typically observed several weeks after cessation of chemotherapy—unlike HSV, which often occurs within 2 to 3 weeks after chemotherapy is discontinued.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1197"><Title>Cytomegalovirus</Title><Para id="_1198">Oral lesions associated with cytomegalovirus have been documented in immunocompromised patients, including those who have undergone a bone marrow transplant.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_1199">Appearance is not pathognomonic and is characterized by multiple mild to moderate
ulcerations with irregular margins.  The lesions initially present during early
periods of marrow regeneration (e.g., 3 weeks after chemotherapy is
discontinued) and are characterized by nonspecific pseudomembranous fibrin exudate–covered ulcerations with a  granulomatous-appearing base.  Surface swab cultures may yield false-negative results, perhaps
because of viral propensity for infecting endothelial cells and fibroblasts, resulting in low levels of free virus.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1201"><Title>Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)</Title><Para id="_1202">EBV is linked to tumor development. In addition, oral hairy leukoplakia has been attributed to EBV infection in
immunocompromised patients, as seen in HIV-infected patients and solid organ transplant patients. 
However, the lesion does not appear to be clinically significant in chemotherapy
recipients.  </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1204"><Title>Non–herpes group virus infections</Title><Para id="_1205">Infections caused by non–herpes group viruses are more common in immunocompromised
 patients, with the risk of infection apparently increasing with the depth and duration of immunosuppression.  Oral lesions caused by adenovirus and oral human
papillomavirus (HPV) have been described.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>] Often, patients with increased cutaneous HPV lesions will develop oral lesions.   These lesions can present as hyperkeratotic verrucoid lesions or as flat acuminata-like lesions.</Para><Para id="_1206">Restoration of immune function often results in a digression and, possibly, the disappearance of the oral mucosal lesions.  Laser surgery or cryotherapy are
typically used to remove oral HPV lesions when medically or cosmetically required. Intralesional injections of
 interferon-alpha may prove effective for recurrent lesions. Infection with coxsackie viruses can occur but is generally uncommon.  Although adenovirus infections are often implicated as a potential cause of oral lesions, their true incidence is not known.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663089" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: IV</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="29878444">Pedersen AML, Sørensen CE, Proctor GB, et al.: Salivary secretion in health and disease. J Oral Rehabil 45 (9): 730-746, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="32166855">Spijkervet FKL, Schuurhuis JM, Stokman MA, et al.: Should oral foci of infection be removed before the onset of radiotherapy or chemotherapy? Oral Dis 27 (1): 7-13, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="31802252">de Oliveira MCQ, Lebre Martins BNF, Santos-Silva AR, et al.: Dental treatment needs in hospitalized cancer patients: a retrospective cohort study. Support Care Cancer 28 (7): 3451-3457, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="31018870">Hong BY, Sobue T, Choquette L, et al.: Chemotherapy-induced oral mucositis is associated with detrimental bacterial dysbiosis. Microbiome 7 (1): 66, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="27339055">Ullmann AJ, Schmidt-Hieber M, Bertz H, et al.: Infectious diseases in allogeneic haematopoietic stem cell transplantation: prevention and prophylaxis strategy guidelines 2016. Ann Hematol 95 (9): 1435-55, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="29126490">Villa A, Akintoye SO: Dental Management of Patients Who Have Undergone Oral Cancer Therapy. Dent Clin North Am 62 (1): 131-142, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28735355">Hong CHL, Hu S, Haverman T, et al.: A systematic review of dental disease management in cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 26 (1): 155-174, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28750016">Kishimoto M, Akashi M, Tsuji K, et al.: Intensity and duration of neutropenia relates to the development of oral mucositis but not odontogenic infection during chemotherapy for hematological malignancy. PLoS One 12 (7): e0182021, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="31851665">Mauramo M, Grolimund P, Egli A, et al.: Dissociations of oral foci of infections with infectious complications and survival after haematopoietic stem cell transplantation. PLoS One 14 (12): e0225099, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Castagnola E, Mikulska M, Viscoli C: Prophylaxis and Empirical Therapy of Infection in Cancer Patients. In: Bennett JE, Dolin R, Blaser MJ, eds.: Principles and Practice of Infectious Diseases. 8th ed.: Elsevier, Inc., 2015, Elsevier, Inc., 2015, pp 3395-413. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7173426/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed October 10, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="33392808">Ohbayashi Y, Imataki O, Uemura M, et al.: Oral microorganisms and bloodstream infection in allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Clin Oral Investig 25 (7): 4359-4367, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="31222393">Zecha JAEM, Raber-Durlacher JE, Laheij AMGA, et al.: The impact of the oral cavity in febrile neutropenia and infectious complications in patients treated with myelosuppressive chemotherapy. Support Care Cancer 27 (10): 3667-3679, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29910997">Decker AM, Taichman LS, D'Silva NJ, et al.: Periodontal Treatment in Cancer Patients: An Interdisciplinary Approach. Curr Oral Health Rep 5 (1): 7-12, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="28194493">Bogusławska-Kapała A, Hałaburda K, Rusyan E, et al.: Oral health of adult patients undergoing hematopoietic cell transplantation. Pre-transplant assessment and care. Ann Hematol 96 (7): 1135-1145, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="29509233">Bollero P, Passarelli PC, D'Addona A, et al.: Oral management of adult patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci 22 (4): 876-887, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="30693459">Hellstein JW, Marek CL: Candidiasis: Red and White Manifestations in the Oral Cavity. Head Neck Pathol 13 (1): 25-32, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="29123282">Lewis MAO, Williams DW: Diagnosis and management of oral candidosis. Br Dent J 223 (9): 675-681, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="31177394">Nishii M, Soutome S, Kawakita A, et al.: Factors associated with severe oral mucositis and candidiasis in patients undergoing radiotherapy for oral and oropharyngeal carcinomas: a retrospective multicenter study of 326 patients. Support Care Cancer 28 (3): 1069-1075, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="28258917">Singh GK, Capoor MR, Nair D, et al.: Spectrum of fungal infection in head and neck cancer patients on chemoradiotherapy. J Egypt Natl Canc Inst 29 (1): 33-37, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="30383690">Kawashita Y, Funahara M, Yoshimatsu M, et al.: A retrospective study of factors associated with the development of oral candidiasis in patients receiving radiotherapy for head and neck cancer: Is topical steroid therapy a risk factor for oral candidiasis? Medicine (Baltimore) 97 (44): e13073, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="28877386">Cheong HS, Kim SY, Ki HK, et al.: Oral mucormycosis in patients with haematologic malignancies in a bone marrow transplant unit. Mycoses 60 (12): 836-841, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="20544224">Elad S, Zadik Y, Hewson I, et al.: A systematic review of viral infections associated with oral involvement in cancer patients: a spotlight on Herpesviridea. Support Care Cancer 18 (8): 993-1006, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="23">Schubert MM, Correa MEP, Peterson DE: Oral complications of hematopoietic cell transplantation. In: Forman SJ, Negrin RS, Antin JH, et al., eds.: Thomas’ Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation: Stem Cell Transplantation. 5th ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, 2016, pp 1242-56.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_904"><Title>Hemorrhage</Title><Para id="_1272">Hemorrhage is a concern for patients who are receiving high-dose chemotherapy or undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant. It may occur during treatment-induced thrombocytopenia and/or coagulopathy.<Reference refidx="1"/> Spontaneous gingival oozing may occur when platelet counts drop below 20,000/µL, especially when there is preexisting gingivitis or periodontitis. Even normal function or routine oral hygiene (brushing and flossing) can induce gingival oozing with preexisting gingivitis and periodontitis, compounded by hematologic change and biochemical changes in coagulation.  Management requires attention by a multidisciplinary team to local measures, platelet count and function, and coagulation.</Para><Para id="_906">Although rarely serious, oral bleeds can be of concern to the patient and family. Oral bleeding may be mild (e.g., petechiae located on the lips, soft palate, or floor of the mouth) or severe (e.g., persistent gingival hemorrhage or bleeding from herpes simplex virus ulcers in the face of severe thrombocytopenia).</Para><Para id="_1207">Healthy gingival tissues do not bleed unless traumatized. Discontinuation of routine oral hygiene can increase the risk of gingival infection, which may promote bleeding and increase the risk of local and systemic infection due to accumulation of bacterial plaque. This may lead to periodontal infections and tissue breakdown.</Para><Para id="_1208">The degree of health professional oversight of thrombocytopenic patients is an important consideration relative to risk of mechanical hygiene procedures. With comprehensive monitoring, patients can often safely use dental brushing and interdental cleaning throughout the thrombocytopenic episode.</Para><Para id="_1209">Local measures to manage oral bleeds include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1210" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Pressure application.</Strong> Pressure can be applied by gauze or custom-made oral appliances; these can also be used to deliver and maintain topical agents at the site of bleeding. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Locally applied clot-forming agents.</Strong> Topical thrombin and/or hemostatic collagen agents and tranexamic acid can be used to stabilize clots.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Vasoconstrictors.</Strong> Epinephrine can be used topically to reduce blood flow rates through bleeding vessels, although vessel rebound is a potential concern.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Tissue protectants.</Strong> Application of mucosal adherent products (including cyanoacrylate products) help seal bleeding sites and protect organized clots; platelet-rich plasma may be used.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1211">Patients who tend to form friable and easily dislodged clots will benefit from topical application of aminocaproic acid. In some instances, intravenous administration can be considered to improve coagulation and the formation of stable clots.</Para><Para id="_1212">Application of 3% hydrogen peroxide and 0.9% saline (1:2 to 1:3 by volume) can aid in wound cleansing and removal of superficial blood debris. Care must be taken not to disturb clots, which might promote bleeding.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Laser application for local coagulation may be considered.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Schubert MM, Correa MEP, Peterson DE: Oral complications of hematopoietic cell transplantation. In: Forman SJ, Negrin RS, Antin JH, et al., eds.: Thomas’ Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation: Stem Cell Transplantation. 5th ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, 2016, pp 1242-56.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_907"><Title>Relapse and Second Malignancy</Title><Para id="_908">Gingival infiltrates, oral infection, and/or bleeding disproportionate to local etiology can indicate a possible relapse, especially in patients treated for leukemias or lymphomas. </Para><Para id="_1213">Relapse of non–head and neck solid tumors occurring as oral metastases is rarely observed. Second head and neck tumors are expected to occur in up to 15% of head and neck cancer patients in a stable incidence over the years, and human papillomavirus status may influence this outcome.<Reference refidx="1"/> Locoregional recurrences usually occur in the first 2 years after treatment. The same follow-up protocol is indicated in cases of a second malignant event.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="30582167">Adjei Boakye E, Buchanan P, Hinyard L, et al.: Risk and outcomes for second primary human papillomavirus-related and -unrelated head and neck malignancy. Laryngoscope 129 (8): 1828-1835, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="31400079">Brands MT, Smeekens EAJ, Takes RP, et al.: Time patterns of recurrence and second primary tumors in a large cohort of patients treated for oral cavity cancer. Cancer Med 8 (12): 5810-5819, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_910"><Title>Taste Disorder</Title><Para id="_1274">Dysgeusia, taste disorder, can be a prominent symptom in patients who are receiving chemotherapy or head/neck radiation.<Reference refidx="1"/> Etiology is likely associated with several factors, including direct neurotoxicity to taste buds, xerostomia, infection, and psychologic conditioning. Also, cancer treatments may impair taste bud cell regeneration, leading to a diminished function.<Reference refidx="2"/>   In addition, taste dysfunction can be associated with damage caused by graft-versus-host disease to the taste perception units. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_1069" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">GVHD</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_912">Patients receiving chemotherapy may experience unpleasant taste secondary to diffusion of drug into the oral cavity. In addition, patients often describe dysgeusia in the early weeks after cessation of cytotoxic therapy that has a negative impact on quality of life. Taste disturbances during chemotherapy are influenced by nausea and reduced appetite, so they can impact nutrition.   This symptom is generally reversible, and taste sensation returns to normal in the ensuing months. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000276584" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/appetite-loss/nutrition-hp-pdq">Nutrition in Cancer Care</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_1214">By comparison, a total fractionated radiation dose higher than 3,000 Gy reduces acuity of sweet, sour, bitter, and salt tastes.  Damage to the
microvilli and outer surface of taste cells has been proposed as the
principal mechanism for loss of the sense of taste. Even patients with non-oral head and neck cancer frequently show disturbed taste when they are treated with mouth-sparing radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20495984">Hovan AJ, Williams PM, Stevenson-Moore P, et al.: A systematic review of dysgeusia induced by cancer therapies. Support Care Cancer 18 (8): 1081-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="26820877">Epstein JB, Smutzer G, Doty RL: Understanding the impact of taste changes in oncology care. Support Care Cancer 24 (4): 1917-31, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="31345378">Barbosa da Silva JL, Doty RL, Miyazaki JVMK, et al.: Gustatory disturbances occur in patients with head and neck cancer who undergo radiotherapy not directed to the oral cavity. Oral Oncol 95: 115-119, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_913"><Title>Medication-Related Osteonecrosis of the Jaw</Title><SummarySection id="_1215"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_1216">Bisphosphonates are potent inhibitors of osteoclasts. They are used in cancer patients with skeletal metastases, including breast, prostate, or lung cancer, and in patients with multiple myeloma. Bisphosphonates are also used to treat hypercalcemia of malignancy and to prevent osteoporosis in patients with cancer.<Reference refidx="1"/> <Reference refidx="2"/> For more information on bisphosphonates, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062738#_387" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-hp-pdq">Bisphosphonates and denosumab</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Pain.</Para><Para id="_1219">Clinical trials reveal that antiangiogenic drugs  can be associated with the development of medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw (MRONJ) when used as a single drug or in combination with bone-modifying agents (BMAs). When antiangiogenics are used with bisphosphonates, the risk of MRONJ increases significantly.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_1220">Osteonecrosis of the jaw is no longer a problem exclusively associated with the use of bisphosphonates; it is also associated with the use of other drugs such as the monoclonal antibody denosumab and antiangiogenics such as bevacizumab and sorafenib. For this reason, the term <Strong>MRONJ,</Strong> rather than the term <Strong>bisphosphonate-related osteonecrosis of the jaw,</Strong>  should be used to refer to bone necrosis associated with pharmacological therapies.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Table id="_1436"><Title>Table 13.  Cancer Drugs and Biologics Associated With Medication-Related Osteonecrosis of the Jaw</Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColWidth="20.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Generic Drug (Trade Name)</entry><entry>Indication</entry><entry>Class of Drug</entry><entry>Mode of Action</entry><entry>Reported to Cause MRONJ?</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0">GIST = gastrointestinal stromal tumor; MRONJ = medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw; RANKL = receptor activator of nuclear factor kappa beta ligand; VEGF = vascular endothelial growth factor.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Zoledronic acid </entry><entry>Bone metastasis; bone loss from cancer therapy)</entry><entry>Bisphosphonate </entry><entry>Inhibition of osteoclasts</entry><entry>Yes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Pamidronate </entry><entry>Bone loss from cancer therapy</entry><entry>Bisphosphonate </entry><entry>Inhibition of osteoclasts</entry><entry>Yes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Alendronate </entry><entry>Bone loss from cancer therapy</entry><entry>Bisphosphonate </entry><entry>Inhibition of osteoclasts</entry><entry>Yes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Denosumab </entry><entry> Bone metastasis; osteoporosis; bone loss from cancer therapy</entry><entry>Humanized monoclonal antibody </entry><entry>Suppression of bone remodeling by inhibition of RANKL</entry><entry>Yes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Bevacizumab </entry><entry>Metastatic colorectal cancer; nonsquamous non-small cell lung cancer; metastatic breast cancer; glioblastoma; metastatic renal cell carcinoma</entry><entry>Antiangiogenic</entry><entry>Inhibition of angiogenesis by blocking the action of VEGF</entry><entry>Yes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sunitinib </entry><entry>Advanced renal cell carcinoma; GIST</entry><entry>Antiangiogenic</entry><entry>Inhibition of angiogenesis by blocking VEGF tyrosine kinase</entry><entry>Yes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Sorafenib </entry><entry>Renal cell carcinoma; hepatocellular carcinoma</entry><entry>Antiangiogenic</entry><entry>Inhibition of angiogenesis by blocking VEGF tyrosine kinase</entry><entry>Yes, when combined with bone-modifying agent</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1221"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_1222">The occurrence of MRONJ ranges between 1% and 8% in patients treated with a BMA for bone metastases or multiple myeloma, and between 0 and 1.8% in cancer patients treated with adjuvant BMA for osteoporosis prevention.<Reference refidx="8"/>  The prevalence of MRONJ varies according to study design, diagnostic criteria, type of BMA, and dosage.  MRONJ lesions are also more prevalent in areas with thin mucosa overlying bone prominences, such as tori, exostoses, and the mylohyoid ridge.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1223"><Title>Diagnosis</Title><Para id="_1224">A diagnosis of MRONJ is based on the following factors:<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_1225" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Exposed bone or bone that can be probed through an intraoral or extra oral fistula(e) in the maxillofacial region and that does not heal within 8 weeks.</ListItem><ListItem>Patient has received a BMA or angiogenic inhibitor agent.</ListItem><ListItem>Patient has no history of head and neck radiation.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1226">It is also possible that symptoms of dental disease, periodontal disease, or both may be present, without visible exposed bone.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Table id="_1437"><Title>Table 14.  Bone-Modifying Agents and Risk of Medication-Related Osteonecrosis of the Jaw<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="6"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="16.42%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="9.60%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="18.05%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="22.19%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColWidth="16.52%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColWidth="17.19%"/><THead><Row><entry>Drug</entry><entry>Indication</entry><entry>Route</entry><entry>Dose (mg)</entry><entry>Schedule</entry><entry>Frequency of MRONJ, %<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col0">IV = intravenous; MRONJ = medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw; SC = subcutaneous.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Yarom et al.<Reference refidx="8"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Risk of MRONJ varies by duration of treatment.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col5" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>c</Superscript>The estimate of 6.9% is from the open-label extension phase of two phase III studies.<Reference refidx="7"/> It is not adjusted for patient-years of exposure or patient follow-up and does not include cases that occurred during the blinded treatment phase. The patient-year adjusted incidence of confirmed MRONJ was 1.1% during the first year of denosumab treatment, 3.7% in the second year, and 4.6% per year thereafter.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Pamidronate</entry><entry>Bone metastasis of solid tumors; multiple myeloma</entry><entry>IV</entry><entry>90</entry><entry>Every 3-4 wk</entry><entry>3.2–5.0<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry>Zoledronic acid</entry><entry>Bone metastasis of solid tumors</entry><entry>IV</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>Every 3–4 wk or 12 wk</entry><entry>1.0–8.0<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Adjuvant treatment</entry><entry>IV</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>Every 3–6 mo</entry><entry>0–1.8<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Denosumab</entry><entry>Bone metastasis of solid tumors</entry><entry>SC</entry><entry>120</entry><entry>Every 4 wk</entry><entry>0.7–6.9<Superscript>c</Superscript><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>  </entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>Adjuvant treatment</entry><entry>SC</entry><entry>60</entry><entry>Every 6 mo</entry><entry>0<Reference refidx="19"/> </entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1227"><Title>Staging of MRONJ</Title><Para id="_1228">A well-established staging system should be used to quantify the severity and extent of MRONJ and to guide management decisions. The same system should be used throughout the patient’s MRONJ course of case. Diagnostic imaging may be used as an adjunct to these staging systems. Optimally, staging should be performed by a clinician who is experienced with the management of MRONJ.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_1229">The following two staging systems represent the most frequently used scales, as reported in the literature:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1230" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>American Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons (AAOMS) system.<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem>Osteonecrosis of the jaw severity scale (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events).<Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1231">In 2009, AAOMS added a stage 0, which refers to any symptoms of bone pain, fistulous track formation, abscess formation, and altered sensory function. It also includes abnormal radiographic findings that, in the absence of a fistula to bone or frank bone exposure, extend beyond the confines of the alveolar bone as a definitive precursor to MRONJ in patients receiving BMA therapy. The risk of a patient's stage 0 disease progressing to a higher disease stage remains unclear, although case studies suggest that such progression may occur in up to 50% of patients.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_1232">The International Task Force of Osteonecrosis of the Jaw expressed concern that the use of stage 0 terminology may lead to overdiagnosis of MRONJ because initial presenting symptoms may ultimately lead to an alternative diagnosis.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/>  The Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer/International Society of Oral Oncology/American Society of Clinical Oncology Expert Panel shares these concerns and suggests considering stage 0 as an indicator of increased risk of MRONJ. Identifying the increased risk status could prompt a referral to a dental specialist for close follow-up with assessment for early-stage MRONJ, should it develop, to optimize oral health.</Para><Table id="_1438"><Title>Table 15.  Staging and Treatment Strategies for Medication-Related Osteonecrosis of the Jaw<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>MRONJ Staging</entry><entry>Clinical and Radiographic Presentations</entry><entry>Treatment Strategies</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col0">IV = intravenous; MRONJ = medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Yarom et al.<Reference refidx="8"/> and Ruggiero et al.<Reference refidx="6"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>At-risk category</entry><entry>No apparent necrotic bone in patients who have been treated with either oral or IV bisphosphonates</entry><entry>No treatment indicated; patient education and reduction of modifiable risk factors</entry></Row><Row><entry>Increased risk</entry><entry>No clinical evidence of necrotic bone, but nonspecific clinical findings and symptoms</entry><entry>Systemic management, including use of pain medication and close scrutiny and follow-up; refer to dental specialist and follow up every 8 wk with communication of lesion status to oncologist; patient education and reduction of modifiable risk factors</entry></Row><Row><entry>Stage 1</entry><entry>Exposed and necrotic bone in patients who are asymptomatic and have no evidence of infection</entry><entry>Antibacterial mouth rinse; clinical follow-up every 3 mo; patient education; review of indications for continued bisphosphonate therapy</entry></Row><Row><entry>Stage 2</entry><entry>Exposed and necrotic bone associated with infection, as evidenced by pain and erythema in the region of the exposed bone, with or without purulent drainage</entry><entry>Symptomatic treatment with oral antibiotics; oral antibacterial mouth rinse; pain control; superficial debridement to relieve irritation of soft tissue</entry></Row><Row><entry>Stage 3</entry><entry>Exposed and necrotic bone in patients with pain, infection, and one or more of the following: exposed and necrotic bone extending beyond the region of alveolar bone (i.e., inferior border and ramus in the mandible, maxillary sinus, and zygoma in the maxilla), resulting in pathological fracture, extraoral fistula, oral antral/oral nasal communication, or osteolysis extending to the inferior border of the mandible of sinus floor</entry><entry>Antibacterial mouth rinse; antibiotic therapy and pain control; surgical debridement/resection for longer-term palliation of infection and pain</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_1233"><Title>Management of MRONJ measures</Title><Para id="_1235">Aggressive surgical interventions (e.g., mucosal flap elevation, block resection of necrotic bone, soft tissue closer) may be used if MRONJ results in persistent symptoms or impacts function despite initial conservative treatment. Aggressive surgical intervention is not recommended for asymptomatic bone exposure. In advance of the aggressive surgical intervention, the multidisciplinary care team and the patient should thoroughly discuss the risks and benefits of the proposed intervention.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para><Table id="_1439"><Title>Table 16.  Proposed Terms to Characterize Osteonecrosis of the Jaw After Treatment<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColNum="1" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="2" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="20.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Term</entry><entry>Mucosal Coverage</entry><entry>Symptom/Pain</entry><entry>Sign of Infection/Inflammation</entry><entry>Radiographic Presentation</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0">VAS = visual analog scale.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Yarom et al.<Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Resolved</entry><entry>Complete healing</entry><entry>No pain</entry><entry>None</entry><entry>Trabecular pattern, formation lamina dura resorbed</entry></Row><Row><entry>Improving</entry><entry>Significant improvement (&gt;50% of mucosal coverage)</entry><entry>Significant improvement (&gt;50% reduction of pain, VAS)</entry><entry>Significant improvement (no signs of infection/inflammation)</entry><entry>Improved trabecular pattern, signs of sequestra</entry></Row><Row><entry>Stable</entry><entry>Mild improvement (&lt;50% of mucosal coverage)</entry><entry>Mild improvement (&lt;50% reduction of pain, VAS)</entry><entry>Mild improvement (mild signs of infection/inflammation)</entry><entry>No changes</entry></Row><Row><entry>Progressive</entry><entry>No improvement or worsening</entry><entry>No improvement or worsening</entry><entry>No improvement</entry><entry>Lytic changes, decreasing trabeculation, increased size of radiographic lesion</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1237"><Title>Reducing Risk of Development of MRONJ</Title><Para id="_1238">For cancer patients scheduled to receive a BMA in a nonurgent setting, oral care assessment (including a comprehensive dental, periodontal, and oral radiographic exam, when feasible to do so) is undertaken before therapy is initiated. After  the assessment, the dentist and oncologist will develop and implement a dental care plan and coordinate with each other to ensure that medically necessary dental procedures are undertaken before a BMA is initiated. The dentist will follow up on a routine schedule once therapy with a BMA has started.</Para><Table id="_1440"><Title>Table 17.  Complete, Partial, and Minimal Dental Evaluation Protocols, Based on Dental and/or Periodontal Pathology<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Dental Pathology</entry><entry>Complete<Superscript>b</Superscript> </entry><entry>Partial<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry><entry>Minimal, Incomplete, or No Clearance<Superscript>d</Superscript> </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from  Hong et al.<Reference refidx="25"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Adapted from Haytac et al.<Reference refidx="26"/> and Melkos et al.<Reference refidx="27"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Adapted from Schuuhuis et al.<Reference refidx="28"/> and Tsuji et al.<Reference refidx="29"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>d</Superscript>Adapted from Haytac et al.,<Reference refidx="26"/> Melkos et al.,<Reference refidx="27"/> Schuuhuis et al.,<Reference refidx="28"/>, Tsuji et al.<Reference refidx="29"/>, and Gurgan et al.<Reference refidx="30"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Caries</entry><entry>Restore all teeth</entry><entry>Restore mild/moderate caries if time permits</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Intervene only if symptomatic</entry></Row><Row><entry>Severe caries/pulp involvement/dental abscess</entry><entry>Perform root canal treatment or extraction</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Apical periodontitis</entry><entry>Retreat</entry><entry>Treat symptomatic lesions and lesions &gt;5 mm </entry></Row><Row><entry>Perform apicoectomy</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Observe asymptomatic lesions and lesions &lt;5 mm </entry><entry MoreRows="2"/></Row><Row><entry>Extract teeth </entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Advanced periodontal disease</entry><entry>Extract teeth with:</entry><entry>Extract teeth with:</entry></Row><Row><entry>– Probing depth &gt;6 mm</entry><entry>– Probing depth &gt;8 mm</entry><entry MoreRows="4"/></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry>– Furcation I, II, III; Mobility III</entry><entry>– Mobility III</entry></Row><Row><entry>– Severe inflammation</entry><entry>– Severe inflammation</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Partially erupted third molars</entry><entry MoreRows="1">Extract partially erupted third molars</entry><entry>Observe asymptomatic teeth </entry></Row><Row><entry>Extract partially erupted third molars with purulence of pericoronitis </entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_1239">Members of the multidisciplinary team should address modifiable risk factors for MRONJ with the patient as early as possible. These risk factors include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1240" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Dental extractions.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/></ListItem><ListItem>Other oral surgeries.<Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="34"/></ListItem><ListItem>Ill-fitting dentures.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="35"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Intravenous bisphosphonates (pamidronate, zoledronic acid, denosumab).<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="33"/></ListItem><ListItem>Time on medication.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="36"/></ListItem><ListItem>Poor dental and periodontal health.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="37"/></ListItem><ListItem>Tobacco use.<Reference refidx="38"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1242">Elective dentoalveolar surgical procedures (e.g., medically unnecessary extractions, alveoplasties, and implants) should not be performed during active therapy with a BMA at an oncologic dose. Exceptions may be considered when a dental specialist with expertise in prevention and treatment of MRONJ has reviewed the benefits and risks of the proposed invasive procedure with the patient and the oncology team.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_1243">If dentoalveolar surgery is performed, the dental specialist must evaluate patients frequently until full mucosal coverage of the surgical site has occurred. Communication with the oncologist regarding the status of healing is encouraged, particularly when considering future use of BMA.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_1244">For patients with cancer who are receiving a BMA at an oncologic dose, there is insufficient evidence to support or refute discontinuation of the BMA before dentoalveolar surgery. Administration of the BMA may be deferred at the discretion of the treating physician, in consultation with the patient and oral health-provider.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="39"/></Para><Table id="_1441"><Title>Table 18.  Daily Oral Care Plan for Patients (Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer/International Society of Oral Oncology)<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Intervention</entry><entry>Basic Oral Care Plan</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col1" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Yarom et al.<Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Flossing</entry><entry>Floss at least once/d; waxed floss may be easier to use and minimize trauma to the gingivae.</entry></Row><Row><entry>If flossing causes bleeding of the gums that does not stop after 2 minutes, consult oncology team.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Brushing</entry><entry>Use a small, ultra-soft-headed, round-end, bristle toothbrush (an ultrasonic toothbrush may be acceptable).</entry></Row><Row><entry>Rinse toothbrush in hot water to soften brush before using.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5"/><entry>Use prescription-strength fluoride toothpaste; spit out the foam but do not rinse the mouth.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Use remineralizing pastes and chewing gum containing calcium and phosphate.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Brush within 30 min after eating and before bed; include the gingival portion of the tooth and periodontal sulcus.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Brush tongue gently from back to front.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Rinse brush after use in hot water and allow to air dry.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Change toothbrush when bristles are not standing up straight.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">For patients with dentures</entry><entry>Remove dentures before brushing.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Brush and rinse dentures after meals and at bedtime.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Remove from mouth for long periods (at least 8 hours per 24 hours) and soak in rinsing solution.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Rinsing</entry><entry>Rinse the oral cavity vigorously to help maintain moisture in the mouth, remove remaining debris, and reduce  accumulation of plaque and infection.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Rinse, swish, and spit with a bland rinse (1 tsp salt and 1 tsp baking soda in 4 c water) several times a day.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Avoid club soda because of the presence of carbonic acids.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Commercial mouthwashes with alcohol base or astringent properties are not recommended for patients with oral complications.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Debride only if absolutely necessary and if loose tissue causes gagging or choking.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Moisturizing the oral cavity</entry><entry>Moisturize the mouth with water, artificial saliva products, or other water-soluble lubricants for use inside the mouth.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Avoid glycerin or lemon-glycerin swabs, as they dry the mouth and do not moisturize.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1"/><entry>Apply lubricant after each cleaning, at bedtime, and as needed. Apply water-based lubricant more frequently.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Rinse often with basic mouth rinse.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Lip care</entry><entry>To keep lips lubricated and moisturized, use only animal- or plant-based oils such as beeswax, cocoa butter, and lanolin. Avoid petroleum-based products, as these cause drying and cracking.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Visit the dentist at least every 6 mo.</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>Notify dentist or oncologist of any oral signs or symptoms.</entry><entry/></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="31532726">Shapiro CL, Van Poznak C, Lacchetti C, et al.: Management of Osteoporosis in Survivors of Adult Cancers With Nonmetastatic Disease: ASCO Clinical Practice Guideline. J Clin Oncol 37 (31): 2916-2946, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16383047">Migliorati CA, Casiglia J, Epstein J, et al.: Managing the care of patients with bisphosphonate-associated osteonecrosis: an American Academy of Oral Medicine position paper. J Am Dent Assoc 136 (12): 1658-68, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23642545">Smidt-Hansen T, Folkmar TB, Fode K, et al.: Combination of zoledronic Acid and targeted therapy is active but may induce osteonecrosis of the jaw in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma. J Oral Maxillofac Surg 71 (9): 1532-40, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="30353228">Nicolatou-Galitis O, Kouri M, Papadopoulou E, et al.: Osteonecrosis of the jaw related to non-antiresorptive medications: a systematic review. Support Care Cancer 27 (2): 383-394, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="30055439">Otto S, Pautke C, Van den Wyngaert T, et al.: Medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw: Prevention, diagnosis and management in patients with cancer and bone metastases. Cancer Treat Rev 69: 177-187, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="25234529">Ruggiero SL, Dodson TB, Fantasia J, et al.: American Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons position paper on medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw--2014 update. J Oral Maxillofac Surg 72 (10): 1938-56, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26335402">Stopeck AT, Fizazi K, Body JJ, et al.: Safety of long-term denosumab therapy: results from the open label extension phase of two phase 3 studies in patients with metastatic breast and prostate cancer. Support Care Cancer 24 (1): 447-455, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="31329513">Yarom N, Shapiro CL, Peterson DE, et al.: Medication-Related Osteonecrosis of the Jaw: MASCC/ISOO/ASCO Clinical Practice Guideline. J Clin Oncol 37 (25): 2270-2290, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="26493811">Khan A, Morrison A, Cheung A, et al.: Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ): diagnosis and management in 2015. Osteoporos Int 27 (3): 853-859, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20863761">Gimsing P, Carlson K, Turesson I, et al.: Effect of pamidronate 30 mg versus 90 mg on physical function in patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma (Nordic Myeloma Study Group): a double-blind, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 11 (10): 973-82, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="17804475">Jadu F, Lee L, Pharoah M, et al.: A retrospective study assessing the incidence, risk factors and comorbidities of pamidronate-related necrosis of the jaws in multiple myeloma patients. Ann Oncol 18 (12): 2015-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="28030702">Himelstein AL, Foster JC, Khatcheressian JL, et al.: Effect of Longer-Interval vs Standard Dosing of Zoledronic Acid on Skeletal Events in Patients With Bone Metastases: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 317 (1): 48-58, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="19805682">Vahtsevanos K, Kyrgidis A, Verrou E, et al.: Longitudinal cohort study of risk factors in cancer patients of bisphosphonate-related osteonecrosis of the jaw. J Clin Oncol 27 (32): 5356-62, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="30591866">Coleman RE, Collinson M, Gregory W, et al.: Benefits and risks of adjuvant treatment with zoledronic acid in stage II/III breast cancer. 10 years follow-up of the AZURE randomized clinical trial (BIG 01/04). J Bone Oncol 13: 123-135, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="18711172">Hershman DL, McMahon DJ, Crew KD, et al.: Zoledronic acid prevents bone loss in premenopausal women undergoing adjuvant chemotherapy for early-stage breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 26 (29): 4739-45, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="21324674">Shapiro CL, Halabi S, Hars V, et al.: Zoledronic acid preserves bone mineral density in premenopausal women who develop ovarian failure due to adjuvant chemotherapy: final results from CALGB trial 79809. Eur J Cancer 47 (5): 683-9, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="23605142">Qi WX, Tang LN, He AN, et al.: Risk of osteonecrosis of the jaw in cancer patients receiving denosumab: a meta-analysis of seven randomized controlled trials. Int J Clin Oncol 19 (2): 403-10, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="23154554">Scagliotti GV, Hirsh V, Siena S, et al.: Overall survival improvement in patients with lung cancer and bone metastases treated with denosumab versus zoledronic acid: subgroup analysis from a randomized phase 3 study. J Thorac Oncol 7 (12): 1823-1829, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="26040499">Gnant M, Pfeiler G, Dubsky PC, et al.: Adjuvant denosumab in breast cancer (ABCSG-18): a multicentre, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet 386 (9992): 433-43, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="20">National Cancer Institute: Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 5.0. Bethesda, Md: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, National Institutes of Health, 2017. <ExternalRef xref="https://ctep.cancer.gov/protocolDevelopment/electronic_applications/docs/CTCAE_v5_Quick_Reference_8.5x11.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed Dec. 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="24332520">Schiodt M, Reibel J, Oturai P, et al.: Comparison of nonexposed and exposed bisphosphonate-induced osteonecrosis of the jaws: a retrospective analysis from the Copenhagen cohort and a proposal for an updated classification system. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol 117 (2): 204-13, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="25414052">Khan AA, Morrison A, Hanley DA, et al.: Diagnosis and management of osteonecrosis of the jaw: a systematic review and international consensus. J Bone Miner Res 30 (1): 3-23, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="27956123">Khan AA, Morrison A, Kendler DL, et al.: Case-Based Review of Osteonecrosis of the Jaw (ONJ) and Application of the International Recommendations for Management From the International Task Force on ONJ. J Clin Densitom 20 (1): 8-24, 2017 Jan - Mar.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="28527518">El-Rabbany M, Sgro A, Lam DK, et al.: Effectiveness of treatments for medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw: A systematic review and meta-analysis. J Am Dent Assoc 148 (8): 584-594.e2, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="28735355">Hong CHL, Hu S, Haverman T, et al.: A systematic review of dental disease management in cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 26 (1): 155-174, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="15641766">Haytac MC, Dogan MC, Antmen B: The results of a preventive dental program for pediatric patients with hematologic malignancies. Oral Health Prev Dent 2 (1): 59-65, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="12768464">Melkos AB, Massenkeil G, Arnold R, et al.: Dental treatment prior to stem cell transplantation and its influence on the posttransplantation outcome. Clin Oral Investig 7 (2): 113-5, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="27002936">Schuurhuis JM, Span LF, Stokman MA, et al.: Effect of leaving chronic oral foci untreated on infectious complications during intensive chemotherapy. Br J Cancer 114 (9): 972-8, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="25503612">Tsuji K, Shibuya Y, Akashi M, et al.: Prospective study of dental intervention for hematopoietic malignancy. J Dent Res 94 (2): 289-96, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="22487659">Gürgan CA, Özcan M, Karakuş Ö, et al.: Periodontal status and post-transplantation complications following intensive periodontal treatment in patients underwent allogenic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation conditioned with myeloablative regimen. Int J Dent Hyg 11 (2): 84-90, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="23212125">Barasch A, Cunha-Cruz J, Curro F, et al.: Dental risk factors for osteonecrosis of the jaws: a CONDOR case-control study. Clin Oral Investig 17 (8): 1839-45, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="23524435">Kato GF, Lopes RN, Jaguar GC, et al.: Evaluation of socket healing in patients undergoing bisphosphonate therapy: experience of a single Institution. Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal 18 (4): e650-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="29275525">Schiodt M, Vadhan-Raj S, Chambers MS, et al.: A multicenter case registry study on medication-related osteonecrosis of the jaw in patients with advanced cancer. Support Care Cancer 26 (6): 1905-1915, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="25662540">Vidal-Real C, Pérez-Sayáns M, Suárez-Peñaranda JM, et al.: Osteonecrosis of the jaws in 194 patients who have undergone intravenous bisphosphonate therapy in Spain. Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal 20 (3): e267-72, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="23582590">Tsao C, Darby I, Ebeling PR, et al.: Oral health risk factors for bisphosphonate-associated jaw osteonecrosis. J Oral Maxillofac Surg 71 (8): 1360-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="22093187">Smith MR, Saad F, Coleman R, et al.: Denosumab and bone-metastasis-free survival in men with castration-resistant prostate cancer: results of a phase 3, randomised, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet 379 (9810): 39-46, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="25319961">Gabbert TI, Hoffmeister B, Felsenberg D: Risk factors influencing the duration of treatment with bisphosphonates until occurrence of an osteonecrosis of the jaw in 963 cancer patients. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 141 (4): 749-58, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="26225065">Rabelo GD, Assunção JN, Chavassieux P, et al.: Bisphosphonate-Related Osteonecrosis of the Jaws and Its Array of Manifestations. J Maxillofac Oral Surg 14 (3): 699-705, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="23533811">Fusco V, Galassi C, Berruti A, et al.: Decreasing frequency of osteonecrosis of the jaw in cancer and myeloma patients treated with bisphosphonates: the experience of the oncology network of piedmont and aosta valley (north-Western Italy). ISRN Oncol 2013: 672027, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_928"><Title>Special Considerations in Pediatric Populations</Title><Para id="_929">There has been a marked increase in the survival rates of childhood cancers because of advances in cancer therapy. However, this progress has resulted in an increase in the number of the late effects from antineoplastic therapy observed in children.<Reference refidx="1"/> Approximately 60% to 80% of childhood cancer survivors develop at least one chronic condition caused by previous cancer treatment.<Reference refidx="1"/> Altered dental growth and craniofacial development is a frequent complication in childhood cancer survivors who received high-dose chemotherapy and/or head and neck radiation.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343584" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-hp-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_930">The severity and location of dental and craniofacial abnormalities are typically associated with the type of cancer modality used and the age at which cancer therapy began.</Para><SummarySection id="_1253"><Title>Dental Abnormalities</Title><Para id="_1254">The reported incidence and types of dental abnormalities, such as hypodontia, may also alter craniofacial development and lead to malocclusion.</Para><Para id="_1255">The following cancer modalities have been associated with higher incidence and more severe dental defects:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1256" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>High-dose chemotherapy, especially that  involving alkylating agents (e.g., cyclophosphamide) and anthracyclines.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Multimodality cancer regimens.<Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem>Hematopoietic stem cell transplant conditioning regimens.<Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem><ListItem>Head and neck radiation.<Reference refidx="11"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>] For doses of 20 Gy or more, the odds ratio (OR) of developing at least one dental abnormality has been reported to be 5.6 (confidence interval [CI], 3.7–8.5) versus 1.3 (CI, 1.2–1.5) for radiation doses of 0 to 19 Gy.<Reference refidx="4"/> Even though modern conformal intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) has been suggested to minimize these effects, reports have shown that IMRT still results in both dental and craniofacial developmental abnormalities.<Reference refidx="12"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1257">The association between risk of dental abnormalities and age at time of cancer therapy ranges between age 3 years or younger to age 8 years.<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>]<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]  However, there appear to be more reports documenting that children younger than 5 years at the time of chemotherapy are at increased risk of developing dental abnormalities. For head and neck radiation with doses 20 Gy or higher, the OR of having at least one dental abnormality was 5.6 for those aged 0 to 5 years and 9.6 for those aged 6 to 10 years.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_1258">The impact of cancer therapy on dental age is unclear, with one study <Reference refidx="15"/>  reporting an advanced dental age and other studies reporting either no difference <Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>  or a delay in dental age.<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663087" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: III</LOERef>];<Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000663072" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: II</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="29556926">Crowder SL, Douglas KG, Yanina Pepino M, et al.: Nutrition impact symptoms and associated outcomes in post-chemoradiotherapy head and neck cancer survivors: a systematic review. J Cancer Surviv 12 (4): 479-494, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="24781353">Effinger KE, Migliorati CA, Hudson MM, et al.: Oral and dental late effects in survivors of childhood cancer: a Children's Oncology Group report. Support Care Cancer 22 (7): 2009-19, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24424790">Gawade PL, Hudson MM, Kaste SC, et al.: A systematic review of dental late effects in survivors of childhood cancer. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (3): 407-16, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19834960">Kaste SC, Goodman P, Leisenring W, et al.: Impact of radiation and chemotherapy on risk of dental abnormalities: a report from the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study. Cancer 115 (24): 5817-27, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21523736">Hsieh SG, Hibbert S, Shaw P, et al.: Association of cyclophosphamide use with dental developmental defects and salivary gland dysfunction in recipients of childhood antineoplastic therapy. Cancer 117 (10): 2219-27, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="23336315">Nishimura S, Inada H, Sawa Y, et al.: Risk factors to cause tooth formation anomalies in chemotherapy of paediatric cancers. Eur J Cancer Care (Engl) 22 (3): 353-60, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="19484760">Maciel JC, de Castro CG, Brunetto AL, et al.: Oral health and dental anomalies in patients treated for leukemia in childhood and adolescence. Pediatr Blood Cancer 53 (3): 361-5, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9177429" MedlineID="97320578">Kaste SC, Hopkins KP, Jones D, et al.: Dental abnormalities in children treated for acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Leukemia 11 (6): 792-6, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="21254371">Cubukcu CE, Sevinir B, Ercan I: Disturbed dental development of permanent teeth in children with solid tumors and lymphomas. Pediatr Blood Cancer 58 (1): 80-4, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="15739206">Hölttä P, Hovi L, Saarinen-Pihkala UM, et al.: Disturbed root development of permanent teeth after pediatric stem cell transplantation. Dental root development after SCT. Cancer 103 (7): 1484-93, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="6728583">Jaffe N, Toth BB, Hoar RE, et al.: Dental and maxillofacial abnormalities in long-term survivors of childhood cancer: effects of treatment with chemotherapy and radiation to the head and neck. Pediatrics 73 (6): 816-23, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="27689858">Owosho AA, Brady P, Wolden SL, et al.: Long-term effect of chemotherapy-intensity-modulated radiation therapy (chemo-IMRT) on dentofacial development in head and neck rhabdomyosarcoma patients. Pediatr Hematol Oncol 33 (6): 383-392, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="11121653" MedlineID="20573313">Paulino AC, Simon JH, Zhen W, et al.: Long-term effects in children treated with radiotherapy for head and neck rhabdomyosarcoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 48 (5): 1489-95, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="20059589">Hutton A, Bradwell M, English M, et al.: The oral health needs of children after treatment for a solid tumour or lymphoma. Int J Paediatr Dent 20 (1): 15-23, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="19147312">Vasconcelos NP, Caran EM, Lee ML, et al.: Dental maturity assessment in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia after cancer therapy. Forensic Sci Int 184 (1-3): 10-4, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="25572724">Flores AP, Monti CF, Brunotto M: Dental and chronological age in children under oncological treatment. J Forensic Sci 60 (2): 453-6, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="18298546">Martin MB, Li CS, Rowland CC, et al.: Correlation of bone age, dental age, and chronological age in survivors of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukaemia. Int J Paediatr Dent 18 (3): 217-23, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="24745592">Bagattoni S, D'Alessandro G, Prete A, et al.: Oral health and dental late adverse effects in children in remission from malignant disease. A pilot case-control study in Italian children. Eur J Paediatr Dent 15 (1): 45-50, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="3162858">Purdell-Lewis DJ, Stalman MS, Leeuw JA, et al.: Long term results of chemotherapy on the developing dentition: caries risk and developmental aspects. Community Dent Oral Epidemiol 16 (2): 68-71, 1988.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_931"><Title>Special Considerations in Geriatric Populations</Title><Para id="_932">An aging population is living with more chronic diseases, comorbidities, multidrug use, and cancers. The special care needs of the geriatric population should be assessed and considered in the development of cancer treatment protocols.</Para><Para id="_1268">Oncologists need to promote oral health in frail older adults when they are about to undergo a cancer therapy that could have permanent or temporary impacts on oral/dental health. Pretherapy oral/dental evaluation is mandatory, and the follow-up of an older adult with frailty involves close monitoring (face to face or telehealth) and education of caregivers regarding oral and dental hygiene.</Para><Para id="_1269">Quality-of-life (QOL) considerations should be a fundamental component in cancer management, whatever a patient’s age. In the field of oncology, it is apparent that the geriatric cancer population has special oral/dental needs. Special precautions are advised for this patient group. Dental professionals need to be part of the geriatric oncology team for better support of QOL.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_916"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (02/16/2024)</Title><Para id="_917">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_918">This summary was renamed from Oral Complications of Chemotherapy and Head/Neck Radiation.</Para><Para id="_934">This summary was comprehensively reviewed and extensively revised.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062870#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the pathophysiology and treatment of oral complications of cancer therapies. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Megan Reimann, PharmD, BCOP (Total CME)</ListItem><ListItem>Andrea Ruskin, MD (VA Connecticut Healthcare System)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000660468" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389320]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-02-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
