<Summary id="CDR0000062872" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>The Rare Cancers of Childhood Treatment summary addresses the treatment options for many uncommon childhood cancers. Get information about the diagnosis and treatment of cancers of the head and neck, chest, genitourinary system, and others in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp/rare-childhood-cancers-pdq">Rare Cancers of Childhood (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/patient/rare-childhood-cancers-pdq">Rare Cancers of Childhood (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038073">unusual cancers of childhood</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1556">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of rare cancers of childhood. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_1557">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Adrenocortical carcinoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Breast cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Carcinoma of unknown primary</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Cardiac tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Chordoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Colorectal cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Esophageal Cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Esthesioneuroblastoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Gastric cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Juvenile granulosa cell tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Laryngeal cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Lung cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Melanoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Mesothelioma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Multiple endocrine neoplasia</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Nasopharyngeal cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Oral cavity cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Pancreatic cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Papillomatosis</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Paraganglioma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Pheochromocytoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Pleuropulmonary blastoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Salivary gland cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Skin cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Thymic Carcinoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Thymoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Unusual cancers of childhood</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Uveal melanoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Rare Cancers of Childhood Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Rare Cancers of Childhood Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Rare Cancers of Childhood Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_105"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038073">unusual cancers of childhood</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Rare Cancers of Childhood</Title><SummarySection id="_641"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_643">Cancer in children and adolescents is rare, although the overall incidence has slowly increased since 1975.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Children and adolescents with cancer should be referred to medical centers that have a multidisciplinary team of cancer specialists with experience treating the cancers that occur during childhood and adolescence. This multidisciplinary team approach incorporates the skills
of primary care physicians, pediatric surgeons, pathologists, pediatric radiation
oncologists, pediatric medical oncologists and hematologists, rehabilitation
specialists, pediatric oncology nurses, social workers, child-life professionals, psychologists, nutritionists, and others to ensure that children receive treatment, supportive care, and rehabilitation
to achieve optimal survival and quality of life.  For specific information about supportive care for children and adolescents with cancer, see the summaries on <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/supportive-care">Supportive and Palliative Care</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_644">The American Academy of Pediatrics has outlined guidelines for
pediatric cancer centers and their role in the treatment of children and adolescents
with cancer.<Reference refidx="2"/>  At
these centers, clinical trials are available for most  types of cancer that occur in children and adolescents, and the opportunity
to participate is offered to most patients and their families.  Clinical
trials for children and adolescents diagnosed with cancer are generally
designed to compare potentially better therapy with current standard therapy.  Other types of clinical trials test novel therapies when there is no standard therapy for a cancer diagnosis. Most of the progress in identifying curative
therapies for childhood cancers has been achieved through clinical trials.
Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_645">Dramatic improvements in survival have been achieved for children and adolescents with cancer. Between 1975 and 2020, childhood cancer mortality decreased by more than 50%.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  Childhood and adolescent cancer survivors require close monitoring because side effects  of cancer therapy may persist or develop months or years after treatment.  For information about the incidence, type, and monitoring of late effects in childhood and adolescent cancer survivors, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343584" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-hp-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_646">Childhood cancer is a rare disease, with about 15,000 cases diagnosed annually in the United States in individuals younger than 20 years.<Reference refidx="6"/> The U.S. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.congress.gov/107/plaws/publ280/PLAW-107publ280.pdf">Rare Diseases Act of 2002</ExternalRef> defines a rare disease as one that affects populations smaller than 200,000 people. Therefore, all pediatric cancers are considered rare.</Para><Para id="_2119">The designation of a rare tumor is not uniform among pediatric and adult groups. In adults, rare cancers are defined as those with an annual incidence of fewer than six cases per 100,000 people. They account for up to 24% of all cancers diagnosed in the European Union and about 20% of all cancers diagnosed in the United States.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> In children and adolescents, the designation of a rare tumor is not uniform among international groups, as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1323" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A consensus effort between the European Union Joint Action on Rare Cancers and the European Cooperative Study Group for Rare Pediatric Cancers (EXPeRT) estimated that 11% of all cancers in patients younger than 20 years could be categorized as very rare. This consensus group defined very rare cancers as those with annual incidences of fewer than 2 cases per 1 million people. However, three additional histologies (thyroid carcinoma, melanoma, and testicular cancer) with incidences of more than 2 cases per 1 million people were also included  in the very rare group due to a lack of knowledge and expertise in the management of these tumors.<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Children's Oncology Group (COG) defines rare pediatric cancers as those listed in the International Classification of Childhood Cancer subgroup XI, which includes thyroid cancers, melanomas and nonmelanoma skin cancers, and multiple types of carcinomas (e.g., adrenocortical carcinomas, nasopharyngeal carcinomas, and most adult-type carcinomas such as breast cancers and colorectal cancers).<Reference refidx="10"/>  These diagnoses account for about 5% of the cancers diagnosed in children aged 0 to 14 years and about 27% of the cancers diagnosed in adolescents aged 15 to 19 years.<Reference refidx="4"/><Para id="_2120"> Most cancers in subgroup XI are either melanomas or thyroid cancers, with other cancer types accounting for only 2% of the cancers in children aged 0 to 14 years and 9.3% of the cancers in adolescents aged 15 to 19 years.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1383">These rare cancers are extremely challenging to study because of the relatively few patients with any individual diagnosis, the predominance of rare cancers in the adolescent population, and the small number of clinical trials for adolescents with rare cancers.</Para><Para id="_649">Some investigators have used large databases, such as the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program and the National Cancer Database, to gain more insight into these rare childhood cancers. However, these database studies are limited. Several initiatives to study rare pediatric cancers have been developed by the COG and other international groups, including the Société Internationale D'Oncologie Pédiatrique (SIOP). The Gesellschaft für Pädiatrische Onkologie und Hämatologie  (GPOH) rare tumor project was founded in Germany in 2006.<Reference refidx="11"/> The Italian Tumori Rari in Eta Pediatrica (TREP) group was launched  in 2000,<Reference refidx="12"/> and the Polish Pediatric Rare Tumor Study Group was launched in 2002.<Reference refidx="13"/> In Europe, the rare tumor study groups from France, Germany, Italy, Poland, and the United Kingdom joined to become the EXPeRT group, focusing on international collaboration and analyses of specific rare tumor entities.<Reference refidx="14"/> Within the COG, efforts have concentrated on increasing accrual to COG  registries (Project Every Child) and tumor banking protocols, developing single-arm clinical trials, and increasing cooperation with adult cooperative group trials.<Reference refidx="15"/> The accomplishments and challenges of this initiative have been described in detail.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_650">The tumors listed in this summary are very diverse. They are arranged in
descending anatomic order, from infrequent tumors of the head and neck to rare
tumors of the urogenital tract and skin.  All of these cancers are rare enough
that pediatric hospitals might see less than a handful of some histologies in several years. Most of the histologies listed here occur more frequently in adults.  Information about these tumors may also be found in sources relevant to
adults with cancer.
</Para><Para id="_2406">The Rare Cancers of Childhood Treatment summary has been separated into individual summaries for each topic. Please use the lists below or the following link to find the individual summaries: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Cancer Information Summaries: Pediatric Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20404250">Smith MA, Seibel NL, Altekruse SF, et al.: Outcomes for children and adolescents with cancer: challenges for the twenty-first century. J Clin Oncol 28 (15): 2625-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2">American Academy of Pediatrics: Standards for pediatric cancer centers. Pediatrics  134 (2): 410-4, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/134/2/410">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24853691">Smith MA, Altekruse SF, Adamson PC, et al.: Declining childhood and adolescent cancer mortality. Cancer 120 (16): 2497-506, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4">National Cancer Institute: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://NCCRExplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Surveillance Research Program, National Cancer Institute: SEER*Explorer: An interactive website for SEER cancer statistics. 	Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statistics-network/explorer/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24488779">Ward E, DeSantis C, Robbins A, et al.: Childhood and adolescent cancer statistics, 2014. CA Cancer J Clin 64 (2): 83-103, 2014 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28687376">Gatta G, Capocaccia R, Botta L, et al.: Burden and centralised treatment in Europe of rare tumours: results of RARECAREnet-a population-based study. Lancet Oncol 18 (8): 1022-1039, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28542893">DeSantis CE, Kramer JL, Jemal A: The burden of rare cancers in the United States. CA Cancer J Clin 67 (4): 261-272, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="30785015">Ferrari A, Brecht IB, Gatta G, et al.: Defining and listing very rare cancers of paediatric age: consensus of the Joint Action on Rare Cancers in cooperation with the European Cooperative Study Group for Pediatric Rare Tumors. Eur J Cancer 110: 120-126, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20956621">Pappo AS, Krailo M, Chen Z, et al.: Infrequent tumor initiative of the Children's Oncology Group: initial lessons learned and their impact on future plans. J Clin Oncol 28 (33): 5011-6, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="19437371">Brecht IB, Graf N, Schweinitz D, et al.: Networking for children and adolescents with very rare tumors: foundation of the GPOH Pediatric Rare Tumor Group. Klin Padiatr 221 (3): 181-5, 2009 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="17049226">Ferrari A, Bisogno G, De Salvo GL, et al.: The challenge of very rare tumours in childhood: the Italian TREP project. Eur J Cancer 43 (4): 654-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="15686048">Balcerska A, Godziński J, Bień E, et al.: [Rare tumours--are they really rare in the Polish children population?]. Przegl Lek 61 (Suppl 2): 57-61, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="23143769">Bisogno G, Ferrari A, Bien E, et al.: Rare cancers in children - The EXPeRT Initiative: a report from the European Cooperative Study Group on Pediatric Rare Tumors. Klin Padiatr 224 (6): 416-20, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="24889136">Musselman JR, Spector LG, Krailo MD, et al.: The Children's Oncology Group Childhood Cancer Research Network (CCRN): case catchment in the United States. Cancer 120 (19): 3007-15, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="26304909">Pappo AS, Furman WL, Schultz KA, et al.: Rare Tumors in Children: Progress Through Collaboration. J Clin Oncol 33 (27): 3047-54, 2015.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><Title>Head and Neck Cancers</Title><Para id="_1385">These cancers are seen very infrequently in patients younger than 15 years, and most of the evidence is derived from small case series or cohorts combining pediatric and adult patients.</Para><Para id="_2443">Childhood sarcomas often occur in the head and neck area and they are described in other summaries. Rare pediatric head and neck cancers include the following:</Para><SummarySection id="_107"><Title>Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_2411">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000784522" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Nasopharyngeal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_116"><Title>Esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_2412">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790381" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/esthesioneuroblastoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Esthesioneuroblastoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_108"><Title>Thyroid Tumors</Title><Para id="_2413">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790382" url="/types/thyroid/hp/child-thyroid-treatment-pdq">Childhood Thyroid Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_109"><Title>Oral Cavity Cancer</Title><Para id="_2414">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790383" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/oral-cavity-treatment-pdq">Childhood Oral Cavity Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_110"><Title>Salivary Gland Tumors </Title><Para id="_2415">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790384" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/salivary-gland-treatment-pdq">Childhood Salivary Gland Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_111"><Title>Laryngeal  Cancer and Papillomatosis </Title><Para id="_2416">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790385" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/laryngeal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Laryngeal  Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_141"><Title>NUT Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_2417">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790386" url="/types/midline/hp-child-midline-tract-carcinoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood NUT Carcinoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_112"><Title>Thoracic Cancers</Title><Para id="_1394">  The prognosis, diagnosis, classification, and
treatment of pediatric thoracic cancers are discussed below. These cancers are seen very infrequently in patients younger than 15 years, and most of the evidence is derived from case series.</Para><Para id="_2444">Rare pediatric thoracic cancers include the following:</Para><SummarySection id="_29"><Title>Breast Cancer</Title><Para id="_2418">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799416" url="/types/breast/hp/child-breast-treatment-pdq">Childhood Breast Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_837"><Title>Lung Cancer</Title><Para id="_1264">Most pulmonary malignant neoplasms in children result from metastatic disease. The approximate ratio of primary malignant tumors to metastatic disease is 1:5.<Reference refidx="1"/>  </Para><Para id="_947">The most common malignant primary tumors of the lung include the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_2126" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062872#_2452" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp/rare-childhood-cancers-pdq">Pulmonary inflammatory myofibroblastic tumors</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062872#_31" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp/rare-childhood-cancers-pdq">Tracheobronchial tumors</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062872#_33" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp/rare-childhood-cancers-pdq">Pleuropulmonary blastoma</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_2452"><Title>Pulmonary Inflammatory Myofibroblastic Tumors</Title><Para id="_2453">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000806827" url="/types/lung/hp/child-pulmonary-inflammatory-myofibroblastic-tumor-treatment-pdq">Childhood Pulmonary Inflammatory Myofibroblastic Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Tracheobronchial Tumors</Title><Para id="_2419">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799362" url="/types/lung/hp/child-tracheobronchial-treatment-pdq">Childhood Tracheobronchial Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><Title>Pleuropulmonary Blastoma</Title><Para id="_2420">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799361" url="/types/lung/hp/child-pleuropulmonary-blastoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Pleuropulmonary Blastoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Esophageal Cancer</Title><Para id="_2421">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799417" url="/types/esophageal/hp/child-esophageal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Esophageal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><Title>Thymoma and Thymic Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_2422">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799418" url="/types/thymoma/hp/child-thymoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Thymoma and Thymic Carcinoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><Title>Cardiac Tumors</Title><Para id="_2423">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799419" url="/types/cardiac/hp-child-cardiac-treatment-pdq">Childhood Cardiac Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18158138">Weldon CB, Shamberger RC: Pediatric pulmonary tumors: primary and metastatic. Semin Pediatr Surg 17 (1): 17-29, 2008.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_113"><Title>Abdominal Cancers</Title><Para id="_1404">The prognosis,
diagnosis, classification, and treatment of pediatric abdominal cancers are
discussed below. These cancers are seen very infrequently in patients younger than 15 years, and most of the evidence is derived from case series.
For information about kidney tumors, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062789" url="/types/kidney/hp/wilms-treatment-pdq">Wilms Tumor and Other Childhood Kidney Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_2445">Rare pediatric abdominal cancers include the following:</Para><SummarySection id="_51"><Title>Adrenocortical Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_2425">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799714" url="/types/adrenocortical/hp/child-adrenocortical-treatment-pdq">Childhood Adrenocortical Carcinoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_58"><Title>Gastric Cancer</Title><Para id="_2426">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799715" url="/types/stomach/hp/pediatric-gastric-treatment-pdq">Pediatric Gastric Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1354"><Title>Pancreatic Cancer</Title><Para id="_2427">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799716" url="/types/pancreatic/hp/child-pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Childhood Pancreatic Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><Title>Colorectal Cancer</Title><Para id="_2428">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799717" url="/types/colorectal/hp/child-colorectal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Colorectal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_73"><Title>Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors</Title><Para id="_2429">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799718" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/hp/pediatric-gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Pediatric Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_267"><Title>Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors (GIST)</Title><Para id="_2430">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799719" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/child-gist-treatment-pdq">Childhood Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_114"><Title>Genital/Urinary Tumors</Title><Para id="_1431">The prognosis, diagnosis, classification, and treatment of pediatric
genital/urinary tumors are discussed below. These tumors are seen very infrequently in patients younger than 15 years, and most of the evidence is derived from case series. 
</Para><Para id="_2446">Rare pediatric genital/urinary tumors include the following:</Para><SummarySection id="_77"><Title>Bladder Cancer</Title><Para id="_2431">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799767" url="/types/bladder/hp/child-bladder-treatment-pdq">Childhood Bladder Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_486"><Title>Testicular Cancer (Non–Germ Cell)</Title><Para id="_2432">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799768" url="/types/testicular/hp/child-testicular-treatment-pdq">Childhood Testicular Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><Title>Ovarian Cancer (Non–Germ Cell)</Title><Para id="_2433">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799769" url="/types/ovarian/hp/child-ovarian-treatment-pdq">Childhood Ovarian Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_181"><Title>Cervical and Vaginal Cancer</Title><Para id="_2434">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799770" url="/types/cervical/hp/child-cervical-vaginal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Cervical and Vaginal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_115"><Title>Other Rare Childhood Cancers</Title><Para id="_1442">The prognosis, diagnosis, classification, and treatment of other rare childhood cancers are discussed below.
 These cancers are seen very infrequently in patients younger than 15 years, and most of the evidence is derived from case series.</Para><Para id="_2447">Other rare childhood cancers include the following:</Para><SummarySection id="_45"><Title>Mesothelioma</Title><Para id="_2424">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799420" url="/types/mesothelioma/hp/child-mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Mesothelioma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_84"><Title>Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia (MEN) Syndromes</Title><Para id="_2435">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000800107" url="/types/multiple-endocrine-neoplasia/hp-child-men-syndromes-treatment-pdq">Childhood Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia (MEN) Syndromes Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_863"><Title>Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma</Title><Para id="_2436">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000800108" url="/types/pheochromocytoma/hp/child-pheochromocytoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><Title>Skin Cancer (Melanoma, Basal Cell Carcinoma [BCC], and Squamous Cell Carcinoma [SCC])</Title><Para id="_1227">For more information about specific genetic variants and related hereditary skin cancer syndromes, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000552637" url="/types/skin/hp/skin-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Skin Cancer</SummaryRef>. For information about uveal melanoma in children, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000800111" url="/types/eye/hp/child-intraocular-melanoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Intraocular (Uveal) Melanoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_698"><Title>Melanoma</Title><Para id="_2437">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000800109" url="/types/skin/hp/child-melanoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Melanoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_713"><Title>BCC and SCC</Title><Para id="_2438">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000800110" url="/types/skin/hp/child-skin-treatment-pdq">Childhood Basal Cell Carcinoma and Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Skin Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1607"><Title>Intraocular (Uveal) Melanoma</Title><Para id="_2439">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000800111" url="/types/eye/hp/child-intraocular-melanoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Intraocular (Uveal) Melanoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_195"><Title>Chordoma</Title><Para id="_2440">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000800112" url="/types/bone/hp/child-chordoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Chordoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_97"><Title>Cancer of Unknown Primary (CUP) Site</Title><Para id="_2441">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000800113" url="/types/unknown-primary/hp/child-unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Childhood Cancer of Unknown Primary (CUP) Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (09/27/2024)</Title><Para id="_124">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_2465">This summary was comprehensively reviewed.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062872#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp/rare-childhood-cancers-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of rare cancers of childhood. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Rare Cancers of Childhood Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Denise Adams, MD (Children's Hospital Boston)</ListItem><ListItem>Sally J. Cohen-Cutler, MD, MS (Children's Hospital of Philadelphia)</ListItem><ListItem>Karen J. Marcus, MD, FACR (Dana-Farber of Boston Children's Cancer Center and Blood Disorders Harvard Medical School)</ListItem><ListItem>William H. Meyer, MD</ListItem><ListItem>Paul A. Meyers, MD (Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Thomas A. Olson, MD (Aflac Cancer and Blood Disorders Center of Children's Healthcare of Atlanta - Egleston Campus)</ListItem><ListItem>Alberto S. Pappo, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>D. Williams Parsons, MD, PhD (Texas Children's Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Arthur Kim Ritchey, MD (Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC)</ListItem><ListItem>Carlos Rodriguez-Galindo, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Stephen J. Shochat, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Rare Cancers of Childhood Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp/rare-childhood-cancers-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp/rare-childhood-cancers-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389315]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-09-27</DateLastModified></Summary>
