<Summary id="CDR0000062879" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Prevention</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Cigarette smoking: Health Risks and How to Quit explains how smoking avoidance and cessation result in decreased incidence and mortality from cancer. Quit counseling and physician advice improve cessation rates. Get detailed information about smoking risks and quitting in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-hp-pdq">Cigarette Smoking: Health Risks and How to Quit (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-pdq">Cigarette Smoking: Health Risks and How to Quit (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041654">smoking cessation intervention</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041588">cancer prevention</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_308">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the prevention and cessation of cigarette smoking and the control of tobacco use. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_309">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer prevention</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>smoking cessation intervention</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Cigarette Smoking:  Health Risks and How to Quit (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Cigarette Smoking:  Health Risks and How to Quit (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Cigarette Smoking:  Health Risks and How to Quit</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_171">Note: The Overview section summarizes the published evidence on this topic. The rest of the summary describes the evidence in more detail.</Para><Para id="_368">A separate PDQ summary on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">Levels of Evidence for Cancer Screening and Prevention Studies</SummaryRef> is also available.</Para><Para id="_2">The   cancer prevention summaries in PDQ refer to cancer
prevention, defined as a reduction in the incidence of cancer.  The PDQ
includes summaries generally classified by histological type of cancer,
especially when there are known risk factors for the specific types of cancer. 
This summary addresses a specific risk factor, tobacco use, which is associated
with a large number of different cancers (and other chronic diseases) and
unequivocally contains human carcinogens.<Reference refidx="1"/> The focus of this summary is on
clinical interventions by health professionals that decrease the use of
tobacco.</Para><SummarySection id="_134"><Title>Effects of Smoking  Cessation</Title><Para id="_3">Based on    solid   evidence,  cigarette smoking causes  cancers of the lung, oral cavity and pharynx, larynx, esophagus, bladder, kidney, pancreas, stomach, uterine cervix, colon and rectum, liver, and acute myeloid leukemia.<Reference refidx="2"/> Smoking avoidance and smoking cessation result in decreased
incidence and mortality from cancer.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_176" Style="simple"><ListTitle>Description of the Evidence</ListTitle><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Evidence obtained from a randomized controlled trial (RCT).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnitude of Effects on Health Outcomes</Strong>: The relative risk (RR) of several cancers is much greater in cigarette smokers compared with nonsmokers (depending on the anatomical site of the cancer and the intensity and duration of smoking, the RR can range from twofold to tenfold or greater in smoking populations). A reduction of 15% is seen in the RR of all-cause mortality in heavy smokers subjected to intensive clinical cessation interventions.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_249"><Title>Physician or Nurse Advice and Smoking Cessation</Title><Para id="_250">Based on solid evidence, brief advice from a physician or nurse to stop smoking improves smoking cessation rates.</Para><ItemizedList id="_251" Style="simple"><ListTitle>Description of the Evidence</ListTitle><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Evidence obtained from RCTs.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnitude of Effects on Health Outcomes</Strong>: Physician advice improves cessation rates (RR, 1.66; 95%  confidence interval [CI], 1.42–1.94).<Reference refidx="4"/> Nurse advice improves cessation rates (RR, 1.29; 95% CI, 1.21–1.38).<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_424"><Title>Counseling and Smoking Cessation</Title><Para id="_6">Based on   solid  evidence,  counseling by a health professional improves smoking
cessation rates.</Para><ItemizedList id="_177" Style="simple"><ListTitle>Description of the Evidence</ListTitle><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Evidence obtained from  RCTs.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnitude of Effects on Health Outcomes</Strong>: Counseling improves cessation rates (odds ratio [OR], 1.44; 95% credibility interval, 1.22–1.70).<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><Title>Pharmacological Treatment and Smoking Cessation</Title><Para id="_9">Based on    solid evidence,  drug treatments, including nicotine replacement
therapies (NRTs)  (gum, patch, spray, lozenge,  and inhaler), selected antidepressant therapies (e.g.,
bupropion hydrochloride [HCI]), and  nicotinic receptor agonist therapy (varenicline), result in better smoking cessation rates than placebo.</Para><ItemizedList id="_178" Style="simple"><ListTitle>Description of the Evidence</ListTitle><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Evidence obtained from RCTs.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnitude of Effects on Health Outcomes</Strong>: NRTs, alone or in combination, improve cessation rates over placebo  after 6 months (RR, 1.55; 95% CI, 1.49–1.61).<Reference refidx="7"/>  Treatment with bupropion HCI improves cessation rates over placebo after 6 months (OR, 1.94; 95% CI, 1.72–2.19; RR, 1.60; 95% CI, 1.49–1.72).<Reference refidx="8"/> Varenicline therapy treatment improves cessation rates over placebo after 6 months (RR, 2.32; 95% CI, 2.15–2.51).<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_381"><Title>Pharmacological Treatment Combined With Counseling and Smoking Cessation</Title><Para id="_379">Based on solid evidence, drug treatments combined with counseling by a health professional result in better smoking cessation rates than drug treatments with minimal or no counseling support.</Para><ItemizedList id="_380" Style="simple">
     <ListTitle>Description of the Evidence</ListTitle><ListItem><Strong>Study Design</Strong>: Evidence obtained from RCTs.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Consistency</Strong>: Good.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Magnitude of Effects on Health Outcomes</Strong>: Drug treatments combined with counseling (behavioral support) improve cessation rates over drug treatments combined with minimal or no counseling support after 6 months (RR, 1.83; 95% CI, 1.68–1.98).<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>External Validity</Strong>: Good.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15285078">IARC Working Group on the Evaluation of Carcinogenic Risks to Humans: Tobacco smoke and involuntary smoking. IARC Monogr Eval Carcinog Risks Hum 83: 1-1438, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="2">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: The Health Consequences of Smoking—50 Years of Progress: A Report of the Surgeon General. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, CDC, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK179276/">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="3">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: Smoking Cessation: A Report of 
the Surgeon General.  U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Chronic Disease 
Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health, 2020. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/2020-cessation-sgr-full-report.pdf">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="23728631">Stead LF, Buitrago D, Preciado N, et al.: Physician advice for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2013 (5): CD000165, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="29243221">Rice VH, Heath L, Livingstone-Banks J, et al.: Nursing interventions for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 12 (12): CD001188, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="33411338">Hartmann-Boyce J, Livingstone-Banks J, Ordóñez-Mena JM, et al.: Behavioural interventions for smoking cessation: an overview and network meta-analysis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 1: CD013229, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="29852054">Hartmann-Boyce J, Chepkin SC, Ye W, et al.: Nicotine replacement therapy versus control for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 5 (5): CD000146, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="37230961">Hajizadeh A, Howes S, Theodoulou A, et al.: Antidepressants for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 5 (5): CD000031, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="37142273">Livingstone-Banks J, Fanshawe TR, Thomas KH, et al.: Nicotine receptor partial agonists for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 5 (5): CD006103, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="27009521">Stead LF, Koilpillai P, Fanshawe TR, et al.: Combined pharmacotherapy and behavioural interventions for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 3 (3): CD008286, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><Title>Evidence of Benefit</Title><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>Background</Title><Para id="_322">In the United States, smoking-related illnesses accounted for an estimated  
 480,000 deaths each year.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> On average, these deaths occur 12 years earlier than would
be expected, so the aggregate annual loss   exceeds  5 million life-years.<Reference refidx="3"/>  These
deaths are primarily due to smoking’s role as a major cause of cancer, cardiovascular disease,
and chronic lung disease.  The known adverse health effects also include other respiratory diseases and symptoms, nuclear cataract, hip fractures, reduced female fertility, diabetes, erectile dysfunction, rheumatoid arthritis, and diminished health status.  Maternal smoking during pregnancy is associated with fetal growth restriction, low birth weight, and complications of pregnancy.<Reference refidx="2"/> About 50% of
cancer deaths in the United States are
attributable to modifiable behavioral risk factors, one of which is smoking.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_323">Tobacco  products are the leading avoidable cause of cancer, causing more than 
155,000 deaths among smokers in the United States annually due to various
cancers.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Most cancers of the lung, trachea, bronchus, larynx,
pharynx, oral cavity, nasal cavity, and esophagus are attributable to tobacco products, particularly cigarettes.  Smoking is also causally associated with cancers of the pancreas, kidney, bladder,   stomach, colon, rectum, liver, and
cervix, and with myeloid leukemia.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_324">Smoking also has substantial effects on the health of nonsmokers. 
Environmental or secondhand tobacco smoke is implicated in causing lung
cancer, coronary heart disease, stroke, nasal irritation, and reproductive effects in women (low birth weight in newborns of these women).<Reference refidx="2"/> Among children, secondhand smoke exposure is causally associated with sudden infant death syndrome, lower respiratory tract illnesses, otitis media, middle ear effusion, exacerbated asthma, and respiratory effects such as cough, wheeze, and dyspnea.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_325">Environmental tobacco smoke has the
same components as inhaled mainstream smoke, although in lower absolute
concentrations, between 1% and 10%, depending on the constituent.  Carcinogenic
compounds in tobacco smoke include the polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs),
including the carcinogen benzo[a]pyrene (BaP) and the nicotine-derived
tobacco-specific nitrosamine, 4-(methylnitrosamino)-1-(3-pyridyl)-1-butanone
(NNK).<Reference refidx="7"/> 
Elevated biomarkers of tobacco exposure, including urinary cotinine,
tobacco-related carcinogen metabolites, and carcinogen-protein adducts, are
seen in passive or secondhand smokers.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></Para><Para id="_326">In 2021, 13.1% of adult men and 10.1% of adult women in the United States were
current smokers, and 24.1% of adult men and 13.6% of adult women reported the use of any tobacco product.<Reference refidx="12"/>      Cigarette smoking is particularly common among  American
Indian and Alaska Native individuals.  The prevalence of smoking also varies inversely
with education, and was highest among adults who had earned a General Educational Development  diploma (30.1%)  and generally decreased with increasing years of education.<Reference refidx="12"/>  From 2011 to 2014, significant declines occurred in the use of  cigarettes among middle school (4.3% to 2.5%) and high school (15.8% to 9.2%) students.<Reference refidx="13"/>  Cigarette smoking prevalence among male and
female high school students  increased substantially during the  1990s in
all ethnic groups, with rates between 20% and 30%.  However, by 2023, the cigarette smoking rate in high school students declined to 2%.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> (<ExternalRef xref="https://monitoringthefuture.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vol1_2001.pdf">Also available online.</ExternalRef>)</Para><Para id="_327">The effect of tobacco use on population-level health outcomes is illustrated
by the example of lung cancer mortality trends.  Smoking by women increased
between 1940 and the early 1960s, resulting in a greater than 600% increase in
female lung cancer mortality since 1950. Lung cancer is now the leading cause
of cancer death in women.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="16"/>    In the last 30 years, prevalence of current
cigarette use has generally decreased, though far more rapidly in men.  Lung
cancer mortality in men peaked in the 1980s, and   has been  declining since then; this
decrease has occurred predominantly in squamous cell and small cell carcinomas,
the histological types most strongly associated with smoking.<Reference refidx="14"/>  Variations in
lung cancer mortality rates by state also more or less parallel long-standing
state-specific differences in tobacco use.  Among    men, the average
annual age-adjusted lung cancer death rates from 2018 to 2022 were highest in
Mississippi (63.1 per 100,000),<Reference refidx="4"/> where 22%  of men in Mississippi were current smokers in 2021,
and lowest in Utah (18.0 per 100,000), where only 8% of men smoked.  Among
women, lung cancer death rates were highest in Kentucky (43.2 per 100,000), where
21% of women were current smokers, and lowest in Utah (13.5 per 100,000),
where only 6% of women smoked.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_328"><Title>Tobacco Use Interventions</Title><Para id="_329">Many health risks related to tobacco smoking can be reduced by smoking
cessation.  People who quit smoking before  age  50 years have up to half the
risk of dying   within 15 years   compared with people who continue to smoke. In addition,  the risk
of dying is reduced substantially even among people who stop smoking after age
70  years.<Reference refidx="19"/>  After 10 years of abstinence from smoking, the risk of lung cancer is 30% to 50% lower than that of continuing
smokers, and the risk of oral and esophageal
cancer is halved within 5 years of cessation.<Reference refidx="19"/>   People who quit smoking also  lower
their risk of acute myeloid leukemia and cancers of the  cervix, stomach, larynx, pancreas, colon and rectum, liver, kidney, and bladder.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_410">In a randomized trial of heavy smokers, the long-term follow-up results demonstrated that compared with the nonintervention group (n = 1,964), those randomly assigned to a smoking cessation intervention (n = 3,923) experienced a 15% reduction in all-cause mortality rates (8.83 vs. 10.38 per 1,000 person-years; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03).<Reference refidx="22"/> The smoking cessation intervention consisted of a strong physician message plus 12 group sessions and nicotine gum administered during a 10-week period.  Decreases in the risk of lung cancer and other cancers,    coronary heart disease, cardiovascular disease, and respiratory disease contributed to the  benefit in the patients randomly assigned to the smoking cessation intervention.</Para><Para id="_411">The most recent Surgeon General's Report on the benefits of smoking cessation also outlined the accumulated evidence about health benefits associated with tobacco cessation for chronic cardiovascular diseases, respiratory diseases, and reproductive outcomes. Smoking cessation reduces the risk of morbidity and mortality from cardiovascular disease and stroke, reduces the risk of an abdominal aortic aneurysm and coronary heart disease, reduces the levels of inflammatory and hypercoagulability markers, leads to a reduction in the development of atherosclerosis, and reduces the burden of cardiovascular disease. Smoking cessation also reduces the risk of developing chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and is the only recognized intervention to attenuate the loss of lung function among people with COPD. Smoking cessation benefits the health of pregnant women and their child. Benefits include a reduced risk of birthing a small-for-gestational-age infant and a reduced effect of smoking on fetal growth.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_330">Several approaches at the policy, legislative, and regulatory levels have
been attempted to effect widespread reduction in or prevention of commencement
of   tobacco use.  Various efforts at the community, state, and national level
have been credited with reducing the prevalence of smoking over time.  These
efforts include reducing minors’ access to tobacco products, disseminating effective
school-based prevention curricula together with media strategies, raising the
cost of tobacco products, using tobacco excise taxes to fund community-level
interventions such as mass media, providing proven quitting strategies
through health care organizations, and adopting smoke-free laws and
policies.<Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/></Para><Para id="_412">As discussed in more detail below, clinical interventions targeted at individuals have shown promising results.         A   meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials (RCTs) showed that 6-month  cessation rates were significantly improved with the use of nicotine replacement therapy (NRT)  products compared  with placebo or no intervention (relative risk [RR], 1.55; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.49–1.61).<Reference refidx="25"/>  The benefits of using NRT products have been consistently observed regardless of whether the product used was the patch, gum, nasal spray, inhaler, or lozenge.<Reference refidx="25"/> Smoking cessation counseling alone is  also effective.<Reference refidx="26"/> Even a brief
intervention by a health care professional significantly increases the smoking
cessation rate.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><SummarySection id="_137"><Title>Tobacco cessation guidelines</Title><Para id="_26">In 1996, the Agency for Health Care Policy and Research (AHCPR), now the Agency
for Healthcare Research and Quality,  released a landmark set of clinical
smoking-cessation guidelines for helping nicotine-dependent patients and
health care providers.  Now sponsored by the U.S. Public Health Service, the updated 2008 guidelines,          "<ExternalRef xref="https://www.ahrq.gov/professionals/clinicians-providers/guidelines-recommendations/tobacco/index.html">Treating Tobacco Use and Dependence</ExternalRef>"  are available online.<Reference refidx="28"/> The broad elements of these guidelines are:</Para><OrderedList id="_97" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Clinicians should document the tobacco-use status of every patient.
</ListItem><ListItem>Clinicians should assess the readiness to quit of patients who use           
tobacco and assist those who wish to quit in setting a quit date.
</ListItem><ListItem>Patients using tobacco should be provided with at least one of the
effective brief cessation interventions that are available.
</ListItem><ListItem>In general, more intense interventions are more effective than less
intense interventions in producing long-term tobacco abstinence,
reflecting the dose-response relationship between the intervention and
its outcome.
</ListItem><ListItem>One or more of the three treatment elements identified as being particularly
effective should be included in smoking-cessation treatment:<OrderedList id="_98" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>Social support from clinicians in the form of encouragement and
assistance.</ListItem><ListItem>Skills training/problem solving (cessation/abstinence techniques).</ListItem><ListItem>Pharmacotherapy, such as NRT products (e.g., patches, gum).</ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem><ListItem>To be effective, health care systems must make institutional changes
resulting in systematic identification of tobacco users and intervention
with these patients at every visit.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_42">For individual interventions, these guidelines  <Reference refidx="28"/>  suggested a model based on
outcomes from six major clinical trials of physician-delivered smoking
intervention conducted in the late 1980s:<Reference refidx="29"/> the ASK, ADVISE, ASSESS, ASSIST,
and ARRANGE model.  The physician provides a brief intervention that entails
asking about smoking status at every visit, advising abstinence, assisting by
setting a quit date, providing self-help materials and recommending use of
NRT, and arranging for a follow-up visit.  See below
for brief intervention outlines.  The recommendations also
strongly supported the value of referral to more intensive counseling.
</Para><OrderedList id="_102" Style="UAlpha"><ListTitle>Ask, Advise, Assess, Assist, Arrange: Key Elements
</ListTitle><ListItem>Ask  <ItemizedList id="_103" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Screen for smoking status at every visit or admission.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Advise<ItemizedList id="_104" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Minimal Advice: “As your physician, I must advise you that smoking is bad
for your health, and it would be important for you to stop.”</ListItem><ListItem>Augmented Advice: “Because of your (__________) condition, it is
particularly important for you to stop.  If you stop now, (briefly educate
patient about basic health benefits from quitting).”</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Assess<ItemizedList id="_105" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Minimal Assessment: Ask every tobacco user if he/she is willing to make a    
quit attempt at this time.</ListItem><ListItem>Augmented Assessment: Assess characteristics of smoking history and
patterns.<ItemizedList id="_106" Style="dash"><ListItem>Amount smoked.
</ListItem><ListItem>Quit history.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Assist/Counsel<ItemizedList id="_108" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Minimal Assistance: Provide self-help materials; assess interest in
quitting; and assess interest in and appropriateness of pharmacological aids.
</ListItem><ListItem>Augmented Assistance: Provide brief 5- to 7-minute patient-centered counseling.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Arrange Follow-Up Support<ItemizedList id="_109" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Minimal Follow-Up Support: Arrange for single follow-up contact by visit or
by telephone in about 2 weeks; provide referral to a smoking counselor or
group.
</ListItem><ListItem>Extended Follow-Up Support: Establish “quit smoking” contract with quit
date.  Arrange three or more follow-up contacts by visit or by telephone.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Para id="_413">In 2021, the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF) published an updated recommendation statement based on a systematic review that included 67 reviews addressing behavioral and pharmacological interventions for smoking cessation among the general population of adults that are largely in line with previous guidelines. In addition to asking all patients about tobacco use and advising them to abstain, the USPSTF recommended that clinicians provide evidence-based behavioral interventions and one or more of the seven pharmacotherapies approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for adults who use tobacco.<Reference refidx="30"/></Para><Para id="_414">The USPSTF recommendation was based on robust evidence that a variety of behavioral interventions (such as brief advice or support, counseling in various modalities, internet-based interventions, and financial incentives); all forms of NRT, bupropion hydrochloride (HCI), and varenicline; and the combination of behavioral and pharmacological interventions were significantly associated with increased abstinence rates of more than 6 months when compared with usual care or a minimal intervention. The USPSTF concluded with high certainty (the evidence was assigned an A grade) that the net benefit of evidence-based behavioral interventions and FDA-approved pharmacotherapy for tobacco cessation, alone or combined, is significant in adults  who smoke.<Reference refidx="31"/>  Of note, the guidelines for pregnant women are similar, in that they recommend that clinicians ask all patients about tobacco use, advise them to abstain, and provide evidence-based behavioral interventions. However, the guidelines indicated that the evidence is insufficient to assess the benefits and harms of pharmacotherapy. The 2020 Surgeon General’s Report on smoking cessation, based on an independent evidence review, similarly concluded that evidence-based behavioral and pharmacological interventions for smoking cessation are safe and effective treatments.<Reference refidx="21"/> The World Health Organization, the American College of Cardiology, the American Thoracic Society, and other similar organizations have issued guidance that is consistent with the USPSTF’s recommendations.<Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/></Para><Para id="_343">Promoting smoking cessation among cancer patients and survivors is also essential because the deleterious health effects of cigarette smoking may impact prognosis in both the short term and long term. In an RCT of a peer-delivered smoking cessation intervention among childhood cancer survivors, a significantly higher 12-month quit rate was observed in the intervention group (15% vs. 9%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01).<Reference refidx="35"/> Continued smoking after a cancer diagnosis increases all-cause and cancer-specific mortality. Continued smoking is also associated with a higher risk of  a recurrence or a second primary cancer, a poorer response to treatment, and increased treatment-related side effects.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Consistent with the tobacco cessation guidelines noted previously in the general adult population, the National Comprehensive Cancer Network Clinical Practice Guidelines for Smoking Cessation recommend that all cancer patients be assessed for tobacco use at regular intervals. They also recommend that patient treatment plans include evidence-based behavioral/motivational counseling, pharmacotherapy, and follow-up (with additional treatment if needed).<Reference refidx="36"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_415"><Title>Behavioral Interventions to Assist in Tobacco Cessation</Title><Para id="_416">A wide array of behavioral interventions for smoking cessation that vary in content, mode of delivery, intensity, and duration have demonstrated various degrees of efficacy. Behavioral interventions may  include advice to quit, cognitive, behavioral, and motivational counseling, internet or mobile applications, self-help materials, and financial incentives.<Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="31"/></Para><Para id="_417">The following sections summarize the evidence for the effect of these interventions on abstinence rates.</Para><SummarySection id="_418"><Title>Physician or nurse advice and smoking cessation</Title><Para id="_419">The importance of health care providers in the identification of individuals who use tobacco and the provision of advice to quit has been consistently highlighted in evidence-based smoking cessation guidelines.<Reference refidx="30"/> In an analysis pooling data from 17 trials, brief physician advice versus no advice (or usual care) was associated with a significant increase in abstinence rates at 6 months (RR, 1.66; 95% CI, 1.42–1.94). Although there was no statistical difference in abstinence rates between minimal advice and more intensive subgroups, the estimated effect was higher for the more intensive interventions (RR, 1.84; 95% CI, 1.60–2.13).<Reference refidx="27"/>   Similarly, a separate review reported moderate-quality evidence suggesting that compared with usual care, behavioral support/advice delivered by nurses resulted in increased abstinence rates (RR, 1.29; 95% CI, 1.21–1.38).<Reference refidx="37"/> The analysis found no evidence that high-intensity interventions or interventions with additional follow-up increased abstinence rates. Even though the absolute effects of brief advice from a physician or nurse may be smaller than other interventions for smoking cessation, the impact on public health can still be substantial if a large volume of these clinicians offer advice to quit to people who use tobacco.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_420"><Title>Financial incentive programs for smoking cessation </Title><Para id="_421">Financial incentive programs can offer additional support for smoking cessation efforts and may involve incentives for program engagement, compliance with program processes or milestones, and/or tobacco or smoking abstinence outcomes. Results from a randomized trial suggest that the efficacy of such programs may be influenced greatly by the way rewards are disbursed.<Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/></Para><Para id="_312">The trial randomly assigned 2,538 participants to either one of four incentive programs or usual care. The four programs were combinations of scope (two programs targeted individuals, and two targeted groups of six participants) and incentive structure (one of the individual-focused programs and one of the group-focused programs provided rewards of approximately $800 to participants who achieved cessation at 6 months; the others required an initial refundable deposit of $150, supplemented with $650 in reward payments for successful cessation). The rationale for the four intervention arms was based on behavioral observations that 1) people are more loss averse than gain seeking and 2) collaboration/competition with others can bolster intervention efficacy.<Reference refidx="38"/></Para><Para id="_316">Two main dimensions of the intervention effects were explored:</Para><OrderedList id="_317" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Acceptance of the intervention.</ListItem><ListItem>Efficacy of the intervention. </ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_313">Both intent-to-treat and per-protocol analyses were performed, with an in-depth sensitivity analysis for potential biases accompanying the latter. In the intent-to-treat analyses (which evaluated the overall efficacy of the interventions), all of the financial incentive arms demonstrated significantly higher 6-month abstinence rates than the usual care arm (9.4%–16%, compared with 6% for usual care). The 6-month abstinence rates were similar between the group-focused and individual-focused arms (13.7% and 12.1%, respectively; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .29), but the reward-based programs were associated with higher abstinence rates than were the deposit-based ones (15.7% vs. 10.2%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="38"/></Para><Para id="_314">However, per-protocol analyses that accounted for the dramatically lower acceptance rate for the deposit-based interventions  than for the reward-based interventions (14% vs. 90%) estimated that 6-month abstinence rates could be 13.2 percentage points (95% CI, 3.1–22.8) higher in the deposit-based programs than in the reward-based programs among the estimated 13.7% of participants who would participate in either type of program. That is, deposit-based interventions may be more efficacious than reward-based interventions, but it is harder to get people to commit to them.<Reference refidx="38"/></Para><Para id="_422">A systematic review of 33 trials included more than 21,000 participants. The pooled RR for quitting with incentives at 6 months was 1.49 (95% CI, 1.28–1.73; 31 RCTs; adjusted N = 20,097; I<Superscript>2</Superscript> = 33%), compared with controls, indicating that there is high certainty evidence that the use of incentives improves abstinence rates.<Reference refidx="40"/> After excluding six studies that offered incentives at the 6-month follow-up time point, the results remained consistent (RR, 1.40; 95% CI, 1.16–1.69; 25 RCTs; adjusted N = 17,058; I<Superscript>2</Superscript> = 36%), suggesting that the effect of those incentives persisted after the incentives ended. The authors noted that the financial value of the incentives varied across studies (including some that involved redeemable self-deposits), but there were no clear effects related to incentive value. They also examined the effect of incentives on smoking cessation in people who were pregnant and reported moderate-quality evidence (limited by the risk of bias) that incentive programs initiated at the end of pregnancy or postpartum led to increased abstinence rates at 24 weeks postpartum (RR, 2.38; 95% CI, 1.54–3.69; N = 2,273; I<Superscript>2</Superscript> = 41%).</Para><Para id="_429"> A subsequent component network meta-analysis assessed the effect of behavioral interventions on abstinence across 33 systematic reviews, which included 312 RCTs and more than 250,000 participants. Results indicated that the only interventions that demonstrated benefit were the provision of financial incentives and the provision of counseling.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_119"><Title>Pharmacological Interventions to Assist in Tobacco Cessation</Title><Para id="_72">Pharmacological agents have been used successfully to aid in the cessation of
smoking in the general population.<Reference refidx="41"/>  Since the original AHCPR guidelines <Reference refidx="42"/>
were published in 1996, various nicotine replacement products have been
approved for over-the-counter sale, and additional evidence of the
effectiveness of therapies for smoking cessation has been published.<Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/> 
Pharmacotherapy of smoking cessation, including NRTs (gum,
patch, spray, lozenge,  and inhaler) and non-nicotine medications  (e.g., bupropion HCI and varenicline), results
in statistically significant increases in smoking cessation rates over those of a placebo.<Reference refidx="47"/></Para><Para id="_73">A growing number of smoking cessation pharmacotherapies have demonstrated efficacy in significantly increasing rates of smoking cessation. The choice of therapy should be individualized based on several factors, including past experience, patient and/or physician preference, and
potential agent side effects.
As more is learned about specific genetic variants that influence a smoker's response to smoking cessation pharmacotherapies—such as polymorphisms in genes encoding enzymes involved in nicotine metabolism—this information could eventually be integrated into smoking cessation treatment planning.<Reference refidx="48"/> Presently, the evidence is not yet sufficient to be integrated into clinical practice.</Para><Para id="_74">The following sections summarize available pharmacological interventions to assist
in tobacco cessation.  More comprehensive information is available from product package inserts.</Para><SummarySection id="_121"><Title> Nicotine replacement therapy (NRT)</Title><Para id="_79">NRT products, including nicotine patches, gums, lozenges, inhalers, and nasal sprays, are designed to relieve nicotine withdrawal
symptoms.  There are several precautions before initiating therapy, but these precautions do
not constitute absolute contraindications. Special            
considerations are necessary in some patient groups (e.g., those with        
medical conditions such as arrhythmias, uncontrolled hypertension,          
esophagitis, peptic ulcer disease, insulin-treated diabetes, or asthma; pregnant or breast-feeding women; and adolescent smokers).<Reference refidx="49"/> Commonly reported side effects differ by product type. These side effects include erythema, pruritus, local irritation, stomatitis, sore throat, jaw soreness, gastrointestinal complaints (including nausea and vomiting), heart palpitations, insomnia, hiccups, and coughing.<Reference refidx="50"/></Para><Para id="_369">Based on a synthesis of the results of 133 randomized trials, researchers found that NRTs, alone or in combination, improved cessation rates over placebos after 6 months (RR, 1.55; 95% CI, 1.49–1.61). In addition, similar benefits of NRT product use were observed regardless of the product type (patch, gum, nasal spray, inhaler, or lozenge).<Reference refidx="25"/>  When compared directly, the use of a single fast-acting NRT (such as nicotine lozenges or gum) or the nicotine patch results in similar 6-month cessation rates (RR, 0.90; 95% CI, 0.77–1.05).<Reference refidx="51"/>  The results of an  analysis that included 16 randomized trials concluded that combining a fast-acting NRT with the nicotine patch resulted in higher 6-month cessation rates compared with the nicotine patch alone (RR, 1.27; 95% CI, 1.17–1.37).<Reference refidx="51"/>  However, not all trials supported this conclusion.<Reference refidx="52"/></Para><Para id="_279">Current guidelines generally recommend 8 to 12 weeks of transdermal nicotine therapy, starting on the quit day. Findings from two randomized placebo-controlled trials of transdermal therapy differed in their findings as to whether extended therapy (22–24 weeks vs. 8 weeks) improves quit rates.<Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_208"><Title>Non-nicotine products</Title><SummarySection id="_213"><Title>Bupropion hydrochloride (HCI)</Title><Para id="_214">Also used as an antidepressant, bupropion HCl is a
   non-nicotine aid to smoking cessation.  It is a relatively weak inhibitor of
   the neuronal uptake of norepinephrine, serotonin, and dopamine, and does not
   inhibit monoamine oxidase.  The exact mechanism by which bupropion HCl
   enhances the ability of patients to abstain from smoking is unknown. However, it is presumed that this action is mediated by noradrenergic or
   dopaminergic mechanisms. Based on the results of 50 randomized trials that compared bupropion HCI with placebo, after 6 months of follow-up, bupropion was associated with a statistically significant increase in the likelihood of quitting smoking (RR, 1.60; 95% CI, 1.49–1.72).<Reference refidx="55"/>  There was insufficient evidence to support the idea that combining bupropion HCI with NRT increases smoking cessation rates over those of NRT alone (RR, 1.17; 95% CI, 0.95–1.44). However, results (based on three trials) indicated that the combination of bupropion HCI and varenicline may result in higher 6-month cessation rates compared with varenicline alone (RR, 1.21; 95% CI, 0.95–1.55). Although there was no difference in the efficacy of bupropion HCI compared with single-form NRT (RR, 1.03; 95% CI, 0.93–1.13), there was evidence that the use of bupropion HCI resulted in lower cessation rates than varenicline (RR, 0.73; 95% CI, 0.67–0.80) and combination NRT (RR, 0.74; 95% CI, 0.55–0.98), and higher cessation rates than the antidepressant, nortriptyline (RR, 1.30; 95% CI, 0.93–1.82).<Reference refidx="55"/> Commonly reported side effects of bupropion HCI include insomnia, dry mouth, dizziness, and rhinitis. A higher incidence of seizures was also reported in patients being treated for bulimia/anorexia.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_370"><Title>Varenicline</Title><Para id="_371">Varenicline is a selective partial agonist at the alpha-4-beta-2 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor, which mediates nicotine dependence through dopamine release.  Varenicline prevents nicotine from binding to the receptor and reduces both the rewarding effects of smoking and withdrawal symptoms.   The most commonly reported side effects of varenicline include nausea, abnormal dreams, and insomnia. In two of the initial RCTs for smoking cessation, varenicline was titrated to a dose of 1 mg twice a day and  compared with bupropion HCI sustained-release (SR) 150 mg twice a day and a placebo group.<Reference refidx="56"/><Reference refidx="57"/>   Treatment lasted for 12 weeks, with an additional 40 weeks of posttreatment follow-up. In both studies, varenicline was  more efficacious than bupropion HCI and placebo for continuous abstinence from smoking at 9 to 12 weeks and at 9 to   24 weeks of follow-up.  For 9 to 52 weeks of follow-up, varenicline was  more efficacious than placebo in both studies.<Reference refidx="56"/><Reference refidx="57"/>  At 52 weeks of follow-up, the 7-day point prevalence of smoking abstinence was 46% higher in the varenicline group than in the bupropion HCI SR group (odds ratio [OR], 1.46; 95% CI, 1.04–2.06).<Reference refidx="56"/> The other  study also showed a 46% higher continuous abstinence  in the varenicline group (OR, 1.46; 95% CI,  0.99–2.17).<Reference refidx="57"/> Approximately 30% of the participants who were randomly assigned to receive varenicline reported nausea, more than double the rate in the bupropion HCI groups, and triple the rate seen in the placebo groups.</Para><Para id="_430">                    In a randomized trial comparing varenicline with transdermal nicotine,                            continuous abstinence was greater in the varenicline group than in the transdermal nicotine group at the end of treatment (56% vs. 43%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt;   .001) and during posttreatment follow-up (26% vs.     20%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> =                              .06).<Reference refidx="58"/>   The prevalence of nausea in the varenicline group (37%) was more than triple that in the transdermal nicotine group (10%). However, this result was not confirmed in a subsequent randomized trial that compared varenicline with the nicotine patch.<Reference refidx="52"/> There was little difference in 7-day point-prevalence abstinence after 26 weeks (24% vs. 23%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> =  .82) or 52 weeks (19% vs. 21%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .61) between those randomly assigned  to the varenicline intervention and  those assigned to the nicotine-patch intervention.</Para><Para id="_372">The results of a synthesis of 41 randomized trials indicated that varenicline results in increased 6-month cessation rates when compared with placebo (RR, 2.32; 95% CI, 2.15–2.51), bupropion HCI (RR, 1.36; 95% CI, 1.25–1.49), and single-form NRT (RR, 1.25; 95% CI, 1.14–1.37), but provided no clear evidence that varenicline was superior to dual NRT (RR, 1.02; 95% CI, 0.87–1.20 ).<Reference refidx="59"/></Para><Para id="_373">After a period of postmarketing surveillance, on July 1, 2009, the FDA required additions to the Boxed Warnings for both bupropion HCI and varenicline to describe the risk of serious neuropsychiatric symptoms associated with these products.  Symptoms include: “changes in behavior, hostility, agitation, depressed mood, suicidal thoughts and behavior, and attempted suicide.”<Reference refidx="60"/>   The FDA further advised that the important health benefits of quitting smoking “should be weighed against the small, but real, risk of serious adverse events with the use of varenicline or bupropion.”<Reference refidx="60"/> Subsequently, the FDA required the manufacturers of bupropion HCI and varenicline to conduct a clinical trial to evaluate the neuropsychiatric safety of these medications in patients with and without a history of psychiatric disorders (EAGLES trial). This randomized, double-blind, triple-dummy, placebo-controlled and active-controlled (nicotine patch) trial of varenicline and bupropion HCI included over 8,000 cigarette smokers (one-half of which had current or a history of psychiatric disorders) from 140 sites in 16 countries. In the nonpsychiatric cohort, the varenicline-placebo and bupropion-placebo risk differences (RDs) for moderate and severe neuropsychiatric adverse events were -1.28 (95% CI, -2.40 to -0.15) and -0.08 (95% CI, -1.37 to 1.21), respectively. In the psychiatric cohort, the varenicline-placebo and bupropion-placebo RDs were 1.59 (95% CI, -0.42 to 3.59) and 1.78 (95% CI, -0.24 to 3.81), respectively. The most frequent adverse events by treatment group were nausea (varenicline, 25%), insomnia (bupropion HCI, 12%), abnormal dreams (nicotine patch, 12%), and headache (placebo, 10%). The results of the trial did not show a significant increase in rates of moderate-to-severe neuropsychiatric adverse events with either varenicline or bupropion HCI in those with or without psychiatric disorders  <Reference refidx="61"/> and were supported by other studies analyzing data from multiple cessation trials.<Reference refidx="62"/><Reference refidx="63"/><Reference refidx="64"/> These results prompted the FDA to remove the Boxed Warnings for both bupropion HCI and varenicline in 2016, noting that although the risk of mental health side effects is still present, particularly for individuals with some mental illnesses, the “results of the trial confirm that the benefits of stopping smoking outweigh the risks of these medicines.”<Reference refidx="65"/></Para><Para id="_374">A meta-analysis of double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized trials of varenicline administered for at least 1 week (N = 14 trials) indicated that varenicline was associated with an increased risk of serious adverse cardiovascular events (RR, 1.72; 95% CI, 1.09–2.71).<Reference refidx="66"/>  This finding is particularly noteworthy because almost all of the randomized trials included in the meta-analysis had the following in common: they excluded patients with cardiovascular disease (CVD) at baseline; the usual average age of the patient populations (early 40s) was young for CVD; varenicline was usually given for 12 weeks or less; and varenicline is efficacious for smoking cessation, which would act to decrease CVD risk. A subsequent extension study to the EAGLES trial,<Reference refidx="61"/> described above, evaluated the time to development of major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE: cardiovascular death, nonfatal myocardial infarction, or nonfatal stroke) across treatment groups (placebo, NRT, bupropion HCI, and varenicline) as a primary outcome. The extension study reported no significant difference in time to onset of MACE for varenicline or bupropion HCI, compared with placebo (varenicline: hazard ratio [HR], 0.29; 95% CI, 0.05–1.68 and bupropion HCI: HR, 0.50; 95% CI, 0.10–2.50) and no significant differences in the incidence of cardiovascular events during treatment by treatment group.<Reference refidx="67"/> An analysis of 18 studies reported that while more people taking varenicline experienced cardiac serious adverse events compared with placebo or no medication (RR, 1.20; 95% CI, 0.79–1.8), conclusions about harm are limited because of imprecision in the estimates.<Reference refidx="59"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_216"><Title> Fluoxetine</Title><Para id="_217">Although Zyban (bupropion HCl) is the only
    antidepressant approved by the FDA for smoking cessation, Prozac  (fluoxetine
   HCl) has  been  shown to be effective in some studies.<Reference refidx="68"/> Pooled results from two RCTs indicated no significant difference in cessation rates after 6 months between selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor users (including fluoxetine HCI) and the control arms in two studies (RR, 0.93; 95% CI, 0.71–1.22). There was also no significant increase in cessation rates when fluoxetine HCI was added to NRT in three studies (RR, 0.70; 95% CI, 0.64–1.82).<Reference refidx="69"/> The most commonly reported side effects of fluoxetine HCI include insomnia, dizziness, anorexia, sexual dysfunction, and confusion.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_300"><Title>Cytisine</Title><Para id="_301">Cytisine is a naturally occurring compound isolated more than 50 years ago from the plant <ScientificName>Cytisus laburnum</ScientificName>, a partial nicotinic acetylcholine receptor agonist.<Reference refidx="70"/>  It has a long history of use for smoking cessation in Bulgaria and other eastern European nations, including clinical trials published in the 1970s.  As this older evidence has been uncovered, it has led to more recent trials in western nations. A systematic review and meta-analysis showed clear benefit for cytisine compared with placebo.<Reference refidx="70"/>  For all trials combined (n = 9 trials; 2,141 cytisine participants, 1,879 placebo participants), the pooled RR for abstinence from smoking at the longest follow-up for cytisine was 1.59 (95% CI, 1.43–1.75), compared with placebo.  When the analyses were limited to two high-quality trials published since 2008, the pooled RR for smoking abstinence was 3.29 (95% CI, 1.84–5.90).<Reference refidx="70"/>  There was no evidence of serious adverse events, but gastrointestinal symptoms were more common in the cytisine (12%) group than in the placebo (7%) group.<Reference refidx="70"/></Para><Para id="_302">A randomized trial in New Zealand compared cytisine (n = 655) with NRT (n = 655).<Reference refidx="71"/>  Compared with the NRT group, the cytisine group had higher continued abstinence at 1 month (40% vs. 31%; RD, 9%; 95% CI, 4%–15%), 2 months (31% vs. 22%; RD, 9%; 95% CI, 4%–14%), and 6 months (22% vs. 15%; RD, 7%; 95% CI, 2%–11%).<Reference refidx="71"/>  There were no differences between treatment groups, but nausea and vomiting (28 events vs. 2 events) and sleep disorders (28 events vs. 2 events) were more common in the cytisine group, compared with the NRT group.<Reference refidx="71"/> This trial is noteworthy because of the following results:</Para><OrderedList id="_304" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>It considerably strengthened an already substantial body of evidence indicating that cytisine is an efficacious smoking cessation pharmacotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>It showed that cytisine is more efficacious than  NRT products that are known to be effective.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_382">Based on a synthesis of the results of four randomized trials (4,623 participants), researchers found that cytisine improved cessation rates over placebo after 6 months (RR, 1.30; 95% CI, 1.15–1.61), with no evidence of an increase in serious adverse events (RR, 1.04; 95% CI, 0.78–1.37). Pooled results from two studies indicated no significant difference in cessation rates after 6 months between cytisine and varenicline (RR, 1.00; 95% CI, 0.79–1.26).<Reference refidx="59"/> In a subsequent randomized noninferiority trial,  cytisine was associated with lower cessation  rates (OR, 0.63; 95% CI, 0.39–0.98) and fewer total adverse events (incidence rate ratio, 0.59; 95% CI, 0.43–0.81) than varenicline.<Reference refidx="72"/> The most commonly reported side effects of cytisine include nausea, vomiting, and sleep disturbance.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_221"><Title>Other agents</Title><Para id="_222">Nortriptyline has been  suggested as a possibly useful second-line pharmacotherapy but is not approved  for smoking cessation by the FDA. Nortriptyline is an antidepressant that does not contain nicotine. A meta-analysis of five RCTs found that smokers who received nortriptyline were 2.4 times more likely (95% CI, 1.7–3.6) than smokers who received a placebo to remain abstinent from smoking after 6 months.<Reference refidx="73"/> Pooled results from six studies indicated that nortriptyline improved cessation rates over placebo after 6 months (RR, 2.03; 95% CI, 1.48–2.78), including limited evidence that bupropion HCI improved cessation rates over nortriptyline (RR, 1.30; 95% CI, 0.93–1.82).<Reference refidx="55"/></Para><Para id="_383">Lobeline (Bantron) is classified as a category III agent by the FDA, safe but not proven effective. This product is not recommended for use in any smoking cessation program due to its lack of efficacy.<Reference refidx="74"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_401"><Title>Pharmacotherapy Combinations and Adaptations</Title><Para id="_402">Strategies to enhance the effectiveness of pharmacotherapy for smoking cessation have been explored, including combining medications and adjusting dosages and/or treatment duration.<Reference refidx="75"/> As noted previously, a recent meta-analysis concluded that combining a fast-acting NRT with the nicotine patch (i.e., combined NRT) resulted in higher 6-month cessation rates compared with the nicotine patch alone (RR, 1.27; 95% CI, 1.17–1.37). The analysis included moderate-certainty evidence (limited by imprecision) indicating that 21 mg patches are more effective than 14 mg patches (RR, 1.48; 95% CI, 1.06–2.08) but that 42 mg patches are just as effective as 21 mg (24-hour) patches (RR, 1.09; 95% CI, 0.93–1.29). A subset of studies tested the effect of preloading NRT before quit day versus starting NRT on the quit day. In that subset, there was moderate-certainty evidence, limited by risk of bias, of a positive effect of preloading NRT on abstinence (RR, 1.25; 95% CI, 1.08–1.44). There was no reliable evidence of an effect of duration of single or combined NRT use on abstinence.<Reference refidx="51"/> In another meta-analysis, results (based on three trials) indicated that the combination of bupropion HCI and varenicline may result in higher 6-month cessation rates compared with varenicline alone (RR, 1.21; 95% CI, 0.95–1.55). However, there was insufficient evidence to suggest that combining bupropion HCI plus NRT increases smoking cessation rates over those of NRT alone (RR, 1.17; 95% CI, 0.95–1.44).<Reference refidx="55"/></Para><Para id="_403">A 2015 meta-analysis included randomized trials that compared the combination of varenicline and NRT therapy with varenicline alone. The analysis showed a statistically significant association with a smoking cessation benefit for the combination treatment, especially if a nicotine patch was given before treatment with varenicline.<Reference refidx="76"/> In a subsequent double-blind, 2 × 2 factorial RCT, 1,251 individuals who smoked were randomly assigned to receive smoking cessation counseling and varenicline monotherapy for 12 weeks, varenicline plus NRT (patch) for 12 weeks, varenicline monotherapy for 24 weeks, or varenicline plus NRT for 24 weeks.<Reference refidx="77"/> For the primary outcome of abstinence at 52 weeks, there was no significant interaction between medication type and medication duration (OR, 1.03; 95% CI, 0.91–1.17; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .66). The abstinence rate was 24.8% for  individuals randomly assigned to 24-week treatment duration versus 24.3% for those randomly assigned to 12-week treatment duration (risk difference, -0.4%; 95% CI, -5.2% to 4.3%; OR, 1.01; 95% CI, 0.89–1.15). The abstinence rate was 24.3% for  individuals randomly assigned to varenicline-combination therapy versus 24.8% for those randomly assigned to varenicline monotherapy (risk difference, 0.4%; 95% CI, -4.3% to 5.2%; OR, 0.99; 95% CI, 0.87–1.12). Adverse effects across the four treatment groups included nausea (24.0%–30.9%) and insomnia (24.4%–30.5%). These findings do not support the addition of NRT to varenicline or the extension of varenicline or combination therapy beyond the standard 12 weeks.<Reference refidx="77"/></Para><Para id="_404">In a double-blind, placebo-controlled, sequential, multiple-assignment randomized trial (SMART), 490 individuals who smoked were randomly assigned to receive 6 weeks of varenicline (2 mg/d) or combined NRT (21 mg/d patch and 2 mg lozenges as needed) and smoking cessation counseling. After 6 weeks, abstainers continued their assigned medication and nonabstainers were randomly assigned again to continue the initially assigned medication at the initial dose, switch between varenicline and combined NRT at the initial dose, or increase the varenicline (3 mg/d) or combined NRT (42 mg/d patch) dose for an additional 6 weeks.<Reference refidx="78"/></Para><Para id="_405">At 12 weeks, the probability of abstinence for those initially randomly assigned to varenicline who were abstinent at 6 weeks and continued on treatment (not randomized again) was 72% (95% credible interval [Crl], 65%–78%) compared with 78% (95% Crl, 69%–85%) for those initially randomly assigned to combined NRT who were abstinent at 6 weeks and continued on treatment. The posterior probability of a nonzero difference between these two conditions was 88% (absolute risk difference [ARD], 6%; 95% CrI, -5% to 16%). The probability of abstinence at 12 weeks (end of treatment) for the individuals initially assigned to varenicline who were not abstinent at 6 weeks was 20% (95% CrI, 16%–26%) for those who increased their varenicline dosage, 0% for those who switched to combined NRT, and 3% (95% CrI, 1%–4%) for those who were assigned to the continued-varenicline treatment group (ARD, -3%; 95% CrI, -4% to -1%). There was a more than 99% posterior probability that continuing varenicline at the initial dosage was worse than switching to a higher dosage. Increasing the varenicline dosage had an ARD of 18% (95% CrI, 13%–24%) and a more than 99% posterior probability of conferring benefit. The probability of abstinence at 12 weeks for the individuals initially assigned to combined NRT who were not abstinent at 6 weeks was 8% (95% CrI, 6%–10%) for those who continued at the initial dosage, 14% (95% CrI, 10%–18%) for those who increased their dosage, and 14% (95% CrI, 10%–18%) for those who switched to varenicline (ARD, 6%; 95% CrI, 6%–11%). There was a more than 99% posterior probability that either strategy conferred benefit over continuing at the initial dosage. The secondary outcome of continuous abstinence at 6-months post-quit indicated that only increased dosages of varenicline and combined NRT provided benefit over continuation of the initial treatment dosages. Relative to continuing the same medication, there was no evidence indicating an increased risk of adverse events associated with the dosage increases for either medication. Additionally, no major differences in treatment adherence were reported between treatment groups.</Para><Para id="_406">In summary, these results suggest that individuals who are not able to abstain from smoking after initial treatment with varenicline benefit most from increasing the varenicline dose. For the individuals who continue to smoke after initial treatment with combined NRT, switching to varenicline or increasing the dose of combined NRT resulted in similar end-of-treatment abstinence probabilities. The secondary outcome of continuous abstinence at 6 months favored the dose-increase conditions for both varenicline and combined NRT, relative to continuation.<Reference refidx="78"/></Para><Para id="_423">On the other hand, in an RCT of 392 Black adults who smoked daily, switching from the nicotine patch to varenicline at 2 weeks or to bupropion HCI plus the nicotine patch at 6 weeks (adapted care) for individuals who did not quit smoking at those respective time points did not significantly improve abstinence rates, compared with standard treatment with the nicotine patch at 12 weeks (17.4% vs. 11.7%; OR, 1.58; 95% CI, 0.89–2.80; <Emphasis>P </Emphasis>= .12), 18 weeks (16.3% vs. 15.8%; OR, 1.04; 95% CI, 0.61–1.78; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .89), or 26 weeks (12.2% vs. 13.3%; OR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.50–1.65; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .76).<Reference refidx="79"/> The results also indicated that those who quit smoking within the first 2 weeks of treatment were significantly more likely to be abstinent at subsequent assessment points. However, the overall study abstinence rates were lower than those found in similar studies that included Black adults who were using the nicotine patch for smoking cessation.<Reference refidx="80"/><Reference refidx="81"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_211"><Title>Smoking Reduction</Title><Para id="_349">Among smokers who are interested in quitting but not ready to make an immediate quit attempt, gradually decreasing the number of cigarettes smoked per day leading up to a quit attempt may prove to be a viable intervention strategy.  This <Strong>reduce to quit</Strong> approach was tested in the context of an RCT. In this study, both the intervention group and control group received counseling, with the goals of reducing the number of cigarettes smoked per day by 75% or greater by week 8 and to quit smoking entirely by week 12.<Reference refidx="82"/>  The intervention group (n = 760) also received smoking cessation pharmacotherapy (varenicline at a maintenance dose of 1 mg bid for 24 weeks), whereas the control group (n = 750) received placebo tablets.  For the primary end point of self-reported smoking abstinence during weeks 15 through 24, a statistically significant RD of 25.2% (varenicline group, 32.1% vs. placebo group, 6.9%; 95% CI, 21.4%–29.0%) was observed.  The clinical significance of this finding is that it provides evidence of benefit for a pharmacotherapy-enhanced intervention aimed to motivate smokers who are interested in quitting, but not yet ready to quit, to start by cutting down on the number of cigarettes per day as a lead-in to a subsequent quit attempt.</Para><Para id="_350">For a smoker who wants to quit, an important practical question is whether a quit attempt is more likely to successfully result in smoking cessation if it involves abruptly stopping smoking or gradually decreasing the number of cigarettes smoked per day leading up to a quit attempt.  U.S. evidence-based guidelines recommend abrupt quitting as the preferred approach,<Reference refidx="83"/> but guidelines from other countries vary on this matter.  To directly test this question, 697 smokers who wanted to quit were recruited from 31 primary care clinics in England, and randomly assigned to either a gradual or abrupt smoking cessation intervention.<Reference refidx="84"/> In this noninferiority trial, both groups were provided with access to NRT during the two weeks before the planned quit date. In the gradual cessation group, plans were made to cut down the number of cigarettes per day by 75% by the planned quit date. However, the abrupt cessation group was advised to follow usual smoking patterns until stopping smoking entirely on the planned quit date.  Both groups were provided with NRT after the quit date and throughout the trial.  For the primary end point of prolonged validated smoking abstinence at 4 weeks, the gradual cessation arm was less likely to quit smoking than the abrupt cessation arm (39.2% vs. 49.0%); the difference was statistically significant (RD, -9.8%; 95% CI, 2.5%–17.1%).  The statistically significantly lower likelihood of smoking cessation in the gradual versus abrupt intervention arms persisted during follow-up at 8 weeks (29.2% vs. 36.6%; RD, -7.4%; 95% CI, 0.4%–14.3%) and 6 months (15.5% vs. 22.0%; RD, -6.5%; 95% CI, 0.7%–12.2%).  Baseline patient preferences for a gradual or abrupt quit attempt indicated that smokers who preferred the gradual quitting approach had a lower likelihood of smoking abstinence at 4 weeks (38% vs. 52%), suggesting that patient preferences for these methods may be a marker for other factors associated with successful quitting, such as motivation to quit. However, even when stratified by baseline patient preferences, the gradual cessation method resulted in lower likelihood of cessation both among those who preferred the gradual approach (34.6% vs. 42.0%) and those who preferred the abrupt approach (45.8% vs. 58.1%).  The overall clinical significance of this study is that it provides evidence that in the setting of a pharmacotherapy-aided quit attempt among smokers interested in quitting, quitting abruptly is a more effective smoking cessation strategy than gradually cutting down on the number of cigarettes smoked before making a quit attempt. This result holds true regardless of smoker preferences in methods.  A quit attempt regardless of method should never be discouraged, but abrupt cessation appears to be the most effective strategy.  In this context,  abrupt cessation is distinct from making an unaided quit attempt (i.e., quitting “cold turkey”).<Reference refidx="85"/></Para><Para id="_391">A systematic review of this topic revealed substantial heterogeneity in the results across studies, but the results showed that gradual cessation was associated with a 6% lower likelihood of smoking cessation than abrupt cessation, although this finding was not statistically significant  (RR, 0.94; 95% CI, 0.79–1.13).<Reference refidx="85"/> In an updated review of 51 trials that included more than 22,000 participants, the authors concluded, with moderate-certainty evidence, that long-term (≥ 6 months) abstinence rates did not differ in participants who were randomly assigned to either a gradual cessation intervention or an abrupt quitting intervention (RR, 1.01; 95% CI, 0.87–1.17; I<Superscript>2</Superscript> = 29%; 22 studies, 9,219 participants).<Reference refidx="86"/>   When comparing the effects of a gradual cessation intervention with  no smoking cessation intervention on abstinence rates, the authors reported low-certainty evidence (limited by inconsistency, imprecision, and risk of bias) that was inconclusive (RR, 1.74; 95% CI, 0.90–3.38; I<Superscript>2</Superscript> = 45%; 6 studies, 1,599 participants). The authors also reported low-certainty evidence that suggested gradual reduction methods may be more effective when combined with pharmacotherapy (RR, 1.68; 95% CI, 1.09–2.58; I<Superscript>2</Superscript> = 78%; 11 studies, 8,636 participants). A subgroup analysis of these 11 studies reported  the same conclusions, with moderate-certainty evidence, specifically when fast-acting NRTs or varenicline was used as pharmacotherapy (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001, I<Superscript>2</Superscript> = 80% for subgroup differences).<Reference refidx="86"/></Para><Para id="_212">Among dependent smokers, complete abstinence from smoking is the ultimate goal.  Even in instances when complete abstinence from smoking is not achieved, smoking cessation pharmacotherapies may benefit individual health—and ultimately the public’s health—if the smoker reduces the number of cigarettes smoked.  The relationship between cigarette smoking and lung cancer, and other smoking-associated malignancies, is strongly dose-dependent.  Thus, an individual smoker who is unable to achieve abstinence or who is not motivated to quit smoking may benefit by using pharmacotherapies (or other means) to reduce the number of cigarettes smoked per day.  NRT has thus generated attention as a viable means of <Strong>harm reduction</Strong>.  In studies that included smokers who were not trying to quit and were randomly assigned  to receive either NRT or placebo, a greater proportion of those who received NRT reduced the number of cigarettes per day, compared with placebo.<Reference refidx="87"/><Reference refidx="88"/>   However, the impact of NRT on smoking reduction appears not to be sustained in the long run.<Reference refidx="89"/> Less evidence is available for bupropion HCI,    varenicline, and psychosocial interventions as a means of harm reduction.  A potential problem with such a harm reduction strategy would be if it prevented cessation among smokers who would have otherwise quit smoking.  Evidence shows that smoking reduction is actually associated with increased likelihood of future cessation.<Reference refidx="88"/><Reference refidx="90"/> Another potential negative aspect of harm reduction would be if smokers reduced the number of cigarettes smoked per day but modified the way the cigarettes were smoked in such a way that exposure to tobacco toxins was not actually reduced             (e.g., by inhaling more deeply).  Compensatory behaviors such as inhaling more deeply or smoking more of a cigarette are attempts by the smoker to try to maintain nicotine levels, so the use of supplemental NRT presumably safeguards against this.  Evidence from studies of smoking reduction with NRT that measured smoking biomarkers indicates that compensation occurs, but not to such an  extent that it would be expected to outweigh the reduction in exposure from the reduced number of cigarettes per day.<Reference refidx="87"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_333"><Title>School-Based Interventions</Title><Para id="_334">School-based interventions alone have not demonstrated 
a long-term impact on smoking prevention.<Reference refidx="91"/> One of the highest-quality studies was a large   randomized trial
in which children received a theory-based
program that incorporated various social-influence approaches from grade 3 through grade 12. There was  no
difference in smoking outcomes observed either at grade 12 or  at 2 years after high school  between school
districts who received the intervention and those in the control arm.<Reference refidx="92"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_426"><Title>Community Intervention Trial for Smoking Cessation (COMMIT)</Title><Para id="_427">The Community Intervention Trial for Smoking Cessation (COMMIT) was a National Cancer Institute–funded, large-scale study to assess a combination of community-based
interventions designed to help smokers cease using tobacco.  COMMIT involved 11
matched pairs of communities in North America, which were randomly assigned to
an arm offering an active community-wide intervention or a control arm (no
active intervention).<Reference refidx="93"/>  The 4-year intervention included messaging through
existing media channels, major community organizations, and social institutions
capable of influencing smoking behavior in large groups of people.  The
interventions were implemented in each community through a local community
board that provided oversight and management of COMMIT activities.</Para><Para id="_428">In  COMMIT, there was no difference in the mean quit rate
of heavy smokers in the intervention communities (18.0%), compared with  the
control communities (18.7%).  The difference in light-to-moderate smoker quit rates were
statistically significant: averages of 30.6% for the intervention communities and 27.5% for the control communities (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .004).  Although no
significant differences in quit rates between the sexes were observed,
less-educated light-to-moderate smokers were more responsive to the
intervention than were college-educated light-to-moderate smokers.<Reference refidx="94"/><Reference refidx="95"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_290"><Title>A Changing Marketplace for Tobacco Products and Nicotine-Delivery Devices</Title><Para id="_291">The expansion in the marketplace of tobacco products and devices that deliver nicotine poses new challenges to tobacco control.<Reference refidx="96"/><Reference refidx="97"/><Reference refidx="98"/><Reference refidx="99"/><Reference refidx="100"/> Examples of nontraditional tobacco products in the U.S. market include small cigars, water pipe tobacco smoking (hookah), and new types of flavored, smokeless tobacco products modeled after Swedish snus.  Prominent among non–tobacco-containing nicotine delivery devices are electronic cigarettes (or e-cigarettes) that have experienced a rapid upsurge in use and are now marketed by the major U.S. tobacco companies.<Reference refidx="96"/><Reference refidx="97"/> Monitoring this expansion in products, how the products are used (e.g., product switching, multiple use, and use for tobacco cigarette smoking cessation), and the harms and benefits associated with their use compared with the use of tobacco cigarettes is critical to the development of more effective tobacco control strategies.</Para><Para id="_292">Research to determine the potential risks and benefits of these new products is emerging, and initial findings are mixed.<Reference refidx="101"/><Reference refidx="102"/>  The potential benefits of e-cigarettes as a smoking cessation aid for adult smokers is further complicated by two additional factors. First, there has been a marked increase in the use of e-cigarettes  by adolescents, with current (past 30 days) e-cigarette use by high school seniors rising dramatically over the last 3 years, to 27.5% in 2019.<Reference refidx="103"/>  Second, the product has evolved rapidly, with newer electronic nicotine delivery systems, such as JUUL, more quickly and effectively delivering nicotine to the lungs and more closely mimicking cigarettes in terms of their pharmacokinetics.</Para><Para id="_360">In one study,  886 adults who attended the U.K. National Health Service stop-smoking services were randomly assigned to either starter packs of nicotine replacement medication or e-cigarettes.  At 1 year, biochemically confirmed abstinence was 18.0% in the e-cigarette group compared with 9.9% in the nicotine-replacement group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).  However, at 1 year, 80% of abstinent e-cigarette users were still using e-cigarettes, compared with 9% of abstinent nicotine-replacement medication users still using their products.<Reference refidx="104"/> In contrast, a recent pragmatic trial randomly assigned smokers who were employed at 54 companies to access one of four interventions, which included usual care (information and motivational text messages), FDA-approved cessation medications, e-cigarettes, and financial incentives.  The authors found that financial incentives added to free FDA-approved cessation medications resulted in higher quit rates than cessation medications alone. Among smokers who received usual care, the addition of free cessation medications or e-cigarettes did not provide an added benefit.<Reference refidx="105"/></Para><Para id="_361">Evidence suggests that cessation interventions delivered during children's pediatric visits to parents who smoked boost cessation rates.<Reference refidx="83"/>  A recent cluster randomized clinical trial <Reference refidx="106"/> demonstrated higher quit rates 2 years after cessation interventions were delivered during pediatric visits, although there were a limited number of clusters (n = 10) included in the trial.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="38143046">Le TTT, Méndez D, Warner KE: New Estimates of Smoking-Attributable Mortality in the U.S. From 2020 Through 2035. Am J Prev Med 66 (5): 877-882, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="2">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: The Health Consequences of Smoking—50 Years of Progress: A Report of the Surgeon General. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, CDC, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK179276/">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19008791">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): Smoking-attributable mortality, years of potential life lost, and productivity losses--United States, 2000-2004. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 57 (45): 1226-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="4">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention: Targeting Tobacco Use: The Nation's Leading Cause of Death 2005. CDC, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Ontario Task Force on the Primary Prevention of Cancer: Recommendations for the Primary Prevention of Cancer. Queen's Printer for Ontario, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9414173" MedlineID="98074984">Cinciripini PM, Hecht SS, Henningfield JE, et al.: Tobacco addiction: implications for treatment and cancer prevention. J Natl Cancer Inst 89 (24): 1852-67, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9771747" MedlineID="98442690">Finette BA, O'Neill JP, Vacek PM, et al.: Gene mutations with characteristic deletions in cord blood T lymphocytes associated with passive maternal exposure to tobacco smoke. Nat Med 4 (10): 1144-51, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9021312" MedlineID="97173406">Benowitz NL: Cotinine as a biomarker of environmental tobacco smoke exposure. Epidemiol Rev 18 (2): 188-204, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="12082012" MedlineID="22076994">Hecht SS: Human urinary carcinogen metabolites: biomarkers for investigating tobacco and cancer. Carcinogenesis 23 (6): 907-22, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="11">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: The Health Consequences of Involuntary Exposure to Tobacco Smoke: A Report of the Surgeon General. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and
Prevention, Coordinating Center for Health Promotion, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health, 2006. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK44324/">Also available online</ExternalRef>.                       Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="37141154">Cornelius ME, Loretan CG, Jamal A, et al.: Tobacco Product Use Among Adults - United States, 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 72 (18): 475-483, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Youth and Tobacco Use. Atlanta, Ga: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2015. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cdc.gov/tobacco/php/data-statistics/youth-data-tobacco/?CDC_AAref_Val=https://www.cdc.gov/tobacco/data_statistics/fact_sheets/youth_data/tobacco_use/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="19033571">Jemal A, Thun MJ, Ries LA, et al.: Annual report to the nation on the status of cancer, 1975-2005, featuring trends in lung cancer, tobacco use, and tobacco control. J Natl Cancer Inst 100 (23): 1672-94, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="15">Johnston LD, O'Malley PM, Bachman JG: Monitoring the Future: National Survey Results on Drug Use, 1975-2001. Volume I: Secondary School Students. National Institute on Drug Abuse, 2002. NIH Pub. No. 02-5106. <ExternalRef xref="https://monitoringthefuture.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vol1_2001.pdf">Also available online</ExternalRef>.  Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="16">U.S. Preventive Services Task Force: Guide to Clinical Preventive Services: Report of the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. 2nd ed. Williams &amp; Wilkins, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="17">American Cancer Society: Cancer Prevention &amp; Early Detection 
Facts &amp; Figures 2023-2024. American Cancer Society, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/cancer-prevention-and-early-detection-facts-and-figures/2024-cped-files/cped-2024-cff.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="25116426">Schoenborn CA, Adams PF, Peregoy JA: Health behaviors of adults: United States, 2008-2010. Vital Health Stat 10  (257): 1-184, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="19">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: The Health Benefits of Smoking Cessation. A Report of the Surgeon General. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 1990. DHHS Publ No. (CDC) 90-8416.</Citation><Citation idx="20">The Health Consequences of Smoking: A Report of the Surgeon General. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, CDC, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health, 2004. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK44695/">Also available online</ExternalRef>.                Last accessed April 9, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="21">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services: Smoking Cessation: A Report of 
the Surgeon General.  U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Chronic Disease 
Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health, 2020. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/2020-cessation-sgr-full-report.pdf">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="15710956">Anthonisen NR, Skeans MA, Wise RA, et al.: The effects of a smoking cessation intervention on 14.5-year mortality: a randomized clinical trial. Ann Intern Med 142 (4): 233-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="10218505" MedlineID="99232873">Wingo PA, Ries LA, Giovino GA, et al.: Annual report to the nation on the status of cancer, 1973-1996, with a special section on lung cancer and tobacco smoking. J Natl Cancer Inst 91 (8): 675-90, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="10218498" MedlineID="99232866">Koh HK: The end of the "tobacco and cancer" century. J Natl Cancer Inst 91 (8): 660-1, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="29852054">Hartmann-Boyce J, Chepkin SC, Ye W, et al.: Nicotine replacement therapy versus control for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 5 (5): CD000146, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="33411338">Hartmann-Boyce J, Livingstone-Banks J, Ordóñez-Mena JM, et al.: Behavioural interventions for smoking cessation: an overview and network meta-analysis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 1: CD013229, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="23728631">Stead LF, Buitrago D, Preciado N, et al.: Physician advice for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2013 (5): CD000165, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="28">Fiore MC, Jaén CR, Baker TB: Treating Tobacco Use and Dependence [Electronic Resource] : 2008 Update. Rockville, Md: Public Health Service,  U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 2008. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/wysiwyg/professionals/clinicians-providers/guidelines-recommendations/tobacco/clinicians/update/treating_tobacco_use08.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="2118257" MedlineID="90363766">Glynn TJ, Manley MW, Pechacek TF: Physician-initiated smoking cessation program: the National Cancer Institute trials. Prog Clin Biol Res 339: 11-25, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="33464343">Krist AH, Davidson KW, Mangione CM, et al.: Interventions for Tobacco Smoking Cessation in Adults, Including Pregnant Persons: US Preventive Services Task Force Recommendation Statement. JAMA 325 (3): 265-279, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="33464342">Patnode CD, Henderson JT, Coppola EL, et al.: Interventions for Tobacco Cessation in Adults, Including Pregnant Persons: Updated Evidence Report and Systematic Review for the US Preventive Services Task Force. JAMA 325 (3): 280-298, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="32">World Health Organization: WHO Clinical Treatment Guideline for Tobacco Cessation in Adults. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK604670/pdf/Bookshelf_NBK604670.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 7, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="30527452">Barua RS, Rigotti NA, Benowitz NL, et al.: 2018 ACC Expert Consensus Decision Pathway on Tobacco Cessation Treatment: A Report of the American College of Cardiology Task Force on Clinical Expert Consensus Documents. J Am Coll Cardiol 72 (25): 3332-3365, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="32663106">Leone FT, Zhang Y, Evers-Casey S, et al.: Initiating Pharmacologic Treatment in Tobacco-Dependent Adults. An Official American Thoracic Society Clinical Practice Guideline. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 202 (2): e5-e31, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="16116148">Emmons KM, Puleo E, Park E, et al.: Peer-delivered smoking counseling for childhood cancer survivors increases rate of cessation: the partnership for health study. J Clin Oncol 23 (27): 6516-23, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="36898367">Shields PG, Bierut L, Arenberg D, et al.: Smoking Cessation, Version 3.2022, NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 21 (3): 297-322, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="29243221">Rice VH, Heath L, Livingstone-Banks J, et al.: Nursing interventions for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 12 (12): CD001188, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="25970009">Halpern SD, French B, Small DS, et al.: Randomized trial of four financial-incentive programs for smoking cessation. N Engl J Med 372 (22): 2108-17, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="25970008">Sunstein CR: Nudging smokers. N Engl J Med 372 (22): 2150-1, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="31313293">Notley C, Gentry S, Livingstone-Banks J, et al.: Incentives for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 7 (7): CD004307, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="10728115" MedlineID="20192283">Okuyemi KS, Ahluwalia JS, Harris KJ: Pharmacotherapy of smoking cessation. Arch Fam Med 9 (3): 270-81, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="42">Fiore MC, Bailey WC, Cohen SJ, et al.: Smoking Cessation: Clinical Practice Guideline No 18. US Department of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service, Agency for Health Care Policy and Research, 1996. AHCPR Publ No 96-0692.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="8179658" MedlineID="94129259">Tang JL, Law M, Wald N: How effective is nicotine replacement therapy in helping people to stop smoking? BMJ 308 (6920): 21-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="9337378" MedlineID="97465738">Hurt RD, Sachs DP, Glover ED, et al.: A comparison of sustained-release bupropion and placebo for smoking cessation. N Engl J Med 337 (17): 1195-202, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="10053177" MedlineID="99150066">Jorenby DE, Leischow SJ, Nides MA, et al.: A controlled trial of sustained-release bupropion, a nicotine patch, or both for smoking cessation. N Engl J Med 340 (9): 685-91, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="9892454" MedlineID="99107472">Hughes JR, Goldstein MG, Hurt RD, et al.: Recent advances in the pharmacotherapy of smoking. JAMA 281 (1): 72-6, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="23728690">Cahill K, Stevens S, Perera R, et al.: Pharmacological interventions for smoking cessation: an overview and network meta-analysis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 5: CD009329, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="17579497">Ray R, Schnoll RA, Lerman C: Pharmacogenetics and smoking cessation with nicotine replacement therapy. CNS Drugs 21 (7): 525-33, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="49">Fincham JE: Smoking cessation products. In: Covington TR, Berardi RR, Young LL, et al., eds.: Handbook of Nonprescription Drugs. 11th ed. American Pharmaceutical Association, 1996, pp 715-723.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="20626883">Mills EJ, Wu P, Lockhart I, et al.: Adverse events associated with nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) for smoking cessation. A systematic review and meta-analysis of one hundred and twenty studies involving 177,390 individuals. Tob Induc Dis 8 (1): 8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="37335995">Theodoulou A, Chepkin SC, Ye W, et al.: Different doses, durations and modes of delivery of nicotine replacement therapy for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 6 (6): CD013308, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="26813210">Baker TB, Piper ME, Stein JH, et al.: Effects of Nicotine Patch vs Varenicline vs Combination Nicotine Replacement Therapy on Smoking Cessation at 26 Weeks: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 315 (4): 371-9, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="20124230">Schnoll RA, Patterson F, Wileyto EP, et al.: Effectiveness of extended-duration transdermal nicotine therapy: a randomized trial. Ann Intern Med 152 (3): 144-51, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="10065662">Tønnesen P, Paoletti P, Gustavsson G, et al.: Higher dosage nicotine patches increase one-year smoking cessation rates: results from the European CEASE trial. Collaborative European Anti-Smoking Evaluation. European Respiratory Society. Eur Respir J 13 (2): 238-46, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="37230961">Hajizadeh A, Howes S, Theodoulou A, et al.: Antidepressants for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 5 (5): CD000031, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="16820547">Jorenby DE, Hays JT, Rigotti NA, et al.: Efficacy of varenicline, an alpha4beta2 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor partial agonist, vs placebo or sustained-release bupropion for smoking cessation: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA 296 (1): 56-63, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="57" PMID="16820546">Gonzales D, Rennard SI, Nides M, et al.: Varenicline, an alpha4beta2 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor partial agonist, vs sustained-release bupropion and placebo for smoking cessation: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA 296 (1): 47-55, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="58" PMID="18263663">Aubin HJ, Bobak A, Britton JR, et al.: Varenicline versus transdermal nicotine patch for smoking cessation: results from a randomised open-label trial. Thorax 63 (8): 717-24, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="59" PMID="37142273">Livingstone-Banks J, Fanshawe TR, Thomas KH, et al.: Nicotine receptor partial agonists for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 5 (5): CD006103, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="60">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: Information for Healthcare Professionals: Varenicline (Marketed as Chantix) and Bupropion (Marketed as Zyban, Wellbutrin, and Generics). Rockville, Md: U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2009. <ExternalRef xref="https://wayback.archive-it.org/7993/20170112032419/http:/www.fda.gov/Drugs/DrugSafety/PostmarketDrugSafetyInformationforPatientsandProviders/DrugSafetyInformationforHeathcareProfessionals/ucm169986.htm">Archived page available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="61" PMID="27116918">Anthenelli RM, Benowitz NL, West R, et al.: Neuropsychiatric safety and efficacy of varenicline, bupropion, and nicotine patch in smokers with and without psychiatric disorders (EAGLES): a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled clinical trial. Lancet 387 (10037): 2507-20, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="62" PMID="25767129">Thomas KH, Martin RM, Knipe DW, et al.: Risk of neuropsychiatric adverse events associated with varenicline: systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ 350: h1109, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="63" PMID="24030388">Gibbons RD, Mann JJ: Varenicline, smoking cessation, and neuropsychiatric adverse events. Am J Psychiatry 170 (12): 1460-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="64" PMID="18646137">Cahill K, Stead LF, Lancaster T: Nicotine receptor partial agonists for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (3): CD006103, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="65">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: FDA Drug Safety Communication: FDA Revises Description of Mental Health Side Effects of the Stop-Smoking Medicines Chantix (varenicline) and Zyban (bupropion) to Reflect Clinical Trial Findings. U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2016. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/drug-safety-and-availability/fda-drug-safety-communication-fda-revises-description-mental-health-side-effects-stop-smoking">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="66" PMID="21727225">Singh S, Loke YK, Spangler JG, et al.: Risk of serious adverse cardiovascular events associated with varenicline: a systematic review and meta-analysis. CMAJ 183 (12): 1359-66, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="67" PMID="29630702">Benowitz NL, Pipe A, West R, et al.: Cardiovascular Safety of Varenicline, Bupropion, and Nicotine Patch in Smokers: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Intern Med 178 (5): 622-631, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="68">Drug Facts and Comparisons. 54th ed. Facts and Comparisons, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="69" PMID="24402784">Hughes JR, Stead LF, Hartmann-Boyce J, et al.: Antidepressants for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2014 (1): CD000031, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="70" PMID="23404838">Hajek P, McRobbie H, Myers K: Efficacy of cytisine in helping smokers quit: systematic review and meta-analysis. Thorax 68 (11): 1037-42, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="71" PMID="25517706">Walker N, Howe C, Glover M, et al.: Cytisine versus nicotine for smoking cessation. N Engl J Med 371 (25): 2353-62, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="72" PMID="37291049">Oreskovic T, Percac-Lima S, Ashburner JM, et al.: Cytisine Versus Varenicline for Smoking Cessation in a Primary Care Setting: A Randomized Non-inferiority Trial. Nicotine Tob Res 25 (9): 1547-1555, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="73" PMID="15733245">Wagena EJ, Knipschild P, Zeegers MP: Should nortriptyline be used as a first-line aid to help smokers quit? Results from a systematic review and meta-analysis. Addiction 100 (3): 317-26, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="74">Drug Facts and Comparisons. Facts and Comparisons, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="75">Patnode CD, Henderson JT, Melnikow J, et al.: Interventions for Tobacco Cessation in Adults, Including Pregnant Women: an Evidence Update for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. Rockville, Md: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, 2021. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK567066/">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="76" PMID="26198192">Chang PH, Chiang CH, Ho WC, et al.: Combination therapy of varenicline with nicotine replacement therapy is better than varenicline alone: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. BMC Public Health 15: 689, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="77" PMID="34665204">Baker TB, Piper ME, Smith SS, et al.: Effects of Combined Varenicline With Nicotine Patch and of Extended Treatment Duration on Smoking Cessation: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 326 (15): 1485-1493, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="78" PMID="38696203">Cinciripini PM, Green CE, Shete S, et al.: Smoking Cessation After Initial Treatment Failure With Varenicline or Nicotine Replacement: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 331 (20): 1722-1731, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="79" PMID="37338906">Nollen NL, Ahluwalia JS, Mayo MS, et al.: Multiple Pharmacotherapy Adaptations for Smoking Cessation Based on Treatment Response in Black Adults Who Smoke: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Netw Open 6 (6): e2317895, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="80" PMID="33464316">Nollen NL, Ahluwalia JS, Sanderson Cox L, et al.: Assessment of Racial Differences in Pharmacotherapy Efficacy for Smoking Cessation: Secondary Analysis of the EAGLES Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Netw Open 4 (1): e2032053, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="81" PMID="9462488">Ahluwalia JS, McNagny SE, Clark WS: Smoking cessation among inner-city African Americans using the nicotine transdermal patch. J Gen Intern Med 13 (1): 1-8, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="82" PMID="25688780">Ebbert JO, Hughes JR, West RJ, et al.: Effect of varenicline on smoking cessation through smoking reduction: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA 313 (7): 687-94, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="83" PMID="18617085">Clinical Practice Guideline Treating Tobacco Use and Dependence 2008 Update Panel, Liaisons, and Staff: A clinical practice guideline for treating tobacco use and dependence: 2008 update. A U.S. Public Health Service report. Am J Prev Med 35 (2): 158-76, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="84" PMID="26975007">Lindson-Hawley N, Banting M, West R, et al.: Gradual Versus Abrupt Smoking Cessation: A Randomized, Controlled Noninferiority Trial. Ann Intern Med 164 (9): 585-92, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="85" PMID="23821093">Lindson-Hawley N, Aveyard P, Hughes JR: Gradual reduction vs abrupt cessation as a smoking cessation strategy in smokers who want to quit. JAMA 310 (1): 91-2, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="86" PMID="31565800">Lindson N, Klemperer E, Hong B, et al.: Smoking reduction interventions for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 9 (9): CD013183, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="87" PMID="16042638">Hughes JR, Carpenter MJ: The feasibility of smoking reduction: an update. Addiction 100 (8): 1074-89, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="88" PMID="16338284">Batra A, Klingler K, Landfeldt B, et al.: Smoking reduction treatment with 4-mg nicotine gum: a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study. Clin Pharmacol Ther 78 (6): 689-96, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="89" PMID="17414237">Etter JF, Laszlo E: Postintervention effect of nicotine replacement therapy for smoking reduction: a randomized trial with a 5-year follow-up. J Clin Psychopharmacol 27 (2): 151-5, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="90" PMID="17132521">Hughes JR, Carpenter MJ: Does smoking reduction increase future cessation and decrease disease risk? A qualitative review. Nicotine Tob Res 8 (6): 739-49, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="91" PMID="16855966">Thomas R, Perera R: School-based programmes for preventing smoking. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 3: CD001293, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="92" PMID="11121460" MedlineID="21063807">Peterson AV, Kealey KA, Mann SL, et al.: Hutchinson Smoking Prevention Project: long-term randomized trial in school-based tobacco use prevention--results on smoking. J Natl Cancer Inst 92 (24): 1979-91, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="93" PMID="1749015" MedlineID="92085311">Community Intervention Trial for Smoking Cessation (COMMIT): summary of design and intervention. COMMIT Research Group. J Natl Cancer Inst 83 (22): 1620-8, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="94" PMID="7856777" MedlineID="95160166">Community Intervention Trial for Smoking Cessation (COMMIT): I. cohort results from a four-year community intervention. Am J Public Health 85 (2): 183-92, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="95" PMID="7856778" MedlineID="95160167">Community intervention trial for smoking cessation (COMMIT): II. Changes in adult cigarette smoking prevalence. Am J Public Health 85 (2): 193-200, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="96" PMID="23488521">Popova L, Ling PM: Alternative tobacco product use and smoking cessation: a national study. Am J Public Health 103 (5): 923-30, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="97" PMID="23709584">Kamerow D: Big Tobacco lights up e-cigarettes. BMJ 346: f3418, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="98" PMID="23072873">Schuster RM, Hertel AW, Mermelstein R: Cigar, cigarillo, and little cigar use among current cigarette-smoking adolescents. Nicotine Tob Res 15 (5): 925-31, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="99" PMID="23863044">Jawad M, McEwen A, McNeill A, et al.: To what extent should waterpipe tobacco smoking become a public health priority? Addiction 108 (11): 1873-84, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="100" PMID="22854624">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): Consumption of cigarettes and combustible tobacco--United States, 2000-2011. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 61 (30): 565-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="101" PMID="24029165">Bullen C, Howe C, Laugesen M, et al.: Electronic cigarettes for smoking cessation: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 382 (9905): 1629-37, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="102">National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine. Committee on the Review of the Health Effects of Electronic Nicotine Delivery Systems: Public Health Consequences of E-Cigarettes. The National Academies Press, 2018. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29894118">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 20, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="103" PMID="31688912">Cullen KA, Gentzke AS, Sawdey MD, et al.: e-Cigarette Use Among Youth in the United States, 2019. JAMA 322 (21): 2095-2103, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="104" PMID="30699054">Hajek P, Phillips-Waller A, Przulj D, et al.: A Randomized Trial of E-Cigarettes versus Nicotine-Replacement Therapy. N Engl J Med 380 (7): 629-637, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="105" PMID="29791259">Halpern SD, Harhay MO, Saulsgiver K, et al.: A Pragmatic Trial of E-Cigarettes, Incentives, and Drugs for Smoking Cessation. N Engl J Med 378 (24): 2302-2310, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="106" PMID="31403675">Nabi-Burza E, Drehmer JE, Hipple Walters B, et al.: Treating Parents for Tobacco Use in the Pediatric Setting: The Clinical Effort Against Secondhand Smoke Exposure Cluster Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Pediatr 173 (10): 931-939, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (02/21/2025)</Title><Para id="_141">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_425">This summary was comprehensively reviewed and extensively revised.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062879#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the prevention and cessation of cigarette smoking and the control of tobacco use. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000304747" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/screening-prevention">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Cigarette Smoking. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco/quit-smoking-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389444]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-02-21</DateLastModified></Summary>
