<Summary id="CDR0000062888" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Prevention</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Esophageal cancer prevention strategies include avoiding risk factors like alcohol and tobacco. Learn more about risk factors and possible protective factors for esophageal cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-prevention-pdq">Esophageal Cancer (PDQ®): Prevention</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/hp/esophageal-prevention-pdq">Esophageal Cancer (PDQ®): Prevention</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043615">esophageal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041588">cancer prevention</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_121">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about esophageal cancer prevention. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_122">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer prevention</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>esophageal cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Esophageal Cancer Prevention (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Esophageal Cancer Prevention</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Esophageal Cancer Prevention</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Rationale for prevention</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>What Is Prevention?</Title><Para id="_2">Cancer prevention is action taken to lower the chance of getting 
         cancer. By preventing cancer, the number of new cases of cancer 
         in a group or population is lowered. Hopefully, this will lower 
         the number of deaths caused by cancer.</Para><Para id="_3">To prevent new cancers from starting, scientists look at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk 
         factors</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factors</GlossaryTermRef>. Anything that increases your 
         chance of developing cancer is called a cancer risk factor; 
         anything that decreases your chance of developing cancer is 
         called a cancer protective factor.</Para><Para id="_4">Some risk factors for cancer can be avoided, but many cannot. 
         For example, both smoking and inheriting certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> are 
         risk factors for some types of cancer, but only smoking can be 
         avoided. Regular exercise and a healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef> may be protective 
         factors for some types of cancer. Avoiding risk factors and 
         increasing protective factors may lower your risk, but it does 
         not mean that you will not get cancer.</Para><Para id="_5">Different ways to prevent cancer are being studied.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>General Information About Esophageal Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_8"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_9">Esophageal cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer)
		  cells form in the tissues of the esophagus.</KeyPoint><Para id="_10">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef> is the hollow, muscular tube that moves food and
		  liquid from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef> to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>. The wall of the esophagus is made up of several tissue layers,
		  including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucous membrane</GlossaryTermRef>, muscle, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Esophageal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>
		  starts in the inner lining of the esophagus and spreads outward through the
		  other layers as it grows.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000428446" type="image/jpeg" alt="Gastrointestinal (digestive) system anatomy; drawing shows the esophagus, liver, stomach, small intestine, and large intestine." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_11"><Caption language="en">The esophagus and stomach are part of the upper gastrointestinal (digestive) system.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_12">The two most common types of esophageal cancer are named for the
		  type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> that become cancerous:</Para><ItemizedList id="_13" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046595" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Squamous cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>: Cancer forms in the thin, flat cells lining the inside of the esophagus. This cancer is most often found
			 in the upper and middle part of the esophagus but can occur anywhere along the esophagus. This is also called epidermoid
			 carcinoma.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>: Cancer begins in
			 glandular cells.
			 Glandular cells in the lining of the esophagus produce and release fluids such
			 as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046274" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucus</GlossaryTermRef>. Adenocarcinoma usually  forms in the lower part of the esophagus, near
			 the stomach.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_14">Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summaries containing information related to esophageal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000304521" url="/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-screening-pdq">Esophageal Cancer Screening</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062960" url="/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-treatment-pdq">Esophageal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">Esophageal cancer is found more often in men.</KeyPoint><Para id="_133">Rates of esophageal cancer cases and deaths have decreased slightly over recent years. Men are about four times more likely than women to develop esophageal cancer. The chance of  developing this disease increases with age in all racial and ethnic groups. White men are more likely to develop esophageal cancer and have higher death rates from it than Black men across all age groups.  Black women are more likely to develop esophageal cancer until age 74 years, after which White women have a higher risk. Black women have higher death rates from this disease until  age  69 years, after which White women have higher death rates.</Para><Para id="_134">In the United States, rates of adenocarcinoma of the esophagus rose rapidly through the 1990s, overtaking rates of squamous cell carcinoma. Although the rates of squamous cell carcinoma are  declining overall, they  remain much higher  among Black men than White men, while adenocarcinoma rates are higher among White men.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_80"><Title>Esophageal Cancer Prevention</Title><SummarySection id="_127"><KeyPoint id="_128">Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may help prevent cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_127_md_53">Avoiding <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> may help <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> certain cancers. Risk factors include smoking, having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overweight</GlossaryTermRef>, and not getting enough exercise.  Increasing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439422" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protective factors</GlossaryTermRef> such as quitting smoking and exercising may also help prevent some cancers. Talk to your doctor or other health care professional about how you might lower your risk of cancer.</Para><Para id="_130">The risk factors and protective factors for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046595" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">squamous cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the esophagus are not the same.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_81"><KeyPoint id="_82">The following <Emphasis>risk</Emphasis> factors increase 
         the risk of squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_83"><KeyPoint id="_84">Smoking and alcohol use</KeyPoint><Para id="_85">Studies have shown that the risk of squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus is increased in people who smoke or drink a lot.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_89"><KeyPoint id="_90">The following <Emphasis>protective</Emphasis> factors may 
         decrease the risk of squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_91"><KeyPoint id="_92">Avoiding tobacco and alcohol use</KeyPoint><Para id="_93">Studies have shown that  the risk of squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus is lower in people who do not use <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439432" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tobacco</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_94"><KeyPoint id="_95">Chemoprevention with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</KeyPoint><Para id="_131"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045487" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemoprevention</GlossaryTermRef> is the use of drugs, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, or other substances to help lower a person's risk of developing cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</GlossaryTermRef> (NSAIDs)  include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045176" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aspirin</GlossaryTermRef> and other drugs that reduce swelling and pain.</Para><Para id="_96">Some studies have shown that the use of NSAIDs  

 may lower the risk of squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus. However, the use of NSAIDs increases the risk of heart attack, heart failure, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stroke</GlossaryTermRef>,  bleeding in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestines</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef>      damage.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_98"><KeyPoint id="_99">The following <Emphasis>risk</Emphasis> factors increase 
         the risk of adenocarcinoma of the esophagus:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_100"><KeyPoint id="_101">Gastric reflux</KeyPoint><Para id="_102">Adenocarcinoma of the esophagus is strongly linked to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastroesophageal reflux</GlossaryTermRef> disease (GERD), especially when the GERD lasts a long time and severe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> occur daily. GERD is a condition in which the contents of the stomach, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000657842" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach acid</GlossaryTermRef>, flow up  into the lower part of the esophagus. This  irritates the inside of the esophagus, and over time, may affect the cells lining the lower part of the esophagus. This condition is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Barrett esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>. Over time, the affected cells are replaced with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> cells, which may later become adenocarcinoma of the esophagus. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Obesity</GlossaryTermRef> in combination with GERD may further increase the risk of adenocarcinoma of the esophagus.</Para><Para id="_123">The use of medicines that relax the lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sphincter</GlossaryTermRef> muscle of the esophagus may  increase  the likelihood of developing GERD. When the lower sphincter muscle is relaxed, stomach acid may flow up into the lower part of the esophagus.</Para><Para id="_103">It is not known if surgery or other medical treatment to stop <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390280" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastric reflux</GlossaryTermRef> lowers the risk of  adenocarcinoma of the esophagus. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> are being done to see if surgery or medical treatments can prevent Barrett esophagus.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_104"><KeyPoint id="_105">The following <Emphasis>protective</Emphasis> factors may 
         decrease the risk of adenocarcinoma of the esophagus:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_106"><KeyPoint id="_107">Chemoprevention with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</KeyPoint><Para id="_132">Chemoprevention is the use of drugs, vitamins, or other substances to help lower a person's risk of developing cancer.  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) include aspirin and other drugs that reduce swelling and pain.</Para><Para id="_108">Some studies have shown that the use of NSAIDs  

 may lower the risk of adenocarcinoma of the esophagus. However, the use  of NSAIDs increases the risk of heart attack, heart failure, stroke,  bleeding in the stomach and intestines, and kidney      damage.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_109"><KeyPoint id="_110">Radiofrequency ablation of the esophagus</KeyPoint><Para id="_111">Patients with Barrett esophagus who have abnormal cells in the lower esophagus may be treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044865" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiofrequency ablation</GlossaryTermRef>. This procedure  uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef> to heat and destroy abnormal cells, which may become cancer. Risks of using radiofrequency ablation include narrowing of the esophagus and bleeding in the esophagus, stomach, or intestines.</Para><Para id="_126">One study of patients who have Barrett esophagus and abnormal cells in the esophagus compared patients who received radiofrequency ablation with patients who did not. Patients who received radiofrequency ablation were less likely to be diagnosed with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophageal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. More studies are needed  to know whether radiofrequency ablation decreases the risk of adenocarcinoma of the esophagus in  patients with these conditions.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_113"><KeyPoint id="_114">Cancer prevention clinical trials are used to study ways 
    to prevent cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_113_md_14">Cancer prevention <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> are used to study ways to lower the risk of developing certain types of cancer. Some cancer prevention trials include healthy people who may or may not have an increased risk of cancer. Other prevention trials include people who have had cancer and are trying to prevent recurrence or a second cancer.</Para><Para id="_113_md_15">The purpose of some cancer prevention clinical trials is to find out whether actions people take can prevent cancer. These may include eating fruits and vegetables, exercising, quitting smoking, or taking certain medicines, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>, or food <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463726" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><KeyPoint id="_66">
      
     New ways to prevent esophageal cancer are being studied in clinical 
     trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_65_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about esophageal cancer prevention.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Esophageal Cancer Prevention. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-prevention-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/esophageal-prevention-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389280]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062880"/><DateLastModified>2025-03-11</DateLastModified></Summary>
