<Summary id="CDR0000062886" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Vulvar cancer treatment options include a variety of surgical procedures, topical imiquimod, radiation therapy, chemotherapy, and chemoradiation. Get detailed treatment information for newly diagnosed and recurrent vulvar cancer in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Vulvar Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar/patient/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Vulvar Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037961">vulvar cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_422">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of vulvar cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_423">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>vulvar cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Vulvar Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Vulvar Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Vulvar Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037961">vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_426">This  summary addresses squamous cell cancer of the vulva and vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia (VIN). VIN may be a precursor to invasive squamous cell cancer. </Para><Para id="_427">About 50% of vulvar carcinomas arise in the labia majora, the most common site. The labia minora are the site of 15% to 20% of vulvar carcinoma cases. The clitoris and Bartholin glands are less frequently involved.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Lesions are multifocal in about 5% of cases. More than 90% of invasive vulvar cancers are squamous cell carcinomas.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><SummarySection id="_188"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_386">Vulvar cancer accounts for about 6% of cancers of the female genital system in the United States.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_131">Estimated new  cases and deaths from vulvar cancer in the United States in 2025:<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_132" Style="bullet"><ListItem>New cases:  7,480.</ListItem><ListItem>Deaths:  1,770.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_428"><Title>Anatomy</Title><Para id="_429">The vulva is the area immediately external to the vagina, including the mons pubis, labia, clitoris, and Bartholin glands.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000742480" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the vulva; drawing shows the mons pubis, clitoris, urethral opening, inner and outer lips of the vagina, and the vaginal opening. Also shown are the perineum and anus." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_564"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the vulva. The vulva includes the mons pubis, clitoris, inner and outer lips of the vagina, and the openings of the  urethra and vagina.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_394"><Title>Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_430">Increasing age is the most important risk factor for most cancers. Other risk factors associated with vulvar cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_434" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Human papillomavirus (HPV) infection: In many cases, the development of vulvar cancer is preceded by condyloma or
squamous dysplasia.  The prevailing evidence favors HPV
infection as a causative factor in many genital tract carcinomas.<Reference refidx="4"/> <Para id="_532">HPV-associated VIN,  termed <Emphasis>usual-type VIN</Emphasis> when high grades 2 and 3, is most common in women younger than 50  years, whereas non–HPV-associated VIN, termed <Emphasis>differentiated-type VIN</Emphasis> when high grade 3, is most common in older women.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  </Para><Para id="_533">The former lesion-type VIN grade 1 is no longer classified as a true VIN.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> The HPV-related basaloid and warty types are associated with VIN.  About 75% to 100% of basaloid and warty carcinomas harbor HPV infection. In addition to the much higher prevalence of HPV in these subtypes than in the keratinizing subtypes, the basaloid and warty subtypes also share many common risk factors with cervical cancers, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_550" Style="bullet"><ListItem>High number of sexual partners.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem><ListItem>Initiation of sexual intercourse at an early age.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem><ListItem>History of abnormal Pap smears.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_552"> For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062759" url="/types/cervical/hp/cervical-treatment-pdq">Cervical Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_435"><Title>Clinical Features</Title><Para id="_436">Women with  VIN may not present with symptoms at diagnosis.   </Para><Para id="_534">Possible signs and symptoms of invasive squamous cell cancers of the vulva include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_437" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Vulvar lesion.</ListItem><ListItem>Vulvar pruritus.</ListItem><ListItem>Bleeding.</ListItem><ListItem>Pain.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_438"><Title>Diagnostic and Staging Evaluation</Title><Para id="_439">The following procedures may be used to diagnose and stage vulvar cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_440" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Physical examination and history.</ListItem><ListItem>Pelvic examination.</ListItem><ListItem>Pap smear.</ListItem><ListItem>HPV testing.</ListItem><ListItem>Biopsy. The patient may be examined under anesthesia.</ListItem><ListItem>Colposcopy.</ListItem><ListItem>Imaging studies (magnetic resonance imaging, computed tomography [CT], and positron emission tomography-CT).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_431"><Title>Prognosis</Title><Para id="_432">Prognosis depends on the pathological status of the inguinal lymph nodes and whether spread to adjacent structures has occurred.<Reference refidx="8"/>  In patients  with operable disease without lymph node involvement, the overall survival (OS) rate is 90%. However,
in patients with nodal involvement, the 5-year OS rate is approximately 50%
to 60%.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_433"> The size of the primary tumor is less important in defining prognosis.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_441"><Title>Follow-Up After Treatment</Title><Para id="_442">Invasive and preinvasive neoplasms of the vulva may be HPV-induced, and the carcinogenic effect may be widespread in the vulvar epithelium. As a result, patients are monitored regularly for signs or symptoms of recurrence.  </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3020404" MedlineID="87014616">Macnab JC, Walkinshaw SA, Cordiner JW, et al.: Human papillomavirus in clinically and histologically normal tissue of patients with genital cancer. N Engl J Med 315 (17): 1052-8, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Eifel PJ, Klopp AH, Berek JS, et al.: Cancer of the cervix, vagina, and vulva. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 1171-1210.</Citation><Citation idx="3">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="17138767">Hampl M, Sarajuuri H, Wentzensen N, et al.: Effect of human papillomavirus vaccines on vulvar, vaginal, and anal intraepithelial lesions and vulvar cancer. Obstet Gynecol 108 (6): 1361-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21491403">Pepas L, Kaushik S, Bryant A, et al.: Medical interventions for high grade vulval intraepithelial neoplasia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (4): CD007924, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16419625">Sideri M, Jones RW, Wilkinson EJ, et al.: Squamous vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia: 2004 modified terminology, ISSVD Vulvar Oncology Subcommittee. J Reprod Med 50 (11): 807-10, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="12807940">Schiffman M, Kjaer SK: Chapter 2: Natural history of anogenital human papillomavirus infection and neoplasia. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr  (31): 14-9, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="8">Olawaiye AB, Hagemann I, Bhoshale P, et al.: Vulva. In: Goodman KA, Gollub M, Eng C, et al.: AJCC Cancer Staging System. Version 9. American Joint Committee on Cancer; American College of Surgeons, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="2014852" MedlineID="91196796">Homesley HD, Bundy BN, Sedlis A, et al.: Assessment of current International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics staging of vulvar carcinoma relative to prognostic factors for survival (a Gynecologic Oncology Group study). Am J Obstet Gynecol 164 (4): 997-1003; discussion 1003-4, 1991.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037961">vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular Classification of Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_6">The histological classification of vulvar
disease and precursor lesions of cancer of the vulva was developed by the
International Society for the Study of Vulvovaginal Disease (ISSVD).<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_417"><Strong>Nonneoplastic epithelial disorders of vulvar skin and mucosa</Strong></Para><ItemizedList id="_8" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lichen sclerosus (lichen sclerosus et atrophicus).
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Squamous cell hyperplasia (formerly hyperplastic dystrophy).
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Other dermatoses.
</ListItem>
</ItemizedList><Para id="_418"><Strong>Vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia (VIN)</Strong></Para><ItemizedList id="_530" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion (SIL)  of the vulva (vulvar LSIL) encompasses flat condyloma or human papillomavirus effect.</ListItem><ListItem>High-grade SIL (vulvar HSIL) was termed VIN, usual type in the 2004 ISSVD terminology.</ListItem><ListItem>VIN, differentiated type.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_419"><Strong>Paget disease of the vulva</Strong></Para><ItemizedList id="_12" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Characteristic large pale cells in the epithelium and skin adnexa.
</ListItem>
</ItemizedList><Para id="_420"><Strong>Other histologies
</Strong></Para><ItemizedList id="_14" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Basal cell carcinoma.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Langerhans cell histiocytosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Malignant melanoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Sarcoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Verrucous carcinoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26704327">Bornstein J, Bogliatto F, Haefner HK, et al.: The 2015 International Society for the Study of Vulvovaginal Disease (ISSVD) Terminology of Vulvar Squamous Intraepithelial Lesions. J Low Genit Tract Dis 20 (1): 11-4, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037961">vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_535">The staging evaluation for vulvar cancer may include the following procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_536" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Cystoscopy.</ListItem><ListItem>Proctoscopy.</ListItem><ListItem>X-ray examination of the lungs.</ListItem><ListItem>Intravenous (IV) urography (also known as IV pyelography).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_17">  Suspected bladder or rectal involvement
must be confirmed by biopsy.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><SummarySection id="_234"><Title>The Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique (FIGO) Staging</Title><Para id="_18">FIGO and the American Joint Committee on Cancer have designated staging to define vulvar cancer; the FIGO system is most commonly used.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Stage is based on pathological staging at the time of surgery or before any radiation or chemotherapy, if they are the initial treatment modalities.<Reference refidx="3"/>
</Para><Para id="_446">The staging system does not apply to malignant melanoma of the vulva, which is staged like melanoma of the skin.<Reference refidx="1"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062917#_884" url="/types/skin/hp/melanoma-treatment-pdq">Stage Information for Melanoma</SummaryRef> section in Melanoma Treatment.</Para><Table id="_556"><Title>Table 1. Definitions of FIGO Stage I, IA, and IB<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="28.32%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="10.64%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="61.02%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">Definition</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Depth of invasion is measured from the basement membrane of the deepest, adjacent, dysplastic, tumor-free rete ridge (or nearest dysplastic rete peg)  to the deepest point of invasion.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">I</entry><entry>Tumor confined to the vulva.</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IA</entry><entry>Tumor size ≤2 cm and stromal invasion ≤1 mm<Superscript>b</Superscript>.</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IB</entry><entry>Tumor size &gt;2 cm or stromal invasion &gt;1 mm<Superscript>b</Superscript>.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_557"><Title>Table 2. Definition of FIGO Stage II<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="39.21%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="60.78%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">Definition</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry Align="Center">II</entry><entry>Tumor of any size with extension to lower one-third of the urethra, lower one-third of the vagina, lower one-third of the anus with negative nodes.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_558"><Title>Table 3. Definitions of FIGO Stage III, IIIA, IIIB, and IIIC<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="28.58%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="12.06%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="59.34%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">Definition</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Regional refers to inguinal and femoral lymph nodes.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">III</entry><entry>Tumor of any size with extension to upper part of  adjacent perineal structures, or with any number of nonfixed, nonulcerated lymph nodes.</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIA</entry><entry>Tumor of any size with disease extension to upper two-thirds of the urethra, upper two-thirds of the vagina, bladder mucosa, rectal mucosa, or regional lymph node metastases ≤5 mm.</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIB</entry><entry>Regional<Superscript>b</Superscript> lymph node metastases &gt;5 mm.</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIC</entry><entry>Regional<Superscript>b</Superscript> lymph  node metastases with extracapsular spread.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_559"><Title>Table 4. Definitions of FIGO Stage IV, IVA, and IVB<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="29.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="13.12%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="57.87%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">Definition</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Regional refers to inguinal and femoral lymph nodes.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IV</entry><entry>Tumor of any size fixed to bone, or fixed, ulcerated lymph node metastases, or distant metastases.</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IVA</entry><entry>Disease fixed to pelvic bone, <Strong>or</Strong> fixed or ulcerated regional<Superscript>b</Superscript> lymph node metastases.</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IVB</entry><entry>Distant metastases.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_200">Grade is reported in registry systems and may differ between systems;   a two-, three-, or four-grade system may be applied.  If not specified, the following system is generally used:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_201" Style="bullet"><ListItem>GX:	Grade cannot be assessed.</ListItem><ListItem>	G1:	Well differentiated.</ListItem><ListItem>G2:	Moderately differentiated.</ListItem><ListItem>G3:	Poorly differentiated.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_443">Overall, about 30% of
patients with operable disease have lymph node spread.  The pattern of spread is influenced by the histology.  Risk factors for lymph node metastasis include:<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_444" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Clinical node status.</ListItem><ListItem>  Age.</ListItem><ListItem> Degree
of tumor differentiation.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor stage.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor thickness.</ListItem><ListItem>Depth of stromal invasion.</ListItem><ListItem>Presence of capillary-lymphatic space invasion.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_537">Well-differentiated
lesions tend to spread along the surface with minimal invasion, whereas
anaplastic lesions are more likely to be deeply invasive.  Spread beyond the
vulva is either to adjacent organs such as the vagina, urethra, and anus, or
via the lymphatics to the inguinal and femoral lymph nodes, followed by the deep
pelvic nodes.  Hematogenous spread appears to be uncommon.
</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Olawaiye AB, Hagemann I, Bhoshale P, et al.: Vulva. In: Goodman KA, Gollub M, Eng C, et al.: AJCC Cancer Staging System. Version 9. American Joint Committee on Cancer; American College of Surgeons, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="34669204">Olawaiye AB, Cuello MA, Rogers LJ: Cancer of the vulva: 2021 update. Int J Gynaecol Obstet 155 (Suppl 1): 7-18, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1427397" MedlineID="93051692">Hopkins MP, Reid GC, Johnston CM, et al.: A comparison of staging systems for squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 47 (1): 34-7, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="2014852" MedlineID="91196796">Homesley HD, Bundy BN, Sedlis A, et al.: Assessment of current International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics staging of vulvar carcinoma relative to prognostic factors for survival (a Gynecologic Oncology Group study). Am J Obstet Gynecol 164 (4): 997-1003; discussion 1003-4, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3972295" MedlineID="85128632">Boyce J, Fruchter RG, Kasambilides E, et al.: Prognostic factors in carcinoma of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 20 (3): 364-77, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="3578430" MedlineID="87210420">Sedlis A, Homesley H, Bundy BN, et al.: Positive groin lymph nodes in superficial squamous cell vulvar cancer. A Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. Am J Obstet Gynecol 156 (5): 1159-64, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="1691127" MedlineID="90215384">Binder SW, Huang I, Fu YS, et al.: Risk factors for the development of lymph node metastasis in vulvar squamous cell carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 37 (1): 9-16, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8314530" MedlineID="93300422">Homesley HD, Bundy BN, Sedlis A, et al.: Prognostic factors for groin node metastasis in squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva (a Gynecologic Oncology Group study) Gynecol Oncol 49 (3): 279-83, 1993.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037961">vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_202">The primary treatment for vulvar cancer is surgery.  Radiation therapy is also given to patients with stage III or IV disease.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  Newer strategies have integrated surgery, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy and tailor the treatment to the extent of clinical and pathological disease.  Patterns of practice in combining these treatments vary.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_203">Because there are few patients with advanced disease (stages III and IV), only limited data are available on treatment efficacy in this setting, and there is no standard chemotherapy regimen for these patients. Physicians may offer eligible patients with stage III or IV disease participation in clinical trials. </Para><Para id="_387">Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Table id="_553"><Title>Table 5. Treatment Options for Vulvar Cancer</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage (<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_234" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">FIGO Staging Criteria</SummaryRef>)</entry><entry>Treatment Options</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique; VIN = vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">VIN (this stage is not recognized by FIGO)</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_221" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_451" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Topical imiquimod</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Stages I and II vulvar cancer</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_456" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_460" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery and radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_462" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy alone</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Stage III vulvar cancer</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_473" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery with or without radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_476" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy or chemoradiation therapy followed by surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_478" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Stage IVA vulvar cancer</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_482" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_484" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery and radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_486" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy or chemoradiation therapy followed by surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_488" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry>Stage IVB vulvar cancer</entry><entry>Chemotherapy</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Recurrent vulvar cancer</entry><entry>Wide local excision with or without radiation therapy</entry></Row><Row><entry>Radical vulvectomy and pelvic exenteration </entry></Row><Row><entry>Synchronous radiation therapy and cytotoxic chemotherapy with or without surgery</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_204"><Title>Surgery</Title><SummarySection id="_369"><Title>Surgical resection</Title><Para id="_371">Since the 1980s, the trend of surgical resection in patients with vulvar cancer has been toward more limited surgery, often combined with radiation therapy to minimize morbidity.<Reference refidx="5"/> In tumors clinically confined to the vulva or perineum,  radical local excision with a margin of at least 1 cm has generally replaced radical vulvectomy; separate incision has replaced en bloc inguinal lymph node dissection; ipsilateral inguinal node dissection has replaced bilateral dissection for laterally localized tumors; and femoral lymph node dissection has been omitted in many cases.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  However, the different surgical techniques have not been directly compared in randomized controlled trials.  In addition, nonrandomized studies lack uniform staging definitions and clear descriptions of lymph node dissection or ancillary radiation.<Reference refidx="8"/>[Levels of evidence <LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">C2</LOERef> and <LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">C3</LOERef>] The evidence base is, therefore, limited.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_372"><Title>Sentinel lymph node dissection (SLND)</Title><Para id="_373">Another strategy to minimize the morbidity incurred by groin lymph node dissection in patients with early clinical-stage disease is SLND, reserving groin dissection for those with metastases to the sentinel node(s).  </Para><Para id="_503">Evidence (SLND):</Para><OrderedList id="_504" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>In a multicenter case series, 403 patients with primary vulvar squamous cell cancers smaller than 4 cm and clinically negative groin lymph nodes underwent 623 SLNDs (using radioactive tracer and blue dye for sentinel node identification).<Reference refidx="9"/> All patients had radical resection of the primary tumor.  Node metastases were identified in 26% of SLND procedures, and these patients went on to full inguinofemoral lymphadenectomy.  The patients with negative sentinel nodes received no further therapy.  After two local recurrences in 17 patients with multifocal primary tumors, the protocol was amended to allow only patients with unifocal tumors into the study.<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]  <ItemizedList id="_505" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Local morbidity was much lower in patients who underwent SLND than in patients with positive sentinel nodes who also underwent inguinofemoral lymphadenectomy (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_546" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Table 6</SummaryRef>).  <Table id="_546"><Title>Table 6. Comparison<Superscript>a</Superscript> of Local Morbidity in Patients Treated With SLND Versus SLND and Inguinofemoral Lymphadenectomy</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center" Valign="Middle">Complications</entry><entry Align="Center" Valign="Middle">Local Morbidity From SLND (%)</entry><entry Align="Center" Valign="Middle">Local Morbidity From SLND and Inguinofemoral Lymphadenectomy (%) </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">SLND = Sentinel lymph node dissection.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript><Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001 for all comparisons.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Wound breakdown</entry><entry Align="Center">11.7</entry><entry Align="Center">34</entry></Row><Row><entry>Cellulitis</entry><entry Align="Center">4.5</entry><entry Align="Center">21.3</entry></Row><Row><entry>Chronic lymphedema</entry><entry Align="Center">1.9</entry><entry Align="Center">25.2</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></ListItem><ListItem>The mean hospital stay was 8.4 days for patients who underwent SLND and 13.7 days for patients who underwent SLND and inguinofemoral lymphadenectomy (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).  </ListItem><ListItem>The actuarial groin recurrence rate for all patients with negative SLND results at 2 years was 3% (95% confidence interval [CI], 1%–6%) and 2% (95% CI, 1%–5%) for those with unifocal primary tumors.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_376">SLND may be useful when performed by a surgeon experienced in the procedure, and it may avoid the need for full groin lymph node dissection or radiation therapy  in patients with clinically nonsuspicious lymph nodes. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_208"><Title>Radiation Therapy</Title><Para id="_448">Radical radiation therapy can be used for patients unable to tolerate surgery or when surgery is not an option because of the site or extent of disease.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_209">Groin lymph node metastases are present in approximately 20% to 35% of patients with tumors clinically confined to the vulva and with clinically negative nodes.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="14"/>  Lymph node dissection is  traditionally part of the primary surgical therapy in all but the smallest tumors.  Some investigators recommend radiation therapy as a means to avoid the morbidity of lymph node dissection, but it is not clear whether radiation therapy can achieve the same local control rates or survival rates as lymph node dissection in early-stage disease.  </Para><SummarySection id="_377"><Title>Localized node-negative disease</Title><Para id="_378">A randomized trial to address the efficacy of radiation therapy in patients with clinically localized vulvar cancer has been reported.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>  In that study, women with disease clinically confined to the vulva, who did not have clinically suspicious groin lymph node metastases,  underwent radical vulvectomy followed by either groin radiation (50 Gy at 2 Gy per fraction) or groin dissection (plus groin radiation if nodes were pathologically involved).  Although the planned accrual was 300 patients, the study was stopped after 58 women were randomly assigned because of worse outcomes in the radiation therapy arm.  </Para><ItemizedList id="_538" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Five of 27 (18.5%) women in the radiation therapy arm and 0 of 25 women in the groin dissection arm had a groin recurrence, but this difference was not statistically significant (relative risk [RR], 10.21; 95% CI, 0.59–175.78).  </ListItem><ListItem>There were ten deaths in the radiation therapy arm and three deaths in the groin dissection arm (RR, 4.31; 95% CI, 1.03–18.15).  </ListItem><ListItem>Disease-specific mortality was not statistically significantly different between the two arms. However, there were eight vulvar cancer–related deaths in the radiation therapy arm versus two  vulvar cancer–related deaths in the groin dissection arm (including one related to the groin dissection surgery) (RR, 3.70; 95% CI, 0.87–15.80).<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  </ListItem><ListItem>There were fewer cases of lymphedema (none in the radiation therapy arm vs. seven in the groin dissection arm) and shorter hospital stays in the radiation therapy arm. The dose penetration of the radiation (3 cm for full dose) has been criticized as inadequate.<Reference refidx="14"/>  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_539">In summary, the trial was stopped prematurely, and little can be said about the relative efficacy of the two treatment approaches.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_380"><Title>Pelvic node–positive disease</Title><Para id="_381">Pelvic radiation therapy has been compared with pelvic node resection in patients with documented groin node–positive disease.  </Para><Para id="_506">Evidence (pelvic node resection vs. pelvic radiation therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_507" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Patients with clinical stage I to stage IV primary squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva in whom groin node metastases were found at radical vulvectomy and bilateral groin lymph node dissection were randomly assigned (during the surgical procedure) to receive either ipsilateral pelvic node resection or pelvic radiation therapy (45 Gy–50 Gy at 1.8 Gy–2.0 Gy per fraction).<Reference refidx="16"/> Because of a perceived emerging benefit of radiation therapy, the planned accrual of 152 patients was stopped after 114 patients were randomly assigned.  However, the apparent benefit of radiation was subsequently attenuated with further follow-up.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  <ItemizedList id="_508" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>After a median follow-up of 74 months, the 6-year overall survival (OS) rate was 51% in the pelvic radiation therapy arm versus 41% in the pelvic node resection arm (hazard ratio [HR], 0.61; 95% CI, 0.3–1.3; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .18).  </ListItem><ListItem>Vulvar cancer–specific mortality was statistically significantly lower in the pelvic radiation therapy arm (29% in the pelvic radiation therapy arm vs. 51% in the pelvic node resection arm) (HR, 0.49; 95% CI, 0.28–0.87; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .015).  However, there were 14 intercurrent deaths in the pelvic radiation therapy arm versus two deaths in the pelvic node resection arm.</ListItem><ListItem>Late chronic lymphedema was similar in both trial arms with 16% in the pelvic radiation therapy arm and 22% in the pelvic node resection  arm.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_212"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_213">There is no standard chemotherapy for vulvar cancer, and reports describing the use of this modality in the setting of metastatic or recurrent disease are  anecdotal.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_540">  Extrapolating from regimens used for anal or cervical squamous cell cancers, chemotherapy has been studied in combination with radiation in the neoadjuvant setting or as primary therapy in advanced disease. Chemotherapy regimens have included various combinations of fluorouracil (5-FU), cisplatin, mitomycin, or bleomycin.<Reference refidx="5"/> </Para><Para id="_541">There is no clear evidence of improvement in survival or palliation.  Given the advanced age and comorbidities of many patients with advanced or recurrent vulvar cancer, patient tolerance is a major consideration in the use of these agents. </Para><SummarySection id="_382"><Title>Systemic treatment for inoperable patients</Title><Para id="_383">A systematic review of the use of neoadjuvant chemoradiation therapy in patients who were considered inoperable or who would have required extensive surgery, such as pelvic exenteration, colostomy, or urinary diversion, revealed no randomized trials.<Reference refidx="17"/> Five nonrandomized studies that met the inclusion criteria of neoadjuvant chemoradiation therapy administered in this population with an intent to permit curative surgery were reviewed.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/>  The five studies used four different chemoradiation therapy schedules and different radiation therapy dose-fractionation techniques.  In the four studies using 5-FU with either cisplatin or mitomycin, the operability rate after chemoradiation therapy ranged from 63% to 92%.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/> In the one study using bleomycin, the operability rate was only 20%.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_398"> In summary, there is evidence that neoadjuvant chemoradiation therapy with 5-FU plus either cisplatin or mitomycin may convert patients to a more operable status, but the evidence base is limited by study design. In addition to a paucity of randomized trials, interpretation of these studies is complicated by the lack of a standard definition of operability.<Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]  Treatment-related toxicity is substantial.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_384"><Title>Systemic treatment for operable patients</Title><Para id="_385">There is limited evidence about the use of neoadjuvant chemoradiation therapy in advanced operable vulvar cancer, and the available data do not suggest an advantage to this approach.  A systematic review found only one randomized trial that addressed this issue, and it was published only in abstract form.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="23"/>  In that trial, 68 patients with advanced vulvar cancer (T2* &gt;4 cm, T3*, any case with positive lymph nodes) were randomly assigned to either receive preoperative neoadjuvant radiation therapy (50 Gy) concomitantly with 5-FU and mitomycin or primary surgery.  Neoadjuvant therapy–related serious toxicity was high (13 of 24 patients; 10 patients had wound diastasis).  After a mean follow-up of 42 months, the 5-year OS rate was 30% in the neoadjuvant chemoradiation therapy arm and 49% in the primary surgery arm (RR<Subscript>death</Subscript>, 1.39; 95% CI, 0.94–2.06; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .19).<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] <Note>*T2 is defined as tumor confined to the vulva and/or
perineum, more than 2 cm in greatest
dimension, and T3 is defined as tumor that invades any of the following: the
lower urethra, vagina, or anus.</Note></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_569"><Title>Fluorouracil dosing</Title><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000813769_3"><Para id="_sm_CDR0000813769_4">The <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> gene encodes an enzyme that catabolizes pyrimidines and fluoropyrimidines, like capecitabine and fluorouracil. An estimated 1% to 2% of the population has germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName>, which lead to reduced DPD protein function and an accumulation of pyrimidines and fluoropyrimidines in the body.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/> Patients with the <GeneName>DPYD*2A</GeneName> variant who receive fluoropyrimidines may experience severe, life-threatening toxicities that are sometimes fatal. Many other <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> variants have been identified,  with a range of clinical effects.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/> Fluoropyrimidine avoidance or a dose reduction of 50% may be recommended based on  the patient's <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> genotype and number of functioning <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> alleles.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/> <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> genetic testing costs less than $200, but insurance coverage varies due to  a lack of national guidelines.<Reference refidx="30"/> In addition, testing may delay therapy by 2 weeks, which would not be advisable in urgent situations. This controversial issue requires further evaluation.<Reference refidx="31"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="8431905" MedlineID="93161306">Hacker NF, Van der Velden J: Conservative management of early vulvar cancer. Cancer 71 (4 Suppl): 1673-7, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1916517" MedlineID="92009508">Thomas GM, Dembo AJ, Bryson SC, et al.: Changing concepts in the management of vulvar cancer. Gynecol Oncol 42 (1): 9-21, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="3785783" MedlineID="87066001">Homesley HD, Bundy BN, Sedlis A, et al.: Radiation therapy versus pelvic node resection for carcinoma of the vulva with positive groin nodes. Obstet Gynecol 68 (6): 733-40, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="21491387">Shylasree TS, Bryant A, Howells RE: Chemoradiation for advanced primary vulval cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (4): CD003752, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Eifel PJ, Klopp AH, Berek JS, et al.: Cancer of the cervix, vagina, and vulva. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 1171-1210.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2652013" MedlineID="89219903">Hoffman MS, Roberts WS, Lapolla JP, et al.: Recent modifications in the treatment of invasive squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva. Obstet Gynecol Surv 44 (4): 227-33, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="2227541" MedlineID="91033191">Heaps JM, Fu YS, Montz FJ, et al.: Surgical-pathologic variables predictive of local recurrence in squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 38 (3): 309-14, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="10796849">Ansink A, van der Velden J: Surgical interventions for early squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (2): CD002036, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="18281661">Van der Zee AG, Oonk MH, De Hullu JA, et al.: Sentinel node dissection is safe in the treatment of early-stage vulvar cancer. J Clin Oncol 26 (6): 884-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="8244830" MedlineID="94064447">Petereit DG, Mehta MP, Buchler DA, et al.: Inguinofemoral radiation of N0,N1 vulvar cancer may be equivalent to lymphadenectomy if proper radiation technique is used. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 27 (4): 963-7, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2924095" MedlineID="89167510">Slevin NJ, Pointon RC: Radical radiotherapy for carcinoma of the vulva. Br J Radiol 62 (734): 145-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="8490921" MedlineID="93258756">Perez CA, Grigsby PW, Galakatos A, et al.: Radiation therapy in management of carcinoma of the vulva with emphasis on conservation therapy. Cancer 71 (11): 3707-16, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="3212218" MedlineID="89099741">Kumar PP, Good RR, Scott JC: Techniques for management of vulvar cancer by irradiation alone. Radiat Med 6 (4): 185-91, 1988 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="1526880" MedlineID="92406591">Stehman FB, Bundy BN, Thomas G, et al.: Groin dissection versus groin radiation in carcinoma of the vulva: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 24 (2): 389-96, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="21563133">van der Velden J, Fons G, Lawrie TA: Primary groin irradiation versus primary groin surgery for early vulvar cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (5): CD002224, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="19701032">Kunos C, Simpkins F, Gibbons H, et al.: Radiation therapy compared with pelvic node resection for node-positive vulvar cancer: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol 114 (3): 537-46, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="16856018">van Doorn HC, Ansink A, Verhaar-Langereis M, et al.: Neoadjuvant chemoradiation for advanced primary vulvar cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 3: CD003752, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="7557615">Eifel PJ, Morris M, Burke TW, et al.: Prolonged continuous infusion cisplatin and 5-fluorouracil with radiation for locally advanced carcinoma of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 59 (1): 51-6, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="8641609">Landoni F, Maneo A, Zanetta G, et al.: Concurrent preoperative chemotherapy with 5-fluorouracil and mitomycin C and radiotherapy (FUMIR) followed by limited surgery in locally advanced and recurrent vulvar carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 61 (3): 321-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="11072157">Montana GS, Thomas GM, Moore DH, et al.: Preoperative chemo-radiation for carcinoma of the vulva with N2/N3 nodes: a gynecologic oncology group study. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 48 (4): 1007-13, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="9747823">Moore DH, Thomas GM, Montana GS, et al.: Preoperative chemoradiation for advanced vulvar cancer: a phase II study of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 42 (1): 79-85, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="7505091">Scheiströen M, Tropé C: Combined bleomycin and irradiation in preoperative treatment of advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva. Acta Oncol 32 (6): 657-61, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="23">Maneo A, Landoni F, Colombo A, et al.: Randomised study between neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy and primary surgery for the treatment of advanced vulvar cancer. [Abstract] Int J Gynecol Cancer  13 (Suppl 1): A-PL19, 6, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="34506675">Sharma BB, Rai K, Blunt H, et al.: Pathogenic DPYD Variants and Treatment-Related Mortality in Patients Receiving Fluoropyrimidine Chemotherapy: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Oncologist 26 (12): 1008-1016, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="27569869">Lam SW, Guchelaar HJ, Boven E: The role of pharmacogenetics in capecitabine efficacy and toxicity. Cancer Treat Rev 50: 9-22, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="33410339">Shakeel F, Fang F, Kwon JW, et al.: Patients carrying DPYD variant alleles have increased risk of severe toxicity and related treatment modifications during fluoropyrimidine chemotherapy. Pharmacogenomics 22 (3): 145-155, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="29152729">Amstutz U, Henricks LM, Offer SM, et al.: Clinical Pharmacogenetics Implementation Consortium (CPIC) Guideline for Dihydropyrimidine Dehydrogenase Genotype and Fluoropyrimidine Dosing: 2017 Update. Clin Pharmacol Ther 103 (2): 210-216, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="30348537">Henricks LM, Lunenburg CATC, de Man FM, et al.: DPYD genotype-guided dose individualisation of fluoropyrimidine therapy in patients with cancer: a prospective safety analysis. Lancet Oncol 19 (11): 1459-1467, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="34996412">Lau-Min KS, Varughese LA, Nelson MN, et al.: Preemptive pharmacogenetic testing to guide chemotherapy dosing in patients with gastrointestinal malignancies: a qualitative study of barriers to implementation. BMC Cancer 22 (1): 47, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="35668003">Brooks GA, Tapp S, Daly AT, et al.: Cost-effectiveness of DPYD Genotyping Prior to Fluoropyrimidine-based Adjuvant Chemotherapy for Colon Cancer. Clin Colorectal Cancer 21 (3): e189-e195, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="36821823">Baker SD, Bates SE, Brooks GA, et al.: DPYD Testing: Time to Put Patient Safety First. J Clin Oncol 41 (15): 2701-2705, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037910">stage 0 vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Vulvar Intraepithelial Neoplasia</Title><SummarySection id="_522"><Title>Treatment Options for Vulvar Intraepithelial Neoplasia (VIN)</Title><Para id="_449">Treatment options for VIN include:</Para><OrderedList id="_527" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_221" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_528" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Separate excision of focal lesions.<Reference refidx="1"/> </ListItem><ListItem> Wide local excision.<Reference refidx="1"/>
</ListItem><ListItem>Carbon dioxide	(CO<Subscript>2</Subscript>) laser surgery and vaporization.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>   A disadvantage of vaporization is that it does not provide tissue for histological examination to confirm complete removal of the lesion and the absence of invasive disease.</ListItem><ListItem>	Ultrasonic surgical aspiration.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem> Superficial skinning vulvectomy with or without grafting.<Reference refidx="1"/>
</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_451" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Topical imiquimod</SummaryRef> for patients who want to avoid surgery.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_216">Traditionally, there were three grades of VIN, however, there is little evidence that all three grades are part of the same biological continuum or that grade 1 is even a cancer precursor.  In 2004, the International Society for the Study of Vulvovaginal Disease (ISSVD) changed its terminology, reserving the designation VIN for two categories of lesions based on morphological appearance.<Reference refidx="9"/> In 2015, the ISSVD developed terminology for vulvar squamous intraepithelial lesions (SIL), which includes:<Reference refidx="10"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_551" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Low-grade SIL  of the vulva (vulvar LSIL) encompasses flat condyloma or human papillomavirus effect.</ListItem><ListItem>High-grade SIL (vulvar HSIL) was termed VIN, usual type in the 2004 ISSVD terminology.</ListItem><ListItem>VIN, differentiated type.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_219">High-grade VIN is usually managed with active therapy because of a higher risk for progression to invasive disease.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Estimates of progression rates are imprecise.  A systematic literature review that included 88 untreated patients with VIN 3 reported a 9% progression rate (8 of 88 patients) to invasive vulvar cancer during 12 to 96 months of observation.  In the same review, the spontaneous regression rate was 1.2%, all of which occurred in women younger than 35 years.<Reference refidx="1"/>  However, in a single-center study, 10 of 63 (16%) untreated women with VIN 2 or VIN 3 progressed to invasive cancer after a mean of 3.9 years.<Reference refidx="11"/>  </Para><Para id="_220">VIN lesions may be multifocal or confluent and extensive.  It is important to perform multiple biopsies in treatment planning to exclude occult invasive disease. VIN located in nonhairy areas can be considered an epithelial disease; however, VIN found in hairy sites usually involves the pilosebaceous apparatus and requires a greater depth of excision because it can track along hair roots. </Para><SummarySection id="_221"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_400">The principal treatment approach is surgery, but there is no consensus on the optimal surgical procedure.  The goal is to remove or destroy the entire VIN lesion while preserving vulvar anatomy and function. Simple vulvectomy yields a 5-year survival rate of nearly 100% but is
seldom indicated.  Other more limited surgical procedures, including separate excision of multiple lesions, are less deforming.<Reference refidx="12"/>  The choice of treatment depends on the extent of the disease and the experience of the treating physician.  There are no reliable data comparing the efficacy and safety of the various surgical approaches.</Para><Para id="_71">  A systematic literature review identified only a single randomized trial comparing any of the surgical approaches.<Reference refidx="2"/>  In that trial, 30 women with high-grade VIN were randomly assigned to either receive CO<Subscript>2</Subscript> laser ablation or ultrasound surgical aspiration.<Reference refidx="3"/>  There were no statistically significant differences in disease recurrence, painful  dysuria or burning, adhesions, or eschar formation between the two treatments after 1 year of follow-up.  Scarring was observed in 5 of 16 women treated with laser ablation and 0 of 14 women treated with ultrasound surgical aspiration (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01), but consequences of the scarring on sexual function or quality of life were not reported.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]   The trial was too small to draw reliable conclusions about the relative efficacy of these surgical techniques.  The remainder of the surgical literature is derived from case series and is prone to important study biases.[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]  </Para><Para id="_236">Whatever procedure is used, patients are at substantial risk of recurrence, particularly when the lesions are high grade or multifocal.<Reference refidx="13"/>  The most common sites of recurrence are the perianal skin, presacral area, and clitoral hood. About 4% of patients treated for VIN subsequently develop invasive cancer.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_222"><Title>Nonsurgical interventions</Title><SummarySection id="_451"><Title>Topical imiquimod</Title><Para id="_452">Among women with high-grade VIN, substantial response rates and acceptable tolerability were reported for topical imiquimod 5%, an immune-response modifier with activity in human papillomavirus types 6- and 11-associated vulvar condylomata.  </Para><Para id="_509">Evidence (imiquimod):</Para><OrderedList id="_510" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Three randomized placebo-controlled trials (including a total of 104 patients) with clinical response as the primary end points have been reported in either peer-reviewed-journals or in abstract format.<Reference refidx="7"/>;<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]  The results of these trials were summarized in a systematic review.<Reference refidx="8"/>  <ItemizedList id="_511" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>At 5 to 6 months, the complete response rates in patients were 36 of 62 in the combined imiquimod arm versus 0 of 42 in the combined placebo arm, and the partial response rates were 18 of 62 in the combined imiquimod arm versus 1 of 42 in the combined placebo arm (relative risk, 11.95; 95% confidence interval, 3.21–44.51).  </ListItem><ListItem>In the only trial reporting progression to cancer at 12 months, there was no difference in progression rate, but the trial was severely underpowered because only 3 of the total 52 women developed invasive disease by 12 months.<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem>The only trial reporting quality of life <Reference refidx="6"/> showed no difference between imiquimod and placebo.</ListItem><ListItem>Local side effects of imiquimod included pain, edema, erythema, and a single case of erosion.  However, no patients had to discontinue treatment as a result of toxicity.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_493"><Title>Other nonsurgical interventions</Title><Para id="_494">Nonsurgical approaches have been studied because of the physical and psychosexual morbidity associated with many vulvar surgical procedures.  Some of these approaches, including topical fluorouracil, recombinant interferon gamma, bleomycin, and trinitrochlorobenzene, have been largely abandoned because of   high recurrence rates or intolerable local side effects, such as pain, irritation, and ulceration.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="16"/>  </Para><Para id="_542">Photodynamic therapy, using topically applied 5-aminolevulinic acid as the sensitizing agent for 635 nm laser light, has also been studied.  However, data are limited to small case series with variable response rates.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_70_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_70_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15863172">van Seters M, van Beurden M, de Craen AJ: Is the assumed natural history of vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia III based on enough evidence? A systematic review of 3322 published patients. Gynecol Oncol 97 (2): 645-51, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21249698">Kaushik S, Pepas L, Nordin A, et al.: Surgical interventions for high grade vulval intraepithelial neoplasia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (1): CD007928, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="17400858">von Gruenigen VE, Gibbons HE, Gibbins K, et al.: Surgical treatments for vulvar and vaginal dysplasia: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol 109 (4): 942-7, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Sterling JC, Smith NA, Loo WJ, et al.: Randomized, doubleblind, placebo-controlled trial for treatment of high grade vulval intraepithelial neoplasia with imiquimod. [Abstract] J Eur Acad Derm Venereol  19 (Suppl 2): A-FC06.1, 22, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="17655918">Mathiesen O, Buus SK, Cramers M: Topical imiquimod can reverse vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia: a randomised, double-blinded study. Gynecol Oncol 107 (2): 219-22, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="18385498">van Seters M, van Beurden M, ten Kate FJ, et al.: Treatment of vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia with topical imiquimod. N Engl J Med 358 (14): 1465-73, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21239049">Terlou A, van Seters M, Ewing PC, et al.: Treatment of vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia with topical imiquimod: seven years median follow-up of a randomized clinical trial. Gynecol Oncol 121 (1): 157-62, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="21491403">Pepas L, Kaushik S, Bryant A, et al.: Medical interventions for high grade vulval intraepithelial neoplasia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (4): CD007924, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="16419625">Sideri M, Jones RW, Wilkinson EJ, et al.: Squamous vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia: 2004 modified terminology, ISSVD Vulvar Oncology Subcommittee. J Reprod Med 50 (11): 807-10, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="26704327">Bornstein J, Bogliatto F, Haefner HK, et al.: The 2015 International Society for the Study of Vulvovaginal Disease (ISSVD) Terminology of Vulvar Squamous Intraepithelial Lesions. J Low Genit Tract Dis 20 (1): 11-4, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="16319258">Jones RW, Rowan DM, Stewart AW: Vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia: aspects of the natural history and outcome in 405 women. Obstet Gynecol 106 (6): 1319-26, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="12">Eifel PJ, Klopp AH, Berek JS, et al.: Cancer of the cervix, vagina, and vulva. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 1171-1210.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="9109080">Küppers V, Stiller M, Somville T, et al.: Risk factors for recurrent VIN. Role of multifocality and grade of disease. J Reprod Med 42 (3): 140-4, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="7352086">Buscema J, Woodruff JD, Parmley TH, et al.: Carcinoma in situ of the vulva. Obstet Gynecol 55 (2): 225-30, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="7936504">Jones RW, Rowan DM: Vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia III: a clinical study of the outcome in 113 cases with relation to the later development of invasive vulvar carcinoma. Obstet Gynecol 84 (5): 741-5, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="2984615">Sillman FH, Sedlis A, Boyce JG: A review of lower genital intraepithelial neoplasia and the use of topical 5-fluorouracil. Obstet Gynecol Surv 40 (4): 190-220, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="10699944">Hillemanns P, Untch M, Dannecker C, et al.: Photodynamic therapy of vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia using 5-aminolevulinic acid. Int J Cancer 85 (5): 649-53, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="11136571">Fehr MK, Hornung R, Schwarz VA, et al.: Photodynamic therapy of vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia III using topically applied 5-aminolevulinic acid. Gynecol Oncol 80 (1): 62-6, 2001.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037915">stage I vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037926">stage II vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stages I and II Vulvar Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_523"><Title>Treatment Options for Stages I and II Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_79">Treatment options for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_556" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">stage I</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_557" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">stage II vulvar cancer</SummaryRef> include:
</Para><OrderedList id="_499" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_456" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_460" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery and radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_462" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy alone</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_456"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_457">Radical local excision with ipsilateral or bilateral inguinal and femoral lymph node dissection may be indicated. For stage I microinvasive lesions (&lt;1 mm invasion) with no associated severe
vulvar dystrophy, a  wide (1 cm margin) excision (without lymph node dissection) may be done.  For all
other stage I lesions, if well lateralized, without diffuse severe dystrophy,
and with clinically negative nodes, a radical local excision with complete
unilateral lymphadenectomy may be done.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Candidates for this
procedure should have lesions 2 cm or smaller in diameter with 5
mm or less invasion, no capillary-lymphatic space invasion, and
clinically uninvolved nodes.<Reference refidx="2"/>  <Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_512">For stage II disease, large T2* tumors may require modified radical vulvectomy or radical vulvectomy.<Reference refidx="4"/> <Note>*T2 is defined as tumor confined to the vulva and/or
perineum, more than 2 cm in greatest
dimension.</Note>  </Para><Para id="_459">For both stage I and stage II disease, radical local excision and sentinel node dissection is indicated and groin dissection is reserved for those with metastasis to the sentinel node(s).<Reference refidx="5"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_460"><Title>Surgery and radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_461">Some investigators recommend radical excision and groin nodal radiation therapy as a means to avoid the morbidity of lymph node dissection.  However, it is not clear whether radiation therapy can achieve the same local control rates or survival rates as lymph node dissection in early-stage disease.  A randomized trial to address this issue in patients with clinically localized vulvar disease was stopped early as a result of  early emergence of worse outcomes in the radiation therapy arm.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> For stage II disease, adjuvant local radiation therapy may be indicated for surgical margins smaller than 8 mm, capillary-lymphatic space invasion, and thickness greater than 5 mm.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_462"><Title>Radiation therapy alone</Title><Para id="_463">For patients unable to tolerate radical surgery or deemed
ineligible for surgery because of the site or extent of disease, radical radiation
therapy may be associated with favorable survival.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_76_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_76_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="4079427" MedlineID="86090554">Malfetano JH, Piver MS, Tsukada Y, et al.: Univariate and multivariate analyses of 5-year survival, recurrence, and inguinal node metastases in stage I and II vulvar carcinoma. J Surg Oncol 30 (2): 124-31, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1553164" MedlineID="92204547">Stehman FB, Bundy BN, Dvoretsky PM, et al.: Early stage I carcinoma of the vulva treated with ipsilateral superficial inguinal lymphadenectomy and modified radical hemivulvectomy: a prospective study of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. Obstet Gynecol 79 (4): 490-7, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8431905" MedlineID="93161306">Hacker NF, Van der Velden J: Conservative management of early vulvar cancer. Cancer 71 (4 Suppl): 1673-7, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Eifel PJ, Klopp AH, Berek JS, et al.: Cancer of the cervix, vagina, and vulva. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 1171-1210.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18281661">Van der Zee AG, Oonk MH, De Hullu JA, et al.: Sentinel node dissection is safe in the treatment of early-stage vulvar cancer. J Clin Oncol 26 (6): 884-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="1526880" MedlineID="92406591">Stehman FB, Bundy BN, Thomas G, et al.: Groin dissection versus groin radiation in carcinoma of the vulva: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 24 (2): 389-96, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21563133">van der Velden J, Fons G, Lawrie TA: Primary groin irradiation versus primary groin surgery for early vulvar cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (5): CD002224, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="1916517" MedlineID="92009508">Thomas GM, Dembo AJ, Bryson SC, et al.: Changing concepts in the management of vulvar cancer. Gynecol Oncol 42 (1): 9-21, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9226327" MedlineID="97369886">Faul CM, Mirmow D, Huang Q, et al.: Adjuvant radiation for vulvar carcinoma: improved local control. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 38 (2): 381-9, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="8244830" MedlineID="94064447">Petereit DG, Mehta MP, Buchler DA, et al.: Inguinofemoral radiation of N0,N1 vulvar cancer may be equivalent to lymphadenectomy if proper radiation technique is used. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 27 (4): 963-7, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2924095" MedlineID="89167510">Slevin NJ, Pointon RC: Radical radiotherapy for carcinoma of the vulva. Br J Radiol 62 (734): 145-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="8490921" MedlineID="93258756">Perez CA, Grigsby PW, Galakatos A, et al.: Radiation therapy in management of carcinoma of the vulva with emphasis on conservation therapy. Cancer 71 (11): 3707-16, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="3212218" MedlineID="89099741">Kumar PP, Good RR, Scott JC: Techniques for management of vulvar cancer by irradiation alone. Radiat Med 6 (4): 185-91, 1988 Jul-Aug.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037930">stage III vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III Vulvar Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_524"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage III Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_91">Treatment options for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_558" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">stage III vulvar cancer</SummaryRef> include:
</Para><OrderedList id="_501" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_473" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery with or without radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_476" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy or chemoradiation therapy followed by surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_478" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_473"><Title>Surgery with or without radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_474">Modified radical or radical vulvectomy with inguinal and femoral lymphadenectomy is the standard
therapy.<Reference refidx="1"/>   
Nodal involvement is a key determinant of survival.  
Radiation therapy is given to patients with large primary lesions and
narrow margins.
Radiation therapy to the pelvis and groin is given  if inguinal lymph nodes are
positive.<Reference refidx="2"/> Radiation therapy to the pelvis and groin is usually given if two or more
groin nodes are involved.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_475">Localized adjuvant radiation therapy consisting of 45 Gy to 50 Gy
may also be indicated when there is capillary-lymphatic space invasion and a
thickness of greater than 5 mm, particularly if the nodes are
involved.<Reference refidx="1"/>  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_476"><Title>Radiation therapy or chemoradiation therapy followed by surgery</Title><Para id="_477">Preoperative neoadjuvant radiation therapy or chemoradiation therapy may be used  to improve
operability and even decrease the extent of surgery required.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_478"><Title>Radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_479">For patients unable to tolerate radical surgery or deemed ineligible for surgery because of the site or extent of disease, radical radiation therapy may be associated with long-term survival.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Some physicians prefer to add concurrent fluorouracil (5-FU) or 5-FU and cisplatin.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_88_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_88_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1916517" MedlineID="92009508">Thomas GM, Dembo AJ, Bryson SC, et al.: Changing concepts in the management of vulvar cancer. Gynecol Oncol 42 (1): 9-21, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="19701032">Kunos C, Simpkins F, Gibbons H, et al.: Radiation therapy compared with pelvic node resection for node-positive vulvar cancer: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol 114 (3): 537-46, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8314530" MedlineID="93300422">Homesley HD, Bundy BN, Sedlis A, et al.: Prognostic factors for groin node metastasis in squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva (a Gynecologic Oncology Group study) Gynecol Oncol 49 (3): 279-83, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="3565317" MedlineID="87181554">Boronow RC, Hickman BT, Reagan MT, et al.: Combined therapy as an alternative to exenteration for locally advanced vulvovaginal cancer. II. Results, complications, and dosimetric and surgical considerations. Am J Clin Oncol 10 (2): 171-81, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7635775" MedlineID="95362598">Anderson JM, Cassady JR, Shimm DS, et al.: Vulvar carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 32 (5): 1351-7, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16856018">van Doorn HC, Ansink A, Verhaar-Langereis M, et al.: Neoadjuvant chemoradiation for advanced primary vulvar cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 3: CD003752, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="7557615">Eifel PJ, Morris M, Burke TW, et al.: Prolonged continuous infusion cisplatin and 5-fluorouracil with radiation for locally advanced carcinoma of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 59 (1): 51-6, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8641609">Landoni F, Maneo A, Zanetta G, et al.: Concurrent preoperative chemotherapy with 5-fluorouracil and mitomycin C and radiotherapy (FUMIR) followed by limited surgery in locally advanced and recurrent vulvar carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 61 (3): 321-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11072157">Montana GS, Thomas GM, Moore DH, et al.: Preoperative chemo-radiation for carcinoma of the vulva with N2/N3 nodes: a gynecologic oncology group study. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 48 (4): 1007-13, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="9747823">Moore DH, Thomas GM, Montana GS, et al.: Preoperative chemoradiation for advanced vulvar cancer: a phase II study of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 42 (1): 79-85, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8490921" MedlineID="93258756">Perez CA, Grigsby PW, Galakatos A, et al.: Radiation therapy in management of carcinoma of the vulva with emphasis on conservation therapy. Cancer 71 (11): 3707-16, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="2924095" MedlineID="89167510">Slevin NJ, Pointon RC: Radical radiotherapy for carcinoma of the vulva. Br J Radiol 62 (734): 145-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Eifel PJ, Klopp AH, Berek JS, et al.: Cancer of the cervix, vagina, and vulva. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 1171-1210.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_96"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000739551">stage IVA vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IVA Vulvar Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_525"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage IVA Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_480">Treatment options for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_559" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">stage IVA vulvar cancer</SummaryRef> include:</Para><OrderedList id="_481" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_482" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_484" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Surgery and radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_486" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy or chemoradiation therapy followed by surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_488" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_482"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_483">Radical vulvectomy and pelvic exenteration may be indicated for patients with stage IVA vulvar cancer.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_484"><Title>Surgery and radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_485">Surgery followed by radiation therapy may be done for large resected
lesions with narrow margins.  Localized adjuvant radiation therapy consisting
of 45 Gy to 50 Gy may also be indicated when there is capillary-lymphatic space
invasion and thickness greater than 5 mm.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Radiation therapy to the pelvis and groin is given if two or
more groin lymph nodes are involved.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_486"><Title>Radiation therapy or chemoradiation therapy followed by surgery</Title><Para id="_487">Neoadjuvant radiation therapy or chemoradiation therapy of large primary lesions (to improve operability) may be done, followed by
radical surgery.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  <Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_488"><Title>Radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_489">For patients unable to tolerate radical vulvectomy or who are deemed
ineligible for surgery because of the site or extent of disease, radical radiation
therapy may be associated with long-term survival.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>  When radiation therapy is
used for primary definitive treatment of vulvar cancer, some physicians prefer to
add concurrent fluorouracil (5-FU) or 5-FU and cisplatin.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>  </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_96_sid_8"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_96_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1916517" MedlineID="92009508">Thomas GM, Dembo AJ, Bryson SC, et al.: Changing concepts in the management of vulvar cancer. Gynecol Oncol 42 (1): 9-21, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="3785783" MedlineID="87066001">Homesley HD, Bundy BN, Sedlis A, et al.: Radiation therapy versus pelvic node resection for carcinoma of the vulva with positive groin nodes. Obstet Gynecol 68 (6): 733-40, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19701032">Kunos C, Simpkins F, Gibbons H, et al.: Radiation therapy compared with pelvic node resection for node-positive vulvar cancer: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol 114 (3): 537-46, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="3565317" MedlineID="87181554">Boronow RC, Hickman BT, Reagan MT, et al.: Combined therapy as an alternative to exenteration for locally advanced vulvovaginal cancer. II. Results, complications, and dosimetric and surgical considerations. Am J Clin Oncol 10 (2): 171-81, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7635775" MedlineID="95362598">Anderson JM, Cassady JR, Shimm DS, et al.: Vulvar carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 32 (5): 1351-7, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16856018">van Doorn HC, Ansink A, Verhaar-Langereis M, et al.: Neoadjuvant chemoradiation for advanced primary vulvar cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 3: CD003752, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="7557615">Eifel PJ, Morris M, Burke TW, et al.: Prolonged continuous infusion cisplatin and 5-fluorouracil with radiation for locally advanced carcinoma of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 59 (1): 51-6, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8641609">Landoni F, Maneo A, Zanetta G, et al.: Concurrent preoperative chemotherapy with 5-fluorouracil and mitomycin C and radiotherapy (FUMIR) followed by limited surgery in locally advanced and recurrent vulvar carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 61 (3): 321-7, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11072157">Montana GS, Thomas GM, Moore DH, et al.: Preoperative chemo-radiation for carcinoma of the vulva with N2/N3 nodes: a gynecologic oncology group study. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 48 (4): 1007-13, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="9747823">Moore DH, Thomas GM, Montana GS, et al.: Preoperative chemoradiation for advanced vulvar cancer: a phase II study of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 42 (1): 79-85, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2924095" MedlineID="89167510">Slevin NJ, Pointon RC: Radical radiotherapy for carcinoma of the vulva. Br J Radiol 62 (734): 145-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="8490921" MedlineID="93258756">Perez CA, Grigsby PW, Galakatos A, et al.: Radiation therapy in management of carcinoma of the vulva with emphasis on conservation therapy. Cancer 71 (11): 3707-16, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="1427394" MedlineID="93051689">Russell AH, Mesic JB, Scudder SA, et al.: Synchronous radiation and cytotoxic chemotherapy for locally advanced or recurrent squamous cancer of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 47 (1): 14-20, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="1955180" MedlineID="92064266">Berek JS, Heaps JM, Fu YS, et al.: Concurrent cisplatin and 5-fluorouracil chemotherapy and radiation therapy for advanced-stage squamous carcinoma of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 42 (3): 197-201, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="8344850" MedlineID="93346253">Koh WJ, Wallace HJ, Greer BE, et al.: Combined radiotherapy and chemotherapy in the management of local-regionally advanced vulvar cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 26 (5): 809-16, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="2504651" MedlineID="89357614">Thomas G, Dembo A, DePetrillo A, et al.: Concurrent radiation and chemotherapy in vulvar carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 34 (3): 263-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="17">Eifel PJ, Klopp AH, Berek JS, et al.: Cancer of the cervix, vagina, and vulva. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 1171-1210.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_490"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037940">stage IVB vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IVB Vulvar Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_549"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage IVB Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_491">There is no standard treatment approach in the management of <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_559" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">stage IVB vulvar cancer</SummaryRef>.  </Para><Para id="_543">Local therapy must be individualized depending on the extent of local and metastatic disease.  </Para><Para id="_544">There is no standard chemotherapy for metastatic disease, and reports describing the use of this modality are anecdotal.<Reference refidx="1"/>  However, by largely extrapolating from regimens used for anal or cervical cancer, chemotherapy has been studied. Regimens have included various combinations of fluorouracil, cisplatin, mitomycin, or bleomycin.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  Given the advanced age and comorbidity of many patients with advanced or recurrent vulvar cancer, patient tolerance is a major consideration in the use of these agents.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_490_sid_9"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_490_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Eifel PJ, Klopp AH, Berek JS, et al.: Cancer of the cervix, vagina, and vulva. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 1171-1210.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16856018">van Doorn HC, Ansink A, Verhaar-Langereis M, et al.: Neoadjuvant chemoradiation for advanced primary vulvar cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 3: CD003752, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19923866">Cormio G, Loizzi V, Gissi F, et al.: Cisplatin and vinorelbine chemotherapy in recurrent vulvar carcinoma. Oncology 77 (5): 281-4, 2009.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_103"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000037950">recurrent vulvar cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Vulvar Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_548"><Title>Treatment Options for Recurrent Vulvar Cancer</Title><Para id="_513">Treatment options for recurrent vulvar cancer include:</Para><OrderedList id="_514" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Wide local excision with or without radiation therapy in patients with local
recurrence.
</ListItem><ListItem>Radical vulvectomy and pelvic exenteration in patients with local recurrence.
</ListItem><ListItem> Synchronous radiation therapy and cytotoxic chemotherapy with or without surgery.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_104">Treatment and outcome depend on the site and extent of
recurrence.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Radical excision of localized recurrence may be considered if technically feasible.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Palliative radiation therapy is used for some patients.  Radiation
therapy with or without chemotherapy may be associated with substantial disease-free periods  in some patients with a small
local recurrence.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  When local recurrence occurs more than 2 years after
primary treatment, a combination of radiation therapy and surgery may result in
a 5-year survival rate of greater than 50%.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_103_sid_10"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_103_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1427394" MedlineID="93051689">Russell AH, Mesic JB, Scudder SA, et al.: Synchronous radiation and cytotoxic chemotherapy for locally advanced or recurrent squamous cancer of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 47 (1): 14-20, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="8428690" MedlineID="93154623">Piura B, Masotina A, Murdoch J, et al.: Recurrent squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva: a study of 73 cases. Gynecol Oncol 48 (2): 189-95, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2342725" MedlineID="90259408">Hopkins MP, Reid GC, Morley GW: The surgical management of recurrent squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva. Obstet Gynecol 75 (6): 1001-5, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6415281" MedlineID="84035954">Miyazawa K, Nori D, Hilaris BS, et al.: Role of radiation therapy in the treatment of advanced vulvar carcinoma. J Reprod Med 28 (8): 539-41, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2504651" MedlineID="89357614">Thomas G, Dembo A, DePetrillo A, et al.: Concurrent radiation and chemotherapy in vulvar carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 34 (3): 263-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="6823350" MedlineID="83116029">Podratz KC, Symmonds RE, Taylor WF, et al.: Carcinoma of the vulva: analysis of treatment and survival. Obstet Gynecol 61 (1): 63-74, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3721307" MedlineID="86248859">Shimm DS, Fuller AF, Orlow EL, et al.: Prognostic variables in the treatment of squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol 24 (3): 343-58, 1986.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/14/2025)</Title><Para id="_129">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_577">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062886#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of vulvar cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Vulvar Cancer Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Olga T.  Filippova, MD (Lenox Hill Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Marina Stasenko, MD (New York University Medical Center)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Vulvar Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/vulvar/hp/vulvar-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389203]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-05-14</DateLastModified></Summary>
