<Summary id="CDR0000062903" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Endometrial cancer is usually diagnosed at an early stage and can be treated with surgery. Learn about the symptoms, diagnosis, prognosis, staging, and treatment for early- and advanced-stage endometrial cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Endometrial Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/patient/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Endometrial Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038737">endometrial cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_648">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of endometrial cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_649">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>endometrial cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Endometrial Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Endometrial Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Endometrial Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038737">endometrial cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Endometrial Cancer</Title><Para id="_320">Cancer of the endometrium is the most common gynecologic malignancy in the United States and
accounts for 7% of all cancers in women.  Most cases are diagnosed at an early stage and are amenable to treatment with surgery alone.<Reference refidx="1"/>  However, patients with pathological features predictive of a high rate of relapse and patients with extrauterine spread at diagnosis have a high rate of relapse despite adjuvant therapy. The most common cause of death in patients with endometrial cancer is cardiovascular disease because of related metabolic risk factors.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><SummarySection id="_167"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_81">Estimated new cases and deaths from cancer of the uterine corpus, which includes the endometrium,  in the United States in 2025:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_82" Style="bullet"><ListItem>New cases: 69,120.</ListItem><ListItem>Deaths: 13,860.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_374"><Title>Anatomy</Title><Para id="_574">The endometrium is the inner lining of the uterus and has both functional and basal layers.  The functional layer is hormonally sensitive and is shed in a cyclical pattern during menstruation in reproductive-age women.  Both estrogen and progesterone are necessary to maintain a normal endometrial lining.  However, factors that lead to an excess of estrogen, including obesity and anovulation, lead to an increase in the deposition of the endometrial lining.   These changes may lead to endometrial hyperplasia and, in some cases, endometrial cancer.  Whatever the cause, a thickened lining will lead to sloughing of the endometrial tissue through the endometrial canal and into the vagina.  As a result, heavy menstrual bleeding or bleeding after menopause are often the initial signs of endometrial cancer.  This symptom tends to happen early in the disease course, allowing for identification of the disease at an early stage for most women.  </Para><Para id="_375"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000609921" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the female reproductive system; drawing shows the uterus, myometrium (muscular outer layer of the uterus), endometrium (inner lining of the uterus), ovaries, fallopian tubes, cervix, and vagina." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_286"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the female reproductive system.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_248"><Title>Risk Factors</Title><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000770686_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038737">endometrial cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_sm_CDR0000770686_2">Increasing age is the most important risk factor for most cancers. Other risk factors for endometrial cancer include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000770686_3" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Hormone therapy.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000770686_4" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Postmenopausal estrogen therapy.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Selective estrogen receptor modifiers.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000770686_7" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Tamoxifen therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Obesity.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem><ListItem>Metabolic syndrome.<Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem><ListItem>Diabetes.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem><ListItem>Reproductive factors.<ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000770686_5" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Nulliparity.<Reference refidx="23"/></ListItem><ListItem>Early menarche or late menopause.<Reference refidx="24"/></ListItem><ListItem>Polycystic ovary syndrome.<Reference refidx="25"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Family history/genetic predisposition.<ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000770686_6" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>	Mother, sister, or daughter with uterine cancer.<Reference refidx="26"/></ListItem><ListItem>Certain genetic syndromes, such as Lynch syndrome.<Reference refidx="27"/> <Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Endometrial hyperplasia.<Reference refidx="31"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_570">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062823" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-prevention-pdq">Endometrial Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_309">Prolonged,
unopposed estrogen exposure has been associated with an increased
risk of endometrial cancer.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="32"/>  However, combined estrogen and
progesterone therapy prevents this increased risk.<Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/></Para><Para id="_383">Tamoxifen, which is used to treat and prevent breast cancer (<ExternalRef xref="http://www.nsabp.pitt.edu/B-14.asp">NSABP-B-14</ExternalRef>), is associated with an increased
risk of endometrial cancer  related to the estrogenic effect
of tamoxifen on the endometrium.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="35"/>  It is important that patients who are receiving 
tamoxifen and experiencing abnormal uterine bleeding have follow-up examinations and biopsy of the endometrial lining. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration released a <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2005/17970s053lbl.pdf">black box warning</ExternalRef> that includes data about the increase in uterine malignancies associated with tamoxifen use. For more information about risk factors for Lynch syndrome–associated endometrial cancer, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062855#_3750" url="/types/breast/hp/breast-ovarian-genetics-pdq">Lynch Syndrome</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Breast and Gynecologic Cancers.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_253"><Title>Clinical Features</Title><Para id="_254">
          
          Irregular vaginal bleeding is the most common presenting sign of endometrial cancer.  It generally occurs early in the disease process and is the reason why most patients are diagnosed with highly curable stage I endometrial cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_250"><Title>Diagnostic Evaluation</Title><Para id="_427">The following procedures may be used to detect endometrial cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_428" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Transvaginal ultrasonography.</ListItem><ListItem>Endometrial biopsy.</ListItem><ListItem>Pelvic examination.</ListItem><ListItem>Dilatation and curettage.</ListItem><ListItem>Hysteroscopy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_466">To
definitively diagnose endometrial cancer, a procedure that directly samples the endometrial
tissue is necessary.</Para><Para id="_429">The Pap smear is not a reliable screening procedure for the detection of
endometrial cancer, even though a retrospective study found a strong correlation
between positive cervical cytology and high-risk endometrial disease (i.e., high-grade
tumor and deep myometrial invasion).<Reference refidx="36"/> A prospective study found a statistically significant association between malignant cytology and increased risk of nodal
disease.<Reference refidx="37"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_252"><Title>Prognostic Factors</Title><Para id="_467">Prognostic factors for endometrial cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_468" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_430" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Tumor stage and grade (including extrauterine nodal spread)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_471" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Hormone receptor status</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_430"><Title>Tumor stage and grade (including extrauterine nodal spread)</Title><Para id="_431"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_571" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef> highlights the risk of nodal metastasis based on findings at the time of staging surgery:<Reference refidx="38"/></Para><Table id="_571"><Title>Table 1.  Risk of Nodal Metastasis in Clinical Stage I Endometrial Cancer</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Prognostic Group</entry><entry>Patient Characteristics</entry><entry>Risk of Nodal Involvement</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">A</entry><entry>Grade 1 tumors involving only endometrium</entry><entry MoreRows="1">&lt;5% </entry></Row><Row><entry>No evidence of intraperitoneal spread</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">B</entry><entry>Grade 2–3 tumors</entry><entry MoreRows="1">5%–9%  pelvic nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry>Invasion of &lt;50% of myometrium</entry></Row><Row><entry>No intraperitoneal spread</entry><entry>4% para-aortic nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">C</entry><entry>Deep muscle invasion</entry><entry>20%–60% pelvic nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry>High-grade tumors</entry><entry MoreRows="1">10%–30% para-aortic nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry>Intraperitoneal spread</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_568">A Gynecologic Oncology Group study related
surgical-pathological parameters and postoperative treatment to recurrence-free
interval and recurrence site.  Grade 3 histology and deep myometrial invasion in patients without extrauterine spread were the greatest determinants of recurrence. In this study, the presence of the following factors greatly increased the frequency of recurrence:<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_569" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Positive pelvic nodes.</ListItem><ListItem>Adnexal metastasis.</ListItem><ListItem>Positive peritoneal cytology.</ListItem><ListItem>Capillary space involvement.</ListItem><ListItem>Involvement of the isthmus or cervix.</ListItem><ListItem>Positive para-aortic nodes (includes all grades and depth of invasion). Of the cases with aortic node metastases, 98% were in patients with positive pelvic nodes, intra-abdominal metastases, or tumor invasion of the outer 33% of the myometrium.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_575">When the only evidence of extrauterine spread is positive peritoneal cytology,
the influence on outcome is unclear.  The value of therapy directed at this
cytological finding is not well founded,<Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/><Reference refidx="43"/><Reference refidx="44"/><Reference refidx="45"/><Reference refidx="46"/> and some data are contradictory.<Reference refidx="47"/>  Although the collection of cytology specimens  is still suggested, a positive result does not upstage the cancer.  Other extrauterine disease must be present before
additional postoperative therapy is considered.</Para><Para id="_576">Involvement of the capillary-lymphatic space on histopathological
examination correlates with extrauterine and nodal spread of tumor.<Reference refidx="48"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_471"><Title>Hormone receptor status</Title><Para id="_472">When possible, progesterone and estrogen
receptor statuses, assessed either by biochemical or immunohistochemical methods,
are included in the evaluation of patients with stage I and stage II
cancer.<Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/></Para><Para id="_473">One report found progesterone receptor levels to be the single most important
prognostic indicator of 3-year survival in clinical stages I and II disease. 
Patients with progesterone receptor levels of 100 or greater had a 3-year
disease-free survival rate of 93%, compared with 36% for those with a level below 100.  After adjusting for progesterone receptor levels, only
cervical involvement and peritoneal cytology were significant prognostic
variables.<Reference refidx="52"/></Para><Para id="_474">Other reports
confirm the importance of hormone receptor status as an independent prognostic
factor.<Reference refidx="53"/>  Additionally, immunohistochemical staining of paraffin-embedded
tissue for both estrogen and progesterone receptors has been shown to correlate
with Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique (FIGO)  grade and survival.<Reference refidx="49"/><Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_475"><Title>Other prognostic factors</Title><Para id="_476">Other factors predictive of poor prognosis include:<Reference refidx="51"/><Reference refidx="54"/><Reference refidx="55"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_477" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>A high S-phase fraction.</ListItem><ListItem>Aneuploidy.</ListItem><ListItem><GeneName>PTEN</GeneName> loss-of-function variant.</ListItem><ListItem>	<GeneName>PIK3CA</GeneName> variant.</ListItem><ListItem>	<GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variant.</ListItem><ListItem>Oncogene expression (e.g., overexpression of the <GeneName>HER2/neu</GeneName> oncogene has been
associated with a poor overall prognosis).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_481">A general review of prognostic
factors has been published.<Reference refidx="56"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="22507532">Ward KK, Shah NR, Saenz CC, et al.: Cardiovascular disease is the leading cause of death among endometrial cancer patients. Gynecol Oncol 126 (2): 176-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="15866308">Beral V, Bull D, Reeves G, et al.: Endometrial cancer and hormone-replacement therapy in the Million Women Study. Lancet 365 (9470): 1543-51, 2005 Apr 30-May 6.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15082697">Anderson GL, Limacher M, Assaf AR, et al.: Effects of conjugated equine estrogen in postmenopausal women with hysterectomy: the Women's Health Initiative randomized controlled trial. JAMA 291 (14): 1701-12, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="19370558">Furness S, Roberts H, Marjoribanks J, et al.: Hormone therapy in postmenopausal women and risk of endometrial hyperplasia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (2): CD000402, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="7824251">Grady D, Gebretsadik T, Kerlikowske K, et al.: Hormone replacement therapy and endometrial cancer risk: a meta-analysis. Obstet Gynecol 85 (2): 304-13, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="1186789" MedlineID="76051178">Smith DC, Prentice R, Thompson DJ, et al.: Association of exogenous estrogen and endometrial carcinoma. N Engl J Med 293 (23): 1164-7, 1975.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="177870" MedlineID="76174341">Mack TM, Pike MC, Henderson BE, et al.: Estrogens and endometrial cancer in a retirement community. N Engl J Med 294 (23): 1262-7, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="171569" MedlineID="76051179">Ziel HK, Finkle WD: Increased risk of endometrial carcinoma among users of conjugated estrogens. N Engl J Med 293 (23): 1167-70, 1975.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="463863" MedlineID="79228972">Walker AM, Jick H: Cancer of the corpus uteri: increasing incidence in the United States, 1970--1975. Am J Epidemiol 110 (1): 47-51, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="193072" MedlineID="77171944">Gray LA, Christopherson WM, Hoover RN: Estrogens and endometrial carcinoma. Obstet Gynecol 49 (4): 385-9, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="190887" MedlineID="77131902">McDonald TW, Annegers JF, O'Fallon WM, et al.: Exogenous estrogen and endometrial carcinoma: case-control and incidence study. Am J Obstet Gynecol 127 (6): 572-80, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="213722" MedlineID="79053188">Antunes CM, Strolley PD, Rosenshein NB, et al.: Endometrial cancer and estrogen use. Report of a large case-control study. N Engl J Med 300 (1): 9-13, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="2995807" MedlineID="86014238">Shapiro S, Kelly JP, Rosenberg L, et al.: Risk of localized and widespread endometrial cancer in relation to recent and discontinued use of conjugated estrogens. N Engl J Med 313 (16): 969-72, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="8133536" MedlineID="94180408">Fisher B, Costantino JP, Redmond CK, et al.: Endometrial cancer in tamoxifen-treated breast cancer patients: findings from the National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project (NSABP) B-14. J Natl Cancer Inst 86 (7): 527-37, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="10376571" MedlineID="99303064">Cummings SR, Eckert S, Krueger KA, et al.: The effect of raloxifene on risk of breast cancer in postmenopausal women: results from the MORE randomized trial. Multiple Outcomes of Raloxifene Evaluation. JAMA 281 (23): 2189-97, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="18757329">DeMichele A, Troxel AB, Berlin JA, et al.: Impact of raloxifene or tamoxifen use on endometrial cancer risk: a population-based case-control study. J Clin Oncol 26 (25): 4151-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="11169969" MedlineID="21101244">Bergström A, Pisani P, Tenet V, et al.: Overweight as an avoidable cause of cancer in Europe. Int J Cancer 91 (3): 421-30, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="25791635">Aune D, Navarro Rosenblatt DA, Chan DS, et al.: Anthropometric factors and endometrial cancer risk: a systematic review and dose-response meta-analysis of prospective studies. Ann Oncol 26 (8): 1635-48, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="23640372">Esposito K, Chiodini P, Capuano A, et al.: Metabolic syndrome and endometrial cancer: a meta-analysis. Endocrine 45 (1): 28-36, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="9290508" MedlineID="97435841">Troisi R, Potischman N, Hoover RN, et al.: Insulin and endometrial cancer. Am J Epidemiol 146 (6): 476-82, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="25555821">Tsilidis KK, Kasimis JC, Lopez DS, et al.: Type 2 diabetes and cancer: umbrella review of meta-analyses of observational studies. BMJ 350: g7607, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="19924816">Dossus L, Allen N, Kaaks R, et al.: Reproductive risk factors and endometrial cancer: the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition. Int J Cancer 127 (2): 442-51, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="25555473">Brown SB, Hankinson SE: Endogenous estrogens and the risk of breast, endometrial, and ovarian cancers. Steroids 99 (Pt A): 8-10, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="24688118">Barry JA, Azizia MM, Hardiman PJ: Risk of endometrial, ovarian and breast cancer in women with polycystic ovary syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Hum Reprod Update 20 (5): 748-58, 2014 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="25560109">Win AK, Reece JC, Ryan S: Family history and risk of endometrial cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Obstet Gynecol 125 (1): 89-98, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="22846735">Daniels MS: Genetic testing by cancer site: uterus. Cancer J 18 (4): 338-42, 2012 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="11104559">Dunlop MG, Farrington SM, Nicholl I, et al.: Population carrier frequency of hMSH2 and hMLH1 mutations. Br J Cancer 83 (12): 1643-5, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="8030707">Lynch HT, Lynch J, Conway T, et al.: Familial aggregation of carcinoma of the endometrium. Am J Obstet Gynecol 171 (1): 24-7, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="17925543">Lu KH, Schorge JO, Rodabaugh KJ, et al.: Prospective determination of prevalence of lynch syndrome in young women with endometrial cancer. J Clin Oncol 25 (33): 5158-64, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="11578482">Widra EA, Dunton CJ, McHugh M, et al.: Endometrial hyperplasia and the risk of carcinoma. Int J Gynecol Cancer 5 (3): 233-235, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="8380547" MedlineID="93129672">Jick SS, Walker AM, Jick H: Estrogens, progesterone, and endometrial cancer. Epidemiology 4 (1): 20-4, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="8347751" MedlineID="93350068">Jick SS: Combined estrogen and progesterone use and endometrial cancer. Epidemiology 4 (4): 384, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="34">Bilezikian JP: Major issues regarding estrogen replacement therapy in postmenopausal women. J Womens Health  3 (4): 273-82, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="7905955" MedlineID="94142428">van Leeuwen FE, Benraadt J, Coebergh JW, et al.: Risk of endometrial cancer after tamoxifen treatment of breast cancer. Lancet 343 (8895): 448-52, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="1992417" MedlineID="91125744">DuBeshter B, Warshal DP, Angel C, et al.: Endometrial carcinoma: the relevance of cervical cytology. Obstet Gynecol 77 (3): 458-62, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="8058238" MedlineID="94336122">Larson DM, Johnson KK, Reyes CN, et al.: Prognostic significance of malignant cervical cytology in patients with endometrial cancer. Obstet Gynecol 84 (3): 399-403, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="8692516" MedlineID="96305283">Takeshima N, Hirai Y, Tanaka N, et al.: Pelvic lymph node metastasis in endometrial cancer with no myometrial invasion. Obstet Gynecol 88 (2): 280-2, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="1989916" MedlineID="91115216">Morrow CP, Bundy BN, Kurman RJ, et al.: Relationship between surgical-pathological risk factors and outcome in clinical stage I and II carcinoma of the endometrium: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Gynecol Oncol 40 (1): 55-65, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="8255995" MedlineID="94077989">Lanciano RM, Corn BW, Schultz DJ, et al.: The justification for a surgical staging system in endometrial carcinoma. Radiother Oncol 28 (3): 189-96, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="1371712" MedlineID="92174071">Ambros RA, Kurman RJ: Combined assessment of vascular and myometrial invasion as a model to predict prognosis in stage I endometrioid adenocarcinoma of the uterine corpus. Cancer 69 (6): 1424-31, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="2812655" MedlineID="90045272">Turner DA, Gershenson DM, Atkinson N, et al.: The prognostic significance of peritoneal cytology for stage I endometrial cancer. Obstet Gynecol 74 (5): 775-80, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="1473752" MedlineID="93114661">Piver MS, Recio FO, Baker TR, et al.: A prospective trial of progesterone therapy for malignant peritoneal cytology in patients with endometrial carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 47 (3): 373-6, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="1500014" MedlineID="92363279">Kadar N, Homesley HD, Malfetano JH: Positive peritoneal cytology is an adverse factor in endometrial carcinoma only if there is other evidence of extrauterine disease. Gynecol Oncol 46 (2): 145-9, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="1500013" MedlineID="92363278">Lurain JR: The significance of positive peritoneal cytology in endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 46 (2): 143-4, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="2047070" MedlineID="91261340">Lurain JR, Rice BL, Rademaker AW, et al.: Prognostic factors associated with recurrence in clinical stage I adenocarcinoma of the endometrium. Obstet Gynecol 78 (1): 63-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="23032094">Garg G, Gao F, Wright JD, et al.: Positive peritoneal cytology is an independent risk-factor in early stage endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 128 (1): 77-82, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="3978563" MedlineID="85151608">Hanson MB, van Nagell JR, Powell DE, et al.: The prognostic significance of lymph-vascular space invasion in stage I endometrial cancer. Cancer 55 (8): 1753-7, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="1697729" MedlineID="90372301">Carcangiu ML, Chambers JT, Voynick IM, et al.: Immunohistochemical evaluation of estrogen and progesterone receptor content in 183 patients with endometrial carcinoma. Part I: Clinical and histologic correlations. Am J Clin Pathol 94 (3): 247-54, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="1697730" MedlineID="90372302">Chambers JT, Carcangiu ML, Voynick IM, et al.: Immunohistochemical evaluation of estrogen and progesterone receptor content in 183 patients with endometrial carcinoma. Part II: Correlation between biochemical and immunohistochemical methods and survival. Am J Clin Pathol 94 (3): 255-60, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="1999848" MedlineID="91155130">Gurpide E: Endometrial cancer: biochemical and clinical correlates. J Natl Cancer Inst 83 (6): 405-16, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="2745195" MedlineID="89308142">Ingram SS, Rosenman J, Heath R, et al.: The predictive value of progesterone receptor levels in endometrial cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 17 (1): 21-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="53" PMID="8431882" MedlineID="93161278">Creasman WT: Prognostic significance of hormone receptors in endometrial cancer. Cancer 71 (4 Suppl): 1467-70, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="54" PMID="8175025" MedlineID="94229619">Friberg LG, Norén H, Delle U: Prognostic value of DNA ploidy and S-phase fraction in endometrial cancer stage I and II: a prospective 5-year survival study. Gynecol Oncol 53 (1): 64-9, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="1361478" MedlineID="93106494">Hetzel DJ, Wilson TO, Keeney GL, et al.: HER-2/neu expression: a major prognostic factor in endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 47 (2): 179-85, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="56" PMID="24956294">Binder PS, Mutch DG: Update on prognostic markers for endometrial cancer. Womens Health (Lond Engl) 10 (3): 277-88, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038737">endometrial cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular Classification of Endometrial Cancer</Title><Para id="_258">Endometrial cancers are classified as one of the following two types:</Para><ItemizedList id="_259" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Type 1 may arise from complex atypical hyperplasia and is pathogenetically linked to unopposed estrogenic stimulation.</ListItem><ListItem>	Type 2 develops from atrophic endometrium and is not linked to hormonally driven pathogenesis.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_504">The most common type of endometrial cancer is endometrioid adenocarcinoma.</Para><Para id="_458">Frequency of endometrial cancer cell types is as follows:</Para><OrderedList id="_11" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Endometrioid (75%) comprises malignant glandular epithelial elements; an admixture of
squamous metaplasia is not uncommon.
<OrderedList id="_69" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>Ciliated adenocarcinoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Secretory adenocarcinoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Papillary and villoglandular adenocarcinomas are histologically similar
to those noted in the ovary and the fallopian tube. The prognosis is worse
for these tumors.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem>Adenocarcinoma with squamous differentiation.<ItemizedList id="_318" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Adenoacanthoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Adenosquamous cells contain malignant
 glandular and squamous epithelial elements.<Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList>

</ListItem>
<ListItem>  Mixed, defined as two carcinomatous cell types, with the smaller component making up at least 10% of the total  (10%).</ListItem><ListItem>Uterine papillary serous (&lt;10%).</ListItem><ListItem>Clear cell (4%) is histologically similar
to those noted in the ovary and the fallopian tube. The prognosis for clear cell tumors is worse.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem>
<ListItem>Carcinosarcoma (3%), also known as malignant mixed mesodermal tumor, has both carcinomatous and sarcomatous elements.  This tumor was historically categorized as a subtype of uterine sarcomas; however, recent evidence points to its origin as an adenocarcinoma that has undergone differentiation into the sarcomatous elements.</ListItem><ListItem> Mucinous (1%).</ListItem>

<ListItem>   Squamous cell (&lt;1%).</ListItem>

<ListItem> Undifferentiated (&lt;1%).</ListItem>
</OrderedList><SummarySection id="_547"><Title>Molecular Subgroups</Title><Para id="_577"><GeneName>PTEN</GeneName> variants are more common in type 1 endometrial cancers;  <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> and <GeneName>HER2/neu</GeneName> overexpression are more common in type 2 endometrial cancers, although some overlap exists.  </Para><Para id="_548">The Cancer Genome Atlas's  full genetic display of hundreds of endometrial cancers identified four subtypes to further characterize endometrial cancers:<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_578" Style="bullet"><ListTitle/><ListItem>	<GeneName>POLE</GeneName> ultramutated. This subtype has clinical significance, and adjuvant therapies are avoided. </ListItem><ListItem>	Microsatellite instability hypermutated. </ListItem><ListItem>	Copy number low. </ListItem><ListItem>	Copy number high. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_579">These categories can be used to stratify patients into low- and high-risk prognostic categories.  A modification of The Cancer Genome Atlas methods into more accessible tests was also successful in discriminating cancers into relevant prognostic categories.  However, a combination of previously known risk factors with the genetic data was the most effective at determining prognostic categories.<Reference refidx="4"/>  </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="8431881" MedlineID="93161277">Gusberg SB: Virulence factors in endometrial cancer. Cancer 71 (4 Suppl): 1464-6, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1913465" MedlineID="92005187">Zaino RJ, Kurman R, Herbold D, et al.: The significance of squamous differentiation in endometrial carcinoma. Data from a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Cancer 68 (10): 2293-302, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23636398">Kandoth C, Schultz N, Cherniack AD, et al.: Integrated genomic characterization of endometrial carcinoma. Nature 497 (7447): 67-73, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="26172027">Talhouk A, McConechy MK, Leung S, et al.: A clinically applicable molecular-based classification for endometrial cancers. Br J Cancer 113 (2): 299-310, 2015.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038737">endometrial cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Endometrial Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_437"><Para id="_438">The pattern of endometrial cancer spread is partially dependent on the degree of cellular
differentiation.  Well-differentiated tumors tend to limit their spread to the
surface of the endometrium; myometrial invasion is less common. Myometrial invasion occurs much more
frequently in patients
with poorly differentiated tumors and is frequently a harbinger of lymph node
involvement and distant metastases.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_459"> Metastatic spread occurs in a characteristic pattern. 
 Regional spread to the pelvic and para-aortic nodes is common.  Distant metastasis most commonly involves the following sites:</Para><ItemizedList id="_442" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Lungs.</ListItem><ListItem>Inguinal and supraclavicular nodes.</ListItem><ListItem>Liver.</ListItem><ListItem>Bones.</ListItem><ListItem>Brain.</ListItem><ListItem>Vagina.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_141"><Title>FIGO Staging</Title><Para id="_142">The Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique (FIGO) and the American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) have both designated staging systems for endometrial cancer. The FIGO system is the most commonly used staging system for endometrial cancer.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> The 2023 FIGO staging update has not been widely adopted because it incorporates molecular-based results, and some physicians do not have access to those data for their patients. Additionally, given the significant changes in the 2023 FIGO staging system, especially in the definition of early stage disease, more outcome data are needed so it might be more prudent to use the 2021 system in a clinical setting while discussing prognosis and treatment with patients. Therefore, both the 2023 and the 2021 FIGO staging systems are presented in this section. </Para><Para id="_144">  FIGO stages I to IV are further subdivided by the histological grade (G) of the tumor, for example, stage IB G2. Carcinosarcomas, which had previously been designated as sarcomas, are now considered poorly differentiated adenocarcinomas; as such, they are included in this system.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><SummarySection id="_700"><Title>2023 FIGO staging for endometrial cancer</Title><Table id="_701"><Title>Table 2.  2023 FIGO Definitions for Stage I Cancer of the Endometrium<Superscript>a,b,c</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="5.43%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="43.23%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="51.33%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">Stage</entry><entry>Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis; p = pathological; AJCC = American Joint Committee on Cancer; ESGO-ESTRO-ESP = European Society of Gynaecological Oncology, European Society for Radiotherapy and Oncology, European Society of Pathology; FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique; ITC = isolated tumor cell; LVSI = lymphovascular space involvement; MMRd = mismatch repair deficiency; NSMP = no specific molecular profile; <GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName> = pathogenic <GeneName>POLE</GeneName> mutation; p53abn = <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> abnormal; SLN = sentinel lymph node; WHO = World Health Organization.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Endometrial cancer is surgically staged and pathologically examined. In all stages, the grade of the lesion, the histological type and LVSI must be recorded. If available and feasible, molecular classification testing (<GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName>, MMRd, NSMP, p53abn) is encouraged in all patients with endometrial cancer for prognostic risk-group stratification and as factors that might influence adjuvant and systemic treatment decisions (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_706" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Table 6</SummaryRef>).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>In early endometrial cancer, the standard surgery is a total hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy via a minimally invasive laparoscopic approach. Staging procedures include infracolic omentectomy in specific histological subtypes, such as serous and undifferentiated endometrial carcinoma, as well as carcinosarcoma, due to the high risk of microscopic omental metastases. Lymph node staging should be performed in patients with intermediate-high/high-risk disease. SLN biopsy is an adequate alternative to systematic lymphadenectomy for staging proposes. SLN biopsy can also be considered in patients with low−/low-intermediate-risk disease to rule out occult lymph node metastases and to identify disease truly confined to the uterus. Thus, the ESGO-ESTRO-ESP guidelines allow an approach of SLN in all patients with endometrial carcinoma, which is endorsed by FIGO. In assumed early endometrial cancer, an SLN biopsy in an adequate alternative to systematic lymphadenectomy in high-intermediate and high-risk cases for the purpose of lymph node staging and can also be considered in low–/intermediate-risk disease to rule out occult lymph node metastases. An SLN biopsy should be done in association with thorough (ultrastaging) staging as it will increase the detection of low-volume disease in lymph nodes.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>d</Superscript>Low-grade endometrioid carcinomas involving both the endometrium and the ovary are considered to have a good prognosis, and no adjuvant treatment is recommended if all the below criteria are met. Disease limited to low-grade endometrioid carcinomas involving the endometrium and ovaries (Stage IA3) must be distinguished from extensive spread of the endometrial carcinoma to the ovary (Stage IIIA1), by the following criteria: (1) no more than superficial myometrial invasion is present (&lt;50%); (2) absence of extensive/substantial LVSI; (3) absence of additional metastases; and (4) the ovarian tumor is unilateral, limited to the ovary, without capsule invasion/rupture (equivalent to pT1a).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>e</Superscript>LVSI as defined in WHO 2021: extensive/substantial, ≥5 vessels involved.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>f</Superscript>Grade and histological type are as follows: (1) Serous adenocarcinomas, clear cell adenocarcinomas, mesonephric-like carcinomas, gastrointestinal-type mucinous endometrial carcinoma, undifferentiated carcinomas, and carcinosarcomas are considered high grade by definition. For endometrioid carcinomas, grade is based on the proportion of solid areas: low grade = grade 1 (≤5%) and grade 2 (6%–50%); and high grade = grade 3 (&gt;50%). Nuclear atypia excessive for the grade raises the grade of a grade 1 or 2 tumor by one. The presence of unusual nuclear atypia in an architecturally low-grade tumor should prompt the evaluation of <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> and consideration of serous carcinoma. Adenocarcinomas with squamous differentiation are graded according to the microscopic features of the glandular component; (2) Nonaggressive histological types are composed of low-grade (grade 1 and 2) endometrioid carcinomas. Aggressive histological types are composed of high-grade endometrioid carcinomas (grade 3), serous, clear cell, undifferentiated, mixed, mesonephric-like, gastrointestinal mucinous type carcinomas, and carcinosarcomas; and (3) It should be noted that high-grade endometrioid carcinomas (grade 3) are a prognostically, clinically, and molecularly heterogenous disease, and the tumor type that benefits most from applying molecular classification for improved prognostication and for treatment decision-making. Without molecular classification, high-grade endometrioid carcinomas cannot appropriately be allocated to a risk group, and thus, molecular profiling is particularly recommended in these patients. For practical purposes and to avoid undertreatment of patients, if the molecular classification is unknown, high-grade endometrioid carcinomas were grouped together with the aggressive histological types in the actual FIGO classification.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>g</Superscript>Micrometastases are considered to be metastatic involvement (pN1 [mi]). The prognostic significance of ITCs is unclear. The presence of ITCs should be documented and is regarded as pN0(I+). According to the AJCC 8th edition staging, macrometastases are &gt;2 mm in size, micrometastases are &gt;0.2–2 mm and/or &gt;200 cells, and ITCs are ≤0.2 mm and ≤200 cells. These definitions are based on staging established by FIGO and the 8th edition of the AJCC Cancer Staging Manual.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">I</entry><entry>Confined to the uterine corpus and ovary.<Superscript>d</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IA</entry><entry>Disease limited to the endometrium OR nonaggressive histological type, i.e., low-grade endometrioid, with invasion of less than half of myometrium with no or focal LVSI OR good prognosis disease.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IA1</entry><entry>Nonaggressive histological type limited to an endometrial polyp OR confined to the endometrium.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IA2</entry><entry>Nonaggressive histological types involving less than half of the myometrium with no or focal LVSI.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IA3</entry><entry>Low-grade endometrioid carcinomas limited to the uterus and ovary.<Superscript>d</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IB</entry><entry>Nonaggressive histological types with invasion of half or more of the myometrium, and with no or focal LVSI.<Superscript>e</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IC</entry><entry>Aggressive histological types<Superscript>f</Superscript> limited to a polyp or confined to the endometrium.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_702"><Title>Table 3.  2023 FIGO Definitions for Stage II Cancer of the Endometrium<Superscript>a,b,c</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage</entry><entry>Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique; LVSI = lymphovascular space involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">For the explanations for footnotes <Superscript>b−f</Superscript>, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_701" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>II</entry><entry>Invasion of cervical stroma without extrauterine extension OR with substantial LVSI OR aggressive histological types with myometrial invasion.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IIA</entry><entry>	Invasion of the cervical stroma of nonaggressive histological types.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IIB</entry><entry>Substantial LVSI<Superscript>e</Superscript> of nonaggressive histological types.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IIC</entry><entry>Aggressive histological types<Superscript>f</Superscript> with any myometrial involvement.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_703"><Title>Table 4.  2023 FIGO Definitions for Stage III Cancer of the Endometrium<Superscript>a,b,c</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="5.85%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="45.05%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="49.09%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">Stage</entry><entry>Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">For the explanations for footnotes <Superscript>b−d</Superscript> and <Superscript>g</Superscript>, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_701" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">III</entry><entry>Local and/or regional spread of the tumor of any histological subtype.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIA</entry><entry>	Invasion of uterine serosa, adnexa, or both by direct extension or metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIA1</entry><entry>Spread to ovary or fallopian tube (except when meeting stage IA3 criteria).<Superscript>d</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIA2</entry><entry>Involvement of uterine subserosa or spread through the uterine serosa.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIB</entry><entry>Metastasis or direct spread to the vagina and/or to the parametria or pelvic peritoneum.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIB1</entry><entry>Metastasis or direct spread to the vagina and/or the parametria.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIB2</entry><entry>Metastasis to the pelvic peritoneum.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col1">IIIC</entry><entry>Metastasis to the pelvic or para-aortic lymph nodes or both.<Superscript>g</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIC1</entry><entry>Metastasis to the pelvic lymph nodes.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIC1i</entry><entry>Micrometastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIC1ii</entry><entry>Macrometastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIC2</entry><entry>Metastasis to para-aortic lymph nodes up to the renal vessels, with or without metastasis to the pelvic lymph nodes.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIC2i</entry><entry>Micrometastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry>IIIC2ii</entry><entry>Macrometastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_704"><Title>Table 5.  2023 FIGO Definitions for Stage IV Cancer of the Endometrium<Superscript>a,b,c</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage</entry><entry>Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">For the explanations for footnotes <Superscript>b−c</Superscript>, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_701" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>IV</entry><entry>Spread to the bladder mucosa and/or intestinal mucosa and/or distance metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IVA</entry><entry>	Invasion of the bladder mucosa and/or the intestinal/bowel mucosa.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IVB</entry><entry>Abdominal peritoneal metastasis beyond the pelvis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IVC</entry><entry>Distant metastasis, including metastasis to any extra- or intra-abdominal lymph nodes above the renal vessels, lungs, liver, brain, or bone.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_706"><Title>Table 6.  2023 FIGO Definitions for Endometrial Cancer Stage With Molecular Classification<Superscript>a,b</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage Designation</entry><entry>Molecular Findings in Patients With Early Endometrial Cancer (Stages I and II After Surgical Staging)</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique; LVSI = lymphovascular space involvement; MMRd = mismatch repair deficiency; MSI = microsatellite instability; NSMP = no specific molecular profile; <GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName> = pathogenic <GeneName>POLE</GeneName> mutation; p53abn = <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> abnormal.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>When feasible, the addition of molecular subtype to the staging criteria allows a better prediction of prognosis in a staging/prognosis scheme. The performance of complete molecular classification (<GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName>, MMRd, NSMP, p53abn) is encouraged in all cases of endometrial cancer for prognostic risk-group stratification and as potential influencing factors of adjuvant or systemic treatment decisions. Molecular subtype assignment can be done on a biopsy, in which case it need not be repeated on the hysterectomy specimen. When performed, these molecular classifications should be recorded in all stages.
A pathogenic <GeneName>POLE</GeneName> mutation (<GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName>) is associated with a good prognosis. MMRd or MSI and NSMP are associated with an intermediate prognosis. Abnormal <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> (p53abn) is associated with a poor prognosis.
When the molecular classification is known the staging is modified as follows:
(1) FIGO Stages I and II are based on surgical/anatomical and histological findings. In case the molecular classification reveals <GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName> or p53abn status, the FIGO stage is modified in the early stage of the disease. This is depicted in the FIGO stage by the addition of “m” for molecular classification, and a subscript is added to denote <GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName> or p53abn status, as shown in the table. MMRd or NSMP status do not modify early FIGO stages; however, these molecular classifications should be recorded for the purpose of data collection. When molecular classification reveals MMRd or NSMP, it should be recorded as Stage Im<Subscript>MMRd</Subscript> or Stage Im<Subscript>NSMP</Subscript> and Stage IIm<Subscript>MMRd</Subscript> or Stage IIm<Subscript>NSMP</Subscript>; (2)
FIGO Stages III and IV are based on surgical/anatomical findings. The stage category is not modified by molecular classification; however, the molecular classification should be recorded if known. When the molecular classification is known, it should be recorded as Stage IIIm or Stage IVm with the appropriate subscript for the purpose of data collection. For example, when molecular classification reveals p53abn, it should be recorded as Stage IIIm<Subscript>p53abn</Subscript> or Stage IVm<Subscript>p53abn</Subscript>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>IAm<Subscript><GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName></Subscript></entry><entry><GeneName>POLEmut</GeneName> endometrial carcinoma, confined to the uterine corpus or with cervical extension, regardless of the degree of LVSI or histological type.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IICm<Subscript>p53abn</Subscript></entry><entry>p53abn endometrial carcinoma confined to the uterine corpus with any myometrial invasion, with or without cervical invasion, and regardless of the degree of LVSI or histological type.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_705"><Title>2021 FIGO staging for endometrial cancer</Title><Table id="_319"><Title>Table 7.  2021 FIGO Definitions for Stage I Cancer of the Endometrium<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage  </entry><entry>Description </entry><entry>Illustration </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="4"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>G1, G2, or G3 (G = grade).</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>I<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Tumor confined to the corpus uteri. </entry><entry MoreRows="2"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000735233" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IA and stage IB endometrial cancer shown in two cross-section drawings of the uterus and cervix. Drawing on the left shows stage IA, with cancer in the endometrium and myometrium of the uterus. Drawing on the right shows stage IB, with cancer more than halfway through the myometrium. Also shown are the fallopian tubes, ovaries, and vagina" language="en" placement="image-center" id="_288"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>IA<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>No or less than half myometrial invasion. </entry></Row><Row><entry>IB<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Invasion equal to or more than half of the myometrium. </entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_289"><Title>Table 8.  2021 FIGO Definitions for Stage II Cancer of the Endometrium<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage  </entry><entry>Description </entry><entry>Illustration </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="4"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>G1, G2, or G3 (G = grade).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Endocervical glandular involvement is considered stage I; it is no longer considered stage II.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>II<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Tumor invades cervical stroma but does not extend beyond the uterus.<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000735235" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage II endometrial cancer shown in a cross-section drawing of the uterus, cervix, fallopian tubes, ovaries, and vagina. Cancer is shown in the endometrium and myometrium of the uterus and in the cervix." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_290"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_291"><Title>Table 9.  2021 FIGO Definitions for Stage III Cancer of the Endometrium<Superscript>a</Superscript> </Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage  </entry><entry>Description </entry><entry>Illustration </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="4"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>G1, G2, or G3 (G = grade).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Positive cytology has to be reported separately without changing the stage.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>III<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Local and/or regional spread of the tumor. </entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>IIIA<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Tumor invades the serosa of the corpus uteri and/or adnexae.<Superscript>c</Superscript> </entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000735614" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IIIA endometrial cancer shown in a cross-section drawing of the uterus, ligaments of the uterus, cervix, fallopian tubes, ovaries, and vagina. Cancer is shown in the endometrium of the uterus, the outer layer of the uterus, a fallopian tube, an ovary, and a ligament of the uterus." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_292"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>IIIB<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Vaginal and/or parametrial involvement.<Superscript>c</Superscript> </entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000735615" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IIIB endometrial cancer shown in a cross-section drawing of the uterus, cervix, fallopian tubes, ovaries, and vagina. Cancer is shown in the endometrium of the uterus, the parametrium, the cervix, and the vagina." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_293"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>IIIC<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Metastases to pelvic and/or para-aortic lymph nodes.<Superscript>c</Superscript> </entry><entry MoreRows="2"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000735673" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IIIC endometrial cancer; drawing shows cancer in the endometrium and myometrium of the uterus. Also shown is cancer in lymph nodes in the pelvis and near the aorta." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_294"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>IIIC1<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Positive pelvic nodes. </entry></Row><Row><entry>IIIC2<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Positive para-aortic lymph nodes with or without positive pelvic lymph nodes. </entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_295"><Title> Table 10.  2021 FIGO Definitions for Stage IV Cancer of the Endometrium<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage  </entry><entry>Description</entry><entry>Illustration </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from FIGO Committee on Gynecologic Oncology.<Reference refidx="4"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>G1, G2, or G3 (G = grade).</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>IV<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Tumor invades bladder and/or bowel mucosa, and/or distant metastases. </entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>IVA<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Tumor invasion of bladder and/or bowel mucosa. </entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000735680" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IVA endometrial cancer shown in a side-view cross-section drawing of the uterus, bladder, cervix, vagina, small intestine, and large intestine. Cancer is shown in the bladder, uterus, and bowel." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_296"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>IVB<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Distant metastases, including intra-abdominal metastases and/or inguinal lymph nodes. </entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000738209" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IVB endometrial cancer; drawing shows cancer that has spread to parts of the body outside the pelvis, including the abdomen and lymph nodes in the groin. An inset shows cancer cells spreading from the endometrium, through the blood and lymph system, to another part of the body where metastatic cancer has formed." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_297"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="6284595" MedlineID="82237179">Hendrickson M, Ross J, Eifel PJ, et al.: Adenocarcinoma of the endometrium: analysis of 256 cases with carcinoma limited to the uterine corpus. Pathology review and analysis of prognostic variables. Gynecol Oncol 13 (3): 373-92, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="3104248" MedlineID="87165252">Nori D, Hilaris BS, Tome M, et al.: Combined surgery and radiation in endometrial carcinoma: an analysis of prognostic factors. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 13 (4): 489-97, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="37337978">Berek JS, Matias-Guiu X, Creutzberg C, et al.: FIGO staging of endometrial cancer: 2023. Int J Gynaecol Obstet 162 (2): 383-394, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="34669196">Koskas M, Amant F, Mirza MR, et al.: Cancer of the corpus uteri: 2021 update. Int J Gynaecol Obstet 155 (Suppl 1): 45-60, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Corpus uteri – carcinoma and carcinosarcoma. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 8th ed. Springer; 2017, pp 661-69.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038737">endometrial cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Endometrial Cancer</Title><Para id="_443">The degree of tumor differentiation has an important effect on the
natural history of this disease and on treatment selection.</Para><Para id="_37">Patients with endometrial cancer who have localized disease  are usually cured.  Best results are obtained with one of two standard treatments:</Para><ItemizedList id="_549" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy.</ListItem><ListItem>Hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy and adjuvant radiation therapy (when deep invasion of the myometrial muscle [more than 50% of the myometrium] or grade 3 tumor with myometrial invasion is present). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_550">Patients with regional and distant metastases are rarely cured,
although they are occasionally responsive to standard hormone therapy.  </Para><Para id="_38">Progestational agents have been evaluated as adjuvant therapy in several randomized trials. A meta-analysis by the Cochrane group confirms no clinical benefit to adjuvant progestogens in clinical stage I disease.<Reference refidx="1"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_397">The treatment options for each stage of endometrial cancer are presented in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_418" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Table 11</SummaryRef>.</Para><Table id="_418"><Title>Table 11.  Treatment Options for Endometrial Cancer</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_14" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Stage (FIGO Staging Definitions)</SummaryRef></entry><entry>Treatment Options </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="4">Stage I and stage II endometrial cancer</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Grades 1 and 2</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_398" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Surgery with or without lymph node sampling</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_403" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Postoperative vaginal brachytherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_489" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy alone</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Grade 3 (includes serous, clear cell, and carcinosarcoma)</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_484" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef> </entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_484" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Postoperative chemotherapy   with or without radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5">Stage III, stage IV, and recurrent endometrial cancer</entry><entry>Operable disease</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_511" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Surgery followed by chemotherapy or radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry>Inoperable disease</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_359" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy and radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Inoperable disease in which the patient is not a candidate for radiation therapy </entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_360" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Hormone therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_613" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Biological therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Advanced or recurrent disease</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_709" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Immunotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_720" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Clinical trials</SummaryRef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21678331">Martin-Hirsch PP, Bryant A, Keep SL, et al.: Adjuvant progestagens for endometrial cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (6): CD001040, 2011.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_40"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038739">stage I endometrial carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038740">stage II endometrial carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage I and Stage II Endometrial Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_394"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage I and Stage II Endometrial Cancer</Title><Para id="_483">Treatment of stage I and stage II endometrial cancer depends on the grade and histological type.</Para><Para id="_619">In the current Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique (FIGO) staging system, stage II describes tumor that invades the cervical stroma; this is equivalent to the prior stage IIB.  Almost all randomized trials for early-stage cancer excluded stage IIB patients.  As a result, there is a paucity of quality data on which to base clinical decisions for patients with stage II endometrial cancer. </Para><Para id="_580"><Strong>Low-risk histology:</Strong></Para><Para id="_581">Grades 1 and 2 tumors are considered low-risk unless they have serous or clear cell histologies.  </Para><Para id="_582">Treatment options for patients with low-risk histological subtypes of stage I endometrial cancer include:</Para><OrderedList id="_583" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_641" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>: Hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy and possible lymph node dissection.</ListItem><ListItem>	<SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_403" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Postoperative vaginal brachytherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_489" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">	Radiation therapy alone</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_584">Most patients do well with surgery alone. However, patients with stage I disease who have high-risk histologies are at a greater risk of recurrence and are eligible for adjuvant therapy.</Para><Para id="_585"><Strong>High-risk histology:</Strong></Para><Para id="_586">Grade 3 tumors of any histology and any serous tumors, clear cell tumors, or carcinosarcomas are considered high-risk.  </Para><Para id="_484">Treatment options for patients with stage I or stage II endometrial cancer who have high-risk histologies include:</Para><OrderedList id="_485" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_398" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>: Hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, with pelvic and para-aortic lymph node dissection.</ListItem><ListItem> Postoperative chemotherapy with or without radiation therapy.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_447">Patients with serous or clear cell histologies have higher rates of recurrence than do patients with other stage I or stage II endometrioid carcinomas. Management guidelines are based on the outcomes reported in institutional case series that used a regimen of adjuvant carboplatin plus paclitaxel, and occasionally, radiation therapy for patients with this histological subtype.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_637">Carcinosarcomas have been evaluated in clinical trials both separately and with other sarcomas because of their prior designation in this group.  In a nonrandomized Gynecologic Oncology Group (GOG) study of patients with stage I or II carcinosarcomas, patients who underwent pelvic radiation therapy had a significant reduction in recurrences within the radiation treatment field but no improvement in survival.<Reference refidx="10"/> One nonrandomized study that predominantly included patients with carcinosarcomas appeared to show benefit for adjuvant therapy with cisplatin and doxorubicin.<Reference refidx="11"/>  </Para><SummarySection id="_641"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_642">If the uterine cervix is involved, patients may consider one or more of the following options:</Para><ItemizedList id="_643" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Standard hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, followed by adjuvant radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>	Radical hysterectomy.</ListItem><ListItem>	Pelvic and para-aortic lymph node dissection.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_644">Single-institution reviews suggest that radical hysterectomy is more beneficial than standard hysterectomy in cases of cervical involvement of the tumor.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_398"><Title>Surgery with or without lymph node sampling</Title><Para id="_587"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_647" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Table 12</SummaryRef> highlights the risk of nodal metastasis based on findings at the time of staging surgery:<Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Table id="_647"><Title>Table 12.  Risk of Nodal Metastasis in Clinical Stage I Endometrial Cancer</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Prognostic Group</entry><entry>Patient Characteristics</entry><entry>Risk of Nodal Involvement</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="1">A</entry><entry>Grade 1 tumors involving only endometrium</entry><entry MoreRows="1">&lt;5% </entry></Row><Row><entry>No evidence of intraperitoneal spread</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">B</entry><entry>Grade 2–3 tumors</entry><entry MoreRows="1">5%–9%  pelvic nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry>Invasion of &lt;50% of myometrium</entry></Row><Row><entry>No intraperitoneal spread</entry><entry>4% para-aortic nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">C</entry><entry>Deep muscle invasion</entry><entry>20%–60% pelvic nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry>High-grade tumors</entry><entry MoreRows="1">10%–30% para-aortic nodes </entry></Row><Row><entry>Intraperitoneal spread</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_589">For patients in Group A, lymph node dissection has limited utility.  Conversely, full pelvic and para-aortic lymph node dissection is important for patients in Group C, given the likelihood of positive findings. The difficulty lies in determining how to manage patients in Group B.  </Para><Para id="_590">There are several accepted surgical approaches for patients with presumed stage I endometrial cancer, with intermediate risk for lymphatic spread.</Para><Para id="_592">Both retrospective and prospective data support stratifying patients with presumed stage I endometrial cancer into two groups based on the following characteristics:</Para><ItemizedList id="_593" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Low risk: Well-differentiated or moderately differentiated tumor and/or depth of myometrial invasion is less than 50% and/or tumor is smaller than 2 cm.</ListItem><ListItem>High risk: Poorly differentiated tumor and/or depth of myometrial invasion is 50% or more and/or tumor  is 2 cm or larger.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_609">Evidence (lymph node dissection):</Para><OrderedList id="_594" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In two studies, patients with low-risk cancer had a sufficiently low risk of lymph node metastasis such that lymph node sampling could be omitted.  For patients meeting high-risk criteria, a full pelvic and para-aortic lymph node dissection was suggested, given patterns of lymphatic spread.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/> </ListItem><ListItem>An alternative strategy is the use of sentinel lymph node dissection in patients with presumed stage I endometrial cancer.<Reference refidx="18"/> Although this strategy has been widely adopted at various academic centers, a prospective multicenter trial to determine the false-negative rate for this protocol is lacking. For cases in which isolated tumor cells are identified using the sentinel lymph node approach, it is unclear whether treatment is necessary.</ListItem><ListItem>In patients with high-risk histology (serous, clear cell, carcinosarcoma, or undifferentiated tumors), hysterectomy and bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy with pelvic and para-aortic lymph node dissection is the standard approach. </ListItem><ListItem>Laparotomy has been the standard surgical approach. However, laparoscopy is now favored because of the improvement in patients' postoperative recovery without significant impact on outcomes.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_449">Evidence (treatment or surgical staging using laparoscopy vs. laparotomy):</Para><OrderedList id="_450" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>For patients with early-stage endometrial cancer, several randomized trials have compared total laparoscopic hysterectomy (TLH) with the standard open procedure, total abdominal hysterectomy (TAH).  Feasibility of the laparoscopic approach has been confirmed, but this approach is associated with a longer operative time.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> TLH has an improved <Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="19"/> or similar <Reference refidx="20"/> adverse event profile and a shorter hospital stay <Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> than does TAH.   <ItemizedList id="_487" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>TLH is associated with less pain and a quicker resumption of daily activities,<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/> although one study found that most of the gains in quality of life favoring laparoscopy at the 6-week postsurgical period were no longer significant at 6 months.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A GOG trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00002706">GOG-LAP2</ProtocolRef>) randomly assigned 2,616 patients with clinical stages I to IIA disease in a 2:1 ratio to comprehensive surgical staging via laparoscopy or laparotomy.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]<Para id="_488">Time to recurrence was the primary end point, with noninferiority defined as a difference in recurrence rate of less than 5.3% between the two groups at 3 years.</Para><OrderedList id="_372" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>The recurrence rate at 3 years was 10.24% for patients in the laparotomy arm and 11.39% for patients in the laparoscopy arm, with an estimated difference between groups of 1.14% (90% lower bound, -1.278; 95% upper bound, 3.996).  <ItemizedList id="_373" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Although this difference was lower than the prespecified limit, the statistical requirements for noninferiority were not met because of fewer-than-expected recurrences in both groups.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year overall survival (OS) rate was 89.8% in both groups.  </ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem><ListItem>A Cochrane review of the use of laparoscopic staging included four randomized controlled trials that reported OS and progression-free survival (PFS). Ninety percent of the patients were from the GOG-LAP2 trial.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_505" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Overall, laparoscopy and laparotomy were associated with similar OS and PFS rates.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_455">Future analyses may determine whether there are subgroups of patients for whom there is a clinically significant decrement when laparoscopic staging is used.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_403"><Title>Postoperative   vaginal brachytherapy</Title><Para id="_108">Adjuvant radiation therapy reduces the
incidence of local and regional recurrence. However, improved survival rates have not been confirmed, and radiation therapy increased toxicity.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/> Vaginal cuff brachytherapy is associated with less radiation-related morbidity than  is  external-beam radiation therapy (EBRT)  and has been shown to be equivalent to EBRT in the short term for patients with stage I disease.<Reference refidx="29"/> However, long-term follow up of a randomized trial comparing EBRT plus vaginal brachytherapy (VBT) to VBT alone found decreased OS and increased toxicity in the EBRT plus VBT arm.<Reference refidx="30"/>  </Para><Para id="_338">Evidence (VBT):</Para><OrderedList id="_339" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Results
of two randomized trials that used adjuvant radiation therapy in patients with
stage I disease did not show improved survival but did show reduced locoregional recurrence (3%–4% in the radiation therapy group vs. 12%–14% in the control group after median follow-up of 5–6 years; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001), with an increase in side effects.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]  
</ListItem><ListItem>Results of a study by the Danish Endometrial Cancer Group suggest that the absence of radiation therapy does not improve the survival of patients with stage I intermediate-risk disease (grades 1 and 2 with &gt;50% myometrial invasion or grade 3 with &lt;50% myometrial invasion).<Reference refidx="33"/></ListItem><ListItem>The <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00411138">PORTEC-2</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT00411138) randomly assigned patients with stage I endometrial cancer who did not undergo lymph node dissection to undergo VBT or EBRT, with prevention of vaginal recurrence as the primary outcome.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="34"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  <ItemizedList id="_342" Style="bullet"><ListItem>At 5 years, there was no difference in the rates of vaginal recurrence, locoregional recurrence, PFS, or OS (84.8% [95% confidence interval (CI), 79.3%–90.3%] for VBT vs. 79.6% [95% CI, 71.2%–88.0%] for EBRT; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .57).  </ListItem><ListItem>The VBT group had significantly fewer  gastrointestinal toxic effects and improved quality of life, making VBT the preferred option for adjuvant treatment of patients with stage I disease.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	The Norwegian Radium Hospital trial included 568 patients with clinical stage I endometrial cancer between 1968 and 1974 (before FIGO surgical staging was initiated).<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  After hysterectomy and bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, patients were randomly assigned to receive either EBRT and VBT or VBT alone.  <ItemizedList id="_610" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	An updated report presenting over 20 years of follow-up data showed no difference in OS between the treatment groups.  Median OS was 20.5 years in the EBRT/VBT group and 20.48 years in the VBT-alone group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .186).  In all women, there was an increased risk of secondary cancers after EBRT (hazard ratio [HR], 1.42; 95% CI, 1.01–2.0).</ListItem><ListItem>	A post hoc subset analysis of women  younger than 60 years at the time of trial registration showed increased mortality in the EBRT/VBT arm (HR, 1.36; 95% CI, 1.06–1.76).  Further, the risk of secondary cancers doubled in this group (HR, 2.02; 95% CI, 1.3–3.15).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_645"><Title>Postoperative radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_646">If the cervix is not clinically involved, but extension to the cervix is noted on postoperative pathology, radiation therapy is considered.<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_489"><Title>Radiation therapy alone</Title><Para id="_490">Patients who have medical
contraindications to surgery may be treated with radiation therapy alone,
but cure rates may be lower than those attained with surgery.<Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_40_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_40_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="22850412">Kiess AP, Damast S, Makker V, et al.: Five-year outcomes of adjuvant carboplatin/paclitaxel chemotherapy and intravaginal radiation for stage I-II papillary serous endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 127 (2): 321-5, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="19592079">Boruta DM, Gehrig PA, Fader AN, et al.: Management of women with uterine papillary serous cancer: a Society of Gynecologic Oncology (SGO) review. Gynecol Oncol 115 (1): 142-53, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="14675664">Huh WK, Powell M, Leath CA, et al.: Uterine papillary serous carcinoma: comparisons of outcomes in surgical Stage I patients with and without adjuvant therapy. Gynecol Oncol 91 (3): 470-5, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19306417">Fader AN, Drake RD, O'Malley DM, et al.: Platinum/taxane-based chemotherapy with or without radiation therapy favorably impacts survival outcomes in stage I uterine papillary serous carcinoma. Cancer 115 (10): 2119-27, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="16005947">Kelly MG, O'malley DM, Hui P, et al.: Improved survival in surgical stage I patients with uterine papillary serous carcinoma (UPSC) treated with adjuvant platinum-based chemotherapy. Gynecol Oncol 98 (3): 353-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="17355889">Havrilesky LJ, Secord AA, Bae-Jump V, et al.: Outcomes in surgical stage I uterine papillary serous carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 105 (3): 677-82, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="16154185">Dietrich CS, Modesitt SC, DePriest PD, et al.: The efficacy of adjuvant platinum-based chemotherapy in Stage I uterine papillary serous carcinoma (UPSC). Gynecol Oncol 99 (3): 557-63, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="23262378">Townamchai K, Berkowitz R, Bhagwat M, et al.: Vaginal brachytherapy for early stage uterine papillary serous and clear cell endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 129 (1): 18-21, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="22543202">Barney BM, Petersen IA, Mariani A, et al.: The role of vaginal brachytherapy in the treatment of surgical stage I papillary serous or clear cell endometrial cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 85 (1): 109-15, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="3793549" MedlineID="87083034">Hornback NB, Omura G, Major FJ: Observations on the use of adjuvant radiation therapy in patients with stage I and II uterine sarcoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 12 (12): 2127-30, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="2767523" MedlineID="89357623">Peters WA, Rivkin SE, Smith MR, et al.: Cisplatin and adriamycin combination chemotherapy for uterine stromal sarcomas and mixed mesodermal tumors. Gynecol Oncol 34 (3): 323-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="15047207">Ayhan A, Taskiran C, Celik C, et al.: The long-term survival of women with surgical stage II endometrioid type endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 93 (1): 9-13, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="10385555">Eltabbakh GH, Moore AD: Survival of women with surgical stage II endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 74 (1): 80-5, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="19345400">Orezzoli JP, Sioletic S, Olawaiye A, et al.: Stage II endometrioid adenocarcinoma of the endometrium: clinical implications of cervical stromal invasion. Gynecol Oncol 113 (3): 316-23, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="19805679">Walker JL, Piedmonte MR, Spirtos NM, et al.: Laparoscopy compared with laparotomy for comprehensive surgical staging of uterine cancer: Gynecologic Oncology Group Study LAP2. J Clin Oncol 27 (32): 5331-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="18304622">Mariani A, Dowdy SC, Cliby WA, et al.: Prospective assessment of lymphatic dissemination in endometrial cancer: a paradigm shift in surgical staging. Gynecol Oncol 109 (1): 11-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="10871473">Mariani A, Webb MJ, Keeney GL, et al.: Low-risk corpus cancer: is lymphadenectomy or radiotherapy necessary? Am J Obstet Gynecol 182 (6): 1506-19, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="22366409">Barlin JN, Khoury-Collado F, Kim CH, et al.: The importance of applying a sentinel lymph node mapping algorithm in endometrial cancer staging: beyond removal of blue nodes. Gynecol Oncol 125 (3): 531-5, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="20638899">Janda M, Gebski V, Brand A, et al.: Quality of life after total laparoscopic hysterectomy versus total abdominal hysterectomy for stage I endometrial cancer (LACE): a randomised trial. Lancet Oncol 11 (8): 772-80, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="20638901">Mourits MJ, Bijen CB, Arts HJ, et al.: Safety of laparoscopy versus laparotomy in early-stage endometrial cancer: a randomised trial. Lancet Oncol 11 (8): 763-71, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="19805678">Kornblith AB, Huang HQ, Walker JL, et al.: Quality of life of patients with endometrial cancer undergoing laparoscopic international federation of gynecology and obstetrics staging compared with laparotomy: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 27 (32): 5337-42, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="22291074">Walker JL, Piedmonte MR, Spirtos NM, et al.: Recurrence and survival after random assignment to laparoscopy versus laparotomy for comprehensive surgical staging of uterine cancer: Gynecologic Oncology Group LAP2 Study. J Clin Oncol 30 (7): 695-700, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="22972096">Galaal K, Bryant A, Fisher AD, et al.: Laparoscopy versus laparotomy for the management of early stage endometrial cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 9: CD006655, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="6999399" MedlineID="81031423">Aalders J, Abeler V, Kolstad P, et al.: Postoperative external irradiation and prognostic parameters in stage I endometrial carcinoma: clinical and histopathologic study of 540 patients. Obstet Gynecol 56 (4): 419-27, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="1989916" MedlineID="91115216">Morrow CP, Bundy BN, Kurman RJ, et al.: Relationship between surgical-pathological risk factors and outcome in clinical stage I and II carcinoma of the endometrium: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Gynecol Oncol 40 (1): 55-65, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="2323613" MedlineID="90215375">Marchetti DL, Caglar H, Driscoll DL, et al.: Pelvic radiation in stage I endometrial adenocarcinoma with high-risk attributes. Gynecol Oncol 37 (1): 51-4, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="10791524" MedlineID="20250163">Creutzberg CL, van Putten WL, Koper PC, et al.: Surgery and postoperative radiotherapy versus surgery alone for patients with stage-1 endometrial carcinoma: multicentre randomised trial. PORTEC Study Group. Post Operative Radiation Therapy in Endometrial Carcinoma. Lancet 355 (9213): 1404-11, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="22962693">Kong A, Johnson N, Kitchener HC, et al.: Adjuvant radiotherapy for stage I endometrial cancer: an updated Cochrane systematic review and meta-analysis. J Natl Cancer Inst 104 (21): 1625-34, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="20206777">Nout RA, Smit VT, Putter H, et al.: Vaginal brachytherapy versus pelvic external beam radiotherapy for patients with endometrial cancer of high-intermediate risk (PORTEC-2): an open-label, non-inferiority, randomised trial. Lancet 375 (9717): 816-23, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="24019546">Onsrud M, Cvancarova M, Hellebust TP, et al.: Long-term outcomes after pelvic radiation for early-stage endometrial cancer. J Clin Oncol 31 (31): 3951-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="14984936">Keys HM, Roberts JA, Brunetto VL, et al.: A phase III trial of surgery with or without adjunctive external pelvic radiation therapy in intermediate risk endometrial adenocarcinoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Gynecol Oncol 92 (3): 744-51, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="15927414">Scholten AN, van Putten WL, Beerman H, et al.: Postoperative radiotherapy for Stage 1 endometrial carcinoma: long-term outcome of the randomized PORTEC trial with central pathology review. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 63 (3): 834-8, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="21885985">Bertelsen K, Ortoft G, Hansen ES: Survival of Danish patients with endometrial cancer in the intermediate-risk group not given postoperative radiotherapy: the Danish Endometrial Cancer Study (DEMCA). Int J Gynecol Cancer 21 (7): 1191-9, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="22176868">Nout RA, Putter H, Jürgenliemk-Schulz IM, et al.: Five-year quality of life of endometrial cancer patients treated in the randomised Post Operative Radiation Therapy in Endometrial Cancer (PORTEC-2) trial and comparison with norm data. Eur J Cancer 48 (11): 1638-48, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="9226326" MedlineID="97369885">Eltabbakh GH, Piver MS, Hempling RE, et al.: Excellent long-term survival and absence of vaginal recurrences in 332 patients with low-risk stage I endometrial adenocarcinoma treated with hysterectomy and vaginal brachytherapy without formal staging lymph node sampling: report of a prospective trial. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 38 (2): 373-80, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="3957733" MedlineID="86167671">Stokes S, Bedwinek J, Kao MS, et al.: Treatment of stage I adenocarcinoma of the endometrium by hysterectomy and adjuvant irradiation: a retrospective analysis of 304 patients. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 12 (3): 339-44, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="3558039" MedlineID="87165251">Grigsby PW, Kuske RR, Perez CA, et al.: Medically inoperable stage I adenocarcinoma of the endometrium treated with radiotherapy alone. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 13 (4): 483-8, 1987.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_54"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038741">stage III endometrial carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038742">stage IV endometrial carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038743">recurrent endometrial carcinoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III, Stage IV, and Recurrent Endometrial Cancer </Title><SummarySection id="_347"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage III, Stage IV, and Recurrent  Endometrial Cancer</Title><Para id="_348">Treatment options for patients with stage III, stage IV, and recurrent endometrial cancer include:</Para><OrderedList id="_349" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_511" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Surgery followed by chemotherapy or radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_359" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy and radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_360" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Hormone therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_613" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Biological therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_709" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Immunotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_720" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Clinical trials</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_546">Treatment of patients with stage IV endometrial cancer is dictated by the site of metastatic disease and symptoms related to disease sites.</Para><SummarySection id="_511"><Title>Surgery followed by chemotherapy or radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_552">In general, patients with stage III or stage IV endometrial cancer are treated with surgery, followed by chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or both.
Observational studies support maximal cytoreductive surgery for patients with stage IV disease, although these conclusions need to be interpreted with care because of the small number of cases and likely selection bias.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_512">For many years, radiation therapy was the standard adjuvant treatment for patients with endometrial cancer.  However, several randomized trials have confirmed improved survival when adjuvant chemotherapy is used instead of radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_629">Doxorubicin was historically the most active anticancer agent used,
with useful but temporary responses obtained in as many as 33% of patients
with recurrent disease.  Paclitaxel, when combined with platinum chemotherapy or when used as a single agent, also has significant anticancer activity.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_513">Evidence (surgery followed by chemotherapy or radiation therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_514" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Several randomized trials by the Gynecologic Oncology Group (GOG) have used doxorubicin because of its known antitumor activity.<Reference refidx="4"/><ItemizedList id="_515" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Adding cisplatin to doxorubicin increased response rates and progression-free survival (PFS) when compared with doxorubicin alone. However, adding cisplatin did not affect overall survival (OS).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A  three-drug regimen of doxorubicin, cisplatin, and paclitaxel  with granulocyte-colony stimulating factor (G-CSF) was significantly superior to cisplatin and doxorubicin, as shown by the following results:<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>] <ItemizedList id="_554" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Response rate was 57% with the three-drug regimen, compared with 34% with the cisplatin and doxorubicin regimen. </ListItem><ListItem>PFS  was 8.3 months with the three-drug regimen, compared with 5.3 months with the cisplatin and doxorubicin regimen.</ListItem><ListItem>OS was 15.3 months with the three-drug regimen, compared with 12.3 months with the cisplatin and doxorubicin regimen.</ListItem><ListItem>The 3-drug regimen was associated with grade 3 peripheral neuropathy in 12% of patients and grade 2 peripheral neuropathy in 27% of patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_555">Given the toxicity and limited efficacy of these regimens, other treatment options have been widely sought.  Several observational  studies <Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> and phase II studies <Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> suggest clinical activity with the combination of platinum chemotherapy and paclitaxel in patients with endometrial cancer and measurable disease either after primary surgery or at recurrence.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>The phase III, randomized, open-label, noninferiority <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00063999">GOG-0209</ProtocolRef>  trial (NCT000063999) compared the combination of paclitaxel, doxorubicin, cisplatin (TAP), and G-CSF with carboplatin and paclitaxel (TC) in 1,381 women.<Reference refidx="13"/><ItemizedList id="_556" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The median OS was 37 months for patients in the TC group and 41 months for patients in the TAP group (hazard ratio [HR], 1.002; 90% confidence interval [CI], 0.9–1.12). The median PFS was 13 months for patients in the TC group and 14 months for patients in the TAP group (HR, 1.032; 90% CI, 0.93–1.15).<Reference refidx="13"/> </ListItem><ListItem>These results led to the use of TC as the standard adjuvant treatment for patients with stages III and IV disease.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The use of  cisplatin and doxorubicin compared with whole-abdominal radiation therapy was studied in a trial of patients with stage III or IV disease with residual tumors smaller  than 2 cm and no parenchymal organ involvement.<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_557" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Results suggest that cisplatin and doxorubicin improved OS, compared with whole-abdominal radiation therapy (5-year survival rate, 55% for cisplatin and doxorubicin vs. 42% for whole-abdominal radiation; adjusted HR, 0.68; 95% CI, 0.52–0.89; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	Several trials support combination chemotherapy for patients with stage III, stage IV, and recurrent carcinosarcoma.  <OrderedList id="_638" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>	The GOG-108 trial of ifosfamide, with or without cisplatin, as first-line therapy in patients with measurable advanced or recurrent carcinosarcomas demonstrated a higher response rate (54% vs. 34%) and longer PFS in the combination arm (6 months vs. 4 months), but there was no significant improvement in survival (9 months vs. 8 months).<Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] </ListItem><ListItem>The follow-up <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00003128">GOG-0161</ProtocolRef> study
(NCT00003128)
used 3-day ifosfamide regimens (instead of the more-toxic 5-day regimen in the preceding study) for the control and ifosfamide combined with paclitaxel (with G-CSF starting on day 4) for the study arm.<Reference refidx="16"/> <ItemizedList id="_639" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The combination regimen produced superior response rates (45% vs. 29%), PFS (8.4 months vs. 5.8 months), and OS (13.5 months vs. 8.4 months). The HR for death also favored the combination regimen  (HR, 0.69; 95% CI, 0.49–0.97).<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem> In this study, 52% of 179 evaluable patients had recurrent disease, 18% had stage III disease, and 30% had stage IV disease.  In addition, there were imbalances between the treatment arms with respect to the sites of disease and the use of prior radiation therapy, and 30 patients were excluded for wrong pathology.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_359"><Title>Chemotherapy and radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_213">Patients with inoperable disease caused by tumor that extends to the pelvic wall may be treated with a combination of chemotherapy and  radiation therapy.  The usual
approach for radiation therapy is a combination of intracavitary and external-beam radiation
therapy (EBRT).<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>  </Para><Para id="_630">For patients with localized recurrences (pelvic and para-aortic lymph nodes) or distant
metastases in selected sites, radiation therapy may be an effective palliative
therapy.  Pelvic radiation therapy may be curative in patients with pure vaginal
recurrence when no previous radiation therapy has been used.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_360"><Title>Hormone therapy</Title><Para id="_558">Progesterone and estrogen hormone receptors are commonly found in 
endometrial carcinoma tissues.  Response to hormone therapy is correlated with the
presence and level of hormone receptors and the degree of tumor
differentiation.<Reference refidx="19"/> Patients with tumors that are positive for
estrogen and progesterone receptors respond best to progestin therapy.    </Para><Para id="_83">When distant metastases, especially pulmonary metastases, are present, hormonal therapy is indicated. Patients who are not candidates for either surgery or radiation therapy may
be treated with progestational agents, the most common hormonal treatment.  Progestational agents
produce good antitumor responses in 15% to 30% of patients.   These
responses are associated with significant improvement in survival.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><Para id="_463">  Standard progestational agents include:<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_464" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Hydroxyprogesterone.</ListItem><ListItem>Medroxyprogesterone. </ListItem><ListItem>Megestrol.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_631">Evidence (progestin therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_632" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>One study followed 115 patients with advanced endometrial cancer treated with progestins.<Reference refidx="20"/><ItemizedList id="_633" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Responses occurred in 75% of patients (42 of 56) with progesterone receptor–positive tumors.</ListItem><ListItem>Responses occurred in 7% of patients (4 of 59) without detectable progesterone
receptors.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_634">  A receptor-poor status may predict a poor
response to progestins and a better response to cytotoxic
chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_635">Other hormonal agents have shown benefit in treating endometrial cancer. Tamoxifen (20 mg
bid) yields a 20% response rate in patients who do not respond to
standard progesterone therapy.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_600">Aromatase inhibitors have also been evaluated for the treatment of advanced and recurrent endometrial cancer, although they yield lower response rates than progestational agents.<Reference refidx="23"/>  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_613"><Title>Biological therapy</Title><Para id="_614">Several biological agents have been evaluated for the treatment of endometrial cancer.</Para><OrderedList id="_615" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) inhibitors.<Para id="_616">Endometrial cancers often show alterations in the AKT-PI3K pathway, making mTOR inhibitors an attractive choice for clinical study in patients with metastatic or recurrent disease.  Phase II studies of single-agent everolimus <Reference refidx="24"/> and ridaforolimus <Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/> have predominantly shown disease stabilization.  A phase II study of the combination of everolimus and letrozole showed a 32% response rate.<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></ListItem><ListItem>Bevacizumab.<ItemizedList id="_617" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Bevacizumab was used as a single agent in a phase II trial. The overall response rate was 13.5%.<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Bevacizumab combined with temsirolimus has been used.<Reference refidx="29"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_709"><Title>Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_710">With the published results of The Cancer Genome Atlas, and as more is learned about the molecular drivers of endometrial cancer, the use of immunotherapy has been evaluated for the treatment of advanced and recurrent disease.</Para><Para id="_711">Evidence (immunotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_712" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03517449">Study 309/KEYNOTE-775</ProtocolRef> (NCT03517449) was a large, international, multicenter, randomized trial that compared the combination of pembrolizumab (200mg intravenously [IV] every 3 weeks for up to 35 cycles) and lenvatinib (20mg orally daily) with physician's choice of chemotherapy. The study enrolled women with advanced or recurrent endometrial cancer who had disease progression after a platinum-based regimen (measurable disease was required). All histologies except carcinosarcoma and sarcoma were permitted. Patients were stratified by mismatch repair (MMR) status. The two primary end points were PFS and OS.<Reference refidx="30"/> <ItemizedList id="_714" Style="bullet"><ListItem>After a median follow-up of approximately 12 months in both groups,  survivals were statistically longer for patients in the pembrolizumab-lenvatinib group. The benefit persisted despite the patients' MMR statuses. Among all patients, the median PFS was 7.3 months for patients who received pembrolizumab and lenvatinib and 3.8 months for patients who received chemotherapy (HR, 0.56; 95% CI, 0.48–0.66; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). The median OS was 18.7 months for patients who received pembrolizumab and lenvatinib and 11.9 months for patients who received chemotherapy (HR, 0.65; 95% CI, 0.55–0.77; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>The most frequent serious side effect in the experimental group was hypertension. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The double-blind placebo-controlled <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03914612">KEYNOTE-868</ProtocolRef> study (NCT03914612) included 810 patients with advanced (stage III, stage IVA, or stage IVB) or recurrent endometrial cancer.<Reference refidx="31"/> Patients were randomly assigned to receive six cycles of paclitaxel and carboplatin with either pembrolizumab or placebo. Afterwards, patients received up to 14 cycles of maintenance therapy with pembrolizumab or placebo. Patients were stratified according to MMR statuses (proficient [pMMR; n =588] or deficient [dMMR; n = 222]) to investigate if the checkpoint inhibitor, pembrolizumab, was  efficacious in patients with dMMR tumors.<ItemizedList id="_733" Style="bullet"><ListItem>After a median follow-up of 12.0 months, the 1-year PFS for patients with dMMR tumors was 74% in the pembrolizumab group and 38% in the  placebo group (HR, 0.30; 95% CI, 0.19–0.48; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>After a median follow-up of 7.9 months, the median PFS for patients with pMMR tumors was 13.1 months in the pembrolizumab group and 8.7 months in the placebo group (HR, 0.54; 95% CI, 0.41–0.71; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Regardless of MMR status, pembrolizumab showed significant PFS improvement in patients with advanced or recurrent endometrial cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The phase III randomized	<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04634877">KEYNOTE-B21</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT04634877) included 1,095 patients with newly diagnosed high-risk stage I to stage IVA endometrial cancer (including carcinosarcoma) without evidence of disease postsurgery. All patients received either six cycles of chemotherapy with optional EBRT or four cycles of chemotherapy followed by chemoradiation therapy. Vaginal brachytherapy was allowed in both groups. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either adjuvant pembrolizumab or placebo every 3 weeks for six cycles, then every 6 weeks for six cycles. A total of 66% of patients had stage III or stage IVA disease, 26% had dMMR tumors, and 67% were treated with radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><ItemizedList id="_736" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	After a median follow-up of 24 months, the 2-year disease-free survival (DFS) rate was 75% in the pembrolizumab group and 76% in the placebo group (HR, 1.02; 95% CI, 0.79–1.32; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .57).<Reference refidx="33"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>	In the dMMR cohort, the 2-year DFS rate was 92.4% in the pembrolizumab group and 80.2% in the placebo group (HR, 0.31; 95% CI, 0.14–0.69).</ListItem><ListItem>	No other predetermined subgroup benefitted from adding pembrolizumab.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_737">This study evaluated giving pembrolizumab to patients with positive lymph nodes after surgery who had no other visible evidence of disease. It also evaluated combining radiation therapy and pembrolizumab. Results were significant because they expanded the population of patients who can receive pembrolizumab. </Para></ListItem><ListItem>The <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03981796">RUBY</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT03981796) was a large multicenter trial in women with Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique stage III, IV, or recurrent endometrial cancer of all histologies not amenable to curative therapy. Unlike the Study 309/KEYNOTE-775 trial, some patients without measurable disease qualified for inclusion. Women were randomly assigned to receive TC with or without dostarlimab (500 mg IV) every 3 weeks for six cycles followed by maintenance dostarlimab (1,000 mg IV every 6 weeks) for up to 3 years. Patients were stratified by MMR status. The primary end point was PFS.<Reference refidx="34"/> <ItemizedList id="_716" Style="bullet"><ListItem>After a median follow-up of approximately 2 years, the dostarlimab group from the overall population had a 36% lower risk of progression or death (HR, 0.64; 95% CI, 0.51–0.80; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). The dostarlimab group from the dMMR population had a 72% lower risk of progression or death (HR, 0.28; 95% CI, 0.16–0.50; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). Similar benefit was seen in OS (HR, 0.64; 95% CI, 0.46–0.87, <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0021 for the overall population; HR, 0.30; 95% CI, 0.13–0.70 for the dMMR population).<Reference refidx="34"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_713">These three studies demonstrate the activity and benefit of immunotherapy in the treatment of patients with advanced stage and recurrent endometrial cancer. These results may also facilitate the incorporation of such treatments into the up-front setting. More data are needed to help discern the role of immunotherapy in patients whose treatment plan would historically include radiation therapy. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_720"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_721">All patients with advanced disease should consider clinical trials
that evaluate single-agent or combination therapy for this disease.</Para><Para id="_722">Studies of treatment failure patterns have found a high rate of distant
metastases in the upper abdomen and  in extra-abdominal sites.<Reference refidx="35"/> For this reason,
patients with stage III disease may be candidates for innovative clinical
trials.</Para><Para id="_723">Treatment options under clinical evaluation for stage IV endometrial cancer include the following  agents:</Para><OrderedList id="_724" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>	Paclitaxel and carboplatin with or without metformin in stages III, IV, and recurrent endometrial cancer (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02065687">GOG-0286B</ProtocolRef> [NCT02065687]). </ListItem><ListItem>PI3K/mTOR inhibitor in recurrent or persistent endometrial cancer (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02549989">15-079</ProtocolRef> [NCT02549989]).</ListItem><ListItem>	Everolimus and letrozole or hormonal therapy in recurrent or persistent endometrial cancer  (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02228681">GOG-3007</ProtocolRef> [NCT02228681]).</ListItem><ListItem>	Everolimus, letrozole, and metformin in advanced or recurrent endometrial cancer   (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01797523">2012-0543</ProtocolRef> [NCT01797523]).</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_54_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_54_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21664663">Shih KK, Yun E, Gardner GJ, et al.: Surgical cytoreduction in stage IV endometrioid endometrial carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 122 (3): 608-11, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="20434198">Barlin JN, Puri I, Bristow RE: Cytoreductive surgery for advanced or recurrent endometrial cancer: a meta-analysis. Gynecol Oncol 118 (1): 14-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8751561" MedlineID="96350573">Ball HG, Blessing JA, Lentz SS, et al.: A phase II trial of paclitaxel in patients with advanced or recurrent adenocarcinoma of the endometrium: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Gynecol Oncol 62 (2): 278-81, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15459211">Thigpen JT, Brady MF, Homesley HD, et al.: Phase III trial of doxorubicin with or without cisplatin in advanced endometrial carcinoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 22 (19): 3902-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15169803">Fleming GF, Brunetto VL, Cella D, et al.: Phase III trial of doxorubicin plus cisplatin with or without paclitaxel plus filgrastim in advanced endometrial carcinoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 22 (11): 2159-66, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15277255">Fleming GF, Filiaci VL, Bentley RC, et al.: Phase III randomized trial of doxorubicin + cisplatin versus doxorubicin + 24-h paclitaxel + filgrastim in endometrial carcinoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Ann Oncol 15 (8): 1173-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="16996113">Arimoto T, Nakagawa S, Yasugi T, et al.: Treatment with paclitaxel plus carboplatin, alone or with irradiation, of advanced or recurrent endometrial carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 104 (1): 32-5, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="16677690">Sovak MA, Hensley ML, Dupont J, et al.: Paclitaxel and carboplatin in the adjuvant treatment of patients with high-risk stage III and IV endometrial cancer: a retrospective study. Gynecol Oncol 103 (2): 451-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11600606">Hoskins PJ, Swenerton KD, Pike JA, et al.: Paclitaxel and carboplatin, alone or with irradiation, in advanced or recurrent endometrial cancer: a phase II study. J Clin Oncol 19 (20): 4048-53, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="18299146">Pectasides D, Xiros N, Papaxoinis G, et al.: Carboplatin and paclitaxel in advanced or metastatic endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 109 (2): 250-4, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="20696677">Nomura H, Aoki D, Takahashi F, et al.: Randomized phase II study comparing docetaxel plus cisplatin, docetaxel plus carboplatin, and paclitaxel plus carboplatin in patients with advanced or recurrent endometrial carcinoma: a Japanese Gynecologic Oncology Group study (JGOG2041). Ann Oncol 22 (3): 636-42, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="10873410">Dimopoulos MA, Papadimitriou CA, Georgoulias V, et al.: Paclitaxel and cisplatin in advanced or recurrent carcinoma of the endometrium: long-term results of a phase II multicenter study. Gynecol Oncol 78 (1): 52-7, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="33078978">Miller DS, Filiaci VL, Mannel RS, et al.: Carboplatin and Paclitaxel for Advanced Endometrial Cancer: Final Overall Survival and Adverse Event Analysis of a Phase III Trial (NRG Oncology/GOG0209). J Clin Oncol 38 (33): 3841-3850, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="16330675">Randall ME, Filiaci VL, Muss H, et al.: Randomized phase III trial of whole-abdominal irradiation versus doxorubicin and cisplatin chemotherapy in advanced endometrial carcinoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 24 (1): 36-44, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="11063636" MedlineID="20519489">Sutton G, Brunetto VL, Kilgore L, et al.: A phase III trial of ifosfamide with or without cisplatin in carcinosarcoma of the uterus: A Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. Gynecol Oncol 79 (2): 147-53, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="17290061">Homesley HD, Filiaci V, Markman M, et al.: Phase III trial of ifosfamide with or without paclitaxel in advanced uterine carcinosarcoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 25 (5): 526-31, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="20122872">Wegner RE, Beriwal S, Heron DE, et al.: Definitive radiation therapy for endometrial cancer in medically inoperable elderly patients. Brachytherapy 9 (3): 260-5, 2010 Jul-Sep.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="8244810">Kupelian PA, Eifel PJ, Tornos C, et al.: Treatment of endometrial carcinoma with radiation therapy alone. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 27 (4): 817-24, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="8310300" MedlineID="94143746">Lentz SS: Advanced and recurrent endometrial carcinoma: hormonal therapy. Semin Oncol 21 (1): 100-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="2675940" MedlineID="90000882">Kauppila A: Oestrogen and progestin receptors as prognostic indicators in endometrial cancer. A review of the literature. Acta Oncol 28 (4): 561-6, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="6946673" MedlineID="82064670">Kauppila A, Friberg LG: Hormonal and cytotoxic chemotherapy for endometrial carcinoma. Steroid receptors in the selection of appropriate therapy. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand Suppl 101: 59-64, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="2909443" MedlineID="89079077">Quinn MA, Campbell JJ: Tamoxifen therapy in advanced/recurrent endometrial carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol 32 (1): 1-3, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="24498853">Lindemann K, Malander S, Christensen RD, et al.: Examestane in advanced or recurrent endometrial carcinoma: a prospective phase II study by the Nordic Society of Gynecologic Oncology (NSGO). BMC Cancer 14: 68, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="20681032">Slomovitz BM, Lu KH, Johnston T, et al.: A phase 2 study of the oral mammalian target of rapamycin inhibitor, everolimus, in patients with recurrent endometrial carcinoma. Cancer 116 (23): 5415-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="23403817">Colombo N, McMeekin DS, Schwartz PE, et al.: Ridaforolimus as a single agent in advanced endometrial cancer: results of a single-arm, phase 2 trial. Br J Cancer 108 (5): 1021-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="25173583">Tsoref D, Welch S, Lau S, et al.: Phase II study of oral ridaforolimus in women with recurrent or metastatic endometrial cancer. Gynecol Oncol 135 (2): 184-9, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="25624430">Slomovitz BM, Jiang Y, Yates MS, et al.: Phase II study of everolimus and letrozole in patients with recurrent endometrial carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 33 (8): 930-6, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="21537039">Aghajanian C, Sill MW, Darcy KM, et al.: Phase II trial of bevacizumab in recurrent or persistent endometrial cancer: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 29 (16): 2259-65, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="23262204">Alvarez EA, Brady WE, Walker JL, et al.: Phase II trial of combination bevacizumab and temsirolimus in the treatment of recurrent or persistent endometrial carcinoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Gynecol Oncol 129 (1): 22-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="37058687">Makker V, Colombo N, Casado Herráez A, et al.: Lenvatinib Plus Pembrolizumab in Previously Treated Advanced Endometrial Cancer: Updated Efficacy and Safety From the Randomized Phase III Study 309/KEYNOTE-775. J Clin Oncol 41 (16): 2904-2910, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="36972022">Eskander RN, Sill MW, Beffa L, et al.: Pembrolizumab plus Chemotherapy in Advanced Endometrial Cancer. N Engl J Med 388 (23): 2159-2170, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="39284383">Van Gorp T, Cibula D, Lv W, et al.: ENGOT-en11/GOG-3053/KEYNOTE-B21: a randomised, double-blind, phase III study of pembrolizumab or placebo plus adjuvant chemotherapy with or without radiotherapy in patients with newly diagnosed, high-risk endometrial cancer. Ann Oncol 35 (11): 968-980, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="39411812">Slomovitz BM, Cibula D, Lv W, et al.: Pembrolizumab or Placebo Plus Adjuvant Chemotherapy With or Without Radiotherapy for Newly Diagnosed, High-Risk Endometrial Cancer: Results in Mismatch Repair-Deficient Tumors. J Clin Oncol 43 (3): 251-259, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="36972026">Mirza MR, Chase DM, Slomovitz BM, et al.: Dostarlimab for Primary Advanced or Recurrent Endometrial Cancer. N Engl J Med 388 (23): 2145-2158, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="2745205" MedlineID="89308156">Greven KM, Curran WJ, Whittington R, et al.: Analysis of failure patterns in stage III endometrial carcinoma and therapeutic implications. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 17 (1): 35-9, 1989.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_73"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/14/2025)</Title><Para id="_74">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.

</Para><Para id="_741">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of endometrial cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Endometrial Cancer Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Olga T.  Filippova, MD (Lenox Hill Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Marina Stasenko, MD (New York University Medical Center)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Endometrial Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389270]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-05-14</DateLastModified></Summary>
