<Summary id="CDR0000062918" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma treatment options include radiation therapy, chemoradiation followed by adjuvant chemotherapy, surgery, and chemotherapy. Get detailed information about the treatment of newly diagnosed and recurrent nasopharyngeal carcinoma in this summary for clinicians.  </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Nasopharyngeal carcinoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Nasopharyngeal carcinoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_314">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of adult nasopharyngeal carcinoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_315">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adult nasopharyngeal carcinoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_163"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_497">Tumors of many histologies can occur in the nasopharynx, but only nasopharyngeal carcinomas (also called NPC) are covered in this summary. The American Joint Committee on Cancer nasopharynx staging refers exclusively to the World Health Organization's (WHO) classification of grades I, II, and III nasopharyngeal carcinoma. </Para><SummarySection id="_394"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_395">Less than one person out of 100,000 is diagnosed with nasopharyngeal carcinoma in the world each year, with most cases found in  southern China, Southeast Asia, the Arctic, and the Middle East/North Africa. The incidence is higher in males than in females.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> WHO grade I nasopharyngeal carcinoma (keratinizing subtype) accounts for less than 20% of cases in the United States and WHO grades II and III represent the endemic form of nasopharyngeal carcinoma and are found mostly in Asia. Nonkeratinizing subtypes are associated with Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) infection and account for most cases.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_156"><Title>Anatomy</Title><Para id="_2">The nasopharynx has a cuboidal shape.  The lateral walls are formed by the
eustachian tube and the fossa of Rosenmuller.  The roof, sloping downward from
anterior to posterior, is bordered by the pharyngeal hypophysis, pharyngeal
tonsil, and pharyngeal bursa with the base of the skull above.  Anteriorly, the
nasopharynx abuts the posterior choanae and nasal cavity, and the posterior
boundary is formed by the muscles of the posterior pharyngeal wall. 
Inferiorly, the nasopharynx ends at an imaginary horizontal line formed by the
upper surface of the soft palate and the posterior pharyngeal wall.
Nasopharyngeal carcinoma originates from the epithelial cells that line the nasopharynx.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000713970" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the pharynx; drawing shows the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and hypopharynx. Also shown are the nasal cavity, oral cavity, hyoid bone, larynx, esophagus, and trachea." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_527"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the pharynx.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><Title>Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_3">Risk factors for nasopharyngeal carcinoma include:<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> 
</Para><ItemizedList id="_913" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>Risk factors for keratinizing squamous cell carcinoma (WHO grade I):</ListTitle><ListItem>Heavy alcohol intake.</ListItem><ListItem>History of smoking.</ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_167" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>Risk factors for nonkeratinizing carcinoma (WHO grades II and III):</ListTitle><ListItem>Asian race.</ListItem><ListItem>EBV exposure.</ListItem><ListItem>Family history.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_129"><Title>Clinical Features</Title><Para id="_4">Signs and symptoms at presentation include: 
</Para><ItemizedList id="_130" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Headache caused by cranial nerve dysfunction (usually II–VI or IX–XII).</ListItem><ListItem>Diplopia.</ListItem><ListItem>Facial numbness.</ListItem><ListItem>Cervical adenopathy (present in approximately 75% of patients and often bilateral and
posterior).</ListItem><ListItem>Nasal obstruction.</ListItem><ListItem>Epistaxis.</ListItem><ListItem>Diminished hearing.</ListItem><ListItem>Tinnitus.</ListItem><ListItem>Otitis media.</ListItem><ListItem>Sore throat.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_131">In patients who present with cervical
adenopathy alone, the finding of EBV genomic material in the tissue using polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is strong evidence
of a nasopharyngeal primary tumor, and that area should be examined closely.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_132"><Title>Diagnostic Evaluation</Title><SummarySection id="_914"><Title>Diagnostic tests and procedures</Title><Para id="_915">Diagnosis is made by biopsy of the nasopharyngeal mass.  The following tests and procedures are used in the diagnosis of nasopharyngeal carcinoma:<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_916" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Careful visual examination by fiberoptic nasal endoscopic examination and/or examination under anesthesia.</ListItem><ListItem>Endoscopic biopsy.</ListItem><ListItem>Physical examination and health history. Documentation
of the size and location of the tumor and cervical lymph nodes is noted. </ListItem><ListItem>Evaluation of cranial
nerve function including neuro-ophthalmological evaluation and audiological evaluation.</ListItem><ListItem>Computed tomography (CT) scan and/or positron emission tomography (PET)-CT scan.</ListItem><ListItem>Magnetic
resonance imaging (MRI) to evaluate skull base invasion. </ListItem><ListItem>Circulating cancer-derived EBV DNA in plasma.<Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem><ListItem>	Human papillomavirus (HPV) type 16 blood test if EBV negative.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_917">Any clinical or
laboratory finding that suggests distant metastasis may prompt further evaluation of
other sites.  MRI is
often more helpful than CT scans in assessing skull base involvement and in defining
the   extent of abnormalities detected.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_500"><Title>Circulating cancer-derived EBV DNA</Title><Para id="_501">EBV DNA in plasma samples in endemic populations may be useful in screening for early asymptomatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Circulating cancer-derived EBV DNA in plasma is an established tumor marker for nasopharyngeal carcinoma, with a sensitivity of 96% and a specificity of 93%.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/> The presence of short EBV DNA fragments of fewer than 181 base pairs in the plasma of nasopharyngeal carcinoma patients suggests that EBV DNA molecules are released into the circulation by apoptosis of cancer cells rather than by active viral replication.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_502">Evidence (EBV DNA in plasma for screening and diagnosis of nasopharyngeal carcinoma):</Para><OrderedList id="_503" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>In a   study of 20,174 participants in China, EBV DNA in plasma was used to screen for early nasopharyngeal carcinoma.<Reference refidx="14"/><ItemizedList id="_514" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Initially, 1,112 participants tested positive for EBV DNA in plasma.  </ListItem><ListItem>Three hundred and nine participants (1.5% of all participants, and 27.8% of those who initially tested positive) had persistently detectable EBV DNA in plasma at baseline and follow-up.</ListItem><ListItem>Among the 309   participants, nasopharyngeal carcinoma was confirmed after nasal endoscopic examination, MRI, and biopsy in 34 participants (11.0%).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_505"><Title>HPV</Title><Para id="_506">Differentiating HPV-related nasopharyngeal carcinoma requires identification of p16 immunohistochemical staining, <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization, and/or PCR similar to the method for  differentiating HPV-related oropharyngeal cancer. Less than 10% of nonkeratinizing nasopharyngeal carcinomas are associated with HPV infection.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/> </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><Title>Prognostic Factors</Title><Para id="_7">The following major prognostic factors adversely influence treatment outcome:<Reference refidx="20"/>
</Para><ItemizedList id="_136" Style="bullet"><ListItem>WHO grade I.</ListItem><ListItem>A higher tumor (T) stage.</ListItem><ListItem>The presence of involved cervical
lymph nodes (N).</ListItem><ListItem>	High plasma/serum EBV DNA levels before and after treatment.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem><ListItem>Large tumor volume.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><Title>Follow-Up Testing and Late Effects</Title><Para id="_12">Follow-up testing for tumor recurrence includes:<Reference refidx="24"/> 
</Para><ItemizedList id="_141" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Routine periodic examination of the original
tumor site and neck.</ListItem><ListItem>CT or PET-CT scan.</ListItem><ListItem>MRI scan.</ListItem><ListItem>Plasma/serum EBV DNA levels. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_142">Patients should be monitored for the following potential late effects of treatment:<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_143" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Xerostomia.</ListItem><ListItem>Dental and oral complications.</ListItem><ListItem>Hearing loss.</ListItem><ListItem>Vision loss.</ListItem><ListItem>Dysphagia.</ListItem><ListItem>Trismus.</ListItem><ListItem>Thyroid and pituitary function.
</ListItem><ListItem>Cranial
neuropathies.</ListItem><ListItem>Cognitive impairment.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_144">Although most recurrences occur within 5 years of diagnosis, relapse can be
seen at longer intervals.  The incidence of second primary malignancies  after treatment is lower for nasopharyngeal carcinoma than for other head and neck cancer sites.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_918">Accumulating evidence has demonstrated a high incidence (&gt;30%–40%) of
hypothyroidism in patients who have received radiation therapy that delivered external-beam radiation therapy (EBRT) to the entire thyroid gland or to the pituitary gland. 
Thyroid-function testing of patients should be considered before therapy and
as part of posttreatment follow-up.<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/></Para><Para id="_919"> Careful dental and oral hygiene evaluation and therapy is
particularly important before initiation of radiation treatment.  Intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) results in a lower incidence of xerostomia and may provide a better quality of life than conventional three-dimensional or two-dimensional radiation therapy (2DRT).<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810021" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A3</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_920">Evidence (IMRT vs. 2DRT and incidence of xerostomia):</Para><OrderedList id="_927" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A randomized prospective study assessed the incidence of xerostomia in patients with early-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma  treated with IMRT (n = 28) or 2DRT (n = 28).<Reference refidx="32"/> Long-term toxicities were graded with the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group (RTOG) criteria.<ItemizedList id="_944" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The incidence of grade 2 xerostomia was 20% for patients who received IMRT and 90% for patients who received 2DRT (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001). There was no significant difference between the groups with the xerostomia questionnaire.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients who received IMRT had lower scores for dry mouth than patients who received 2DRT.</ListItem><ListItem>The overall survival rate was 82% in the IMRT group versus 54% in the 2DRT group.</ListItem><ListItem>The relapse-free survival rate was 70% in the IMRT group versus 54% in the 2DRT group.</ListItem><ListItem>More late complications were reported among patients in the 2DRT group.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The phase II <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/study/NCT00057785">RTOG-0225</ExternalRef> study tested the feasibility of IMRT in a multi-institutional setting.<Reference refidx="33"/><ItemizedList id="_945" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The rate of grade 2 xerostomia at 1 year from start of IMRT was 13.5%.</ListItem><ListItem>The rate of grades 3 and 4 xerostomia was minimal.<ItemizedList id="_946" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Only 2 of 68  patients were reported with  grade 3 xerostomia.</ListItem><ListItem>None of the patients had grade 4 xerostomia.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25769204">Petersson F: Nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a review. Semin Diagn Pathol 32 (1): 54-73, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25220842">Ferlay J, Soerjomataram I, Dikshit R, et al.: Cancer incidence and mortality worldwide: sources, methods and major patterns in GLOBOCAN 2012. Int J Cancer 136 (5): E359-86, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="17035381">Chang ET, Adami HO: The enigmatic epidemiology of nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 15 (10): 1765-77, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="31178151">Chen YP, Chan ATC, Le QT, et al.: Nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Lancet 394 (10192): 64-80, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="11756578" MedlineID="21630064">Chien YC, Chen JY, Liu MY, et al.: Serologic markers of Epstein-Barr virus infection and nasopharyngeal carcinoma in Taiwanese men. N Engl J Med 345 (26): 1877-82, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="19116871">Chen L, Gallicchio L, Boyd-Lindsley K, et al.: Alcohol consumption and the risk of nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a systematic review. Nutr Cancer 61 (1): 1-15, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="31759378">Okekpa SI, S M N Mydin RB, Mangantig E, et al.: Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma (NPC) Risk Factors: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of the Association with Lifestyle, Diets, Socioeconomic and Sociodemographic in Asian Region. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev 20 (11): 3505-3514, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25822573">Xie SH, Yu IT, Tse LA, et al.: Tobacco smoking, family history, and the risk of nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a case-referent study in Hong Kong Chinese. Cancer Causes Control 26 (6): 913-21, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="1309196" MedlineID="92072651">Feinmesser R, Miyazaki I, Cheung R, et al.: Diagnosis of nasopharyngeal carcinoma by DNA amplification of tissue obtained by fine-needle aspiration. N Engl J Med 326 (1): 17-21, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Cummings CW, Fredrickson JM, Harker LA, et al.: Otolaryngology - Head and Neck Surgery. Mosby-Year Book, Inc., 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="28721913">Kim KY, Le QT, Yom SS, et al.: Clinical Utility of Epstein-Barr Virus DNA Testing in the Treatment of Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Patients. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 98 (5): 996-1001, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="12">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Laramore GE, ed.: Radiation Therapy of Head and Neck Cancer. Springer-Verlag, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="28792880">Chan KCA, Woo JKS, King A, et al.: Analysis of Plasma Epstein-Barr Virus DNA to Screen for Nasopharyngeal Cancer. N Engl J Med 377 (6): 513-522, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="10096545">Lo YM, Chan LY, Lo KW, et al.: Quantitative analysis of cell-free Epstein-Barr virus DNA in plasma of patients with nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Cancer Res 59 (6): 1188-91, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="17135642">Leung SF, Zee B, Ma BB, et al.: Plasma Epstein-Barr viral deoxyribonucleic acid quantitation complements tumor-node-metastasis staging prognostication in nasopharyngeal carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 24 (34): 5414-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="12727814">Chan KC, Zhang J, Chan AT, et al.: Molecular characterization of circulating EBV DNA in the plasma of nasopharyngeal carcinoma and lymphoma patients. Cancer Res 63 (9): 2028-32, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="29072774">Huang WB, Chan JYW, Liu DL: Human papillomavirus and World Health Organization type III nasopharyngeal carcinoma: Multicenter study from an endemic area in Southern China. Cancer 124 (3): 530-536, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="23938045">Robinson M, Suh YE, Paleri V, et al.: Oncogenic human papillomavirus-associated nasopharyngeal carcinoma: an observational study of correlation with ethnicity, histological subtype and outcome in a UK population. Infect Agent Cancer 8 (1): 30, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="9169804" MedlineID="97313200">Sanguineti G, Geara FB, Garden AS, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx treated by radiotherapy alone: determinants of local and regional control. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 37 (5): 985-96, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="12872347">Leung SF, Chan AT, Zee B, et al.: Pretherapy quantitative measurement of circulating Epstein-Barr virus DNA is predictive of posttherapy distant failure in patients with early-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma of undifferentiated type. Cancer 98 (2): 288-91, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="12419787">Chan AT, Lo YM, Zee B, et al.: Plasma Epstein-Barr virus DNA and residual disease after radiotherapy for undifferentiated nasopharyngeal carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst 94 (21): 1614-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="20222940">Lee CC, Huang TT, Lee MS, et al.: Clinical application of tumor volume in advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma to predict outcome. Radiat Oncol 5: 20, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="7713779">Cooper JS, Fu K, Marks J, et al.: Late effects of radiation therapy in the head and neck region. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 31 (5): 1141-64, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="32596155">McDowell L, Corry J, Ringash J, et al.: Quality of Life, Toxicity and Unmet Needs in Nasopharyngeal Cancer Survivors. Front Oncol 10: 930, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="32426699">Fong R, Ward EC, Rumbach AF: Dysphagia after chemo-radiation for nasopharyngeal cancer: A scoping review. World J Otorhinolaryngol Head Neck Surg 6 (1): 10-24, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="2001556" MedlineID="91159942">Cooper JS, Scott C, Marcial V, et al.: The relationship of nasopharyngeal carcinomas and second independent malignancies based on the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group experience. Cancer 67 (6): 1673-7, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="7836081" MedlineID="95137798">Turner SL, Tiver KW, Boyages SC: Thyroid dysfunction following radiotherapy for head and neck cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 31 (2): 279-83, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="7836099" MedlineID="95137818">Constine LS: What else don't we know about the late effects of radiation in patients treated for head and neck cancer? Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 31 (2): 427-9, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="17145528">Pow EH, Kwong DL, McMillan AS, et al.: Xerostomia and quality of life after intensity-modulated radiotherapy vs. conventional radiotherapy for early-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma: initial report on a randomized controlled clinical trial. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 66 (4): 981-91, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="17971582">Kam MK, Leung SF, Zee B, et al.: Prospective randomized study of intensity-modulated radiotherapy on salivary gland function in early-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma patients. J Clin Oncol 25 (31): 4873-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="33576030">Poon DMC, Kam MKM, Johnson D, et al.: Durability of the parotid-sparing effect of intensity-modulated radiotherapy (IMRT) in early stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma: A 15-year follow-up of a randomized prospective study of IMRT versus two-dimensional radiotherapy. Head Neck 43 (6): 1711-1720, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="19564532">Lee N, Harris J, Garden AS, et al.: Intensity-modulated radiation therapy with or without chemotherapy for nasopharyngeal carcinoma: radiation therapy oncology group phase II trial 0225. J Clin Oncol 27 (22): 3684-90, 2009.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular Classification of Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_231">The World Health Organization (WHO) definition of nasopharyngeal carcinoma is a “carcinoma arising in the nasopharyngeal mucosa that shows light microscopic or ultrastructural evidence of squamous differentiation.” The WHO classification for nasopharyngeal carcinoma has evolved over time, and the 2005 classification is the current version.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> The three versions below are all used, and in particular, the undifferentiated carcinomas that carry the worst prognosis and the greatest sensitivity to chemoradiation are generally classified according to the  1978 definitions.<Reference refidx="4"/>  </Para><Para id="_328">1978 WHO classification:</Para><OrderedList id="_329" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Squamous cell carcinoma.</ListItem><ListItem>	Nonkeratinizing squamous cell carcinoma.</ListItem><ListItem>	Undifferentiated carcinoma (most common subtype).</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_330">1991 WHO classification:</Para><OrderedList id="_331" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>	Squamous cell carcinoma. </ListItem><ListItem>	Nonkeratinizing squamous cell carcinoma.<ItemizedList id="_332" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Differentiated nonkeratinizing carcinoma. </ListItem><ListItem>Undifferentiated carcinoma.
	
</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_333">2005 WHO classification:</Para><OrderedList id="_334" Style="Arabic">	<ListItem>Keratinizing squamous cell carcinoma.</ListItem><ListItem>	Nonkeratinizing carcinoma.<ItemizedList id="_335" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Differentiated nonkeratinizing carcinoma. </ListItem><ListItem>Undifferentiated carcinoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	Basaloid squamous cell carcinoma.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_398">Previous subdivisions of nasopharyngeal carcinoma included lymphoepithelioma, which is now classified as WHO grade III and  characterized by lymphoid infiltrate.<Reference refidx="5"/>  </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20614287">Thompson LD: Update on nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Head Neck Pathol 1 (1): 81-6, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="27146632">Wang HY, Chang YL, To KF, et al.: A new prognostic histopathologic classification of nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Chin J Cancer 35: 41, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="28247232">Stelow EB, Wenig BM: Update From The 4th Edition of the World Health Organization Classification of Head and Neck Tumours: Nasopharynx. Head Neck Pathol 11 (1): 16-22, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="225002">Shanmugaratnam K, Chan SH, de-Thé G, et al.: Histopathology of nasopharyngeal carcinoma: correlations with epidemiology, survival rates and other biological characteristics. Cancer 44 (3): 1029-44, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Shanmugaratnam   K, Sobin  L: Histological Typing of Upper Respiratory Tract Tumours. World Health Organization, 1978. International Histologic Classification of Tumours: No. 19.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_17">Staging systems used  for clinical staging are  based on the best possible estimate
of the extent of disease before treatment.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>    
</Para><Para id="_453">Assessment of the primary
tumor is made on the basis of inspection, palpation, and fiberoptic endoscopic evaluation.  The tumor must be
confirmed histologically, and any other pathologic data obtained on biopsy may
be included.  Evaluation of the function of the cranial nerves is important for tumors of the nasopharynx.  Nodal drainage
areas are examined by careful palpation and radiological evaluation.  The retropharyngeal lymph nodes are the first echelon of drainage.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_399">Information from the following diagnostic
imaging studies may be used in staging:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_400" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Magnetic resonance imaging provides additional information to computed tomography (CT) scanning in the evaluation of skull base invasion and intracranial spread.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem>Positron emission tomography scans combined with CT are helpful in radiation treatment planning for targeted delineation of the primary tumor and  aid in the detection of metastatic nodal involvement and metastatic spread, such as that found in lung or skeletal metastases in patients with advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma.<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18">If the disease relapses, a complete reassessment must be done to select the
appropriate additional therapy.
</Para><SummarySection id="_219"><Title>American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) Stage Groupings and  TNM Definitions</Title><Para id="_203">The AJCC has designated staging by TNM (tumor, node, metastasis)
classification to define nasopharyngeal carcinoma.<Reference refidx="7"/>
</Para><Table id="_337"><Title>Table 1.  Definition of TNM Stage 0<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="12.67%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="27.75%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="59.56%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasopharynx. In: Amin MB, Edge SB,  Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 103–11.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="2">0</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Tis, N0, M0</entry><entry>Tis = Carcinoma <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_338"><Title> Table 2. Definition of TNM Stage I<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="12.98%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="27.14%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="59.87%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasopharynx. In: Amin MB, Edge SB,  Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 103–11.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="2">I</entry><entry MoreRows="2">T1, N0, M0</entry><entry>T1 = Tumor confined to nasopharynx, or extension to oropharynx and/or nasal cavity without parapharyngeal involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_339"><Title>Table 3.  Definition of TNM Stage II<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="13.58%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.27%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="61.14%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis; EBV = Epstein-Barr virus.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasopharynx. In: Amin MB, Edge SB,  Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 103–11.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="10">II</entry><entry MoreRows="4">T0, Tis, T1, N1, M0</entry><entry>T0 = No tumor identified, but EBV-positive cervical node(s) involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Tis = Carcinoma <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T1 = Tumor confined to nasopharynx, or extension to oropharynx and/or nasal cavity without parapharyngeal involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N1 = Unilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s) and/or unilateral or bilateral metastasis in retropharyngeal lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T2, N0, M0</entry><entry>T2 = Tumor with extension to parapharyngeal space, and/or adjacent soft tissue involvement (medial pterygoid, lateral pterygoid, prevertebral muscles).</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T2, N1, M0</entry><entry>T2 = Tumor with extension to parapharyngeal space, and/or adjacent soft tissue involvement (medial pterygoid, lateral pterygoid, prevertebral muscles).</entry></Row><Row><entry>N1 = Unilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s) and/or unilateral or bilateral metastasis in retropharyngeal lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_340"><Title>Table 4.  Definition of TNM Stage III<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="13.17%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.55%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="61.26%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis; EBV = Epstein-Barr virus.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasopharynx. In: Amin MB, Edge SB,  Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 103–11.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="16">III</entry><entry MoreRows="4">T0, Tis, T1, N2, M0</entry><entry>T0 = No tumor identified, but EBV-positive cervical node(s) involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Tis = Carcinoma <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T1 = Tumor confined to nasopharynx, or extension to oropharynx and/or nasal cavity without parapharyngeal involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N2 = Bilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T2, N2, M0</entry><entry>T2 = Tumor with extension to parapharyngeal space, and/or adjacent soft tissue involvement (medial pterygoid, lateral pterygoid, prevertebral muscles).</entry></Row><Row><entry>N2 = Bilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T3, N0, M0</entry><entry>T3 = Tumor with infiltration of bony structures at skull base, cervical vertebra, pterygoid structures, and/or paranasal sinuses.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T3, N1, M0</entry><entry>T3 = Tumor with infiltration of bony structures at skull base, cervical vertebra, pterygoid structures, and/or paranasal sinuses.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N1 = Unilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s) and/or unilateral or bilateral metastasis in retropharyngeal lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T3, N2, M0</entry><entry>T3 = Tumor with infiltration of bony structures at skull base, cervical vertebra, pterygoid structures, and/or paranasal sinuses.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N2 = Bilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_341"><Title>Table 5.  Definition of TNM Stages IVA and IVB<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="13.08%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.91%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="60.99%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis; EBV = Epstein-Barr virus.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasopharynx. In: Amin MB, Edge SB,  Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 103–11.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="17">IVA</entry><entry MoreRows="2">T4, N0, M0</entry><entry>T4 = Tumor with intracranial extension, involvement of cranial nerves, hypopharynx, orbit, parotid gland, and/or extensive soft tissue infiltration beyond the lateral surface of the lateral pterygoid muscle.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T4, N1, M0</entry><entry>T4 = Tumor with intracranial extension, involvement of cranial nerves, hypopharynx, orbit, parotid gland, and/or extensive soft tissue infiltration beyond the lateral surface of the lateral pterygoid muscle.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N1 = Unilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s) and/or unilateral or bilateral metastasis in retropharyngeal lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T4, N2, M0</entry><entry>T4 = Tumor with intracranial extension, involvement of cranial nerves, hypopharynx, orbit, parotid gland, and/or extensive soft tissue infiltration beyond the lateral surface of the lateral pterygoid muscle.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N2 = Bilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="8">Any T, N3, M0</entry><entry>TX = Primary tumor cannot be assessed.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T0 = No tumor identified, but EBV-positive cervical node(s) involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Tis = Carcinoma <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T1 = Tumor confined to nasopharynx, or extension to oropharynx and/or nasal cavity without parapharyngeal involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T2 = Tumor with extension to parapharyngeal space, and/or adjacent soft tissue involvement (medial pterygoid, lateral pterygoid, prevertebral muscles).</entry></Row><Row><entry>T3 = Tumor with infiltration of bony structures at skull base, cervical vertebra, pterygoid structures, and/or paranasal sinuses.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T4 = Tumor with intracranial extension, involvement of cranial nerves, hypopharynx, orbit, parotid gland, and/or extensive soft tissue infiltration beyond the lateral surface of the lateral pterygoid muscle.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N3 = Unilateral or bilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s), &gt;6 cm in greatest dimension, and/or extension below the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="6">IVB</entry><entry MoreRows="6">Any T, Any N, M1</entry><entry>Any T = See Stage IVA above.</entry></Row><Row><entry>NX = Regional lymph nodes cannot be assessed.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N1 =  Unilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s) and/or unilateral or bilateral metastasis in retropharyngeal lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N2 = Bilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s), ≤6 cm in greatest dimension, above the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N3 = Unilateral or bilateral metastasis in cervical lymph node(s), &gt;6 cm in greatest dimension, and/or extension below the caudal border of cricoid cartilage.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M1 = Distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1985736" MedlineID="91091779">Teo PM, Leung SF, Yu P, et al.: A comparison of Ho's, International Union Against Cancer, and American Joint Committee stage classifications for nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Cancer 67 (2): 434-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10096252" MedlineID="99193916">Lee AW, Foo W, Law SC, et al.: Staging of nasopharyngeal carcinoma: from Ho's to the new UICC system. Int J Cancer 84 (2): 179-87, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Laramore GE, ed.: Radiation Therapy of Head and Neck Cancer. Springer-Verlag, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3279242" MedlineID="88155850">Consensus conference. Magnetic resonance imaging. JAMA 259 (14): 2132-8, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16446332">Liu FY, Chang JT, Wang HM, et al.: [18F]fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography is more sensitive than skeletal scintigraphy for detecting bone metastasis in endemic nasopharyngeal carcinoma at initial staging. J Clin Oncol 24 (4): 599-604, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Nasopharynx. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 8th ed. Springer; 2017, pp. 103–11.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><Table id="_912"><Title>Table 6.  Treatment Options for Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Options</entry></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry>Stage I nasopharyngeal carcinoma</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_411" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="6">Stages II, III, and IV nasopharyngeal carcinoma</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_437" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_422" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Concurrent chemoradiation </SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_422" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Neoadjuvant chemotherapy and concurrent chemoradiation</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_422" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Concurrent chemoradiation and adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_422" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Neoadjuvant chemotherapy followed by radiation therapy alone</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_930" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_932" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">Metastatic and recurrent nasopharyngeal carcinoma</entry><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_444" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_446" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef> (for highly selected patients) </entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_448" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy/immunotherapy</SummaryRef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_947"><Title>Fluorouracil Dosing</Title></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000813769_3"><Para id="_sm_CDR0000813769_4">The <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> gene encodes an enzyme that catabolizes pyrimidines and fluoropyrimidines, like capecitabine and fluorouracil. An estimated 1% to 2% of the population has germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName>, which lead to reduced DPD protein function and an accumulation of pyrimidines and fluoropyrimidines in the body.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Patients with the <GeneName>DPYD*2A</GeneName> variant who receive fluoropyrimidines may experience severe, life-threatening toxicities that are sometimes fatal. Many other <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> variants have been identified,  with a range of clinical effects.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Fluoropyrimidine avoidance or a dose reduction of 50% may be recommended based on  the patient's <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> genotype and number of functioning <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> alleles.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> genetic testing costs less than $200, but insurance coverage varies due to  a lack of national guidelines.<Reference refidx="7"/> In addition, testing may delay therapy by 2 weeks, which would not be advisable in urgent situations. This controversial issue requires further evaluation.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="34506675">Sharma BB, Rai K, Blunt H, et al.: Pathogenic DPYD Variants and Treatment-Related Mortality in Patients Receiving Fluoropyrimidine Chemotherapy: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Oncologist 26 (12): 1008-1016, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="27569869">Lam SW, Guchelaar HJ, Boven E: The role of pharmacogenetics in capecitabine efficacy and toxicity. Cancer Treat Rev 50: 9-22, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="33410339">Shakeel F, Fang F, Kwon JW, et al.: Patients carrying DPYD variant alleles have increased risk of severe toxicity and related treatment modifications during fluoropyrimidine chemotherapy. Pharmacogenomics 22 (3): 145-155, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="29152729">Amstutz U, Henricks LM, Offer SM, et al.: Clinical Pharmacogenetics Implementation Consortium (CPIC) Guideline for Dihydropyrimidine Dehydrogenase Genotype and Fluoropyrimidine Dosing: 2017 Update. Clin Pharmacol Ther 103 (2): 210-216, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="30348537">Henricks LM, Lunenburg CATC, de Man FM, et al.: DPYD genotype-guided dose individualisation of fluoropyrimidine therapy in patients with cancer: a prospective safety analysis. Lancet Oncol 19 (11): 1459-1467, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="34996412">Lau-Min KS, Varughese LA, Nelson MN, et al.: Preemptive pharmacogenetic testing to guide chemotherapy dosing in patients with gastrointestinal malignancies: a qualitative study of barriers to implementation. BMC Cancer 22 (1): 47, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="35668003">Brooks GA, Tapp S, Daly AT, et al.: Cost-effectiveness of DPYD Genotyping Prior to Fluoropyrimidine-based Adjuvant Chemotherapy for Colon Cancer. Clin Colorectal Cancer 21 (3): e189-e195, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="36821823">Baker SD, Bates SE, Brooks GA, et al.: DPYD Testing: Time to Put Patient Safety First. J Clin Oncol 41 (15): 2701-2705, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_54"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038905">stage I nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage I Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><SummarySection id="_351"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage I Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_410">Treatment options for stage I nasopharyngeal carcinoma include:</Para><OrderedList id="_411" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_936" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_936"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_938">High-dose radiation therapy with chemotherapy is the initial treatment of nasopharyngeal carcinoma.<Reference refidx="1"/>    High-dose radiation therapy is given to the primary tumor site and prophylactic
radiation therapy is given to the bilateral regional lymph nodes  in the neck.<Reference refidx="2"/> Radiation therapy dose and
field margins are individually tailored to the location and size of the primary
tumor and lymph nodes.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_939">Most tumors are exclusively treated with
external-beam radiation therapy. For some patients, radiation therapy may be
boosted with intracavitary or interstitial implants, or by the use of stereotactic radiosurgery when clinical
expertise is available and the anatomy is suitable.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_54_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_54_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="16377415">Baujat B, Audry H, Bourhis J, et al.: Chemotherapy in locally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: an individual patient data meta-analysis of eight randomized trials and 1753 patients. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 64 (1): 47-56, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="19231110">Xiao WW, Han F, Lu TX, et al.: Treatment outcomes after radiotherapy alone for patients with early-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 74 (4): 1070-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1587746" MedlineID="92267885">Perez CA, Devineni VR, Marcial-Vega V, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx: factors affecting prognosis. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 23 (2): 271-80, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="8330138" MedlineID="93321014">Lee AW, Law SC, Foo W, et al.: Nasopharyngeal carcinoma: local control by megavoltage irradiation. Br J Radiol 66 (786): 528-36, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="9165137" MedlineID="97307795">Geara FB, Sanguineti G, Tucker SL, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx treated by radiotherapy alone: determinants of distant metastasis and survival. Radiother Oncol 43 (1): 53-61, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="9169804" MedlineID="97313200">Sanguineti G, Geara FB, Garden AS, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx treated by radiotherapy alone: determinants of local and regional control. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 37 (5): 985-96, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="1924860" MedlineID="92021574">Itami J, Anzai Y, Nemoto K, et al.: Prognostic factors for local control in nasopharyngeal cancer (NPC): analysis by multivariate proportional hazard models. Radiother Oncol 21 (4): 233-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9626223" MedlineID="98289463">Levendag PC, Schmitz PI, Jansen PP, et al.: Fractionated high-dose-rate brachytherapy in primary carcinoma of the nasopharynx. J Clin Oncol 16 (6): 2213-20, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="10661353" MedlineID="20124969">Teo PM, Leung SF, Lee WY, et al.: Intracavitary brachytherapy significantly enhances local control of early T-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma: the existence of a dose-tumor-control relationship above conventional tumoricidal dose. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 46 (2): 445-58, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="12829140">Le QT, Tate D, Koong A, et al.: Improved local control with stereotactic radiosurgical boost in patients with nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 56 (4): 1046-54, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038908">stage IV nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stages II, III, and IV Nonmetastatic Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><SummarySection id="_365"><Title>Treatment Options for Stages II, III, and IV Nonmetastatic Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_366">Treatment options for stages II, III, and IV nonmetastatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma include:</Para><OrderedList id="_457" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_437" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_422" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Concurrent chemoradiation</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_422" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Neoadjuvant chemotherapy and concurrent chemoradiation</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_422" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Concurrent chemoradiation and adjuvant chemotherapy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_422" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Neoadjuvant chemotherapy followed by radiation therapy alone</SummaryRef>. This option is being studied.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_930" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_932" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_437"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_940">High-dose radiation therapy with chemotherapy is the initial treatment of nasopharyngeal carcinoma.<Reference refidx="2"/>    High-dose radiation therapy is given to the primary tumor site and prophylactic
radiation therapy is given to the bilateral regional lymph nodes  in the neck.<Reference refidx="3"/> Some studies have reported treatment using altered fractionation radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Radiation therapy dose and
field margins are individually tailored to the location and size of the primary
tumor and lymph nodes.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_941">Most tumors are exclusively treated with
external-beam radiation therapy (EBRT). For some patients, radiation therapy may be
boosted with intracavitary or interstitial implants, or by the use of stereotactic radiosurgery when clinical
expertise is available and the anatomy is suitable.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_948">Evidence (radiation therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_949" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>
A multicenter, noninferiority, phase III trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02633202">NCT02633202</ProtocolRef>) evaluated radiation therapy alone versus chemoradiation therapy for patients with low-risk, stage II, T3, N0, M0 (American Joint Committee on Cancer 7th edition staging) nasopharyngeal carcinoma. The study was performed in endemic China, where almost all cases of nasopharyngeal carcinoma are caused by the Epstein-Barr virus (EBV). In this trial, 341 patients were randomly assigned to receive either intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) alone (n = 172) or concurrent chemoradiation therapy (IMRT with cisplatin 100 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> every 3 weeks for three cycles [n = 169]). The primary end point was 3-year failure-free survival (FFS).<Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_950" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 3-year FFS rate was 90.5% in the IMRT-alone group and 91.9% in the concurrent chemoradiation therapy group (difference, −1.4%; one-sided 95% confidence interval [CI], −7.4% to infinity; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> for noninferiority &lt; .001). There were no differences in rates of overall survival (OS), locoregional relapse, or distant metastasis between the two arms.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients in the IMRT-alone group experienced significantly lower grades 3 and 4 toxicity, including hematologic and nonhematologic toxicities (nausea, vomiting, anorexia, weight loss, mucositis). The IMRT-alone group had better quality-of-life scores during radiation therapy.  </ListItem><ListItem>In addition to the trial being conducted in an area where almost all patients with nasopharyngeal carcinoma had cases caused by EBV, all patients had an EBV DNA cut-off of fewer than 4,000 copies/mL to be eligible for entry into the trial. Patients with stage II (T1–2, N1) tumors and nodal disease had to have a nodal size smaller than 3 cm, without extranodal extension, to be eligible for the trial.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_951">This trial shows that radiation therapy alone could be used for limited-stage disease if the EBV titers (which are not usually tested in the United States) show fewer than 4,000 copies/mL. Radiation therapy alone was not previously considered a standard of care, but based on these results, patients with lower-volume disease and a low EBV titer may consider radiation therapy alone.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_422"><Title>Chemoradiation therapy</Title><Para id="_423">Studies and meta-analyses investigating chemoradiation combinations have been reported.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/> Overall, these results report increased survival when chemotherapy is added to radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="31"/></Para><Para id="_952">Evidence (neoadjuvant chemotherapy vs. chemoradiation therapy):</Para><Para id="_953">Data from phase III randomized trials support induction chemotherapy with gemcitabine plus cisplatin before concurrent chemoradiation therapy.<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/></Para><OrderedList id="_954" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A multicenter, randomized, controlled, phase III trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01872962">NCT01872962</ProtocolRef>) compared gemcitabine and cisplatin induction chemotherapy plus concurrent chemoradiation therapy  with concurrent chemoradiation therapy alone. At a median follow-up of 42.7 months, the 3-year recurrence-free survival rate was 85.3% for patients in the induction chemotherapy group and 76.5% for patients in the standard therapy group (stratified hazard ratio [HR] <Subscript>recurrence or death</Subscript>, 0.51; 95% CI, 0.34–0.77; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001).<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] <Para id="_959">In a multicenter phase III trial, patients were randomly assigned to receive either concurrent chemoradiation therapy alone (standard therapy, n = 238) or gemcitabine and cisplatin induction chemotherapy before concurrent chemoradiation therapy (n = 242). With a median follow-up of 69.8 months, patients in the induction chemotherapy group had a significantly higher 5-year OS rate (87.9%) than those in the standard therapy group (78.8%) (HR, 0.51; 95% CI, 0.34–0.78; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .001). The risk of  late toxicities was comparable (grade 3 or higher toxicity, 11.3% vs. 11.4%).<Reference refidx="32"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</Para></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_924">Evidence (chemoradiation therapy plus adjuvant chemotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_925" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Chemoradiation therapy followed by adjuvant chemotherapy was used  in the INT-0099 trial.<Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] <ItemizedList id="_926" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Patients with parapharyngeal extension were originally staged as T3 in the INT-0099 study and are now considered T2 in the current staging. </ListItem><ListItem>The control rate at 3 years was 91.7% in the radiation therapy group (median follow-up period, 34 months) and 100% in the chemoradiation and adjuvant chemotherapy group (median follow-up period, 44 months) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> =.10). The 3-year disease-free survival (DFS) rate was 91.7% in the radiation therapy group and 96.9% in the chemoradiation and adjuvant chemotherapy group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> =.66).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_515">Evidence (combination chemotherapy plus radiation therapy vs.  radiation therapy alone):</Para><OrderedList id="_516" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Three randomized
prospective trials compared combination chemotherapy (i.e., cisplatin, epirubicin,
and bleomycin or cisplatin plus fluorouracil [5-FU] infusion) plus radiation therapy with
radiation therapy alone.<Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]  <ItemizedList id="_517" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Although DFS was improved in the chemotherapy group,
for both groups, improvement in OS was reported only from the
Intergroup trial  in which chemotherapy with cisplatin was  given concurrently with radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="17"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_518">Evidence (chemoradiation therapy using carboplatin vs. cisplatin):</Para><OrderedList id="_519" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>A study of 1,355 patients compared radiation therapy given concurrently with carboplatin or cisplatin that was administered  with a 96-hour infusion of 5-FU monthly for three cycles.<Reference refidx="37"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_520" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 3-year DFS rate was 63.4% for patients in the cisplatin arm and 60.9% for patients in  the carboplatin arm (HR, 0.70; 95% CI, 0.50–0.98; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .961).  </ListItem><ListItem>OS rates were 77% for patients in the cisplatin arm and 79% for patients in the carboplatin arm (HR, 0.83; 95% CI, 0.63–1.010; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .988). </ListItem><ListItem>Toxicity to kidneys and red blood cell count was greater in patients in the cisplatin group.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_930"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_931">Neck dissection may be indicated for patients with persistent or recurrent lymph nodes if the
primary tumor site is controlled.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_932"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_934">Clinical trials for patients with advanced tumors to evaluate the use of chemotherapy before
radiation therapy, concurrent with radiation therapy, or as adjuvant therapy
after radiation therapy should be considered.<Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/><Reference refidx="41"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_70_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_70_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="32721816">Wang Q, Xu G, Xia Y, et al.: Comparison of induction chemotherapy plus concurrent chemoradiotherapy and induction chemotherapy plus radiotherapy in locally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Oral Oncol 111: 104925, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16377415">Baujat B, Audry H, Bourhis J, et al.: Chemotherapy in locally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: an individual patient data meta-analysis of eight randomized trials and 1753 patients. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 64 (1): 47-56, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19231110">Xiao WW, Han F, Lu TX, et al.: Treatment outcomes after radiotherapy alone for patients with early-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 74 (4): 1070-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1571905" MedlineID="92240564">Johnson CR, Schmidt-Ullrich RK, Wazer DE: Concomitant boost technique using accelerated superfractionated radiation therapy for advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. Cancer 69 (11): 2749-54, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="19451314">Chen CY, Han F, Zhao C, et al.: Treatment results and late complications of 556 patients with locally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma treated with radiotherapy alone. Br J Radiol 82 (978): 452-8, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="1587746" MedlineID="92267885">Perez CA, Devineni VR, Marcial-Vega V, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx: factors affecting prognosis. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 23 (2): 271-80, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="8330138" MedlineID="93321014">Lee AW, Law SC, Foo W, et al.: Nasopharyngeal carcinoma: local control by megavoltage irradiation. Br J Radiol 66 (786): 528-36, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9165137" MedlineID="97307795">Geara FB, Sanguineti G, Tucker SL, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx treated by radiotherapy alone: determinants of distant metastasis and survival. Radiother Oncol 43 (1): 53-61, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9169804" MedlineID="97313200">Sanguineti G, Geara FB, Garden AS, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx treated by radiotherapy alone: determinants of local and regional control. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 37 (5): 985-96, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="1924860" MedlineID="92021574">Itami J, Anzai Y, Nemoto K, et al.: Prognostic factors for local control in nasopharyngeal cancer (NPC): analysis by multivariate proportional hazard models. Radiother Oncol 21 (4): 233-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="9626223" MedlineID="98289463">Levendag PC, Schmitz PI, Jansen PP, et al.: Fractionated high-dose-rate brachytherapy in primary carcinoma of the nasopharynx. J Clin Oncol 16 (6): 2213-20, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="10661353" MedlineID="20124969">Teo PM, Leung SF, Lee WY, et al.: Intracavitary brachytherapy significantly enhances local control of early T-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma: the existence of a dose-tumor-control relationship above conventional tumoricidal dose. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 46 (2): 445-58, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="12829140">Le QT, Tate D, Koong A, et al.: Improved local control with stereotactic radiosurgical boost in patients with nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 56 (4): 1046-54, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="35997729">Tang LL, Guo R, Zhang N, et al.: Effect of Radiotherapy Alone vs Radiotherapy With Concurrent Chemoradiotherapy on Survival Without Disease Relapse in Patients With Low-risk Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 328 (8): 728-736, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="10811668" MedlineID="20271992">Cheng SH, Tsai SY, Yen KL, et al.: Concomitant radiotherapy and chemotherapy for early-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 18 (10): 2040-5, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="9552031" MedlineID="98211757">Al-Sarraf M, LeBlanc M, Giri PG, et al.: Chemoradiotherapy versus radiotherapy in patients with advanced nasopharyngeal cancer: phase III randomized Intergroup study 0099. J Clin Oncol 16 (4): 1310-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="10030248" MedlineID="99153319">Teo PM, Chan AT, Lee WY, et al.: Enhancement of local control in locally advanced node-positive nasopharyngeal carcinoma by adjunctive chemotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 43 (2): 261-71, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="11956263" MedlineID="21953228">Chan AT, Teo PM, Ngan RK, et al.: Concurrent chemotherapy-radiotherapy compared with radiotherapy alone in locoregionally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: progression-free survival analysis of a phase III randomized trial. J Clin Oncol 20 (8): 2038-44, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="12040275" MedlineID="22034882">Huncharek M, Kupelnick B: Combined chemoradiation versus radiation therapy alone in locally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: results of a meta-analysis of 1,528 patients from six randomized trials. Am J Clin Oncol 25 (3): 219-23, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="12586799" MedlineID="22474353">Lin JC, Jan JS, Hsu CY, et al.: Phase III study of concurrent chemoradiotherapy versus radiotherapy alone for advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: positive effect on overall and progression-free survival. J Clin Oncol 21 (4): 631-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="15657403">Chua DT, Ma J, Sham JS, et al.: Long-term survival after cisplatin-based induction chemotherapy and radiotherapy for nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a pooled data analysis of two phase III trials. J Clin Oncol 23 (6): 1118-24, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="16170180">Wee J, Tan EH, Tai BC, et al.: Randomized trial of radiotherapy versus concurrent chemoradiotherapy followed by adjuvant chemotherapy in patients with American Joint Committee on Cancer/International Union against cancer stage III and IV nasopharyngeal cancer of the endemic variety. J Clin Oncol 23 (27): 6730-8, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="16230677">Zhang L, Zhao C, Peng PJ, et al.: Phase III study comparing standard radiotherapy with or without weekly oxaliplatin in treatment of locoregionally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: preliminary results. J Clin Oncol 23 (33): 8461-8, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="17054200">Baujat B, Audry H, Bourhis J, et al.: Chemotherapy as an adjunct to radiotherapy in locally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (4): CD004329, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="18472356">Chen Y, Liu MZ, Liang SB, et al.: Preliminary results of a prospective randomized trial comparing concurrent chemoradiotherapy plus adjuvant chemotherapy with radiotherapy alone in patients with locoregionally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma in endemic regions of china. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 71 (5): 1356-64, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="20634482">Lee AW, Tung SY, Chua DT, et al.: Randomized trial of radiotherapy plus concurrent-adjuvant chemotherapy vs radiotherapy alone for regionally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst 102 (15): 1188-98, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="20971520">Lee AW, Tung SY, Chan AT, et al.: A randomized trial on addition of concurrent-adjuvant chemotherapy and/or accelerated fractionation for locally-advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Radiother Oncol 98 (1): 15-22, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="21112774">Lee AW, Tung SY, Ngan RK, et al.: Factors contributing to the efficacy of concurrent-adjuvant chemotherapy for locoregionally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: combined analyses of NPC-9901 and NPC-9902 Trials. Eur J Cancer 47 (5): 656-66, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="31150573">Zhang Y, Chen L, Hu GQ, et al.: Gemcitabine and Cisplatin Induction Chemotherapy in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma. N Engl J Med 381 (12): 1124-1135, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="34935776">Blanchard P, Lee AWM, Carmel A, et al.: Meta-analysis of chemotherapy in nasopharynx carcinoma (MAC-NPC): An update on 26 trials and 7080 patients. Clin Transl Radiat Oncol 32: 59-68, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="35709465">Zhang Y, Chen L, Hu GQ, et al.: Final Overall Survival Analysis of Gemcitabine and Cisplatin Induction Chemotherapy in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma: A Multicenter, Randomized Phase III Trial. J Clin Oncol 40 (22): 2420-2425, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="27686945">Sun Y, Li WF, Chen NY, et al.: Induction chemotherapy plus concurrent chemoradiotherapy versus concurrent chemoradiotherapy alone in locoregionally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a phase 3, multicentre, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol 17 (11): 1509-1520, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="31425966">Yang Q, Cao SM, Guo L, et al.: Induction chemotherapy followed by concurrent chemoradiotherapy versus concurrent chemoradiotherapy alone in locoregionally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: long-term results of a phase III multicentre randomised controlled trial. Eur J Cancer 119: 87-96, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="8655368" MedlineID="96272184">Preliminary results of a randomized trial comparing neoadjuvant chemotherapy (cisplatin, epirubicin, bleomycin) plus radiotherapy vs. radiotherapy alone in stage IV(&gt; or = N2, M0) undifferentiated nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a positive effect on progression-free survival. International Nasopharynx Cancer Study Group. VUMCA I trial. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 35 (3): 463-9, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="16192584">Lee AW, Lau WH, Tung SY, et al.: Preliminary results of a randomized study on therapeutic gain by concurrent chemotherapy for regionally-advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: NPC-9901 Trial by the Hong Kong Nasopharyngeal Cancer Study Group. J Clin Oncol 23 (28): 6966-75, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="17467265">Chitapanarux I, Lorvidhaya V, Kamnerdsupaphon P, et al.: Chemoradiation comparing cisplatin versus carboplatin in locally advanced nasopharyngeal cancer: randomised, non-inferiority, open trial. Eur J Cancer 43 (9): 1399-406, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="8410119" MedlineID="94015211">Dimery IW, Peters LJ, Goepfert H, et al.: Effectiveness of combined induction chemotherapy and radiotherapy in advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 11 (10): 1919-28, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="7558945" MedlineID="96027768">Chan AT, Teo PM, Leung TW, et al.: A prospective randomized study of chemotherapy adjunctive to definitive radiotherapy in advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 33 (3): 569-77, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="8609658" MedlineID="96199879">Merlano M, Benasso M, Corvò R, et al.: Five-year update of a randomized trial of alternating radiotherapy and chemotherapy compared with radiotherapy alone in treatment of unresectable squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. J Natl Cancer Inst 88 (9): 583-9, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="10735893" MedlineID="20200498">Jeremic B, Shibamoto Y, Milicic B, et al.: Hyperfractionated radiation therapy with or without concurrent low-dose daily cisplatin in locally advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck: a prospective randomized trial. J Clin Oncol 18 (7): 1458-64, 2000.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_80"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038909">recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic and Recurrent Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><SummarySection id="_374"><Title>Treatment Options for Metastatic and Recurrent Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</Title><Para id="_375">Treatment options for metastatic and recurrent nasopharyngeal carcinoma include:</Para><OrderedList id="_458" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_444" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_446" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef> (for highly selected patients).</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_448" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy/immunotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_444"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_942">High-dose radiation therapy with chemotherapy is the initial treatment of patients with nasopharyngeal carcinoma for the primary tumor site and the neck.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Selected patients with local recurrence may be retreated with moderate-dose external-beam
radiation therapy (EBRT) using intensity-modulated radiation therapy, stereotactic radiation therapy, or intracavitary or interstitial
radiation to the site of recurrence.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>; <Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] Radiation therapy dose and
field margins are individually tailored to the location and size of the primary
tumor and lymph nodes.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_943">Most tumors are treated with
EBRT exclusively. For some patients, radiation therapy may be
boosted with intracavitary or interstitial implants or by the use of stereotactic radiosurgery when clinical
expertise is available and the anatomy is suitable.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_446"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_447">In highly selected patients, surgical resection of locally recurrent lesions may be
considered.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_448"><Title>Chemotherapy/Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_449">If a patient has metastatic disease or local recurrence that is no longer
amenable to surgery or radiation therapy, chemotherapy or immunotherapy may be considered.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_450">Evidence (chemotherapy/immunotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_451" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>The international, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, phase III <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03581786">JUPITOR-02</ProtocolRef> study (NCT03581786) was conducted in nasopharyngeal carcinoma–endemic regions, including mainland China, Taiwan, and Singapore. The trial randomly assigned 289 patients to receive either toripalimab, a humanized IgG4K monoclonal antibody against human programmed death 1 (PD-1),  (240 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) or placebo in combination with gemcitabine and cisplatin for up to six cycles. Patients also received maintenance therapy with toripalimab or placebo until disease progression, intolerable toxicity, or completion of 2 years of treatment. The primary end point was progression-free survival (PFS) as assessed by a blinded independent central review. Secondary end points included objective response rate, overall survival (OS), PFS as assessed by an investigator, duration of response, and safety. The median survival follow-up was 36 months.<Reference refidx="21"/><ItemizedList id="_963" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The median OS was not reached  in the toripalimab group (95% confidence interval [CI], 38.7 months–not estimable) and was 33.7 months (95% CI, 27.0–44.2) in the placebo group (hazard ratio [HR], 0.63; 95% CI, 0.45–0.89; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0083).<Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>PFS was significantly longer in the toripalimab arm compared with the placebo arm, with a median PFS of 21.4 months in the toripalimab group versus 8.2 months in the placebo group (HR, 0.52; 95% CI, 0.37–0.73). </ListItem><ListItem>	Grade 3 or higher immune-related adverse events occurred in 9.6% of patients in the toripalimab group. Treatment discontinuation occurred in 11.6% of patients in the toripalimab group and 4.9% of patients in the placebo group.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A multicenter, randomized, open-label, phase III trial included patients with recurrent or metastatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma recruited from 22 hospitals in China. Patients were randomly assigned in a 1:1 ratio to receive either gemcitabine (1 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> intravenously [IV] on days 1 and 8) and cisplatin (80 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> IV on day 1), or fluorouracil ([5-FU] 4 g/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> in continuous IV infusion over 96 h) and cisplatin (80 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> IV on day 1) once every 3 weeks for a maximum of six cycles.<Reference refidx="22"/> Of the 362 patients, 181 were assigned to the gemcitabine-plus-cisplatin group and 181 to the 5-FU-plus-cisplatin group.<ItemizedList id="_452" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The median follow-up time for PFS was 19.4 months (interquartile range [IQR], 12.1–35.6). The median PFS was 7.0 months (range, 4.4–10.9) in the gemcitabine group and 5.6 months (range, 3.0–7.0) in the 5-FU group (HR, 0.55; 95% CI,  0.44–0.68; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]  </ListItem><ListItem>There were significant differences in the incidences of the following grade 3 or 4 treatment-related adverse events: <ItemizedList id="_494" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Leukopenia (52 [29%] in the gemcitabine group vs.15 [9%] in the 5-FU group; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).</ListItem><ListItem>Neutropenia (41 [23%] in the gemcitabine group vs. 23 [13%] in the 5-FU group; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0251).</ListItem><ListItem>Thrombocytopenia (24 [13%] in the gemcitabine group vs. 3 [2%] in the 5-FU group; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0007).</ListItem><ListItem>Mucosal inflammation (0 in the gemcitabine group vs. 25 [14%] in the 5-FU group; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001). </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Serious treatment-related adverse events occurred in seven patients (4%) in the gemcitabine group and ten patients (6%) in the 5-FU group.</ListItem><ListItem>Six patients (3%) in the gemcitabine group and 14 patients (8%) in the 5-FU group discontinued treatment because of drug-related adverse events. </ListItem><ListItem>No treatment-related deaths occurred in either group.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02915432">POLARIS-02</ProtocolRef> (NCT02915432) was a phase II, open-label, multicenter, single-arm trial in China that enrolled 190 patients with recurrent or metastatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma.  Patients received toripalimab (3 mg/kg) once every 2 weeks until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients had received prior platinum-based chemotherapy or had disease progression within 6 months of completion of platinum-based chemotherapy given as neoadjuvant, adjuvant, or definitive chemoradiation therapy for locally advanced disease. The primary end point was objective response rate. The secondary end points included safety, duration of response, PFS, and OS.<Reference refidx="23"/> <ItemizedList id="_964" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	The objective response rate was  20.5%, with a median duration of response  of 12.8 months, a median PFS of 1.9 months, and a median OS of 17.4 months.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_965">The 	U.S. Food and Drug Administration has approved toripalimab with cisplatin and gemcitabine as first-line treatment for patients with metastatic or recurrent locally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma.  It is also approved as a single agent for adults with recurrent unresectable or metastatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma with disease progression during or after platinum-containing therapy.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_80_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_80_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="16377415">Baujat B, Audry H, Bourhis J, et al.: Chemotherapy in locally advanced nasopharyngeal carcinoma: an individual patient data meta-analysis of eight randomized trials and 1753 patients. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 64 (1): 47-56, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="4051112" MedlineID="86023387">Vikram B, Strong EW, Shah JP, et al.: Intraoperative radiotherapy in patients with recurrent head and neck cancer. Am J Surg 150 (4): 485-7, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19467802">Koutcher L, Lee N, Zelefsky M, et al.: Reirradiation of locally recurrent nasopharynx cancer with external beam radiotherapy with or without brachytherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 76 (1): 130-7, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15122654">Lu JJ, Shakespeare TP, Tan LK, et al.: Adjuvant fractionated high-dose-rate intracavitary brachytherapy after external beam radiotherapy in Tl and T2 nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Head Neck 26 (5): 389-95, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="10571198">Tate DJ, Adler JR, Chang SD, et al.: Stereotactic radiosurgical boost following radiotherapy in primary nasopharyngeal carcinoma: impact on local control. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 45 (4): 915-21, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="12694836">Chua DT, Sham JS, Kwong PW, et al.: Linear accelerator-based stereotactic radiosurgery for limited, locally persistent, and recurrent nasopharyngeal carcinoma: efficacy and complications. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 56 (1): 177-83, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12203799">Pai PC, Chuang CC, Wei KC, et al.: Stereotactic radiosurgery for locally recurrent nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Head Neck 24 (8): 748-53, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11516866">Xiao J, Xu G, Miao Y: Fractionated stereotactic radiosurgery for 50 patients with recurrent or residual nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 51 (1): 164-70, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="1587746" MedlineID="92267885">Perez CA, Devineni VR, Marcial-Vega V, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx: factors affecting prognosis. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 23 (2): 271-80, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8330138" MedlineID="93321014">Lee AW, Law SC, Foo W, et al.: Nasopharyngeal carcinoma: local control by megavoltage irradiation. Br J Radiol 66 (786): 528-36, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="9165137" MedlineID="97307795">Geara FB, Sanguineti G, Tucker SL, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx treated by radiotherapy alone: determinants of distant metastasis and survival. Radiother Oncol 43 (1): 53-61, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="9169804" MedlineID="97313200">Sanguineti G, Geara FB, Garden AS, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasopharynx treated by radiotherapy alone: determinants of local and regional control. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 37 (5): 985-96, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="1924860" MedlineID="92021574">Itami J, Anzai Y, Nemoto K, et al.: Prognostic factors for local control in nasopharyngeal cancer (NPC): analysis by multivariate proportional hazard models. Radiother Oncol 21 (4): 233-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="9626223" MedlineID="98289463">Levendag PC, Schmitz PI, Jansen PP, et al.: Fractionated high-dose-rate brachytherapy in primary carcinoma of the nasopharynx. J Clin Oncol 16 (6): 2213-20, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="10661353" MedlineID="20124969">Teo PM, Leung SF, Lee WY, et al.: Intracavitary brachytherapy significantly enhances local control of early T-stage nasopharyngeal carcinoma: the existence of a dose-tumor-control relationship above conventional tumoricidal dose. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 46 (2): 445-58, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="12829140">Le QT, Tate D, Koong A, et al.: Improved local control with stereotactic radiosurgical boost in patients with nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 56 (4): 1046-54, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="3278391" MedlineID="88145720">Al-Sarraf M: Head and neck cancer: chemotherapy concepts. Semin Oncol 15 (1): 70-85, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="1732427" MedlineID="92121936">Jacobs C, Lyman G, Velez-García E, et al.: A phase III randomized study comparing cisplatin and fluorouracil as single agents and in combination for advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. J Clin Oncol 10 (2): 257-63, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="11865813" MedlineID="21851883">Foo KF, Tan EH, Leong SS, et al.: Gemcitabine in metastatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma of the undifferentiated type. Ann Oncol 13 (1): 150-6, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="38015220">Mai HQ, Chen QY, Chen D, et al.: Toripalimab Plus Chemotherapy for Recurrent or Metastatic Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma: The JUPITER-02 Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 330 (20): 1961-1970, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="27567279">Zhang L, Huang Y, Hong S, et al.: Gemcitabine plus cisplatin versus fluorouracil plus cisplatin in recurrent or metastatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a multicentre, randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet 388 (10054): 1883-1892, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="33492986">Wang FH, Wei XL, Feng J, et al.: Efficacy, Safety, and Correlative Biomarkers of Toripalimab in Previously Treated Recurrent or Metastatic Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma: A Phase II Clinical Trial (POLARIS-02). J Clin Oncol 39 (7): 704-712, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_100"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/14/2025)</Title><Para id="_101">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_969">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of adult nasopharyngeal carcinoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Andrea Bonetti, MD (Pederzoli Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Minh Tam Truong, MD (Boston University Medical Center)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389193]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-05-14</DateLastModified></Summary>
