<Summary id="CDR0000062914" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Kaposi sarcoma treatment depends upon the type and can include curettage and desiccation, radiation therapy, surgery, and sometimes chemotherapy. Get detailed information about the diagnosis and treatment of newly diagnosed and recurrent Kaposi sarcoma in this summary for clinicians. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Kaposi Sarcoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/patient/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Kaposi Sarcoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038811">Kaposi sarcoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_144">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of Kaposi sarcoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_145">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Kaposi sarcoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Kaposi Sarcoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Kaposi Sarcoma Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Kaposi Sarcoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038811">Kaposi sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>Epidemiology</Title><Para id="_2">Kaposi sarcoma (KS) was first described in 1872 by the Hungarian
dermatologist, Moritz Kaposi.  From that time until the HIV and AIDS epidemic, KS remained a rare tumor.  Classic KS is most commonly seen in Europe and North America in older men of Italian
or Eastern European Jewish ancestry,<Reference refidx="1"/>  and endemic KS is most commonly seen in sub-Saharan Africa. The disseminated, fulminant form of KS associated with HIV disease is
referred to as AIDS-associated KS to distinguish it from classic and
endemic KS. Transplant-related KS (also sometimes  called iatrogenic KS) is seen in patients receiving chronic immunosuppression therapy, such as after organ transplant.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><Title>Histopathology</Title><Para id="_99">Although
the histopathology of the different types of KS is essentially
identical, the clinical manifestations and course of the
disease differ dramatically.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Human herpesvirus 8
(HHV8), also known as Kaposi sarcoma-associated herpesvirus, was identified
in KS tissue biopsies from almost all patients with classic,
endemic, AIDS-associated, and transplant-related KS but was absent from noninvolved
tissue.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Classic Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_4">Classic KS is considered a rare disease. It occurs more often in men, at a ratio
of approximately 10 to 15 men to 1 woman.  In North American and European populations,
the usual age at onset is between 50 and 70 years.  Classic KS tumors
usually present with one or more asymptomatic red, purple, or brown patches,
plaques, or nodular skin lesions.  The disease is often limited to single or
multiple lesions usually localized to one or both lower extremities, especially
involving the ankles and soles.  
</Para><Para id="_100">Classic KS most commonly runs a
relatively benign, indolent course for 10 to 15 years or more, with slow
enlargement of the original tumors and the gradual development of additional
lesions.  Venous stasis and lymphedema of the involved lower extremity are
frequent complications.  In long-standing cases, systemic lesions can develop
along the gastrointestinal tract, in lymph nodes, and in other organs.  The
visceral lesions are generally asymptomatic and are most often discovered only
at autopsy, though clinically, gastrointestinal bleeding can occur.  As many as 33% of patients with classic KS develop a second primary malignancy,
which is most often non-Hodgkin lymphoma.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_211"><Title>Endemic Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_212">Endemic KS refers to KS diagnosed in patients, typically children and younger adults, living in sub-Saharan Africa. This classification was based on several reports from the 1950s of KS in this younger HIV-negative cohort in human herpesvirus–endemic African countries. Prior to the AIDS epidemic, the estimated incidence for endemic KS was highest (&gt;6 per 1,000 person-years) in Uganda, Tanzania, Cameroon, and Congo. The etiology behind endemic KS is unclear but may possibly be related to saliva-sharing practices, chronic infection, and malnutrition.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para><Para id="_213">The clinical presentation of endemic KS varies and differs between children and adults. Whereas adults present with disease that resembles classic KS, children can have more aggressive disease, including diffuse lymphadenopathy, significant lymphedema, and visceral dissemination.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>AIDS-Associated Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_11">  The use of antiretroviral therapy for patients with AIDS-associated KS has been associated with a sustained and substantial decline in KS incidence in multiple large cohorts.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> Antiretroviral therapy has delayed or
prevented the emergence of drug-resistant HIV strains, profoundly decreased viral
load, led to increased survival, and lessened the risk of opportunistic
infections.<Reference refidx="8"/> KS can still appear during antiretroviral therapy with complete suppression of HIV; most cases in the United States occur in patients with  high CD4 counts receiving ongoing antiretroviral therapy.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_101">The disease often progresses in an orderly fashion from a few localized or widespread mucocutaneous lesions that may involve the skin, oral mucosa, and lymph
nodes to more numerous lesions and generalized skin disease that involves visceral organs, such as the gastrointestinal tract, lung, liver, and
spleen.  Most patients with HIV disease who present with mucocutaneous
KS lesions feel healthy and are usually free of systemic symptoms, as
compared with HIV   patients who first develop an opportunistic
infection.  AIDS-associated KS presents at sites that are much more
varied than those seen in other types of this neoplasm.  While most patients present with skin
disease, KS involvement of lymph nodes or the gastrointestinal tract may
occasionally precede the appearance of the cutaneous lesions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_214"><Title>Transplant-Related Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_215">Transplant-related KS (also called iatrogenic KS) is diagnosed in patients who are therapeutically immunosuppressed, such as after an organ transplant. In fact, solid-organ transplant recipients are 200-fold more likely to develop KS than the general population. Risk factors include male sex, older age, higher levels of immune suppression, and living in HHV8-endemic areas.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_216">Transplant-related KS typically yields cutaneous lesions, though mucosal and visceral disease can occur. The lesions commonly occur within the first several months of immunosuppression therapy and regress with changes or reductions in immunosuppression.<Reference refidx="3"/>       </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="23806158">Ruocco E, Ruocco V, Tornesello ML, et al.: Kaposi's sarcoma: etiology and pathogenesis, inducing factors, causal associations, and treatments: facts and controversies. Clin Dermatol 31 (4): 413-422, 2013 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21377267">Uldrick TS, Whitby D: Update on KSHV epidemiology, Kaposi Sarcoma pathogenesis, and treatment of Kaposi Sarcoma. Cancer Lett 305 (2): 150-62, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="30705286">Cesarman E, Damania B, Krown SE, et al.: Kaposi sarcoma. Nat Rev Dis Primers 5 (1): 9, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6249516" MedlineID="80244571">Safai B, Good RA: Kaposi's sarcoma: a review and recent developments. Clin Bull 10 (2): 62-9, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="12853764">Portsmouth S, Stebbing J, Gill J, et al.: A comparison of regimens based on non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors or protease inhibitors in preventing Kaposi's sarcoma. AIDS 17 (11): F17-22, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12455069">Carrieri MP, Pradier C, Piselli P, et al.: Reduced incidence of Kaposi's sarcoma and of systemic non-hodgkin's lymphoma in HIV-infected individuals treated with highly active antiretroviral therapy. Int J Cancer 103 (1): 142-4, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="16849755">Grabar S, Abraham B, Mahamat A, et al.: Differential impact of combination antiretroviral therapy in preventing Kaposi's sarcoma with and without visceral involvement. J Clin Oncol 24 (21): 3408-14, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="20442214">Lodi S, Guiguet M, Costagliola D, et al.: Kaposi sarcoma incidence and survival among HIV-infected homosexual men after HIV seroconversion. J Natl Cancer Inst 102 (11): 784-92, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="27507879">Yanik EL, Achenbach CJ, Gopal S, et al.: Changes in Clinical Context for Kaposi's Sarcoma and Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma Among People With HIV Infection in the United States. J Clin Oncol 34 (27): 3276-83, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038811">Kaposi sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information and Response Evaluation for Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_217"><Title>Staging</Title><Para id="_218">The staging evaluation of patients with classic Kaposi sarcoma (KS) should be
individualized.  The advanced age of most patients, localized nature
of the tumor, rarity of visceral involvement, and usually indolent course of
the disease should temper the extent of the evaluation.  A careful examination
of the skin and lymph nodes is sufficient in most cases.  </Para><Para id="_219">For the rare 
patient with a rapidly progressive tumor or signs or symptoms of visceral
involvement, appropriate evaluation is indicated. No universally
accepted classification is available for AIDS-associated KS.  Staging schemes that incorporate laboratory parameters as well as clinical features have been proposed.  Since
most patients with AIDS-associated KS do not die of the disease, factors besides tumor burden are apparently involved in survival.
</Para><Para id="_220">The conventions used to stage KS and the methods used to evaluate the benefits
of KS treatment continue to evolve because of changes in
the treatment of HIV and in recognition of deficiencies in standard tumor
assessment.  The clinical course of KS, the selection of treatment, and
the response to treatment are heavily influenced by the degree of underlying immune
dysfunction and opportunistic infections.
</Para><Para id="_221">The AIDS Clinical Trials Group (ACTG) Oncology Committee has published criteria
for the evaluation of AIDS-associated KS.<Reference refidx="1"/>  The staging system incorporates
measures of extent of disease, severity of immunodeficiency, and presence of
systemic symptoms.  As shown in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_223" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef> below, the ACTG criteria categorize the extent of
the tumor as localized or disseminated, the CD4 cell number as high or low, and
systemic illness as absent or present.  </Para><Para id="_222">A subsequent prospective analysis of
294 patients entered on ACTG trials for KS between 1989 and 1995 showed that
each of the tumor (T), immune system (I), and systemic illness (S) variables was
independently associated with survival.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Multivariate analysis showed that
immune system impairment was the most important single predictor of survival. 
In patients with relatively high CD4 counts, tumor stage was predictive.  A CD4
count of 150 cells/µL may be a better discriminator than the
published cutoff of 200 cells/µL.  A study is under way to
determine if quantifying viral load adds predictive value.  None of the previous studies were conducted at a time when antiretroviral therapy was readily available.  The impact of antiretroviral therapy on
survival in KS requires continued assessment.
</Para><Table id="_223">
     <Title>Table 1.  AIDS Clinical Trials Group (ACTG) Staging Classification</Title>
      <TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="15.06%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="39.90%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="45.03%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center" RowSep="0">Variable</entry><entry Align="Center" RowSep="0">Good Risk (0) </entry><entry Align="Center" RowSep="0">Poor Risk (1) </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">KS = Kaposi sarcoma; OI = opportunistic infection.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Minimal oral disease is non-nodular KS confined to the palate.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>"B” symptoms are unexplained fever, night sweats, &gt;10%
  involuntary weight loss, or diarrhea persisting &gt;2 weeks.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry/><entry Align="Center"><Strong>(Any of the following)</Strong></entry><entry Align="Center"><Strong>(Any of the following)</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Tumor (T)</entry><entry MoreRows="3">Confined to skin             
                       and/or lymph nodes          
                       and/or minimal oral        
                       disease<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry><entry>Tumor-associated edema or ulceration  </entry></Row><Row><entry>Extensive oral KS   </entry></Row><Row><entry>Gastrointestinal KS</entry></Row><Row><entry>KS in other non-nodal
                                                    viscera</entry></Row><Row><entry>Immune system (I)</entry><entry>CD4 cells ≥200/µL </entry><entry>CD4 cells &lt;200/µL</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">Systemic illness (S)</entry><entry>No history of OIs or          
                       thrush                       
                       </entry><entry>History of OIs and/or thrush   </entry></Row><Row><entry>No “B” symptoms<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>“B” symptoms  present  </entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="1">Performance status         
                       ≥70 (Karnofsky)          
</entry><entry>Performance status
                                                    &lt;70</entry></Row><Row><entry>Other HIV-related
                                                    illness (e.g.,
                                                    neurological disease
                                                    or lymphoma)</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_224"><Title>Response Evaluation</Title><Para id="_225">The ACTG proposed a unified treatment response evaluation system for AIDS-related KS for clinical practice and research.<Reference refidx="1"/>   After appropriate clinical examination and relevant interval imaging or endoscopy, patients are characterized as having complete response (CR), partial response (PR), stable disease (SD), or progressive disease (PD), based on the following criteria:</Para><ItemizedList id="_226" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	<Strong>CR:</Strong> No detectable residual disease and no tumor-related edema for at least 4 weeks. </ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong>PR:</Strong> No new mucocutaneous lesions, visceral disease, or worsening tumor-related edema. Existing sites show a 50% reduction in (1) the number of lesions, (2) the form of lesions (i.e. flattening of raised lesions), and/or (3) the sum of the products of the largest perpendicular diameters of five measurable lesions. If residual tumor-related edema is present despite meeting CR criteria, the response is still characterized as a PR.</ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong>PD:</Strong> Increase of  more than 25% in (1) the size of existing lesions and/or (2) the number of existing lesions that have more nodular or plaque-like form, or the development of new sites of disease.</ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong>SD:</Strong> No PR, CR, or PD.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2671281" MedlineID="89361553">Krown SE, Metroka C, Wernz JC: Kaposi's sarcoma in the acquired immune deficiency syndrome: a proposal for uniform evaluation, response, and staging criteria. AIDS Clinical Trials Group Oncology Committee. J Clin Oncol 7 (9): 1201-7, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9294471" MedlineID="97440163">Krown SE, Testa MA, Huang J: AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma: prospective validation of the AIDS Clinical Trials Group staging classification. AIDS Clinical Trials Group Oncology Committee. J Clin Oncol 15 (9): 3085-92, 1997.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_21"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039073">classic Kaposi sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Classic and Endemic Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_22">Classic Kaposi sarcoma (KS), as well as endemic KS in adult patients, is usually limited to the skin and has an indolent
course.   Thus, management for both is typically similar. Patients are predisposed to develop a
second primary malignancy, and the treating physician should consider this
factor when arranging a schedule of follow-up treatment for the patient.
</Para><SummarySection id="_227"><Title>Treatment Options for Localized Classic and Endemic Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_228">Treatment options for localized skin disease include (options are equivalent):</Para><OrderedList id="_229" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_230" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_233" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_319" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Other options (cryo-laser, intralesional, and topical therapy)</SummaryRef>.	</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_230"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_231">For solitary lesions or lesions of limited extent,
modest doses of radiation applied with a limited
margin provide excellent control of disease in the treated area.  Usually,
superficial radiation beams, such as electron beams, are used.  Some authors believe disease
recurrence in adjacent untreated skin is common if
only involved-field radiation therapy is used and claim better cure
rates when extended-field radiation therapy is used.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_372">For low-voltage (100 kv) photon radiation therapy,  8 Gy to 10 Gy is given as a single dose
or 15 Gy to 20 Gy is given over 1 week because solitary lesions control nearly
100% of local disease, but recurrence in adjacent areas is common.</Para><Para id="_373">For electron-beam radiation therapy (EBRT),  4 Gy is given once weekly for 6 to 8 consecutive weeks
with a 4-MeV to 6-MeV electron beam.  Ports should include the entire skin
surface 15 cm above the lesion.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_233"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_234">Surgical excision may benefit patients with small superficial
lesions,  but local recurrence is likely to occur.  However, multiple
small excisions can continue to be performed  for good disease
control.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_319"><Title>Other options</Title><Para id="_320">Based on extent and accessibility of lesions, alternate modalities such as cryo-, laser, intralesional, and topical therapy can be used. Use of these modalities is based on evidence extrapolated from treatment of AIDS-associated KS.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_268"><Title>Treatment Options for Advanced Classic and Endemic Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_269">Treatment options for advanced skin disease include:</Para><OrderedList id="_270" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_271" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Radiation therapy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_275" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_291" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Biological and targeted therapy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_303" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Immunotherapy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_271"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_272">Modest doses can be effective in controlling widespread skin disease.  The
type of radiation (i.e., photon vs. electron) and fields used must be
tailored to suit the distribution of disease in the individual patient.<Reference refidx="1"/> Radiation therapy options include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_273" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Extended-field EBRT.</ListItem><ListItem>For
disease limited to areas distal to the knee,  subtotal-skin EBRT directed to skin below the umbilicus.</ListItem><ListItem>For disease that extends above the knee, total-skin EBRT.<Para id="_274">EBRT used in this manner gave long-term results that were superior to
those obtained with radiation therapy administered to successive individual lesions as they
appeared.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></ListItem><ListItem>For extensive disease, EBRT  4 Gy given once weekly for 6 to 8 consecutive weeks,
and subtotal- or total-skin radiation therapy.

</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_275"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_277">Because classic KS is such a rare disease in
the United States, and is usually treated initially with radiation therapy, few
patients have been treated with chemotherapy. Its use in classic KS is based on data extrapolated from treatment of AIDS-associated KS, and no randomized prospective
trials have compared one agent with another in classic KS.  The agents listed below have potential benefit.</Para><SummarySection id="_278"><Title>Pegylated liposomal doxorubicin (PLD)</Title><Para id="_280">PLD has shown activity in several case series and single-institution analyses.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_321">Evidence (PLD):</Para><OrderedList id="_281" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A multicenter trial included 55 patients with classic KS who were treated over a decade.<Reference refidx="5"/><ItemizedList id="_322" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A 71% overall response rate was seen using PLD, with a median response duration of 25 months.<Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_282"><Title>Taxanes</Title><Para id="_284">Paclitaxel has shown activity in both AIDS-associated and classic KS in small case series.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_323">Evidence (taxanes):</Para><OrderedList id="_285" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A small trial included 73 patients with AIDS-associated KS (32% had an undetectable HIV viral load). Patients  were randomly assigned to receive either PLD or paclitaxel.<Reference refidx="9"/><ItemizedList id="_324" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Response rates were 46% for patients who received PLD and 56% for patients who received paclitaxel. The median progression-free survival (PFS) was 12 months for patients who received PLD and 18 months for patients who received paclitaxel. The 2-year overall survival rates were 78% for patients who received PLD and 79% for patients who received paclitaxel.<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_286"><Title>Other chemotherapy agents</Title><Para id="_288">  Single-agent vinblastine <Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/>, oral etoposide <Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/>, and gemcitabine <Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/> have all shown good activity in classic and AIDS-associated KS.</Para><Para id="_325">Evidence (other chemotherapy agents):</Para><OrderedList id="_289" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A phase III trial included 65 patients with classic KS. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either oral etoposide or vinblastine.<Reference refidx="18"/><ItemizedList id="_326" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Response rates were relatively high and did not significantly differ (58% for patients who received PLD and 74% for patients who received paclitaxel).<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_291"><Title>Biological and targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_293">	Agents that modulate the immune system, such as imide drugs and interferon alfa-2b, have shown efficacy in both classic and AIDS-associated KS. </Para><SummarySection id="_294"><Title>Pomalidomide</Title><Para id="_296">The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved pomalidomide for the treatment of KS in patients with and without HIV.  </Para><Para id="_327">Evidence (pomalidomide):</Para><OrderedList id="_297" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A phase I/II study of pomalidomide included 28 patients with KS. Ten patients were HIV-positive and 18 patients were  HIV-negative.<Reference refidx="23"/> <ItemizedList id="_328" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The overall response rate was 71%, and  80% among patients without HIV. The median PFS was 10 months.<Reference refidx="23"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Pomalidomide was generally well tolerated. Common adverse events included neutropenia, anemia, fatigue, constipation, and rash. There were few grade 3 events (neutropenia, infection, and edema).<Reference refidx="24"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_298">Pomalidomide is teratogenic, prescribed through a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) program, and it should be given with aspirin to mitigate venous thromboembolism risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_299"><Title>Interferon alfa-2b</Title><Para id="_301"> The FDA approved interferon alfa-2b for the treatment of AIDS-associated KS. It is sometimes used off-label for classic KS. </Para><Para id="_329">Evidence (interferon alfa-2b):</Para><OrderedList id="_302" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A small case series included 16 patients without HIV.<Reference refidx="25"/><ItemizedList id="_330" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Treatment with interferon alfa-2b led to a response in ten patients (one complete response [CR], nine partial responses [PRs]).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_303"><Title>Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_305"> Immune checkpoint inhibitor therapy has been tested in classic KS and yielded promising results.</Para><SummarySection id="_306"><Title>Pembrolizumab monotherapy</Title><Para id="_331">Evidence (pembrolizumab monotherapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_309" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Pembrolizumab monotherapy (given every 3 weeks for up to 6 months) was evaluated in a multicenter, single-arm, phase II study of 17 patients. Eight patients had classic KS and nine patients had endemic KS.<Reference refidx="26"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] <ItemizedList id="_310" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	At a median follow-up of 20.4 months, with 88% of patients completing 6 months of treatment, the best overall response rate was 71% (12% with CR, 59% with PR). An additional 29% of patients had stable disease based on AIDS Clinical Trials Group response evaluation. </ListItem><ListItem>	The median time to response was 5 months (interquartile range, 3.4–12), the estimated median duration of response was 23 months (95% confidence interval [CI], 21.2–not reached [NR]), and the median time to progression (TTP) was 24 months (95% CI, 15–NR).  </ListItem><ListItem>	Sixty-four percent (7 of 11) of pretreated patients and 83% (5 of 6) of chemotherapy-naïve patients had a CR or PR. </ListItem><ListItem>	Pembrolizumab was generally well tolerated. Two patients (12%) had grade 3 events: acute cardiac decompensation and granulomatous reaction in the lung. Two patients discontinued treatment due to grade 2 pancreatitis and grade 3 acute cardiac decompensation, respectively. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_312"><Title>Ipilimumab and nivolumab</Title><Para id="_332">Evidence (ipilimumab and nivolumab):</Para><OrderedList id="_313" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Ipilimumab and nivolumab combination therapy was evaluated in a phase II study of 18 patients with refractory classic KS. Patients received nivolumab 240 mg every 2 weeks and ipilimumab 1 mg/kg every 6 weeks until disease progression, for up to 24 months.<Reference refidx="27"/> <ItemizedList id="_314" Style="bullet"><ListItem>At a median follow-up of 24.4 months, the overall response rate was 87% by Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria. The 6- and 12-month PFS rates were 77% and 59%, respectively.<Reference refidx="27"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_21_sid_3"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_21_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="27701876">Tsao MN, Sinclair E, Assaad D, et al.: Radiation therapy for the treatment of skin Kaposi sarcoma. Ann Palliat Med 5 (4): 298-302, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2819653" MedlineID="90058398">Epstein JB, Lozada-Nur F, McLeod WA, et al.: Oral Kaposi's sarcoma in acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. Review of management and report of the efficacy of intralesional vinblastine. Cancer 64 (12): 2424-30, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11705307">Bodsworth NJ, Bloch M, Bower M, et al.: Phase III vehicle-controlled, multi-centered study of topical alitretinoin gel 0.1% in cutaneous AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma. Am J Clin Dermatol 2 (2): 77-87, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6784910" MedlineID="81185884">Nisce LZ, Safai B, Poussin-Rosillo H: Once weekly total and subtotal skin electron beam therapy for Kaposi's sarcoma. Cancer 47 (4): 640-4, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18185536">Di Lorenzo G, Kreuter A, Di Trolio R, et al.: Activity and safety of pegylated liposomal doxorubicin as first-line therapy in the treatment of non-visceral classic Kaposi's sarcoma: a multicenter study. J Invest Dermatol 128 (6): 1578-80, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="17853313">Castiñeiras I, Almagro M, Rodríguez-Lozano J, et al.: Disseminated classic Kaposi's sarcoma. Two cases with excellent response to pegylated liposomal doxorubicin. J Dermatolog Treat 17 (6): 377-80, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="18098221">Di Lorenzo G, Di Trolio R, Montesarchio V, et al.: Pegylated liposomal doxorubicin as second-line therapy in the treatment of patients with advanced classic Kaposi sarcoma: a retrospective study. Cancer 112 (5): 1147-52, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="18067475">Potouridou I, Korfitis C, Ioannidou D, et al.: Low to moderate cumulative doses of pegylated liposomal doxorubicin in the treatment of classic Kaposi sarcoma in elderly patients with comorbidities. Br J Dermatol 158 (2): 431-2, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="20564162">Cianfrocca M, Lee S, Von Roenn J, et al.: Randomized trial of paclitaxel versus pegylated liposomal doxorubicin for advanced human immunodeficiency virus-associated Kaposi sarcoma: evidence of symptom palliation from chemotherapy. Cancer 116 (16): 3969-77, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="18363766">Brambilla L, Romanelli A, Bellinvia M, et al.: Weekly paclitaxel for advanced aggressive classic Kaposi sarcoma: experience in 17 cases. Br J Dermatol 158 (6): 1339-44, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="11299806">Chao SC, Lee JY, Tsao CJ: Treatment of classical type Kaposi's sarcoma with paclitaxel. Anticancer Res 21 (1B): 571-3, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="16534786">Fardet L, Stoebner PE, Bachelez H, et al.: Treatment with taxanes of refractory or life-threatening Kaposi sarcoma not associated with human immunodeficiency virus infection. Cancer 106 (8): 1785-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="7226013" MedlineID="81185883">Solan AJ, Greenwald ES, Silvay O: Long-term complete remissions of Kaposi's sarcoma with vinblastine therapy. Cancer 47 (4): 637-9, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="938075" MedlineID="76230418">Tucker SB, Winkelmann RK: Treatment of Kaposi sarcoma with vinblastine. Arch Dermatol 112 (7): 958-61, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="5933581" MedlineID="66131851">Scott WP, Voight JA: Kaposi's sarcoma. Management with vincaleucoblastine. Cancer 19 (4): 557-64, 1966.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="7353196" MedlineID="80110893">Klein E, Schwartz RA, Laor Y, et al.: Treatment of Kaposi's sarcoma with vinblastine. Cancer 45 (3): 427-31, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="22188463">Tas F, Sen F, Keskin S, et al.: Oral etoposide as first-line therapy in the treatment of patients with advanced classic Kaposi's sarcoma (CKS): a single-arm trial (oral etoposide in CKS). J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol 27 (6): 789-92, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="7954250">Brambilla L, Labianca R, Boneschi V, et al.: Mediterranean Kaposi's sarcoma in the elderly. A randomized study of oral etoposide versus vinblastine. Cancer 74 (10): 2873-8, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="2466707">Brambilla L, Boneschi V, Fossati S, et al.: Oral etoposide for Kaposi's Mediterranean sarcoma. Dermatologica 177 (6): 365-9, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="11306832">Brambilla L, Labianca R, Ferrucci SM, et al.: Treatment of classical Kaposi's sarcoma with gemcitabine. Dermatology 202 (2): 119-22, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="19856679">Zustovich F, Lombardi G, Pastorelli D: Important role of gemcitabine in the treatment of classic Kaposi's sarcoma. Tumori 95 (4): 562-3, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="24324093">Zustovich F, Ferro A, Toso S: Gemcitabine for the treatment of classic Kaposi's Sarcoma: a case series. Anticancer Res 33 (12): 5531-4, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="34862247">Ramaswami R, Polizzotto MN, Lurain K, et al.: Safety, Activity, and Long-term Outcomes of Pomalidomide in the Treatment of Kaposi Sarcoma among Individuals with or without HIV Infection. Clin Cancer Res 28 (5): 840-850, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="27863194">Polizzotto MN, Uldrick TS, Wyvill KM, et al.: Pomalidomide for Symptomatic Kaposi's Sarcoma in People With and Without HIV Infection: A Phase I/II Study. J Clin Oncol 34 (34): 4125-4131, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="8607632">Costa da Cunha CS, Lebbe C, Rybojad M, et al.: Long-term follow-up of non-HIV Kaposi's sarcoma treated with low-dose recombinant interferon alfa-2b. Arch Dermatol 132 (3): 285-90, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="35279271">Delyon J, Biard L, Renaud M, et al.: PD-1 blockade with pembrolizumab in classic or endemic Kaposi's sarcoma: a multicentre, single-arm, phase 2 study. Lancet Oncol 23 (4): 491-500, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="35339649">Zer A, Icht O, Yosef L, et al.: Phase II single-arm study of nivolumab and ipilimumab (Nivo/Ipi) in previously treated classical Kaposi sarcoma (cKS). Ann Oncol 33 (7): 720-727, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039075">AIDS-related Kaposi sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of AIDS-Associated Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_46">Treatment of AIDS-associated  Kaposi sarcoma (KS) may result in the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_103" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The disappearance or reduction in size of specific skin
lesions, thereby alleviating the discomfort associated with the chronic edema
and ulcerations that often accompany multiple skin tumors seen on the lower
extremities.</ListItem><ListItem>Control of symptoms associated with mucosal or visceral
lesions.  </ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_104">No data are available to show that treatment improves
survival.<Reference refidx="1"/> In addition to antitumor treatment, essential components of an
optimal KS treatment strategy in this population include antiretroviral
treatment, prophylaxis for opportunistic infections, and rapid recognition and
treatment of intercurrent infections. Therefore, close collaboration between oncologists and HIV specialists is vital. </Para><Para id="_84">Most patients with good-risk disease, defined by the AIDS Clinical Trials Group as T0, show tumor regression with antiretroviral therapy alone.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Patients with poor-risk disease, defined as T1, usually require a combination of antiretroviral therapy and chemotherapy with discontinuation of the chemotherapy after disappearance of the skin lesion.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><SummarySection id="_185"><Title>Treatment Options for AIDS-Associated Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_186">Treatment options for AIDS-associated KS include:</Para><OrderedList id="_187" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_188" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Local modalities</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_190" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_193" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">Biological and targeted therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_188"><Title>Local modalities</Title><Para id="_189">Small localized lesions of KS may be treated by electrodesiccation and
curettage, cryotherapy, or by surgical excision.  KS tumors are also generally
very responsive to local radiation therapy, and excellent palliation has been
obtained with doses at 20  Gy or slightly higher.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> Radiation therapy is generally reserved to treat localized areas of the skin
and oral cavity.  It is used less often to control pulmonary, gastrointestinal
tract, or other sites of KS lesions.  Localized KS lesions have also
been effectively treated with intralesional injections of vinblastine.<Reference refidx="7"/>
Alitretinoin 0.1% gel provided local control in a randomized, prospective, multicenter trial.<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_190"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_191">In AIDS-associated KS, the already profoundly depressed immunologic status of the patient
limits the therapeutic usefulness of systemic chemotherapy.  Systemic
chemotherapy studies in patients with AIDS-associated KS have used doxorubicin, bleomycin, vinblastine, vincristine, etoposide, paclitaxel, and docetaxel alone or in combination.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] The combination of antiretroviral therapy and liposomal doxorubicin resulted in a 5-year overall survival rate of 85% in 140 patients with T1 disease.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_192">  Randomized multicenter trials
showed an improvement in response rate (45%–60% vs. 20%–25%) and a more favorable toxic effects
profile for pegylated liposomal doxorubicin (PLD) or liposomal daunorubicin, compared with the combination of doxorubicin, bleomycin, and vincristine or bleomycin and vincristine.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]
During antiretroviral therapy, both PLD and paclitaxel are active single agents with response rates close to 50%.<Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_193"><Title>Biological and targeted therapy</Title><SummarySection id="_333"><Title>Interferon alfa</Title><Para id="_334">The interferon alfas have also been widely studied and show  a 40% objective
response rate in patients with AIDS-associated KS.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/>  In these reports, the
responses differed significantly according to the following prognostic factors:</Para><ItemizedList id="_374" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> Extent
of disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Prior or coexistent opportunistic infections.</ListItem><ListItem>Prior treatment with
chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>CD4 lymphocyte counts lower than 200 cells/µL.</ListItem><ListItem>Presence of circulating acid-labile interferon alfa.</ListItem><ListItem>Increase in
beta-2-microglobulin.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_375">Several treatment studies have combined interferon alfa
with other chemotherapeutic agents.  Overall, these trials have shown no
benefit with the interferon-chemotherapy combinations as compared with the
single-agent activities.</Para><Para id="_335">Recombinant interferon alfa-2a and recombinant interferon alfa-2b were the first agents
approved for the treatment of KS.  Approval was based on single-agent studies
performed in the 1980s before the advent of antiretroviral therapy.  The early
studies demonstrated improved efficacy at relatively high doses.  
</Para><Para id="_371">High-dose
monotherapy is rarely used today, and instead, interferon is given in
combination with other anti-HIV drugs in doses of 4 to 18 million units. 
Neutropenia is dose limiting, and trials of doses of 1 to 10 million units
combined with less myelosuppressive antiretroviral agents are in progress.  Response
to interferon is slow, and  the maximum effect is seen after 6 or more months.  
Interferon should probably not be used to treat patients with rapidly progressive,
symptomatic KS.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_336"><Title>Imatinib</Title><Para id="_354">Imatinib is a c-kit/platelet-derived growth factor receptor inhibitor.</Para><Para id="_355">Evidence (imatinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_356" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A phase II trial included 30 patients with AIDS-associated KS.<Reference refidx="20"/><ItemizedList id="_357" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A partial response (PR) was seen in 10 of 30 previously treated patients . Previous treatment included antiretroviral therapy and chemotherapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_338"><Title>Bevacizumab</Title><Para id="_358">Bevacizumab is a humanized, anti–vascular endothelial growth factor monoclonal antibody.</Para><Para id="_359">Evidence (bevacizumab):</Para><OrderedList id="_360" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A phase II study included 16 assessable patients with KS and HIV. Patients received bevacizumab intravenously (IV) on days 1 and 8 and then every 3 weeks.<Reference refidx="21"/><ItemizedList id="_361" Style="bullet"><ListItem>There was a response in 5 of 16 patients. These patients had not improved after prior antiretroviral therapy and chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_340"><Title>Interleukin-12</Title><Para id="_341">Evidence (interleukin-12):</Para><OrderedList id="_342" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A phase I and phase II trial included 24 evaluable patients. Patients received interleukin-12 subcutaneously twice weekly.<Reference refidx="22"/><ItemizedList id="_343" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Treatment resulted in a response rate of 71% (95% confidence interval, 48%–89%).<Reference refidx="22"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_344"><Title>Pomalidomide</Title><Para id="_345">The U.S. Food and Drug Administration approved pomalidomide for patients with AIDS-associated KS. </Para><Para id="_346">Evidence (pomalidomide):</Para><OrderedList id="_347" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A phase I/II study of pomalidomide included 28 patients with KS. Ten patients were HIV-positive and 18 patients were HIV-negative.<Reference refidx="23"/><ItemizedList id="_348" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The overall response rate was 71%, and 80% among patients without HIV. The median progression-free survival was 10 months.<Reference refidx="23"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Pomalidomide was generally well tolerated. Common adverse events included neutropenia, anemia, fatigue, constipation, and rash. There were few grade 3 events (neutropenia, infection, and edema).<Reference refidx="24"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_349">Pomalidomide is teratogenic, prescribed through a Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) program, and it should be given with aspirin to mitigate venous thromboembolism risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_350"><Title>Bortezomib</Title><Para id="_351">Evidence (bortezomib):</Para><OrderedList id="_352" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Bortezomib was evaluated in a small phase I dose-escalation study of 17 patients with AIDS-associated KS. Patients received bortezomib IV on days 1, 8, and 15 of 28-day cycles.<Reference refidx="25"/><ItemizedList id="_353" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Bortezomib was relatively well tolerated and led to a PR in 60% of all evaluable patients. Among those receiving the highest bortezomib dose, 83% of patients had a PR and 17% had stable disease.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_316"><Title>Management of Immune Reconstitution Inflammatory Syndrome in AIDS-Associated Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_318">Immune reconstitution inflammatory syndrome (IRIS) is a hyperimmune response in patients with HIV/AIDS within the first 6 months of starting antiretroviral therapy. Kaposi sarcoma (KS)-associated IRIS (KS-IRIS) is not well-defined, but is considered to be the sudden clinical worsening of previous KS ("paradoxical") or the new presentation of KS (“unmasked”) in close proximity to starting or modifying antiretroviral therapy.<Reference refidx="26"/>  </Para><Para id="_362">Estimates for KS-IRIS incidence vary from 2% to 39%, with the highest risk in patients with any of the following characteristics:<Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/>   </Para><ItemizedList id="_376" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>High HIV viral loads (&gt;10,000 copies/mL).</ListItem><ListItem>CD4 lymphocyte count less than 200 cells/µL.</ListItem><ListItem>Detectable plasma human herpesvirus  8 DNA.</ListItem><ListItem>Pulmonary KS involvement.</ListItem><ListItem>Recent steroid use.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_377"> KS-IRIS typically presents with increased swelling/tenderness of lesions, new or worsening edema, and visceral or pulmonary involvement.</Para><Para id="_363">Management of KS-IRIS typically includes continuing antiretroviral therapy and initiating systemic treatment, such as liposomal doxorubicin or paclitaxel, for KS. The evidence for use of chemotherapy to prevent KS-IRIS is mixed, but can be considered on an individual basis.<Reference refidx="26"/>  Glucocorticoids are avoided due to the risk of dramatic worsening of KS.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/> Thalidomide has also been used for steroid-refractory IRIS.<Reference refidx="29"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_45_sid_4"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_45_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Safai B: Kaposi's sarcoma and acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. In: DeVita VT, Hellman S, Rosenberg S, eds.: AIDS: Etiology, Diagnosis, Treatment and Prevention. 4th ed. Lippincott-Raven Publishers, 1997, pp 295-318.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="14752065">Krown SE: Highly active antiretroviral therapy in AIDS-associated Kaposi's sarcoma: implications for the design of therapeutic trials in patients with advanced, symptomatic Kaposi's sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 22 (3): 399-402, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24378415">Bower M, Dalla Pria A, Coyle C, et al.: Prospective stage-stratified approach to AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 409-14, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="24378412">Krell J, Stebbing J: Broader implications of a stage-guided stratified therapeutic approach for AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 373-5, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18439694">Singh NB, Lakier RH, Donde B: Hypofractionated radiation therapy in the treatment of epidemic Kaposi sarcoma--a prospective randomized trial. Radiother Oncol 88 (2): 211-6, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="27701876">Tsao MN, Sinclair E, Assaad D, et al.: Radiation therapy for the treatment of skin Kaposi sarcoma. Ann Palliat Med 5 (4): 298-302, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="2819653" MedlineID="90058398">Epstein JB, Lozada-Nur F, McLeod WA, et al.: Oral Kaposi's sarcoma in acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. Review of management and report of the efficacy of intralesional vinblastine. Cancer 64 (12): 2424-30, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11705307">Bodsworth NJ, Bloch M, Bower M, et al.: Phase III vehicle-controlled, multi-centered study of topical alitretinoin gel 0.1% in cutaneous AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma. Am J Clin Dermatol 2 (2): 77-87, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12149296" MedlineID="22144287">Evans SR, Krown SE, Testa MA, et al.: Phase II evaluation of low-dose oral etoposide for the treatment of relapsed or progressive AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma: an AIDS Clinical Trials Group clinical study. J Clin Oncol 20 (15): 3236-41, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="7603142" MedlineID="95326733">Saville MW, Lietzau J, Pluda JM, et al.: Treatment of HIV-associated Kaposi's sarcoma with paclitaxel. Lancet 346 (8966): 26-8, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="15578686">Lim ST, Tupule A, Espina BM, et al.: Weekly docetaxel is safe and effective in the treatment of advanced-stage acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related Kaposi sarcoma. Cancer 103 (2): 417-21, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="10561228">Gill PS, Tulpule A, Espina BM, et al.: Paclitaxel is safe and effective in the treatment of advanced AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 17 (6): 1876-83, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="17267331">Di Lorenzo G, Konstantinopoulos PA, Pantanowitz L, et al.: Management of AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma. Lancet Oncol 8 (2): 167-76, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="9469358" MedlineID="98129260">Stewart S, Jablonowski H, Goebel FD, et al.: Randomized comparative trial of pegylated liposomal doxorubicin versus bleomycin and vincristine in the treatment of AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma. International Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin Study Group. J Clin Oncol 16 (2): 683-91, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="9667262" MedlineID="98329836">Northfelt DW, Dezube BJ, Thommes JA, et al.: Pegylated-liposomal doxorubicin versus doxorubicin, bleomycin, and vincristine in the treatment of AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma: results of a randomized phase III clinical trial. J Clin Oncol 16 (7): 2445-51, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="8708728" MedlineID="96326437">Gill PS, Wernz J, Scadden DT, et al.: Randomized phase III trial of liposomal daunorubicin versus doxorubicin, bleomycin, and vincristine in AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 14 (8): 2353-64, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="20564162">Cianfrocca M, Lee S, Von Roenn J, et al.: Randomized trial of paclitaxel versus pegylated liposomal doxorubicin for advanced human immunodeficiency virus-associated Kaposi sarcoma: evidence of symptom palliation from chemotherapy. Cancer 116 (16): 3969-77, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="3958767" MedlineID="86170648">Real FX, Oettgen HF, Krown SE: Kaposi's sarcoma and the acquired immunodeficiency syndrome: treatment with high and low doses of recombinant leukocyte A interferon. J Clin Oncol 4 (4): 544-51, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="6712031" MedlineID="84176875">Groopman JE, Gottlieb MS, Goodman J, et al.: Recombinant alpha-2 interferon therapy for Kaposi's sarcoma associated with the acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. Ann Intern Med 100 (5): 671-6, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="24378417">Koon HB, Krown SE, Lee JY, et al.: Phase II trial of imatinib in AIDS-associated Kaposi's sarcoma: AIDS Malignancy Consortium Protocol 042. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 402-8, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="22430271">Uldrick TS, Wyvill KM, Kumar P, et al.: Phase II study of bevacizumab in patients with HIV-associated Kaposi's sarcoma receiving antiretroviral therapy. J Clin Oncol 30 (13): 1476-83, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="16507779">Little RF, Pluda JM, Wyvill KM, et al.: Activity of subcutaneous interleukin-12 in AIDS-related Kaposi sarcoma. Blood 107 (12): 4650-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="34862247">Ramaswami R, Polizzotto MN, Lurain K, et al.: Safety, Activity, and Long-term Outcomes of Pomalidomide in the Treatment of Kaposi Sarcoma among Individuals with or without HIV Infection. Clin Cancer Res 28 (5): 840-850, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="27863194">Polizzotto MN, Uldrick TS, Wyvill KM, et al.: Pomalidomide for Symptomatic Kaposi's Sarcoma in People With and Without HIV Infection: A Phase I/II Study. J Clin Oncol 34 (34): 4125-4131, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="31624104">Reid EG, Suazo A, Lensing SY, et al.: Pilot Trial AMC-063: Safety and Efficacy of Bortezomib in AIDS-associated Kaposi Sarcoma. Clin Cancer Res 26 (3): 558-565, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="35205734">Poizot-Martin I, Brégigeon S, Palich R, et al.: Immune Reconstitution Inflammatory Syndrome Associated Kaposi Sarcoma. Cancers (Basel) 14 (4): , 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="26636923">Fernández-Sánchez M, Iglesias MC, Ablanedo-Terrazas Y, et al.: Steroids are a risk factor for Kaposi's sarcoma-immune reconstitution inflammatory syndrome and mortality in HIV infection. AIDS 30 (6): 909-14, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="18317012">Volkow PF, Cornejo P, Zinser JW, et al.: Life-threatening exacerbation of Kaposi's sarcoma after prednisone treatment for immune reconstitution inflammatory syndrome. AIDS 22 (5): 663-5, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="22874513">Brunel AS, Reynes J, Tuaillon E, et al.: Thalidomide for steroid-dependent immune reconstitution inflammatory syndromes during AIDS. AIDS 26 (16): 2110-2, 2012.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_364"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039074">immunosuppressive treatment related Kaposi sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Transplant-Related Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_365"><Title>Treatment Options for Transplant-Related Kaposi Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_366">In general, transplant-related Kaposi sarcoma is effectively managed by reduction in immunosuppression and does not require systemic treatment. Transitioning immunosuppression therapy to an mTOR inhibitor, such as sirolimus, has demonstrated efficacy in small studies and can be considered.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_364_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_364_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15800227">Stallone G, Schena A, Infante B, et al.: Sirolimus for Kaposi's sarcoma in renal-transplant recipients. N Engl J Med 352 (13): 1317-23, 2005.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_77"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/07/2025)</Title><Para id="_78">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_367">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062914#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of Kaposi sarcoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Kaposi Sarcoma Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Eric J. Seifter, MD (Johns Hopkins University)</ListItem><ListItem>Minh Tam Truong, MD (Boston University Medical Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Vinayak Venkataraman, MD (Dana Farber Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Kaposi Sarcoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/kaposi-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389335]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-05-07</DateLastModified></Summary>
