<Summary id="CDR0000062926" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Hairy cell leukemia treatment options include surveillance, chemotherapy, targeted therapy/immunotherapy, and splenectomy. The decision to treat is based on cytopenias, splenomegaly, or infectious complications. Get detailed information about hairy cell leukemia in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Hairy Cell Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/patient/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Hairy Cell Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039065">hairy cell leukemia</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_110">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of hairy cell leukemia. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_111">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>hairy cell leukemia</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Hairy Cell Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Hairy Cell Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Hairy Cell Leukemia Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039065">hairy cell leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Hairy Cell Leukemia</Title><SummarySection id="_215"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_216">Hairy cell leukemia is an indolent, low-grade, B-cell lymphoid malignancy. It is rare, with only 1,200 to 1,300 new cases annually in the United States.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_105"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_99">Hairy cell leukemia usually presents with:</Para><ItemizedList id="_100" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Splenomegaly.</ListItem><ListItem>Varying degrees
of leukopenia (occasionally leukocytosis).</ListItem><ListItem>Pancytopenia.</ListItem><ListItem>Monocytopenia.</ListItem><ListItem> Bone marrow
infiltration by atypical cells with prominent cytoplasmic projections (i.e., hairy
cells).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_229">Lymphadenopathy is absent, except with multiply recurrent progressive disease. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><Title>Diagnostic Evaluation</Title><Para id="_219">The following tests and procedures may be used to diagnose hairy cell leukemia:</Para><ItemizedList id="_220" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Flow cytometry.</ListItem><ListItem>Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy.</ListItem><ListItem>Immunophenotyping.</ListItem><ListItem>Cytogenetic analysis.</ListItem><ListItem><GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> gene testing.</ListItem><ListItem>Computed tomography scan.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_222">  The bone marrow is usually fibrotic and is not easily aspirated.  It has circulating B cells with cytoplasmic projections (hairy appearance).  Although a bone marrow biopsy may be required to enroll in a clinical trial, the hairy cell leukemia diagnosis can usually be made by flow cytometry.</Para><Para id="_104">In addition to the B-cell antigens CD19, CD20 (very high levels), and CD22, the cells coexpress CD11c, CD25, and CD103.  The <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> V600E pathogenic variant is a hairy cell leukemia–defining genetic feature that can aid in diagnosis.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_359">There is a variation of hairy cell leukemia (HCL-v) which accounts for 10% of cases. HCL-v is distinguished clinically by an elevated white blood cell count (15–50 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L) and aberrant markers, including variable (instead of bright) CD103 and the absence of CD23, CD25, CD12, and CD43.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> HCL-v cells also lack <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> variants. Patients with HCL-v have  more aggressive clinical courses,  reduced responses to purine nucleoside analogue-based therapy, and shorter durations of response.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_309">The depth of a complete remission can be evaluated with measurable residual disease (MRD) by testing for a <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> variant or an immunoglobulin heavy chain gene rearrangement. However, the usefulness of altering therapeutic choices with MRD remains unclear and requires further evaluation.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="39383460">Falini B, Tiacci E: Hairy-Cell Leukemia. N Engl J Med 391 (14): 1328-1341, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="22028477">Tiacci E, Schiavoni G, Forconi F, et al.: Simple genetic diagnosis of hairy cell leukemia by sensitive detection of the BRAF-V600E mutation. Blood 119 (1): 192-5, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="22212971">Naik RR, Saven A: My treatment approach to hairy cell leukemia. Mayo Clin Proc 87 (1): 67-76, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="22111844">Jones G, Parry-Jones N, Wilkins B, et al.: Revised guidelines for the diagnosis and management of hairy cell leukaemia and hairy cell leukaemia variant*. Br J Haematol 156 (2): 186-95, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="33368172">Troussard X, Grever MR: The revised guidelines for the diagnosis and management of hairy cell leukaemia and the hairy cell leukaemia variant. Br J Haematol 193 (1): 11-14, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="36509740">Ravandi F, Kreitman RJ, Tiacci E, et al.: Consensus opinion from an international group of experts on measurable residual disease in hairy cell leukemia. Blood Cancer J 12 (12): 165, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039065">hairy cell leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Hairy Cell Leukemia</Title><Para id="_4">There is no generally accepted staging system used in the prognosis
and treatment of hairy cell leukemia.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039065">hairy cell leukemia</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Hairy Cell Leukemia</Title><Para id="_15">Hairy cell leukemia is highly treatable but rarely cured.  Because  it is easily
controlled, many patients have prolonged survival with the use of sequential therapies. 
The decision to treat is based on signs of disease progression, including any of the following factors:</Para><ItemizedList id="_247" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Cytopenias (especially if symptomatic).</ListItem><ListItem>Increasing splenomegaly.</ListItem><ListItem>The
presence of other, usually infectious, complications.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_248">If the patient is asymptomatic and if blood counts are maintained in an
acceptable range, therapy may not be needed.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para><SummarySection id="_252"><Title>Treatment Options for Hairy Cell Leukemia</Title><Para id="_360">Prior to the COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2) pandemic, the standard initial therapy for patients with hairy cell leukemia was infusion of cladribine daily for 5 days, given with or without eight weekly doses of rituximab.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> However, treatment with a purine analogue–based regimen led to significant and prolonged neutropenia and impairment of T-cell function, which were both problematic during the pandemic in fighting viral infection and establishing vaccination-induced immunity.</Para><Para id="_361">Other options for initial standard therapy, instead of cladribine or pentostatin, may offer less toxicity in terms of infection and long-term risk of secondary malignancies. However,  these options may provide less durable response.</Para><Para id="_362">The Hairy Cell Leukemia Foundation convened a virtual meeting of 39 experts from around the world to amend the 2017 consensus recommendations.<Reference refidx="5"/> The adapted treatment guidelines, published in 2021, are based primarily on anecdotal experience and expert opinion, as controlled trials for this indolent leukemia cannot be completed expeditiously given the low incidence of this disease.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] The adapted treatment guidelines are summarized below.</Para><OrderedList id="_308" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Consider watchful waiting when feasible; asymptomatic patients with noncritical levels of pancytopenia can be monitored closely.</ListItem><ListItem>Cladribine, with or without rituximab,<Reference refidx="4"/>  remains the standard of care. However, due to the risk of serious and prolonged immunosuppression, nonchemotherapy treatment options may be preferable for older, frail patients with higher risk of infection (or for those who have active infections).</ListItem><ListItem>BRAF inhibitors such as vemurafenib, dabrafenib, or encorafenib are nonchemotherapeutic options that can be combined with rituximab or obinutuzumab.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> Most patients with hairy cell leukemia have <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> pathogenic variants, but this should be verified by flow cytometry. Despite extensive experience with vemurafenib for patients with relapsed disease, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has not approved oral vemurafenib for patients with hairy cell leukemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Consider using rituximab alone intravenously (IV) for 4 to 8 weeks or in combination with a BRAF inhibitor.<Reference refidx="11"/> Anti-CD20 monoclonal antibodies can impair future vaccine response, but they do not affect immunity from prior vaccination.</ListItem><ListItem>In patients with relapsed disease, the previously  mentioned options are available, along with ibrutinib (the Bruton tyrosine kinase inhibitor).<Reference refidx="12"/> </ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_253">Treatment options for hairy cell leukemia include:</Para><OrderedList id="_254" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Watchful waiting, if feasible.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_279" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Cladribine with or without rituximab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_336" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">BRAF inhibitors (vemurafenib or dabrafenib) with or without rituximab or trametinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_346" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Rituximab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_289" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Pentostatin</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_269" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Ibrutinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_294" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Re-treatment with cladribine or pentostatin</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_314" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Bendamustine with rituximab</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_296" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Splenectomy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_348" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Interferon</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_279"><Title>Cladribine with or without rituximab</Title><Para id="_280">Cladribine may be given with or without rituximab to treat hairy cell leukemia.</Para><Para id="_281">Evidence (cladribine with or without rituximab):</Para><OrderedList id="_282" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>In a phase II study, 68 patients with previously untreated hairy cell leukemia were randomly assigned to receive cladribine (0.15 mg/kg IV) on days 1 to 5, with eight weekly doses of rituximab either concurrently (starting on day 1) or delayed (starting after 6 months of cladribine treatment) if still positive with measurable residual disease (MRD) testing.<Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_313" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 96 months, 94% of patients who received concurrent therapy were MRD-free, compared with  12% of patients who received delayed  therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Although patients who underwent concurrent therapy had more need for platelet transfusions, they demonstrated higher neutrophil and platelet counts after 1 month.</ListItem><ListItem>A retrospective case series reported a median progression-free survival (PFS) of 67 months in patients with relapsed disease who received a purine nucleoside analogue (usually cladribine) plus rituximab.<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>A retrospective case series of nine patients with a histologic variation of hairy cell leukemia (HCL-v) reported an 88% complete response rate and 3-year PFS rate of 42% (95% confidence interval [CI], 1%–84%) after treatment with a purine nucleoside analogue (usually cladribine) plus rituximab.<Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Cladribine was given by daily subcutaneous injections or by daily 2-hour IV infusions for 5 to 7 days.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] 
Purine analogues should be avoided in cases of active infection or moderate to severe  hepatic or renal impairment.<ItemizedList id="_283" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The complete response rate was 50% to 80%.</ListItem><ListItem>The overall response rate was 85% to 95%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A National Cancer Institute group C protocol of 979 patients treated with cladribine reported lower response rates (i.e., 50% complete remission rate, 37% partial
remission rate) compared with other studies.<Reference refidx="18"/>  Responses were durable in patients treated with a short course of cladribine,
and patients who had a relapse often responded to re-treatment with cladribine.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem><ListItem>A retrospective review included 83 patients, aged 40 years and younger.<Reference refidx="2"/><ItemizedList id="_284" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The median time to first relapse was 54 months for all responders,  and the median overall survival (OS) was 21 years from diagnosis.</ListItem><ListItem>Cladribine may cause fever and immunosuppression;  documented infection was found in 33% of treated patients. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_287">In a retrospective study of patients with
cladribine-associated neutropenic fever, filgrastim (G-CSF) did not reduce the percentage of febrile patients, number of febrile days, or
frequency of hospital admissions to receive antibiotics.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_336"><Title>BRAF inhibitors (vemurafenib or dabrafenib) with or without rituximab or trametinib</Title><Para id="_337"><GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> V600E pathogenic variants are found in almost 100% of patients with classic-form hairy cell leukemia and almost never found in patients with other B-cell lymphomas and leukemias, including HCL-v.<Reference refidx="20"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]  Vemurafenib or other  BRAF inhibitors such as dabrafenib can be given with rituximab or obinutuzumab.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="21"/> The FDA has not approved BRAF inhibitors for hairy cell leukemia, but they can be used off-label in clinical practice.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para><Para id="_338">Evidence (vemurafenib with or without rituximab):</Para><OrderedList id="_339" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Several multicenter studies evaluated vemurafenib, given orally alone for 4 months or orally for 2 months with rituximab infused in eight doses over 18 weeks, in patients with relapsed or refractory hairy cell leukemia.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]<OrderedList id="_340" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>After a median follow-up of 23 to 40 months, for the 86 patients treated with vemurafenib alone, the following was reported in two studies:<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_341" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The overall response rate was 86% to 98%.</ListItem><ListItem>The complete response rate was 33% to 38%.</ListItem><ListItem>The median treatment-free survival was 18 to 25 months.</ListItem><ListItem>Retreatment at relapse resulted in an 86% response rate, and the median relapse-free survival was 12.7 months in one of the trials, with a 40-month median follow-up.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>After a median follow-up of 37 months, for the 30 patients treated with vemurafenib plus rituximab, the following was reported:<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_342" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The complete response rate was 87%. </ListItem><ListItem>The PFS rate was 78% at 37 months.</ListItem><ListItem>In patients who had a complete response, 65% had no MRD.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_343">Evidence (dabrafenib plus trametinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_344" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In a phase II trial of patients with relapsed or refractory disease, 55 patients received dabrafenib and trametinib orally until their disease progressed, they experienced unacceptable toxicity, or death occurred.<Reference refidx="24"/><ItemizedList id="_345" Style="bullet"><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 43.2 months, the overall response rate was 89.0% (95% CI, 77.8%–95.9%), the complete response rate was 65.5%, the 2-year PFS rate was 94.5%, and the 2-year OS rate was 95.5%.<Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_346"><Title>Rituximab</Title><Para id="_347">Rituximab can induce durable remissions (with minimal toxic effects), but rarely complete remissions, in patients with multiple relapses or refractory disease after treatment with a purine analogue or  interferon.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="25"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_289"><Title>Pentostatin</Title><Para id="_290">Pentostatin given IV every other week for 3 to 6 months produced
a 50% to 76% complete response rate and an 80% to 87% overall response
rate.<Reference refidx="26"/>  Complete remissions were of substantial duration.  Purine analogues should be avoided in cases of active infection or moderate to severe  hepatic or renal impairment.</Para><Para id="_291">Evidence (pentostatin):</Para><OrderedList id="_292" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Two trials
reported results on the 9-year median follow-up of patients treated with pentostatin.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><ItemizedList id="_293" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The relapse-free survival rates ranged from 56% to
67%.</ListItem><ListItem>Side effects included fever, immunosuppression, cytopenias, and
renal dysfunction. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	A randomized trial compared pentostatin to recombinant interferon alfa-2a.<Reference refidx="26"/><ItemizedList id="_303" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Pentostatin demonstrated higher response rates and more durable responses.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_269"><Title>Ibrutinib</Title><Para id="_270">Ibrutinib, a tyrosine kinase inhibitor, has been studied in the treatment of hairy cell leukemia.</Para><Para id="_271">Evidence (ibrutinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_272" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>In a phase II study, 37 patients with refractory hairy cell leukemia were treated with ibrutinib. The median follow-up was 42 months.<Reference refidx="29"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] <ItemizedList id="_273" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The response rate was 54%.</ListItem><ListItem>The estimated 36-month PFS rate was 73%.</ListItem><ListItem>The OS rate was 85%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_294"><Title>Re-treatment with cladribine or pentostatin</Title><Para id="_295">Patients with hairy cell leukemia who have a relapse after the first course of cladribine or pentostatin often respond
well to re-treatment with the same or another purine analogue, especially if relapse occurs after several years.<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_314"><Title>Bendamustine with rituximab</Title><Para id="_315">Evidence (bendamustine with rituximab):</Para><OrderedList id="_316" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A phase II study evaluated 12 patients with relapsed or refractory disease, three of whom were negative for <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> variants. Patients received the combination of bendamustine and rituximab.<Reference refidx="30"/><ItemizedList id="_317" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The overall response rate was 100%, and the complete remission rate was 50%.<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_296"><Title>Splenectomy</Title><Para id="_297">Splenectomy plays a
decreasing role in treating hairy cell leukemia because  effective alternatives are available. Splenectomy will partially or completely normalize the peripheral blood in
most patients with hairy cell leukemia.<Reference refidx="31"/>  After a splenectomy, there is usually
little or no change in the bone marrow, and virtually all
patients have progressive disease within 12 to 18 months.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_348"><Title>Interferon</Title><Para id="_349">Interferon alfa is no longer available because production has been halted.<Reference refidx="32"/> According to the  Hairy Cell Leukemia Foundation, ropeginterferon alfa-2b-njft is the best available preparation, but it is not FDA approved for hairy cell leukemia.</Para><Para id="_350">Interferon is useful when treating hairy cell leukemia during pregnancy because it does not involve cytotoxic agents.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_13_sid_3"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_13_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="34710243">Troussard X, Maître E, Cornet E: Hairy cell leukemia 2022: Update on diagnosis, risk-stratification, and treatment. Am J Hematol 97 (2): 226-236, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="24192579">Rosenberg JD, Burian C, Waalen J, et al.: Clinical characteristics and long-term outcome of young hairy cell leukemia patients treated with cladribine: a single-institution series. Blood 123 (2): 177-83, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10194424" MedlineID="99211930">Saven A, Burian C, Adusumalli J, et al.: Filgrastim for cladribine-induced neutropenic fever in patients with hairy cell leukemia. Blood 93 (8): 2471-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="32109194">Chihara D, Arons E, Stetler-Stevenson M, et al.: Randomized Phase II Study of First-Line Cladribine With Concurrent or Delayed Rituximab in Patients With Hairy Cell Leukemia. J Clin Oncol 38 (14): 1527-1538, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="27903528">Grever MR, Abdel-Wahab O, Andritsos LA, et al.: Consensus guidelines for the diagnosis and management of patients with classic hairy cell leukemia. Blood 129 (5): 553-560, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="33947938">Grever M, Andritsos L, Banerji V, et al.: Hairy cell leukemia and COVID-19 adaptation of treatment guidelines. Leukemia 35 (7): 1864-1872, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26352686">Tiacci E, Park JH, De Carolis L, et al.: Targeting Mutant BRAF in Relapsed or Refractory Hairy-Cell Leukemia. N Engl J Med 373 (18): 1733-47, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="26941398">Dietrich S, Pircher A, Endris V, et al.: BRAF inhibition in hairy cell leukemia with low-dose vemurafenib. Blood 127 (23): 2847-55, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="31187521">Falini B, Tiacci E: New treatment options in hairy cell leukemia with focus on BRAF inhibitors. Hematol Oncol 37 (Suppl 1): 30-37, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="33979489">Tiacci E, De Carolis L, Simonetti E, et al.: Vemurafenib plus Rituximab in Refractory or Relapsed Hairy-Cell Leukemia. N Engl J Med 384 (19): 1810-1823, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="18798112">Angelopoulou MK, Pangalis GA, Sachanas S, et al.: Outcome and toxicity in relapsed hairy cell leukemia patients treated with rituximab. Leuk Lymphoma 49 (9): 1817-20, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="12">Jones J, Andritsos L, Kreitman RJ: Efficacy and safety of the Bruton tyrosine kinase inhibitor ibrutinib in patients with hairy cell leukemia: stage 1 results of a phase 2 study. [Abstract] Blood  128 (22): A-1215, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="35043475">Hu R, Wei W, Mian A, et al.: Treatment outcomes with purine nucleoside analog alone or with rituximab for hairy cell leukemia at first relapse. Eur J Haematol 108 (5): 379-382, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="35437610">Wang Y, Wang T, Yu Y, et al.: Purine nucleoside analogs plus rituximab are an effective treatment choice for hairy cell leukemia-variant. Ann Hematol 101 (6): 1201-1210, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="35853850">Pagano L, Criscuolo M, Broccoli A, et al.: Long-term follow-up of cladribine treatment in hairy cell leukemia: 30-year experience in a multicentric Italian study. Blood Cancer J 12 (7): 109, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="19672771">Zenhäusern R, Schmitz SF, Solenthaler M, et al.: Randomized trial of daily versus weekly administration of 2-chlorodeoxyadenosine in patients with hairy cell leukemia: a multicenter phase III trial (SAKK 32/98). Leuk Lymphoma 50 (9): 1501-11, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="35218397">Hermel DJ, Cheng B, Bhangoo MS, et al.: Long-term outcomes of elderly hairy cell leukemia patients treated with cladribine. Ann Hematol 101 (5): 1089-1096, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="9738569" MedlineID="98408949">Cheson BD, Sorensen JM, Vena DA, et al.: Treatment of hairy cell leukemia with 2-chlorodeoxyadenosine via the Group C protocol mechanism of the National Cancer Institute: a report of 979 patients. J Clin Oncol 16 (9): 3007-15, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="26614900">Else M, Dearden CE, Catovsky D: Long-term follow-up after purine analogue therapy in hairy cell leukaemia. Best Pract Res Clin Haematol 28 (4): 217-29, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="25480661">Pettirossi V, Santi A, Imperi E, et al.: BRAF inhibitors reverse the unique molecular signature and phenotype of hairy cell leukemia and exert potent antileukemic activity. Blood 125 (8): 1207-16, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="38320179">Park JH, Devlin S, Durham BH, et al.: Vemurafenib and Obinutuzumab as Frontline Therapy for Hairy Cell Leukemia. NEJM Evid 2 (10): EVIDoa2300074, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="35143639">Falini B, De Carolis L, Tiacci E: How I treat refractory/relapsed hairy cell leukemia with BRAF inhibitors. Blood 139 (15): 2294-2305, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="35930750">Handa S, Lee JO, Derkach A, et al.: Long-term outcomes in patients with relapsed or refractory hairy cell leukemia treated with vemurafenib monotherapy. Blood 140 (25): 2663-2671, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="36108341">Kreitman RJ, Moreau P, Ravandi F, et al.: Dabrafenib plus trametinib in patients with relapsed/refractory BRAF V600E mutation-positive hairy cell leukemia. Blood 141 (9): 996-1006, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="12816862">Thomas DA, O'Brien S, Bueso-Ramos C, et al.: Rituximab in relapsed or refractory hairy cell leukemia. Blood 102 (12): 3906-11, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="7707126" MedlineID="95222328">Grever M, Kopecky K, Foucar MK, et al.: Randomized comparison of pentostatin versus interferon alfa-2a in previously untreated patients with hairy cell leukemia: an intergroup study. J Clin Oncol 13 (4): 974-82, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="10877049" MedlineID="20333542">Johnston JB, Eisenhauer E, Wainman N, et al.: Long-term outcome following treatment of hairy cell leukemia with pentostatin (Nipent): a National Cancer Institute of Canada study. Semin Oncol 27 (2 Suppl 5): 32-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="11049974" MedlineID="20504037">Flinn IW, Kopecky KJ, Foucar MK, et al.: Long-term follow-up of remission duration, mortality, and second malignancies in hairy cell leukemia patients treated with pentostatin. Blood 96 (9): 2981-6, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="33754642">Rogers KA, Andritsos LA, Wei L, et al.: Phase 2 study of ibrutinib in classic and variant hairy cell leukemia. Blood 137 (25): 3473-3483, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="24097860">Burotto M, Stetler-Stevenson M, Arons E, et al.: Bendamustine and rituximab in relapsed and refractory hairy cell leukemia. Clin Cancer Res 19 (22): 6313-21, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="6821700" MedlineID="83101766">Golomb HM, Vardiman JW: Response to splenectomy in 65 patients with hairy cell leukemia: an evaluation of spleen weight and bone marrow involvement. Blood 61 (2): 349-52, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="33932027">Assanto GM, Riemma C, Malaspina F, et al.: The current role of interferon in hairy cell leukaemia: clinical and molecular aspects. Br J Haematol 194 (1): 78-82, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (02/21/2025)</Title><Para id="_33">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_351"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_1" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">General Information About Hairy Cell Leukemia</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_352">Added Falini et al. as <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_216" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">reference 1</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_353"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_13" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Hairy Cell Leukemia</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_357">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_308" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that cladribine, with or without rituximab,  remains the standard of care. However, due to the risk of serious and prolonged immunosuppression, nonchemotherapy treatment options may be preferable for older, frail patients with higher risks of infection (or for those who have active infections). BRAF inhibitors such as vemurafenib, dabrafenib, or encorafenib are nonchemotherapeutic options that can be combined with rituximab or obinutuzumab.</Para><Para id="_354">Revised the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_253" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">list</SummaryRef> of treatment options for hairy cell leukemia to include interferon.</Para><Para id="_358">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_337" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that vemurafenib or other BRAF inhibitors such as dabrafenib can be given with rituximab or obinutuzumab (cited Park et al. as reference 21).</Para><Para id="_355">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_348" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">Interferon</SummaryRef> as a new subsection.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062926#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of hairy cell leukemia. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewer for Hairy Cell Leukemia Treatment is:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Eric J. Seifter, MD (Johns Hopkins University)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Hairy Cell Leukemia Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/hairy-cell-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389184]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2025-02-21</DateLastModified></Summary>
