<Summary id="CDR0000062938" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Uterine sarcoma treatment is primarily surgery, with or without radiation or chemotherapy. Get detailed information about the treatment options for newly diagnosed or recurrent uterine sarcoma cancer in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/hp/uterine-sarcoma-treatment-pdq">Uterine Sarcoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/patient/uterine-sarcoma-treatment-pdq">Uterine Sarcoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040484">uterine sarcoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_158">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of uterine sarcoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_159">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>uterine sarcoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Uterine Sarcoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Uterine Sarcoma Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Uterine Sarcoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040484">uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Uterine Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_2">Uterine sarcoma accounts for less than 1% of gynecologic malignancies and 2% to 5%
of all uterine malignancies.<Reference refidx="1"/>  The following  tumors arise primarily from three distinct
tissues: </Para><OrderedList id="_83" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Carcinosarcoma arises in the endometrium,  in other organs of mullerian origin, and accounts for 40% to 50% of all uterine sarcomas.</ListItem><ListItem>Leiomyosarcoma arises from myometrial muscle, with a peak incidence occurring at age 50 years, and accounts for 30% of all uterine sarcomas.</ListItem><ListItem>Sarcoma arises in the endometrial stroma, with a peak incidence occurring before menopause for the low-grade tumors and after menopause for the high-grade tumors. It accounts for 15% of all uterine sarcomas.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_84">These three distinct entities are often grouped together as uterine sarcomas; however, each type of tumor is being studied in separate clinical trials.</Para><Para id="_85">Carcinosarcoma (the preferred designation by the World Health Organization [WHO]) is also referred to as mixed mesodermal sarcoma or mullerian tumor. Controversy exists about the following issues: </Para><ItemizedList id="_99" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Whether carcinosarcoma is a true sarcoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether the sarcomatous elements are actually derived from a common epithelial-cell precursor that also gives rise to the usually more abundant adenocarcinomatous elements. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_100">The stromal components of carcinosarcoma are further characterized by homologous elements, such as malignant mesenchymal tissue considered possibly native to the uterus, or heterologous elements, such as striated muscle, cartilage, or bone, which are foreign to the uterus. Carcinosarcoma parallels endometrial cancer in its postmenopausal predominance and in other epidemiological features. Increasingly, the treatment of carcinosarcoma is becoming similar to combined modality approaches for endometrial adenocarcinoma.</Para><Para id="_142">Other rare forms of uterine sarcoma also fall under the WHO classification for mesenchymal and mixed tumors of the uterus.  These sarcomas include the following:<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_143" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Mixed endometrial stromal and smooth muscle tumors.</ListItem><ListItem>Adenosarcomas, in which the epithelial elements appear benign within a malignant mesenchymal background.</ListItem><ListItem>Embryonal botryoides or rhabdomyosarcomas, which are found almost exclusively in infants.</ListItem><ListItem>PEComa—a perivascular epithelial-cell tumor that may behave in a malignant fashion, which is the latest to be added.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_86">  For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062792" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/rhabdomyosarcoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Rhabdomyosarcoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_87"><Title>Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_88">The only documented
etiological factor in 10% to 25% of these malignancies is prior pelvic radiation therapy,
which is often administered for benign uterine bleeding that began 5 to 25 years earlier.
An increased incidence of uterine sarcoma has been associated with tamoxifen in the treatment of breast cancer. Subsequently, increases have also been noted when tamoxifen  was given to prevent breast cancer in women at increased risk—a possible result of the estrogenic effect of tamoxifen on the uterus. Because of this increase, patients taking tamoxifen should have follow-up pelvic examinations and should undergo endometrial biopsy if there is any abnormal uterine bleeding.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_89"><Title>Prognosis</Title><Para id="_144">The prognosis for women with uterine sarcoma primarily depends on the extent of
disease at the time of diagnosis.<Reference refidx="7"/> For women with carcinosarcoma, significant
predictors of metastatic disease at initial surgery include:<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_145" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Isthmic or cervical location.</ListItem><ListItem>Lymphatic vascular space invasion.</ListItem><ListItem>Serous and clear cell histology.</ListItem><ListItem>Grade 2 or 3 carcinoma.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_150">These factors, in addition to the following ones, correlate with a progression-free interval:<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_151" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Adnexal spread.</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph node metastases.</ListItem><ListItem> Tumor size.</ListItem><ListItem>Peritoneal cytologic
findings.</ListItem><ListItem>Depth of myometrial invasion.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_152">Factors that bear no relationship to the presence or absence of metastases at surgical exploration include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_153" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Presence or absence of stromal heterologous elements.</ListItem><ListItem>Types of such elements.</ListItem><ListItem>Grade of the stromal components.</ListItem><ListItem>Mitotic
activity of the stromal components.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3">    In one study, women
with well-differentiated sarcomatous components or carcinosarcomas had
significantly longer progression-free intervals than those with moderately to
poorly differentiated sarcomas for the homologous and heterologous types. 
The recurrence rate was 44% for homologous tumors and 63% for heterologous
tumors.  The type of heterologous sarcoma had no effect on the progression-free
interval.  </Para><Para id="_90">For women with leiomyosarcomas, some investigators consider tumor size to be the most
important prognostic factor. Women with tumors larger than 5.0 cm in maximum
diameter have a poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="8"/>  However, in a Gynecologic Oncology Group
study, the mitotic index was the only factor significantly related to
progression-free interval.<Reference refidx="7"/>  Leiomyosarcomas matched for other known
prognostic factors may be more aggressive than their carcinosarcoma 
counterparts.<Reference refidx="9"/>  The 5-year survival rate for women with stage I disease, which is 
confined to the corpus, is approximately 50% versus 0% to 20% for the remaining
stages.
</Para></SummarySection><Para id="_4">Surgery alone can be curative if the malignancy is contained within the uterus. 
The value of pelvic radiation therapy is not established.  Current studies consist
primarily of phase II chemotherapy trials for patients with advanced disease.  Adjuvant
chemotherapy following complete resection  for patients with stage I or II disease was not found to be effective in a randomized trial.<Reference refidx="10"/>  Yet, nonrandomized
trials have reported improved survival following adjuvant chemotherapy with or
without radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/>
</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Forney JP, Buschbaum HJ: Classifying, staging, and treating uterine sarcomas. Contemp Ob Gyn  18(3):47, 50, 55-56, 61-62, 64, 69, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Gershenson D, McGuire W, Gore Martin, et al.: Gynecologic Cancer: Controversies in Management. 3rd ed. Churchill Livingstone, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Tavassoéli F, Devilee P, et al.: Pathology and Genetics of Tumours of the Breast and Female Genital Organs. International Agency for Research on Cancer, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11036892" MedlineID="20488363">Bergman L, Beelen ML, Gallee MP, et al.: Risk and prognosis of endometrial cancer after tamoxifen for breast cancer. Comprehensive Cancer Centres' ALERT Group. Assessment of Liver and Endometrial cancer Risk following Tamoxifen. Lancet 356 (9233): 881-7, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15297160">Cohen I: Endometrial pathologies associated with postmenopausal tamoxifen treatment. Gynecol Oncol 94 (2): 256-66, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12039943">Wickerham DL, Fisher B, Wolmark N, et al.: Association of tamoxifen and uterine sarcoma. J Clin Oncol 20 (11): 2758-60, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="8381710" MedlineID="93161310">Major FJ, Blessing JA, Silverberg SG, et al.: Prognostic factors in early-stage uterine sarcoma. A Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Cancer 71 (4 Suppl): 1702-9, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="3179938" MedlineID="89028107">Evans HL, Chawla SP, Simpson C, et al.: Smooth muscle neoplasms of the uterus other than ordinary leiomyoma. A study of 46 cases, with emphasis on diagnostic criteria and prognostic factors. Cancer 62 (10): 2239-47, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="1326319" MedlineID="92399365">Oláh KS, Dunn JA, Gee H: Leiomyosarcomas have a poorer prognosis than mixed mesodermal tumours when adjusting for known prognostic factors: the result of a retrospective study of 423 cases of uterine sarcoma. Br J Obstet Gynaecol 99 (7): 590-4, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="3897471" MedlineID="85291965">Omura GA, Blessing JA, Major F, et al.: A randomized clinical trial of adjuvant adriamycin in uterine sarcomas: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 3 (9): 1240-5, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="3045423" MedlineID="88317629">Piver MS, Lele SB, Marchetti DL, et al.: Effect of adjuvant chemotherapy on time to recurrence and survival of stage I uterine sarcomas. J Surg Oncol 38 (4): 233-9, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="3948125" MedlineID="86133123">van Nagell JR, Hanson MB, Donaldson ES, et al.: Adjuvant vincristine, dactinomycin, and cyclophosphamide therapy in stage I uterine sarcomas. A pilot study. Cancer 57 (8): 1451-4, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="2767523" MedlineID="89357623">Peters WA, Rivkin SE, Smith MR, et al.: Cisplatin and adriamycin combination chemotherapy for uterine stromal sarcomas and mixed mesodermal tumors. Gynecol Oncol 34 (3): 323-7, 1989.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040484">uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular Classification of Uterine Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_157">The most common histological types of uterine sarcomas include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_63" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Carcinosarcoma (mixed
mesodermal sarcoma [40%–50%]).</ListItem><ListItem>Leiomyosarcoma (30%).</ListItem><ListItem>Endometrial stromal
sarcoma (15%).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_7">The uterine neoplasm classification of the International Society of
Gynecologic Pathologists and the World Health Organization uses the term <Strong>carcinosarcoma</Strong> for all primary uterine
neoplasms containing malignant elements of both epithelial and stromal light
microscopic appearances, regardless of whether malignant heterologous
elements are present.<Reference refidx="1"/>
</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2152890" MedlineID="90093651">Silverberg SG, Major FJ, Blessing JA, et al.: Carcinosarcoma (malignant mixed mesodermal tumor) of the uterus. A Gynecologic Oncology Group pathologic study of 203 cases. Int J Gynecol Pathol 9 (1): 1-19, 1990.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040484">uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Uterine Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_124"><Title>FIGO Staging</Title><Para id="_125">The Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique (FIGO) and the American Joint Committee on Cancer have designated staging to define uterine
sarcoma; the FIGO system is most commonly used.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_126">The FIGO staging system has two divisions, one for
leiomyosarcoma and endometrial stromal sarcoma, and one for
adenosarcoma. Carcinosarcoma is staged using the designated endometrial
carcinoma definitions. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062903" url="/types/uterine/hp/endometrial-treatment-pdq">Endometrial Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Table id="_165"><Title>Table 1.  FIGO Definitions of Uterine Sarcoma–Leiomyosarcoma and Endometrial Stromal Sarcoma<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.57%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="74.42%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage</entry><entry>Definition</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from the Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.<Reference refidx="1"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>I</entry><entry>Tumor limited to uterus.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IA</entry><entry>Tumor ≤5 cm.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IB</entry><entry>Tumor &gt;5 cm.</entry></Row><Row><entry>II</entry><entry>Tumor extends beyond the uterus,
within the pelvis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIA</entry><entry>Adnexal involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIB</entry><entry>Involvement of other pelvic tissues.</entry></Row><Row><entry>III</entry><entry>Tumor invades abdominal tissues (not
just protruding into the abdomen).</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIIA</entry><entry>One site.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIIB</entry><entry>More than one site.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIIC</entry><entry>Metastasis to pelvic and/or para-aortic
lymph nodes.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IV</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>–IVA</entry><entry>Tumor invades bladder and/or rectum.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IVB</entry><entry>Distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_166"><Title>Table 2.  FIGO Definitions of Uterine Sarcoma–Adenosarcoma<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.31%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="74.68%"/><THead><Row><entry>Stage</entry><entry>Definition</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">FIGO = Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from the Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique.<Reference refidx="1"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>I</entry><entry>Tumor limited to uterus.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IA</entry><entry>Tumor limited to endometrium/endocervix with no myometrial invasion.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IB</entry><entry>Less than or equal to half myometrial
invasion.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IC</entry><entry>More than half myometrial invasion.</entry></Row><Row><entry>II</entry><entry>Tumor extends to the pelvis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIA</entry><entry>Adnexal involvement.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIB</entry><entry>Tumor extends to extrauterine pelvic
tissue.</entry></Row><Row><entry>III</entry><entry>Tumor invades abdominal tissues (not
just protruding into the abdomen).</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIIA</entry><entry>One site.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIIB</entry><entry>More than one site.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IIIC</entry><entry>Metastasis to pelvic and/or para-aortic
lymph nodes.</entry></Row><Row><entry>IV</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>–IVA</entry><entry>Tumor invades bladder and/or rectum.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–IVB</entry><entry>Distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="30306577">Mbatani N, Olawaiye AB, Prat J: Uterine sarcomas. Int J Gynaecol Obstet 143 (Suppl 2): 51-58, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Corpus uteri – sarcoma. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 8th ed. Springer; 2017, pp 671-80.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_24"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040484">uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Uterine Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_25">Surgery is often the principal means of diagnosis and is the primary treatment for all patients with uterine sarcoma. If the diagnosis is known, the extent of surgery is planned according to the stage of the tumor.  Hysterectomy is usually performed when a uterine malignancy is suspected, except for rare instances when preservation of the uterus in a young patient is deemed safe for the type of cancer (e.g., a totally confined low-grade leiomyosarcoma in a woman who desires to retain childbearing potential).  Medically suitable patients with the preoperative diagnosis of uterine sarcoma
are considered candidates for abdominal hysterectomy, bilateral
salpingo-oophorectomy, and pelvic and periaortic selective lymphadenectomy. 
Cytologic washings are obtained from the pelvis and abdomen.  Thorough
examination of the diaphragm, omentum, and upper abdomen is performed.
</Para><Para id="_26">There is no firm evidence from a prospective study that adjuvant chemotherapy
or radiation therapy is of benefit for patients with uterine sarcoma.<Reference refidx="1"/> 
In one Gynecologic Oncology Group (GOG) study, the use of adjuvant doxorubicin did not alter the survival rate of patients with resected stage I or stage II uterine sarcomas; however, interpretation of these results is difficult because this study included some patients who received radiation and three types of uterine sarcomas that have variable responses to doxorubicin.<Reference refidx="1"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] Because the risk of disease recurrence is high, even with localized
presentations, many physicians have considered the use of adjuvant chemotherapy
or radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="2"/>
Another GOG   study  (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00002546">GOG-0150</ProtocolRef> [NCT00002546]) addressed radiation therapy versus adjuvant chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3897471" MedlineID="85291965">Omura GA, Blessing JA, Major F, et al.: A randomized clinical trial of adjuvant adriamycin in uterine sarcomas: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 3 (9): 1240-5, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="3002919" MedlineID="86109714">Kohorn EI, Schwartz PE, Chambers JT, et al.: Adjuvant therapy in mixed mullerian tumors of the uterus. Gynecol Oncol 23 (2): 212-21, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="17822748">Wolfson AH, Brady MF, Rocereto T, et al.: A gynecologic oncology group randomized phase III trial of whole abdominal irradiation (WAI) vs. cisplatin-ifosfamide and mesna (CIM) as post-surgical therapy in stage I-IV carcinosarcoma (CS) of the uterus. Gynecol Oncol 107 (2): 177-85, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041011">stage I uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage I Uterine Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_169"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage I Uterine Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_170">Treatment options for stage I uterine sarcoma include:</Para><OrderedList id="_171" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Surgery (total abdominal hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, and
pelvic and periaortic selective lymphadenectomy).
</ListItem><ListItem> Surgery plus pelvic radiation therapy.
</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery plus adjuvant chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery plus adjuvant radiation therapy.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_172">A nonrandomized Gynecologic Oncology Group study examined the effect of pelvic radiation therapy on patients with stage I
and II carcinosarcomas. Patients who had pelvic radiation therapy had a significant
reduction in tumor recurrences within the radiation treatment field but no alteration
in survival.<Reference refidx="1"/>  A large nonrandomized study demonstrated improved survival and
a lower local failure rate in patients with mixed mullerian tumors following
postoperative external and intracavitary radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="2"/>  One
nonrandomized study that predominantly included patients with carcinosarcomas showed that adjuvant chemotherapy with cisplatin
and doxorubicin benefitted participants.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_28_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_28_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3793549" MedlineID="87083034">Hornback NB, Omura G, Major FJ: Observations on the use of adjuvant radiation therapy in patients with stage I and II uterine sarcoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 12 (12): 2127-30, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2157241" MedlineID="90207727">Larson B, Silfverswärd C, Nilsson B, et al.: Mixed müllerian tumours of the uterus--prognostic factors: a clinical and histopathologic study of 147 cases. Radiother Oncol 17 (2): 123-32, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2767523" MedlineID="89357623">Peters WA, Rivkin SE, Smith MR, et al.: Cisplatin and adriamycin combination chemotherapy for uterine stromal sarcomas and mixed mesodermal tumors. Gynecol Oncol 34 (3): 323-7, 1989.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041012">stage II uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage II Uterine Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_173"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage II Uterine Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_174">Treatment options for stage II uterine sarcoma include:</Para><OrderedList id="_175" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Surgery (total abdominal hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, and
pelvic and periaortic selective lymphadenectomy).
</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery plus pelvic radiation therapy.
</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery plus adjuvant chemotherapy.
</ListItem><ListItem> Surgery plus adjuvant radiation therapy.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_176">A nonrandomized Gynecologic Oncology Group study examined the effect of pelvic radiation therapy on patients with stage I
and II carcinosarcomas. Patients who had pelvic radiation therapy had a significant
reduction in tumor recurrences within the radiation treatment field but no alteration
in survival.<Reference refidx="1"/>  One
nonrandomized study that predominantly included patients with carcinosarcomas showed that adjuvant chemotherapy with cisplatin
and doxorubicin benefitted participants.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_35_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_35_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3793549" MedlineID="87083034">Hornback NB, Omura G, Major FJ: Observations on the use of adjuvant radiation therapy in patients with stage I and II uterine sarcoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 12 (12): 2127-30, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2767523" MedlineID="89357623">Peters WA, Rivkin SE, Smith MR, et al.: Cisplatin and adriamycin combination chemotherapy for uterine stromal sarcomas and mixed mesodermal tumors. Gynecol Oncol 34 (3): 323-7, 1989.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041013">stage III uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III Uterine Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_177"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage III Uterine Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_178">Treatment options for stage III uterine sarcoma include:</Para><OrderedList id="_179" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Surgery (total abdominal hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy,
pelvic and periaortic selective lymphadenectomy, and resection of all gross
tumor).</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery plus pelvic radiation therapy (under clinical evaluation).</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery plus adjuvant chemotherapy (under clinical evaluation).</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Para id="_47">Phase II chemotherapy studies by the Gynecologic Oncology Group have documented some antitumor activity for cisplatin, doxorubicin, and ifosfamide.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  These studies have also documented differences in response leading to separate trials for patients with carcinosarcomas and leiomyosarcomas.  In  patients previously untreated with chemotherapy,
ifosfamide had a 32.2% response rate in patients  with carcinosarcomas <Reference refidx="3"/> and a 17.2%
partial response rate in patients with leiomyosarcomas.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_75">GOG-108 was a randomized trial that examined the use of ifosfamide with or without cisplatin as first-line therapy for patients with measurable advanced or recurrent carcinosarcomas. Patients in the combination arm had a higher response rate (54% vs. 34%) and longer progression-free survival (PFS) (6 months   vs. 4 months). However, patients did not have a significant improvement in survival (9 months vs. 8 months).<Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] The follow-up <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00003128">GOG-0161</ProtocolRef> study
[NCT00003128]
used 3-day ifosfamide regimens (instead of the more toxic 5-day regimen in the preceding study) given alone or in combination with paclitaxel (with filgrastim starting on day 4).<Reference refidx="5"/> The combination was superior in response rates (45% vs. 29%), PFS (8.4 months vs. 5.8 months), and overall survival (13.5 months vs. 8.4 months). The hazard ratio for death favored the combination (0.69; 95% confidence interval, 0.49–0.97).<Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] In this study, 52% of 179 evaluable patients had recurrent disease, 18% had stage III disease, and 30% had stage IV disease.  In addition, imbalances were present in the sites of disease and in the use of prior radiation therapy, and 30 patients were excluded for wrong pathology. 
</Para><Para id="_78">A role for chemotherapy as an adjuvant to surgery has not been established.</Para><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_42_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_42_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1941054" MedlineID="92044710">Thigpen JT, Blessing JA, Beecham J, et al.: Phase II trial of cisplatin as first-line chemotherapy in patients with advanced or recurrent uterine sarcomas: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 9 (11): 1962-6, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1536229" MedlineID="92160896">Sutton GP, Blessing JA, Barrett RJ, et al.: Phase II trial of ifosfamide and mesna in leiomyosarcoma of the uterus: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Am J Obstet Gynecol 166 (2): 556-9, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2548382" MedlineID="89349247">Sutton GP, Blessing JA, Rosenshein N, et al.: Phase II trial of ifosfamide and mesna in mixed mesodermal tumors of the uterus (a Gynecologic Oncology Group study). Am J Obstet Gynecol 161 (2): 309-12, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11063636" MedlineID="20519489">Sutton G, Brunetto VL, Kilgore L, et al.: A phase III trial of ifosfamide with or without cisplatin in carcinosarcoma of the uterus: A Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. Gynecol Oncol 79 (2): 147-53, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="17290061">Homesley HD, Filiaci V, Markman M, et al.: Phase III trial of ifosfamide with or without paclitaxel in advanced uterine carcinosarcoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 25 (5): 526-31, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041014">stage IV uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IV Uterine Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_181"><Title>Treatment Options for Stage IV Uterine Sarcoma</Title></SummarySection><Para id="_64">There is currently no standard therapy for patients with stage IV disease. 
These patients should enroll in an ongoing clinical trial.</Para><Para id="_49">    Phase II chemotherapy studies by the Gynecologic Oncology Group have documented some antitumor activity for cisplatin, doxorubicin, and ifosfamide.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  These studies have also documented differences in response leading to separate trials for patients with carcinosarcomas and leiomyosarcomas.  In patients
previously untreated with chemotherapy, ifosfamide had a 32.2% response rate in
patients with carcinosarcomas,<Reference refidx="2"/> a 33% response rate in patients with endometrial stromal cell
sarcomas,<Reference refidx="3"/>, and a 17.2% partial response rate in patients with leiomyosarcomas.<Reference refidx="4"/>   Doxorubicin
in combination with dacarbazine or cyclophosphamide is no more active than
doxorubicin alone for advanced disease.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  Cisplatin has activity as
first-line therapy and minimal activity as second-line therapy for patients
with carcinosarcomas, but cisplatin is inactive as first- or
second-line therapy for patients with leiomyosarcomas.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_76">GOG-108 was a randomized trial that examined the use of ifosfamide with or without cisplatin as first-line therapy for patients with measurable advanced or recurrent carcinosarcomas. Patients in the combination arm had a higher response rate (54% vs. 34%) and longer progression-free survival (PFS) (6 months   vs. 4 months). However, patients did not have a significant improvement in survival (9 months vs. 8 months).<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] The follow-up <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00003128">GOG-0161</ProtocolRef> study 
[NCT00003128] used 3-day ifosfamide regimens (instead of the more toxic 5-day regimen in the preceding study) given alone or in combination with paclitaxel (with filgrastim starting on day 4).<Reference refidx="9"/> The combination was superior in response rates (45% vs. 29%), PFS (8.4 months vs. 5.8 months), and overall survival (13.5 months vs. 8.4 months). The hazard ratio for death favored the combination (0.69; 95% confidence interval, 0.49–0.97).<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] In this study, 52% of 179 evaluable patients had recurrent disease, 18% had stage III disease, and 30% had stage IV disease.  In addition, imbalances were present in the sites of disease and in the use of prior radiation therapy, and 30 patients were excluded for wrong pathology. 
</Para><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_48_sid_8"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_48_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1941054" MedlineID="92044710">Thigpen JT, Blessing JA, Beecham J, et al.: Phase II trial of cisplatin as first-line chemotherapy in patients with advanced or recurrent uterine sarcomas: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 9 (11): 1962-6, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2548382" MedlineID="89349247">Sutton GP, Blessing JA, Rosenshein N, et al.: Phase II trial of ifosfamide and mesna in mixed mesodermal tumors of the uterus (a Gynecologic Oncology Group study). Am J Obstet Gynecol 161 (2): 309-12, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8677079" MedlineID="96200610">Sutton G, Blessing JA, Park R, et al.: Ifosfamide treatment of recurrent or metastatic endometrial stromal sarcomas previously unexposed to chemotherapy: a study of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. Obstet Gynecol 87 (5 Pt 1): 747-50, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1536229" MedlineID="92160896">Sutton GP, Blessing JA, Barrett RJ, et al.: Phase II trial of ifosfamide and mesna in leiomyosarcoma of the uterus: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Am J Obstet Gynecol 166 (2): 556-9, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="6344983" MedlineID="83232642">Omura GA, Major FJ, Blessing JA, et al.: A randomized study of adriamycin with and without dimethyl triazenoimidazole carboxamide in advanced uterine sarcomas. Cancer 52 (4): 626-32, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="3884128" MedlineID="85151591">Muss HB, Bundy B, DiSaia PJ, et al.: Treatment of recurrent or advanced uterine sarcoma. A randomized trial of doxorubicin versus doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide (a phase III trial of the Gynecologic Oncology Group). Cancer 55 (8): 1648-53, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3953489" MedlineID="86155591">Thigpen JT, Blessing JA, Wilbanks GD: Cisplatin as second-line chemotherapy in the treatment of advanced or recurrent leiomyosarcoma of the uterus. A phase II trial of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. Am J Clin Oncol 9 (1): 18-20, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11063636" MedlineID="20519489">Sutton G, Brunetto VL, Kilgore L, et al.: A phase III trial of ifosfamide with or without cisplatin in carcinosarcoma of the uterus: A Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. Gynecol Oncol 79 (2): 147-53, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="17290061">Homesley HD, Filiaci V, Markman M, et al.: Phase III trial of ifosfamide with or without paclitaxel in advanced uterine carcinosarcoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 25 (5): 526-31, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041015">recurrent uterine sarcoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Uterine Sarcoma</Title><SummarySection id="_182"><Title>Treatment Options for Recurrent Uterine Sarcoma</Title><Para id="_65">There is currently no standard therapy for patients with recurrent disease. 
These patients should enroll in an ongoing clinical trial. </Para><Para id="_51">      Phase II chemotherapy studies by the Gynecologic Oncology Group have documented some antitumor activity for cisplatin, doxorubicin, and ifosfamide.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  These studies have also documented differences in response leading to separate trials for patients with carcinosarcomas and leiomyosarcomas.  In patients previously untreated with chemotherapy, ifosfamide had a 32.2% response rate in
patients with carcinosarcomas,<Reference refidx="2"/> a 33% response rate in patients with endometrial stromal cell sarcomas,<Reference refidx="3"/> and a 17.2% partial response rate in patients with leiomyosarcomas.<Reference refidx="4"/>  Doxorubicin
in combination with dacarbazine or cyclophosphamide is no more active than
doxorubicin alone for recurrent disease.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  Cisplatin has activity as
first-line therapy and minimal activity as second-line therapy for patients
with carcinosarcomas, but cisplatin is inactive as first- or
second-line therapy for patients with  leiomyosarcomas.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  A regimen of gemcitabine plus docetaxel had a 53% response rate in patients with unresectable leiomyosarcomas and is undergoing further study.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_77">GOG-108 was a randomized trial that examined the use of ifosfamide with or without cisplatin as first-line therapy for patients with measurable advanced or recurrent carcinosarcomas. Patients in the combination arm had a higher response rate (54% vs. 34%) and longer progression-free survival (PFS) (6 months   vs. 4 months). However, patients did not have a significant improvement in survival (9 months vs. 8 months).<Reference refidx="9"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] The follow-up <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00003128">GOG-0161</ProtocolRef> study 
[NCT00003128] used 3-day ifosfamide regimens (instead of the more toxic 5-day regimen in the preceding study) given alone or in combination with paclitaxel (with filgrastim starting on day 4).<Reference refidx="10"/> The combination was superior in response rates (45% vs. 29%), PFS (8.4 months vs. 5.8 months), and overall survival (13.5 months vs. 8.4 months). The hazard ratio for death favored the combination (0.69; 95% confidence interval, 0.49–0.97).<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] In this study, 52% of 179 evaluable patients had recurrent disease, 18% had stage III disease, and 30% had stage IV disease.  In addition, imbalances were present in the sites of disease and in the use of prior radiation therapy, and 30 patients were excluded for wrong pathology. 
</Para><Para id="_52">Radiation therapy may be an effective
method of palliative care for patients with carcinosarcoma who have localized recurrence in the pelvis
confirmed by computed tomography.  Phase I and II clinical trials are appropriate for patients who
have disease recurrence with distant metastasis and are unresponsive to first-line phase II
trials.  High-dose progesterone hormone therapy may be of some benefit to
patients with low-grade stromal sarcoma.<Reference refidx="11"/>
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_50_sid_9"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_50_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1941054" MedlineID="92044710">Thigpen JT, Blessing JA, Beecham J, et al.: Phase II trial of cisplatin as first-line chemotherapy in patients with advanced or recurrent uterine sarcomas: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol 9 (11): 1962-6, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2548382" MedlineID="89349247">Sutton GP, Blessing JA, Rosenshein N, et al.: Phase II trial of ifosfamide and mesna in mixed mesodermal tumors of the uterus (a Gynecologic Oncology Group study). Am J Obstet Gynecol 161 (2): 309-12, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8677079" MedlineID="96200610">Sutton G, Blessing JA, Park R, et al.: Ifosfamide treatment of recurrent or metastatic endometrial stromal sarcomas previously unexposed to chemotherapy: a study of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. Obstet Gynecol 87 (5 Pt 1): 747-50, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1536229" MedlineID="92160896">Sutton GP, Blessing JA, Barrett RJ, et al.: Phase II trial of ifosfamide and mesna in leiomyosarcoma of the uterus: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Am J Obstet Gynecol 166 (2): 556-9, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="6344983" MedlineID="83232642">Omura GA, Major FJ, Blessing JA, et al.: A randomized study of adriamycin with and without dimethyl triazenoimidazole carboxamide in advanced uterine sarcomas. Cancer 52 (4): 626-32, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="3884128" MedlineID="85151591">Muss HB, Bundy B, DiSaia PJ, et al.: Treatment of recurrent or advanced uterine sarcoma. A randomized trial of doxorubicin versus doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide (a phase III trial of the Gynecologic Oncology Group). Cancer 55 (8): 1648-53, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3953489" MedlineID="86155591">Thigpen JT, Blessing JA, Wilbanks GD: Cisplatin as second-line chemotherapy in the treatment of advanced or recurrent leiomyosarcoma of the uterus. A phase II trial of the Gynecologic Oncology Group. Am J Clin Oncol 9 (1): 18-20, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12065559" MedlineID="22060840">Hensley ML, Maki R, Venkatraman E, et al.: Gemcitabine and docetaxel in patients with unresectable leiomyosarcoma: results of a phase II trial. J Clin Oncol 20 (12): 2824-31, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="11063636" MedlineID="20519489">Sutton G, Brunetto VL, Kilgore L, et al.: A phase III trial of ifosfamide with or without cisplatin in carcinosarcoma of the uterus: A Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. Gynecol Oncol 79 (2): 147-53, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="17290061">Homesley HD, Filiaci V, Markman M, et al.: Phase III trial of ifosfamide with or without paclitaxel in advanced uterine carcinosarcoma: a Gynecologic Oncology Group Study. J Clin Oncol 25 (5): 526-31, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="3792939" MedlineID="87081575">Katz L, Merino MJ, Sakamoto H, et al.: Endometrial stromal sarcoma: a clinicopathologic study of 11 cases with determination of estrogen and progestin receptor levels in three tumors. Gynecol Oncol 26 (1): 87-97, 1987.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (12/17/2024)</Title><Para id="_71">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_180">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062938#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/uterine/hp/uterine-sarcoma-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of uterine sarcoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewer for Uterine Sarcoma Treatment is:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Marina Stasenko, MD (New York University Medical Center)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Uterine Sarcoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/hp/uterine-sarcoma-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/uterine/hp/uterine-sarcoma-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389327]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-12-17</DateLastModified></Summary>
