<Summary id="CDR0000062931" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer treatment often is a combination of surgery and radiation therapy for operable tumors. Chemotherapy may be used as palliation in recurrent disease. Get detailed treatment information for newly diagnosed and recurrent disease in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040127">paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_320">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of adult paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_321">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adult paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040127">paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_308"><Title>Incidence and Mortality</Title><Para id="_2">Most tumors of the paranasal sinuses present with advanced disease,
and cure rates are generally poor (≤50%).  Squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) is the most frequent
type of malignant tumor in the nose and paranasal sinuses (70%–80%). 
Papillomas are distinct entities that may undergo malignant degeneration.  The
cancers grow within the bony confines of the sinuses and are often asymptomatic
until they erode and invade adjacent structures.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>
</Para><Para id="_314">Nodal involvement is
infrequent.  Metastases from both  the nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses may occur, and distant metastases are found in 20% to 40% of
patients who do not respond to treatment. However, locoregional recurrence accounts for most cancer deaths because most patients die of direct extension into vital areas of the skull or of
rapidly recurring local disease.</Para><Para id="_315">Cancers of the maxillary sinus are the most common of the paranasal sinus
cancers.  Tumors of the ethmoid sinuses, nasal vestibule, and nasal cavity are
less common, and tumors of the sphenoid and frontal sinuses are rare.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_316"><Title>Anatomy</Title><Para id="_317">The major lymphatic drainage route of the maxillary antrum is through the
lateral and inferior collecting trunks to the first station submandibular,
parotid, and jugulodigastric nodes and through the superoposterior trunk to
retropharyngeal and jugular nodes.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_309"><Title>Clinical Evaluation and Follow-Up</Title><Para id="_3">Pretreatment evaluation and staging, as well as the need for
multidisciplinary planning of treatment, is very important.  Generally, the
first opportunity to treat patients with head and neck cancers is the most
effective, although salvage surgery or salvage radiation therapy,
as appropriate, may occasionally be successful.  </Para><Para id="_345">Because most treatment failures occur
within 2 years, patients must be monitored frequently and meticulously
during this period.  Lifetime follow-up is essential because nearly 33% of these patients
develop second primary cancers in the aerodigestive tract.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_311"><Title>Carcinogenesis and Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_6">Data indicate that various industrial exposures may be related to cancer
of the paranasal sinus and nasal cavity.  The risk of a second primary head and
neck tumor is considerably increased.<Reference refidx="4"/> A study has shown that a subgroup of paranasal sinus and nasal cavity SCCs are associated with human papilloma  virus (HPV) infection and that HPV-positive patients   may have a better prognosis than those who are HPV negative.<Reference refidx="5"/>
</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Laramore GE, ed.: Radiation Therapy of Head and Neck Cancer. Springer-Verlag, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Thawley SE, Panje WR, Batsakis JG, et al., eds.: Comprehensive Management of Head and Neck Tumors. 2nd ed. WB Saunders, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Johns ME, Kaplan MJ: Advances in the management of paranasal sinus tumors. In: Wolf GT, ed.: Head and Neck Oncology. Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 1984, pp 27-52.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="19365846">Alos L, Moyano S, Nadal A, et al.: Human papillomaviruses are identified in a subgroup of sinonasal squamous cell carcinomas with favorable outcome. Cancer 115 (12): 2701-9, 2009.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040127">paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular Classification of Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</Title><Para id="_8">The most common cell type for paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancers is
squamous cell carcinoma.  Minor salivary gland tumors comprise 10% to 15% of
these neoplasms.  Malignant melanoma presents in less than 1% of neoplasms in
this region.  Some 5% of cases are  malignant lymphomas.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>
</Para><Para id="_9">Esthesioneuroepithelioma, sometimes confused with undifferentiated carcinoma or
undifferentiated lymphoma, arises from the olfactory nerves.<Reference refidx="3"/>
</Para><Para id="_10">Chondrosarcoma, osteosarcoma, Ewing sarcoma, and most soft tissue sarcomas
have been reported for this region.
</Para><Para id="_11">Inverting papilloma is considered a low-grade benign tumor with a tendency to
recur and, in a small percentage of cases, to transform into a malignant tumor.
</Para><Para id="_12">Midline granuloma, a progressively destructive condition, also involves this region.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11338653" MedlineID="21237326">Goldenberg D, Golz A, Fradis M, et al.: Malignant tumors of the nose and paranasal sinuses: a retrospective review of 291 cases. Ear Nose Throat J 80 (4): 272-7, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="17372086">Jethanamest D, Morris LG, Sikora AG, et al.: Esthesioneuroblastoma: a population-based analysis of survival and prognostic factors. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 133 (3): 276-80, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040127">paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</Title><Para id="_14">The staging systems are clinical estimates of the extent of disease.  The
assessment of the tumor is based on inspection, palpation, and direct endoscopy
when necessary.  The tumor must be confirmed histologically, and any other
pathological data obtained on biopsy may be included.  The appropriate nodal
drainage areas are examined by careful palpation.  Computed tomographic and/or
magnetic resonance imaging studies are generally required to adequately
evaluate tumor extent before surgical resection or definitive
radiation therapy.  If a patient's disease relapses, complete restaging must be done to select the appropriate additional therapy.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>
</Para><SummarySection id="_286"><Title>American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) Stage Groupings and TNM Definitions</Title><Para id="_283">Staging for nasal cavity and paranasal sinus carcinomas is not as well
established as staging for other head and neck tumors.  For cancer of the maxillary sinus, the nasal cavity,  and the ethmoid sinus, the
AJCC has designated staging by TNM (tumor, node, metastasis) classification. Lymphomas, sarcomas, and mucosal melanomas of the paranasal sinuses and nasal cavity are not staged using this system.<Reference refidx="3"/> The staging described below is used only for patients who have not had a lymph node dissection of the neck.</Para><Table id="_334"><Title>Table 1.  Definition of Primary Tumor (T)<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">T Category </entry><entry Align="Center">Maxillary Sinus T Criteria </entry><entry Align="Center">Nasal Cavity and Ethmoid 
Sinus T Criteria 
</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 137–47.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>TX</entry><entry>Primary tumor cannot be assessed.</entry><entry>Primary tumor cannot be assessed.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Tis</entry><entry>Carcinoma <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis>.</entry><entry>Carcinoma <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T1</entry><entry>Tumor limited to maxillary sinus mucosa with no erosion or destruction of bone.</entry><entry>Tumor restricted to any one subsite, with or without bony invasion.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T2</entry><entry>Tumor causing bone erosion or destruction including extension into the hard palate and/or middle nasal meatus, except extension to posterior wall of maxillary sinus and pterygoid plates.</entry><entry>Tumor invading two subsites in a single region or extending to involve an adjacent region within the nasoethmoidal complex, with or without bony invasion.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T3</entry><entry>Tumor invades any of the following: bone of the posterior wall of maxillary sinus, subcutaneous tissues, floor or medial wall of orbit, pterygoid fossa, ethmoid sinuses.</entry><entry>Tumor extends to invade the medial wall or floor of the orbit, maxillary sinus, palate, or cribriform plate.</entry></Row><Row><entry>T4</entry><entry>Moderately advanced or very advanced local disease.</entry><entry>Moderately advanced or very advanced local disease.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–T4a</entry><entry>Moderately advanced local disease. Tumor invades anterior orbital contents, skin of cheek, pterygoid plates, infratemporal fossa, cribriform plate, sphenoid or frontal sinuses. </entry><entry>Moderately advanced local disease. Tumor invades any of the following: anterior orbital contents, skin of nose or cheek, minimal extension to anterior cranial fossa, pterygoid plates, sphenoid or frontal sinuses.</entry></Row><Row><entry>–T4b</entry><entry>Very advanced local disease. Tumor invades any of the following: orbital apex, dura, brain, middle cranial fossa, cranial nerves other than maxillary division of trigeminal nerve (V2), nasopharynx, or clivus.</entry><entry>Very advanced local disease. Tumor invades any of the following: orbital apex, dura, brain, middle cranial fossa, cranial nerves other than V2, nasopharynx, or clivus.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_343"><Title>Table 2.  Definition of Regional Lymph Node (N)<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="50.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>N Category </entry><entry>Clinical Node (cN) Criteria </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">ENE = extranodal extension.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 137–47.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">Note: A designation of “U” or “L” may be used for any N category to indicate metastasis above the lower border of the cricoid (U) or below the lower border of the cricoid (L).</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>NX</entry><entry>Regional lymph nodes cannot be assessed. </entry></Row><Row><entry>N0</entry><entry>No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N1</entry><entry>Metastasis in a single ipsilateral lymph node, ≤3 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒).</entry></Row><Row><entry>N2</entry><entry>Metastasis in a single ipsilateral node &gt;3 cm but ≤6 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒); <Emphasis>or</Emphasis> metastases in multiple ipsilateral lymph nodes, none &gt;6 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒); <Emphasis>or</Emphasis> in bilateral or contralateral lymph nodes, none &gt;6 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒).</entry></Row><Row><entry>–N2a</entry><entry>Metastasis in a single ipsilateral node &gt;3 cm but ≤6 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒).</entry></Row><Row><entry>–N2b</entry><entry>Metastases in multiple ipsilateral nodes, none &gt;6 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒).</entry></Row><Row><entry>–N2c</entry><entry>Metastases in bilateral or contralateral lymph nodes, none &gt;6 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒).</entry></Row><Row><entry>N3</entry><entry>Metastasis in a lymph node &gt;6 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒); <Emphasis>or</Emphasis> metastasis in any node(s) with clinically overt ENE(+).</entry></Row><Row><entry>–N3a</entry><entry>Metastasis in a lymph node &gt;6 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒).</entry></Row><Row><entry>–N3b</entry><entry>Metastasis in any node(s) with clinically overt ENE (ENEc).</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_344"><Title>Table 3.  Definition of Distant Metastasis (M)<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="2"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="12.50%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="87.50%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">M Category</entry><entry Align="Center">M Criteria</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 137–47.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>M0</entry><entry>No distant metastasis (no pathologic M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row><Row><entry>M1</entry><entry>Distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_332"><Title>Table 4.  Definition of TNM Stage 0<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="22.56%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="18.34%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="59.08%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 137–47.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="2">0</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Tis, N0, M0</entry><entry>Tis = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_333"><Title>Table 5.  Definition of TNM Stage I<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="22.12%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="27.87%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="50.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col2" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 137–47.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="2">I</entry><entry MoreRows="2">T1, N0, M0</entry><entry>T1 = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_336"><Title>Table 6.  Definition of TNM Stage II<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.15%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="17.36%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="49.47%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 137–47.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="2">II</entry><entry MoreRows="2">T2, N0, M0</entry><entry>T2 = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_337"><Title>Table 7.  Definitions of TNM Stage III<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="11.23%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="21.91%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="66.85%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis; ENE = extranodal extension.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 137–47.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="5">III</entry><entry MoreRows="2">T3, N0, M0 </entry><entry>T3 = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0 = No regional lymph node metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T1, T2, T3; N1, M0</entry><entry>T1, T2, T3 = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N1 = Metastasis in a single ipsilateral lymph node, ≤3 cm in greatest dimension and ENE(‒).</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_338"><Title>Table 8.  Definitions of TNM Stage IVA, IVB, and IVC<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="10.19%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="20.18%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="69.62%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">TNM</entry><entry Align="Center">Description</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">T = primary tumor; N = regional lymph node; M = distant metastasis.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted with permission from AJCC: Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp 137–47.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="5">IVA</entry><entry MoreRows="2">T4a; N0, N1; M0 </entry><entry>T4a = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N0, N1 = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_343" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">2</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T1, T2, T3, T4a; N2, M0</entry><entry>T1, T2, T3, T4a  = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N2 = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_343" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">2</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="5">IVB</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Any T, N3, M0 </entry><entry>Any T = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>N3 = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_343" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">2</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">T4b, Any N, M0</entry><entry>T4b = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Any N = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_343" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">2</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M0 = No distant metastasis (no pathological M0; use clinical M to complete stage group).</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="2">IVC</entry><entry MoreRows="2">Any T, Any N, M1</entry><entry>Any T = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_334" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">1</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>Any N = See Table <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_343" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">2</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry>M1 = Distant metastasis.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Laramore GE, ed.: Radiation Therapy of Head and Neck Cancer. Springer-Verlag, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 8th ed. Springer; 2017, pp 137-47.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_54"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040127">paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</Title><Para id="_55">Except for patients with T1 mucosal carcinomas, the accepted method of treatment is a
combination of radiation therapy and surgery.  The incidence of lymph node
metastases is generally low (approximately 20% of cases).  Thus, routine
radical neck dissection or elective neck radiation therapy is recommended only for
patients presenting with positive nodes.  
</Para><Para id="_210">For patients with operable tumors,
radical surgery is generally performed first to remove the bulk of the tumor
and to establish drainage of the affected sinus(es).  This is followed by
postoperative radiation therapy.  Some institutions continue to give a full
dose of radiation therapy preoperatively for all patients with stage II and stage III tumors and
operate 4 to 6 weeks later.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  A review of published clinical results of
radical radiation therapy for head and neck cancer suggested a significant loss
of local control with prolonged radiation therapy;
therefore, lengthening of standard treatment schedules should be avoided
whenever possible.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><SummarySection id="_211"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_292">Surgical exploration may be required to determine operability.</Para><Para id="_212">   Relative contraindications to surgery include destruction of
the base of the skull (i.e., anterior cranial fossa), cavernous sinus, or the pterygoid
process; infiltration of the mucous membranes of the nasopharynx; or
nonresectable lymph node metastases. 
Surgical approaches include fenestration with removal of the bulk tumor, which
is usually followed by radiation therapy or block resection of the upper jaw. 
A combined craniofacial approach, including resection of the floor of the
anterior cranial fossa, has been used with success in selected patients.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Removal of
the eye is performed if the orbit is extensively invaded by cancer.  Clinically
positive nodes, if resectable, may be treated with radical neck dissection.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_213"><Title>Radiation Therapy</Title><Para id="_214">Radiation therapy must be carried to high doses for any significant probability
of permanent control.  The treatment volume must include all of the maxillary
antrum and involved hemiparanasal sinus and contiguous areas.  The orbit and
its contents are excluded except under unusual circumstances.  Lymph nodes of
the neck, when palpable, should be treated in conjunction with treatment of
advanced carcinomas of the antrum.  This may be unnecessary for early tumors.</Para><Para id="_215">Accumulating evidence has demonstrated a high incidence (&gt;30%–40%) of
hypothyroidism in patients who have received external-beam radiation therapy to the
entire thyroid gland or to the pituitary gland.  Thyroid function testing of
patients should be considered prior to therapy and as part of posttreatment
follow-up.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_216"><Title>Recurrent Disease</Title><Para id="_217">Patients with recurrent disease should consider chemotherapy clinical trials. 
Chemotherapy for recurrent squamous cell cancer of the head and neck has been
shown to be efficacious as palliation and may improve a patient's quality of life and
length of survival.  Various drug combinations, including cisplatin,
fluorouracil, and methotrexate, are effective.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_60">Treatment of tumors of the paranasal sinuses and of the nasal cavity should be
planned on an individual basis because of the complexity involved.
</Para><SummarySection id="_499"><Title>Fluorouracil dosing</Title><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000813769_3"><Para id="_sm_CDR0000813769_4">The <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> gene encodes an enzyme that catabolizes pyrimidines and fluoropyrimidines, like capecitabine and fluorouracil. An estimated 1% to 2% of the population has germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName>, which lead to reduced DPD protein function and an accumulation of pyrimidines and fluoropyrimidines in the body.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> Patients with the <GeneName>DPYD*2A</GeneName> variant who receive fluoropyrimidines may experience severe, life-threatening toxicities that are sometimes fatal. Many other <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> variants have been identified,  with a range of clinical effects.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Fluoropyrimidine avoidance or a dose reduction of 50% may be recommended based on  the patient's <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> genotype and number of functioning <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> alleles.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> <GeneName>DPYD</GeneName> genetic testing costs less than $200, but insurance coverage varies due to  a lack of national guidelines.<Reference refidx="16"/> In addition, testing may delay therapy by 2 weeks, which would not be advisable in urgent situations. This controversial issue requires further evaluation.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Mendenhall WM, Werning JW, Pfister DG: Treatment of head and neck cancer. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA: Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology. 9th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, 2011, pp 729-80.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Laramore GE, ed.: Radiation Therapy of Head and Neck Cancer. Springer-Verlag, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Thawley SE, Panje WR, Batsakis JG, et al., eds.: Comprehensive Management of Head and Neck Tumors. 2nd ed. WB Saunders, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1534082" MedlineID="92267912">Fowler JF, Lindstrom MJ: Loss of local control with prolongation in radiotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 23 (2): 457-67, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15825201">Ganly I, Patel SG, Singh B, et al.: Craniofacial resection for malignant paranasal sinus tumors: Report of an International Collaborative Study. Head Neck 27 (7): 575-84, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="7836081" MedlineID="95137798">Turner SL, Tiver KW, Boyages SC: Thyroid dysfunction following radiotherapy for head and neck cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 31 (2): 279-83, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="7836099" MedlineID="95137818">Constine LS: What else don't we know about the late effects of radiation in patients treated for head and neck cancer? Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 31 (2): 427-9, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="1732427" MedlineID="92121936">Jacobs C, Lyman G, Velez-García E, et al.: A phase III randomized study comparing cisplatin and fluorouracil as single agents and in combination for advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. J Clin Oncol 10 (2): 257-63, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="7602354" MedlineID="95325882">Schornagel JH, Verweij J, de Mulder PH, et al.: Randomized phase III trial of edatrexate versus methotrexate in patients with metastatic and/or recurrent squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck: a European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Head and Neck Cancer Cooperative Group study. J Clin Oncol 13 (7): 1649-55, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="34506675">Sharma BB, Rai K, Blunt H, et al.: Pathogenic DPYD Variants and Treatment-Related Mortality in Patients Receiving Fluoropyrimidine Chemotherapy: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Oncologist 26 (12): 1008-1016, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="27569869">Lam SW, Guchelaar HJ, Boven E: The role of pharmacogenetics in capecitabine efficacy and toxicity. Cancer Treat Rev 50: 9-22, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="33410339">Shakeel F, Fang F, Kwon JW, et al.: Patients carrying DPYD variant alleles have increased risk of severe toxicity and related treatment modifications during fluoropyrimidine chemotherapy. Pharmacogenomics 22 (3): 145-155, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29152729">Amstutz U, Henricks LM, Offer SM, et al.: Clinical Pharmacogenetics Implementation Consortium (CPIC) Guideline for Dihydropyrimidine Dehydrogenase Genotype and Fluoropyrimidine Dosing: 2017 Update. Clin Pharmacol Ther 103 (2): 210-216, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="30348537">Henricks LM, Lunenburg CATC, de Man FM, et al.: DPYD genotype-guided dose individualisation of fluoropyrimidine therapy in patients with cancer: a prospective safety analysis. Lancet Oncol 19 (11): 1459-1467, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="34996412">Lau-Min KS, Varughese LA, Nelson MN, et al.: Preemptive pharmacogenetic testing to guide chemotherapy dosing in patients with gastrointestinal malignancies: a qualitative study of barriers to implementation. BMC Cancer 22 (1): 47, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="35668003">Brooks GA, Tapp S, Daly AT, et al.: Cost-effectiveness of DPYD Genotyping Prior to Fluoropyrimidine-based Adjuvant Chemotherapy for Colon Cancer. Clin Colorectal Cancer 21 (3): e189-e195, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="36821823">Baker SD, Bates SE, Brooks GA, et al.: DPYD Testing: Time to Put Patient Safety First. J Clin Oncol 41 (15): 2701-2705, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_62"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040128">stage I paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage I Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer </Title><Para id="_224">Stage I  disease includes small lesions.</Para><SummarySection id="_346"><Title>Maxillary Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_347">Maxillary sinus tumors are small lesions of the infrastructure.</Para><Para id="_348">Treatment options for stage I maxillary sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_349" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical resection.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Postoperative radiation therapy should be considered for close margins
(particularly in tumors of the suprastructure).

</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_350"><Title>Ethmoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_351">Ethmoid sinus tumors are usually extensive when diagnosed.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_352">Treatment options for stage I ethmoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_353" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>External-beam radiation therapy alone is generally used for
unresectable lesions.

</ListItem>
<ListItem>Well-localized lesions can be resected, but resection of the ethmoids, maxilla, and orbit, with consideration for
a craniofacial approach, is generally required.

</ListItem>
<ListItem>If surgery can be done with good functional and cosmetic results,
postoperative radiation therapy should be given even with clear
surgical margins.

</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_354"><Title>Sphenoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_355">Treatment options  for stage I sphenoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_356" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Treatment is the same as for nasopharyngeal cancers, primarily
radiation therapy. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_54" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Stage I Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> section in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_357"><Title>Nasal Cavity Tumors</Title><Para id="_358">For nasal cavity tumors (squamous cell carcinomas), treatment preferences
are either surgery or radiation therapy, which have equal cure rates.
</Para><Para id="_359">Treatment options  for stage I nasal cavity tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_360" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery for tumors of the septum.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radiation therapy for tumors of the lateral and superior walls.<Reference refidx="4"/>
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Surgery plus radiation therapy for tumors of the septal and lateral
walls.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_361"><Title>Inverting Papillomas</Title><Para id="_362">Treatment options  for stage I inverting papillomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_363" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Re-excision for surgery failures.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radical surgery may eventually be necessary.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radiation therapy has been used successfully for surgical failures.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_364"><Title>Melanomas and Sarcomas</Title><Para id="_365">Treatment options  for stage I melanomas and sarcomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_366" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision if possible.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Combined surgery, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy are recommended for
rhabdomyosarcoma.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_367"><Title>Midline Granulomas</Title><Para id="_368">Treatment options  for stage I midline granulomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_369" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Radiation therapy to nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_370"><Title>Nasal Vestibule Tumors</Title><Para id="_371">Treatment options  for stage I nasal vestibule tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_372" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery or radiation therapy may be performed.  If lesions are extremely small,
surgery is preferred, provided that no deformity is expected and a need
for reconstruction is not anticipated.  Radiation therapy is preferred
for other small lesions.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  Treatment of the ipsilateral neck should be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_62_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_62_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1313248" MedlineID="92207473">Kraus DH, Sterman BM, Levine HL, et al.: Factors influencing survival in ethmoid sinus cancer. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 118 (4): 367-72, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10635391" MedlineID="20101308">Shah JP: Surgery of the anterior skull base for malignant tumors. Acta Otorhinolaryngol Belg 53 (3): 191-4, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10208659" MedlineID="99223358">Cantù G, Solero CL, Mariani L, et al.: Anterior craniofacial resection for malignant ethmoid tumors--a series of 91 patients. Head Neck 21 (3): 185-91, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="2846481" MedlineID="89033230">Hawkins RB, Wynstra JH, Pilepich MV, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasal cavity--results of primary and adjuvant radiotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 15 (5): 1129-33, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="1410570" MedlineID="93029625">Ang KK, Jiang GL, Frankenthaler RA, et al.: Carcinomas of the nasal cavity. Radiother Oncol 24 (3): 163-8, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2262359" MedlineID="91086145">Levendag PC, Pomp J: Radiation therapy of squamous cell carcinoma of the nasal vestibule. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 19 (6): 1363-7, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3046644" MedlineID="88326701">Wong CS, Cummings BJ: The place of radiation therapy in the treatment of squamous cell carcinoma of the nasal vestibule. A review. Acta Oncol 27 (3): 203-8, 1988.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_87"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040129">stage II paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage II Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</Title><Para id="_225">Stage II disease includes small and moderately advanced lesions.</Para><SummarySection id="_373"><Title>Maxillary Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_374">Treatment options  for stage II maxillary sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_375" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical resection with high-dose preoperative or postoperative
radiation therapy.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_376"><Title>Ethmoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_377">Ethmoid sinus tumors are usually extensive when diagnosed.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_378">Treatment options  for stage II ethmoid sinus tumors include the following:
</Para><OrderedList id="_379" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>External-beam radiation therapy alone is generally used and produces
better overall results than surgery.

</ListItem>
<ListItem>Well-localized lesions can be resected, but resection of the ethmoids,
maxilla, and orbit, often with a combined neurosurgical sinus
craniofacial approach, is generally required.

</ListItem>
<ListItem>If surgery can be done with good functional and cosmetic results,
postoperative radiation therapy should be given, even when surgical margins are clear.

</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_380"><Title>Sphenoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_381">Treatment options  for stage II sphenoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_382" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Treatment is the same as for nasopharyngeal cancers, primarily
radiation therapy.   Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_70" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Stages II, III, and IV Nonmetastatic Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> section in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment.</ListItem>

</OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_383"><Title>Nasal Cavity Tumors</Title><Para id="_384">For nasal cavity tumors (squamous cell carcinomas), treatment preferences
are either surgery or radiation therapy, which have equal cure rates.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_385">Treatment options  for stage II nasal cavity tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_386" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery or radiation therapy for tumors of the septum.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radiation therapy for tumors of the lateral and superior walls.
Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Surgery plus radiation therapy for tumors of the septal and lateral
walls.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_387"><Title>Inverting Papillomas</Title><Para id="_388">Treatment options  for stage II inverting papillomas include the following:
</Para><OrderedList id="_389" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Re-excision for surgery failures.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radiation therapy for radical surgery failures may eventually be
necessary.

</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_390"><Title>Melanomas and Sarcomas</Title><Para id="_391">Treatment options  for stage II melanomas and sarcomas include the following:
</Para><OrderedList id="_392" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision if possible.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Combined surgery, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy are recommended for
rhabdomyosarcoma.

</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_393"><Title>Midline Granulomas</Title><Para id="_394">Treatment options  for stage II midline granulomas include the following:
</Para><OrderedList id="_395" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Radiation therapy to nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_396"><Title>Nasal Vestibule Tumors</Title><Para id="_397">Treatment options  for stage II nasal vestibule tumors include the following:
</Para><OrderedList id="_398" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery or radiation therapy may be performed.  If tumors are extremely
small, surgery is preferred, provided that no deformity is expected and
a need for reconstruction is not anticipated.  Radiation therapy is
preferred for other small lesions.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  Treatment of the neck should
be considered.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_87_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_87_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1313248" MedlineID="92207473">Kraus DH, Sterman BM, Levine HL, et al.: Factors influencing survival in ethmoid sinus cancer. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 118 (4): 367-72, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10208659" MedlineID="99223358">Cantù G, Solero CL, Mariani L, et al.: Anterior craniofacial resection for malignant ethmoid tumors--a series of 91 patients. Head Neck 21 (3): 185-91, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10635391" MedlineID="20101308">Shah JP: Surgery of the anterior skull base for malignant tumors. Acta Otorhinolaryngol Belg 53 (3): 191-4, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="2846481" MedlineID="89033230">Hawkins RB, Wynstra JH, Pilepich MV, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasal cavity--results of primary and adjuvant radiotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 15 (5): 1129-33, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="1410570" MedlineID="93029625">Ang KK, Jiang GL, Frankenthaler RA, et al.: Carcinomas of the nasal cavity. Radiother Oncol 24 (3): 163-8, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2262359" MedlineID="91086145">Levendag PC, Pomp J: Radiation therapy of squamous cell carcinoma of the nasal vestibule. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 19 (6): 1363-7, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3046644" MedlineID="88326701">Wong CS, Cummings BJ: The place of radiation therapy in the treatment of squamous cell carcinoma of the nasal vestibule. A review. Acta Oncol 27 (3): 203-8, 1988.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_112"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040130">stage III paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage III Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</Title><Para id="_226">Stage III disease includes small and moderately advanced lesions.</Para><SummarySection id="_399"><Title>Maxillary Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_400">Treatment options  for stage III maxillary sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_401" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical resection with high-dose preoperative or postoperative
radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Superfractionated preoperative or postoperative radiation therapy (under clinical evaluation).<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_404"><Title>Ethmoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_405">Treatment options  for stage III ethmoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_406" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Generally, a craniofacial resection in combination with postoperative
radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>
</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials using new drug combinations for advanced tumors should be
considered to evaluate chemotherapy preoperatively or before radiation therapy. Adjuvant therapy after surgery or after combined-modality
therapy should also be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_409"><Title>Sphenoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_410">Treatment options  for stage III sphenoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_411" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Treatment is the same as for nasopharyngeal cancers, primarily
radiation therapy.
 For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_70" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Stages II, III, and IV Nonmetastatic Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> section in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment. </ListItem>

<ListItem>Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_412"><Title>Nasal Cavity Tumors</Title><Para id="_413">Nasal cavity tumors are squamous cell carcinomas.</Para><Para id="_414">Treatment options  for stage III nasal cavity tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_415" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery alone.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radiation therapy alone.<Reference refidx="5"/> Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Combined surgery and radiation therapy (postoperative radiation
therapy is preferred).<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>
</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials using new drug combinations for advanced tumors should be
considered to evaluate chemotherapy preoperatively or before radiation therapy. Adjuvant therapy after surgery or after combined-modality
therapy should also be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_418"><Title>Inverting Papillomas</Title><Para id="_419">Treatment options  for stage III inverting papillomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_420" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Re-excision for surgery failures.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radiation therapy or radical surgery may eventually be necessary.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_421"><Title>Melanomas and Sarcomas</Title><Para id="_422">Treatment options  for stage III melanomas and sarcomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_423" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision if possible; otherwise, consider radiation therapy.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Combined surgery, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy are recommended for
rhabdomyosarcoma.

</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_424"><Title>Midline Granulomas</Title><Para id="_425">Treatment options  for stage III midline granulomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_426" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Radiation therapy to nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_427"><Title>Nasal Vestibule Tumors</Title><Para id="_428">Treatment options  for stage III nasal vestibule tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_429" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Generally, radiation is preferred to minimize deformity.<Reference refidx="7"/>  External-beam (photons or electrons) and/or interstitial implantation can be
used.  Surgery is reserved for salvage.</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials using new drug combinations for advanced tumors should be
considered to evaluate chemotherapy preoperatively or before radiation therapy. Adjuvant therapy after surgery or after combined-modality
therapy should also be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_112_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_112_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1571905" MedlineID="92240564">Johnson CR, Schmidt-Ullrich RK, Wazer DE: Concomitant boost technique using accelerated superfractionated radiation therapy for advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. Cancer 69 (11): 2749-54, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1313248" MedlineID="92207473">Kraus DH, Sterman BM, Levine HL, et al.: Factors influencing survival in ethmoid sinus cancer. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 118 (4): 367-72, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10208659" MedlineID="99223358">Cantù G, Solero CL, Mariani L, et al.: Anterior craniofacial resection for malignant ethmoid tumors--a series of 91 patients. Head Neck 21 (3): 185-91, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10635391" MedlineID="20101308">Shah JP: Surgery of the anterior skull base for malignant tumors. Acta Otorhinolaryngol Belg 53 (3): 191-4, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2846481" MedlineID="89033230">Hawkins RB, Wynstra JH, Pilepich MV, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasal cavity--results of primary and adjuvant radiotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 15 (5): 1129-33, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="1410570" MedlineID="93029625">Ang KK, Jiang GL, Frankenthaler RA, et al.: Carcinomas of the nasal cavity. Radiother Oncol 24 (3): 163-8, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3046644" MedlineID="88326701">Wong CS, Cummings BJ: The place of radiation therapy in the treatment of squamous cell carcinoma of the nasal vestibule. A review. Acta Oncol 27 (3): 203-8, 1988.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040131">stage IV paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IV Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</Title><Para id="_227">Stage IV disease includes advanced lesions.</Para><SummarySection id="_432"><Title>Maxillary Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_433">Treatment options  for stage IV maxillary sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_434" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>High-dose radiation therapy is used because extension to the base of the skull and nasopharynx is
a potential, but not absolute, contraindication to surgery.  If radiation therapy is to be used alone, localized
drainage of the sinus(es) must be established before radiation
therapy treatments are initiated.</ListItem><ListItem>Superfractionated radiation therapy (under clinical evaluation).<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials for advanced tumors should be
considered to evaluate chemotherapy preoperatively or before radiation therapy. Adjuvant therapy after surgery or after combined-modality therapy should also be considered.</ListItem><ListItem>Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_435"><Title>Ethmoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_436">Treatment options  for stage IV ethmoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_437" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Generally, a craniofacial resection in combination with preoperative or
postoperative radiation therapy is performed.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>
</ListItem><ListItem>Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered for patients with inoperable tumors.</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials for advanced tumors should be
considered to evaluate chemotherapy preoperatively or before radiation therapy. Adjuvant therapy after surgery or after combined-modality therapy should also be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_438"><Title>Sphenoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_439">Treatment options  for stage IV sphenoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_440" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Treatment is the same as for nasopharyngeal cancers, primarily
radiation therapy.
 For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_70" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Stages II, III, and IV Nonmetastatic Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_80" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic and Recurrent Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> sections in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_441"><Title>Nasal Cavity Tumors</Title><Para id="_442">Nasal cavity tumors are squamous cell carcinomas.</Para><Para id="_443">Treatment options  for stage IV nasal cavity tumors include the following:
</Para><OrderedList id="_444" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery alone.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radiation therapy alone.<Reference refidx="5"/> Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Combined surgery and radiation therapy (postoperative radiation
therapy is preferred).<Reference refidx="5"/>
</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials for advanced tumors should be
considered to evaluate chemotherapy preoperatively or before radiation therapy. Adjuvant therapy after surgery or after combined-modality therapy should also be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_445"><Title>Inverting Papillomas</Title><Para id="_446">Treatment options  for stage IV inverting papillomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_447" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Re-excision for surgery failures.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radiation therapy or radical surgery may eventually be necessary.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_448"><Title>Melanomas and Sarcomas</Title><Para id="_449">Treatment options  for stage IV melanomas and sarcomas include the following:
</Para><OrderedList id="_450" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision if possible.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Appropriate radiation therapy and various chemotherapy agents should be
considered.

</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_451"><Title>Midline Granulomas</Title><Para id="_452">Treatment options  for stage IV midline granulomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_453" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Radiation therapy to nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_460"><Title>Nasal Vestibule Tumors</Title><Para id="_461">Treatment options  for stage IV nasal vestibule tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_462" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Generally, radiation therapy is preferred to minimize deformity.  External-beam (i.e., photons or electrons) and/or interstitial implantation can be
used.  Surgery is reserved for salvage.  Treatment of the neck should
be considered.</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials for advanced tumors should be
considered to evaluate chemotherapy preoperatively or before radiation therapy. Adjuvant therapy after surgery or after combined-modality therapy should also be considered.</ListItem><ListItem>Concurrent chemotherapy and radiation therapy may be considered.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Para id="_261">Neoadjuvant chemotherapy as used in clinical trials has been used to shrink
tumors and to render them more definitively treatable with either surgery
or radiation therapy.  This chemotherapy is given before the other modalities; therefore, 
the designation of <Emphasis>neoadjuvant</Emphasis> is used to distinguish it from standard adjuvant therapy,
which is given after or during definitive therapy with radiation or after
surgery.  Many drug combinations have been used in  neoadjuvant
chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_140_sid_8"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_140_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1571905" MedlineID="92240564">Johnson CR, Schmidt-Ullrich RK, Wazer DE: Concomitant boost technique using accelerated superfractionated radiation therapy for advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. Cancer 69 (11): 2749-54, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1313248" MedlineID="92207473">Kraus DH, Sterman BM, Levine HL, et al.: Factors influencing survival in ethmoid sinus cancer. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 118 (4): 367-72, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10208659" MedlineID="99223358">Cantù G, Solero CL, Mariani L, et al.: Anterior craniofacial resection for malignant ethmoid tumors--a series of 91 patients. Head Neck 21 (3): 185-91, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10635391" MedlineID="20101308">Shah JP: Surgery of the anterior skull base for malignant tumors. Acta Otorhinolaryngol Belg 53 (3): 191-4, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2846481" MedlineID="89033230">Hawkins RB, Wynstra JH, Pilepich MV, et al.: Carcinoma of the nasal cavity--results of primary and adjuvant radiotherapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 15 (5): 1129-33, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="8209266" MedlineID="94269651">Stupp R, Weichselbaum RR, Vokes EE: Combined modality therapy of head and neck cancer. Semin Oncol 21 (3): 349-58, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3278391" MedlineID="88145720">Al-Sarraf M: Head and neck cancer: chemotherapy concepts. Semin Oncol 15 (1): 70-85, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8418313" MedlineID="93116111">Dimery IW, Hong WK: Overview of combined modality therapies for head and neck cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst 85 (2): 95-111, 1993.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_165"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040132">recurrent paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</Title><Para id="_166">Chemotherapy for recurrent head and neck squamous cell cancer has shown
promise.  Chemotherapy may be indicated when there is recurrence in either
distant or local disease after primary surgery or radiation therapy, and when there is
residual disease after primary treatment.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  Survival may be improved in
those achieving a complete response to chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Combined-modality
therapy with platinum and radiation therapy has been used in clinical trials such as  UMCC-8810.<Reference refidx="4"/>  
</Para><SummarySection id="_465"><Title>Maxillary Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_466">Treatment options  for recurrent maxillary sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_467" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>After surgery, radiation therapy or craniofacial resection with
postoperative radiation therapy.

</ListItem>
<ListItem>After radiation therapy, craniofacial resection if indicated.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Chemotherapy should be considered for patients with disease that does not respond to other treatments.
</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials using chemotherapy should be
considered.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_470"><Title>Ethmoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_471">Treatment options  for recurrent ethmoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_472" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>After limited surgery, craniofacial resection, radiation therapy, or
both.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>

</ListItem>
<ListItem>After radiation therapy, craniofacial resection.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Chemotherapy should be considered for patients with disease that does not respond to  other treatments.</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials using chemotherapy should be
considered.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_475"><Title>Sphenoid Sinus Tumors</Title><Para id="_476">Treatment options  for recurrent sphenoid sinus tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_477" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Treatment is the same as for nasopharyngeal cancers, primarily
radiation therapy. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_80" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic and Recurrent Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> section in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment.</ListItem>
<ListItem>Chemotherapy should be considered for patients with disease that does not respond to other treatments.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_478"><Title>Nasal Cavity Tumors</Title><Para id="_479"> For nasal cavity tumors (squamous cell carcinomas), salvage is possible in
approximately 25% of patients.</Para><Para id="_480">Treatment options  for recurrent nasal cavity tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_481" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>For disease that does not respond to radiation therapy, craniofacial resection.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>For disease that does not respond to surgery, radiation therapy.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Chemotherapy should be considered for patients with disease that does not respond to radiation therapy or surgery.
</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials using chemotherapy should be
considered.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_484"><Title>Inverting Papillomas</Title><Para id="_485">Treatment options  for recurrent inverting papillomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_486" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Re-excision for surgery failures.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Radical surgery or radiation therapy may eventually be necessary.
</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_487"><Title>Melanomas and Sarcomas</Title><Para id="_488">Treatment options  for recurrent melanomas and sarcomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_489" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgical excision if possible.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Appropriate chemotherapy geared specifically to cell type.  For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062918#_80" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic and Recurrent Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</SummaryRef> section in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Treatment and the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062920#_96" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/salivary-gland-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Recurrent Major Salivary Gland Cancer</SummaryRef> section in Salivary Gland Cancer Treatment.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_490"><Title>Midline Granulomas</Title><Para id="_491">Treatment options  for recurrent midline granulomas include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_492" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Radiation therapy to nasal cavity and paranasal sinuses.
</ListItem>
</OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_493"><Title>Nasal Vestibule Tumors</Title><Para id="_494">Treatment options  for recurrent nasal vestibule tumors include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_495" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>For disease that does not respond to radiation therapy, surgery.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>For disease that does not respond to  surgery, radiation therapy or a combination of surgery and
radiation therapy.
</ListItem>
<ListItem>Chemotherapy should be considered for patients with disease that does not respond to radiation therapy or surgery.
</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical trials using chemotherapy should be
considered.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_165_sid_9"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_165_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="4047673" MedlineID="86015609">Kies MS, Levitan N, Hong WK: Chemotherapy of head and neck cancer. Otolaryngol Clin North Am 18 (3): 533-41, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2454717" MedlineID="88253092">LoRusso P, Tapazoglou E, Kish JA, et al.: Chemotherapy for paranasal sinus carcinoma. A 10-year experience at Wayne State University. Cancer 62 (1): 1-5, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2433016" MedlineID="87102455">Al-Kourainy K, Kish J, Ensley J, et al.: Achievement of superior survival for histologically negative versus histologically positive clinically complete responders to cisplatin combination in patients with locally advanced head and neck cancer. Cancer 59 (2): 233-8, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="3802013" MedlineID="87102459">Al-Sarraf M, Pajak TF, Marcial VA, et al.: Concurrent radiotherapy and chemotherapy with cisplatin in inoperable squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. An RTOG Study. Cancer 59 (2): 259-65, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="8663951">Brasnu D, Laccourreye O, Bassot V, et al.: Cisplatin-based neoadjuvant chemotherapy and combined resection for ethmoid sinus adenocarcinoma reaching and/or invading the skull base. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 122 (7): 765-8, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12598339">Licitra L, Locati LD, Cavina R, et al.: Primary chemotherapy followed by anterior craniofacial resection and radiotherapy for paranasal cancer. Ann Oncol 14 (3): 367-72, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="1313248" MedlineID="92207473">Kraus DH, Sterman BM, Levine HL, et al.: Factors influencing survival in ethmoid sinus cancer. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 118 (4): 367-72, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="10208659" MedlineID="99223358">Cantù G, Solero CL, Mariani L, et al.: Anterior craniofacial resection for malignant ethmoid tumors--a series of 91 patients. Head Neck 21 (3): 185-91, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="10635391" MedlineID="20101308">Shah JP: Surgery of the anterior skull base for malignant tumors. Acta Otorhinolaryngol Belg 53 (3): 191-4, 1999.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_206"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (07/05/2024)</Title><Para id="_207">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_500"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_54" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview for Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_501">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_499" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">Fluorouracil dosing</SummaryRef> as a new subsection.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062931#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of adult paranasal sinus and nasal cavity cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Andrea Bonetti, MD (Pederzoli Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Minh Tam Truong, MD (Boston University Medical Center)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/paranasal-sinus-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389272]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-07-05</DateLastModified></Summary>
