<Summary id="CDR0000062940" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>AIDS-related lymphoma treatment may include chemotherapy, radiation therapy, high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell transplant, and/or targeted therapy. Get detailed information about the diagnosis and treatment of newly diagnosed and recurrent HIV-related lymphoma in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/hp/aids-related-treatment-pdq">AIDS-Related Lymphoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/patient/aids-related-treatment-pdq">AIDS-Related Lymphoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040813">AIDS-related lymphoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_162">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of AIDS-related lymphoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_163">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>AIDS-related lymphoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>AIDS-Related Lymphoma Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">AIDS-Related Lymphoma Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">AIDS-Related Lymphoma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040813">AIDS-related lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About AIDS-Related Lymphoma</Title><SummarySection id="_151"><Title>Background and Definitions</Title><Para id="_2">AIDS was first described in 1981, and
the first definitions included certain opportunistic infections, Kaposi
sarcoma, and central nervous system (CNS) lymphomas.    
In 1984, a multicenter
study described the clinical spectrum of non-Hodgkin lymphomas (NHLs) in the
populations at risk of AIDS.<Reference refidx="1"/>  The incidence of NHL has increased in a course almost parallel
 to that of the AIDS epidemic and accounts for 2% to 3% of newly diagnosed AIDS
cases.<Reference refidx="2"/> Since the introduction of  highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) in the mid-1990s, the incidence of lymphomas has decreased, and outcomes have improved.<Reference refidx="3"/> Higher CD4-positive T-lymphocyte (CD4) counts in the HAART era have been associated with a shift in histological diagnoses. The shift is away from primary effusion lymphoma and primary CNS lymphoma, which occur with the lowest CD4 counts, and toward histologies that occur at higher CD4 counts, such as Burkitt lymphoma and Hodgkin lymphoma (HL).<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> In contrast to less-frequent incidences of all the lymphoproliferative disorders in the HAART era, the incidence rate of anal cancer has not changed.<Reference refidx="7"/>  
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_152"><Title>Histology</Title><Para id="_3">Pathologically, AIDS-related lymphomas comprise a narrow spectrum of
histological types consisting almost exclusively of B-cell tumors of aggressive
type.  These include:
</Para><ItemizedList id="_46" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (including B-cell immunoblastic lymphoma).</ListItem><ListItem>Small
noncleaved lymphoma, either Burkitt or Burkitt-like.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_61">The HIV-associated lymphomas
can be categorized as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_48" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Aggressive B-cell lymphoma (see above).</ListItem><ListItem>Primary CNS lymphoma (PCNSL). </ListItem><ListItem>Primary effusion lymphoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Plasmablastic multicentric Castleman disease.</ListItem><ListItem>HL.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_166"><Title>HIV-associated Hodgkin lymphoma</Title><Para id="_167">Multiple reviews  of HL occurring in patients
at risk of AIDS have been done;<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  however, HL is still
not part of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) definition of AIDS because  no clear
demonstration of its increased incidence in conjunction with HIV has been shown, as is the
case for aggressive NHL.  The CDC, in conjunction with the
San Francisco Department of Public Health, has reported a cohort study in which
HIV-infected men had an excess risk that was attributable to the HIV infection
in 19.3 cases of HL per 100,000 person-years and 224.9 cases of
NHL per 100,000 person-years.  Although this report found an excess incidence
of HL in HIV-infected homosexual men, additional epidemiologic studies will be needed before the CDC will reconsider
HL as an HIV-associated malignancy.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_168">HIV-associated HL presents in an aggressive fashion, often with
extranodal or bone marrow involvement.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="11"/>  A distinctive feature of
HIV-associated HL is the lesser frequency of mediastinal
adenopathy compared with non–HIV-associated HL.  Most patients in
these series had either mixed cellularity or lymphocyte-depleted HL, expression of Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)-associated proteins in Reed-Sternberg cells, B symptoms, and a median CD4 lymphocyte count of 300/dL or
lower.<Reference refidx="12"/>  
In a retrospective multicenter review of 62 patients, those receiving HAART with chemotherapy had a 74% 2-year overall survival (OS) rate  versus a 30% OS rate for those not receiving HAART (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] Among 201 patients with classical HL and HIV positivity, the 2- to 5-year OS rate of 88% to 90% after treatment with ABVD (doxorubicin, bleomycin, vinblastine, and dacarbazine), or similar regimens, and HAART, was not significantly different from the OS rate of HIV-negative patients with newly diagnosed HL in two uncontrolled comparisons.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] These studies confirm that patients with HL who were treated with standard regimens and HAART have outcomes that are similar to those of the uninfected population.<Reference refidx="16"/> Furthermore,  immune function recovers over the course of 6 to 9 months after completion of chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_153"><Title>Primary effusion lymphoma</Title><Para id="_49">Primary effusion lymphoma has been associated with Kaposi
sarcoma (KS)-associated herpesvirus (KSHV)/human herpes virus type 8 (HHV8).<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/> 
Primary effusion lymphoma presents as a liquid phase spreading along serous membranes in the absence of masses or adenopathy.<Reference refidx="17"/> In addition to HHV8, many cases are also associated with EBV.  Extension of lymphoma from the effusion to underlying tissue may occur. A series of 20 patients, including 19 treated with modified infusional etoposide, vincristine, and doxorubicin plus cyclophosphamide and prednisone (modEPOCH), had a 3-year cancer-specific survival rate of 47% and a median OS of 22 months.<Reference refidx="19"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_164"><Title>Multicentric Castleman disease </Title><Para id="_165">The plasmablastic type of multicentric Castleman disease is also associated with a coinfection of KSHV/HHV8 and HIV.<Reference refidx="20"/> Patients typically present with fever, night sweats, weight loss, lymphadenopathy, and hepatosplenomegaly.  Patients may progress to primary effusion lymphoma or to plasmablastic or anaplastic large cell lymphoma.  Anecdotal responses to the anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody rituximab alone (along with HAART), have been reported.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] For a prospective cohort of 84 patients treated with rituximab for HIV and HHV8 multicentric Castleman disease, the 5-year rate of relapse-free survival  was 82% (95% confidence interval [CI], 72%–92%), and all patients responded again to rituximab at relapse.<Reference refidx="24"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_154"><Title>Incidence and Prevention</Title><Para id="_4">An international database of 48,000 HIV-seropositive individuals from the
United States, Europe, and Australia found a 42% decline in the incidence of 
NHLs from 1997 to 1999 compared with the same incidences in 1992 to 1996, both for
PCNSL and for systemic lymphoma.<Reference refidx="25"/>  The introduction of HAART is the proposed explanation for this decline.<Reference refidx="26"/>  The diagnosis of AIDS precedes the onset of
NHL in approximately 50% of the patients; however,   in the other half of the patients, the
diagnosis of AIDS is made at the time of the diagnosis of NHL and HIV positivity.<Reference refidx="3"/>  The geographic distribution of these lymphomas
is also similar to the geographic spread of AIDS.  Unlike KS,
which has a predilection for homosexual men and appears to be on the decline in
incidence, all risk groups appear to have an excess number of NHLs; these risk groups include intravenous drug users and children of
HIV-positive individuals.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_155"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_116">In general, the clinical setting and response to treatment of patients with
AIDS-related lymphoma is very different from that of the non-HIV patients with
lymphoma.  The HIV-infected individual with aggressive lymphoma usually
presents with advanced-stage disease that is frequently extranodal.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_117">Common extranodal sites include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_118" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Bone marrow.</ListItem><ListItem>Liver.</ListItem><ListItem>Meninges.</ListItem><ListItem>Gastrointestinal tract.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_119">Very unusual sites are also characteristic and include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_120" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Anus.</ListItem><ListItem>Heart.</ListItem><ListItem>Bile duct.</ListItem><ListItem>Gingiva.</ListItem><ListItem>Muscles.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_5"> 
  The clinical course is
more aggressive, and the disease is both more extensive and less responsive to
chemotherapy.  Immunodeficiency and cytopenias, common in these patients at the
time of initial presentation, are exacerbated by the administration of
chemotherapy.  Treatment of the malignancy increases the risk of
opportunistic infections, which further compromise the delivery of
adequate treatment.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_156"><Title>Prognosis and Survival</Title><Para id="_121">Prognoses of patients with AIDS-related lymphoma have been associated with:<Reference refidx="28"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_122" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Stage (i.e., extent of disease, extranodal involvement, lactate dehydrogenase level, and bone marrow involvement).</ListItem><ListItem>Age.</ListItem><ListItem>Severity of the underlying immunodeficiency (measured by CD4 lymphocyte count
in peripheral blood).</ListItem><ListItem>Performance status.</ListItem><ListItem>Prior AIDS diagnosis (i.e., history of opportunistic infection or KS).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_6">  Patients with AIDS-related
PCNSL appear to have more severe underlying HIV-related disease
than do patients with systemic lymphoma.  In one report, this severity was
evidenced by patients with PCNSL who had a higher incidence of 
previously diagnosed  AIDS (73% vs. 37%), lower median number of CD4 lymphocytes
(30/dL vs. 189/dL), and a worse median survival time (2.5 months vs. 6.0
months).<Reference refidx="29"/>  This report also showed that patients with poor risk factors—defined as Karnofsky Performance Status score lower than 70%, history of previously diagnosed  AIDS, and bone marrow involvement—had a median survival time of 4.0
months compared with patients in a good prognosis group who had none of these risk factors,
and who had a median survival time of 11.3 months.  </Para><Para id="_67">In another report (NIAID-ACTG-142), prognostic
factors were evaluated in a group of 192 patients with newly diagnosed
AIDS-related lymphoma who were randomly assigned to receive either low-dose
methotrexate, bleomycin, doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, and
dexamethasone (m-BACOD) or standard-dose m-BACOD with granulocyte-macrophage
colony-stimulating factor.<Reference refidx="30"/>  No differences existed between these two 
treatments in terms of efficacy for disease-free survival, median survival, or
risk ratio for death.<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]  On multivariate analysis,
factors associated with decreased survival included age older than 35 years,
history of intravenous drug use, stage III or stage IV disease, and CD4 counts lower than 100 cells/mm<Superscript>3</Superscript>.  The
International Prognostic Index may also be predictive for survival.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/>
In a multicenter cohort study of 203 patients, in a multivariable Cox model, response to HAART was independently associated with prolonged survival (relative hazard, 0.32; 95% CI, 0.16–0.62).<Reference refidx="34"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="6611504" MedlineID="84270591">Ziegler JL, Beckstead JA, Volberding PA, et al.: Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma in 90 homosexual men. Relation to generalized lymphadenopathy and the acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. N Engl J Med 311 (9): 565-70, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="7966400" MedlineID="95055827">Rabkin CS, Yellin F: Cancer incidence in a population with a high prevalence of infection with human immunodeficiency virus type 1. J Natl Cancer Inst 86 (22): 1711-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="30992269">Noy A: Optimizing treatment of HIV-associated lymphoma. Blood 134 (17): 1385-1394, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12642005">Little RF, Wilson WH: Update on the Pathogenesis, Diagnosis, and Therapy of AIDS-related Lymphoma. Curr Infect Dis Rep 5 (2): 176-184, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="16115121">Carbone A, Gloghini A: AIDS-related lymphomas: from pathogenesis to pathology. Br J Haematol 130 (5): 662-70, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="23892362">Gopal S, Patel MR, Yanik EL, et al.: Temporal trends in presentation and survival for HIV-associated lymphoma in the antiretroviral therapy era. J Natl Cancer Inst 105 (16): 1221-9, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="23091098">Piketty C, Selinger-Leneman H, Bouvier AM, et al.: Incidence of HIV-related anal cancer remains increased despite long-term combined antiretroviral treatment: results from the french hospital database on HIV. J Clin Oncol 30 (35): 4360-6, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="10950375" MedlineID="20405308">Spina M, Vaccher E, Nasti G, et al.: Human immunodeficiency virus-associated Hodgkin's disease. Semin Oncol 27 (4): 480-8, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15151213">Thompson LD, Fisher SI, Chu WS, et al.: HIV-associated Hodgkin lymphoma: a clinicopathologic and immunophenotypic study of 45 cases. Am J Clin Pathol 121 (5): 727-38, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="1637026" MedlineID="92344158">Hessol NA, Katz MH, Liu JY, et al.: Increased incidence of Hodgkin disease in homosexual men with HIV infection. Ann Intern Med 117 (4): 309-11, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="11753946" MedlineID="21621808">Re A, Casari S, Cattaneo C, et al.: Hodgkin disease developing in patients infected by human immunodeficiency virus results in clinical features and a prognosis similar to those in patients with human immunodeficiency virus-related non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Cancer 92 (11): 2739-45, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11423259" MedlineID="21315861">Dolcetti R, Boiocchi M, Gloghini A, et al.: Pathogenetic and histogenetic features of HIV-associated Hodgkin's disease. Eur J Cancer 37 (10): 1276-87, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16565210">Hentrich M, Maretta L, Chow KU, et al.: Highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) improves survival in HIV-associated Hodgkin's disease: results of a multicenter study. Ann Oncol 17 (6): 914-9, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="23045581">Montoto S, Shaw K, Okosun J, et al.: HIV status does not influence outcome in patients with classical Hodgkin lymphoma treated with chemotherapy using doxorubicin, bleomycin, vinblastine, and dacarbazine in the highly active antiretroviral therapy era. J Clin Oncol 30 (33): 4111-6, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="23045592">Hentrich M, Berger M, Wyen C, et al.: Stage-adapted treatment of HIV-associated Hodgkin lymphoma: results of a prospective multicenter study. J Clin Oncol 30 (33): 4117-23, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="23045587">Kaplan LD: Management of HIV-associated Hodgkin lymphoma: how far we have come. J Clin Oncol 30 (33): 4056-8, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="14581418">Simonelli C, Spina M, Cinelli R, et al.: Clinical features and outcome of primary effusion lymphoma in HIV-infected patients: a single-institution study. J Clin Oncol 21 (21): 3948-54, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="8695812" MedlineID="96289513">Nador RG, Cesarman E, Chadburn A, et al.: Primary effusion lymphoma: a distinct clinicopathologic entity associated with the Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpes virus. Blood 88 (2): 645-56, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="30782610">Lurain K, Polizzotto MN, Aleman K, et al.: Viral, immunologic, and clinical features of primary effusion lymphoma. Blood 133 (16): 1753-1761, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="21555697">Bower M, Newsom-Davis T, Naresh K, et al.: Clinical Features and Outcome in HIV-Associated Multicentric Castleman's Disease. J Clin Oncol 29 (18): 2481-6, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="21">Goedert JJ: Multicentric Castleman disease: viral and cellular targets for intervention. Blood  102 (8): 2710-11, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="25331113">Uldrick TS, Polizzotto MN, Aleman K, et al.: Rituximab plus liposomal doxorubicin in HIV-infected patients with KSHV-associated multicentric Castleman disease. Blood 124 (24): 3544-52, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="12842986">Marcelin AG, Aaron L, Mateus C, et al.: Rituximab therapy for HIV-associated Castleman disease. Blood 102 (8): 2786-8, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="28143881">Pria AD, Pinato D, Roe J, et al.: Relapse of HHV8-positive multicentric Castleman disease following rituximab-based therapy in HIV-positive patients. Blood 129 (15): 2143-2147, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="11078759" MedlineID="21062176">International Collaboration on HIV and Cancer: Highly active antiretroviral therapy and incidence of cancer in human immunodeficiency virus-infected adults. J Natl Cancer Inst 92 (22): 1823-30, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="15169806">Stebbing J, Gazzard B, Mandalia S, et al.: Antiretroviral treatment regimens and immune parameters in the prevention of systemic AIDS-related non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. J Clin Oncol 22 (11): 2177-83, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="11423261" MedlineID="21315863">Sparano JA: Clinical aspects and management of AIDS-related lymphoma. Eur J Cancer 37 (10): 1296-305, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="16103470">Bower M, Gazzard B, Mandalia S, et al.: A prognostic index for systemic AIDS-related non-Hodgkin lymphoma treated in the era of highly active antiretroviral therapy. Ann Intern Med 143 (4): 265-73, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="1933784" MedlineID="92034592">Levine AM, Sullivan-Halley J, Pike MC, et al.: Human immunodeficiency virus-related lymphoma. Prognostic factors predictive of survival. Cancer 68 (11): 2466-72, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="9171066" MedlineID="97301686">Kaplan LD, Straus DJ, Testa MA, et al.: Low-dose compared with standard-dose m-BACOD chemotherapy for non-Hodgkin's lymphoma associated with human immunodeficiency virus infection. National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases AIDS Clinical Trials Group. N Engl J Med 336 (23): 1641-8, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="9676023" MedlineID="98340674">Navarro JT, Ribera JM, Oriol A, et al.: International prognostic index is the best prognostic factor for survival in patients with AIDS-related non-Hodgkin's lymphoma treated with CHOP. A multivariate study of 46 patients. Haematologica 83 (6): 508-13, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="10590382" MedlineID="20059595">Rossi G, Donisi A, Casari S, et al.: The International Prognostic Index can be used as a guide to treatment decisions regarding patients with human immunodeficiency virus-related systemic non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Cancer 86 (11): 2391-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="9817281" MedlineID="99032193">Straus DJ, Huang J, Testa MA, et al.: Prognostic factors in the treatment of human immunodeficiency virus-associated non-Hodgkin's lymphoma: analysis of AIDS Clinical Trials Group protocol 142--low-dose versus standard-dose m-BACOD plus granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor. National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases. J Clin Oncol 16 (11): 3601-6, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="12824790">Hoffmann C, Wolf E, Fätkenheuer G, et al.: Response to highly active antiretroviral therapy strongly predicts outcome in patients with AIDS-related lymphoma. AIDS 17 (10): 1521-9, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040813">AIDS-related lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular Classification of AIDS-Related Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_11">Pathologically, AIDS-related lymphomas comprise a narrow spectrum of
histological types consisting almost exclusively of B-cell tumors of aggressive
type.  These include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_50" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (B-cell immunoblastic lymphoma).</ListItem><ListItem>Small
noncleaved lymphoma, either Burkitt or Burkitt-like.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_12">AIDS-related lymphomas, though usually of B-cell origin as demonstrated by
immunoglobulin heavy-chain gene rearrangement studies, have also been shown to
be oligoclonal, polyclonal, and  monoclonal in origin.  Although HIV
does not appear to have a direct etiologic role, HIV infection does lead to an
altered immunologic milieu.  HIV generally infects T lymphocytes with the  loss of
regulation function that leads to hypergammaglobulinemia and polyclonal B-cell
hyperplasia.  B cells are not the targets of HIV infection.  Instead,
Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) is thought to be at least a cofactor in the etiology
of some of these lymphomas.  The EBV genome has been detected in most patients with AIDS-related lymphomas; molecular analysis suggests
that the cells were infected before clonal proliferation began.<Reference refidx="1"/>  The rare  primary effusion lymphoma consistently
harbors human herpes virus type 8 and frequently contains EBV.<Reference refidx="2"/>  HIV-related T-cell
lymphomas have also been identified and appear to be associated with EBV
infection.<Reference refidx="3"/>
</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15044644">Thorley-Lawson DA, Gross A: Persistence of the Epstein-Barr virus and the origins of associated lymphomas. N Engl J Med 350 (13): 1328-37, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="14581418">Simonelli C, Spina M, Cinelli R, et al.: Clinical features and outcome of primary effusion lymphoma in HIV-infected patients: a single-institution study. J Clin Oncol 21 (21): 3948-54, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8389615" MedlineID="93283686">Thomas JA, Cotter F, Hanby AM, et al.: Epstein-Barr virus-related oral T-cell lymphoma associated with human immunodeficiency virus immunosuppression. Blood 81 (12): 3350-6, 1993.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040813">AIDS-related lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for AIDS-Related Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_14">Although stage is important in selecting the treatment of patients with
non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL) who do not have AIDS, most patients with AIDS-related lymphomas have far-advanced
disease.</Para><SummarySection id="_195"><Title>Staging Subclassification System</Title><SummarySection id="_196"><Title>Lugano classification</Title><Para id="_197">The American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) has adopted the Lugano classification to evaluate and stage lymphoma.<Reference refidx="1"/> The Lugano classification system replaces the Ann Arbor classification system, which was adopted in 1971 at the Ann Arbor Conference,<Reference refidx="2"/> with some modifications 18 years later from the Cotswolds meeting.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  </Para><Table id="_198">
     <Title>Table 1.  Lugano Classification for Hodgkin and Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="10.71%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="39.76%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="49.51%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Stage</entry><entry Align="Center">	Stage Description</entry><entry Align="Center">Illustration</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">CSF = cerebrospinal fluid; CT = computed tomography; DLBCL = diffuse large B-cell lymphoma; NHL = non-Hodgkin lymphoma.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Hodgkin and Non-Hodgkin Lymphomas. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: <Emphasis>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</Emphasis>. 8th ed. New York, NY: Springer, 2017, pp. 937–58.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Stage II bulky may be considered either early or advanced stage based on lymphoma histology and prognostic factors.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>The definition of disease bulk varies according to lymphoma histology. In the Lugano classification, bulk ln Hodgkin lymphoma is defined as a mass greater than one-third of the thoracic diameter on CT of the chest or a mass &gt;10 cm. For NHL, the recommended definitions of bulk vary by lymphoma histology. In follicular lymphoma, 6 cm has been suggested based on the Follicular Lymphoma International Prognostic Index-2 and its validation. In DLBCL, cutoffs ranging from 5 cm to 10 cm have been used, although 10 cm is recommended.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Emphasis>Limited stage</Emphasis></entry></Row><Row><entry>I</entry><entry>Involvement of a single lymphatic site (i.e., nodal region, Waldeyer’s ring, thymus, or spleen).</entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000614643" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage I adult lymphoma; drawing shows cancer in one lymph node group and in the spleen. Also shown are the Waldeyer’s ring and the thymus. An inset shows a lymph node with a lymph vessel, an artery, and a vein. Cancer cells are shown in the lymph node." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_199"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>IE</entry><entry>Single extralymphatic site in the absence of nodal involvement (rare in Hodgkin lymphoma).</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry>II</entry><entry>Involvement of two or more lymph node regions on the same side of the diaphragm.</entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000614648" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage II adult lymphoma; drawing shows cancer in two lymph node groups above the diaphragm and below the diaphragm. An inset shows a lymph node with a lymph vessel, an artery, and a vein. Cancer cells are shown in the lymph node." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_200"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>IIE</entry><entry>Contiguous extralymphatic extension from a nodal site with or without involvement of other lymph node regions on the same side of the diaphragm.</entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000614650" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IIE adult lymphoma; drawing shows cancer that has spread from a group of lymph nodes to a nearby area. Also shown is a lung and the diaphragm. An inset shows a lymph node with a lymph vessel, an artery, and a vein. Cancer cells are shown in the lymph node." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_201"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>II bulky<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Stage II with disease bulk.<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Emphasis>Advanced stage</Emphasis></entry></Row><Row><entry>III</entry><entry>Involvement of lymph node regions on both sides of the diaphragm; nodes above the diaphragm with spleen involvement.</entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000614684" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage III adult lymphoma; drawing shows the right and left sides of the body. The right side of the body shows cancer in a group of lymph nodes above the diaphragm and below the diaphragm. The left side of the body shows cancer in a group of lymph nodes above the diaphragm and cancer in the spleen." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_202"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>IV</entry><entry>Diffuse or disseminated involvement of one or more extralymphatic organs, with or without associated lymph node involvement; or <Emphasis>noncontiguous</Emphasis> extralymphatic organ involvement in conjunction with nodal stage II disease; or <Emphasis>any</Emphasis> extralymphatic organ involvement in nodal stage III disease. Stage IV includes <Emphasis>any</Emphasis> involvement of the CSF, bone marrow, liver, or lungs (other than by direct extension in stage IIE disease).</entry><entry><MediaLink ref="CDR0000629626" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IV adult lymphoma; drawing shows four panels: (a) the top left panel shows cancer in the liver; (b) the top right panel shows cancer in the left lung and in two groups of lymph nodes below the diaphragm; (c) the bottom left panel shows cancer in the left lung and in a group of lymph nodes above the diaphragm and below the diaphragm; and (d) the bottom right panel shows cancer in both lungs, the liver, and the bone marrow (pullout). Also shown is primary cancer in the lymph nodes and a pullout of the brain with cerebrospinal fluid (in blue)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_203"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">Note: Hodgkin lymphoma uses A or B designation with stage group. A/B is no longer used in NHL.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup>
     </Table></SummarySection></SummarySection><Para id="_140">Occasionally, specialized staging systems are used.  The physician should be
aware of the system used in a specific report.</Para><Para id="_141">The E designation  is used when extranodal lymphoid malignancies arise in
tissues separate from, but near, the major lymphatic aggregates.  Stage IV
refers to disease that is diffusely spread throughout an extranodal site, such
as the liver.  If pathological proof of involvement of one  or more extralymphatic
sites has been documented, the symbol for the site of involvement, followed by
a plus sign (+), is listed.</Para><Table id="_45"><Title>Table 2.  Notation for Identification of Sites</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><TBody><Row><entry> N = nodes</entry><entry> H = liver</entry><entry>L = lung    </entry><entry>M = marrow</entry></Row><Row><entry>S = spleen</entry><entry> P = pleura</entry><entry> O = bone   </entry><entry>D = skin</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_142">Current practice assigns a clinical stage (CS) based on the findings of the
clinical evaluation and a pathological stage (PS) based on the findings made as a
result of invasive procedures beyond the initial biopsy.
</Para><Para id="_143">For example, on percutaneous biopsy, a patient with inguinal adenopathy and a
positive lymphangiogram without systemic symptoms might be found to have
involvement of the liver and bone marrow.  The precise stage of such a patient
would be CS IIA, PS IVA(H+)(M+).
</Para><Para id="_144">A number of other factors that are not included in the above staging system are
important for the staging and prognosis of patients with NHL.   These factors
include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_145" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Age.</ListItem><ListItem>Performance status (PS).</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor size.</ListItem><ListItem>Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) values.</ListItem><ListItem>The number of extranodal sites.</ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Hodgkin and non-Hodgkin lymphoma. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 8th ed. Springer; 2017, pp. 937–58.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="5121694" MedlineID="72046815">Carbone PP, Kaplan HS, Musshoff K, et al.: Report of the Committee on Hodgkin's Disease Staging Classification. Cancer Res 31 (11): 1860-1, 1971.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="2809679" MedlineID="90039442">Lister TA, Crowther D, Sutcliffe SB, et al.: Report of a committee convened to discuss the evaluation and staging of patients with Hodgkin's disease: Cotswolds meeting. J Clin Oncol 7 (11): 1630-6, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6896167" MedlineID="82184061">National Cancer Institute sponsored study of classifications of non-Hodgkin's lymphomas: summary and description of a working formulation for clinical usage. The Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma Pathologic Classification Project. Cancer 49 (10): 2112-35, 1982.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040813">AIDS-related lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for AIDS-Related Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_32">The treatment of patients with AIDS-related lymphomas presents the challenge of integrating therapy
appropriate for the stage and histological subset of malignant lymphoma with the
limitations imposed by HIV infection.<Reference refidx="1"/>  In
addition to antitumor therapy, essential components of an optimal non-Hodgkin
lymphoma treatment strategy include:<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>    
</Para><ItemizedList id="_127" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Highly active antiretroviral therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Prophylaxis for
opportunistic infections.</ListItem><ListItem>Rapid recognition and treatment of intercurrent
infections.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_128">Patients with HIV positivity and underlying immunodeficiency
have poor bone marrow reserve, which compromises the potential for drug dose
intensity.  Intercurrent opportunistic infection is a risk that may
also lead to a decrease in drug delivery.  Furthermore, chemotherapy itself
compromises the immune system and increases the likelihood of opportunistic
infection.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10950371" MedlineID="20405304">Levine AM: Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related lymphoma: clinical aspects. Semin Oncol 27 (4): 442-53, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11423264" MedlineID="21315866">Tirelli U, Bernardi D: Impact of HAART on the clinical management of AIDS-related cancers. Eur J Cancer 37 (10): 1320-4, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="30992269">Noy A: Optimizing treatment of HIV-associated lymphoma. Blood 134 (17): 1385-1394, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041629">AIDS-related peripheral/systemic lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of AIDS-Related Peripheral/Systemic Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_36">The treatment of AIDS-related lymphomas involves overcoming several problems.  These are all
aggressive lymphomas, which by definition are diffuse large cell/immunoblastic
lymphoma or small noncleaved cell lymphoma (Burkitt lymphoma).  These lymphomas frequently involve
the bone marrow and central nervous system (CNS) and, therefore, are usually in an
advanced stage.  In addition, the immunodeficiency of AIDS and the leukopenia
that is commonly seen with HIV infection makes the use of immunosuppressive
chemotherapy challenging.
</Para><Para id="_88">The introduction of highly active  antiretroviral therapy (HAART) has led to a marked reduction in opportunistic infections, prolonged survival with HIV infection, and a median overall survival (OS) for patients with AIDS-related lymphoma that is  comparable with the outcome in  the nonimmunosuppressed population.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] The use of HAART has also allowed standard-dose and even intensive chemotherapy regimens to be given with reasonable safety to patients with AIDS-related lymphomas, which is comparable with the outcome in patients without HIV.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> </Para><Para id="_169">Several prospective nonrandomized trials and pooled individual data from 19 prospective trials that included  1,546 patients show that the addition of rituximab to combination chemotherapy improves the complete response rate, progression-free survival, and OS.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] Several other prospective nonrandomized trials and the pooled individual data from the same 1,546 patients also show that infusional EPOCH (infusional etoposide, infusional vincristine, infusional doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide, and  prednisone) produced better outcomes than did CHOP (cyclophosphamide,
doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone) (hazard ratio<Subscript>OS</Subscript>, 0.33;  <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]  Concurrent use of HAART with the infusional EPOCH regimen is controversial; one group advocated for HAART after completion of chemotherapy,<Reference refidx="7"/> while others allowed concurrent therapy.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_172"> For patients with Burkitt lymphoma, dose-modified regimens such as R-CODOX (cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, methotrexate, cytarabine and rituximab)-M/IVAC (ifosfamide, etoposide, and high-dose cytarabine) or R-EPOCH (etoposide, prednisone, vincristine, and doxorubicin in combination with rituximab) have shown good results with concurrent or sequential HAART.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_170">Patients at risk of subsequent CNS involvement
include those with bone marrow involvement or those with EBV
identified in the primary tumor or in the cerebrospinal fluid (i.e., by polymerase
chain reaction).<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/>  Intrathecal chemotherapy is usually considered for 
patients who are at higher risk of CNS involvement.</Para><Para id="_66">Highly selected patients with resistant or relapsed lymphoma after first-line chemotherapy and with continued responsiveness to HAART underwent second-line chemotherapy followed by high-dose therapy and autologous peripheral stem cell transplant.  Long-term survivors have been reported anecdotally for these highly selected patients who relapsed.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_35_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_35_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="16410446">Mounier N, Spina M, Gabarre J, et al.: AIDS-related non-Hodgkin lymphoma: final analysis of 485 patients treated with risk-adapted intensive chemotherapy. Blood 107 (10): 3832-40, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16502436">Weiss R, Mitrou P, Arasteh K, et al.: Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related lymphoma: simultaneous treatment with combined cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone chemotherapy and highly active antiretroviral therapy is safe and improves survival--results of the German Multicenter Trial. Cancer 106 (7): 1560-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24014242">Barta SK, Xue X, Wang D, et al.: Treatment factors affecting outcomes in HIV-associated non-Hodgkin lymphomas: a pooled analysis of 1546 patients. Blood 122 (19): 3251-62, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="22112600">Wyen C, Jensen B, Hentrich M, et al.: Treatment of AIDS-related lymphomas: rituximab is beneficial even in severely immunosuppressed patients. AIDS 26 (4): 457-64, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="23169503">Levine AM, Noy A, Lee JY, et al.: Pegylated liposomal doxorubicin, rituximab, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, and prednisone in AIDS-related lymphoma: AIDS Malignancy Consortium Study 047. J Clin Oncol 31 (1): 58-64, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20023215">Sparano JA, Lee JY, Kaplan LD, et al.: Rituximab plus concurrent infusional EPOCH chemotherapy is highly effective in HIV-associated B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Blood 115 (15): 3008-16, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="20130244">Dunleavy K, Little RF, Pittaluga S, et al.: The role of tumor histogenesis, FDG-PET, and short-course EPOCH with dose-dense rituximab (SC-EPOCH-RR) in HIV-associated diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. Blood 115 (15): 3017-24, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11304769" MedlineID="21201277">Ratner L, Lee J, Tang S, et al.: Chemotherapy for human immunodeficiency virus-associated non-Hodgkin's lymphoma in combination with highly active antiretroviral therapy. J Clin Oncol 19 (8): 2171-8, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12973843">Wang ES, Straus DJ, Teruya-Feldstein J, et al.: Intensive chemotherapy with cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, high-dose methotrexate/ifosfamide, etoposide, and high-dose cytarabine (CODOX-M/IVAC) for human immunodeficiency virus-associated Burkitt lymphoma. Cancer 98 (6): 1196-205, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="11920506">Cortes J, Thomas D, Rios A, et al.: Hyperfractionated cyclophosphamide, vincristine, doxorubicin, and dexamethasone and highly active antiretroviral therapy for patients with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related Burkitt lymphoma/leukemia. Cancer 94 (5): 1492-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="30992269">Noy A: Optimizing treatment of HIV-associated lymphoma. Blood 134 (17): 1385-1394, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="12">Noy A, Kaplan L, Lee J: Feasibility and toxicity of a modified dose intensive R-CODOX-M/IVAC for HIV-associated Burkitt and atypical Burkitt lymphoma (BL): preliminary results of a prospective multicenter phase II trial of the AIDS Malignancy Consortium (AMC). [Abstract] Blood  114 (22): A-3673, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="11013271" MedlineID="20469572">Cingolani A, Gastaldi R, Fassone L, et al.: Epstein-Barr virus infection is predictive of CNS involvement in systemic AIDS-related non-Hodgkin's lymphomas. J Clin Oncol 18 (19): 3325-30, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="11013270" MedlineID="20469571">Scadden DT: Epstein-Barr virus, the CNS, and AIDS-related lymphomas: as close as flame to smoke. J Clin Oncol 18 (19): 3323-4, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="19451551">Re A, Michieli M, Casari S, et al.: High-dose therapy and autologous peripheral blood stem cell transplantation as salvage treatment for AIDS-related lymphoma: long-term results of the Italian Cooperative Group on AIDS and Tumors (GICAT) study with analysis of prognostic factors. Blood 114 (7): 1306-13, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="15388574">Krishnan A, Molina A, Zaia J, et al.: Durable remissions with autologous stem cell transplantation for high-risk HIV-associated lymphomas. Blood 105 (2): 874-8, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="14770420">Costello RT, Zerazhi H, Charbonnier A, et al.: Intensive sequential chemotherapy with hematopoietic growth factor support for non-Hodgkin lymphoma in patients infected with the human immunodeficiency virus. Cancer 100 (4): 667-76, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="19332732">Balsalobre P, Díez-Martín JL, Re A, et al.: Autologous stem-cell transplantation in patients with HIV-related lymphoma. J Clin Oncol 27 (13): 2192-8, 2009.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_40"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000041630">AIDS-related primary CNS lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of AIDS-Related Primary Central Nervous System Lymphoma</Title><Para id="_41">As with other
AIDS-related lymphomas, primary central nervous system (CNS) lymphoma   (PCNSL) is an aggressive B-cell neoplasm, either
diffuse large B-cell or diffuse immunoblastic non-Hodgkin lymphoma (a subtype of diffuse large B-cell lymphoma).  AIDS-related PCNSL has
been reported to have a 100% association with Epstein-Barr virus (EBV).<Reference refidx="1"/>  These patients usually
have evidence of low CD4-positive T lymphocyte counts, high HIV viral load, severe debilitation, and
focal neurological symptoms such as seizures, changes in mental status, and
paralysis.</Para><Para id="_42">Computed tomographic scans show contrast-enhancing mass lesions that may not
always be distinguished from other CNS diseases, such as toxoplasmosis, that
occur in patients with AIDS.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Magnetic resonance imaging studies using gadolinium
contrast may be a more useful initial diagnostic tool in differentiating
lymphoma from cerebral toxoplasmosis or progressive multifocal
leukoencephalopathy.  Lymphoma tends to present with large lesions, which are
enhanced by gadolinium.  In cerebral toxoplasmosis, ring enhancement is very
common, lesions tend to be smaller, and multiple lesions are seen.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  Use of
positron emission scanning has demonstrated an improved ability to distinguish
PCNSL from toxoplasmosis.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  PCNSL
has an increased uptake while toxoplasmosis lesions are metabolically inactive. 
Antibodies against toxoplasmosis may also be very useful because most cerebral toxoplasmosis occurs as a consequence of reactivity of a
previous infection.  If the immunoglobulin G titer is less than 1:4, the disease is unlikely
to be toxoplasmotic.  A lumbar puncture may be useful to detect  as many as 23%
of patients with malignant cells in their cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). 
Evaluating the CSF for EBV DNA may be a useful lymphoma-specific tool because EBV
is present in all patients with PCNSL.  Despite  the many evaluations,
however, most patients with PCNSL require a pathological
diagnosis.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/>  Diagnosis is made by biopsy.  Sometimes, a biopsy is
attempted only after failure of antibiotics for toxoplasmosis, which will
produce clinical and radiographic improvement within 1 to 3 weeks in patients
with cerebral toxoplasmosis.<Reference refidx="11"/>  </Para><Para id="_43">Radiation therapy alone has usually been used in this group of patients.  With
doses in the range of 35 Gy to 40 Gy, median duration of survival has been only
72 to 119 days.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/>  Survival is longer in younger patients with better
performance status and the absence of opportunistic infection.<Reference refidx="14"/>  In the highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) era, a median survival of 18 months has been seen with radiation therapy alone.<Reference refidx="15"/> An anecdotal report using HAART and high-dose methotrexate for patients with AIDS-related PCNSL showed a median survival that had not been reached with a median follow-up of 27 months.<Reference refidx="16"/> Most patients
respond to treatment by showing partial improvement in neurological symptoms. 
Autopsies have revealed that these patients die of opportunistic infections as
well as tumor progression.  Treatment of these patients is also complicated by
other AIDS-related CNS infections, including subacute AIDS encephalitis,
cytomegalovirus encephalitis, and toxoplasmosis encephalitis.  Spontaneous
remissions have been reported after HAART.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_40_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_40_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1681341" MedlineID="92016946">MacMahon EM, Glass JD, Hayward SD, et al.: Epstein-Barr virus in AIDS-related primary central nervous system lymphoma. Lancet 338 (8773): 969-73, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="2025839" MedlineID="91223454">Goldstein JD, Dickson DW, Moser FG, et al.: Primary central nervous system lymphoma in acquired immune deficiency syndrome. A clinical and pathologic study with results of treatment with radiation. Cancer 67 (11): 2756-65, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="3547679" MedlineID="87149151">Nyberg DA, Federle MP: AIDS-related Kaposi sarcoma and lymphomas. Semin Roentgenol 22 (1): 54-65, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="8239229" MedlineID="94057771">Fine HA, Mayer RJ: Primary central nervous system lymphoma. Ann Intern Med 119 (11): 1093-104, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="2213162" MedlineID="91011612">Ciricillo SF, Rosenblum ML: Use of CT and MR imaging to distinguish intracranial lesions and to define the need for biopsy in AIDS patients. J Neurosurg 73 (5): 720-4, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="8455072" MedlineID="93203932">Hoffman JM, Waskin HA, Schifter T, et al.: FDG-PET in differentiating lymphoma from nonmalignant central nervous system lesions in patients with AIDS. J Nucl Med 34 (4): 567-75, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="7677300" MedlineID="95407800">Pierce MA, Johnson MD, Maciunas RJ, et al.: Evaluating contrast-enhancing brain lesions in patients with AIDS by using positron emission tomography. Ann Intern Med 123 (8): 594-8, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8101902" MedlineID="93341212">Cinque P, Brytting M, Vago L, et al.: Epstein-Barr virus DNA in cerebrospinal fluid from patients with AIDS-related primary lymphoma of the central nervous system. Lancet 342 (8868): 398-401, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9498486" MedlineID="98158251">Cingolani A, De Luca A, Larocca LM, et al.: Minimally invasive diagnosis of acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related primary central nervous system lymphoma. J Natl Cancer Inst 90 (5): 364-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="9498478" MedlineID="98158243">Yarchoan R, Jaffe ES, Little R: Diagnosing central nervous system lymphoma in the setting of AIDS: a step forward. J Natl Cancer Inst 90 (5): 346-7, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8561977" MedlineID="96126178">Mathews C, Barba D, Fullerton SC: Early biopsy versus empiric treatment with delayed biopsy of non-responders in suspected HIV-associated cerebral toxoplasmosis: a decision analysis. AIDS 9 (11): 1243-50, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="2366078" MedlineID="90308530">Baumgartner JE, Rachlin JR, Beckstead JH, et al.: Primary central nervous system lymphomas: natural history and response to radiation therapy in 55 patients with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. J Neurosurg 73 (2): 206-11, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="2233232" MedlineID="91041689">Remick SC, Diamond C, Migliozzi JA, et al.: Primary central nervous system lymphoma in patients with and without the acquired immune deficiency syndrome. A retrospective analysis and review of the literature. Medicine (Baltimore) 69 (6): 345-60, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="9072309" MedlineID="97205642">Corn BW, Donahue BR, Rosenstock JG, et al.: Performance status and age as independent predictors of survival among AIDS patients with primary CNS lymphoma: a multivariate analysis of a multi-institutional experience. Cancer J Sci Am 3 (1): 52-6, 1997 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="11684931">Hoffmann C, Tabrizian S, Wolf E, et al.: Survival of AIDS patients with primary central nervous system lymphoma is dramatically improved by HAART-induced immune recovery. AIDS 15 (16): 2119-27, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="27576871">Gupta NK, Nolan A, Omuro A, et al.: Long-term survival in AIDS-related primary central nervous system lymphoma. Neuro Oncol 19 (1): 99-108, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="9631151" MedlineID="98294612">McGowan JP, Shah S: Long-term remission of AIDS-related primary central nervous system lymphoma associated with highly active antiretroviral therapy. AIDS 12 (8): 952-4, 1998.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (09/18/2024)</Title><Para id="_54">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_212">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062940#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/lymphoma/hp/aids-related-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of AIDS-related lymphoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for AIDS-Related Lymphoma Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Eric J. Seifter, MD (Johns Hopkins University)</ListItem><ListItem>Minh Tam Truong, MD (Boston University Medical Center)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ AIDS-Related Lymphoma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/hp/aids-related-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/hp/aids-related-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389186]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2024-09-18</DateLastModified></Summary>
