<Summary id="CDR0000062957" LegacyPDQID="883"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Pancreatic cancer treatment options depend on extent of disease and may include surgery, radiation, chemotherapy, chemoradiation, and supportive care. Learn more about the treatment of newly diagnosed and recurrent pancreatic cancer in this expert-reviewed information summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Pancreatic Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/pancreatic/hp/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Pancreatic Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041487">pancreatic cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_274">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult pancreatic cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_275">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>pancreatic cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Pancreatic Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Pancreatic Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Pancreatic Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_110"><Title>General Information About Pancreatic Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_111"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_112">Pancreatic cancer is a type of cancer that forms in the tissues of the pancreas.</KeyPoint><Para id="_113">The pancreas is a
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gland</GlossaryTermRef> about 6 inches long that is
		  shaped like a thin pear lying on its side. The wider end of the pancreas is
		  called the head, the middle section is called the body, and the narrow end is
		  called the tail. The pancreas lies between the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000636528" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the pancreas; drawing shows the pancreas, stomach, spleen, liver, bile ducts, gallbladder, small intestine, and colon. An inset shows the head, body, and tail of the pancreas. The bile duct and pancreatic duct are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_250"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the pancreas. The pancreas has three areas: the head, body, and tail. It is found in the abdomen near the stomach, intestines, and other organs. </Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_114">The pancreas has two main jobs in the body:</Para><ItemizedList id="_115" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>to make juices
			 that help break down food into substances the body can use</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>to make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">insulin</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270860" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucagon</GlossaryTermRef>, that help control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658770" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood sugar</GlossaryTermRef>
			 levels and help the body use and store the energy it gets
			 from food</ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_331">Pancreatic cancer can occur in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270856" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">exocrine pancreas cells</GlossaryTermRef>, which produce <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046446" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive</GlossaryTermRef> juices, or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270854" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endocrine pancreas cells</GlossaryTermRef>, which produce hormones. About 95% of pancreatic
		  cancers begin in exocrine
		  cells.</Para><Para id="_117">This summary is about exocrine pancreatic cancer.
		  For information about endocrine pancreatic cancer, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062678" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pnet-treatment-pdq">Pancreatic Neuroendocrine Tumors (Islet Cell Tumors) Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_119">Smoking and health history can affect the risk of pancreatic cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_332">Pancreatic cancer is caused by certain changes to the way pancreatic cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Some risk factors for pancreatic cancer, like smoking, can be changed. However, risk factors also include things people cannot change, like their genetics and their family history. Learning about risk factors for pancreatic cancer can help you make changes that might lower your risk of getting it.</Para><Para id="_333">There are many risk factors for pancreatic cancer, but many do not directly cause cancer. Instead, they increase the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> damage in cells that may lead to pancreatic cancer. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_334">Having one or more of these risk factors does not mean that you will get pancreatic cancer. Many people with risk factors never develop pancreatic cancer, while others with no known risk factors do.</Para><Para id="_268">  Risk       
		  factors for pancreatic cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_121" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>smoking</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>having excess body weight</ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044911" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diabetes</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045106" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatitis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of pancreatic cancer or pancreatitis</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem>having certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hereditary</GlossaryTermRef>
			  conditions, such as:<ItemizedList id="_264" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044884" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hereditary nonpolyposis colon
			 cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (HNPCC; Lynch syndrome)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000377716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Peutz-Jeghers syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000751862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hereditary breast and ovarian cancer syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270857" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">familial
			 atypical multiple mole melanoma (FAMMM) syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ataxia-telangiectasia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_645">Talk with your doctor if you think you might be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_122"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_123">Signs and symptoms of pancreatic cancer include jaundice, pain, and
		  weight loss.</KeyPoint><Para id="_272">Early on, pancreatic cancer may not cause any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, making it hard to detect. As the cancer grows, symptoms may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_125" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">jaundice</GlossaryTermRef>
			 (yellowing of the skin and whites of the eyes)</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>light-colored <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046605" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stools</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>dark urine</ListItem><ListItem>pain in the upper or middle <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> and back</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_646">These symptoms may be caused by many conditions other than pancreatic cancer. It’s important to check with your doctor if you have any of these symptoms to find out the cause and begin treatment, if needed.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_126"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_127">Pancreatic cancer is difficult to diagnose
		  early.</KeyPoint><Para id="_128">Pancreatic cancer is difficult to detect and diagnose for the
		  following reasons:</Para><ItemizedList id="_129" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem>There aren’t any noticeable signs or symptoms in the early
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stages</GlossaryTermRef> of pancreatic
			 cancer.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>The signs and symptoms of pancreatic cancer, when present, are like the
			 signs and symptoms of many other illnesses.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>The pancreas is hidden behind other organs such as the
			 stomach, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>,
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallbladder</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile
			 ducts</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_130"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_131">Tests that examine the pancreas are used to diagnose and stage pancreatic cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_132">Pancreatic cancer is usually diagnosed with tests and procedures
		  that make pictures of the pancreas and the area around it. The process used
		  to find out if cancer cells have spread within and around the pancreas is
		  called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. Tests and procedures
		  to detect, diagnose, and stage pancreatic cancer are usually done at the same
		  time. To plan treatment, it is important to know the stage of
		  the disease and whether the pancreatic cancer can be removed by
		  surgery.</Para><Para id="_266"> In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_133" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong>Blood chemistry study </Strong>is a laboratory test in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044518" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilirubin</GlossaryTermRef>, released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.

</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Tumor marker test</Strong> checks a sample of blood, urine, or tissue to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000633729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CA 19-9</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000357558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoembryonic antigen</GlossaryTermRef> (CEA), made by organs, tissues, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> cells in the body. Certain substances are linked to specific types of cancer when found in increased levels in the body. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor markers</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic
			 resonance imaging)</Strong> uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT
			 scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiral</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044460" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">helical CT</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scan</GlossaryTermRef> makes a series of very detailed pictures of areas inside the body using an x-ray machine that scans the body in a spiral path.</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron
			 emission tomography scan)</Strong> uses a small amount of radioactive sugar (also called glucose) that is injected into a vein. Then a scanner rotates around the body to make detailed, computerized pictures of areas inside the body where the glucose is taken up. Because cancer cells often take up more glucose than normal cells, the pictures can be used to find cancer cells in the body. A PET scan and CT scan may be done at the same time. This is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000742485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET-CT</GlossaryTermRef>.
</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong>Abdominal ultrasound</Strong> makes pictures of the inside of the abdomen. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367430" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound transducer</GlossaryTermRef> is pressed against the skin of the abdomen and directs high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) into the abdomen. The sound waves bounce off the internal tissues and  organs and make echoes.  The transducer receives the echoes and sends them to a computer, which uses the echoes to make pictures called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonograms</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem> <Strong>Endoscopic
			 ultrasound (EUS)</Strong> is a procedure that uses an    endoscope  inserted into the body, usually through the mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>. An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing.  A probe at the end of the endoscope   is used to bounce high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) off internal tissues or organs and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.  This procedure is also called endosonography.</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem><Strong>Endoscopic
			 retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP)</Strong> is a procedure to x-ray the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046441" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ducts</GlossaryTermRef> (tubes) that carry <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef> from the liver to the gallbladder and from the gallbladder to the small intestine.  Sometimes pancreatic cancer causes these ducts to narrow and block or slow the flow of bile, causing jaundice.  An endoscope (a thin, lighted tube) is passed through the mouth, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>, and stomach into the first part of the small intestine.  A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> (a smaller tube) is then inserted through the endoscope into the pancreatic ducts.  A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> is injected through the catheter into the ducts and an x-ray is taken.  If the ducts are blocked by a tumor, a fine tube may be inserted into the duct to unblock it.  This tube (or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stent</GlossaryTermRef>) may be left in place to keep the duct open.  Tissue samples may also be taken.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong>Percutaneous
			 transhepatic cholangiography (PTC)</Strong> is a procedure to x-ray the liver and bile ducts.  A thin needle is inserted through the skin below the ribs and into the liver.  Dye is injected into the liver or bile ducts and an x-ray is taken.  If a blockage is found, a thin, flexible tube called a stent is sometimes left in the liver to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407759" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drain</GlossaryTermRef> bile into the small intestine or a collection bag outside the body. This test is done only if <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046424" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ERCP</GlossaryTermRef> cannot be
			 done.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong>Laparoscopy</Strong> is a surgical procedure to look at the organs inside the abdomen to check for signs of disease.  Small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incisions</GlossaryTermRef> (cuts) are made in the wall of the abdomen and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laparoscope</GlossaryTermRef> (a thin, lighted tube) is inserted into one of the incisions. The laparoscope may have an ultrasound probe at the end in order to bounce high-energy sound waves off internal organs, such as the pancreas. This is called laparoscopic ultrasound. Other instruments may be inserted through the same or other incisions to perform procedures such as taking tissue samples from the pancreas or a sample of fluid     from the abdomen to check for cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Biopsy</Strong> is the removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer. There are several ways to do a biopsy for pancreatic cancer.
			 A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fine needle</GlossaryTermRef> or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641799" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">core needle</GlossaryTermRef> may be inserted into the pancreas during an x-ray or
			 ultrasound to remove cells. Tissue
			 may also be removed during a laparoscopy or surgery to remove the tumor.</ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_642"><KeyPoint id="_641">Some people decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_643">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your pancreatic cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_644">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI’s Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_135">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance
		  of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_227">The prognosis and treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_228" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem>whether the tumor can be removed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>the stage
		  of the cancer (the size of the tumor and whether the cancer has spread outside
		  the pancreas to nearby tissues or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph
		  nodes</GlossaryTermRef> or to other places in the body)</ListItem><ListItem>the patient’s general
		  health</ListItem>
    
    <ListItem>whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has recurred (come back)</ListItem>
   </ItemizedList><Para id="_137">Pancreatic cancer can be controlled only if it is found before it
		  has spread, when it can be completely removed by surgery. If the cancer has spread,
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative treatment</GlossaryTermRef> can improve the patient's
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> by controlling the
		  symptoms and complications of this disease. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><Title>Stages of Pancreatic Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_140"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_295">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_335">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of the pancreatic cancer to plan the best treatment.</Para><Para id="_336">There are several staging systems for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. Pancreatic cancer staging usually uses the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. Your cancer may be described by this staging system in your pathology report. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to your cancer. When talking to you about your cancer, your doctor may describe it as one of these stages.</Para><Para id="_337">To learn how doctors stage pancreatic cancer, visit  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062957#_130" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">tests to diagnose and stage pancreatic cancer</SummaryRef>. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_338">The information in this section is about staging for exocrine pancreatic cancer, the most common type of pancreatic cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_143"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_144">The following stages are used for pancreatic
			 cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_230"><KeyPoint id="_231">Stage 0 (carcinoma in situ)</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000793188" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage 0 pancreatic cancer; drawing shows abnormal cells in the pancreas." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_285"><Caption language="en">Stage 0 pancreatic cancer. Abnormal cells are found in the lining of the pancreas. These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue.
</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_232">In stage 0, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> cells are found in the lining of the pancreas. These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. Stage 0 is also called carcinoma in situ.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_145"><KeyPoint id="_146">Stage I (also called stage 1) pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000687928" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage I pancreatic cancer; drawing on the left shows stage IA pancreatic cancer. The cancer is in the pancreas and the tumor is 2 centimeters or smaller. An inset shows 2 centimeters is about the size of a peanut. The drawing on the right shows stage IB pancreatic cancer. The cancer is in the pancreas and the tumor is larger than 2 centimeters but not larger than 4 centimeters. An inset shows 2 centimeters is about the size of a peanut and 4 centimeters is about the size of a walnut." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_259"><Caption language="en">Stage I pancreatic cancer. Cancer is found in the pancreas only. In stage IA, the tumor is 2 centimeters or smaller. In stage IB, the tumor is larger than 2 centimeters but not larger than 4 centimeters.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_147">In stage I, cancer has formed and is
				found in the pancreas only.  Stage I is divided into
				stages IA and IB,    depending on the size of the tumor.</Para><ItemizedList id="_222" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Stage IA: The tumor is 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller.</ListItem><ListItem>Stage IB: The tumor is larger than 2  centimeters but not larger than 4 centimeters.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><KeyPoint id="_149">Stage II (also called stage 2) pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_150">Stage II is divided into
				stages IIA and IIB, depending on the size of the tumor and where the
				cancer has spread.</Para><ItemizedList id="_223" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Stage IIA: The tumor is larger than 4 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000687932" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IIA pancreatic cancer; drawing shows cancer in the pancreas and the tumor is larger than 4 centimeters. An inset shows 4 centimeters is about the size of a walnut." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_260"><Caption language="en">Stage IIA pancreatic cancer. The tumor is larger than 4 centimeters.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIB: The tumor is any size, and cancer has spread to 1 to 3 nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000742418" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IIB pancreatic cancer; drawing shows cancer in the pancreas and in 1 to 3 nearby lymph nodes." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_261"><Caption language="en">Stage IIB pancreatic cancer. The tumor is any size and cancer has spread to 1 to 3 nearby lymph nodes.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_151"><KeyPoint id="_152">Stage III (also called stage 3) pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000687940" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage III pancreatic cancer; drawing shows cancer in the pancreas and in (a) 4 or more nearby lymph nodes and (b) the common hepatic artery. Also shown are the portal vein, celiac axis (trunk), and superior mesenteric artery." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_262"><Caption language="en">Stage III pancreatic cancer. The tumor is any size and cancer has spread to (a) 4 or more nearby lymph nodes; or (b) the major blood vessels near the pancreas. These include the portal vein, common hepatic artery, celiac axis (trunk), and superior mesenteric artery. </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_283">In stage III, the tumor is any size, and cancer has spread to:</Para><ItemizedList id="_284" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>four or more nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>; or</ListItem><ListItem>the major <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> near the pancreas.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_154"><KeyPoint id="_155">Stage IV (also called stage 4) pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000687943" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IV pancreatic cancer; drawing shows other parts of the body where pancreatic cancer may spread, including the lung, liver, and peritoneal cavity. An inset shows cancer cells spreading from the pancreas, through the blood and lymph system, to another part of the body where metastatic cancer has formed." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_263"><Caption language="en">Stage IV pancreatic cancer. The tumor is any size and cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the lung, liver, or peritoneal cavity (the body cavity that contains most of the organs in the abdomen). </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_156">In stage IV, the tumor is any size, and cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, or peritoneal cavity (the body cavity that contains most of the organs in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para><Para id="_339">Stage IV pancreatic cancer is also called metastatic pancreatic cancer. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the lymphatic system or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if pancreatic cancer spreads to the liver, the cancer cells in the liver are actually pancreatic cancer cells. The disease is called metastatic pancreatic cancer, not liver cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_302"><KeyPoint id="_303">The following groups are used to plan treatment:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_304"><KeyPoint id="_305">Resectable pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_306">Resectable pancreatic cancer can be removed by surgery because it has not grown into major blood vessels near the tumor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_307"><KeyPoint id="_308">Borderline resectable pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_309">Borderline resectable pancreatic cancer has grown into a major blood vessel or nearby tissue or organs. It may be possible to remove the tumor, but there is a high risk that all of the cancer cells will not be removed with surgery.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_310"><KeyPoint id="_311">Locally advanced pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_312"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> pancreatic cancer has grown into or close to nearby lymph nodes or blood vessels, so surgery cannot completely remove the cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_313"><KeyPoint id="_314">Metastatic pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_315"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> pancreatic cancer has spread to other organs, so surgery cannot completely remove the cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_321"><KeyPoint id="_322">Recurrent pancreatic cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_323">Recurrent pancreatic cancer is cancer that has recurred
		(come back) after it has been treated. The cancer may come
		back in the pancreas or in other
		parts of the body. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned in your body. The type of treatment for recurrent pancreatic cancer will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_340">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_162"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_163"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_164">There are different types of treatment for patients with
		  pancreatic cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_341">Different types of treatments are available for people with pancreatic cancer. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the stage of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment.</Para><Para id="_342">Talking with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You’ll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you’ll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_167"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_168">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_169"><KeyPoint id="_170">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_171">One of the following types of surgery may be used to take out the
			 tumor:</Para><ItemizedList id="_172" Style="bullet"> 
			 <ListItem>Whipple
				procedure is surgery to remove the head of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallbladder</GlossaryTermRef>, part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>, part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile duct</GlossaryTermRef>.  Enough of the pancreas is left to produce digestive juices and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">insulin</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
			 <ListItem>Total
				pancreatectomy is surgery to remove the whole pancreas, part
				of the stomach, part of the small
				intestine, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046466" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">common bile
				duct</GlossaryTermRef>, the gallbladder, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef>, and nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Distal pancreatectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is surgery to remove the body and the tail of the
				pancreas. The spleen may also be removed if cancer has spread to the spleen.</ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList><Para id="_173">If the cancer has spread and cannot be removed, the following
			 types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative surgery</GlossaryTermRef> may be
			 done to relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_174" Style="bullet"> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biliary bypass</GlossaryTermRef>: If cancer is blocking the bile duct
				and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef> is building up in the
				gallbladder, a biliary bypass may be done. During this operation, the doctor
				will cut the gallbladder or bile duct in the area before the blockage and sew it to the small intestine to
				create a new pathway around the blocked area. </ListItem> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stent</GlossaryTermRef> placement: If the tumor is blocking the
				bile duct, surgery may be done to put in a stent (a thin tube) to drain bile
				that has built up in the area. The doctor may place the stent through a
				<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> that drains the bile into a bag on the outside
				of the body, or the stent may go around the blocked area and drain the bile into
				the small intestine.</ListItem> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046770" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gastric</GlossaryTermRef> bypass:
				If the tumor is blocking the flow of food from the stomach, the stomach may be
				sewn directly to the small intestine so the patient can continue to eat
				normally.</ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_175"><KeyPoint id="_176">Radiation therapy
			 </KeyPoint><Para id="_177"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation
			 therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells            or keep them from growing.  Pancreatic cancer is sometimes treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">external beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. This type of radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para><Para id="_349">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_178"><KeyPoint id="_179">Chemotherapy </KeyPoint><Para id="_180">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. </Para><Para id="_343">Chemotherapy for pancreatic cancer is usually systemic, meaning it is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or given by mouth. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream to reach cancer cells throughout the body.</Para><Para id="_344">Chemotherapy drugs used to treat pancreatic cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_345" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496354" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/capecitabine">capecitabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537894" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/fluorouracil">fluorouracil (5-FU)</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495426" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemcitabinehydrochloride">gemcitabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537382" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecanhydrochloride">irinotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000776561" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecan-hydrochloride-liposome">irinotecan sucrosofate</DrugRef> (also called nanoliposomal irinotecan)</ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599725" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/leucovorincalcium">leucovorin</DrugRef> (a vitamin that improves the effectiveness of 5-FU)</ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000492041" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/oxaliplatin">oxaliplatin</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_346">Combinations of these drugs may be used. Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_647">Chemotherapy may also be combined with other kinds of treatment. For example, it may be combined with radiation therapy or targeted therapy.</Para><Para id="_347">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_256"><KeyPoint id="_257">Chemoradiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_258">Chemoradiation therapy combines chemotherapy and radiation therapy to increase the effects of both.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_253"><KeyPoint id="_254">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_255">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells.  
<DrugRef href="CDR0000492018" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/erlotinibhydrochloride">Erlotinib</DrugRef> is a targeted therapy drug used to treat pancreatic cancer.</Para><Para id="_348">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_188"><KeyPoint id="_189">There are treatments for pain caused by pancreatic
		  cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_190">Pain can occur when the tumor presses on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef> or other organs
		  near the pancreas. When pain medicine is not enough, there are treatments that
		  act on nerves in the abdomen to
		  relieve the pain. The doctor may inject medicine into the area around affected
		  nerves or may cut the nerves to block the feeling of pain. Radiation therapy
		  with or without chemotherapy can also help relieve pain by shrinking the tumor.     
		  Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062845" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-pdq">Cancer Pain</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_191"><KeyPoint id="_192">Patients with pancreatic cancer have special nutritional
		  needs.</KeyPoint><Para id="_193">Surgery to remove the pancreas may affect its ability to make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046704" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> that help to
		  digest food. As a result, patients may have problems digesting food and
		  absorbing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef> into the body. To prevent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malnutrition</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may prescribe medicines
		  that replace these enzymes.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_181"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_182">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_181_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_181_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_181_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_279"><KeyPoint id="_280">Treatment for pancreatic cancer may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_279_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_247"><KeyPoint id="_248">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_247_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_247_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_286"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042468">stage I pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042484">stage II pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Resectable or  Borderline Resectable Pancreatic Cancer</Title><Para id="_288">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044568" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resectable</GlossaryTermRef> or borderline resectable pancreatic cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_289" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, followed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>surgery</ListItem><ListItem>surgery, followed by chemotherapy</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>surgery, followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306495" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemoradiation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of chemotherapy and/or radiation therapy before surgery</ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of chemoradiation, followed by surgery and then chemotherapy </ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>a clinical trial of different ways of giving radiation therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_324">Surgery to remove the tumor may include  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046653" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Whipple procedure</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046694" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total pancreatectomy</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distal pancreatectomy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_325"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> can be started  at any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of disease. Visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062957#_298" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Palliative Therapy</SummaryRef> section for information about treatments that may improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> or relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> in people with pancreatic cancer.</Para><Para id="_327">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062957#_167" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_286_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_290"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042547">stage IV pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</Title><Para id="_292">Treatment of pancreatic cancer that is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_293" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306495" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemoradiation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>surgery (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046653" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Whipple procedure</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046694" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total pancreatectomy</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distal pancreatectomy</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative</GlossaryTermRef> surgery or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stent</GlossaryTermRef> placement to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046498" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bypass</GlossaryTermRef> blocked areas in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046441" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ducts</GlossaryTermRef>
			 or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>, and possibly chemotherapy and chemoradiation to shrink the tumor to allow for surgery</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of  new anticancer therapies together with  chemotherapy or chemoradiation</ListItem> 
		   
		  <ListItem>a clinical trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> given during surgery or
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">internal radiation</GlossaryTermRef> therapy </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_326"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> can be started  at any  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of disease. Visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062957#_298" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Palliative Therapy</SummaryRef> section for information about treatments that may improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> or relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with pancreatic cancer.</Para><Para id="_328">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062957#_167" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_290_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_294"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042949">recurrent pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic  or  Recurrent Pancreatic Cancer</Title><Para id="_296">Treatment of pancreatic cancer that has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046283" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasized</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_297" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		   
		   
		  <ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of new anticancer agents with or without chemotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_319"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> can be started  at any  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of disease. Visit the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062957#_298" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Palliative Therapy</SummaryRef> section for information about treatments that may improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> or relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with pancreatic cancer.</Para><Para id="_329">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062957#_167" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_294_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_298"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042468">stage I pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000682753">stage IA pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000682755">stage IB pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042484">stage II pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000682756">stage IIA pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000682757">stage IIB pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042505">stage III pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042547">stage IV pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042949">recurrent pancreatic cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Palliative Therapy</Title><Para id="_320"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> can improve the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> by controlling the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> and complications of pancreatic cancer.</Para><Para id="_299">Palliative therapy for pancreatic cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_300" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>palliative surgery or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044903" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stent</GlossaryTermRef> placement to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046498" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bypass</GlossaryTermRef> blocked areas
			 in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046441" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ducts</GlossaryTermRef> or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>palliative <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to help relieve pain by shrinking the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> of medicine to  help relieve pain by blocking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>other palliative medical care alone</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_330">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062957#_167" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_298_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_235"><Title>To Learn More About Pancreatic Cancer</Title><Para id="_236">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  pancreatic cancer, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_237" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/pancreatic">Pancreatic Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000798745" url="/types/pancreatic/patient/child-pancreatic-treatment-pdq">Childhood Pancreatic Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pancreatic">Drugs Approved for Pancreatic Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_235_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_235_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult pancreatic cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Pancreatic Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/pancreatic/patient/pancreatic-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389396]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062951"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
