<Summary id="CDR0000062968" LegacyPDQID="1547"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatment of ovarian borderline tumors depends on tumor size and stage (whether it affects part of or the whole ovary, or has spread to other parts of the body) and the woman's plans for having children. Learn about types of surgery and other treatment options for ovarian borderline      tumors.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/ovarian/patient/ovarian-low-malignant-treatment-pdq">Ovarian Borderline Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/ovarian/hp/ovarian-borderline-tumors-treatment-pdq">Ovarian Borderline Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041115">borderline ovarian surface epithelial-stromal tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_166">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of ovarian borderline tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_167">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in  treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>borderline ovarian surface epithelial-stromal tumor</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Ovarian Borderline Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Treatment of Ovarian Borderline Tumors</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Treatment of Ovarian Borderline Tumors</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>General Information About Ovarian Borderline Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_51"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_52">Ovarian borderline tumor is a disease in which abnormal cells form in
		  the tissue covering the ovary. </KeyPoint><Para id="_53">Ovarian borderline tumors have  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> cells that may become <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, but usually do not. This disease usually remains in the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovary</GlossaryTermRef>. When disease is found in one
		  ovary, the other ovary  should also be checked carefully for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> of
		  disease.</Para><Para id="_54"> The ovaries are a pair of organs in the female
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046564" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reproductive system</GlossaryTermRef>. They are
		  in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, one on each
		  side of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef> (the hollow,
		  pear-shaped organ where a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046400" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fetus</GlossaryTermRef>
		  grows). Each ovary is about the size and shape of an almond. The ovaries
		  make eggs and female <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef>. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000609921" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the female reproductive system; drawing shows the uterus, myometrium (muscular outer layer of the uterus), endometrium (inner lining of the uterus), ovaries, fallopian tubes, cervix, and vagina." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_148"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the female reproductive system. The organs in the female reproductive system include the uterus, ovaries, fallopian tubes, cervix, and vagina. The uterus has a muscular outer layer called the myometrium and an inner lining called the endometrium. </Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_150"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_151">Signs and symptoms of ovarian borderline tumor include pain or swelling in the abdomen.</KeyPoint><Para id="_152">Ovarian borderline tumor may not cause early signs or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. If you do have signs or symptoms, they may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_153" Style="bullet"><ListItem>pain or swelling in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pain in the pelvis</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> problems, such as gas, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bloating</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_154">These signs and symptoms may be caused by other conditions. If they get worse or do not go away on their own, check with your doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_158"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_159">Tests that examine the ovaries are used to diagnose and stage ovarian borderline tumor.</KeyPoint><Para id="_354">In addition to asking about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and doing a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor may perform the following tests and procedures:</Para><ItemizedList id="_161" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pelvic exam</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is an exam of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef>, uterus, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef>, ovaries, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>.    A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046588" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">speculum</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted into the vagina and the doctor or nurse looks at the vagina and cervix for signs of disease.  A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045978" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pap test</GlossaryTermRef> of the cervix is usually done.  The doctor or nurse also inserts one or two lubricated, gloved fingers of one hand into the vagina and places the other hand over the lower abdomen to feel the size, shape, and position of the uterus and ovaries. The doctor or nurse also inserts a lubricated, gloved finger into the rectum to feel for lumps or abnormal areas.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000609924" type="image/jpeg" alt="Pelvic exam; drawing shows a side view of the female reproductive anatomy during a pelvic exam. The uterus, left fallopian tube, left ovary, cervix, vagina, bladder, and rectum are shown. Two gloved fingers of one hand of the doctor or nurse are shown inserted into the vagina, while the other hand is shown pressing on the lower abdomen. The inset shows a woman covered by a drape on an exam table with her legs apart and her feet in stirrups." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_165"><Caption language="en">Pelvic exam. A doctor or nurse inserts one or two lubricated, gloved fingers of one hand into the vagina and presses on the lower abdomen with the other hand. This is done to feel the size, shape, and position of the uterus and ovaries. The vagina, cervix,  fallopian tubes, and rectum are also checked.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> exam</Strong> is a procedure in which high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) are bounced off internal tissues or organs and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>. The picture can be printed to be looked at later.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000618022" type="image/jpeg" alt="Abdominal ultrasound; drawing shows a woman on an exam table during an abdominal ultrasound procedure. A diagnostic sonographer (a person trained to perform ultrasound procedures) is shown passing a transducer (a device that makes sound waves that bounce off tissues inside the body) over the surface of the patient’s abdomen. A computer screen shows a sonogram (computer picture)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_163"><Caption language="en">Abdominal ultrasound. An ultrasound transducer connected to a computer is passed over the surface of the abdomen. The ultrasound transducer bounces sound waves off internal organs and tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture).</Caption></MediaLink>Other patients may have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046633" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transvaginal ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef>. 

<MediaLink ref="CDR0000618018" type="image/jpeg" alt="Transvaginal ultrasound; drawing shows a side view of the female reproductive anatomy during a transvaginal ultrasound procedure. An ultrasound probe (a device that makes sound waves that bounce off tissues inside the body) is shown inserted into the vagina. The bladder, uterus, right fallopian tube, and right ovary are also shown. The inset shows the diagnostic sonographer (a person trained to perform ultrasound procedures) examining a woman on a table, and a computer screen shows an image of the patient’s internal tissues." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_164"><Caption language="en">Transvaginal ultrasound. An ultrasound probe connected to a computer is inserted into the vagina and is gently moved to show different organs. The probe bounces sound waves off internal organs and tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture).</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046490" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CA 125</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044528" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assay</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a laboratory test that measures the level of CA 125 in the blood. CA 125 is a substance released by cells into the bloodstream. An increased CA 125 level is sometimes a sign of cancer or other condition.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is the removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> to check for signs of cancer. The tissue is usually removed during surgery to remove the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Staging <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laparotomy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is surgery to determine the extent of cancer within the abdomen. An
		  incision (cut) is made in the wall of the
		  abdomen to remove tissue so a pathologist can check it for signs of cancer. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_355"><KeyPoint id="_356">Some people decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_357">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your tumor.</Para><Para id="_358">Learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_55"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_56">Certain factors affect prognosis
		  (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_57">The  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on:
		  </Para><ItemizedList id="_102" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the
		  disease (whether it affects part of the
		  ovary, involves the whole ovary, or has spread to other places in the body)</ListItem><ListItem>what type of cells make up the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>the size of the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>the patient's general health</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_157">Patients with ovarian borderline tumors have a good prognosis, especially when the tumor is found early.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><Title>Stages of Ovarian Borderline Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_62"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_125">After ovarian borderline tumor has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if abnormal cells have spread within the ovary or to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_359">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of the ovarian borderline tumors to plan the best treatment. Most people are diagnosed with stage
		  I disease. </Para><Para id="_360">Borderline ovarian tumor staging usually uses the FIGO staging system. The tumor may be described by this staging system in your pathology report. Based on the FIGO results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to your tumor. When talking to you about your diagnosis, your doctor may describe the tumor as one of these stages. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_104"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_105">The following stages are used for ovarian borderline tumor:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_107"><KeyPoint id="_108">Stage I (also called stage 1) ovarian borderline tumor</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000618025" type="image/jpeg" alt="Three-panel drawing of stage IA, stage IB, and stage IC; each panel shows the ovaries, fallopian tubes, uterus, cervix, and vagina. The first panel (stage IA) shows cancer inside one ovary. The second panel (stage IB) shows cancer inside both ovaries. The third panel (stage IC) shows cancer inside both ovaries and (a) the tumor in the ovary on the left has ruptured (broken open), (b) there is cancer on the surface of the ovary on the right, and (c) there are cancer cells in the pelvic peritoneal fluid (inset)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_337"><Caption language="en">In stage IA, cancer is found inside a single ovary or fallopian tube. In stage IB, cancer is found inside both ovaries or fallopian tubes. In stage IC, cancer is found inside one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and one of the following is true: (a) either the tumor or the capsule (outer covering) of the ovary has ruptured (broken open), or (b) cancer is also found on the surface of the ovary or fallopian tube, or (c) cancer cells are found in the pelvic peritoneal fluid.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_109">In stage I, the tumor is found in one or both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef>. Stage I is divided into stage IA, stage IB, and stage IC.

</Para><ItemizedList id="_110" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Stage IA: The tumor is found inside a single ovary or fallopian tube. 
</ListItem><ListItem>Stage IB: The tumor is found inside both ovaries or fallopian tubes. 
</ListItem><ListItem>Stage IC: The tumor is found inside one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and one of the following is true: 
<ItemizedList id="_122" Style="dash"><ListItem>tumor cells are found on the outside surface of one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes; or 
</ListItem><ListItem>the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsule</GlossaryTermRef> (outer covering) of the ovary ruptured (broke open) before or during  surgery; or 
</ListItem><ListItem>tumor cells are found in the fluid of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneal cavity</GlossaryTermRef> (the body cavity that contains most of the organs in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>) or in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000700145" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">washings</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef> (tissue lining the peritoneal cavity). 
</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_111"><KeyPoint id="_112">Stage II (also called stage 2) ovarian borderline tumor</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000618027" type="image/jpeg" alt="Three-panel drawing of stage IIA, stage IIB, and stage II primary peritoneal cancer; the first panel (stage IIA) shows cancer inside both ovaries that has spread to the fallopian tube and uterus. Also shown are the cervix and vagina. The second panel (stage IIB) shows cancer inside both ovaries that has spread to the colon. The third panel (primary peritoneal cancer) shows cancer in the pelvic peritoneum." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_338"><Caption language="en">In stage IIA, cancer is found in one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and has spread to the uterus and/or the fallopian tubes and/or the ovaries. In stage IIB, cancer is found in one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and has spread to organs in the peritoneal cavity, such as the colon. In primary peritoneal cancer,  cancer is found in the pelvic peritoneum and has not spread there from another part of the body.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_113">In stage II, the tumor is found in one or both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef> and has spread into other areas of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary peritoneal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> is found within the pelvis. Stage II is divided into stage IIA and stage IIB.</Para><ItemizedList id="_120" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Stage IIA: The tumor has spread from where it first formed to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef> and/or the fallopian tubes and/or the ovaries. 
</ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIB: The tumor has spread from the ovary or fallopian tube to organs in  the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneal cavity</GlossaryTermRef> (the space that contains the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> organs). 
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_114"><KeyPoint id="_115">Stage III (also called stage 3) ovarian borderline tumor</KeyPoint><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_126"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_331">In stage III, the tumor is found in one or both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef>, or is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386215" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary peritoneal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, and has spread outside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>  to other parts of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> and/or to nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.
			  Stage III is divided into stage IIIA, stage IIIB, and stage IIIC.</Para><ItemizedList id="_328" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In stage IIIA, one of the following is true:<ItemizedList id="_327" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The tumor has spread to lymph nodes in the area outside or behind the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef> only;      or</ListItem><ListItem> Tumor cells that can be seen only with a microscope have spread to the surface of the peritoneum outside the pelvis, such as the  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">omentum</GlossaryTermRef> (a fold of the peritoneum that surrounds the  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> and other organs in the abdomen). The tumor may have spread to nearby lymph nodes. </ListItem></ItemizedList> <MediaLink ref="CDR0000618030" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of stage IIIA shows cancer inside both ovaries that has spread to (a) lymph nodes behind the peritoneum and (b) the omentum. The small intestine, colon, fallopian tubes, uterus, and bladder are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_339"><Caption language="en">In stage IIIA, cancer is found in one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and (a) cancer has spread to lymph nodes behind the peritoneum only, or (b) cancer cells that can be seen only with a microscope have spread to the surface of the peritoneum outside the pelvis, such as the omentum. Cancer may have also spread to nearby lymph nodes.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000612891" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stage IIIB</GlossaryTermRef>: The tumor has spread to the peritoneum outside the pelvis, such as the omentum, and the tumor  in the peritoneum is 2 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller. 
The tumor may have spread to lymph nodes behind the peritoneum.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000655351" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of stage IIIB shows cancer inside both ovaries that has spread to the omentum. The cancer in the omentum is 2 centimeters or smaller. An inset shows 2 centimeters is about the size of a peanut. Also shown are the small intestine, colon, fallopian tubes, uterus, bladder, and lymph nodes behind the peritoneum." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_340"><Caption language="en">In stage IIIB, cancer is found in one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and has spread to the peritoneum outside the pelvis, such as the omentum. The cancer in the omentum is 2 centimeters or smaller. Cancer may have also spread to lymph nodes behind the peritoneum.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIIC: The tumor has spread to the peritoneum outside the pelvis, such as the omentum, and the tumor in the peritoneum is
				larger than 2 centimeters. The tumor may have spread to lymph nodes behind the peritoneum or to the surface of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spleen</GlossaryTermRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000655353" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of stage IIIC shows cancer inside both ovaries that has spread to the omentum. The cancer in the omentum is larger than 2 centimeters. An inset shows 2 centimeters is about the size of a peanut. Also shown are the small intestine, colon, fallopian tubes, uterus, bladder, and lymph nodes behind the peritoneum." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_341"><Caption language="en">In stage IIIC, cancer is found in one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and has spread to the peritoneum outside the pelvis, such as the omentum. The cancer in the omentum is larger than 2 centimeters. Cancer may have also spread to lymph nodes behind the peritoneum or to the surface of the liver or spleen (not shown).</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_117"><KeyPoint id="_118">Stage IV (also called stage 4) ovarian borderline tumor</KeyPoint><Para id="_119">  

In stage IV, tumor  cells have spread beyond the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body. Stage IV is divided into stage IVA and stage IVB. 
<MediaLink ref="CDR0000657667" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of stage IV shows other parts of the body where ovarian cancer may spread, including the lung, liver, and lymph nodes in the groin. An inset on the top shows extra fluid around the lung. An inset on the bottom shows cancer cells spreading through the blood and lymph system to another part of the body where metastatic cancer has formed." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_342"><Caption language="en">In stage IV, cancer has spread beyond the abdomen to other parts of the body. In stage IVA, cancer cells are found in extra fluid that builds up around the lungs. In stage IVB, cancer has spread to organs and tissues outside the abdomen, including the lung, liver, and lymph nodes in the groin.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><ItemizedList id="_329" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Stage IVA: Tumor cells are found in  extra fluid that builds up  around the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Stage IVB: The tumor  has spread to organs and tissues outside the abdomen, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_335"><KeyPoint id="_336">Ovarian borderline
		tumors can recur
		(come back) after  they have been treated. </KeyPoint><Para id="_3370">Recurrent ovarian borderline tumors are tumors that have come back after they have been treated. The tumors  may come back in the other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovary</GlossaryTermRef> or in other parts of the
		body. Tests will be done to help determine where the tumor has returned. The type of treatment for a recurrent ovarian borderline tumor will depend on where it has come back.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_68"><KeyPoint id="_69">There are different types of treatment for patients with ovarian borderline tumors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_361">Different types of treatments are available for ovarian borderline tumors. You and your care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the stage of the tumor, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your tumor, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment. </Para><Para id="_362">Talking with your care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You'll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you'll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Treatment</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_72"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_73">The following types of treatment are used: </KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_74"><KeyPoint id="_75">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_76">The type of surgery (removing the
			 tumor in an operation) depends on
			 the size and spread of the tumor and the patient's plans for having children. Surgery
			 may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_77" Style="bullet"> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322894" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Unilateral
				salpingo-oophorectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is surgery to remove one <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovary</GlossaryTermRef> and one <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tube</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322852" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is surgery to remove both ovaries and both fallopian tubes.</ListItem> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Total hysterectomy</GlossaryTermRef> and
				bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy is surgery to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef>, and both ovaries and fallopian tubes.  If the uterus and cervix are taken out through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>, the operation is called a vaginal hysterectomy.  If the uterus and cervix are taken out through a large incision (cut) in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, the operation is called a total abdominal hysterectomy.  If the uterus and cervix are taken out through a small incision (cut) in the abdomen using a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laparoscope</GlossaryTermRef>, the operation is called a total laparoscopic hysterectomy.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000612116" type="image/jpeg" alt="Hysterectomy; drawing shows the female reproductive anatomy, including the ovaries, uterus, vagina, fallopian tubes, and cervix. Dotted lines show which organs and tissues are removed in a total hysterectomy, a total hysterectomy with salpingo-oophorectomy, and a radical hysterectomy. An inset shows the location of two possible incisions on the abdomen: a low transverse incision is just above the pubic area and a vertical incision is between the navel and the pubic area." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_149"><Caption language="en">Hysterectomy. The uterus is surgically removed with or without other organs or tissues. In a total hysterectomy, the uterus and cervix are removed. In a total hysterectomy with salpingo-oophorectomy, (a) the uterus plus one (unilateral) ovary and fallopian tube are removed; or (b) the uterus plus both (bilateral) ovaries and fallopian tubes are removed. In a radical hysterectomy, the uterus, cervix, both ovaries, both fallopian tubes, and nearby tissue are removed. These procedures are done using a low transverse incision or a vertical incision.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem> 
			 <ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Partial oophorectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is surgery to remove part of one ovary or part of both ovaries.</ListItem> 
			 <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045053" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Omentectomy</GlossaryTermRef> is surgery to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">omentum</GlossaryTermRef> (a tissue layer that lines the abdominal wall).</ListItem> 
		  </ItemizedList><Para id="_78">After the doctor removes all disease that can be seen at the
			 time of the surgery, the patient may be given chemotherapy (also  called chemo) after surgery to kill any tumor
			 cells that are left. Treatment given
			 after the surgery to lower the risk that the tumor will come back is called
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_80">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_81">Chemotherapy uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.  Chemotherapy for ovarian borderline tumors is usually systemic, meaning it is injected into a vein or given by mouth. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream to reach cancer cells throughout the body.  </Para><Para id="_623">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_82"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_83">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical
		  trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_82_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_82_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_82_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_168"><KeyPoint id="_169">Treatment for ovarian borderline tumors may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_168_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_363"><KeyPoint id="_364">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_363_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_363_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_86"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000562737">stage I borderline ovarian surface epithelial-stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000562744">stage II borderline ovarian surface epithelial-stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Early Stage Ovarian Borderline Tumors (Stages I and II)</Title><Para id="_87">Surgery is the
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for early
		  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> ovarian borderline tumors. The type of surgery usually depends on
		  whether a patient plans to have children.</Para><Para id="_88">For patients who plan to have children, surgery is either:</Para><ItemizedList id="_89" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322894" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">unilateral salpingo-oophorectomy</GlossaryTermRef> or
			 </ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">partial oophorectomy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_90">To prevent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrence</GlossaryTermRef> of
		  disease, most doctors recommend surgery to remove the remaining ovarian tissue
		  when a patient no longer plans to have children.</Para><Para id="_91">For patients who do not plan to have children, treatment may
		  be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hysterectomy</GlossaryTermRef> and
			 
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322852" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_365">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062968#_72" url="/types/ovarian/patient/ovarian-low-malignant-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_86_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_93"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000562754">stage III borderline ovarian surface epithelial-stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000562757">stage IV borderline ovarian surface epithelial-stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Advanced Stage Ovarian Borderline Tumors (Stages III and IV)</Title><Para id="_94">Treatment for advanced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> ovarian borderline tumors may
		  be hysterectomy, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322852" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy</GlossaryTermRef>, and
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045053" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">omentectomy</GlossaryTermRef>.  A
			 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node dissection</GlossaryTermRef> may also be
			 done. Patients with advanced disease should undergo a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">total hysterectomy</GlossaryTermRef>, bilateral
salpingo-oophorectomy, omentectomy, node sampling, and aggressive cytoreductive
surgery.</Para><Para id="_366">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062968#_72" url="/types/ovarian/patient/ovarian-low-malignant-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_93_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_96"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000562763">recurrent borderline ovarian surface epithelial-stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Ovarian Borderline Tumors</Title><Para id="_97">Treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef>
		ovarian borderline tumors may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_98" Style="bullet"> 
		<ListItem>surgery to remove cancer that has spread in the abdominal cavity</ListItem> 
		<ListItem>surgery followed by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
	 </ItemizedList><Para id="_368">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062968#_72" url="/types/ovarian/patient/ovarian-low-malignant-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_96_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_127"><Title>To Learn More About Ovarian Borderline Tumors</Title><Para id="_127_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_127_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of ovarian borderline tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Ovarian Borderline Tumors Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/ovarian/patient/ovarian-low-malignant-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/ovarian/patient/ovarian-low-malignant-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389247]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062941"/><DateLastModified>2025-04-10</DateLastModified></Summary>
