<Summary id="CDR0000062966" LegacyPDQID="1371"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Nasopharyngeal cancer treatment options include radiation therapy, chemotherapy, or radiation together with chemotherapy. Sometimes surgery is also needed. Learn more about newly diagnosed and recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Nasopharyngeal Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Nasopharyngeal Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_225">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult nasopharyngeal cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_226">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adult nasopharyngeal cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Nasopharyngeal Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Nasopharyngeal Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Nasopharyngeal Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_89"><Title>General Information About Nasopharyngeal Cancer </Title><SummarySection id="_90"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_91">Nasopharyngeal cancer is a type of head and neck cancer that starts in the tissues of the nasopharynx.</KeyPoint><Para id="_308">The pharynx is a hollow tube in the neck about 5 inches long that is made up of three parts: </Para><ItemizedList id="_309" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The nasopharynx is the upper part of the pharynx, located behind the nose. The nostrils are connected to the nasopharynx. Openings on each side of the nasopharynx lead to the ears.</ListItem><ListItem>The oropharynx is the middle part, located beneath the nasopharynx.</ListItem><ListItem>The hypopharynx is the lowermost part of the pharynx, opening up to both the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> (windpipe) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_310">When we breathe or swallow, the pharynx acts as a passageway for air to reach the lungs and food to reach the stomach. Nasopharyngeal cancer commonly begins in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046056" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">squamous cells</GlossaryTermRef> that line the nasopharynx.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000713970" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the pharynx; drawing shows the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and hypopharynx. Also shown are the nasal cavity, oral cavity, hyoid bone, larynx, esophagus, and trachea." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_311"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the pharynx. The pharynx is a hollow, muscular tube inside the neck that starts behind the nose and opens into the larynx and esophagus. The three parts of the pharynx are the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and hypopharynx.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_93"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_94">Being exposed to the Epstein-Barr virus, your ancestry, and where you live can
		  affect the risk of nasopharyngeal cancer. </KeyPoint><Para id="_276">Nasopharyngeal cancer is caused by certain changes in how nasopharyngeal cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. There are many risk factors for nasopharyngeal cancer, but many do not directly cause cancer. Instead, they increase the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> damage in cells that may lead to nasopharyngeal cancer. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_277">A risk factor is anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease. Some risk factors for nasopharyngeal cancer, like tobacco use, can be changed. Risk factors also include things you cannot change, like your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef>. Learning about risk factors for nasopharyngeal cancer can help you make choices that might prevent or lower your risk of getting it. </Para><Para id="_278">Risk factors for nasopharyngeal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_279" Style="bullet"><ListItem>being infected with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef> (EBV) </ListItem><ListItem>living in or having ancestry in certain parts of Asia, North Africa, and the Arctic</ListItem><ListItem>having a family member with nasopharyngeal cancer</ListItem><ListItem>using tobacco or breathing in secondhand smoke </ListItem><ListItem>frequent and heavy alcohol use</ListItem><ListItem>having a diet high in salt-cured fish and meats because these foods may contain cancer-causing chemicals, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658447" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nitrosamine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_281">Nasopharyngeal cancer can occur at any age. In areas where the disease is not common, it is more likely to be diagnosed in people who are older than 50 years. In high-risk areas, younger people are more likely to be affected. Men tend to develop nasopharyngeal cancer more often than women. In rare  cases, human papillomavirus (HPV), especially HPV type 16, has been linked to nasopharyngeal cancer. Learn about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/infectious-agents/hpv-fact-sheet">HPV and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1752">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco">Tobacco</ExternalRef>, including help with quitting.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_97"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_98">Signs and symptoms of nasopharyngeal cancer include trouble
		  breathing, speaking, or hearing.</KeyPoint><Para id="_312">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of nasopharyngeal cancer can vary from person to person. Early signs and symptoms of nasopharyngeal cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_282" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a lump in the neck</ListItem><ListItem>pain, pulsing, or ringing in the ear</ListItem><ListItem>trouble hearing</ListItem><ListItem>a sore throat</ListItem><ListItem>stuffy nose</ListItem><ListItem>nosebleeds</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_283">	Signs and symptoms of advanced nasopharyngeal cancer (nasopharyngeal cancer that has spread to other parts of the body) may include symptoms of early-stage nasopharyngeal cancer and:</Para><ItemizedList id="_284" Style="bullet"><ListItem>misalignment of the eyes (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000815503" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">strabismus</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>double vision</ListItem><ListItem>headaches</ListItem><ListItem>facial numbness</ListItem><ListItem>facial weakness</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_285">These problems may be caused by conditions other than nasopharyngeal cancer. Check with your doctor if you have any of these problems to find out the cause and begin treatment, if needed.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_101"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_102">Tests that examine the nose, throat, and nearby organs are used to diagnose and stage nasopharyngeal cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_238">If you have symptoms that suggest nasopharyngeal cancer, your doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. They will ask when the symptoms started and how often you have been having them. They will also ask about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>.   Based on these results, the doctor may recommend other tests. If you are diagnosed with nasopharyngeal cancer, the results of these tests will help you and your doctor plan treatment. 
</Para><Para id="_287">The following tests and procedures are used to diagnose and stage nasopharyngeal cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_288" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Nasopharyngoscopy with biopsy</Strong> is a procedure to examine the inside of the nose and back of the throat. The doctor inserts a nasopharyngoscope (a thin, flexible lighted tube) in the nose and advances it to the back of the throat to check for abnormal areas. The nasopharyngoscope may have a tool to remove a sample of cells or tissue (biopsy) so a pathologist can view it under a microscope to check for signs of cancer. Learn about the type of information that can be found in a pathologist's report about the cells or tissue removed during a biopsy at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/diagnosis/pathology-reports-fact-sheet">Pathology Reports</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic
		  resonance imaging)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000742485" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET-CT scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> combines pictures from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">positron emission tomography (PET) scan</GlossaryTermRef> and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">computed tomography (CT) scan</GlossaryTermRef>. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time on the same machine. The combined pictures make a more detailed picture than either test would make by itself.<ItemizedList id="_289" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	For the PET scan, a small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. The scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body. Because cancer cells often take up more glucose than normal cells, the pictures can be used to find cancer cells in the body.</ListItem><ListItem>For the CT scan, a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body is taken from different angles. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) test</Strong> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688783" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood test</GlossaryTermRef> to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> markers that are found in the blood of people who have been infected with EBV.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000752847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Human papillomavirus (HPV) test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> used to check a sample of tissue for certain types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HPV</GlossaryTermRef> infection. An HPV test is usually done if the EBV test is negative. This is because in rare cases, HPV can cause nasopharyngeal cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>A <Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurological exam</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> uses a series of questions and tests to check brain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve</GlossaryTermRef> function. The exam checks your mental status, coordination, and ability to walk normally, and how well the muscles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">senses</GlossaryTermRef>, and reflexes work. This may also be called a neuro exam or a neurologic exam.</ListItem><ListItem>A <Strong>hearing test</Strong> checks your ability to hear soft and loud sounds and low- and high-pitched sounds. Each ear is checked separately. This test is done because nasopharyngeal cancer and its treatment can affect hearing. Hearing tests are usually done before, during, and after treatment.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry study</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><Strong>Complete blood
			 count (CBC)</Strong> is a laboratory test in which a sample of blood is drawn and
			 checked for: 
			 <ItemizedList id="_21" Style="dash"> 
				<ListItem>the number of red blood cells, white blood cells, and
				  platelets</ListItem> 
				<ListItem>the amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemoglobin</GlossaryTermRef> (the substance in the blood that carries oxygen) in
				  the red blood cells</ListItem> 
				<ListItem>the amount of hematocrit (whole blood that is made up of red blood
				  cells)</ListItem> 
			 </ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000526546" type="image/jpeg" alt="Complete blood count (CBC); left panel shows blood being drawn from a vein on the inside of the elbow using a tube attached to a syringe; right panel shows a laboratory test tube with blood cells separated into layers: plasma, white blood cells, platelets, and red blood cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_145"><Caption language="en">Complete blood count (CBC). Blood is collected by inserting a needle into a vein and allowing the blood to flow into a tube. The blood sample is sent to the laboratory and the red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets are counted.  The CBC is used to test for, diagnose, and monitor many different conditions.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_290"><KeyPoint id="_291">Some people may decide to get a second opinion.</KeyPoint><Para id="_292">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your nasopharyngeal cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes or another treatment approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_293">Learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_181"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_106">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_182">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and  treatment options depend on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_180" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the size of the
		  tumor</ListItem><ListItem>the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer, including whether cancer has spread to one or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the neck</ListItem><ListItem>whether there are high levels of EBV antibodies and EBV-DNA markers  in the blood before and after treatment</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_108"><Title>Stages of Nasopharyngeal Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_294"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_295">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body. </KeyPoint><Para id="_296">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. Knowing the cancer stage helps plan treatment.  </Para><Para id="_297">There are several staging systems for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. Nasopharyngeal cancer staging usually uses the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. The cancer may be described by this staging system in your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to the cancer. When talking to you about your diagnosis, your doctor may describe the cancer as one of these stages.</Para><Para id="_298">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_112"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Classification by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_113">The following stages are used for nasopharyngeal
		  cancer:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_114"><KeyPoint id="_115">Stage 0 (also called carcinoma in situ of the nasopharynx)</KeyPoint><Para id="_116">In stage 0, abnormal cells are  found in the lining
			 of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharynx</GlossaryTermRef>. These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_117"><KeyPoint id="_118">Stage I (also called stage 1) nasopharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_119">In stage I, cancer has formed, and the cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_205" Style="bullet"><ListItem>is found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharynx</GlossaryTermRef> only; or</ListItem><ListItem>has spread from the nasopharynx to the
				<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharynx</GlossaryTermRef> and/or to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790106" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasal cavity</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_186"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink><SummarySection id="_120"><KeyPoint id="_121">Stage II (also called stage 2) nasopharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_202">In stage II, one of the following is true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_239" Style="bullet" Compact="No"><ListItem>Cancer has spread to one or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> on one side of the neck and/or to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the back of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef>. The affected lymph nodes are 6 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller. Cancer is found:<ItemizedList id="_243" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharynx</GlossaryTermRef> only or has spread from the nasopharynx to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharynx</GlossaryTermRef> and/or to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790106" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasal cavity</GlossaryTermRef>; or</ListItem><ListItem>only in the lymph nodes in the neck. The cancer cells in the lymph nodes are infected with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef> (a virus linked to nasopharyngeal cancer). Cancer was not found in the nasopharynx.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797784" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">parapharyngeal space</GlossaryTermRef> and/or nearby muscles. Cancer may have also spread to one or more lymph nodes on one side of the neck and/or to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the back of the throat. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_124"><KeyPoint id="_125">Stage III (also called stage 3) nasopharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_126"> In stage III, one of the following is true:</Para><ItemizedList id="_240" Style="bullet" Compact="No"><ListItem>Cancer has spread to one or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>  on both sides of the neck. The affected lymph nodes are 6 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller. Cancer is found:<ItemizedList id="_244" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharynx</GlossaryTermRef> only or has spread from the nasopharynx to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharynx</GlossaryTermRef> and/or to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790106" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasal cavity</GlossaryTermRef>; or</ListItem><ListItem>only in the lymph nodes in the neck. The cancer cells in the lymph nodes are infected with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef> (a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045941" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">virus</GlossaryTermRef> linked to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasopharyngeal cancer</GlossaryTermRef>). Cancer was not found in the nasopharynx.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to the parapharyngeal space and/or nearby muscles. Cancer has also spread to one or more lymph nodes on both sides of the neck. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to the bones at the bottom of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skull</GlossaryTermRef>, the bones in the neck, jaw muscles, and/or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sinuses</GlossaryTermRef> around the nose and eyes. Cancer may have also spread to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the neck and/or the back of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef>. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><KeyPoint id="_129">Stage IV (also called stage 4) nasopharyngeal cancer</KeyPoint><Para id="_130"> Stage IV is divided into stages IVA and IVB.</Para><ItemizedList id="_241" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In stage IVA:<ItemizedList id="_242" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Cancer has spread to the brain, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763009" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cranial</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046029" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypopharynx</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">salivary gland</GlossaryTermRef> in the front of the ear, the bone around the eye, and/or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissues</GlossaryTermRef> of the jaw. Cancer may have also spread to one or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> on one or both sides of the neck and/or the back of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef>. The affected lymph nodes are 6 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeters</GlossaryTermRef> or smaller; or</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the neck. The affected lymph nodes are larger than 6 centimeters and/or are found in the lowest part of the neck.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IVB: Cancer has spread beyond the lymph nodes in the neck to distant lymph nodes, such as those between the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>, below the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collarbone</GlossaryTermRef>, or in the armpit or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef>, or to other parts of the body, such as the lung, bone, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_299">Stage IV nasopharyngeal cancer is also called metastatic nasopharyngeal cancer. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if nasopharyngeal cancer spreads to the lung, the cancer cells in the lung are actually nasopharyngeal cancer cells. The disease is called metastatic nasopharyngeal cancer, not lung cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_250"><KeyPoint id="_251">Nasopharyngeal cancer can recur (come back) after it has been treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_252">Recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. If nasopharyngeal cancer comes back, it may come back in the nasopharynx, lymph nodes, or other parts of the body, such as the lungs, bone, or liver. Tests will help determine where in the body the cancer has returned. The type of treatment that you have for recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_300">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_135"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_136">There are different types of treatment for people with nasopharyngeal
		  cancer. </KeyPoint><Para id="_301">Different types of treatments are available for nasopharyngeal cancer. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the stage of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment. </Para><Para id="_302">Talking with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect will be helpful. You'll want to learn what you need to do before treatment begins, how you'll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Your Treatment</ExternalRef>.    </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_54">People with nasopharyngeal cancer should have their treatment planned by a team of doctors with expertise in treating head and neck cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_55">An oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating people with cancer, oversees treatment for nasopharyngeal cancer. Because the nasopharynx
		  helps in breathing, eating, and talking, you may need help
		  adjusting to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer and its treatment. The oncologist may refer you to other health care providers who are experts in treating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and also specialize in other areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_56" Style="bullet"><ListItem>head and neck surgeon</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046221" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plastic surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389460" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dentist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044661" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietitian</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044459" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">speech therapist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_140">The following types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_141"><KeyPoint id="_142">Radiation therapy
			 </KeyPoint><Para id="_143">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing by damaging their DNA. The way radiation therapy is given depends on the type and stage of the cancer. External and internal radiation therapy are used to treat nasopharyngeal cancer.</Para><ItemizedList id="_229" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000732667" type="image/jpeg" alt="External-beam radiation therapy of the head and neck; drawing shows a patient lying on a table under a machine that is used to aim high-energy radiation at the cancer. An inset shows a mesh mask that helps keep the patient's head and neck from moving during treatment. The mask has pieces of white tape with small ink marks on it. The ink marks are used to line up the radiation machine in the same position before each treatment." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_228"><Caption language="en">External-beam radiation therapy of the head and neck. A machine is used to aim high-energy radiation at the cancer. The machine can rotate around the patient, delivering radiation from many different angles to provide highly conformal treatment. A mesh mask helps keep the patient’s head and neck from moving during treatment. Small ink marks are put on the mask. The ink marks are used to line up the radiation machine in the same position before each treatment.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_232">Certain ways of giving radiation therapy can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy tissue. These include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_230" Style="dash">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient"> Intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (IMRT):  IMRT is a  type of 3-dimensional (3-D) radiation therapy that uses a computer to make pictures of  the size and shape of the tumor. Thin beams of radiation of different intensities (strengths) are aimed at the tumor from many angles. Compared to standard radiation therapy, intensity-modulated radiation therapy may be less likely to cause dry mouth. You will likely have treatment once a day, Monday through Friday, for about 6 to 7 weeks.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Stereotactic radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>:  Stereotactic radiation therapy also uses a computer to make detailed images of the tumor.  Thin beams of radiation are aimed at the tumor from different angles. High-dose radiation is given in one to five sessions spread over several days. This procedure is also called stereotactic external-beam radiation and stereotaxic radiation therapy. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_306">External radiation therapy to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046036" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef> or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pituitary gland</GlossaryTermRef> may change the way the thyroid
			 gland works. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688783" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood test</GlossaryTermRef> to check the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid hormone</GlossaryTermRef> level in the blood is done before and after therapy to make sure the thyroid gland is working properly.  It is also important that a dentist check your teeth, gums, and mouth, and fix any existing problems before radiation therapy begins.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Internal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (also called brachytherapy) uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheters</GlossaryTermRef> that are placed directly into or near the cancer. In some cases, it may be used with external radiation therapy to deliver an extra dose of radiation directly to the tumor. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/brachytherapy">Brachytherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_307"><KeyPoint id="_146">Chemotherapy </KeyPoint><Para id="_147"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.  Chemotherapy for nasopharyngeal cancer is usually systemic, meaning it is taken by mouth or injected into a vein or muscle. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body.</Para><Para id="_303">Chemotherapy drugs used to treat nasopharyngeal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_304" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496383" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/docetaxel">docetaxel</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537894" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/fluorouracil">fluorouracil</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495426" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemcitabinehydrochloride">gemcitabine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_305">Combinations of these drugs may be used. Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_216">Chemotherapy may be combined with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_1750">To learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><KeyPoint id="_149">Surgery </KeyPoint><Para id="_150">Surgery to remove the tumor is
			 sometimes used for nasopharyngeal cancer that does not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> to radiation
			 therapy. If cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph
			 nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, the doctor may remove lymph nodes and other tissues in
			 the neck.</Para><Para id="_1751">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery">Surgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1753"><KeyPoint id="_1754">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_1755"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment that uses the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to fight cancer.  Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the body's natural defenses against cancer.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1756" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000777027" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PD-1</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797389" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PD-L1</GlossaryTermRef> inhibitor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>: PD-1 is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> on the surface of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">T cells</GlossaryTermRef> that helps keep the body’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune responses</GlossaryTermRef> in check. PD-L1 is a protein found on some types of cancer cells. When PD-1 attaches to PD-L1, it stops the T cell from killing the cancer cell. PD-1 and PD-L1 inhibitors keep PD-1 and PD-L1 proteins from attaching to each other. This allows the T cells to kill cancer cells. <DrugRef href="CDR0000814429" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/toripalimab-tpzi">Toripalimab</DrugRef> is a type of PD-1 inhibitor used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> nasopharyngeal cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000774646" type="image/jpeg" alt="Immune checkpoint inhibitor; the panel on the left shows the binding of proteins PD-L1 (on the tumor cell) to PD-1 (on the T cell), which keeps T cells from killing tumor cells in the body. Also shown are a tumor cell antigen and T cell receptor. The panel on the right shows immune checkpoint inhibitors (anti-PD-L1 and anti-PD-1) blocking the binding of PD-L1 to PD-1, which allows the T cells to kill tumor cells." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1757"><Caption language="en">Immune checkpoint inhibitor. Checkpoint proteins, such as PD-L1 on tumor cells and PD-1 on T cells, help keep immune responses in check. The binding of PD-L1 to PD-1 keeps T cells from killing tumor cells in the body (left panel). Blocking the binding of PD-L1 to PD-1 with an immune checkpoint inhibitor (anti-PD-L1 or anti-PD-1) allows the T cells to kill tumor cells (right panel).</Caption></MediaLink><EmbeddedVideo id="_1758" ref="CDR0000795515" hosting="youtube" unique_id="GIUu239FWMg" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>immune checkpoint inhibitors</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Immunotherapy uses the body’s immune system to fight cancer. This animation explains one type of immunotherapy that uses immune checkpoint inhibitors to treat cancer.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></SummarySection><Para id="_1759">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_234"><KeyPoint id="_235">Treatment for nasopharyngeal cancer may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_234_md_73">For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> caused by treatment for cancer, visit our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef> page.</Para><Para id="_272">Side effects from cancer treatment that begin after treatment and continue for months or years are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef>. Late effects of nasopharyngeal cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_273" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>chronic dry mouth</ListItem><ListItem>dental and oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complications</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>hearing loss</ListItem><ListItem>vision loss</ListItem><ListItem>difficulty swallowing</ListItem><ListItem>lockjaw</ListItem><ListItem>problems with the thyroid and pituitary gland</ListItem><ListItem>damage to nerves in the brain</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_274">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your doctor about possible late effects caused by some treatments.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_195"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_196">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials. </KeyPoint><Para id="_195_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_195_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_195_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_199"><KeyPoint id="_200">Follow-up care may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_199_md_33">As you go through treatment, you  will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_199_md_34">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_275">After treatment is complete, it is important to have head and neck exams to look for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> that the cancer has come back.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_253"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038905">stage I nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage I Nasopharyngeal Cancer</Title><Para id="_254">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062966#_139" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_255">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046178" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage I nasopharyngeal
		  cancer</GlossaryTermRef> is usually <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation
		  therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the tumor
		  and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the neck.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_253_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_256"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038906">stage II nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage II, III, and  IVA Nasopharyngeal Cancer</Title><Para id="_257">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062966#_139" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_258">Treatment of stage <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046179" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">II</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046180" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">III</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046181" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">IVA</GlossaryTermRef> (nonmetastatic) nasopharyngeal cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_259" Style="bullet"> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the tumor and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the neck</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>
			 given with radiation therapy, followed by more chemotherapy</ListItem> 
		  <ListItem>chemotherapy followed by more chemotherapy given with radiation therapy</ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy followed by radiation therapy (under study)</ListItem><ListItem>surgery to remove lymph nodes if they still contain cancer cells after initial treatment</ListItem> 
		<ListItem>chemotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_256_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_268"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038909">recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options for recurrent cancer</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Stage IVB  and Recurrent Nasopharyngeal Cancer</Title><Para id="_269">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062966#_139" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_270">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046181" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IVB</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef>) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef>
		nasopharyngeal cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_271" Style="bullet"> 
		<ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335073" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intensity-modulated radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stereotactic radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">internal radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> 
		<ListItem>surgery </ListItem> 
		<ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<DrugRef href="CDR0000814429" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/toripalimab-tpzi">toripalimab</DrugRef>) given alone, or immunotherapy given with chemotherapy</ListItem> 
		</ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_268_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_187"><Title>To Learn More About Nasopharyngeal Cancer</Title><Para id="_188">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about  nasopharyngeal cancer, visit: </Para><ItemizedList id="_189" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck">Head and Neck  Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000593427" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/oral-screening-pdq">Oral Cavity and Nasopharyngeal Cancers Screening</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062871" url="/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/mouth-throat/oral-complications-pdq">Oral Complications of Cancer Therapies</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/head-neck">Drugs Approved for Head and Neck Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/head-neck-fact-sheet">Head and Neck Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/tobacco">Tobacco</ExternalRef> (includes help quitting)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_187_md_40">For general cancer information and other resources from the National Cancer Institute, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_187_md_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/radiation-therapy-and-you">Radiation Therapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of adult nasopharyngeal cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Nasopharyngeal Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/adult/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389409]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000062918"/><DateLastModified>2025-05-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
