<Summary id="CDR0000062976"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Laetrile (Amygdalin) has shown little anticancer activity in animal studies and no anticancer activity in human clinical trials.  Laetrile is not approved for use in the United States. Get detailed information about use of Laetrile for cancer in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/laetrile-pdq">Laetrile/Amygdalin (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/laetrile-pdq">Laetrile/Amygdalin (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000257611">laetrile</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_69">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of laetrile/amygdalin in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_70">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>laetrile</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Laetrile/Amygdalin (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Laetrile/Amygdalin (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Laetrile/Amygdalin</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_92"><Strong>NOTE: There is either no new research on this topic or the recent published research is weak and not appropriate for inclusion in the summary. Therefore, the information in this summary is no longer being updated and is provided for reference purposes only.</Strong></Para><Para id="_2">This  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summary provides
an overview of the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laetrile</GlossaryTermRef> as a treatment for people with cancer.  The summary
includes a history of laetrile research, a review of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory studies</GlossaryTermRef>, the
results of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, and possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of laetrile use.</Para><Para id="_3">This summary contains the following key information:</Para><ItemizedList id="_4" Style="bullet">
         <ListItem>Laetrile is another name for the natural product <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">amygdalin</GlossaryTermRef>, which is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef> constituent found in
the pits of many fruits and in numerous plants.</ListItem>
         <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686192" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hydrogen cyanide</GlossaryTermRef> is thought to be the main anticancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compound</GlossaryTermRef> formed from laetrile via <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> release.</ListItem>
         <ListItem>Laetrile was first used as a cancer treatment in Russia in 1845, and in
the United States in the 1920s.</ListItem>
         <ListItem>Laetrile has shown little anticancer activity in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> and no
anticancer activity in human clinical
trials.</ListItem>
         <ListItem>The side effects associated with laetrile <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> mirror the symptoms of cyanide poisoning, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> damage, difficulty walking (caused by damaged <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef>), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476351" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coma</GlossaryTermRef>, and death.</ListItem><ListItem>Laetrile is not approved for use in the United States.</ListItem>
        <ListItem>Inappropriate advertisement of laetrile as a cancer treatment resulted in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> investigation  that culminated in charges and conviction of one distributor.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_41">Many of the medical and scientific terms used in this summary are hypertext linked (at first use in each section) to the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>, which is oriented toward nonexperts. When a linked term is clicked, a definition will appear in a separate window. </Para><Para id="_42">Reference citations in some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> cancer information summaries may include links to external websites that are operated by individuals or organizations for the purpose of marketing or advocating the use of specific treatments or products. These reference citations are included for informational purposes only. Their inclusion should not be viewed as an endorsement of the content of the websites, or of any treatment or product, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_6">The term <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laetrile</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> is derived from the terms laevorotatory and mandelonitrile and is used
to describe a purified form of the chemical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">amygdalin</GlossaryTermRef>, a 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044018" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyanogenic glucoside</GlossaryTermRef> found in the pits of
many fruits and raw nuts and in other plants, such as lima beans, clover, and
sorghum.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> In body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluids</GlossaryTermRef> and at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045837" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physiological</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000747897" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pH</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686192" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrogen cyanide</GlossaryTermRef> dissolves to form the cyanide anion. The term <Emphasis>vitamin B-17</Emphasis> was given to laetrile by E.T. Krebs Jr, but it is not an approved designation by the Committee on Nomenclature of the American Institute of Nutrition Vitamins.  In the 1970s, laetrile gained popularity as an
anticancer agent.  By 1978, more than 70,000 individuals in the United States
were reported to have been treated with it.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/>  </Para><Para id="_87">Laetrile has
been used for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> treatment both as a single agent and in combination with
a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044057" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolic therapy</GlossaryTermRef> program
that consists of a specialized diet, high-dose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin</GlossaryTermRef> supplements, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046704" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic enzymes</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_7">In the United States, researchers must file an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000762975" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Investigational New Drug</GlossaryTermRef>
(IND) application with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) to conduct
drug research in human subjects.  In 1970, an IND
application to study laetrile was filed by the McNaughton Foundation (San Ysidro,
California).  This request was initially approved but later rejected because 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">preclinical</GlossaryTermRef> evidence in animals showed that laetrile was not likely to be
effective as an anticancer agent,<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> and because there were
questions about how the proposed study was to be conducted.<Reference refidx="13"/> 
Laetrile supporters viewed this reversal as an attempt by the U.S.               government
to block access to new and promising cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef>, and pressure mounted to
make laetrile available to the public.  Court cases in Oklahoma,
Massachusetts, New Jersey, and California challenged the FDA’s role in
determining which drugs should be available to cancer patients.  Consequently,
laetrile was legalized in more than 20 states during the 1970s.  In 1980, the
U.S. Supreme Court acted to uphold a federal ban on interstate shipment of laetrile.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="14"/>  As a result, the
use of laetrile has greatly diminished, but
 the compound continues to be manufactured and administered as an anticancer therapy,
primarily in Mexico, and in some clinics in the United States. </Para><Para id="_8"> Although the names laetrile, Laetrile, vitamin B-17, and amygdalin are often used
interchangeably, they are not the same product.  The chemical composition of
U.S.-patented Laetrile (mandelonitrile-beta-glucuronide), a semisynthetic 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">derivative</GlossaryTermRef> of amygdalin, is different
from the laetrile/amygdalin produced in Mexico (mandelonitrile
beta-D-gentiobioside), which is made from crushed apricot pits.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/>  Mandelonitrile, which contains a cyanide group, is a structural component of
both products.<Reference refidx="15"/>  It has been proposed that released (hydrogen) cyanide is the
active cancer-killing ingredient in laetrile, but  two other breakdown products
of amygdalin—prunasin (which is similar in structure to Laetrile) and 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044000" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benzaldehyde</GlossaryTermRef>—may also be cancer 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> inhibitors.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/>  The studies discussed in this summary used
either Mexican laetrile/amygdalin or the patented form.  In most instances,
the generic term <Emphasis>laetrile</Emphasis> will be used in this summary; however, a distinction will be
made between the products when necessary.</Para><Para id="_9"> Laetrile can be administered <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">orally</GlossaryTermRef> as
a pill, or it can be given by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044048" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intramuscular</GlossaryTermRef>).  It is commonly given
intravenously for a period of time followed by oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.  The
incidence of cyanide poisoning is much higher when laetrile is taken orally
<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/> because <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044046" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestinal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bacteria</GlossaryTermRef> and some commonly
eaten plants contain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> 
(beta-glucosidases) that activate the release of cyanide after laetrile has
been <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ingested</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="22"/> Relatively little breakdown occurs to yield the (hydrogen) cyanide
when laetrile is injected.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="22"/>  Administration schedules
and the length of treatment in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal models</GlossaryTermRef> and humans vary
widely.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="6318190" MedlineID="84095133">Howard-Ruben J, Miller NJ: Unproven methods of cancer management. Part II: Current trends and implications for patient care. Oncol Nurs Forum 11 (1): 67-73, 1984 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Curt GA: Unsound methods of cancer treatment. Princ Pract Oncol Updates  4 (12): 1-10, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="356691" MedlineID="78255119">Dorr RT, Paxinos J: The current status of laetrile. Ann Intern Med 89 (3): 389-97, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="522706" MedlineID="80099090">Calabrese EJ: Possible adverse side effects from treatment with laetrile. Med Hypotheses 5 (9): 1045-9, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="5">The laetrile controversy. In: Moss RW: The Cancer Industry: The Classic Expose on the Cancer Establishment. First Equinox Press, 1996, pp 131-52.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Laetrile at Sloan-Kettering: a case study. In: Moss RW: The Cancer Industry: The Classic Expose on the Cancer Establishment. First Equinox Press, 1996, pp 153-86.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="6781723" MedlineID="81135321">Lerner IJ: Laetrile: a lesson in cancer quackery. CA Cancer J Clin 31 (2): 91-5, 1981 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="683212" MedlineID="78246835">Ellison NM, Byar DP, Newell GR: Special report on Laetrile: the NCI Laetrile Review. Results of the National Cancer Institute's retrospective Laetrile analysis. N Engl J Med 299 (10): 549-52, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="7033783" MedlineID="82103873">Moertel CG, Fleming TR, Rubin J, et al.: A clinical trial of amygdalin (Laetrile) in the treatment of human cancer. N Engl J Med 306 (4): 201-6, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="4042595" MedlineID="86003331">Ross WE: Unconventional cancer therapy. Compr Ther 11 (9): 37-43, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="327697" MedlineID="77217813">Lewis JP: Laetrile. West J Med 127 (1): 55-62, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="4625050" MedlineID="72219290">Unproven methods of cancer management. Laetrile. CA Cancer J Clin 22 (4): 245-50, 1972 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="371476" MedlineID="79143261">Rosen GM, Shorr RI: Laetrile: end play around the FDA. A review of legal developments. Ann Intern Med 90 (3): 418-23, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="7351911" MedlineID="80099483">Curran WJ: Law-medicine notes. Laetrile for the terminally ill: Supreme Court stops the nonsense. N Engl J Med 302 (11): 619-21, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="335509" MedlineID="78034200">Fenselau C, Pallante S, Batzinger RP, et al.: Mandelonitrile beta-glucuronide: synthesis and characterization. Science 198 (4317): 625-7, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="16">Chandler RF, Anderson LA, Phillipson JD: Laetrile in perspective. Can Pharm J  117 (11): 517-20, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="6796962" MedlineID="82082488">Newmark J, Brady RO, Grimley PM, et al.: Amygdalin (Laetrile) and prunasin beta-glucosidases: distribution in germ-free rat and in human tumor tissue. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 78 (10): 6513-6, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="7182513" MedlineID="83216226">Rauws AG, Olling M, Timmerman A: The pharmacokinetics of prunasin, a metabolite of amygdalin. J Toxicol Clin Toxicol 19 (8): 851-6, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="6929727" MedlineID="80199784">Kochi M, Takeuchi S, Mizutani T, et al.: Antitumor activity of benzaldehyde. Cancer Treat Rep 64 (1): 21-3, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="4005876" MedlineID="85228078">Kochi M, Isono N, Niwayama M, et al.: Antitumor activity of a benzaldehyde derivative. Cancer Treat Rep 69 (5): 533-7, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="21">Gostomski FE: The effects of amygdalin on the Krebs-2 carcinoma and adult and fetal DUB(ICR) mice. [Abstract] Diss Abstr Int B  39 (5): 2075-B, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="219680" MedlineID="79162525">Herbert V: Laetrile: the cult of cyanide. Promoting poison for profit. Am J Clin Nutr 32 (5): 1121-58, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="23">Viehoever A, Mack H: Bio-chemistry of amygdalin (bitter, cyanogenetic principle from bitter almonds). Am J Pharm  107 (Oct): 397-450, 1935.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>History</Title><Para id="_11"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Amygdalin</GlossaryTermRef> was first isolated in 1830 by two French chemists.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  It was used as an anticancer agent in Russia as early as 1845, and
positive results were reported for the first patient treated.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  The first recorded use of amygdalin in the United States as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> occurred in
the early 1920s.<Reference refidx="5"/>  At that time, amygdalin was taken in pill
form; however, the formulation was judged too <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxic</GlossaryTermRef>, and the work was
abandoned.  In the 1950s, a purportedly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044509" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nontoxic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> form of amygdalin
was patented as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Laetrile</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_12">Laetrile has been tested on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cultured animal cells</GlossaryTermRef>, in whole animals, in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">xenograft</GlossaryTermRef> models, and in humans to determine whether
it has specific anticancer properties.  As noted in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062976#_5" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/laetrile-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef> section, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686192" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrogen cyanide</GlossaryTermRef> is believed to be the main cancer-killing ingredient in
laetrile.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  When amygdalin interacts with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> beta-glucosidase
or undergoes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044037" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrolysis</GlossaryTermRef> in the absence of enzymes, hydrogen cyanide,
 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044000" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benzaldehyde</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef> are
produced.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/>  Hydrogen cyanide can also be produced from
prunasin, which is a less-than-complete breakdown product of
amygdalin.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_13">Proponents of laetrile have proposed four different theories to explain its purported anticancer activity.  The first of these incorporates elements of the
trophoblastic theory of cancer, a theory that is not widely accepted as an
explanation for cancer formation.  According to the trophoblastic theory, all
cancers arise from primordial <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046382" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ cells</GlossaryTermRef>, some of which become
dispersed throughout the body during 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044250" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embryonic</GlossaryTermRef> development and, therefore, are not confined to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367406" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testes</GlossaryTermRef> or
 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>  The rationale
for laetrile use is the suggestion that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> have higher than
normal levels of an  enzyme called beta-glucuronidase (which is different from
the enzyme beta-glucosidase) and that they are deficient in
another enzyme called rhodanese (thiosulfate sulfurtransferase). Another suggestion is that laetrile is modified in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, and that
beta-glucuronidase breaks down the modified compound, ultimately producing
cyanide.  Rhodanese can convert cyanide into the relatively harmless compound
thiocyanate.  Thus, it has been proposed that cancer cells are more
susceptible to the toxic effects of laetrile than normal cells because of an
imbalance in these two enzymes.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/>  Some experimental evidence does support the idea that normal 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> and malignant tissues differ substantially in their concentrations of
beta-glucuronidase <Reference refidx="21"/> and rhodanese.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/></Para><Para id="_14">The second theory states that cancer cells contain more beta-glucosidase
activity than normal cells and, as in the first theory, that they are
deficient in rhodanese.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/> Again, elevated beta-glucosidase activity in the interstitial regions of some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045771" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignancies</GlossaryTermRef> has been experimentally demonstrated.<Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_15">The third theory states that cancer is the result of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044055" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolic disorder</GlossaryTermRef> caused by a
 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">deficiency</GlossaryTermRef>.  It states further that laetrile, or <Emphasis>amygdalin/vitamin B-17</Emphasis>, is
the missing vitamin needed by the body to restore health.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/>  Experimental evidence indicates that the level of intake of
individual vitamins and/or the vitamin status of an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046250" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organism</GlossaryTermRef> can influence the development of
cancer, but there is no evidence that laetrile is needed for normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> or that it can function as a
vitamin in animals or humans.<Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/></Para><Para id="_16">The fourth theory suggests that the cyanide released by laetrile has a
toxic effect beyond its interference with oxygen utilization by cells. 
According to this theory, cyanide increases the acid content of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef> and
leads to the destruction of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044053" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lysosomes</GlossaryTermRef>.  The injured
lysosomes release their contents, thereby killing the cancer cells and
arresting tumor growth.<Reference refidx="15"/>  According to this theory, another
consequence of  lysosome disruption is stimulation of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="356691" MedlineID="78255119">Dorr RT, Paxinos J: The current status of laetrile. Ann Intern Med 89 (3): 389-97, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Viehoever A, Mack H: Bio-chemistry of amygdalin (bitter, cyanogenetic principle from bitter almonds). Am J Pharm  107 (Oct): 397-450, 1935.</Citation><Citation idx="3">The laetrile controversy. In: Moss RW: The Cancer Industry: The Classic Expose on the Cancer Establishment. First Equinox Press, 1996, pp 131-52.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Laetrile at Sloan-Kettering: a case study. In: Moss RW: The Cancer Industry: The Classic Expose on the Cancer Establishment. First Equinox Press, 1996, pp 153-86.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Curt GA: Unsound methods of cancer treatment. Princ Pract Oncol Updates  4 (12): 1-10, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="335509" MedlineID="78034200">Fenselau C, Pallante S, Batzinger RP, et al.: Mandelonitrile beta-glucuronide: synthesis and characterization. Science 198 (4317): 625-7, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Chandler RF, Anderson LA, Phillipson JD: Laetrile in perspective. Can Pharm J  117 (11): 517-20, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="6796962" MedlineID="82082488">Newmark J, Brady RO, Grimley PM, et al.: Amygdalin (Laetrile) and prunasin beta-glucosidases: distribution in germ-free rat and in human tumor tissue. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 78 (10): 6513-6, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="7182513" MedlineID="83216226">Rauws AG, Olling M, Timmerman A: The pharmacokinetics of prunasin, a metabolite of amygdalin. J Toxicol Clin Toxicol 19 (8): 851-6, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="4042595" MedlineID="86003331">Ross WE: Unconventional cancer therapy. Compr Ther 11 (9): 37-43, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="7273266" MedlineID="82002445">Ames MM, Moyer TP, Kovach JS, et al.: Pharmacology of amygdalin (laetrile) in cancer patients. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 6 (1): 51-7, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="12">Krebs ET Jr, Krebs ET Sr, Beard HH: The unitarian or trophoblastic thesis of cancer. Med Rec  163 (7): 149-74, 1950.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Ellison NM: Unproven methods of cancer therapy. Drug Ther (NY)  10(July): 73-82, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Navarro MD: The Philippine experience in the early detection and chemotherapy of cancer. St Tomas J Med  25 (3): 125-33, 1970.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="6986971" MedlineID="80132137">Greenberg DM: The case against laetrile: the fraudulent cancer remedy. Cancer 45 (4): 799-807, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="16">Levi L, French WN, Bickis IJ, et al.: Laetrile: a study of its physicochemical and biochemical properties. Can Med Assoc J  92 (20): 1057-61, 1965.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="13042670">Treatment of cancer with laetriles; a report by the Cancer Commission of the California Medical Association. Calif Med 78 (4): 320-6, 1953.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="4625050" MedlineID="72219290">Unproven methods of cancer management. Laetrile. CA Cancer J Clin 22 (4): 245-50, 1972 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="19">Navarro MD: Five years experience with laetrile therapy in advanced cancer. Acta Unio Int Contr Cancrum  15(suppl 1): 209-21, 1959.</Citation><Citation idx="20">Morrone JA: Chemotherapy of inoperable cancer: preliminary report of 10 cases treated with laetrile. Exp Med Surg  20: 299-308, 1962.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="12678908">Chen X, Wu B, Wang PG: Glucuronides in anti-cancer therapy. Curr Med Chem Anticancer Agents 3 (2): 139-50, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="14945048">GAL EM, FUNG FH, GREENBERG DM: Studies on the biological action of malononitriles. II. Distribution of rhodanese (transulfurase) in the tissues of normal and tumor-bearing animals and the effect of malononitriles thereon. Cancer Res 12 (8): 574-9, 1952.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="18616471">Sabelli R, Iorio E, De Martino A, et al.: Rhodanese-thioredoxin system and allyl sulfur compounds. FEBS J 275 (15): 3884-99, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="219680" MedlineID="79162525">Herbert V: Laetrile: the cult of cyanide. Promoting poison for profit. Am J Clin Nutr 32 (5): 1121-58, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="25">Scott PJ: Laetrile and cancer quackery problems. Cancer Forum  5 (2): 93-97, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="15658879">Cheng H, Cao X, Xian M, et al.: Synthesis and enzyme-specific activation of carbohydrate-geldanamycin conjugates with potent anticancer activity. J Med Chem 48 (2): 645-52, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="3888385">Bernacki RJ, Niedbala MJ, Korytnyk W: Glycosidases in cancer and invasion. Cancer Metastasis Rev 4 (1): 81-101, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="6781723" MedlineID="81135321">Lerner IJ: Laetrile: a lesson in cancer quackery. CA Cancer J Clin 31 (2): 91-5, 1981 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="6362828" MedlineID="84106292">Lerner IJ: The whys of cancer quackery. Cancer 53 (3 Suppl): 815-9, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="7052177" MedlineID="83000978">Shils ME, Hermann MG: Unproved dietary claims in the treatment of patients with cancer. Bull N Y Acad Med 58 (3): 323-40, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="7237379" MedlineID="81209772">Young VR, Newberne PM: Vitamins and cancer prevention: issues and dilemmas. Cancer 47 (5 Suppl): 1226-40, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="32">Jukes TH: Is laetrile a vitamin? Nutr Today  12 (5): 12-17, 1977.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_17"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><Para id="_18"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Preclinical</GlossaryTermRef> investigations of the potential anticancer activity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laetrile</GlossaryTermRef> have used numerous 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044016" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cultured cell lines</GlossaryTermRef> and 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor models</GlossaryTermRef>, and they explored the
following issues: </Para><ItemizedList id="_66" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Whether laetrile, given alone or in combination with
other substances, exhibits anticancer activity of any kind.</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxic</GlossaryTermRef> 
effects associated with laetrile treatment. </ListItem><ListItem> The location of laetrile
breakdown in the body, and how this breakdown occurs.</ListItem><ListItem>The route(s) of
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476338" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excretion</GlossaryTermRef> for laetrile and its broken-down products.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_19"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> of laetrile have used rodents,<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> dogs,<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> rabbits,<Reference refidx="13"/> and a cat.<Reference refidx="11"/>  Early work led to the
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypothesis</GlossaryTermRef> that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> were necessary to release <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686192" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrogen cyanide</GlossaryTermRef> from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">amygdalin</GlossaryTermRef>. 
When high levels of these enzymes were present, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of cyanide poisoning
were more pronounced.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_88">  In two studies sponsored by the 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef>  and published in 1975, various rodent cancers 
(<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044069" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteogenic sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>,
 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044003" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045963" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>) were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplanted</GlossaryTermRef> into rats and mice.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  In both
studies, the animals were treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046339" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraperitoneal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injections</GlossaryTermRef> of
amygdalin, with or without the enzyme beta-glucosidase.  None of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solid
tumors</GlossaryTermRef> or leukemias that were investigated responded to amygdalin at any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> that was tested. 
No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef> increase in animal survival was observed in any
of the treatment groups.  Similar results were obtained in another study using
human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> implanted into mice.<Reference refidx="10"/>  Amygdalin at every dose level tested produced no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef> either as a single agent or in
combination with beta-glucosidase.   It was discovered that animals
experienced more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> when beta-glucosidase was given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concurrently</GlossaryTermRef> with amygdalin than when amygdalin was given alone.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_20">Additional <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556412" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell culture</GlossaryTermRef> and animal studies involving more than a dozen
other tumor models have been published.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>  In
one study, preliminary findings by one of the principal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">investigators</GlossaryTermRef> that
amygdalin inhibited the growth of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumors</GlossaryTermRef> and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046145" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incidence</GlossaryTermRef> of
lung <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastases</GlossaryTermRef> in mice bearing
spontaneous (not treatment-induced) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mammary</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenocarcinomas</GlossaryTermRef> could not be
confirmed.<Reference refidx="4"/>  However, positive results were obtained in
another study.<Reference refidx="9"/> A summary of study results is provided in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062976#_72" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/laetrile-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062976#_73" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/laetrile-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef> below.</Para><Table id="_72"><Title>Table 1.  <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">In Vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> Studies<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="33.33%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.33%"/><THead><Row><entry>Reference</entry><entry>Cell Line</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Outcome</GlossaryTermRef></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">mg = milligram(s); mL = milliliter(s).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For additional information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="15"/></entry><entry>Two human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046347" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute myeloid leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> cell lines (KG-1 and HL-60)</entry><entry>A 50% inhibition of colony formation by both normal and leukemic cells was observed at an amygdalin <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentration</GlossaryTermRef> of 3.5 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mL</GlossaryTermRef> using both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef> sources; the colony-forming cells from the leukemic cell lines and normal marrow were found to be relatively resistant to amygdalin and its metabolites <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis>; there was no selective kill of clonogenic cells from the human leukemia cell lines as compared to normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="16"/></entry><entry>SNU-C4 human colon cancer cells</entry><entry>Modest (10%–30%) cytotoxicity seen with amygdalin concentrations of 0.5–5.0 mg/mL</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="17"/></entry><entry>Human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cell lines (DU145 and LNCaP)</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Dose-dependent</GlossaryTermRef> cytotoxicity in DU145 with amygdalin concentrations of 0.01–10 mg/mL and in LNCaP cells at concentrations of 0.1–10 mg/mL</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="18"/></entry><entry>HepG2 human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046661" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatoma</GlossaryTermRef> cells</entry><entry>IC50 of amygdalin alone was 458.10 mg/mL and with beta-D-glucosidase was 3.2 mg/mL</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="19"/></entry><entry>HeLa human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cells</entry><entry>Modest (10%–50%) cytotoxicity seen with amygdalin concentrations of 5–20 mg/mL</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_73"><Title>Table 2.  <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">In Vivo</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> Studies<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="33.55%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="32.89%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="33.55%"/><THead><Row><entry>Reference</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Animal Model</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Outcome</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">DMBA = dimethylbenz-alpha-anthracene; kg = <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kilogram</GlossaryTermRef>(s); mg = milligram(s).</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For additional information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="2"/></entry><entry>Four transplantable rodent tumors (L1210 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046298" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoid</GlossaryTermRef> leukemia, P388 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphocytic leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>, B16 melanoma, and Walker 256 carcinosarcoma)</entry><entry>No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antitumor</GlossaryTermRef> activity of amygdalin alone (25–3,200 mg/kg); <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330176" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">potentiation</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> of amygdalin when combined with beta glucosidase</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="3"/></entry><entry>Three transplantable rodent tumors (osteogenic sarcoma, Lewis lung carcinoma, and P388 leukemia)</entry><entry>No antitumor activity at 20% of lethal dose (LD20)</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>DMBA-induced rat mammary carcinoma and the following transplanted <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">experimental</GlossaryTermRef> tumors: sarcoma 180, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma cell</GlossaryTermRef> tumor LPC-1, leukemia L1210, Mecca <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, Ridgway osteogenic sarcoma, sarcoma T241, mammary carcinoma E0771, Taper <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> tumor, Ehrlich carcinoma (solid and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045601" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ascites</GlossaryTermRef>), and Walker carcinosarcoma 256</entry><entry>Not effective at treating, preventing, or delaying development of tumors</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="6"/></entry><entry>B16 melanoma and BW5147 AKR leukemia</entry><entry>Ineffective</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry>Murine mammary adenocarcinoma</entry><entry>No effect of amygdalin alone. Enhanced antitumor activity of combination of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin A</GlossaryTermRef>, amygdalin given intramuscularly, and enzymes injected into and around the tumor</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="10"/></entry><entry>Human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">xenografts</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Inactive</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="19"/></entry><entry>HeLa human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cell xenografts</entry><entry>Modest tumor growth inhibition in mice receiving 300 mg/kg intraperitoneally daily for 14 days</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_25">The toxicity of laetrile appears to be dependent on the route of
administration.  Oral administration is associated with much greater toxicity
than <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef>, intraperitoneal, or intramuscular injection.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/>  As noted in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062976#_10" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/laetrile-pdq">History</SummaryRef> section, most
mammalian cells contain only trace amounts of the enzyme beta-glucosidase;<Reference refidx="23"/>
however, this enzyme is present in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal tract</GlossaryTermRef> 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bacteria</GlossaryTermRef> and in many food plants.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/>  </Para><Para id="_89">Two studies
have examined the role of intestinal bacteria in the breakdown of
orally administered amygdalin.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="27"/>  In one study, rats bred and raised
under <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044032" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ-free</GlossaryTermRef> conditions and rats
bred and raised under normal conditions were given oral amygdalin.  The
germ-free rats exhibited no side effects from the compound, and their blood
concentrations of cyanide were indistinguishable from those of untreated rats. 
Many of the rats with normal quantities of intestinal bacteria
showed signs of cyanide poisoning (e.g., lethargy and convulsions), and they
had high levels of cyanide in their blood.  In the second study, rats were
either treated or not treated with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibiotic</GlossaryTermRef> neomycin before being given
oral amygdalin.<Reference refidx="5"/>  In this study, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinary</GlossaryTermRef> excretion of detoxified cyanide
(i.e., thiocyanate) was measured.  The amount of urinary thiocyanate was
40 times higher in rats that had not been given the antibiotic, indicating
that more amygdalin had been broken down in animals with normal amounts of
intestinal bacteria.  In humans, as in rats, substantial breakdown of
amygdalin occurs in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestines</GlossaryTermRef>;
however, little breakdown of amygdalin occurs in humans, with most of the intact compound eventually
excreted in urine.<Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="28"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Gostomski FE: The effects of amygdalin on the Krebs-2 carcinoma and adult and fetal DUB(ICR) mice. [Abstract] Diss Abstr Int B  39 (5): 2075-B, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1203898" MedlineID="76090254">Wodinsky I, Swiniarski JK: Antitumor activity of amygdalin MF (NSC-15780) as a single agent and with beta-glucosidase (NSC-128056) on a spectrum of transplantable rodent tumors. Cancer Chemother Rep 59 (5): 939-50, 1975 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1060511" MedlineID="76090255">Laster WR, Schabel FM: Experimental studies of the antitumor activity of amygdalin MF (NSC-15780) alone and in combination with beta-glucosidase (NSC-128056). Cancer Chemother Rep 59 (5): 951-65, 1975 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="642516" MedlineID="78154913">Stock CC, Tarnowski GS, Schmid FA, et al.: Antitumor tests of amygdalin in transplantable animal tumor systems. J Surg Oncol 10 (2): 81-8, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7222669" MedlineID="81179012">Newton GW, Schmidt ES, Lewis JP, et al.: Amygdalin toxicity studies in rats predict chronic cyanide poisoning in humans. West J Med 134 (2): 97-103, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="1268862" MedlineID="76186094">Hill GJ, Shine TE, Hill HZ, et al.: Failure of amygdalin to arrest B16 melanoma and BW5147 AKR leukemia. Cancer Res 36 (6): 2102-7, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="7362642" MedlineID="80153530">Carter JH, McLafferty MA, Goldman P: Role of the gastrointestinal microflora in amygdalin (laetrile)-induced cyanide toxicity. Biochem Pharmacol 29 (3): 301-4, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="448892" MedlineID="79196957">Khandekar JD, Edelman H: Studies of amygdalin (laetrile) toxicity in rodents. JAMA 242 (2): 169-71, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Manner HW, DiSanti SJ, Maggio MI, et al.: Amygdalin, vitamin A and enzyme induced regression of murine mammary adenocarcinomas. J Manipulative Physiol Ther  1 (4): 246-8, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="418876" MedlineID="78188776">Ovejera AA, Houchens DP, Barker AD, et al.: Inactivity of DL-amygdalin against human breast and colon tumor xenografts in athymic (nude) mice. Cancer Treat Rep 62 (4): 576-8, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="327697" MedlineID="77217813">Lewis JP: Laetrile. West J Med 127 (1): 55-62, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="203726" MedlineID="78111628">Schmidt ES, Newton GW, Sanders SM, et al.: Laetrile toxicity studies in dogs. JAMA 239 (10): 943-7, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="356691" MedlineID="78255119">Dorr RT, Paxinos J: The current status of laetrile. Ann Intern Med 89 (3): 389-97, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Levi L, French WN, Bickis IJ, et al.: Laetrile: a study of its physicochemical and biochemical properties. Can Med Assoc J  92 (20): 1057-61, 1965.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="6929726" MedlineID="80199762">Koeffler HP, Lowe L, Golde DW: Amygdalin (Laetrile): effect on clonogenic cells from human myeloid leukemia cell lines and normal human marrow. Cancer Treat Rep 64 (1): 105-9, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="16127745">Park HJ, Yoon SH, Han LS, et al.: Amygdalin inhibits genes related to cell cycle in SNU-C4 human colon cancer cells. World J Gastroenterol 11 (33): 5156-61, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="16880611">Chang HK, Shin MS, Yang HY, et al.: Amygdalin induces apoptosis through regulation of Bax and Bcl-2 expressions in human DU145 and LNCaP prostate cancer cells. Biol Pharm Bull 29 (8): 1597-602, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="24751072">Zhou C, Qian L, Ma H, et al.: Enhancement of amygdalin activated with β-D-glucosidase on HepG2 cells proliferation and apoptosis. Carbohydr Polym 90 (1): 516-23, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="23137229">Chen Y, Ma J, Wang F, et al.: Amygdalin induces apoptosis in human cervical cancer cell line HeLa cells. Immunopharmacol Immunotoxicol 35 (1): 43-51, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="7005480" MedlineID="81096871">Moertel CG, Ames MM, Kovach JS, et al.: A pharmacologic and toxicological study of amygdalin. JAMA 245 (6): 591-4, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="6796962" MedlineID="82082488">Newmark J, Brady RO, Grimley PM, et al.: Amygdalin (Laetrile) and prunasin beta-glucosidases: distribution in germ-free rat and in human tumor tissue. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 78 (10): 6513-6, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="22">Navarro MD: Five years experience with laetrile therapy in advanced cancer. Acta Unio Int Contr Cancrum  15(suppl 1): 209-21, 1959.</Citation><Citation idx="23">Conchie J, Findlay J, Levvy GA: Mammalian glycosidases: distribution in the body. Biochem J  71 (2): 318-25, 1959.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="219680" MedlineID="79162525">Herbert V: Laetrile: the cult of cyanide. Promoting poison for profit. Am J Clin Nutr 32 (5): 1121-58, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="7273266" MedlineID="82002445">Ames MM, Moyer TP, Kovach JS, et al.: Pharmacology of amygdalin (laetrile) in cancer patients. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 6 (1): 51-7, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="4625050" MedlineID="72219290">Unproven methods of cancer management. Laetrile. CA Cancer J Clin 22 (4): 245-50, 1972 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="7052177" MedlineID="83000978">Shils ME, Hermann MG: Unproved dietary claims in the treatment of patients with cancer. Bull N Y Acad Med 58 (3): 323-40, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="725316" MedlineID="79075985">Ames MM, Kovach JS, Flora KP: Initial pharmacologic studies of amygdalin (laetrile) in man. Res Commun Chem Pathol Pharmacol 22 (1): 175-85, 1978.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Human/Clinical Studies</Title><Para id="_27"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Laetrile</GlossaryTermRef> has been used as an anticancer treatment in humans
worldwide.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Although many <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043995" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anecdotal reports</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case reports</GlossaryTermRef> are available, findings
from only two <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> have been published.  No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> of laetrile has ever been conducted.</Para><Para id="_28">Case reports and reports of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044006" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case series</GlossaryTermRef> have provided little
evidence to support laetrile as an anticancer
treatment.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/>  The absence of a uniform
documentation of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>, the
use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conventional therapies</GlossaryTermRef> in combination with laetrile, and variations in
the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> and duration of laetrile <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> complicate evaluation of the data. 
In a case series published in 1962,<Reference refidx="6"/> findings from ten patients with
various types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> cancer
were reported.  These patients had been treated with a wide range of doses of
 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) Laetrile (total dose range, 9–133 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">g</GlossaryTermRef>).  Pain relief (reduction or elimination) was the primary benefit reported.  Some 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044067" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">objective responses</GlossaryTermRef>, such as decreased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenopathy</GlossaryTermRef> and decreased tumor size,
were noted.  Information on prior or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concurrent therapy</GlossaryTermRef> was provided;
however, patients were not followed up long-term to determine whether the
benefits continued after treatment was stopped.  Another case series that was
published in 1953 included 44 cancer patients and found no evidence of
objective response that could be attributed to laetrile.<Reference refidx="9"/>  Most patients
with reported cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046039" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regression</GlossaryTermRef> in
this series received recent or concurrent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.  Thus, it is impossible
to determine which treatment produced the positive results.</Para><Para id="_29"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044000" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Benzaldehyde</GlossaryTermRef>, which is one of laetrile’s breakdown products, has also been
tested for anticancer activity in humans.  Two <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical series</GlossaryTermRef> reported a number
of responses to benzaldehyde in patients with advanced cancer for whom
 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard therapy</GlossaryTermRef> had failed.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> In one series, 19 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045652" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complete responses</GlossaryTermRef> and ten <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045819" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">partial responses</GlossaryTermRef> were reported
among 57 patients who had received either <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044083" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectal</GlossaryTermRef> beta-cyclodextrin benzaldehyde;
however, precise response durations were specified for only two of the
patients.<Reference refidx="10"/>  Another series by the same <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">investigators</GlossaryTermRef> used
4,6-benzylidene-alpha-D-glucose, which is an IV formulation of
benzaldehyde.<Reference refidx="11"/>  In this series, seven complete responses and 29 partial
responses were reported among 65 patients, with response durations ranging
from 1.5 to 27 months.  No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> was associated with either preparation of
benzaldehyde, and it was reported that the responses persisted as long as
treatment was continued.  Almost all of the patients in these two series had
been treated previously with chemotherapy or radiation therapy, but the
elapsed time before the initiation of benzaldehyde treatment was not
disclosed.</Para><Para id="_30">In 1978, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> (NCI) requested case reports from practitioners who believed
that their patients had benefitted from laetrile treatment.<Reference refidx="12"/>  Ninety-three cases
were submitted, and 67 were considered evaluable for response.  An expert
panel concluded that two of the 67 patients had complete responses and that
four of the others had partial responses while using laetrile.<Reference refidx="13"/>  On the basis of
these six responses, the NCI agreed to sponsor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045831" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase II clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_31">The phase I study was designed to test the doses, routes of administration,
and the schedule of administration judged representative of those used by
laetrile practitioners.<Reference refidx="3"/>  The study involved six cancer patients.  The
investigators found that IV and oral amygdalin showed minimal
toxicity under the conditions evaluated; however, two patients who ate raw
almonds while undergoing oral treatment developed symptoms of cyanide
poisoning.</Para><Para id="_32">The phase II study was conducted in 1982 and was designed to test the types
of cancer that might benefit from laetrile treatment.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Most
patients had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.  To be eligible for the trial,
patients had to be in good general condition (not totally disabled or near
death), and they must not have received any other cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for at least
1 month before treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">amygdalin</GlossaryTermRef>.  Amygdalin, evaluated for potency
and purity by the NCI,<Reference refidx="14"/> was administered by IV for 21 days,
followed by oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045768" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maintenance therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, utilizing doses and procedures similar
to those evaluated in the phase I study.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamins</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046704" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> were
also administered as part of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044057" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolic therapy</GlossaryTermRef> program that included dietary
changes to restrict the use of caffeine, sugar, meats, dairy products, eggs,
and alcohol.  A small subset of patients received higher-dose amygdalin
therapy and higher doses of some vitamins as part of the trial. 
Patients were followed up until there was definite evidence of cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression</GlossaryTermRef>, elevated blood cyanide
levels, or severe clinical deterioration.  Among 175 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044029" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">evaluable patients</GlossaryTermRef>, only one patient met the criteria for response.  This patient, who had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046770" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastric</GlossaryTermRef> carcinoma with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044102" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> metastasis,
experienced a partial response that was maintained for 10 weeks while on
amygdalin therapy.  Fifty-four percent of the patients had measurable disease
progression at the end of the IV course of treatment, and all
of the patients had disease progression 7 months after completing  IV therapy. 
Seven percent of the patients reported an improvement in performance status
(ability to work or to perform routine daily activities) at some time during
therapy, and 20 percent claimed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptomatic</GlossaryTermRef> relief.  In most patients,
these benefits did not persist.  Blood cyanide levels were not elevated after
IV amygdalin treatment; however, they were elevated after oral
therapy.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_34">Variations in commercial preparations of laetrile from Mexico, the primary
supplier, have been documented.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>  Incorrect product labels have been
found, and samples contaminated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bacteria</GlossaryTermRef> and other substances have been
identified.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/>  When a comparison was made of products manufactured in the
United States and Canada, differences in chemical composition were noted, and
neither product was effective in killing cultured human cancer cells.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Table id="_83"><Title>Table 3.  Clinical Studies of Laetrile/Amygdalin<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="7"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="14.01%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="14.01%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="14.27%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="14.35%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="20.08%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="8.54%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="7" ColWidth="14.70%"/><THead><Row><entry>Reference </entry><entry>Trial Design</entry><entry>Condition or Cancer Type</entry><entry>Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Placebo</GlossaryTermRef> or No Treatment Control)<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Results</entry><entry>Concurrent Therapy Used</entry><entry>Level of Evidence<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1">N/A = not applicable.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For additional information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Number of patients treated plus number of patient controls may not equal number of patients enrolled; number of patients enrolled equals number of patients initially recruited/considered by the researchers who conducted a study; number of patients treated equals number of enrolled patients who were given the treatment being studied AND for whom results were reported.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Strongest evidence reported that the treatment under study has activity or otherwise improves the well-being of cancer patients. For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of evidence</GlossaryTermRef> analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="2"/></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Consecutive case series</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Various cancers</entry><entry>179; 178; N/A</entry><entry>No benefit reported</entry><entry>Metabolic therapy program of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef>, vitamins, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>3iiDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044575" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nonconsecutive case series</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Various diseases</entry><entry>68; 68; 24</entry><entry>Two patients had complete response; four patients had partial response</entry><entry>Chemotherapy</entry><entry>3iiiDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="3"/></entry><entry>Nonconsecutive case series</entry><entry>Advanced cancer</entry><entry>6; 6; N/A</entry><entry>No benefit reported</entry><entry>Vitamins, enzymes</entry><entry>3iiiDiii</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="6"/></entry><entry>Best case series</entry><entry>Various advanced cancers</entry><entry>9; 9; N/A</entry><entry>Pain relief</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>4</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="7"/></entry><entry>Best case series</entry><entry>Various cancers</entry><entry>10; 10; N/A</entry><entry>Pain relief</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Narcotics</GlossaryTermRef> given to seven patients, but discontinued in five patients</entry><entry>4</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry>Best case series</entry><entry>Various cancers</entry><entry>N/A; 44; N/A</entry><entry>No benefit reported</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry>4</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="327697" MedlineID="77217813">Lewis JP: Laetrile. West J Med 127 (1): 55-62, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="7033783" MedlineID="82103873">Moertel CG, Fleming TR, Rubin J, et al.: A clinical trial of amygdalin (Laetrile) in the treatment of human cancer. N Engl J Med 306 (4): 201-6, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="7005480" MedlineID="81096871">Moertel CG, Ames MM, Kovach JS, et al.: A pharmacologic and toxicological study of amygdalin. JAMA 245 (6): 591-4, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Navarro MD: The Philippine experience in the early detection and chemotherapy of cancer. St Tomas J Med  25 (3): 125-33, 1970.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="4042595" MedlineID="86003331">Ross WE: Unconventional cancer therapy. Compr Ther 11 (9): 37-43, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Navarro MD: Five years experience with laetrile therapy in advanced cancer. Acta Unio Int Contr Cancrum  15(suppl 1): 209-21, 1959.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Morrone JA: Chemotherapy of inoperable cancer: preliminary report of 10 cases treated with laetrile. Exp Med Surg  20: 299-308, 1962.</Citation><Citation idx="8">Brown WE, Wood CD, Smith AN: Sodium cyanide as a cancer chemotherapeutic agent: laboratory and clinical studies. Am J Obstet Gynecol  80 (5): 907-18, 1960.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="13042670">Treatment of cancer with laetriles; a report by the Cancer Commission of the California Medical Association. Calif Med 78 (4): 320-6, 1953.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="6929727" MedlineID="80199784">Kochi M, Takeuchi S, Mizutani T, et al.: Antitumor activity of benzaldehyde. Cancer Treat Rep 64 (1): 21-3, 1980.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="4005876" MedlineID="85228078">Kochi M, Isono N, Niwayama M, et al.: Antitumor activity of a benzaldehyde derivative. Cancer Treat Rep 69 (5): 533-7, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="6996807" MedlineID="81001599">Newell GR, Ellison NM: Ethics and designs: laetrile trials as an example. Cancer Treat Rep 64 (2-3): 363-5, 1980 Feb-Mar.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="683212" MedlineID="78246835">Ellison NM, Byar DP, Newell GR: Special report on Laetrile: the NCI Laetrile Review. Results of the National Cancer Institute's retrospective Laetrile analysis. N Engl J Med 299 (10): 549-52, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="627001" MedlineID="78105252">Davignon JP, Trissel LA, Kleinman LM: Pharmaceutical assessment of amygdalin (Laetrile) products. Cancer Treat Rep 62 (1): 99-104, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="917101" MedlineID="78031174">Davignon JP: Contaminated laetrile: a health hazard. N Engl J Med 297 (24): 1355-6, 1977.</Citation><Citation idx="16">Levi L, French WN, Bickis IJ, et al.: Laetrile: a study of its physicochemical and biochemical properties. Can Med Assoc J  92 (20): 1057-61, 1965.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Adverse Effects</Title><Para id="_36">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> associated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laetrile</GlossaryTermRef> treatment mirror the symptoms of
cyanide poisoning.  Cyanide is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurotoxin</GlossaryTermRef> that can cause the following side effects: </Para><ItemizedList id="_90" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and
 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem>Headache.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem>Dizziness.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cyanosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Liver</GlossaryTermRef> damage.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044039" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hypotension</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ptosis</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043999" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ataxic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046041" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuropathies</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem><ListItem>Fever.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem>     Mental confusion.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem><ListItem>Coma.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem><ListItem>Death.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_91">   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Oral</GlossaryTermRef> laetrile causes more severe side effects
than <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> laetrile.  These side effects can be potentiated by
the concurrent administration of raw almonds or crushed fruit pits, and by eating
fruits or vegetables that contain beta-glucosidase (e.g., celery, peaches,
bean sprouts, carrots),<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/> or by taking high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of
 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin</GlossaryTermRef> C orally.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="6318190" MedlineID="84095133">Howard-Ruben J, Miller NJ: Unproven methods of cancer management. Part II: Current trends and implications for patient care. Oncol Nurs Forum 11 (1): 67-73, 1984 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="7033783" MedlineID="82103873">Moertel CG, Fleming TR, Rubin J, et al.: A clinical trial of amygdalin (Laetrile) in the treatment of human cancer. N Engl J Med 306 (4): 201-6, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Chandler RF, Anderson LA, Phillipson JD: Laetrile in perspective. Can Pharm J  117 (11): 517-20, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="3003927" MedlineID="86123070">Leor R, Michaeli J, Brezis M, et al.: Laetrile intoxication and hepatic necrosis: a possible association. South Med J 79 (2): 259-60, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="6982404" MedlineID="83036677">Lee M, Berger HW, Givre HL, et al.: Near fatal laetrile intoxication: complete recovery with supportive treatment. Mt Sinai J Med 49 (4): 305-7, 1982 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Navarro MD: Five years experience with laetrile therapy in advanced cancer. Acta Unio Int Contr Cancrum  15(suppl 1): 209-21, 1959.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="356691" MedlineID="78255119">Dorr RT, Paxinos J: The current status of laetrile. Ann Intern Med 89 (3): 389-97, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="203395" MedlineID="78105239">Smith FP, Butler TP, Cohan S, et al.: Laetrile toxicity: a report of two patients. Cancer Treat Rep 62 (1): 169-71, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="7074524" MedlineID="82184046">Vizel M, Oster MW: Ocular side effects of cancer chemotherapy. Cancer 49 (10): 1999-2002, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="6301673" MedlineID="83180244">Kalyanaraman UP, Kalyanaraman K, Cullinan SA, et al.: Neuromyopathy of cyanide intoxication due to "laetrile" (amygdalin). A clinicopathologic study. Cancer 51 (11): 2126-33, 1983.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="7273266" MedlineID="82002445">Ames MM, Moyer TP, Kovach JS, et al.: Pharmacology of amygdalin (laetrile) in cancer patients. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 6 (1): 51-7, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="7005480" MedlineID="81096871">Moertel CG, Ames MM, Kovach JS, et al.: A pharmacologic and toxicological study of amygdalin. JAMA 245 (6): 591-4, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16175068">O'Brien B, Quigg C, Leong T: Severe cyanide toxicity from 'vitamin supplements'. Eur J Emerg Med 12 (5): 257-8, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Gostomski FE: The effects of amygdalin on the Krebs-2 carcinoma and adult and fetal DUB(ICR) mice. [Abstract] Diss Abstr Int B  39 (5): 2075-B, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="203726" MedlineID="78111628">Schmidt ES, Newton GW, Sanders SM, et al.: Laetrile toxicity studies in dogs. JAMA 239 (10): 943-7, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="219680" MedlineID="79162525">Herbert V: Laetrile: the cult of cyanide. Promoting poison for profit. Am J Clin Nutr 32 (5): 1121-58, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="522711" MedlineID="80099097">Calabrese EJ: Conjoint use of laetrile and megadoses of ascorbic acid in cancer treatment: possible side effects. Med Hypotheses 5 (9): 995-7, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="16014371">Bromley J, Hughes BG, Leong DC, et al.: Life-threatening interaction between complementary medicines: cyanide toxicity following ingestion of amygdalin and vitamin C. Ann Pharmacother 39 (9): 1566-9, 2005.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_37"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Laetrile/Amygdalin</Title><Para id="_38">To assist readers in evaluating the results of human studies of integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of
evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever
possible.  To qualify for a level of evidence analysis, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_50" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Be published in a peer-reviewed scientific journal.</ListItem><ListItem>Report on a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> outcome or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Describe clinical findings in sufficient detail that a meaningful evaluation can be made.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_51">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and scientific strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score. For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis for cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_44"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (06/14/2022)</Title><Para id="_45">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_86">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062976#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/laetrile-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of laetrile/amygdalin in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Laetrile/Amygdalin. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/laetrile-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/laetrile-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389425]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateLastModified>2022-06-14</DateLastModified></Summary>
