<Summary id="CDR0000630144" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Good communication in cancer care between patients, families, caregivers and doctors is important. Talk to your doctor about your cancer diagnosis, goals of treatment, plan of care, and what to expect over time. Learn how good communication between the healthcare team, cancer patients, and family can improve the patient's quality of life in this expert-reviewed summary.
</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/adjusting-to-cancer/communication-pdq">Communication in Cancer Care (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/adjusting-to-cancer/communication-hp-pdq">Communication in Cancer Care (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000640418">communication intervention</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_170">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about communicating with the cancer patient and his or her family. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_171">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>communication intervention</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Communication in Cancer Care (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Communication in Cancer Care</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Communication in Cancer Care</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_2"><KeyPoint id="_3">Good communication between people with cancer, their family,  and the health care team is important in cancer care.</KeyPoint><Para id="_4">Good communication with your family and the health care team has a positive effect on your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> journey. </Para><Para id="_125">The goals of good communication in cancer care are to:</Para><ItemizedList id="_126" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Build a trusting relationship with your health care team.</ListItem><ListItem>	Learn from your health care team about your cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Discuss your options for treatment and care throughout your cancer journey.</ListItem><ListItem>Improve your well-being and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_186">You will face many decisions when you are diagnosed with cancer. Tell your health care team about concerns you have during treatment, and if you have problems <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coping</GlossaryTermRef> with the cancer diagnosis.</Para><Para id="_187">Studies show that there are many positive results  when people with cancer and their doctors communicate well during cancer care. Positive results include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_188" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>More likely to be content with care.</ListItem><ListItem>More likely to follow through with treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Better quality of life.</ListItem><ListItem>Reduced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>More likely to take part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Improved knowledge of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000811791" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disease</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Preferred care is received at end of life.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_189">Ask for help from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000791361" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">patient navigator</GlossaryTermRef>. A patient navigator can guide you through the health care system and help you communicate with your health care team, so you get the information you need to make decisions about your care. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><KeyPoint id="_10">Families may experience communication challenges.</KeyPoint><Para id="_128">You will go through different emotions when you have cancer. You may want to hide feelings of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef> and sadness and act normal  to protect your family and friends. This is also often true for friends and family. Talking about cancer-related issues may help reduce <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef> for you  and your family. Family-focused <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450116" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> may also benefit you and your family.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Factors in Communication</Title><SummarySection id="_131"><KeyPoint id="_132">Tell your health care team how you want to receive information about your cancer and treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_133">You may want written instructions and  phone calls, or you may prefer texts and emails. Let your health care team know how you want to receive your information about your cancer and cancer treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_190"><KeyPoint id="_191">There are ways to improve communication with your doctors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_192">It may be hard to remember what your doctor said and what you want to ask at each appointment. Make a list of the questions you want to ask before your visit. The following suggestions may help you remember what was said:</Para><ItemizedList id="_193" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Have a family member go with you when you meet with your doctor.</ListItem><ListItem>Ask for a copy of the information so you can read it after your visit.</ListItem><ListItem>Record the discussion.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_194">Ask if your doctor or clinic offers any of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_195" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>A packet that includes items such as a question idea sheet, booklets on decision-making and patient rights, and information about the clinic.</ListItem><ListItem>A psychologist you can talk to about how you are feeling.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_152"><KeyPoint id="_153">Culture can also affect communication.</KeyPoint><Para id="_154">Some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476357" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cultures</GlossaryTermRef> place a greater emphasis on communication with the family as a whole unit, while other cultures focus more on the patient's ability to make their own decisions. Tell your health care team how much information you want to receive.</Para><Para id="_163">Your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000489395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">religious</GlossaryTermRef> beliefs may be a source of strength and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coping</GlossaryTermRef> for you. Tell your health care team about any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spiritual</GlossaryTermRef> and religious needs and concerns you want them to know about. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000301599" url="/about-cancer/coping/day-to-day/faith-and-spirituality/spirituality-pdq">Spirituality in Cancer Care</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Communication in Pediatric Cancer Care</Title><SummarySection id="_177"><KeyPoint id="_178">Many parents want to know their child's prognosis.</KeyPoint><Para id="_179">When your child has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, you will likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or course of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000811791" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disease</GlossaryTermRef> is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef>. Ask your child's cancer care team about your child's prognosis. Knowing this information can help you and your loved ones make decisions. No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><KeyPoint id="_137">Children with cancer want to know about their illness and how it will be treated.</KeyPoint><Para id="_138">The amount of information a child may want to know  depends in part on their age. Most children worry about how their illness and treatment will affect their daily lives and the people around them. Studies also show that children have less doubt and fear when they are given information they can understand about their illness, even if it is bad news.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_139"><KeyPoint id="_140">Children may wish to know what is going on when someone they love has cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_141">When a parent has cancer, the child may have high levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>. Children may also experience <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and distress when they see a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000616710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sibling</GlossaryTermRef> going through cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> or dying. Children do better when family members or the health care team talk with them about what to expect and answer their questions. For ways to help teens <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454700" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cope</GlossaryTermRef> and communicate when a loved one has cancer, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/teens">Support for Teens When a Family Member Has Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_181"><Title>Electronic Communication in Cancer Care</Title><SummarySection id="_182"><KeyPoint id="_183">Your health care team may reach out to you using electronic methods.</KeyPoint><Para id="_184">A method to get health information that is used frequently in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef> is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000812871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">eHealth</GlossaryTermRef>. eHealth refers to the use of digital technology, such as home computers, smart phones, and the Internet to  find and send health  information. eHealth helps:</Para><ItemizedList id="_185" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Send information between patients, family members, and the health care team.</ListItem><ListItem>Improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000799190" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">shared decision making</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Improve how patients explain their concerns to the health care team.</ListItem><ListItem>Give <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440116" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social support</GlossaryTermRef> to patients.</ListItem><ListItem>Provide <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> information.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_196"><Title>Communication at End of Life</Title><SummarySection id="_197"><KeyPoint id="_198">Early communication about end-of-life decisions is important.</KeyPoint><Para id="_199">When you learn you have terminal cancer, you're faced with decisions that will affect your end-of-life care. Talk about these decisions early to make it easier on you and your family later. The following are some questions to consider:</Para><ItemizedList id="_200" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>What's important to me at the end of life?</ListItem><ListItem>Is it most important that I be as comfortable and alert as possible during the last stages of cancer?</ListItem><ListItem>Is it most important to continue with treatments that may help me live longer but are painful?</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_201">When you and your family decide it is time to move from active treatment to end-of-life care, your goals and desires are important. It may be difficult to start the discussion about end-of-life care with your doctor, but it is important to make these decisions early in your cancer journey.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_202"><KeyPoint id="_203">Early conversations with your doctors can help you feel prepared for end-of-life decisions.</KeyPoint><Para id="_204">Many people with terminal cancer who start talking with their doctors early about end-of-life issues report feeling better prepared. Early communication with your doctors may make it easier to deal with concerns about being older, living alone, symptom control, spiritual well-being, and how your family will cope in the future.</Para><Para id="_205">	Ask your doctor or clinic about an end-of-life consultation, which includes a list of questions that can help you explain your wishes for the end of life.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_206"><KeyPoint id="_207">Talk with your doctor about your prognosis and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_208">It is important to understand your prognosis when you make decisions about your care and treatment if you have terminal cancer. You may want to know how long you have to live. It can be different for each person and depends on the type of cancer, where it has spread, and whether you have other illnesses. Some people want more information on their prognosis than others.</Para><Para id="_209">Your doctor can talk about treatment options with you and your family and explain the effects they may have on your cancer and your quality of life. Make sure you understand your options and ask questions if you need more information. People who discuss end-of-life choices with their doctors are more likely to receive the care they want.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><Title>Learn More About Communicating When a Family Member Has Cancer </Title><Para id="_147">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about communication in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> care, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_148" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/when-someone-you-love-is-being-treated">When Someone You Love is Being Treated for Cancer: Support for Caregivers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide For Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/advanced-cancer/caregivers">Advanced Cancer and Caregivers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/when-your-parent-has-cancer">When Your Parent Has Cancer: A Guide for Teens</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/sibling-has-cancer">When Your Brother or Sister Has Cancer: A Guide for Teens</ExternalRef>   </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_169"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_169_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about communicating with the cancer patient and his or her family.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Communication in Cancer Care. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/adjusting-to-cancer/communication-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/adjusting-to-cancer/communication-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389345]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000618162"/><DateFirstPublished>2009-05-08</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-04-07</DateLastModified></Summary>
