<Summary id="CDR0000639481" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) treatment depends on the extent of disease and may involve surgery and/or tyrosine kinase inhibitors. Get detailed information about the diagnosis, prognosis, and treatment of newly diagnosed and recurrent GISTs in this summary for clinicians. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/patient/gist-treatment-pdq">Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_205">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of gastrointestinal stromal tumors. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_206">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors (GISTs)</Title><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_6">GISTs comprise less than 1% of all gastrointestinal (GI) tumors but are the most common mesenchymal tumors of the GI tract.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> There are  estimated to be over 6,000 new GIST cases per year in the United States, with an age-adjusted yearly incidence of 6.78 per million from 2001 to 2011. GISTs can affect patients of all ages but are most predominant in older adults (median age, 65–69 years).<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Globally, GISTs affect men and women with equal frequency. Geographically, GISTs are most prevalent in China (Shanghai), Taiwan, Korea, and Norway.<Reference refidx="5"/> In the United States, GISTs are more commonly diagnosed in Black Americans (13.7 per million) and Asian or Pacific Islander Americans (11 per million) than in White Americans (6.5 per million).<Reference refidx="4"/>   </Para><Para id="_312">The true incidence is not known, in part, because small indolent GISTs (i.e., &lt;1 cm) are either not clinically apparent or are not included in cancer registries.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_241">Most GISTs are sporadic, but there are rare familial forms associated with neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) or heritable variants in <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> and <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> GISTs rarely affect children and young adults (&lt;1% of cases), with a median age of 15 years. Those cases are nearly always associated with an underlying genetic predisposition.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799719" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/child-gist-treatment-pdq">Childhood Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_136">GISTs can occur anywhere along the GI tract, but most often are found in the stomach or small intestine.  The American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) Cancer Staging Manual lists the following approximate distributions:<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_9" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Stomach (60%).</ListItem><ListItem>Small intestine, jejunum, and ileum (30%).</ListItem><ListItem>Duodenum (5%).</ListItem><ListItem>Rectum (3%).</ListItem><ListItem>Colon (1%).</ListItem><ListItem>Esophagus (&lt;1%).</ListItem><ListItem>Disseminated tumors without a known primary (rare).</ListItem><ListItem>Omentum/mesentery (rare). </ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000703376" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of the gastrointestinal tract showing the esophagus, stomach, colon, small intestine, and rectum. An inset shows the greater omentum (part of the tissue that surrounds the stomach and other organs in the abdomen)." language="en" placement="image-center-medium" id="_188"><Caption language="en">Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) may be found anywhere in or near the gastrointestinal tract.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_242">GISTs range in size from less than 1 cm to more than 40 cm, with an average size of approximately 5 cm when diagnosed clinically. They typically arise within the muscle wall of the GI tract.<Reference refidx="11"/> Small GISTs may form solid subserosal, intramural, or, less frequently, polypoid intraluminal masses. Large tumors tend to form external masses attached to the outer aspect of the bowel wall involving the muscular layers.<Reference refidx="11"/> </Para><Para id="_11">The clinical presentation of patients with GISTs varies depending on the following:<Reference refidx="12"/> <Reference refidx="13"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_243" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Anatomical location.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor size.</ListItem><ListItem>Rate of tumor growth.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_244">The signs and symptoms of GISTs include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_245" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>GI bleeding (most common presentation), which may be acute (melena or hematemesis) or chronic, resulting in anemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Acute tumor rupture.</ListItem><ListItem>GI obstruction.</ListItem><ListItem>Pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Dysphagia.</ListItem><ListItem>Early satiety.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_116">Smaller lesions may be found incidentally during surgery, radiological studies, or endoscopy. The natural history of these incidental tumors and the frequency of progression to symptomatic disease are unknown. There may be a substantial reservoir of small GISTs that do not progress to symptomatic stages.    </Para><Para id="_12">Common sites of metastasis include the liver and peritoneal dissemination within the abdominal cavity. In adults, lymph node involvement and spread to the lungs or other extra-abdominal sites is unusual.<Reference refidx="14"/> </Para><Para id="_313">Rare paraneoplastic consumptive hypothyroidism (from overexpression of a thyroid-inactivating enzyme) has been reported in a few patients.<Reference refidx="15"/> </Para><Para id="_314">Pediatric GISTs are typically associated with germline <GeneName>SDH</GeneName> loss. The clinical behavior is distinct with typically a gastric location, more indolent course, multifocal presentation, and lymph node metastases. Germline <GeneName>SDH</GeneName> loss is also associated with hereditary kidney cancer, paragangliomas, and other tumors.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_246"><Title>Diagnostic Evaluation</Title><Para id="_13">GISTs should be included in the differential diagnosis of any intra-abdominal nonepithelial malignancy. Standard diagnostic interventions may include:<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_247" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Computed tomography (CT).</ListItem><ListItem>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).</ListItem><ListItem>Positron emission tomography (PET).</ListItem><ListItem>Endoscopy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_120">Endoscopic ultrasound with fine-needle aspiration (FNA) biopsy is useful in the diagnosis of GISTs in the upper GI tract, as most tumors arise below the mucosal layer and grow in an endophytic fashion. Endoscopic ultrasound–guided FNA biopsy is preferred to percutaneous biopsy, given the risk of tumor hemorrhage and peritoneal dissemination.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/> For localized resectable GISTs with classic imaging findings, some surgeons proceed directly to surgery without biopsy.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><Title>Prognosis</Title><Para id="_248">Prognostic factors for nonmetastatic GISTs include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_249" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Mitotic index.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor size. </ListItem><ListItem>	Tumor location (gastric, nongastric, rectal).</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor rupture.</ListItem><ListItem>	Imaging characteristics.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_23">Approximately 20% to 25% of gastric GISTs and 40% to 50% of small intestinal GISTs are clinically  aggressive.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="20"/> It is estimated that approximately 10% to 25% of patients present with metastatic disease.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="20"/> For nonmetastatic GISTs, the key parameters that impact the risk of recurrence or metastasis include mitotic index (mitoses per 50 high-power fields), tumor size, and tumor location (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_456" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/> </Para><Para id="_224">It is also recognized that tumor rupture markedly worsens recurrence-free survival.<Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/> In addition, tumor appearance on CT imaging may predict recurrence risk. Tumors with higher metastatic risk include lobulated or heterogeneously enhancing tumors, as well as those with mesenteric fat infiltration, ulceration, regional lymphadenopathy, or exophytic growth.<Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/>  </Para><Table id="_456"><Title>Table 1.  Risk Assessment of Gastric GISTs by Tumor Size and Mitotic Index<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Mitotic Index (mitoses/HPF)</entry><entry>Size (cm)</entry><entry>Metastasis Rate (%)</entry><entry>Risk of Progressive Disease</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">GISTs = gastrointestinal stromal tumors; HPF = high-power field.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Miettinen et al.<Reference refidx="25"/> and Laurini et al.<Reference refidx="33"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="3">≤5 per 50 </entry><entry>≤2</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;2 to ≤5 </entry><entry>1.9</entry><entry>Very low</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;5 to ≤10 </entry><entry>3.6</entry><entry>Low</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;10</entry><entry>12</entry><entry>Moderate</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">&gt;5 per 50 </entry><entry>≤2</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;2 to ≤5 </entry><entry>16</entry><entry>Moderate</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;5 to ≤10 </entry><entry>55</entry><entry>High</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;10</entry><entry>86</entry><entry>High</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_455"><Title>Table 2.  Risk Assessment of Nongastric GISTs by Tumor Size and Mitotic Index<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Mitotic Index (mitoses/HPF)</entry><entry>Size (cm)</entry><entry>Metastasis Rate (%)</entry><entry>Risk of Progressive Disease</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">GISTs = gastrointestinal stromal tumors; HPF = high-power field.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Adapted from Miettinen et al.<Reference refidx="25"/> and Laurini et al.<Reference refidx="33"/></entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry MoreRows="3">≤5 per 50 </entry><entry>≤2  </entry><entry>0</entry><entry>None</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;2 to ≤5 </entry><entry>1.9–8.5</entry><entry>Low</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;5 to ≤10 </entry><entry>24</entry><entry>Insufficient data–Moderate</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;10</entry><entry>34–52</entry><entry>High</entry></Row><Row><entry MoreRows="3">&gt;5 per 50 </entry><entry>≤2</entry><entry>50–54</entry><entry>Insufficient data–High</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;2 to ≤5 </entry><entry>50–73</entry><entry>High</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;5 to ≤10 </entry><entry>85</entry><entry>High</entry></Row><Row><entry>&gt;10</entry><entry>71–90</entry><entry>High</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_84"><Title>Follow-Up</Title><SummarySection id="_253"><Title>Response to therapy</Title><Para id="_254">CT, fluorine F 18-fludeoxyglucose (18F-FDG) PET, and MRI are used to monitor the effects of systemic therapy in patients with unresectable, metastatic, or recurrent disease.<Reference refidx="34"/> </Para><Para id="_86">A baseline PET should be performed before tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy in patients who will be monitored for response with 18F-FDG PET. PET imaging may detect the activity of imatinib in GISTs much earlier than CT imaging, with decreased tumor avidity detected as soon as 24 hours after the first dose. Thus, PET may be a useful diagnostic modality for the very early assessment of response to imatinib therapy and for detecting resistance to TKIs.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_255"><Title>Surveillance for metastatic or recurrent disease</Title><Para id="_85">The optimal modality  and frequency for surveillance of metastatic or recurrent disease in patients who have undergone GIST resection has not been studied.  Based on the likelihood of recurrence, follow-up recommendations are derived from expert opinion and clinical judgment.  </Para><Para id="_256">For patients with surgically treated localized disease, routine follow-up schedules may differ across institutions and depend on the risk status of the tumor.<Reference refidx="35"/> Abdominal/pelvic imaging may be performed every 3 to 6 months, but very low-risk lesions may not need to be imaged this frequently.<Reference refidx="35"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="17761719">Judson I, Demetri G: Advances in the treatment of gastrointestinal stromal tumours. Ann Oncol 18 (Suppl 10): x20-4, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11213830">Miettinen M, Lasota J: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors--definition, clinical, histological, immunohistochemical, and molecular genetic features and differential diagnosis. Virchows Arch 438 (1): 1-12, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10534170" MedlineID="20001737">Miettinen M, Sarlomo-Rikala M, Lasota J: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: recent advances in understanding of their biology. Hum Pathol 30 (10): 1213-20, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25277795">Ma GL, Murphy JD, Martinez ME, et al.: Epidemiology of gastrointestinal stromal tumors in the era of histology codes: results of a population-based study. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 24 (1): 298-302, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="26618334">Søreide K, Sandvik OM, Søreide JA, et al.: Global epidemiology of gastrointestinal stromal tumours (GIST): A systematic review of population-based cohort studies. Cancer Epidemiol 40: 39-46, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16996566">Kawanowa K, Sakuma Y, Sakurai S, et al.: High incidence of microscopic gastrointestinal stromal tumors in the stomach. Hum Pathol 37 (12): 1527-35, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="17197927">Agaimy A, Wünsch PH, Hofstaedter F, et al.: Minute gastric sclerosing stromal tumors (GIST tumorlets) are common in adults and frequently show c-KIT mutations. Am J Surg Pathol 31 (1): 113-20, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="19499582">Benesch M, Wardelmann E, Ferrari A, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST) in children and adolescents: A comprehensive review of the current literature. Pediatr Blood Cancer 53 (7): 1171-9, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="23623056">Joensuu H, Hohenberger P, Corless CL: Gastrointestinal stromal tumour. Lancet 382 (9896): 973-83, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10">Gastrointestinal stromal tumor. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 8th ed. Springer; 2017, pp. 523–9.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="18039140">Corless CL, Heinrich MC: Molecular pathobiology of gastrointestinal stromal sarcomas. Annu Rev Pathol 3: 557-86, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="12">Casali PG, Dei Tos AP, Gronchi A: Gastrointestinal stromal tumor. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 895-906.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="17090188">Miettinen M, Lasota J: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: review on morphology, molecular pathology, prognosis, and differential diagnosis. Arch Pathol Lab Med 130 (10): 1466-78, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="10636102">DeMatteo RP, Lewis JJ, Leung D, et al.: Two hundred gastrointestinal stromal tumors: recurrence patterns and prognostic factors for survival. Ann Surg 231 (1): 51-8, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="24693892">Maynard MA, Marino-Enriquez A, Fletcher JA, et al.: Thyroid hormone inactivation in gastrointestinal stromal tumors. N Engl J Med 370 (14): 1327-34, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="22525410">Janeway KA, Pappo A: Treatment guidelines for gastrointestinal stromal tumors in children and young adults. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 34 (Suppl 2): S69-72, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="16160481">Miettinen M, Lasota J, Sobin LH: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors of the stomach in children and young adults: a clinicopathologic, immunohistochemical, and molecular genetic study of 44 cases with long-term follow-up and review of the literature. Am J Surg Pathol 29 (10): 1373-81, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="15689683">Nickl NJ: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: new progress, new questions. Curr Opin Gastroenterol 20 (5): 482-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="15211474">Vander Noot MR, Eloubeidi MA, Chen VK, et al.: Diagnosis of gastrointestinal tract lesions by endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration biopsy. Cancer 102 (3): 157-63, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="17018739">Joensuu H: Gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST). Ann Oncol 17 (Suppl 10): x280-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="15613856">Miettinen M, Sobin LH, Lasota J: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors of the stomach: a clinicopathologic, immunohistochemical, and molecular genetic study of 1765 cases with long-term follow-up. Am J Surg Pathol 29 (1): 52-68, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="16625094">Miettinen M, Makhlouf H, Sobin LH, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors of the jejunum and ileum: a clinicopathologic, immunohistochemical, and molecular genetic study of 906 cases before imatinib with long-term follow-up. Am J Surg Pathol 30 (4): 477-89, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="12717247">Miettinen M, Kopczynski J, Makhlouf HR, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors, intramural leiomyomas, and leiomyosarcomas in the duodenum: a clinicopathologic, immunohistochemical, and molecular genetic study of 167 cases. Am J Surg Pathol 27 (5): 625-41, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="11688571">Miettinen M, Furlong M, Sarlomo-Rikala M, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors, intramural leiomyomas, and leiomyosarcomas in the rectum and anus: a clinicopathologic, immunohistochemical, and molecular genetic study of 144 cases. Am J Surg Pathol 25 (9): 1121-33, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="17193820">Miettinen M, Lasota J: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: pathology and prognosis at different sites. Semin Diagn Pathol 23 (2): 70-83, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="20730857">Hohenberger P, Ronellenfitsch U, Oladeji O, et al.: Pattern of recurrence in patients with ruptured primary gastrointestinal stromal tumour. Br J Surg 97 (12): 1854-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="26988241">Hølmebakk T, Bjerkehagen B, Boye K, et al.: Definition and clinical significance of tumour rupture in gastrointestinal stromal tumours of the small intestine. Br J Surg 103 (6): 684-691, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="18774375">Joensuu H: Risk stratification of patients diagnosed with gastrointestinal stromal tumor. Hum Pathol 39 (10): 1411-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="9448764">Chun HJ, Byun JY, Chun KA, et al.: Gastrointestinal leiomyoma and leiomyosarcoma: CT differentiation. J Comput Assist Tomogr 22 (1): 69-74, 1998 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="12640147">Levy AD, Remotti HE, Thompson WM, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: radiologic features with pathologic correlation. Radiographics 23 (2): 283-304, 456; quiz 532, 2003 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="12835984">Ghanem N, Altehoefer C, Furtwängler A, et al.: Computed tomography in gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Eur Radiol 13 (7): 1669-78, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="12563150">Burkill GJ, Badran M, Al-Muderis O, et al.: Malignant gastrointestinal stromal tumor: distribution, imaging features, and pattern of metastatic spread. Radiology 226 (2): 527-32, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="33">Laurini JA, et al.: Protocol For the Examination of Resection Specimens From Patients With Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor (GIST) Version 4.2.0.0. College of American Pathologists, 2021. <ExternalRef xref="https://documents.cap.org/protocols/Stomach.GIST_4.2.0.0.REL_CAPCP.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 13, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="17624289">Demetri GD, Benjamin RS, Blanke CD, et al.: NCCN Task Force report: management of patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST)--update of the NCCN clinical practice guidelines. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 5 (Suppl 2): S1-29; quiz S30, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="18456761">Casali PG, Jost L, Reichardt P, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: ESMO clinical recommendations for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol 19 (Suppl 2): ii35-8, 2008.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Cellular classification--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Cellular and Molecular Classification of GISTs </Title><Para id="_4">Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) appear to originate from interstitial cells of Cajal (ICC) or their stem cell-like precursors.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> ICC are pacemaker-like intermediates between the gastrointestinal (GI) autonomic nervous system and smooth muscle cells regulating GI motility and autonomic nerve function.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  ICC are located around the myenteric plexus and the muscularis propria throughout the GI tract. ICC or their stem cell-like precursors can differentiate into smooth muscle cells if KIT signaling is disrupted.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_250">GISTs  are composed of spindle cells (70%), epithelioid cells (20%), or mixed spindle and epithelioid cells (10%).<Reference refidx="8"/> The histological patterns range from bland-appearing tumors with very low mitotic activity to very aggressive-appearing patterns.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_303">Approximately 85% of GISTs contain oncogenic variants in one of two receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs):<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_251" Style="bullet"><ListItem>KIT.</ListItem><ListItem>PDGFRA.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_252">Constitutive activation of either of these RTKs plays a central role in the pathogenesis of GISTs.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Tumors without detectable <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> or <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> variants account for 12% to 15% of all GISTs. Less than 5% of GISTs occur in patients with syndromic diseases, such as neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1), Carney triad syndrome (<GeneName>SDH</GeneName> deletion), and other familial diseases.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_27">Approximately 95% of GISTs are positive for the CD117 antigen, an epitope of KIT RTK expressed by ICC.<Reference refidx="10"/> However, CD117 immunohistochemistry (IHC) is not specific for GISTs  and can be seen in other mesenchymal, neural, and neuroendocrine neoplasms.<Reference refidx="10"/>   IHC staining for DOG1 helps distinguish GISTs from other mesenchymal tumors, particularly those that are KIT negative.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>  </Para><Para id="_29">Subtypes of GISTs include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_30" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>	<GeneName>KIT</GeneName>-variant GISTs.</Strong> Approximately 80% of all GISTs contain a variant in the <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> gene that results in constitutive activation.<Reference refidx="10"/> The <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> gene maps to 4q12-13, in the vicinity of genes encoding the RTKs PDGFRA and VEGFR2.<Reference refidx="19"/>  Variants in five different <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exons have been observed in GISTs: exon 11 (67%), exon 9 (10%), and exons 8, 13, and 17 (3%).<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="20"/> Typically, GISTs are heterozygous for a particular variant, but loss of the remaining wild-type <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> allele occurs in approximately 8% to 15% of tumors and may be associated with malignant progression.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/> <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> variants exhibit distinct anatomical distributions: exon 8 (small bowel), exon 9 (small bowel, colon), and exons 11, 13, and 17 (all sites).<Reference refidx="10"/> <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>-variant tumors express PKC theta and DOG1, a distinguishing feature of mesenchymal tumors.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="23"/></ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong><GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName>-variant GISTs.</Strong> Approximately 5% to 8% of GISTs harbor a variant in <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName>, a close homolog of <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> with similar extracellular and cytoplasmic domains.<Reference refidx="12"/> <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName>-variant GISTs may differ from <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>-variant GISTs in a number of ways, including a marked predilection for the stomach, epithelioid morphology, myxoid stroma, nuclear pleomorphism, and variable expression of CD117.<Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/> As with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>-variant GISTs, <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName>-variant tumors express PKC theta and DOG1.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="24"/> A <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> variant most commonly occurs in exon 18 (80%–90%), and it can be either a D842V (62%) or non-D842V (27%) variant. <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variants confer resistance to imatinib therapy.<Reference refidx="29"/> </ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong><GeneName>KIT</GeneName>-negative GISTs.</Strong> In approximately 5% of GISTs, IHC for CD117 is completely negative or uncertain. In these instances, IHC may lack sufficient sensitivity to detect small amounts of variant kinase.<Reference refidx="10"/> Approximately 30% of these tumors harbor <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> pathogenic variants while more than one-half have <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> variants.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="28"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>	<GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> wild-type GISTs.</Strong> The so-called wild-type GISTs comprise approximately 12% to 15% of all GISTs. In these tumors, no detectable variants have been identified in either <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> or <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName>. Many of these tumors are <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient or associated with NF1.<ItemizedList id="_315" Style="dash"><ListItem>	<Strong><GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient GISTs</Strong> are characterized by loss-of-function of one of more enzymes within the SDH family (SDHA–D, collectively termed SDHx) either by variant, such as in Carney-Stratakis syndrome, or epigenetic silencing, such as in Carney triad (gastric epithelioid GISTs, extra-adrenal paraganglioma, and pulmonary chondroma). <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient GISTs can be identified with IHC by an absence of SDHB. <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient GISTs are generally found in younger patients, are typically multifocal, and are located in the stomach. They also tend to have an indolent course and are poorly responsive to tyrosine kinase inhibitor therapy.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="30"/></ListItem><ListItem>	<Strong>NF1-related GISTs</Strong> have a propensity for multicentricity within the GI tract and spindle cell morphology. They are typically positive for the CD117 antigen but do not harbor <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> or <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> variants.<Reference refidx="13"/> The clinical course is typically indolent. </ListItem><ListItem>	Other variants seen in <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> wild-type GISTs include <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> V600E <Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/> and <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="33"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>	Familial GISTs.</Strong> Approximately two dozen kindreds with heritable variants in <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> or <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> have been identified. Penetrance in these kindreds is high, with most affected members developing one or more GISTs by middle age. However, in many patients, the tumors follow a benign course.<Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="9438854">Hirota S, Isozaki K, Moriyama Y, et al.: Gain-of-function mutations of c-kit in human gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Science 279 (5350): 577-80, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9588894">Kindblom LG, Remotti HE, Aldenborg F, et al.: Gastrointestinal pacemaker cell tumor (GIPACT): gastrointestinal stromal tumors show phenotypic characteristics of the interstitial cells of Cajal. Am J Pathol 152 (5): 1259-69, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11035578" MedlineID="20489965">Wang L, Vargas H, French SW: Cellular origin of gastrointestinal stromal tumors: a study of 27 cases. Arch Pathol Lab Med 124 (10): 1471-5, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10199467">Sircar K, Hewlett BR, Huizinga JD, et al.: Interstitial cells of Cajal as precursors of gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Am J Surg Pathol 23 (4): 377-89, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="1283735">Maeda H, Yamagata A, Nishikawa S, et al.: Requirement of c-kit for development of intestinal pacemaker system. Development 116 (2): 369-75, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="7530333">Huizinga JD, Thuneberg L, Klüppel M, et al.: W/kit gene required for interstitial cells of Cajal and for intestinal pacemaker activity. Nature 373 (6512): 347-9, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="10381920">Torihashi S, Nishi K, Tokutomi Y, et al.: Blockade of kit signaling induces transdifferentiation of interstitial cells of cajal to a smooth muscle phenotype. Gastroenterology 117 (1): 140-8, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="15365079">Corless CL, Fletcher JA, Heinrich MC: Biology of gastrointestinal stromal tumors. J Clin Oncol 22 (18): 3813-25, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Gastrointestinal stromal tumor. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 8th ed. Springer; 2017, pp. 523–9.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="18039140">Corless CL, Heinrich MC: Molecular pathobiology of gastrointestinal stromal sarcomas. Annu Rev Pathol 3: 557-86, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="17090188">Miettinen M, Lasota J: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: review on morphology, molecular pathology, prognosis, and differential diagnosis. Arch Pathol Lab Med 130 (10): 1466-78, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="12522257">Heinrich MC, Corless CL, Duensing A, et al.: PDGFRA activating mutations in gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Science 299 (5607): 708-10, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16096406">Andersson J, Sihto H, Meis-Kindblom JM, et al.: NF1-associated gastrointestinal stromal tumors have unique clinical, phenotypic, and genotypic characteristics. Am J Surg Pathol 29 (9): 1170-6, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="17549339">Agaimy A, Pelz AF, Corless CL, et al.: Epithelioid gastric stromal tumours of the antrum in young females with the Carney triad: a report of three new cases with mutational analysis and comparative genomic hybridization. Oncol Rep 18 (1): 9-15, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="10377927">Carney JA: Gastric stromal sarcoma, pulmonary chondroma, and extra-adrenal paraganglioma (Carney Triad): natural history, adrenocortical component, and possible familial occurrence. Mayo Clin Proc 74 (6): 543-52, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="15217944">Blay P, Astudillo A, Buesa JM, et al.: Protein kinase C theta is highly expressed in gastrointestinal stromal tumors but not in other mesenchymal neoplasias. Clin Cancer Res 10 (12 Pt 1): 4089-95, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="15289315">Duensing A, Joseph NE, Medeiros F, et al.: Protein Kinase C theta (PKCtheta) expression and constitutive activation in gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs). Cancer Res 64 (15): 5127-31, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="15215166">West RB, Corless CL, Chen X, et al.: The novel marker, DOG1, is expressed ubiquitously in gastrointestinal stromal tumors irrespective of KIT or PDGFRA mutation status. Am J Pathol 165 (1): 107-13, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="2562117">Stenman G, Eriksson A, Claesson-Welsh L: Human PDGFA receptor gene maps to the same region on chromosome 4 as the KIT oncogene. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 1 (2): 155-8, 1989.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="14645423">Heinrich MC, Corless CL, Demetri GD, et al.: Kinase mutations and imatinib response in patients with metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumor. J Clin Oncol 21 (23): 4342-9, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="16327443">O'Riain C, Corless CL, Heinrich MC, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: insights from a new familial GIST kindred with unusual genetic and pathologic features. Am J Surg Pathol 29 (12): 1680-3, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="15930355">Antonescu CR, Besmer P, Guo T, et al.: Acquired resistance to imatinib in gastrointestinal stromal tumor occurs through secondary gene mutation. Clin Cancer Res 11 (11): 4182-90, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="15154005">Wasag B, Debiec-Rychter M, Pauwels P, et al.: Differential expression of KIT/PDGFRA mutant isoforms in epithelioid and mixed variants of gastrointestinal stromal tumors depends predominantly on the tumor site. Mod Pathol 17 (8): 889-94, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="15095270">Debiec-Rychter M, Wasag B, Stul M, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumours (GISTs) negative for KIT (CD117 antigen) immunoreactivity. J Pathol 202 (4): 430-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="15223958">Medeiros F, Corless CL, Duensing A, et al.: KIT-negative gastrointestinal stromal tumors: proof of concept and therapeutic implications. Am J Surg Pathol 28 (7): 889-94, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="15492989">Sakurai S, Hasegawa T, Sakuma Y, et al.: Myxoid epithelioid gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST) with mast cell infiltrations: a subtype of GIST with mutations of platelet-derived growth factor receptor alpha gene. Hum Pathol 35 (10): 1223-30, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="15269295">Wardelmann E, Hrychyk A, Merkelbach-Bruse S, et al.: Association of platelet-derived growth factor receptor alpha mutations with gastric primary site and epithelioid or mixed cell morphology in gastrointestinal stromal tumors. J Mol Diagn 6 (3): 197-204, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="15693889">Pauls K, Merkelbach-Bruse S, Thal D, et al.: PDGFRalpha- and c-kit-mutated gastrointestinal stromal tumours (GISTs) are characterized by distinctive histological and immunohistochemical features. Histopathology 46 (2): 166-75, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="15928335">Corless CL, Schroeder A, Griffith D, et al.: PDGFRA mutations in gastrointestinal stromal tumors: frequency, spectrum and in vitro sensitivity to imatinib. J Clin Oncol 23 (23): 5357-64, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="27011036">Boikos SA, Pappo AS, Killian JK, et al.: Molecular Subtypes of KIT/PDGFRA Wild-Type Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors: A Report From the National Institutes of Health Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor Clinic. JAMA Oncol 2 (7): 922-8, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="18615679">Agaram NP, Wong GC, Guo T, et al.: Novel V600E BRAF mutations in imatinib-naive and imatinib-resistant gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 47 (10): 853-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="20023270">Hostein I, Faur N, Primois C, et al.: BRAF mutation status in gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Am J Clin Pathol 133 (1): 141-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="32669612">Atiq MA, Davis JL, Hornick JL, et al.: Mesenchymal tumors of the gastrointestinal tract with NTRK rearrangements: a clinicopathological, immunophenotypic, and molecular study of eight cases, emphasizing their distinction from gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST). Mod Pathol 34 (1): 95-103, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for GISTs</Title><Para id="_149">A formal staging system for gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs)  is available from the American Joint Committee on  Cancer (AJCC) Staging Manual. In practice, however, AJCC staging is not routinely implemented when risk assessment is determined by the clinical features noted in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_14" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Prognosis</SummaryRef> section.<Reference refidx="1"/>  </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Gastrointestinal stromal tumor. In: Amin MB, Edge SB, Greene FL, et al., eds.: AJCC Cancer Staging Manual. 8th ed. Springer; 2017, pp. 523–9.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment by stage--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Option Overview for GISTs</Title><Para id="_37">The management of patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) is a multidisciplinary effort involving close collaboration between pathologists, medical oncologists, surgeons, and imaging experts.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><SummarySection id="_39"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_41">Surgical resection is the primary treatment modality for the following types of patients:<Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]

</Para><ItemizedList id="_305" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Those  with primary GISTs who do not have evidence of metastasis.</ListItem><ListItem>Those  with tumors that are technically resectable (e.g., GISTs that do not require a formal gastrectomy, pancreatectomy, or other major organ resection) if the risks of morbidity are acceptable.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_225">Endoscopic surveillance is an option for patients with tumors measuring 2 cm or smaller with a mitotic index of 5 or less per 50 high-power fields.  The low rates of progression and metastasis in these tumors make endoscopic surveillance viable in place of surgical resection.<Reference refidx="3"/>

</Para><Para id="_43">The goal of surgery is complete gross resection with an intact pseudocapsule and negative microscopic margins.<Reference refidx="4"/> Because GISTs are generally encapsulated and relatively less infiltrative than other malignancies, wide excision is not necessary. Lymphadenectomy is typically unnecessary, given that lymph node metastasis is rare with GISTs. However, lymphadenectomy should be considered in patients with <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient GISTs and pathologically enlarged lymph nodes. </Para><Para id="_316">If anatomically feasible, laparoscopic surgery is increasingly performed instead of laparotomy. Reports demonstrate lower rates of recurrence, shorter hospital stays, and lower morbidity.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> </Para><Para id="_102">Neoadjuvant imatinib therapy can be given to patients with large tumors or difficult-to-access GISTs that are considered marginally resectable. Significant tumor shrinkage is often seen with targeted therapy, so this approach can potentially avoid major organ resection, or enable organ-sparing surgery. Genetic sequencing may be considered to identify sensitive or resistant variants prior to neoadjuvant imatinib therapy.  </Para><Para id="_226">For patients with oligometastatic recurrences (e.g., isolated intra-abdominal implants or solitary liver lesions), surgical resection may be used in conjunction with tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs).<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>] This should only be considered after multidisciplinary consultation.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_259">There is universal agreement that standard chemotherapy has no role in the primary therapy of GISTs.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_47">Before the advent of molecularly targeted therapy with TKIs, efforts to treat GISTs with conventional cytotoxic chemotherapy were essentially futile.<Reference refidx="1"/> The extreme resistance of GISTs to chemotherapy may be partly caused by the  increased expression of P-glycoprotein, the product of the <GeneName>MDR-1</GeneName>  gene, and MRP1, which are cellular efflux pumps that may prevent chemotherapeutic agents from reaching therapeutic intracellular concentrations in GIST cells.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><Title>Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor (TKI) Therapy</Title><Para id="_317">TKIs work by inhibiting aberrantly functioning KIT or PDGFRA receptor tyrosine kinases and inducing rapid reduction in tumor growth. TKI therapy is indicated for patients with unresectable, borderline resectable, metastatic, or recurrent GISTs. It is also indicated as adjuvant therapy for patients with GISTs at high risk of recurrence. </Para><Para id="_318">The TKI imatinib mesylate is used as first-line therapy for most patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>- and <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName>-variant GISTs.<Reference refidx="14"/> For patients with GISTs characterized by a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant, avapritinib is used as first-line therapy, given the high clinical benefit and imatinib-resistance in this subtype.<Reference refidx="15"/> Other TKI agents approved for subsequent lines of therapy in patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName>-variant GISTs include sunitinib, regorafenib, and ripretinib. Additional TKI agents that are occasionally given include nilotinib, sorafenib, and pazopanib. 
</Para><Para id="_319">Imatinib is not typically given to patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> wild-type GISTs (i.e., <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient or neurofibromatosis type 1 [NF1]-related GISTs) because of high rates of resistance. Other TKIs (i.e., sunitinib or regorafenib) may have some activity, but most patients are recommended to consider enrolling in clinical trials, if eligible.  </Para><Para id="_320">For more information on the efficacy, safety, and management of toxicity of imatinib, or additional agents in the setting of imatinib resistance or intolerance, see the sections on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_58" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Resectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef>, <SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_155" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Unresectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef>, and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_260"><Title>Radiation Therapy</Title><Para id="_261">Radiation therapy rarely has a role in the management of patients with GISTs. It may occasionally be used for palliation of painful metastases or for patients with unresectable bleeding tumors.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Casali PG, Dei Tos AP, Gronchi A: Gastrointestinal stromal tumor. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 895-906.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="17761719">Judson I, Demetri G: Advances in the treatment of gastrointestinal stromal tumours. Ann Oncol 18 (Suppl 10): x20-4, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="15613856">Miettinen M, Sobin LH, Lasota J: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors of the stomach: a clinicopathologic, immunohistochemical, and molecular genetic study of 1765 cases with long-term follow-up. Am J Surg Pathol 29 (1): 52-68, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="17624289">Demetri GD, Benjamin RS, Blanke CD, et al.: NCCN Task Force report: management of patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST)--update of the NCCN clinical practice guidelines. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 5 (Suppl 2): S1-29; quiz S30, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18559753">Huguet KL, Rush RM, Tessier DJ, et al.: Laparoscopic gastric gastrointestinal stromal tumor resection: the mayo clinic experience. Arch Surg 143 (6): 587-90; discussion 591, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="16627057">Otani Y, Furukawa T, Yoshida M, et al.: Operative indications for relatively small (2-5 cm) gastrointestinal stromal tumor of the stomach based on analysis of 60 operated cases. Surgery 139 (4): 484-92, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="16772777">Novitsky YW, Kercher KW, Sing RF, et al.: Long-term outcomes of laparoscopic resection of gastric gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Ann Surg 243 (6): 738-45; discussion 745-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25005014">Chen K, Zhou YC, Mou YP, et al.: Systematic review and meta-analysis of safety and efficacy of laparoscopic resection for gastrointestinal stromal tumors of the stomach. Surg Endosc 29 (2): 355-67, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="28073945">Kanda T, Masuzawa T, Hirai T, et al.: Surgery and imatinib therapy for liver oligometastasis of GIST: a study of Japanese Study Group on GIST. Jpn J Clin Oncol 47 (4): 369-372, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="16785353">Pawlik TM, Vauthey JN, Abdalla EK, et al.: Results of a single-center experience with resection and ablation for sarcoma metastatic to the liver. Arch Surg 141 (6): 537-43; discussion 543-4, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="12181401" MedlineID="22169285">Demetri GD, von Mehren M, Blanke CD, et al.: Efficacy and safety of imatinib mesylate in advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors. N Engl J Med 347 (7): 472-80, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="12197215">Edmonson JH, Marks RS, Buckner JC, et al.: Contrast of response to dacarbazine, mitomycin, doxorubicin, and cisplatin (DMAP) plus GM-CSF between patients with advanced malignant gastrointestinal stromal tumors and patients with other advanced leiomyosarcomas. Cancer Invest 20 (5-6): 605-12, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="10986053">Plaat BE, Hollema H, Molenaar WM, et al.: Soft tissue leiomyosarcomas and malignant gastrointestinal stromal tumors: differences in clinical outcome and expression of multidrug resistance proteins. J Clin Oncol 18 (18): 3211-20, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="18235121">Blanke CD, Demetri GD, von Mehren M, et al.: Long-term results from a randomized phase II trial of standard- versus higher-dose imatinib mesylate for patients with unresectable or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors expressing KIT. J Clin Oncol 26 (4): 620-5, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="32615108">Heinrich MC, Jones RL, von Mehren M, et al.: Avapritinib in advanced PDGFRA D842V-mutant gastrointestinal stromal tumour (NAVIGATOR): a multicentre, open-label, phase 1 trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (7): 935-946, 2020.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_58"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Classification</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Resectable Primary GISTs</Title><SummarySection id="_396"><Title>Treatment Options for Resectable Primary GISTs</Title><Para id="_397">Treatment options for resectable primary gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) include:</Para><OrderedList id="_398" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_399" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Surgery.</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_402" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Postoperative adjuvant tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy.</SummaryRef><ItemizedList id="_447" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_449" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Imatinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_399"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_400">All GISTs measuring 2 cm or larger are typically surgically resected. The management of incidentally encountered GISTs measuring smaller than 2 cm remains controversial. There is no evidence for re-excision in patients with a complete resection of all macroscopic disease but microscopically positive margins. Watchful waiting and adjuvant imatinib therapy may be appropriate for these patients.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_401"> In general, gastric GISTs may be removed by laparoscopic wedge resection, when technically feasible. GISTs rarely involve the locoregional lymph nodes. Thus, extensive lymph node dissection is not indicated unless there is clinically apparent nodal involvement. These tumors may have fragile pseudocapsules, so care must be taken to avoid rupturing the pseudocapsule during surgery, which could result in peritoneal dissemination.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_402"><Title>Postoperative adjuvant TKI therapy</Title><SummarySection id="_449"><Title>Imatinib</Title><Para id="_403">Results from three phase III studies support the use of postoperative adjuvant imatinib for patients with completely resected localized GISTs who have a high risk of recurrence based on tumor size, tumor location, mitotic index, and presence of tumor rupture.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_404">Evidence (phase III studies of postoperative imatinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_405" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00041197">ACOSOG Z9001</ProtocolRef> (NCT00041197) was a phase III, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of 713 patients with fully resected <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>-variant GISTs measuring at least 3 cm. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either imatinib 400 mg daily (n = 359) or placebo (n = 354) for 1 year after surgical resection.<Reference refidx="4"/><ItemizedList id="_406" Style="bullet"><ListItem>After a median follow-up of 19.7 months, disease recurrence or death occurred in 30 patients (8.4%) in the imatinib arm and 70 patients (19.8%) in the placebo arm.</ListItem><ListItem>	The 1-year recurrence-free survival (RFS) rate was 98% in patients who received imatinib (95% confidence interval [CI], 96%–100%) and  83% (95% CI, 78%–88%) in patients who received placebo  (hazard ratio [HR], 0.35; 95% CI, 0.22–0.53; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] No difference was noted in overall survival (OS) (HR, 0.66; 95% CI, 0.22–2.03; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .4714).</ListItem><ListItem>	Dose-reduction or interruption because of adverse events occurred in 14.5% of patients in the imatinib arm and 2.8% of patients in the placebo arm. Grade 3 or 4 events occurred in 30.9% of patients in the imatinib arm and 18.3% of patients in the placebo arm. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00103168">EORTC-62024</ProtocolRef> (NCT00103168) was a phase III open-label trial of 908 patients with fully resected (R0 or R1 margin) <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>-variant GISTs at intermediate or high risk of recurrence. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either imatinib 400 mg daily (n = 454) or observation (n = 454) for 2 years.<Reference refidx="10"/><ItemizedList id="_407" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	At a median follow-up of 4.7 years,	RFS rates were improved for patients who received imatinib compared with patients who underwent observation at 3 years (84% vs. 66%) and 5 years (69% vs. 63%) (log-rank <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] The 5-year OS rate did not differ between the imatinib and observation arms (91.8% vs. 92.7%). </ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year imatinib failure-free survival rate (day of randomization to the start of a new systemic treatment or death) was 87% in the imatinib arm and 84% in the observation arm (HR, 0.79; 98.5% CI, 0.50–1.25; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .21).<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>	A final analysis  at a median follow-up of 9.1 years showed RFS rates of 70% and 63% at 5 and 10 years, respectively, for patients in the imatinib arm, and rates of 63% and 61% at 5 and 10 years, respectively, for patients in the observation arm (HR, 0.71; 95% CI, 0.57–0.89; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .002). There was no difference in OS between patients who received imatinib and patients who underwent observation (93% vs. 92% at 5 years, 80% vs. 78% at 10 years; HR, 0.88; 95% CI, 0.65–1.21; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .43).<Reference refidx="9"/>[Levels of evidence <LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">B1</LOERef> and <LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">A1</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00116935">SSG XVIII</ProtocolRef> (NCT00116935) was a phase III open-label trial of 400 patients with fully resected, high-risk GISTs. Patients were randomly assigned to receive imatinib 400 mg daily for either 1 year (n = 200) or 3 years (n = 200) after resection.<Reference refidx="5"/><ItemizedList id="_408" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	After a median follow-up of 54 months, the RFS rate was 65.6% in the 3-year arm and 47.9% in the 1-year arm (HR, 0.46; 95% CI, 0.32–0.65; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>	 The 5-year OS rate was 92% in the 3-year arm and 81.7% in the 1-year arm (HR, 0.45; 95% CI, 0.22–0.89; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem>	Although generally well-tolerated in both groups, grade 3 or 4 events occurred in 32.8% of patients in 3-year arm and 20.1% of patients in the 1-year arm. Treatment discontinuation occurred in 25.8% of patients in 3-year arm and 12.6% of patients in the 1-year arm.</ListItem><ListItem>A post-hoc exploratory analysis suggested that patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 11–variant GISTs derived the most benefit from a longer duration of imatinib (5-year RFS, 71.0% vs. 41.3%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_409">The recommended length of adjuvant treatment remains unknown. However, based on the SSG XVIII study results, at least 3 years of therapy is generally used in practice. It is important to note that evidence suggests that, instead of being cytotoxic, imatinib may suppress GIST growth. Therefore, recurrence may be delayed by the suppression of undetectable metastatic disease.<Reference refidx="5"/> <Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> For example, the rate of recurrence increased within 6 to 12 months of discontinuing adjuvant imatinib in both the 1-year and 3-year arms in the SSG XVIII trial.<Reference refidx="5"/> This concept has led to higher-risk patients being given imatinib indefinitely, although there is no direct trial evidence to support that.</Para><Para id="_410">Most patients initiate imatinib therapy at a dosage of 400 mg per day. Molecular genotyping of patients with GISTs is recommended as it can impact the use of adjuvant imatinib, as well as the optimal dose. Patients whose tumor harbors a <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 9 variant may benefit from higher-dose imatinib (800 mg per day) based on data in the metastatic setting.<Reference refidx="14"/> Patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> wild-type GISTs (i.e., <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient and neurofibromatosis type 1 [NF1]-related GISTs) or <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V-variant GISTs are unlikely to benefit from adjuvant imatinib therapy.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_411">Although not fully conclusive, there is some phase II evidence to support continuing adjuvant imatinib therapy for 5 years or more.  </Para><Para id="_412">Evidence (phase II studies of postoperative imatinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_413" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00867113">PERSIST-5</ProtocolRef> (NCT00867113) was a single-arm phase II trial of 91 patients with fully resected, high-risk GISTs. Patients received imatinib (400 mg daily) for up to 5 years.<Reference refidx="15"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_414" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	The median treatment duration was 55.1 months, but with a large range (0.5–60.6 months). Only 46 patients (51%) completed all 5 years of therapy. Thus, 49% of patients stopped treatment early because of patient choice (21%), adverse events (16%), or other reasons (12%). </ListItem><ListItem>At a median follow-up of 19.6 months, the estimated 5-year RFS rate was 90% (95% CI, 80%–95%). The OS rate was 95% (95% CI, 86%–99%). Seven patients (7.6%) had a recurrence, 6 of which occurred after treatment discontinuation.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A small, single-institution, retrospective analysis included 234 patients with R0-resected GISTs at moderate to high risk of recurrence. The study evaluated the effect of differing durations of postoperative imatinib on 5-year RFS and OS rates.<Reference refidx="13"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_415" Style="bullet"><ListItem>At a median follow-up of 54 months, the 5-year RFS rate across all groups was 76.2%. The  OS rate across all groups was 83.4%.</ListItem><ListItem>	In high-risk patients, longer durations of imatinib therapy were associated with higher RFS rates (36.5% in the 1-year group, 68.7% in the 1–3-years group, 71.2% in the 3–5-years group, and 90.8% in the &gt;5-years group; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). Longer imatinib therapy duration was also associated with higher OS rates (36.7% in the 1-year group, 76.6% in the 1–3-years group, 84.0% in the 3–5-years group, and 97.4% in the &gt;5-years group; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001).  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_58_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_58_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="17624289">Demetri GD, Benjamin RS, Blanke CD, et al.: NCCN Task Force report: management of patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST)--update of the NCCN clinical practice guidelines. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 5 (Suppl 2): S1-29; quiz S30, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16627057">Otani Y, Furukawa T, Yoshida M, et al.: Operative indications for relatively small (2-5 cm) gastrointestinal stromal tumor of the stomach based on analysis of 60 operated cases. Surgery 139 (4): 484-92, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="3">DeMatteo RP, Owzar K, Antonescu CR, et al.: Efficacy of adjuvant imatinib mesylate following complete resection of localized, primary gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST) at high risk of recurrence: the U.S. Intergroup phase II trial ACOSOG Z9000. [Abstract] American Society of Clinical Oncology 2008 Gastrointestinal Cancers Symposium, 25-27 January 2008, Orlando, FL.  A-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19303137">Dematteo RP, Ballman KV, Antonescu CR, et al.: Adjuvant imatinib mesylate after resection of localised, primary gastrointestinal stromal tumour: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet 373 (9669): 1097-104, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="22453568">Joensuu H, Eriksson M, Sundby Hall K, et al.: One vs three years of adjuvant imatinib for operable gastrointestinal stromal tumor: a randomized trial. JAMA 307 (12): 1265-72, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="28334365">Joensuu H, Wardelmann E, Sihto H, et al.: Effect of KIT and PDGFRA Mutations on Survival in Patients With Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treated With Adjuvant Imatinib: An Exploratory Analysis of a Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Oncol 3 (5): 602-609, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Raut CP, Espat NJ, Maki RG, et al.: Extended treatment with adjuvant imatinib (IM) for patients (pts) with high-risk primary gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST): The PERSIST-5 study. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  35 (Suppl 15):  A-11009, 2017. <ExternalRef xref="https://ascopubs.org/doi/abs/10.1200/JCO.2017.35.15_suppl.11009">Also available online. </ExternalRef>Last accessed December 13, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="23860199">DeMatteo RP, Ballman KV, Antonescu CR, et al.: Long-term results of adjuvant imatinib mesylate in localized, high-risk, primary gastrointestinal stromal tumor: ACOSOG Z9000 (Alliance) intergroup phase 2 trial. Ann Surg 258 (3): 422-9, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="33482247">Casali PG, Le Cesne A, Velasco AP, et al.: Final analysis of the randomized trial on imatinib as an adjuvant in localized gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST) from the EORTC Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group (STBSG), the Australasian Gastro-Intestinal Trials Group (AGITG), UNICANCER, French Sarcoma Group (FSG), Italian Sarcoma Group (ISG), and Spanish Group for Research on Sarcomas (GEIS)☆. Ann Oncol 32 (4): 533-541, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="26573069">Casali PG, Le Cesne A, Poveda Velasco A, et al.: Time to Definitive Failure to the First Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor in Localized GI Stromal Tumors Treated With Imatinib As an Adjuvant: A European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group Intergroup Randomized Trial in Collaboration With the Australasian Gastro-Intestinal Trials Group, UNICANCER, French Sarcoma Group, Italian Sarcoma Group, and Spanish Group for Research on Sarcomas. J Clin Oncol 33 (36): 4276-83, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="26527782">Joensuu H, Eriksson M, Sundby Hall K, et al.: Adjuvant Imatinib for High-Risk GI Stromal Tumor: Analysis of a Randomized Trial. J Clin Oncol 34 (3): 244-50, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="27031092">Blanke CD, DeMatteo RP: Duration of Adjuvant Therapy for Patients With Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors: Where Is Goldilocks When We Need Her? JAMA Oncol 2 (6): 721-2, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="28083710">Lin JX, Chen QF, Zheng CH, et al.: Is 3-years duration of adjuvant imatinib mesylate treatment sufficient for patients with high-risk gastrointestinal stromal tumor? A study based on long-term follow-up. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 143 (4): 727-734, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="20124181">Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor Meta-Analysis Group (MetaGIST): Comparison of two doses of imatinib for the treatment of unresectable or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors: a meta-analysis of 1,640 patients. J Clin Oncol 28 (7): 1247-53, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="30383140">Raut CP, Espat NJ, Maki RG, et al.: Efficacy and Tolerability of 5-Year Adjuvant Imatinib Treatment for Patients With Resected Intermediate- or High-Risk Primary Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor: The PERSIST-5 Clinical Trial. JAMA Oncol 4 (12): e184060, 2018.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_155"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Classification</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Unresectable Primary GISTs</Title><SummarySection id="_450"><Title>Treatment Options for Unresectable Primary GISTs</Title><Para id="_266">Treatment options for unresectable primary gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) include:</Para><OrderedList id="_267" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_268" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Neoadjuvant tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy.</SummaryRef><ItemizedList id="_448" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_452" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Imatinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_268"><Title>Neoadjuvant TKI therapy</Title><SummarySection id="_452"><Title>Imatinib</Title><Para id="_156">Neoadjuvant imatinib may be used for patients with very large primary GISTs or poorly positioned small GISTs (considered unresectable without the risk of significant morbidity or functional deficit, such as needing a formal gastrectomy, pancreatectomy, or other major organ resection) until surgical therapy is feasible, which can take as long as 6 to 12 months.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  Neoadjuvant imatinib therapy in patients with GISTs is supported by the early results of two phase II studies in the United States <Reference refidx="3"/> and Asia <Reference refidx="4"/>, as well as several case series and small retrospective reports.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> Neoadjuvant imatinib may be particularly beneficial in rectal GISTs, given the large bulky nature of the disease and the extensive surgery required for complete resection.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>  </Para><Para id="_372">Evidence (phase II studies of neoadjuvant imatinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_373" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00028002">RTOG-0132/ACRIN-6665</ProtocolRef> (NCT00028002) was a phase II single-arm study of 52 patients with primary GISTs (n = 30) or operable metastatic GISTs (n = 22). Patients received preoperative imatinib (600 mg daily) for 8 to 12 weeks followed by postoperative imatinib for at least 2 years.<Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_374" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	Among patients with primary GISTs,  83% had stable disease and 7% had a partial response (7%). Among patients with metastatic GISTs, 91% had stable disease, 4.5% had a partial response, and 4.5% had disease progression.</ListItem><ListItem>	At a median follow-up of 36 months, the 2-year PFS rate was 83% in patients with primary GISTs and 77% in patients with metastatic GISTs. The OS rate was 93% in patients with primary GISTs and 91% in patients with metastatic GISTs.</ListItem><ListItem>Seventy-seven percent of patients with primary GISTs and 58% of patients with metastatic GISTs went on to have R0 resections. Five patients (10%) had unresectable disease. </ListItem><ListItem>	Imatinib was generally well tolerated, although 35% of patients had grade 3 to 5 adverse events. The median preoperative duration of imatinib was 65 days, and the median time of imatinib discontinuation before surgery was 2 days. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A phase II single-arm study conducted in Asia included 53 evaluable patients with gastric GISTs larger than 10 cm. Patients received preoperative imatinib (400 mg daily) for 6 to 9 months, followed by at least 1 year of postoperative imatinib.<Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_375" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	Forty-six patients (87%) received at least 6 months of preoperative imatinib and 50 patients ultimately underwent gastrectomy. The median duration of preoperative imatinib was 26 weeks. The most common grade 3 to 4 adverse events were neutropenia and rash.  </ListItem><ListItem>	The objective response rate was 62%, and the maximal reduction occurred most commonly at 24 weeks (63% of patients). The R0 resection rate was 91% overall, and at least one-half of the stomach was preserved in 79% of patients.  </ListItem><ListItem>At a median follow-up of 32 months, the 	2-year PFS rate was 89%, and the OS rate was 98%.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_269">If a preoperative TKI is planned, a biopsy to confirm the diagnosis and, potentially, molecular profiling should be considered. Mutational analysis may help to exclude nonsensitive variants before starting imatinib cytoreduction therapy. Biopsy and molecular profiling may also determine whether a tumor harbors a <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 9 variant, which may require an increase in initial imatinib dosing.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="13"/> Neoadjuvant imatinib is not used for patients with GISTs harboring a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant. Some guidelines, such as those from the European Society of Medical Oncology, recommend considering neoadjuvant avapritinib.<Reference refidx="14"/> However, avapritinib has not been tested or validated in the neoadjuvant setting. In addition, patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> wild-type GISTs (i.e., <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient  or neurofibromatosis type 1 [NF1]-related GISTs) would not benefit from neoadjuvant therapy and should proceed directly to surgery, if feasible.  </Para><Para id="_324">If indicated, neoadjuvant imatinib is initiated at 400 mg per day in most patients. Patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon  9–variant GISTs may be offered a higher dose (800 mg per day) based on data from the advanced setting.<Reference refidx="15"/>  Follow-up imaging, with either computed tomography (CT) or positron emission tomography (PET)-CT,  is performed at close intervals. PET-CT can be particularly helpful in assessing initial early response if baseline molecular profiling was not done before neoadjuvant therapy.<Reference refidx="16"/> The optimal duration of neoadjuvant treatment is unknown and should be individualized based on multidisciplinary discussion. Neoadjuvant TKI therapy precludes the ability to risk stratify after surgical resection. Therefore, patients should continue imatinib after surgery for at least 3 total years.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_155_sid_6"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_155_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="17624289">Demetri GD, Benjamin RS, Blanke CD, et al.: NCCN Task Force report: management of patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST)--update of the NCCN clinical practice guidelines. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 5 (Suppl 2): S1-29; quiz S30, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16957966">Bonvalot S, Eldweny H, Péchoux CL, et al.: Impact of surgery on advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST) in the imatinib era. Ann Surg Oncol 13 (12): 1596-603, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="18942073">Eisenberg BL, Harris J, Blanke CD, et al.: Phase II trial of neoadjuvant/adjuvant imatinib mesylate (IM) for advanced primary and metastatic/recurrent operable gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST): early results of RTOG 0132/ACRIN 6665. J Surg Oncol 99 (1): 42-7, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28535156">Kurokawa Y, Yang HK, Cho H, et al.: Phase II study of neoadjuvant imatinib in large gastrointestinal stromal tumours of the stomach. Br J Cancer 117 (1): 25-32, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="17072676">Andtbacka RH, Ng CS, Scaife CL, et al.: Surgical resection of gastrointestinal stromal tumors after treatment with imatinib. Ann Surg Oncol 14 (1): 14-24, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15205603">Katz D, Segal A, Alberton Y, et al.: Neoadjuvant imatinib for unresectable gastrointestinal stromal tumor. Anticancer Drugs 15 (6): 599-602, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="16710031">Raut CP, Posner M, Desai J, et al.: Surgical management of advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors after treatment with targeted systemic therapy using kinase inhibitors. J Clin Oncol 24 (15): 2325-31, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="14672776">Scaife CL, Hunt KK, Patel SR, et al.: Is there a role for surgery in patients with "unresectable" cKIT+ gastrointestinal stromal tumors treated with imatinib mesylate? Am J Surg 186 (6): 665-9, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="21040362">Machlenkin S, Pinsk I, Tulchinsky H, et al.: The effect of neoadjuvant Imatinib therapy on outcome and survival after rectal gastrointestinal stromal tumour. Colorectal Dis 13 (10): 1110-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="23760587">Rutkowski P, Gronchi A, Hohenberger P, et al.: Neoadjuvant imatinib in locally advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST): the EORTC STBSG experience. Ann Surg Oncol 20 (9): 2937-43, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="29058144">Cavnar MJ, Wang L, Balachandran VP, et al.: Rectal Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor (GIST) in the Era of Imatinib: Organ Preservation and Improved Oncologic Outcome. Ann Surg Oncol 24 (13): 3972-3980, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="22806955">Tielen R, Verhoef C, van Coevorden F, et al.: Surgical management of rectal gastrointestinal stromal tumors. J Surg Oncol 107 (4): 320-3, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16624552">Debiec-Rychter M, Sciot R, Le Cesne A, et al.: KIT mutations and dose selection for imatinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours. Eur J Cancer 42 (8): 1093-103, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="34560242">Casali PG, Blay JY, Abecassis N, et al.: Gastrointestinal stromal tumours: ESMO-EURACAN-GENTURIS Clinical Practice Guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol 33 (1): 20-33, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="20124181">Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor Meta-Analysis Group (MetaGIST): Comparison of two doses of imatinib for the treatment of unresectable or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors: a meta-analysis of 1,640 patients. J Clin Oncol 28 (7): 1247-53, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="22381410">Van den Abbeele AD, Gatsonis C, de Vries DJ, et al.: ACRIN 6665/RTOG 0132 phase II trial of neoadjuvant imatinib mesylate for operable malignant gastrointestinal stromal tumor: monitoring with 18F-FDG PET and correlation with genotype and GLUT4 expression. J Nucl Med 53 (4): 567-74, 2012.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_158"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Classification</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</Title><SummarySection id="_451"><Title>Treatment Options for Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</Title><Para id="_270">Treatment options for metastatic or recurrent gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) include: </Para><OrderedList id="_299" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_273" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Initial tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_441" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_453" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Imatinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_416" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Initial TKI therapy for <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842-variant GISTs</SummaryRef>. <ItemizedList id="_442" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_454" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Avapritinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_279" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">TKI therapy for imatinib-resistant GISTs</SummaryRef>.<ItemizedList id="_443" Style="bullet"><ListItem> <SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_334" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Sunitinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_343" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq"> Regorafenib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_427" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">	Additional TKI therapy options</SummaryRef>. <ItemizedList id="_444" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_428" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Ripretinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_435" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Nilotinib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_437" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Sorafenib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_439" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Pazopanib</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>	<SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_445" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">TKI therapy for <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> wild-type GISTs</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_288" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Surgery</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_361" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Clinical trials</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_272">The primary treatment of patients with metastatic or recurrent GISTs involves medical therapy with a TKI. In select cases, surgical therapy may be added. Patients with metastatic or recurrent tumors that do not respond to these measures may be candidates for clinical trials.</Para><SummarySection id="_273"><Title>Initial TKI therapy </Title><SummarySection id="_453"><Title>Imatinib</Title><Para id="_274">Therapy with imatinib is the standard first-line treatment for most patients with metastatic or recurrent disease. The initial dose is 400 mg daily, except for patients with tumors containing <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 9 variants, who may receive 800 mg daily.<Reference refidx="1"/> The only exception is for patients with GISTs characterized by the <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant. In this subtype,  avapritinib is used as first-line therapy given high clinical benefit and imatinib resistance.<Reference refidx="2"/> Most patients can initiate imatinib empirically while awaiting confirmation of their tumor’s molecular profile. That profile may necessitate an imatinib dosing change (i.e., <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 9), a change to avapritinib (i.e., <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant), or indicate likelihood for TKI resistance (i.e., <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient or neurofibromatosis type 1 [NF1]-related GISTs).  </Para><Para id="_159">All patients receiving TKI therapy are closely monitored for tumor response and side effects, which may require dose reductions, interruptions, or cessation of TKI therapy in cases of persistent, excessive toxicity. In addition, dose modification of the TKI or substitution with medications that do not affect cytochrome P450 isoenzyme 3A4 (CYP450 3A4) levels may be necessary for patients taking drugs that affect CYP450 3A4 levels.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_275">Response is evaluated with computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI),  or fluorine F 18-fludeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (18F-FDG PET).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> Treatment is usually continued indefinitely in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, with a median time to progression of 24 to 40 months and median survival approaching 45 to 60 months.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> A cohort of patients from early imatinib trials have continued on therapy with long-term survival.  In a multivariable analysis, age younger than 60 years, performance status 0, smaller size of the largest lesion, and exon 11 <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> variant were significant prognostic factors for the probability of surviving beyond 10 years.<Reference refidx="10"/> A similar finding for exon 11 was seen in a phase II study.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_276">Evidence (imatinib therapy):</Para><OrderedList id="_160" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A phase III trial included 746 patients with advanced unresectable or metastatic GISTs. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either higher-dose treatment with 800 mg imatinib daily or 400 mg imatinib daily as primary systemic therapy. <ItemizedList id="_277" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>No statistically significant differences in objective response rates, progression-free survival (PFS), or overall survival (OS) were observed between patients who received the 800 mg dose and patients who received the 400 mg dose.<Reference refidx="15"/>[Levels of evidence <LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">A1</LOERef>; <LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">B1</LOERef>; and <LOERef href="CDR0000810031" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">B3</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>Among patients who progressed at 400 mg daily and crossed over to 800 mg daily, approximately one-third were able to achieve an objective response or disease stabilization.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Similar findings were seen in a European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer, Italian Sarcoma Group, and Australasian Gastro-Intestinal Trials Group (EORTC-ISG-AGITG) study of 946 patients with GISTs who were randomly assigned to receive 400 mg or 800 mg of imatinib, with crossover permitted at progression.<Reference refidx="16"/>
</ListItem><ListItem>It is now recognized that specific kinase variants in <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> and <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> impact sensitivity/response to imatinib (e.g., exon 11 is imatinib sensitive and exon 9 is imatinib resistant).<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/> In addition, meta-analyses of both trials mentioned above have demonstrated that patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 9 variants have significant benefit with higher-dose imatinib.<Reference refidx="22"/> </ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_163">In the event of tumor progression in patients without <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 9 variants on lower dose imatinib (i.e., 400 mg daily), the imatinib dosage may be increased to 800 mg daily (in split doses).  Alternatively, in the management of imatinib resistance, the patient may be switched directly to sunitinib.<Reference refidx="23"/>  </Para><Para id="_325">The most common toxicities associated with imatinib therapy, all of which may improve with prolonged treatment, include:<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_326" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Fluid retention (especially periorbital edema or peripheral edema; occasionally pleural effusion or ascites).</ListItem><ListItem>Diarrhea.</ListItem><ListItem>Nausea (may be diminished if taken with food).</ListItem><ListItem>Fatigue.</ListItem><ListItem>Muscle cramps.</ListItem><ListItem>Abdominal pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Rash.</ListItem><ListItem>Mild (macrocytic) anemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Hypophosphatemia. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_327">There are rare reports of heart failure related to imatinib use,<Reference refidx="27"/> primarily in patients with preexisting heart disease. No excess cardiac toxicity was noted in either of the phase III trials of imatinib mentioned above for patients with advanced GISTs.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/> However, it is best to inform patients of this risk before starting imatinib and monitor clinically for signs of heart failure or left ventricular dysfunction.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_416"><Title>Initial TKI therapy for <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V-variant GISTs</Title><SummarySection id="_454"><Title>Avapritinib</Title><Para id="_417">Patients with GISTs that harbor a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> exon 18 D842V variant should initially be given avapritinib. However, for patients whose GISTs are asymptomatic or indolent, a period of observation is reasonable to avoid treatment toxicities. </Para><Para id="_418">Evidence (avapritinib in patients with a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant):</Para><OrderedList id="_419" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02508532">NAVIGATOR</ProtocolRef> (NCT02508532) was a phase I, single-arm, open-label trial of 56 patients with a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant. Patients received avapritinib at a daily dose of either 300 mg or 400 mg.<Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_420" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	An overall response was seen in 49 of 56  patients (88%) (95% confidence interval [CI], 76%–95%), with five patients (9%) achieving a complete response. </ListItem><ListItem>The 1-year PFS rate was 81% (95% CI, 67%–94%) and the 1-year duration of response was 70% (95% CI, 54%–87%). </ListItem><ListItem>	At median follow-up of 15.9 months, the estimated 1-year OS rate was 91%, and the estimated 2-year OS rate was 81%.</ListItem><ListItem>	The high overall response rate results of the NAVIGATOR trial led the U.S. Food and Drug Administration  (FDA) to approve avapritinib for patients with GISTs with a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> exon 18 variant, including D842V variants.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_421">Evidence (avapritinib in patients who did not respond to imatinib and at least one additional TKI):</Para><OrderedList id="_422" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03465722">VOYAGER</ProtocolRef> (NCT03465722) was a phase III open-label trial of 476 patients with advanced GISTs that did not respond to imatinib and at least one additional TKI. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either avapritinib 300 mg daily (n = 240) or regorafenib 160 mg daily (3-weeks-on/1-week-off regimen) (n = 236), with crossover allowed from regorafenib to avapritinib.<Reference refidx="28"/><ItemizedList id="_423" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	The median PFS was 4.2 months in the avapritinib arm and 5.6 months in the regorafenib arm (hazard ratio [HR], 1.25; 95% CI, 0.99–1.57; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis>  = .055). Among patients without a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant, the median PFS was 3.9 months in the avapritinib arm and 5.6 months in the regorafenib arm (HR, 1.34; 95% CI, 1.06–1.69; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis>  = .012).<Reference refidx="28"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>	OS data were immature at the time of the report with no interval differences noted between the study arms.</ListItem><ListItem>	Overall and grade 3 or higher treatment-related adverse events did not differ between groups. However, cognitive effects occurred more often in patients who received avapritinib (25.9%) than in patients who received regorafenib (3.8%). </ListItem><ListItem>	Because avapritinib did not improve PFS or OS compared with regorafenib in the treated population, it is not indicated until patients have failed multiple previous TKI therapies (outside of its specific variant indication above).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_424">If indicated, avapritinib is given at 300 mg daily. Avapritinib is teratogenic, and thus, warrants effective contraception during and up to 6 weeks after the final dose.<Reference refidx="29"/> The 300 mg dose was generally well-tolerated in the phase I NAVIGATOR study, with grade 3 to 4 toxicities including anemia, hyperbilirubinemia, fatigue, abdominal pain, diarrhea, peripheral edema, pleural effusion, and cognitive impairment.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_425">Cognitive effects must be closely monitored, with treatment changes (reductions, modifications, discontinuation) made promptly. Based on a post-hoc analysis of patients receiving 300 mg daily, grade 1 to 2 cognitive effects were seen in 37% of patients and 52% of patients older than 65 years. These effects included cognitive impairment, mood changes, sleep disorder, dizziness, hallucinations, and intracranial hemorrhage. These cognitive effects generally improved once treatment changes were made.<Reference refidx="29"/></Para><Para id="_426">Of note, for patients with GISTs who do not harbor a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant, avapritinib should not be used until imatinib and at least two additional agents (sunitinib and regorafenib) are tried. The open-label phase III VOYAGER trial demonstrated that regorafenib improved PFS more than avapritinib in patients without a <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> D842V variant.<Reference refidx="28"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_279"><Title>TKI therapy for imatinib-resistant GISTs</Title><SummarySection id="_334"><Title>Sunitinib</Title><Para id="_335">In the case of tumor progression (or intolerance to imatinib), data support second-line therapy with either imatinib dose escalation to 800 mg per day (as described above) or sunitinib.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="21"/> Sunitinib is given at a dose of 50 mg daily in a 4-weeks-on/2-weeks-off regimen or a daily dose of 37.5 mg.<Reference refidx="30"/> As with imatinib, the response to sunitinib is evaluated with CT, MRI, or 18F-FDG PET, and treatment is usually continued indefinitely in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/><Reference refidx="35"/><Reference refidx="36"/></Para><Para id="_336">Evidence (sunitinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_337" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>An international phase III trial of 312 patients with imatinib-resistant GISTs randomly assigned patients to receive sunitinib or placebo.<Reference refidx="30"/><ItemizedList id="_338" Style="bullet"><ListItem>On the basis of radiological assessment, the median time to tumor progression was more than four times as long with sunitinib (27.3 weeks; 95% CI, 16.0–32.1) than with placebo treatment (6.4 weeks; 95% CI,  4.4–10.0) (HR, 0.33; 95% CI, 0.23–0.47; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>OS was similarly better for sunitinib-treated patients (HR<Subscript>death</Subscript>, 0.49; 95% CI, 0.29–0.83).<Reference refidx="30"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>] 
</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_339">The response to sunitinib is also influenced by the molecular profile of the GIST. Based on a phase I/II study of 97 patients, the highest clinical benefit rate, PFS benefit, and OS benefit were seen in patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 9 variants, compared with patients with <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> wild-type or <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 11 variants.<Reference refidx="33"/> </Para><Para id="_340">Common side effects associated with sunitinib include:<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="37"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_341" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Fatigue.</ListItem><ListItem>Nausea and vomiting.</ListItem><ListItem>Anemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Neutropenia.</ListItem><ListItem>Diarrhea.</ListItem><ListItem>Abdominal pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Mucositis.</ListItem><ListItem>Anorexia.</ListItem><ListItem>Skin or hair discoloration.</ListItem><ListItem>	Proteinuria.</ListItem><ListItem>Hypothyroidism (thyroid function monitoring is generally recommended).</ListItem><ListItem>	Hypertension. </ListItem><ListItem>	Potential for delayed wound healing (may require holding 3–4 days prior to surgery).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_342">Less frequent toxicities include bleeding, fever, and hand-foot syndrome.<Reference refidx="30"/>  Therapy with sunitinib may be cardiotoxic. In a retrospective phase I/II study evaluating the efficacy of sunitinib in patients with imatinib-resistant metastatic GISTs, 8% of patients who received repeated cycles of sunitinib experienced congestive heart failure, while 47% of patients developed hypertension (&gt;150 per 100 mm Hg). Reductions in left ventricular ejection fraction were seen in at least 10% to 28% of patients.<Reference refidx="38"/>  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_343"><Title>Regorafenib</Title><Para id="_344">The FDA has approved regorafenib for the treatment of GISTs that are refractory to first-line therapy.  Regorafenib is a multikinase inhibitor with activity against KIT, PDGFRA, and VEGFR, among others.  Regorafenib has demonstrated anti-GIST activity in phase II and phase III studies.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/></Para><Para id="_345">Evidence (regorafenib):</Para><OrderedList id="_346" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The phase III double-blind <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01271712">GRID</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT01271712) included 199 patients with advanced GISTs who did not respond to previous imatinib and sunitinib therapy. Patients were randomly assigned in a 2:1 ratio to receive either 160 mg daily of regorafenib (3-weeks-on/1-week-off regimen) (n = 133) or placebo (n = 66). Crossover to open-label regorafenib was allowed for patients who had disease progression on the placebo arm.<Reference refidx="40"/>  <ItemizedList id="_347" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	After a median treatment duration of 23 weeks for regorafenib and 7 weeks for placebo, the median PFS was longer in patients who received regorafenib (4.8 months) compared with patients who received placebo (0.9 months) (HR, 0.27; 95% CI, 0.19–0.39; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001).<Reference refidx="40"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>] The OS did not differ between arms (HR, 0.77; 0.4–1.41; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .199). However, 56 patients in the placebo arm (85%) did cross over to receive regorafenib at the time of disease progression.</ListItem><ListItem>	Adverse events were more common in the regorafenib arm (98.5%) compared with the placebo arm (68.2%). The most common grade 3 or greater events were hypertension (23.5%), hand-foot syndrome (19.7%), and diarrhea (5.3%). </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_427"><Title>Additional TKI therapy options</Title><SummarySection id="_428"><Title>Ripretinib</Title><Para id="_429">Ripretinib is indicated for patients with advanced GISTs who have disease progression on (or are intolerant to) three or more TKIs, including imatinib. It works as a switch control inhibitor with multiple targets, including KIT exons 9, 11, 13, 14, 18, and it stabilizes the KIT molecule in its active  form. </Para><Para id="_430">Based on the  toxicity profile of ripretinib, a baseline echocardiogram or multigated acquisition (MUGA) scan should be obtained, and blood pressure and clinical signs of heart failure should be serially monitored. Dermatologic exams are warranted, given the association with the development of cutaneous cancers and hand-foot syndrome. Ripretinib is teratogenic and warrants concomitant effective contraception. It should also not be given perioperatively (1 week before or 2 weeks after surgery) because of the risk of delayed wound healing.<Reference refidx="41"/><Reference refidx="42"/></Para><Para id="_505">Evidence (ripretinib):</Para><OrderedList id="_431" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03353753">INVICTUS</ProtocolRef> (NCT03353753) was a phase III, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of 129 patients with advanced GISTs who had not responded to previous imatinib, sunitinib, and regorafenib therapy. Patients were randomly assigned in a  2:1 ratio to receive either ripretinib 150 mg daily (n = 85) or placebo (n = 44), with an opportunity to cross over at the time of disease progression.<Reference refidx="41"/><ItemizedList id="_432" Style="bullet"><ListItem>	After a median follow-up of 6.3 months for the ripretinib arm and 1.6 months for the placebo arm,  the median OS was longer for patients who received ripretinib (15.1 months), compared with patients who received placebo (6.6 months) (HR, 0.36; 95% CI, 0.21–0.62).<Reference refidx="41"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810017" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence A1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>	The median PFS was longer for patients who received ripretinib (6.3 months) than patients for who received placebo (1.0 month) (HR, 0.15; 95% CI, 0.09–0.25; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001). The PFS rate at 6 months was 51% in the ripretinib arm (95% CI, 39.4%–61.4%) and 3.2% in the placebo arm (95% CI, 0.2%–13.8%).<Reference refidx="41"/></ListItem><ListItem>	Twenty-nine patients (66%) in the placebo arm crossed over to the ripretinib arm. </ListItem><ListItem>	Ripretinib was well tolerated. The most common grade 3 or 4 adverse events were lipase increase (5%), hypertension (4%), fatigue (2%), and hypophosphatemia (2%). </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03673501">INTRIGUE</ProtocolRef> (NCT03673501) was an open-label phase III trial of 453 patients with advanced GISTs who did not respond to imatinib therapy. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either ripretinib 150 mg daily (n = 226) or sunitinib 50 mg (4-weeks-on/2-weeks-off regimen; n = 227).<Reference refidx="43"/><ItemizedList id="_433" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The median PFS did not differ between the ripretinib and sunitinib arms (8.0 months vs. 8.3 months; HR, 1.05; 95% CI, 0.82–1.33; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .72). In addition, there was no difference in the median PFS in the <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> exon 11 cohort (8.3 months vs. 7.0 months; HR, 0.88; 95% CI, 0.66–1.16; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .36).<Reference refidx="43"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810025" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B1</LOERef>]</ListItem><ListItem>	OS data were immature at the time of report.</ListItem><ListItem>	Patients who received ripretinib had fewer treatment-emergent adverse events (41.3% vs. 65.6%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .0001) and were more likely to develop drug-related grade 3 or 4 hypertension (5.8% vs. 22.6%). Dose modifications, interruptions, or discontinuations were all less common with ripretinib.</ListItem><ListItem>	Ripretinib did not lead to a PFS or OS benefit when compared with sunitinib. Therefore, it is not indicated unless the patient's tumor does not respond to prior lines of TKI therapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_435"><Title>Nilotinib</Title><Para id="_436">Nilotinib is a second-generation TKI with similar targets to imatinib. A phase III study of nilotinib versus best supportive care in imatinib- and sunitinib-resistant GISTs showed some PFS benefit based on local assessment but no PFS benefit based on central assessment. Post-hoc analysis did reveal a modest but significant median OS difference of 4 months.<Reference refidx="44"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_437"><Title>Sorafenib</Title><Para id="_438">Sorafenib is a multitarget kinase that is similar in structure and mechanism to regorafenib. A phase II trial of patients with imatinib- and sunitinib-resistant GISTs showed that sorafenib offered potential benefit, with a disease control rate of 68% and a median PFS of 5 months.<Reference refidx="45"/>  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_439"><Title>Pazopanib</Title><Para id="_440">Pazopanib inhibits VEGF signaling and showed modest PFS benefit when compared to best supportive care in a small phase II trial of patients with imatinib- and sunitinib-resistant GISTs. However, pazopanib had a high rate of toxicity.<Reference refidx="46"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_445"><Title>TKI therapy for <GeneName>KIT</GeneName>/<GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> wild-type GISTs</Title><Para id="_446">Patients without <GeneName>KIT</GeneName> or <GeneName>PDGFRA</GeneName> variants, such as <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient and NF1-related GISTs, do not benefit from initial TKI treatment with imatinib. However, these patients may have modest response to sunitinib and regorafenib.<Reference refidx="47"/> These tumors tend to have a relatively indolent course, and optimal management of these patients remains unknown. Thus, patients should be encouraged to enroll in a clinical trial, if available. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_288"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_289">Surgery may be added to medical therapy for selected patients with GISTs in an effort to delay or prevent recurrence, although the benefit of this therapeutic approach in patients with metastatic GISTs has yet to be proven in a randomized clinical trial.</Para><Para id="_290">Evidence (surgery):</Para><OrderedList id="_291" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>A retrospective study involving 69 consecutive patients who underwent surgery for unresectable primary or metastatic GISTs while receiving kinase inhibitors reported the following:<Reference refidx="48"/>[Levels of evidence <LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">C2</LOERef> and <LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">C1</LOERef>]<ItemizedList id="_292" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Patients with stable disease or limited progression were found to have prolonged survival after debulking procedures. In this group of patients with GISTs, no evidence of disease was found after surgery in 78% of patients with stable disease, 25%  of patients with limited progression, and 7% of patients with generalized progression.</ListItem><ListItem> The 12-month PFS rate was 80% for patients with stable disease, 33% for patients with limited progression, and 0% for patients with generalized progression.</ListItem><ListItem>The 12-month OS rate was 95% for patients with stable disease, 86% for patients with limited progression, and 0% for patients with generalized progression.</ListItem><ListItem>  The authors of this study concluded that surgery for patients with generalized progression should be limited to a palliative role.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_167">Overall, the indications for surgery in the management of metastatic or recurrent GISTs include:<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><OrderedList id="_168" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Stable disease (i.e., disease that is stable or shrinking on TKI therapy when gross resection is possible).</ListItem><ListItem>	Limited disease progression  (i.e., isolated tumor deposits that are progressing on TKI therapy after initial response [indicating delayed drug resistance], while other sites of disease remain stable).</ListItem><ListItem>	Oncological emergencies including hemorrhage, perforation, obstruction, or abscess. 

</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_169">Stable disease and limited disease progression identify subsets of patients with advanced disease that are selected for relative disease stability.  Therefore, the favorable outcomes that have been noted in case series may be principally the result of  selection bias rather than true benefit from surgery.</Para><Para id="_293">The median time to the development of secondary resistance to imatinib has been about 2 years.<Reference refidx="12"/> Therefore, it is suggested that surgery for metastatic or recurrent disease in patients receiving imatinib/sunitinib be performed before 2 years. Most experts would recommend considering surgery after 6 to 12 months of disease stability with TKI therapy.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Drug therapy may be continued after surgery. 

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_361"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_362">Patients who have generalized disease progression  while receiving standard therapies, or with certain molecular subtypes (i.e., <GeneName>SDH</GeneName>-deficient or NF1-related GISTs) may benefit from enrolling in clinical trials. These patients should be referred to specialized multidisciplinary research centers. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_158_sid_7"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_158_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="16624552">Debiec-Rychter M, Sciot R, Le Cesne A, et al.: KIT mutations and dose selection for imatinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours. Eur J Cancer 42 (8): 1093-103, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="32615108">Heinrich MC, Jones RL, von Mehren M, et al.: Avapritinib in advanced PDGFRA D842V-mutant gastrointestinal stromal tumour (NAVIGATOR): a multicentre, open-label, phase 1 trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (7): 935-946, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="17624289">Demetri GD, Benjamin RS, Blanke CD, et al.: NCCN Task Force report: management of patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST)--update of the NCCN clinical practice guidelines. J Natl Compr Canc Netw 5 (Suppl 2): S1-29; quiz S30, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Casali PG, Dei Tos AP, Gronchi A: Gastrointestinal stromal tumor. In: DeVita VT Jr, Lawrence TS, Rosenberg SA, et al., eds.: DeVita, Hellman, and Rosenberg’s Cancer: Principles &amp; Practice of Oncology. 11th ed. Wolters Kluwer, 2019, pp 895-906.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Blanke CD, von Mehren M, Joensuu H, et al.: Evaluation of the safety and efficacy of an oral molecularly-targeted therapy, STI157, in patients (pts) with unresectable or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) expressing c-kit (CD117). [Abstract] Proceedings of the American Society of Clinical Oncology  20: A-1, 1a, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11705489">van Oosterom AT, Judson I, Verweij J, et al.: Safety and efficacy of imatinib (STI571) in metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumours: a phase I study. Lancet 358 (9291): 1421-3, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="17470865">Choi H, Charnsangavej C, Faria SC, et al.: Correlation of computed tomography and positron emission tomography in patients with metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumor treated at a single institution with imatinib mesylate: proposal of new computed tomography response criteria. J Clin Oncol 25 (13): 1753-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="17369574">Blay JY, Le Cesne A, Ray-Coquard I, et al.: Prospective multicentric randomized phase III study of imatinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors comparing interruption versus continuation of treatment beyond 1 year: the French Sarcoma Group. J Clin Oncol 25 (9): 1107-13, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="18235121">Blanke CD, Demetri GD, von Mehren M, et al.: Long-term results from a randomized phase II trial of standard- versus higher-dose imatinib mesylate for patients with unresectable or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors expressing KIT. J Clin Oncol 26 (4): 620-5, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="28362562">Casali PG, Zalcberg J, Le Cesne A, et al.: Ten-Year Progression-Free and Overall Survival in Patients With Unresectable or Metastatic GI Stromal Tumors: Long-Term Analysis of the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer, Italian Sarcoma Group, and Australasian Gastrointestinal Trials Group Intergroup Phase III Randomized Trial on Imatinib at Two Dose Levels. J Clin Oncol 35 (15): 1713-1720, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="12181401" MedlineID="22169285">Demetri GD, von Mehren M, Blanke CD, et al.: Efficacy and safety of imatinib mesylate in advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors. N Engl J Med 347 (7): 472-80, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="15451219">Verweij J, Casali PG, Zalcberg J, et al.: Progression-free survival in gastrointestinal stromal tumours with high-dose imatinib: randomised trial. Lancet 364 (9440): 1127-34, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="16110036">Van Glabbeke M, Verweij J, Casali PG, et al.: Initial and late resistance to imatinib in advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors are predicted by different prognostic factors: a European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer-Italian Sarcoma Group-Australasian Gastrointestinal Trials Group study. J Clin Oncol 23 (24): 5795-804, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="17458563">Rutkowski P, Nowecki ZI, Debiec-Rychter M, et al.: Predictive factors for long-term effects of imatinib therapy in patients with inoperable/metastatic CD117(+) gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs). J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 133 (9): 589-97, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="18235122">Blanke CD, Rankin C, Demetri GD, et al.: Phase III randomized, intergroup trial assessing imatinib mesylate at two dose levels in patients with unresectable or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors expressing the kit receptor tyrosine kinase: S0033. J Clin Oncol 26 (4): 626-32, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="16098458">Zalcberg JR, Verweij J, Casali PG, et al.: Outcome of patients with advanced gastro-intestinal stromal tumours crossing over to a daily imatinib dose of 800 mg after progression on 400 mg. Eur J Cancer 41 (12): 1751-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="14645423">Heinrich MC, Corless CL, Demetri GD, et al.: Kinase mutations and imatinib response in patients with metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumor. J Clin Oncol 21 (23): 4342-9, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="15010069">Debiec-Rychter M, Dumez H, Judson I, et al.: Use of c-KIT/PDGFRA mutational analysis to predict the clinical response to imatinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours entered on phase I and II studies of the EORTC Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group. Eur J Cancer 40 (5): 689-95, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="15928335">Corless CL, Schroeder A, Griffith D, et al.: PDGFRA mutations in gastrointestinal stromal tumors: frequency, spectrum and in vitro sensitivity to imatinib. J Clin Oncol 23 (23): 5357-64, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="18955451">Heinrich MC, Owzar K, Corless CL, et al.: Correlation of kinase genotype and clinical outcome in the North American Intergroup Phase III Trial of imatinib mesylate for treatment of advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumor: CALGB 150105 Study by Cancer and Leukemia Group B and Southwest Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol 26 (33): 5360-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="26687836">Patrikidou A, Domont J, Chabaud S, et al.: Long-term outcome of molecular subgroups of GIST patients treated with standard-dose imatinib in the BFR14 trial of the French Sarcoma Group. Eur J Cancer 52: 173-80, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="22">van Glabbeke MM, Owzar K, Rankin C, et al.: Comparison of two doses of imatinib for the treatment of unresectable or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST): a meta-analyis based on 1,640 patients (pts). [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  25 (Suppl 18): A-10004, 546s, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="16496358">Rutkowski P, Nowecki Z, Nyckowski P, et al.: Surgical treatment of patients with initially inoperable and/or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST) during therapy with imatinib mesylate. J Surg Oncol 93 (4): 304-11, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="12374669">Dagher R, Cohen M, Williams G, et al.: Approval summary: imatinib mesylate in the treatment of metastatic and/or unresectable malignant gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Clin Cancer Res 8 (10): 3034-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="25">Benjamin RS, Rankin C, Fletcher C, et al.: Phase III dose-randomized study of imatinib mesylate (STI571) for GIST: Intergroup S0033 early results. [Abstract] Proceedings of the American Society of Clinical Oncology  22:  A-3271, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="12957454">Verweij J, van Oosterom A, Blay JY, et al.: Imatinib mesylate (STI-571 Glivec, Gleevec) is an active agent for gastrointestinal stromal tumours, but does not yield responses in other soft-tissue sarcomas that are unselected for a molecular target. Results from an EORTC Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group phase II study. Eur J Cancer 39 (14): 2006-11, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="16862153">Kerkelä R, Grazette L, Yacobi R, et al.: Cardiotoxicity of the cancer therapeutic agent imatinib mesylate. Nat Med 12 (8): 908-16, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="34343033">Kang YK, George S, Jones RL, et al.: Avapritinib Versus Regorafenib in Locally Advanced Unresectable or Metastatic GI Stromal Tumor: A Randomized, Open-Label Phase III Study. J Clin Oncol 39 (28): 3128-3139, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="33301227">Joseph CP, Abaricia SN, Angelis MA, et al.: Optimal Avapritinib Treatment Strategies for Patients with Metastatic or Unresectable Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors. Oncologist 26 (4): e622-e631, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="17046465">Demetri GD, van Oosterom AT, Garrett CR, et al.: Efficacy and safety of sunitinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumour after failure of imatinib: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 368 (9544): 1329-38, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="19064982">Prior JO, Montemurro M, Orcurto MV, et al.: Early prediction of response to sunitinib after imatinib failure by 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography in patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor. J Clin Oncol 27 (3): 439-45, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="19737946">Demetri GD, Heinrich MC, Fletcher JA, et al.: Molecular target modulation, imaging, and clinical evaluation of gastrointestinal stromal tumor patients treated with sunitinib malate after imatinib failure. Clin Cancer Res 15 (18): 5902-9, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="18955458">Heinrich MC, Maki RG, Corless CL, et al.: Primary and secondary kinase genotypes correlate with the biological and clinical activity of sunitinib in imatinib-resistant gastrointestinal stromal tumor. J Clin Oncol 26 (33): 5352-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="22439647">Rutkowski P, Bylina E, Klimczak A, et al.: The outcome and predictive factors of sunitinib therapy in advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST) after imatinib failure - one institution study. BMC Cancer 12: 107, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="22661587">Demetri GD, Garrett CR, Schöffski P, et al.: Complete longitudinal analyses of the randomized, placebo-controlled, phase III trial of sunitinib in patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor following imatinib failure. Clin Cancer Res 18 (11): 3170-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="25641662">Reichardt P, Kang YK, Rutkowski P, et al.: Clinical outcomes of patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors: safety and efficacy in a worldwide treatment-use trial of sunitinib. Cancer 121 (9): 1405-13, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="18665181">Wolter P, Stefan C, Decallonne B, et al.: The clinical implications of sunitinib-induced hypothyroidism: a prospective evaluation. Br J Cancer 99 (3): 448-54, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="18083403">Chu TF, Rupnick MA, Kerkela R, et al.: Cardiotoxicity associated with tyrosine kinase inhibitor sunitinib. Lancet 370 (9604): 2011-9, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="22614970">George S, Wang Q, Heinrich MC, et al.: Efficacy and safety of regorafenib in patients with metastatic and/or unresectable GI stromal tumor after failure of imatinib and sunitinib: a multicenter phase II trial. J Clin Oncol 30 (19): 2401-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="23177515">Demetri GD, Reichardt P, Kang YK, et al.: Efficacy and safety of regorafenib for advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours after failure of imatinib and sunitinib (GRID): an international, multicentre, randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet 381 (9863): 295-302, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="32511981">Blay JY, Serrano C, Heinrich MC, et al.: Ripretinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours (INVICTUS): a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (7): 923-934, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="32804590">Janku F, Abdul Razak AR, Chi P, et al.: Switch Control Inhibition of KIT and PDGFRA in Patients With Advanced Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor: A Phase I Study of Ripretinib. J Clin Oncol 38 (28): 3294-3303, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="35947817">Bauer S, Jones RL, Blay JY, et al.: Ripretinib Versus Sunitinib in Patients With Advanced Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor After Treatment With Imatinib (INTRIGUE): A Randomized, Open-Label, Phase III Trial. J Clin Oncol 40 (34): 3918-3928, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="22357255">Reichardt P, Blay JY, Gelderblom H, et al.: Phase III study of nilotinib versus best supportive care with or without a TKI in patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumors resistant to or intolerant of imatinib and sunitinib. Ann Oncol 23 (7): 1680-7, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="45">Campbell NP, Wroblewski K, Maki RG, et al.: Final results of a University of Chicago phase II consortium trial of sorafenib (SOR) in patients (pts) with imatinib (IM)- and sunitinib (SU)-resistant (RES) gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST). [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  29 (4): A-4, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="27068858">Mir O, Cropet C, Toulmonde M, et al.: Pazopanib plus best supportive care versus best supportive care alone in advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours resistant to imatinib and sunitinib (PAZOGIST): a randomised, multicentre, open-label phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol 17 (5): 632-41, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="27011036">Boikos SA, Pappo AS, Killian JK, et al.: Molecular Subtypes of KIT/PDGFRA Wild-Type Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors: A Report From the National Institutes of Health Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor Clinic. JAMA Oncol 2 (7): 922-8, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="16710031">Raut CP, Posner M, Desai J, et al.: Surgical management of advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors after treatment with targeted systemic therapy using kinase inhibitors. J Clin Oncol 24 (15): 2325-31, 2006.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_170"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038161">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Classification</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Resistant or Refractory GISTs</Title><Para id="_171">Eventual development of resistance to imatinib, sunitinib, and regorafenib is nearly universal. There is no standard therapy when this occurs, and patients should consider investigational therapy, such as new oral tyrosine kinase inhibitors.  If eligible, patients are encouraged to participate in clinical trials. </Para><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_170_sid_8"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_170_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_383"><Title>Key References for Treatment of GISTs</Title><Para id="_457">These references have been identified by members of the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board as significant in the field of gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST) treatment. This list is provided to inform users of important studies that have helped shape the current understanding of and treatment options for GISTs. Listed after each reference are the sections within this summary where the reference is cited.</Para><SummarySection id="_458"><Title>Preoperative Imatinib</Title><ItemizedList id="_459" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>8 to 12 weeks</ListTitle><ListItem>Eisenberg BL, Harris J, Blanke CD, et al.: Phase II trial of neoadjuvant/adjuvant imatinib mesylate (IM) for advanced primary and metastatic/recurrent operable gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST): early results of RTOG 0132/ACRIN 6665. J Surg Oncol 99 (1): 42-7, 2009. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18942073/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_460">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_461" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_155" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Unresectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_462" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>6 to 9 months</ListTitle><ListItem>Kurokawa Y, Yang HK, Cho H, et al.: Phase II study of neoadjuvant imatinib in large gastrointestinal stromal tumours of the stomach. Br J Cancer 117 (1): 25-32, 2017. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28535156/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_463">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_464" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_155" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Unresectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_465"><Title>Postoperative Imatinib</Title><ItemizedList id="_466" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>1 year of imatinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Dematteo RP, Ballman KV, Antonescu CR, et al.: Adjuvant imatinib mesylate after resection of localised, primary gastrointestinal stromal tumour: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet 373 (9669): 1097-104, 2009. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19303137/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_467">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_468" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_58" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Resectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_469" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>2 years of imatinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Joensuu H, Eriksson M, Sundby Hall K, et al.: One vs three years of adjuvant imatinib for operable gastrointestinal stromal tumor: a randomized trial. JAMA 307 (12): 1265-72, 2012. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22453568/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_470">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_471" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_58" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Resectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_472" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>1 year versus 3 years of imatinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Casali PG, Le Cesne A, Poveda Velasco A, et al.: Time to Definitive Failure to the First Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor in Localized GI Stromal Tumors Treated With Imatinib As an Adjuvant: A European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group Intergroup Randomized Trial in Collaboration With the Australasian Gastro-Intestinal Trials Group, UNICANCER, French Sarcoma Group, Italian Sarcoma Group, and Spanish Group for Research on Sarcomas. J Clin Oncol 33 (36): 4276-83, 2015. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26573069/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_473">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_474" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_58" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Resectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_475" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>5 years of imatinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Raut CP, Espat NJ, Maki RG, et al.: Efficacy and Tolerability of 5-Year Adjuvant Imatinib Treatment for Patients With Resected Intermediate- or High-Risk Primary Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor: The PERSIST-5 Clinical Trial. JAMA Oncol 4 (12): e184060, 2018. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30383140/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_476">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_477" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_58" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Resectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_478" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Varying duration of imatinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Lin JX, Chen QF, Zheng CH, et al.: Is 3-years duration of adjuvant imatinib mesylate treatment sufficient for patients with high-risk gastrointestinal stromal tumor? A study based on long-term follow-up. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 143 (4): 727-734, 2017. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28083710/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_479">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_480" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_58" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Resectable Primary GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_481"><Title>Advanced GIST Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors</Title><ItemizedList id="_482" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Imatinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Demetri GD, von Mehren M, Blanke CD, et al.: Efficacy and safety of imatinib mesylate in advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumors. N Engl J Med 347 (7): 472-80, 2002. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/12181401/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_483">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_484" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_35" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview for GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Blanke CD, Rankin C, Demetri GD, et al.: Phase III randomized, intergroup trial assessing imatinib mesylate at two dose levels in patients with unresectable or metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumors expressing the kit receptor tyrosine kinase: S0033. J Clin Oncol 26 (4): 626-32, 2008. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18235122/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_485">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_486" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_487" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Avapritinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Heinrich MC, Jones RL, von Mehren M, et al.: Avapritinib in advanced PDGFRA D842V-mutant gastrointestinal stromal tumour (NAVIGATOR): a multicentre, open-label, phase 1 trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (7): 935-946, 2020. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32615108/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_488">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_489" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_35" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview for GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_490" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Avapritinib versus regorafenib</ListTitle><ListItem>Kang YK, George S, Jones RL, et al.: Avapritinib Versus Regorafenib in Locally Advanced Unresectable or Metastatic GI Stromal Tumor: A Randomized, Open-Label Phase III Study. J Clin Oncol 39 (28): 3128-3139, 2021. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34343033/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_491">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_492" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_493" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Sunitinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Demetri GD, van Oosterom AT, Garrett CR, et al.: Efficacy and safety of sunitinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumour after failure of imatinib: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 368 (9544): 1329-38, 2006. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17046465/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_494">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_495" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_496" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Regorafenib</ListTitle><ListItem>Demetri GD, Reichardt P, Kang YK, et al.: Efficacy and safety of regorafenib for advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours after failure of imatinib and sunitinib (GRID): an international, multicentre, randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet 381 (9863): 295-302, 2013. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23177515/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_497">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_498" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_499" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Ripretinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Blay JY, Serrano C, Heinrich MC, et al.: Ripretinib in patients with advanced gastrointestinal stromal tumours (INVICTUS): a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (7): 923-934, 2020. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32511981/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_500">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_501" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_502" Style="bullet">
     <ListTitle>Ripretinib versus sunitinib</ListTitle><ListItem>Bauer S, Jones RL, Blay JY, et al.: Ripretinib Versus Sunitinib in Patients With Advanced Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor After Treatment With Imatinib (INTRIGUE): A Randomized, Open-Label, Phase III Trial. J Clin Oncol 40 (34): 3918-3928, 2022. [<ExternalRef xref="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35947817/">PUBMED Abstract</ExternalRef>]<Para id="_504">Cited in:</Para><ItemizedList id="_503" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_158" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Metastatic or Recurrent GISTs</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (12/13/2024)</Title><Para id="_147">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.
</Para><Para id="_237">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000639481#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of gastrointestinal stromal tumors. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewer for Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment is:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Vinayak Venkataraman, MD (Dana Farber Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/gist-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389157]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2011-03-09</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-12-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
