<Summary id="CDR0000660468" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Levels of Evidence for Supportive and Palliative Care Summaries includes cited references primarily from peer-reviewed biomedical literature. Get detailed information about how to weigh the strength of the evidence obtained in supportive and palliative care studies in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">Levels of Evidence for Supportive and Palliative Care Studies (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000257669">evaluation of evidence</TermRef></MainTopics><SecondaryTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000042592">Levels of Evidence</TermRef></SecondaryTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_42">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the formal ranking system used by the PDQ Editorial Boards to assess evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_43">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>evaluation of evidence</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Levels of Evidence</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Levels of Evidence for Supportive and Palliative Care Studies (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Levels of Evidence: Supportive and Palliative Care Studies (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Levels of Evidence: Supportive and Palliative Care Studies</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_2">The <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/supportive-care">PDQ supportive and palliative care information summaries</ExternalRef> provide descriptions of the pathophysiology and treatment of common physical and psychosocial complications of cancer and its treatment, including complications such as pain, anxiety, depression, fatigue, and nausea and vomiting. Each PDQ health professional summary generally includes an overview; information about etiology, assessment, and management; and citations to published medical literature.</Para><Para id="_7">The supportive and palliative care of cancer patients and their informal caregivers can involve the identification and mitigation of physiological, psychological, and spiritual needs.</Para><OrderedList id="_8" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Physiological complications addressed in the PDQ supportive and palliative care summaries include the following:<ItemizedList id="_9" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Cardiopulmonary syndromes.</ListItem><ListItem>Hot flashes and night sweats.</ListItem><ListItem>Gastrointestinal complications.</ListItem><ListItem>Lymphedema.</ListItem><ListItem>Nausea and vomiting.</ListItem><ListItem>Oral complications.</ListItem><ListItem>Pain.</ListItem><ListItem>Dermatological problems.</ListItem><ListItem>Sleep abnormalities.</ListItem><ListItem>	Malnutrition.</ListItem><ListItem>Fatigue.</ListItem><ListItem>Cachexia.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Psychological and behavioral complications addressed in the PDQ supportive and palliative care summaries include the following:<ItemizedList id="_10" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Cancer-related anxiety.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer-related post-traumatic stress.</ListItem><ListItem>Cognitive disorders.</ListItem><ListItem>Depression.</ListItem><ListItem>Normal adjustment issues and adjustment disorders.</ListItem><ListItem>Nutrition/weight management.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychosocial distress.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Spiritual and religious concerns addressed in the PDQ supportive and palliative care summaries include the following:<ItemizedList id="_11" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Spiritual experience.</ListItem><ListItem>Religious beliefs.</ListItem><ListItem>Approaches to addressing these issues.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Planning for end of life and anticipating end-of-life symptoms and needs addressed in the PDQ supportive and palliative care summaries include the following:<ItemizedList id="_44" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>End-of-life care decisions.</ListItem><ListItem>Supportive care.</ListItem><ListItem>Palliative care.</ListItem><ListItem>Hospice care.</ListItem><ListItem>Patient-oncologist communication.</ListItem><ListItem>Grief issues.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_12">References cited in the PDQ supportive and palliative care information summaries are drawn primarily from peer-reviewed biomedical literature. The quality and reliability of such published reports can vary considerably. To help readers assess the strength of findings from clinical research studies, levels-of-evidence rankings are often employed. These rankings generally take into account the strength of a study’s design and the strength of the clinical outcome(s) measured. Clinical research in supportive and palliative care is feasible in some settings but difficult to conduct in others, such as at the end of life. Furthermore, as in other areas of medicine, supportive and palliative care decisions must be made in the context of existing evidence, which may be weaker than ideal.</Para><Para id="_13">In general, the quality of evidence depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_17" Style="bullet"><ListItem> The appropriateness of the study to the question being asked.</ListItem><ListItem>How well the study was designed, implemented, analyzed, and interpreted.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18">For evaluating outcomes of both medical and psychosocial interventions, the strongest evidence is obtained from well-designed, well-conducted randomized clinical trials. For evaluating other questions, particularly those related to symptom management, well-designed descriptive studies may provide the strongest evidence practicable. Particular elements of study design, such as the nature of the population being studied or the duration of observation, may be crucial to assessing the quality of a study. Reviews of studies will indicate the level of evidence and any confounding design issues.</Para><Para id="_14">During the early phases of research in a new area, information relevant to the needs of patients and clinicians may come from a limited number of reports and data of varying strength. This information may include evidence from:</Para><ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Well-designed prospective studies (e.g., randomized trials, nonrandomized trials, cohort studies, and case series).</ListItem><ListItem>Cross-sectional studies (e.g., correlational designs using various levels of analytic sophistication).</ListItem><ListItem>Retrospective studies (e.g., case-control studies, case series, and case reports).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_20">The studies may be interventional, may be observational, or may involve provider or patient self-reports or record reviews.</Para><Para id="_16">In some cases, the best available evidence may reflect clinical/professional experience or expert consensus opinion. All sources may yield information relevant to patients and clinicians, who may be required to make management decisions before the best possible evidence is available.</Para><Para id="_21">In view of this complexity, the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef> took a pragmatic approach to defining the levels of evidence that it would use. The levels used by the Board focus primarily on the strength of a study’s design as appropriate to the questions being investigated. These levels should be easily understood by health professionals and serve as a starting point for discussing the strength of study results.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Study Design Categories, Definitions, and Levels of Evidence</Title><OrderedList id="_22" Style="URoman"><ListItem><Strong>Prospective, randomized, controlled trials and meta-analyses of prospective, randomized, controlled trials.</Strong><Para id="_23">The randomized, double-blinded, controlled trial is the gold standard of study design. To achieve this ranking, the study allocation must be blinded to the investigator both before and after the randomization and the assignment to intervention group. This design provides protection from allocation bias by the investigator and from bias in the assessment of outcomes by both the investigator and the patient.</Para><Para id="_24">Unfortunately, double-blinding after intervention assignment is not always possible because procedures or side effects often vary substantially among study interventions in ways that are obvious to both the investigator and the patient. In some cases, however, it should be possible to blind the investigator and the patient until the randomization has been made, even if intervention delivery cannot be blinded. Furthermore, randomized trials are still subject to imbalances if sample size is inadequate to the question of interest, and they may be less than optimal owing to other design elements such as choice of sample, measurement approach, appropriateness of the comparison condition, or loss to follow-up.</Para><Para id="_25">Meta-analysis of randomized studies offers a quantitative synthesis of previously conducted studies. The strength of the evidence from a meta-analysis is based on the quality of the individual studies included. Moreover, meta-analyses can magnify small systematic errors in individual studies.</Para><Para id="_26">Because the results of meta-analyses and the randomized trials they are based on do not always agree, and because meta-analyses performed by different investigators to address the same issue can reach contradictory conclusions, meta-analyses of randomized studies are placed in the same category of strength of evidence as are randomized studies, not at a higher level.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Prospective, nonrandomized, controlled trials; prospective cohort studies; prospective case series; and cross-sectional studies.</Strong><Para id="_27">In nonrandomized controlled trials, allocation to intervention group is made on the basis of:</Para><ItemizedList id="_28" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Birth date.</ListItem><ListItem>Chart number.</ListItem><ListItem>Bed availability.</ListItem><ListItem>Day of clinic appointment.</ListItem><ListItem>Any other strategy known to the investigator before informed consent is obtained from the patient.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_29">Imbalances can occur in intervention allocations under such circumstances but can also be taken into account statistically.</Para><Para id="_30">A prospective cohort study is a longitudinal study in which a defined group of individuals who share a certain condition and/or who are exposed to a particular intervention are followed over time and compared with another group of individuals who are not exposed to the intervention under study. The general population from which the cohort is drawn or another cohort can be used as the comparison group. Alternatively, subgroups within a cohort can be compared with each other.</Para><Para id="_31">A prospective case series is an uncontrolled study involving either consecutive cases or nonconsecutive cases. Although the evidence from this type of study is weaker than that from a controlled study, this design may be the only one practical in certain settings. Evidence from a consecutive case series is considered stronger than that from a nonconsecutive case series, and population-based series drawn from a well-defined population are stronger than non–population-based series.</Para><Para id="_32">Cross-sectional/correlational studies are widely used to investigate the relationship among variables in one or more groups of individuals. Depending on the research question, they may be the highest level of design possible and may even be the most appropriate to examine the relationships among multiple variables. Analytic strategies, including multivariate approaches, need to be matched to the question at issue. A combination of cross-sectional and longitudinal data collection can be explored with very sophisticated path analytic approaches, with the imputation of causality. Quality can nevertheless vary considerably, depending on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_33" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Choice of measurement.</ListItem><ListItem>Adequacy of sample size.</ListItem><ListItem>Representativeness of sample.</ListItem><ListItem>Quality of statistical analysis.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Retrospective studies.</Strong><Para id="_34">Retrospective studies include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_35" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Case-control studies.</ListItem><ListItem>Retrospective case studies.</ListItem><ListItem>Individual case reports.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_36">In case-control studies, two groups of individuals—one with a disease or condition (cases) and a similar group without the disease or condition (controls)—are compared. The cases should be representative of all cases in a population but do not have to include all cases in a population. The controls should come from the same population as the cases.</Para><Para id="_37">Retrospective studies are prone to numerous biases, including selection bias and lack of information about confounding variables from medical records or memories of the study participants (recall bias). Incident cases are preferable to prevalent cases to help reduce bias.</Para><Para id="_38">Evidence obtained from retrospective studies, especially case reports, is among the weakest forms of evidence. However, systematic qualitative research, while often retrospective in nature, improves substantially on anecdotal case reports.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Opinions of respected authorities based on clinical experience, consensus statements from expert committees, or authoritative reviews.</Strong><Para id="_39">The evidence supporting conclusions or recommendations in opinions, consensus statements, or authoritative reviews can be highly variable and subject to important biases. This category of evidence is usually considered the lowest in many levels-of-evidence rankings.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (07/13/2021)</Title><Para id="_41">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_40">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000660468#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the formal ranking system used by the PDQ Editorial Boards to assess evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000660468" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Levels of Evidence for Supportive and Palliative Care Studies. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/supportive-care</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389413]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2010-01-04</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2021-07-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
