<Summary id="CDR0000700000" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Pediatric hematopoietic stem cell transplant involves the infusion of blood stem cells into a patient to reconstitute the blood system. Get detailed information about autologous and allogeneic transplant, HLA matching, preparative regimens, and complications in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant">Pediatric Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant  and Cellular Therapy for Cancer(PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000579886">hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_441">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of hematopoietic  stem cell transplant  and cellular therapy in treating pediatric cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_442">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>hematopoietic stem cell transplant</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Pediatric Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant and Cellular Therapy for Cancer (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Pediatric HSCT and Cellular Therapy for Cancer (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Pediatric HSCT and Cellular Therapy for Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information About Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT)</Title><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>Rationale for HSCT</Title><Para id="_8">Blood and marrow transplant, or HSCT, is a procedure that involves infusion of hematopoietic stem cells (along with hematopoietic progenitor cells) to reconstitute the hematopoietic system of a patient.  The infusion of hematopoietic stem cells generally follows a preparative regimen consisting of agents designed to do the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Create marrow space.</ListItem><ListItem>Suppress the patient's immune system to prevent rejection.</ListItem><ListItem>Eradicate malignant cells in patients with cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_10">HSCT is currently used in the:</Para><ItemizedList id="_646" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Treatment of malignancies,</ListItem><ListItem>Replacement or modulation of an absent or poorly functioning hematopoietic or immune system, or for the</ListItem><ListItem>Treatment of certain genetic diseases. In these cases, insufficient expression of the affected gene product can be partially or completely overcome by circulating hematopoietic stem cells transplanted from a donor with normal gene expression.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_655">This summary focuses on the use of HSCT in the treatment of childhood malignancies.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_154"><Title>Autologous Versus Allogeneic HSCT</Title><Para id="_369">The two major HSCT approaches  currently in use are the following:   </Para><ItemizedList id="_370" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Autologous (using the patient's own hematopoietic stem cells).</ListItem><ListItem>Allogeneic (using related- or unrelated-donor hematopoietic stem cells).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_155">An autologous transplant treats cancer by exposing patients to high-dose therapy with the intent of overcoming chemotherapy resistance in tumor cells, followed by infusion of the patient’s previously stored hematopoietic stem cells. The transplant can be performed in a single procedure or tandem sequential procedures.</Para><Para id="_162">Allogeneic transplant approaches to cancer treatment also may involve high-dose therapy, but because of immunologic differences between the donor and recipient, an additional graft-versus-tumor or graft-versus-leukemia treatment effect can occur. Although autologous approaches are associated with less short-term mortality, many malignancies are resistant to even high doses of chemotherapy and/or involve the bone marrow. Therefore, patients may require allogeneic approaches for optimal outcomes. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_157"><Title>Determining When HSCT Is Indicated: Comparison of HSCT and Chemotherapy Outcomes</Title><Para id="_158">Because the outcomes using chemotherapy and HSCT treatments have been changing over time, these approaches should be compared regularly to continually redefine optimal therapy for a given patient.  For some diseases, randomized trials or intent-to-treat trials using an HLA-matched sibling donor have established the benefit of HSCT by direct comparison.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> However, for very high-risk patients, such as those with early relapse of acute lymphoblastic leukemia,  randomized trials have not been feasible because of investigator bias.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  </Para><Para id="_372">In general, HSCT typically benefits only children at high risk of relapse with standard chemotherapy approaches. Accordingly, treatment schemas that accurately identify these high-risk patients and offer HSCT if appropriate allogeneic donors are available are the preferred approach for many diseases.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Less well-established, higher-risk approaches to HSCT, such as haploidentical transplant, are sometimes reserved for only the very highest-risk patients. However, these higher-risk approaches are becoming safer and more efficacious and are increasingly used interchangeably with fully matched allogeneic approaches.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000805701#_54" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/allogeneic">Haploidentical HSCT</SummaryRef> section in Pediatric Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant.</Para><Para id="_159">When comparisons of similar patients treated with HSCT or chemotherapy are made in the setting where randomized or intent-to-treat studies are not feasible, the following issues should be considered:    </Para><OrderedList id="_160" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><Strong>Remission/disease status: </Strong>Comparisons of HSCT and chemotherapy should include only patients who obtain remission, preferably after similar approaches to salvage therapy, because patients who fail to obtain remission have poor outcomes with any therapy.<Reference refidx="10"/><Para id="_525">  To account for time-to-transplant bias, the chemotherapy comparator arm should include only patients who maintained remission until the median time to HSCT.  The HSCT comparator arm should also include only patients who achieved the initial remission mentioned above and maintained that remission until the time of HSCT.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_526">High-risk and intermediate-risk patient groups should not be combined because benefit or lack of benefit of HSCT in the high-risk group can be masked by different levels of benefit in the intermediate-risk group.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Therapy approaches used for comparison: </Strong>Comparisons should be made with the best or most used chemotherapy/immunotherapy or HSCT approaches used during the time frame under study.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>HSCT approach: </Strong>HSCT approaches that are very high risk or have documented lower rates of survival should not be combined for analysis with standard-risk HSCT approaches.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Criteria for relapse: </Strong>Risk factors for relapse should be carefully defined, and analysis should be based on the most current knowledge of risk.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Selection bias:</Strong>  Attempts should be made to understand and eliminate or correct for selection bias.  Examples include the following:  <ItemizedList id="_44" Style="dash"><ListItem><Strong>Higher-risk</Strong> patients preferentially undergoing HSCT (i.e., patients who take several rounds to achieve remission or have disease relapse after obtaining remission and go back into a subsequent remission before HSCT).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Sicker</Strong> patients deferred from HSCT because of comorbidities.</ListItem><ListItem>Related to the time-to-transplant bias noted above, patients who undergo HSCT after relapse or recurrence are a subset of all patients with a disease recurrence and will be selected from those who are able to obtain a remission and remain healthy enough to undergo HSCT.</ListItem><ListItem>Patient or parent refusal.</ListItem><ListItem>Lack of or inability to obtain insurance approval for HSCT.</ListItem><ListItem>Lack of access to HSCT because of distance or inability to travel.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_161">Physician bias, for or against HSCT, is difficult to control for or detect.  The effects of access to HSCT and therapeutic bias on outcomes of pediatric malignancies for which HSCT may be indicated have been poorly studied.</Para><Para id="_656">For more information about pediatric HSCT, see the following summaries:</Para><OrderedList id="_657" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000805686" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/autologous">Pediatric Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000805701" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/allogeneic">Pediatric Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000805706" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/car-t-cell-therapy">Pediatric Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T-Cell Therapy</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000805704" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/gvhd">Complications, Graft-Versus-Host Disease, and Late Effects after Pediatric Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10519894" MedlineID="99435540">Matthay KK, Villablanca JG, Seeger RC, et al.: Treatment of high-risk neuroblastoma with intensive chemotherapy, radiotherapy, autologous bone marrow transplantation, and 13-cis-retinoic acid. Children's Cancer Group. N Engl J Med 341 (16): 1165-73, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11133742" MedlineID="20575387">Woods WG, Neudorf S, Gold S, et al.: A comparison of allogeneic bone marrow transplantation, autologous bone marrow transplantation, and aggressive chemotherapy in children with acute myeloid leukemia in remission. Blood 97 (1): 56-62, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10759711" MedlineID="20223068">Lawson SE, Harrison G, Richards S, et al.: The UK experience in treating relapsed childhood acute lymphoblastic leukaemia: a report on the medical research council UKALLR1 study. Br J Haematol 108 (3): 531-43, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="16717292">Gaynon PS, Harris RE, Altman AJ, et al.: Bone marrow transplantation versus prolonged intensive chemotherapy for children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia and an initial bone marrow relapse within 12 months of the completion of primary therapy: Children's Oncology Group study CCG-1941. J Clin Oncol 24 (19): 3150-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="30806963">Merli P, Algeri M, Del Bufalo F, et al.: Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation in Pediatric Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia. Curr Hematol Malig Rep 14 (2): 94-105, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24869942">Bertaina A, Merli P, Rutella S, et al.: HLA-haploidentical stem cell transplantation after removal of αβ+ T and B cells in children with nonmalignant disorders. Blood 124 (5): 822-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="17442774">Handgretinger R, Chen X, Pfeiffer M, et al.: Feasibility and outcome of reduced-intensity conditioning in haploidentical transplantation. Ann N Y Acad Sci 1106: 279-89, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="16883312">Huang XJ, Liu DH, Liu KY, et al.: Haploidentical hematopoietic stem cell transplantation without in vitro T-cell depletion for the treatment of hematological malignancies. Bone Marrow Transplant 38 (4): 291-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="20066512">Luznik L, Fuchs EJ: High-dose, post-transplantation cyclophosphamide to promote graft-host tolerance after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Immunol Res 47 (1-3): 65-77, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="21195303">Pulsipher MA, Peters C, Pui CH: High-risk pediatric acute lymphoblastic leukemia: to transplant or not to transplant? Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 17 (1 Suppl): S137-48, 2011.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TopTrialSearch_sid_2"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TopTrialSearch_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (06/13/2024)</Title><Para id="_96">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_659">This summary was comprehensively reviewed.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000700000#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of hematopoietic  stem cell transplant  and cellular therapy in treating pediatric cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Pediatric Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant and Cellular Therapy for Cancer are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Thomas G. Gross, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Michael A. Pulsipher, MD (Huntsman Cancer Institute at University of Utah)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Pediatric Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant and Cellular Therapy for Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant">https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389503]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2012-02-15</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-06-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
