<Summary id="CDR0000719565"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements summary discusses the use of nutrition and dietary supplements for preventing or treating prostate cancer. Learn more about the use of complementary therapies for prostate cancer in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038782">prostate cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SecondaryTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000372898">CAM nutritional therapy</TermRef></SecondaryTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_470">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of nutrition and dietary supplements for reducing the risk of developing prostate cancer or for treating prostate cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_471">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>CAM nutritional therapy</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>prostate cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_57"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Complementary and alternative medicine</GlossaryTermRef> (CAM) is a form of treatment  used in addition to (complementary) or instead of (alternative) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatments</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_34">In the United States, about 1 out of every 8 men  will be diagnosed with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. It is the second most common <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> in men in the United States. CAM use among men with prostate cancer is common. Studies of why men with prostate cancer decide to use CAM show that their choice is based on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medical history</GlossaryTermRef>,  beliefs about the safety and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of CAM compared to standard treatments, and a need to feel in control of their treatment.</Para><Para id="_702">CAM treatments used  by men with prostate cancer include certain foods, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbs</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_705">Different types of studies have been done to study the use of CAM in prostate cancer. These study types include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_706" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Combined study: A combined study analyzes data from more than one study done on the same topic, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef> to a dietary supplement, risk of getting cancer, or treatment of cancer. The results of a combined study are usually stronger than the results of any study by itself. A combined study is also called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meta-analysis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Population study</GlossaryTermRef>: A population study looks at a group of people who are part of the general population and share a common characteristic, such as age, sex, or health <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>. This group of people may be studied for different reasons, such as their response to a dietary supplement or risk of getting cancer. A population study is also called an epidemiologic study.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>: A clinical trial looks at how well new medical approaches work in people. These studies may test new methods of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef>, diagnosis, or treatment of cancer. Clinical trials with a small number of people or when the treatment is not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322881" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomly</GlossaryTermRef> assigned are not included in this summary. See the clinical trial sections of the health professional version of <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements</SummaryRef> for information on clinical trials done using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef> or supplements.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef>: In laboratory studies, a substance is tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> to find out if it has any anticancer effects. In animal studies, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef>, procedure, or treatment is tested in mice or other animals to see if it is safe and effective. Laboratory and animal studies are done before a substance is tested in people.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_707">CAM treatments have been studied to see if their use lowers the risk of prostate cancer, kills prostate cancer cells, or lowers the risk that cancer will come back after treatment. Most of these studies used <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> (PSA) levels to find out whether the treatment worked. This is a weaker measure of how well the treatment works than direct measures, such as fewer new cases of prostate cancer, or smaller tumor size or lower rate of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrence</GlossaryTermRef> after treatment for prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_55">This  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> summary has sections about the use of specific foods and dietary supplements to prevent or treat prostate cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_234" Style="bullet"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_446" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Calcium</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_175" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Green Tea</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_3" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Lycopene</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_61" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Modified Citrus Pectin</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_79" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Pomegranate</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_250" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Selenium</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_95" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Soy</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_295" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Vitamin D</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_269" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Vitamin E</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_447" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Combination Therapies</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_347" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Other Prostate Health Supplements</SummaryRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_672">Each section includes the following information for each food or dietary supplement:</Para><ItemizedList id="_36" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>How it is given or taken.</ListItem> <ListItem>Results of studies done in people.</ListItem><ListItem>Side effects or risks.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) information.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_56"><Title>Overview of CAM Use in Prostate Cancer</Title><Para id="_37">Studies of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044384" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CAM</GlossaryTermRef> use to treat  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> have shown the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_42" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Men who have prostate cancer are more likely to take <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef> and eat certain foods than men who do not have prostate cancer.</ListItem>
     <ListItem>Men who have prostate cancer and who have healthy eating habits (for example, eating lots of fish rich in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045809" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">omega-3 fatty acids</GlossaryTermRef> and vegetables) are more likely to take dietary supplements.</ListItem><ListItem>Men who have prostate cancer use CAM treatments to help boost the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>, improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>,  and lower the risk of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>  coming back, but only half of them tell their doctors about their use of CAM.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_43">Studies of CAM use  to lower prostate cancer risk or to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> it from coming back have shown the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_44" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>A study of men with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of prostate cancer found that over half used <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef> or other dietary supplements for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef> health or to prevent cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>A study of men at a  prostate cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> clinic found that over half took multivitamins and some took <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbal supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A study of prostate cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> found that up to one-third took vitamins or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_691">For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062853" url="/types/prostate/patient/prostate-prevention-pdq">Prostate Cancer Prevention</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_446"><Title>Calcium: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_409"><QandAEntry id="_410"><Question>What is calcium?</Question><Answer><Para id="_455"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045632" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Calcium</GlossaryTermRef> is a common <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mineral</GlossaryTermRef> in the body that helps <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef>, muscles, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef> send signals from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> to cell and release <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef>. The body stores most calcium in bones and teeth. </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_411"><Question>How is calcium given or taken?</Question><Answer><Para id="_437">The main sources of calcium are in foods and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>. About one-third of dietary calcium  comes from milk and milk products like cheese  and yogurt. Vegetable sources  include bok choy, kale, and broccoli. Calcium is sometimes added to foods and drinks, such as fruit juices, tofu, and cereals. </Para><Para id="_456">Most research about calcium and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> risk has studied calcium in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef>, not calcium in supplements. </Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_412"><Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using calcium?</Question><Answer><Para id="_674">For information on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> done using calcium, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_513" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_413"><Question>Have any  studies of calcium been done in people?</Question><Answer><Para id="_419">Studies  of people in many parts of the world have been done to find out if there is a link between dairy products, calcium supplements, and prostate cancer risk. The results of these studies have been mixed. Some studies have shown that calcium has an effect on the overall risk of developing prostate cancer or on stopping <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> from coming back after treatment, and others have not. </Para><Para id="_744">For information on studies in people taking calcium supplements, dairy products, or non-dairy calcium products, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_436" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Human Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_415"><Question>Is calcium approved by the FDA 
         for use as a cancer treatment in the United States?</Question><Answer><Para id="_457">The FDA has not approved the use of  calcium as a treatment for cancer.</Para><Para id="_458">The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of calcium supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry></QandASet><SummarySection id="_416"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_416_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_175"><Title>Green Tea: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_176">
   <QandAEntry id="_177">
    <Question>What is green tea?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_227"> Tea comes from the <ScientificName>Camellia sinensis</ScientificName> plant. The way tea leaves are processed determines whether green tea, black tea, or oolong tea is made. Green tea is made by steaming and drying the leaves.</Para><Para id="_246">The health benefits studied in green tea are thought to be from  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef> called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256573" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyphenols</GlossaryTermRef>. Polyphenols are a group of plant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemicals</GlossaryTermRef> that include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catechins</GlossaryTermRef>         (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidants</GlossaryTermRef> that help protect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> from damage). Catechins make up most of the polyphenols in green tea and vary based on the source of the tea leaves and how they are processed. This makes it hard to identify most of the chemical factors linked to the health benefits of green tea. </Para> <Para id="_226">Some studies suggest that green tea may protect against <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748138" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessel</GlossaryTermRef> disease.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   <QandAEntry id="_180">
    <Question>How is green tea  given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_181">People usually drink green tea or take it as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplement</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para>
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_182">
    <Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using green tea?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_676">For information on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> done using green tea, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_185" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_183">
    <Question>Have any  studies of green tea been done in people?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_213"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Population studies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> have been done to find out if green tea  can <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> or treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Results have been mixed. Some studies have shown a short-term decrease in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> (PSA) level or a lower risk of having prostate cancer, and others have not. There is not enough evidence to know whether green tea can prevent or treat prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_745">Overall, population studies suggest that green tea may help protect against prostate cancer in Asian populations. Prostate cancer deaths in Asia are among the lowest in the world. Other populations have not been studied.</Para><Para id="_746">For information on studies in people drinking green tea or taking green tea supplements, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_199" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Human Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para> </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_184">
    <Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from green tea?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_479">A trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">green tea extract</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solid tumors</GlossaryTermRef> reported that drinking 7 to 8 Japanese-style cups (equal to 3 ½ to 4 US cups) of tea 3 times a day for 6 months was a safe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_703">Clinical trials have reported on the safety of long-term use of green tea to prevent prostate cancer. In a United States trial,  men at risk of prostate cancer were given green tea extract or a placebo for 1 year. There were more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> in the   group who received the green tea extract than in the group who received the placebo.</Para><Para id="_480">In safety studies of green tea for men with prostate cancer, short-term green tea use for up to 90 days was well tolerated. One study found  that the most reported side effects of green tea were headache, chest pain, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>. These were mild except for two reports of trouble breathing and severe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anorexia</GlossaryTermRef>. In men with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced</GlossaryTermRef> prostate cancer, side effects of green tea included <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">insomnia</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">confusion</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>. In rare cases, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> problems have occurred.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_185">
    <Question>Is green tea approved by the FDA 
         for use as a cancer treatment in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_186">The FDA has not approved the use of  green tea as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or any other medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_694">The FDA Division of Drug Oncology Products recommends that green tea extract be taken with food by participants in clinical trials and that frequent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390293" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver function tests</GlossaryTermRef>   be considered during treatment, especially in the first few months of starting a clinical trial.</Para>
    <Para id="_187">Green tea is available in the United States in food products and dietary supplements. The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of green tea supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet><SummarySection id="_236"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_236_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Lycopene: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_4">
   <QandAEntry id="_5">
    <Question>What is lycopene?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_14"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044909" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lycopene</GlossaryTermRef> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046132" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carotenoid</GlossaryTermRef> (a natural red color made by plants). It mixes with  or dissolves in fats.          Lycopene protects plants from light-related stress and helps them use  the energy of the sun to make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef>. Lycopene is found in  fruits and vegetables like tomatoes, apricots, guavas, and watermelons.</Para><Para id="_58">The main source of lycopene in the United States is tomato-based products. Lycopene is easier for the body to use when it is eaten in processed tomato products like tomato paste and tomato puree than in raw tomatoes. </Para><Para id="_671"> Lycopene has been studied for its role in  the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748138" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessel</GlossaryTermRef> disease. </Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   <QandAEntry id="_6">
    <Question>How is lycopene given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_52">
     
    Lycopene may be eaten in food or taken in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para>  </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_7">
    <Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using lycopene?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_678">For information on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> done using lycopene, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_9" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_8">
    <Question>Have any  studies of lycopene been done in people?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_20"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Population studies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> have been done to find out if lycopene can prevent or treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Some studies have shown a lower risk of prostate cancer or a decrease in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> (PSA) level, and others have not. These mixed results may be explained by differences within the studies, such as the sources and types of lycopene studied, the diets of the participants, and differences in participants' prostate cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetics</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">obesity</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439432" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tobacco</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef> use). Also, most research has studied the effects of  lycopene on  the risk of all prostate cancers, and has not  studied effects of lycopene on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">low-grade</GlossaryTermRef> prostate cancer compared with  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386205" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-grade</GlossaryTermRef> prostate cancer. There is not enough evidence to know whether lycopene can prevent or treat prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_748">For information on studies in people taking lycopene supplements or foods containing lycopene, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_12" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Human Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para><Para id="_749">For information on trials of combination therapies that include lycopene, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719565#_447" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">Combination Therapies</SummaryRef> section of this summary.</Para>
     
     </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_9">
    <Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from lycopene?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_54">Lycopene has been given in many clinical trials with  very few <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>. Side effects, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bloating</GlossaryTermRef>, increased gas, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> irritation have been reported. In one study, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> went away when lycopene was taken with meals. </Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_10">
    <Question>Is lycopene approved by the FDA 
         for use to prevent or treat cancer in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_49">The FDA has not approved the use of lycopene as a treatment for cancer or any other medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_50">Lycopene is available in the United States in food products and dietary supplements. The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of lycopene supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet><SummarySection id="_149"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_149_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><Title>Modified Citrus Pectin: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_62">
   <QandAEntry id="_63">
    <Question>What is modified citrus pectin?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_145">Pectin is a substance made of small sugar <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef> that are linked together. Pectin is found in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> wall of most plants and has gel-like qualities that are useful in making  many types of  food and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_115">Citrus pectin is found in the peel and pulp of citrus fruits such as oranges, grapefruit, lemons, and limes.  Citrus pectin can be modified (changed) during manufacturing so that it can be dissolved in water and absorbed by the body. This changed citrus pectin is called modified citrus pectin (MCP).</Para>
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   <QandAEntry id="_66">
    <Question>How is MCP given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_135">
     
    MCP may be taken by mouth in powder or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsule</GlossaryTermRef> form.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_68">
    <Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using MCP?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_680">For information on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> done using MCP, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_65" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para>
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_72">
    <Question>Have any  studies
         of MCP been done in people?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_146">Few studies have been done in   men with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. There is not enough evidence to know whether MCP has any effect on prostate cancer.</Para>
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_75">
    <Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from MCP?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_76"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that have been reported include itching, upset <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cramps</GlossaryTermRef>, increased gas, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para>
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_77">
    <Question>Is MCP approved by the FDA 
         for use to prevent or treat  cancer in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_117">The FDA has not approved the use of MCP as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or any other medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_118">MCP is available in the United States in food products and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>. The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of MCP supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet><SummarySection id="_158"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_158_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><Title>Pomegranate: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_80">
   <QandAEntry id="_81">
    <Question>What is pomegranate?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_82">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pomegranate</GlossaryTermRef> is a fruit grown in Asia and in the Mediterranean, East Indies, Africa, and the United States. Pomegranate has been used as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef> for hundreds of years.</Para><Para id="_109">The pomegranate is made up of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_83" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The peel, which  makes up half the fruit and contains <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256573" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyphenols</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The seeds.</ListItem><ListItem>The aril (the layer between the peel and the seeds), which contains phenolics and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">flavonoids</GlossaryTermRef> including anthocyanins, which give the pomegranate fruit and juice a red color.</ListItem></ItemizedList></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   
   <QandAEntry id="_84">
    <Question>How is pomegranate given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_136">
     
    Pomegranate fruit and juice may be taken as food, drink, or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplement</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_86">
    <Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using pomegranate?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_682"> For information on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> done using pomegranate, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_85" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_89">
    <Question>Have any   studies of pomegranate been done in people?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_486">In a 2015 study, 183 men with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322881" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomly</GlossaryTermRef> assigned to receive either pomegranate juice, pomegranate extract, or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef>. The study found no difference in how fast the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> (PSA) level rose between the 3 groups. There is not enough evidence to know whether pomegranate can <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> or treat prostate cancer.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_91">
    <Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from pomegranate?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_92">No serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> have been reported from the use of pomegranate. </Para>
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_93">
    <Question>Is pomegranate approved by the FDA 
         for use to prevent or treat cancer  in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_119">The FDA has not approved the use of pomegranate as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or any other medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para>
     
    <Para id="_120">Pomegranate is available in the United States in food products and dietary supplements. The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of pomegranate supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet><SummarySection id="_152"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_152_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_250"><Title>Selenium: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_251">
   <QandAEntry id="_252">
    <Question>What is selenium?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_253"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Selenium</GlossaryTermRef> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mineral</GlossaryTermRef> that is essential to people in tiny amounts. Selenium is needed for many body functions, including reproduction and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468803" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunity</GlossaryTermRef>. Food sources of selenium include meat, vegetables, and nuts. The amount of selenium found in the food depends on the  amount of selenium in the soil where the food grows. Selenium is stored  in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid gland</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pituitary gland</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para>
    <Para id="_310">Selenium may play a role in many diseases, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Results of the large <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef>-sponsored Selenium and Vitamin E Cancer Prevention Trial (SELECT) suggest that men with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> should not take selenium supplements.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   
   <QandAEntry id="_259">
    <Question>How is selenium given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_260">
     
    Selenium may be eaten in food or taken in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary  supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.  </Para>
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_261">
    <Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using selenium?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_684"> For information on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> done using selenium, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_294" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_263">
    <Question>Have any  studies of selenium been done in people?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_318"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Population studies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> have been done to find out if selenium can <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> or treat prostate cancer. The results of these studies have been mixed, but the results of a large, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> showed selenium had no effect on preventing prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_750">For information on studies in people taking selenium, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_307" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Human Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_265">
    <Question>Have any side effects or risks of selenium supplements been reported?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_311">Selenium supplements have been well tolerated in many clinical trials. But, in the Selenium and Vitamin E Cancer Prevention Trial, the use of selenium supplements was linked with a slight  increase in  the rate of diabetes mellitus. </Para><Para id="_713">In several large studies, men with high selenium levels were at greater risk of being diagnosed with aggressive prostate cancer or dying from prostate cancer. </Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_267">
    <Question>Is selenium approved by the FDA 
         for use as a cancer treatment in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_312">The FDA has not approved the use of selenium supplements for the treatment  or prevention of cancer.</Para>
     
    <Para id="_313">Selenium is available in the United States in food products and dietary supplements. The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of selenium supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet><SummarySection id="_400"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_400_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_95"><Title>Soy: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_96">
   <QandAEntry id="_97">
    <Question>What is soy?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_121">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415913" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soybean</GlossaryTermRef> plant has been grown in Asia for food for hundreds of years. Soybeans are used to make soy milk, miso, tofu, soy flour, oil, and other food products. </Para><Para id="_122">Soy foods contain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phytochemicals</GlossaryTermRef> that may have health benefits.   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Isoflavones</GlossaryTermRef> are the most widely    studied <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef> in soy. Major isoflavones in the soybean include  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046107" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genistein</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">daidzein</GlossaryTermRef>, and glycitein.    </Para><Para id="_123">Isoflavones are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330175" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phytoestrogens</GlossaryTermRef>     (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046076" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estrogen</GlossaryTermRef>-like substances found in plants) that attach to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046409" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estrogen receptors</GlossaryTermRef> found in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>. Genistein may affect some processes inside prostate cancer cells that are involved in the growth and spread of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.  </Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   <QandAEntry id="_99">
    <Question>How is soy  given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_137">
     
    Soy may be eaten in food or taken in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_101">
    <Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using soy?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_686"> For information on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> done using soy, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_110" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_103">
    <Question>Have any  studies of soy  been done in people?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_124"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Population studies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> have been done to find out if soy  can <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> or treat prostate cancer. The results of these studies have been mixed. Some studies have shown a lower risk of prostate cancer or a change in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> (PSA) level, and others have not. The results may be mixed because of the small number of men who participated in the studies and the different types and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of soy products given.</Para><Para id="_714">Small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> have been done to study the effects of isoflavones or soy on prostate cancer. The results of these studies have been mixed. See <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_704" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Table 3</SummaryRef>,  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_705" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Table 4</SummaryRef>, and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_706" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Table 5</SummaryRef>  of the health professional version of <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements</SummaryRef> for information on randomized, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef> clinical trials of isoflavones and soy.</Para><Para id="_751">For more information on studies in people taking soy supplements, soy products, or soy found in foods, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_120" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Human Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_105">
    <Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from soy?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_143">Soy  products and isoflavones have caused very few <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> in people with prostate cancer who participated in clinical trials.  The most commonly reported side effects were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_107">
    <Question>Is soy  approved by the FDA 
         for use to prevent or treat cancer in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_130">The FDA has not approved the use of soy as a treatment for cancer or any other medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para>
     
    <Para id="_131">Soy is available in the United States in food products and dietary supplements. The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of soy supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet><SummarySection id="_155"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_155_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_295"><Title>Vitamin D: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_296">
   <QandAEntry id="_297">
    <Question>What is vitamin D?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_305"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000427253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin D</GlossaryTermRef> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fat-soluble vitamin</GlossaryTermRef> found in  fatty fish, fish liver oil, and eggs. Vitamin D may also be added to dairy products. Vitamin D: </Para><ItemizedList id="_370" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Helps absorb <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045632" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">calcium</GlossaryTermRef> from food in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Improves muscle strength and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> function.</ListItem><ListItem>Lowers  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammation</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Maintains levels of calcium and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476349" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phosphate</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Helps with bone growth and protects against <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">osteoporosis</GlossaryTermRef> in adults.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_371">A person's vitamin D level is checked by measuring the amount of 25-hydroxyvitamin D in the blood.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   
   <QandAEntry id="_300">
    <Question>How is vitamin D given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_332">Vitamin D is made by the body when exposed to sunlight.
     
    Vitamin D may also be eaten in food or taken in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary  supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_301">
    <Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using vitamin D?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_688"> For information on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> done using vitamin D, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_363" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_302">
    <Question>Have any  studies of vitamin D been done in people?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_328"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Population studies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> have been done to study the effects of vitamin D on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The results of these studies have been mixed. Some studies have shown a link between Vitamin D levels and prostate cancer, and others have not. There is not enough evidence to know whether vitamin D can <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_739">Studies often look at specific factors that affect a person's vitamin D levels to see how those factors influence prostate cancer risk. Factors that have been studied include:</Para>
     
    <ItemizedList id="_752" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Low sun exposure.</ListItem><ListItem>Levels of vitamin D in the diet and blood.</ListItem><ListItem>Genetic changes.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_753">Some genetic changes in tumor features that interact with vitamin D might affect the growth and spread of prostate cancer. One of those features is a molecule called a vitamin D receptor. Studies suggest that changes in this receptor could influence a person's risk of prostate cancer or increase the chance that the cancer will spread. More research is needed to confirm that vitamin D receptors play a role in prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_754">For information on studies in people taking vitamin D supplements, vitamin D products, or vitamin D in food, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_864" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Human Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   <QandAEntry id="_472"><Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from vitamin D? </Question><Answer><Para id="_473">Vitamin D can cause serious health problems when taken at high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> over many years. Taking high levels of Vitamin D can cause too much calcium to be absorbed in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestines</GlossaryTermRef>, leading to rapid increases in blood calcium levels. This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypercalcemia</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_476">In a  group of 26 studies,  Vitamin D was reviewed for safety, how well it works,  and   whether it <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interacts</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> used to treat prostate cancer and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>.  The reviewers found the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> and interactions with other drugs to be low.</Para><Para id="_477"> Several studies looked at the safety of high-dose vitamin D and how well it  works with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045382" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">docetaxel</GlossaryTermRef>) to treat men with prostate cancer that did not respond to hormone therapy. The side effects that occurred after treatment with high-dose vitamin D and docetaxel were the same as the side effects noted after treatment with docetaxel alone. </Para> </Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_304">
    <Question>Is vitamin D approved by the FDA 
         for use as a cancer treatment in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_379">The FDA has not approved the use of vitamin D as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_380">Vitamin D is available in the United States in food products and dietary supplements. The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of vitamin D supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet><SummarySection id="_403"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_403_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_269"><Title>Vitamin E: Questions and Answers</Title><QandASet id="_270">
   <QandAEntry id="_271">
    <Question>What is vitamin E?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_272"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin E</GlossaryTermRef> is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef> that may help protect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> from damage. Vitamin E also affects how signals are sent within cells and how the cell makes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046568" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RNA</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef>.     </Para><Para id="_390">There are eight forms of  vitamin E: four tocopherols (alpha-, beta-, gamma-, and sigma-) and four tocotrienols (alpha-, beta-, gamma-, and sigma-). <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691423" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Alpha-tocopherol</GlossaryTermRef>, the form of vitamin E used in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>, is found in greater amounts in the body and is the  most active form of vitamin E. Most vitamin E in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef> comes from gamma-tocopherol. Food sources of vitamin E include   vegetable oils, nuts, and egg yolks.</Para>
    <Para id="_273"> Vitamin E may protect against <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic diseases</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748138" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessel</GlossaryTermRef> disease. </Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   
   <QandAEntry id="_276">
    <Question>How is vitamin E  given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer>
     <Para id="_277">
     
    Vitamin E may be eaten in food or taken in dietary  supplements.</Para>
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   <QandAEntry id="_284">
    <Question>Have any  studies of vitamin E been done in people?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_290"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Population studies</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> have been done to find out if vitamin E  may <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The results of these studies have been mixed. Some studies have shown no change in the overall risk of prostate cancer, and others have shown an increased risk of prostate cancer. There is not enough evidence to know whether vitamin E affects the risk of prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_755">For information on studies in people taking vitamin E supplements, vitamin E products, or vitamin E in food, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_336" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">Human Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_286">
    <Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from vitamin E?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_341">In the Physicians' Health Study II and the Alpha-Tocopherol, Beta Carotene Cancer Prevention Study Group, there was a higher number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">strokes</GlossaryTermRef> caused by a broken blood vessel in the brain in men who took vitamin E than in men who took a placebo.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_288">
    <Question>Is vitamin E  approved by the FDA 
         for use as a cancer treatment in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_381">The FDA has not approved the use of vitamin E  as a treatment for cancer.</Para><Para id="_382">Vitamin E is available in the United States in food products and dietary supplements. The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so all batches and brands of vitamin E supplements may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet><SummarySection id="_406"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_406_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_447"><Title>Combination Therapies</Title><SummarySection id="_448"><Title>Pomi-T (Pomegranate, Green Tea, Broccoli, and Turmeric)</Title><Para id="_466"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256573" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Polyphenols</GlossaryTermRef> are found in many plants and give some flowers, fruits, and vegetables their color. Polyphenols have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef> activity that may help protect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> from damage. </Para><Para id="_449">A food <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplement</GlossaryTermRef> that is high in polyphenols was studied in a group of men who had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> that had not spread. This supplement contained the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_467" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pomegranate</GlossaryTermRef> whole fruit powder.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Green tea extract</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Broccoli powder.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Turmeric</GlossaryTermRef> powder.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_463">One hundred and ninety-nine men were randomly assigned to receive either the food supplement or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> for 6 months. The food supplement was well tolerated. However, men  in the supplement group were more likely to have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, such as increased gas and loose bowels.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_660"><Title>Lycopene, Selenium, and Green Tea</Title><Para id="_668">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplement</GlossaryTermRef> was studied in 60 men at high risk of prostate cancer (high-grade <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044345" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostatic intraepithelial neoplasia</GlossaryTermRef>). The supplement contained the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_732" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044909" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lycopene</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Selenium</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Green tea <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catechins</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_733">The men were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322881" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomly</GlossaryTermRef> assigned to receive the supplement or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef>. Men who took the supplement for 6 months had higher rates of prostate cancer when they had a repeat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> than men who did not take the supplement. This result may be due to cancers missed at the start of the study. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_665"><Title>Lycopene and Other Therapies</Title><Para id="_669">A  study enrolled 79 men who were scheduled to have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostatectomy</GlossaryTermRef>. For 3 weeks before <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>, the men were assigned to eat or drink either: </Para><ItemizedList id="_737" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tomato products containing lycopene.</ListItem><ListItem>Tomato products plus selenium, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045809" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">omega 3-fatty acids</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soy</GlossaryTermRef>   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">isoflavones</GlossaryTermRef>, grape/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pomegranate</GlossaryTermRef> juice, and green/black tea.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diet</GlossaryTermRef> without added <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrients</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_735">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> (PSA) levels were the same for men who received added nutrients and those who did not. However, among men with intermediate-risk prostate cancer, lower PSA levels were found in those who ate the tomato products or had the highest increases in lycopene levels.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_161"><Title>Zyflamend</Title><Para id="_726">Zyflamend is a dietary supplement that contains <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> of 10 different <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbs</GlossaryTermRef>  in olive oil:</Para><ItemizedList id="_727" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Rosemary.</ListItem><ListItem>Turmeric.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ginger</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Holy basil.</ListItem><ListItem>Green tea.</ListItem><ListItem>Hu zhang (<ScientificName>Polygonum cuspidatum</ScientificName>).</ListItem><ListItem>Chinese goldthread.</ListItem><ListItem>Barberry.</ListItem><ListItem>Oregano.</ListItem><ListItem>Baikal skullcap.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_728">The herb extracts used in Zyflamend may have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anti-inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef> activity. There is not enough evidence to know whether Zyflamend can <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> or treat prostate cancer.</Para><Para id="_729">Zyflamend is taken as a dietary supplement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsule</GlossaryTermRef> form.</Para><Para id="_731">No serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> have been reported for Zyflamend. In one study, some men had mild heartburn that went away when Zyflamend was taken with food.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_347"><Title>Other Prostate Health Supplements</Title><SummarySection id="_356"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_357">African cherry (<ScientificName>pygeum africanum</ScientificName>) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000773858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta-sitosterol</GlossaryTermRef>  are two  supplements that have been studied for general <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef> health and the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046509" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign prostatic hyperplasia</GlossaryTermRef> (BPH) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.  For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_390" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">African cherry</SummaryRef> (<ScientificName>pygeum africanum</ScientificName>) and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000719335#_394" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/prostate-supplements-pdq">beta-sitosterol</SummaryRef> sections of the health professional version of Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of nutrition and dietary supplements for reducing the risk of developing prostate cancer or for treating prostate cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Prostate Cancer, Nutrition, and Dietary Supplements. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/prostate-supplements-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389501]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_2"><Title>General CAM Information</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_3">Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)—also called integrative medicine—includes a broad range of healing philosophies, approaches, and therapies. A therapy is generally called complementary when it is used in addition to conventional treatments; it is often called alternative when it is used instead of conventional treatment. (Conventional treatments are those that are widely accepted and practiced by the mainstream medical community.) Depending on how they are used, some therapies can be considered either complementary or alternative. Complementary and alternative therapies are used in an effort to prevent illness, reduce stress, prevent or reduce side effects and symptoms, or control or cure disease. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_4">Unlike conventional treatments for cancer, complementary and alternative therapies are often not covered by insurance companies. Patients should check with their insurance provider to find out about coverage for complementary and alternative therapies. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_5">Cancer patients considering complementary and alternative therapies should discuss this decision with their doctor, nurse, or pharmacist as they would any type of treatment. Some complementary and alternative therapies may affect their standard treatment or may be harmful when used with conventional treatment. </Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_6"><Title>Evaluation of CAM Therapies</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_7">It is important that the same scientific methods used to test conventional therapies are used to test CAM therapies. The National Cancer Institute  and the National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) are sponsoring a number of clinical trials (research studies) at medical centers to test CAM therapies for use in cancer. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_8">Conventional approaches to cancer treatment have generally been studied for safety and effectiveness through a scientific process that includes clinical trials with large numbers of patients. Less is known about the safety and effectiveness of complementary and alternative methods. Few CAM therapies have been tested using demanding scientific methods. A small number of CAM therapies that were thought to be purely alternative approaches are now being used in cancer treatment—not as cures, but as complementary therapies that may help patients feel better and recover faster. One example is acupuncture. According to a panel of experts at a National Institutes of Health (NIH) meeting  in November 1997, acupuncture has been found to help control nausea and vomiting caused by chemotherapy and pain related to surgery. However, some approaches, such as the use of laetrile, have been studied and found not to work and to possibly cause harm.</Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_9"><ExternalRef xref="https://cam.cancer.gov/indentifying_novel_cam_therapies/best_case_series_program.htm">The NCI Best Case Series Program</ExternalRef>   which was started  in 1991, is one way CAM approaches that are being used in practice are being studied. The program is overseen by the NCI’s Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM). Health care professionals who offer alternative cancer therapies submit their patients’ medical records and related materials to OCCAM. OCCAM carefully reviews these materials to see if any seem worth further research.</Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_QandA_2"><Title>Questions to Ask Your Health Care Provider About CAM</Title><Para id="_QandA_3">When considering complementary and alternative therapies, patients should ask their health care provider the following questions: </Para><ItemizedList id="_QandA_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>What side effects can be expected?</ListItem><ListItem>What are the risks related to this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>What benefits can be expected from this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>Do the known benefits outweigh the risks?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy affect conventional treatment?</ListItem><ListItem>Is this therapy part of a clinical trial?</ListItem><ListItem>If so, who is the sponsor of the trial?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy be covered by health insurance?</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
   
  <SummarySection id="_ToLearnMore_2"><Title>To Learn More About CAM</Title><Para id="_ToLearnMore_3"><Strong><Emphasis>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_4">The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) facilitates research and evaluation of complementary and alternative practices, and provides information about a variety of approaches to health professionals and the public.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_5" Style="simple"><ListItem>NCCIH Clearinghouse</ListItem><ListItem>Post Office Box 7923 Gaithersburg, MD 20898–7923</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-644-6226 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and hard of hearing callers): 1-866-464-3615</ListItem><ListItem>E-mail: info@nccih.nih.gov</ListItem><ListItem>Website:  <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/">https://nccih.nih.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_15"><Strong><Emphasis>CAM on PubMed</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_16">NCCIH and the NIH National Library of Medicine (NLM) jointly developed <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/research/camonpubmed">CAM on PubMed</ExternalRef>, a free and easy-to-use search tool for finding CAM-related journal citations. As a subset of the NLM's PubMed bibliographic database, CAM on PubMed features more than 230,000 references and abstracts for CAM-related articles from scientific journals. This database also provides links to the websites of over 1,800 journals, allowing users to view full-text articles. (A subscription or other fee may be required to access full-text articles.) </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_17"><Strong><Emphasis>Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_18">The NCI Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM) coordinates the activities of the NCI in the area of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM). OCCAM supports CAM cancer research and provides information about cancer-related CAM to health providers and the general public via the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/">NCI website</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_19"><Strong><Emphasis>National Cancer Institute (NCI) Cancer Information Service</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_20">U.S. residents may call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, toll free at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237) Monday through Friday from 9:00 am to 9:00 pm. A trained Cancer Information Specialist is available to answer your questions.</Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_8"><Strong><Emphasis>Food and Drug Administration </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_9">The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulates drugs and medical devices to ensure that they are safe and effective.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_10" Style="simple"><ListItem>Food and Drug Administration </ListItem><ListItem>10903 New Hampshire Avenue</ListItem><ListItem>Silver Spring, MD 20993</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-463-6332 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/">http://www.fda.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_11"><Strong><Emphasis>Federal Trade Commission </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_12">The Federal Trade Commission (FTC) enforces consumer protection laws. Publications available from the FTC include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_13" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Emphasis>Who Cares: Sources of Information About Health Care Products and Services </Emphasis></ListItem><ListItem><Emphasis>Fraudulent Health Claims: Don’t Be Fooled </Emphasis></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_14" Style="simple"><ListItem>Consumer Response Center</ListItem><ListItem>Federal Trade Commission</ListItem><ListItem>600 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW</ListItem><ListItem>Washington, DC 20580</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-877-FTC-HELP (1-877-382-4357) (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and  hard of hearing callers): 202-326-2502</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ftc.gov/">http://www.ftc.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
  <PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000719335"/><DateFirstPublished>2012-02-01</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-05-08</DateLastModified></Summary>
