<Summary id="CDR0000742114"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Intravenous vitamin C, with and without conventional cancer therapies, appeared promising in early studies and was well tolerated. However, these studies have several limitations due to lack of rigor in trial design. Get detailed information about intravenous vitamin C in cancer in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">Intravenous Vitamin C (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq">Intravenous Vitamin C (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039737">ascorbic acid</TermRef></MainTopics><SecondaryTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000372898">CAM nutritional therapy</TermRef></SecondaryTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_78">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of intravenous vitamin C in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_79">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>ascorbic acid</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>CAM nutritional therapy</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Intravenous Vitamin C (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Intravenous Vitamin C (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Intravenous Vitamin C</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_3">This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summary provides an overview of the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> (also known as ascorbate or L-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ascorbic acid</GlossaryTermRef>) as a treatment for people with cancer.  This summary includes a brief history of early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of the use of IV vitamin C; reviews of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal</GlossaryTermRef>, and human studies; and current clinical trials.</Para><Para id="_46">This summary contains the following key information:</Para><ItemizedList id="_47" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Vitamin C is an essential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrient</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000770929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">redox</GlossaryTermRef> functions at normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045837" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physiologic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentrations</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044006" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Case series</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000286105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">observational studies</GlossaryTermRef> from the 1970s of patients with cancer who received IV vitamin C seemed to indicate a clinical benefit.</ListItem><ListItem>Two early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef> trials that used oral vitamin C (10 g/d) without IV vitamin C noted no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">significant</GlossaryTermRef> differences between ascorbate-treated and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef>-treated groups for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044174" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">performance status</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survival</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Laboratory studies have reported that IV vitamin C has redox properties and decreased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell proliferation</GlossaryTermRef> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatocellular</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000695994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell lines</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>IV vitamin C has been generally well tolerated in clinical trials.</ListItem><ListItem>IV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> of vitamin C of doses over 500 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef> produces much higher <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> concentrations of ascorbate than oral administration of the same dose.</ListItem><ListItem>The use of IV vitamin C alone as ascorbate versus ascorbate formulations plus certain standard cancer therapies have been shown to be well tolerated in clinical trials.</ListItem><ListItem>Two studies that used IV vitamin C in patients with cancer  reported improved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> and decreases in cancer-related toxicities.</ListItem><ListItem>Although early observations from preclinical and clinical trials of IV vitamin C with and without conventional cancer therapies appear promising and the therapy well tolerated, these studies have several limitations due to lack of rigor in trial design.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_52">Many of the medical and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> terms used in this summary are hypertext linked (at first use in each section) to the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>, which is oriented toward nonexperts. When a linked term is clicked, a definition will appear in a separate window.</Para><Para id="_53">Reference citations in some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> cancer information summaries may include links to external websites that are operated by individuals or organizations for the purpose of marketing or advocating the use of specific treatments or products. These reference citations are included for informational purposes only. Their inclusion should not be viewed as an endorsement of the content of the websites, or of any treatment or product, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_6"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> is an essential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrient</GlossaryTermRef> that has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000770929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">redox</GlossaryTermRef> functions, is a cofactor for several <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef>, and plays an important role in the synthesis of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collagen</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/>   A severe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">deficiency</GlossaryTermRef> in vitamin C results in scurvy, which is associated with malaise, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lethargy</GlossaryTermRef>, easy bruising, and spontaneous bleeding.<Reference refidx="2"/> One of the effects of scurvy is a change in collagen structure to a thinner consistency. Normal consistency is achieved with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> of vitamin C.</Para><Para id="_7">In the mid-20th century, a study hypothesized that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may be related to changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, which may be a consequence of vitamin C deficiency.<Reference refidx="3"/> A review of evidence published in 1974 suggested that high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ascorbic acid</GlossaryTermRef> may increase host resistance and be a potential cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_8">Vitamin C is synthesized from D-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef> or D-galactose by many plants and animals. However, humans lack the enzyme L-gulonolactone oxidase required for ascorbic acid synthesis and must obtain vitamin C through food or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_129">Some companies distribute vitamin C as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>. In the United States, dietary supplements are regulated by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) as a separate category from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. Unlike drugs, dietary supplements do not require premarket evaluation and approval by the FDA unless specific disease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> or treatment claims are made. The quality and amount of ingredients in dietary supplements are also regulated by the FDA through Good Manufacturing Practices (GMPs). The FDA GMPs requires that every finished batch of dietary supplement meets each product specification for identity, purity, strength, composition, and  limits on contamination that may <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adulterate</GlossaryTermRef> dietary supplements. Because dietary supplements are not formally reviewed for manufacturing consistency every year, ingredients may vary considerably from lot to lot and there is no guarantee that ingredients claimed on product labels are present (or are present in the specified amounts). The FDA has not approved the use of high-dose vitamin C as a treatment for cancer.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="14498993">Naidu KA: Vitamin C in human health and disease is still a mystery? An overview. Nutr J 2: 7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Padayatty S, Espey MG, Levine M: Vitamin C. In: Coates PM, Betz JM, Blackman MR, et al., eds.: Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2nd ed. Informa Healthcare, 2010, pp 821-31.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="13638066">McCORMICK WJ: Cancer: a collagen disease, secondary to a nutritional deficiency. Arch Pediatr 76 (4): 166-71, 1959.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="4609626">Cameron E, Pauling L: The orthomolecular treatment of cancer. I. The role of ascorbic acid in host resistance. Chem Biol Interact 9 (4): 273-83, 1974.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>History</Title><Para id="_10">The earliest experience of using both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> treatment was by a Scottish <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044306" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgeon</GlossaryTermRef>, Ewan Cameron, and his colleague, Allan Campbell, in the 1970s.<Reference refidx="1"/> This work led to a collaboration between Cameron and the Nobel Prize–winning chemist Linus Pauling, further promoting the potential of vitamin C <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> in cancer management.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  As a result, two <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of oral vitamin C were conducted in the late 1970s and early 1980s.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> These two trials did not use IV vitamin C. </Para><Para id="_11">For more information about these early studies, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742114#_16" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">Human Studies</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_12"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pharmacokinetic</GlossaryTermRef> studies later revealed substantial differences in the maximum achieved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentrations</GlossaryTermRef> of vitamin C based on the route of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef>. When vitamin C is taken orally, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> concentrations of the vitamin are tightly controlled, with a peak achievable concentration less than 300 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">µM</GlossaryTermRef>. However, this tight control is bypassed with IV administration of the vitamin, resulting in very high levels of vitamin C plasma concentration (i.e., levels up to 20 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000659791" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mM</GlossaryTermRef>).<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  Further research suggests that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacological</GlossaryTermRef> concentrations of ascorbate, such as those achieved with IV administration, may result in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> death in many <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000695994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer cell lines</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_13">Health care <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">practitioners</GlossaryTermRef> attending <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary and alternative medicine</GlossaryTermRef> conferences in 2006 and 2008 were surveyed about usage of high-dose IV vitamin C in patients. Of the 199 total respondents, 172 had administered vitamin C to patients. In general, IV vitamin C was commonly used to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infections</GlossaryTermRef>,  cancer, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="4430016">Cameron E, Campbell A: The orthomolecular treatment of cancer. II. Clinical trial of high-dose ascorbic acid supplements in advanced human cancer. Chem Biol Interact 9 (4): 285-315, 1974.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1068480">Cameron E, Pauling L: Supplemental ascorbate in the supportive treatment of cancer: Prolongation of survival times in terminal human cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 73 (10): 3685-9, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="279931">Cameron E, Pauling L: Supplemental ascorbate in the supportive treatment of cancer: reevaluation of prolongation of survival times in terminal human cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 75 (9): 4538-42, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="384241">Creagan ET, Moertel CG, O'Fallon JR, et al.: Failure of high-dose vitamin C (ascorbic acid) therapy to benefit patients with advanced cancer. A controlled trial. N Engl J Med 301 (13): 687-90, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3880867">Moertel CG, Fleming TR, Creagan ET, et al.: High-dose vitamin C versus placebo in the treatment of patients with advanced cancer who have had no prior chemotherapy. A randomized double-blind comparison. N Engl J Med 312 (3): 137-41, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15068981">Padayatty SJ, Sun H, Wang Y, et al.: Vitamin C pharmacokinetics: implications for oral and intravenous use. Ann Intern Med 140 (7): 533-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="18544557">Hoffer LJ, Levine M, Assouline S, et al.: Phase I clinical trial of i.v. ascorbic acid in advanced malignancy. Ann Oncol 19 (11): 1969-74, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="19254759">Verrax J, Calderon PB: Pharmacologic concentrations of ascorbate are achieved by parenteral administration and exhibit antitumoral effects. Free Radic Biol Med 47 (1): 32-40, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="20628650">Padayatty SJ, Sun AY, Chen Q, et al.: Vitamin C: intravenous use by complementary and alternative medicine practitioners and adverse effects. PLoS One 5 (7): e11414, 2010.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_20"><Title><Emphasis>In Vitro</Emphasis> Studies</Title><Para id="_21">Numerous studies have demonstrated that supraphysiologic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentrations</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ascorbic acid</GlossaryTermRef> (0.1–100 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000659791" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mM)</GlossaryTermRef>   decrease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell proliferation</GlossaryTermRef> in a variety of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000695994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer cell lines</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  Specifically, decreases in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> proliferation after ascorbic acid treatment have been reported for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef>,<Reference refidx="6"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044074" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic</GlossaryTermRef>,<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatocellular</GlossaryTermRef>,<Reference refidx="9"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>,<Reference refidx="10"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef>,<Reference refidx="11"/> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="12"/> cell lines.</Para><Para id="_23">The potential mechanisms through which treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacological</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of ascorbic acid may exert its effects on cancer cells have been extensively investigated. Several studies have demonstrated that the <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> direct <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic</GlossaryTermRef> effect of ascorbic acid on various types of cancer cells is mediated through a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef> reaction that generates <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hydrogen peroxide</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/> Treating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cells with 2 mM to 3 mM of ascorbic acid resulted in downregulation of specificity protein (Sp) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef> factors, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iron</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> disruption, and Sp-regulated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> involved in cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="15"/> One study suggested that ascorbate-mediated prostate cancer cell death may occur through activation of an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561319" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">autophagy</GlossaryTermRef> pathway.<Reference refidx="6"/> Data from a 2018 study demonstrated that labile iron and hydrogen peroxide play important roles in the mechanisms of selective <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> of ascorbate and induction of oxidative <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> damage/cancer cell death.<Reference refidx="16"/> Another <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> study found that ascorbic acid killed colorectal cancer cells with <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName> or <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">mutations</GlossaryTermRef> by inhibiting the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_24">Differences in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372925" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemosensitivity</GlossaryTermRef> to ascorbate treatment in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cell lines may depend on expression of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044731" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sodium</GlossaryTermRef>-dependent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> transporter 2 (SVCT-2).<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_54">Research has suggested that pharmacological doses of ascorbic acid enhance the effects of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_113" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046018" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Arsenic trioxide</GlossaryTermRef> on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445074" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovarian cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cells.<Reference refidx="19"/> </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508951" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Gemcitabine</GlossaryTermRef> on pancreatic cancer cells.<Reference refidx="8"/> </ListItem><ListItem>A combination treatment of  gemcitabine and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epigallocatechin-3-gallate</GlossaryTermRef> (EGCG) on mesothelioma cells.<Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_25">Findings from one study reported in 2012 suggested that high-dose ascorbate increases radiosensitivity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glioblastoma multiforme</GlossaryTermRef> cells, resulting in more cell death than from radiation alone.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_26">However, not all studies combining vitamin C with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> have shown improved outcomes.  Treating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> cells with dehydroascorbic acid (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000654996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxidized</GlossaryTermRef> form of vitamin C that increases levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044047" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intracellular</GlossaryTermRef> ascorbic acid) reduced the cytotoxic effects  of various <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044816" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antineoplastic</GlossaryTermRef> agents tested, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef> (relative reductions in cytotoxicity ranged from 30% to 70%).<Reference refidx="22"/> In another study, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045793" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multiple myeloma</GlossaryTermRef> cells were treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bortezomib</GlossaryTermRef> and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> obtained from healthy volunteers who had taken <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> vitamin C <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplements</GlossaryTermRef>. Cells treated with a combination of bortezomib and volunteers’ plasma exhibited lower cytotoxicity than did cells treated with bortezomib alone.<Reference refidx="23"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><Title>Animal Studies</Title><Para id="_82"> In 2007, researches showed that oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045797" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">N-acetylcysteine</GlossaryTermRef>  and vitamin C, both thought to act predominantly as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidants</GlossaryTermRef>, may have antitumorigenic actions <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> by decreasing levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302460" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypoxia</GlossaryTermRef>-inducible factor-1, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef> factor that targets <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vascular endothelial growth factor</GlossaryTermRef> and plays a role in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046529" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">angiogenesis</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para><Para id="_28">Studies have demonstrated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> growth inhibition after treatment with pharmacological ascorbate in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal models</GlossaryTermRef> with the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_114" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Pancreatic cancer.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Liver cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem> Prostate cancer.<Reference refidx="25"/> </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="26"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Mesothelioma.<Reference refidx="11"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Ovarian cancer.<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_29">The effects of parenterally <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administered</GlossaryTermRef> ascorbic acid in combination with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatments</GlossaryTermRef> on tumors have been investigated. In a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mouse model</GlossaryTermRef> of pancreatic cancer, the combination of gemcitabine (30 or 60 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kg</GlossaryTermRef> every 4 days) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046339" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraperitoneal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef>  of ascorbate (4 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">g</GlossaryTermRef>/kg daily) resulted in greater decreases in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor volume</GlossaryTermRef> and weight, compared with gemcitabine treatment alone.<Reference refidx="8"/> A study of mouse models of ovarian cancer found that ascorbate enhanced the tumor inhibitory effect of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carboplatin</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045258" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paclitaxel</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346494" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">first-line</GlossaryTermRef> chemotherapy used in ovarian cancer.<Reference refidx="27"/> One study working with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">xenograft</GlossaryTermRef> models of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-small cell lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and glioblastoma multiforme showed that the combination of chemotherapy (carboplatin for lung cancer and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045387" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">temozolomide</GlossaryTermRef> for glioblastoma), radiation therapy, and pharmacologic ascorbate (4 g/kg/d) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046339" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraperitoneal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injection</GlossaryTermRef> resulted in prolonged survival compared with  just the combination of chemotherapy and radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_103">A study explored the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of parenterally injected ascorbate with gemcitabine or radiation treatment in a mouse sarcoma xenograft model. Treatment involved intraperitoneally administered doses of ascorbate (4 g/kg) combined with gemcitabine (60 mg/kg) or radiation therapy (12 Gy in 2 fractions). Compared with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control group</GlossaryTermRef>, the combination treatments produced significantly greater inhibition of tumor growth, greater <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survival rate</GlossaryTermRef>, and no increase in toxicity, suggesting cancer cell selective toxicity.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_30">There have also been reports of animal studies in which vitamin C has interfered with the anticancer activity of various drugs.  In a study reported in 2008, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> of dehydroascorbic acid to lymphoma-xenograft mice prior to doxorubicin treatment resulted in significantly larger tumors than did treatment with doxorubicin alone.<Reference refidx="22"/> Notably, this study used dehydroascorbate, the oxidized form of vitamin C that is known to be transported actively into cells and then reduced to vitamin C, but is not routinely used. Treating multiple myeloma xenograft mice with a combination of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> vitamin C and bortezomib resulted in significantly greater tumor volume than did treatment with bortezomib alone.<Reference refidx="23"/> This increase in tumor volume was caused by a chemical reaction that occurs in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal tract</GlossaryTermRef> but does not appear to be relevant to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> administration.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21672627">Chen P, Stone J, Sullivan G, et al.: Anti-cancer effect of pharmacologic ascorbate and its interaction with supplementary parenteral glutathione in preclinical cancer models. Free Radic Biol Med 51 (3): 681-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="16157892">Chen Q, Espey MG, Krishna MC, et al.: Pharmacologic ascorbic acid concentrations selectively kill cancer cells: action as a pro-drug to deliver hydrogen peroxide to tissues. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 102 (38): 13604-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19254759">Verrax J, Calderon PB: Pharmacologic concentrations of ascorbate are achieved by parenteral administration and exhibit antitumoral effects. Free Radic Biol Med 47 (1): 32-40, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="18678913">Chen Q, Espey MG, Sun AY, et al.: Pharmacologic doses of ascorbate act as a prooxidant and decrease growth of aggressive tumor xenografts in mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 105 (32): 11105-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="20694726">Frömberg A, Gutsch D, Schulze D, et al.: Ascorbate exerts anti-proliferative effects through cell cycle inhibition and sensitizes tumor cells towards cytostatic drugs. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 67 (5): 1157-66, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="22205155">Chen P, Yu J, Chalmers B, et al.: Pharmacological ascorbate induces cytotoxicity in prostate cancer cells through ATP depletion and induction of autophagy. Anticancer Drugs 23 (4): 437-44, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="20068072">Du J, Martin SM, Levine M, et al.: Mechanisms of ascorbate-induced cytotoxicity in pancreatic cancer. Clin Cancer Res 16 (2): 509-20, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="21402145">Espey MG, Chen P, Chalmers B, et al.: Pharmacologic ascorbate synergizes with gemcitabine in preclinical models of pancreatic cancer. Free Radic Biol Med 50 (11): 1610-9, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="19932582">Lin ZY, Chuang WL: Pharmacologic concentrations of ascorbic acid cause diverse influence on differential expressions of angiogenic chemokine genes in different hepatocellular carcinoma cell lines. Biomed Pharmacother 64 (5): 348-51, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="21919647">Pathi SS, Lei P, Sreevalsan S, et al.: Pharmacologic doses of ascorbic acid repress specificity protein (Sp) transcription factors and Sp-regulated genes in colon cancer cells. Nutr Cancer 63 (7): 1133-42, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="20171954">Takemura Y, Satoh M, Satoh K, et al.: High dose of ascorbic acid induces cell death in mesothelioma cells. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 394 (2): 249-53, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="22469841">Hardaway CM, Badisa RB, Soliman KF: Effect of ascorbic acid and hydrogen peroxide on mouse neuroblastoma cells. Mol Med Report 5 (6): 1449-52, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="22728050">Du J, Cullen JJ, Buettner GR: Ascorbic acid: chemistry, biology and the treatment of cancer. Biochim Biophys Acta 1826 (2): 443-57, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="22332036">Levine M, Padayatty SJ, Espey MG: Vitamin C: a concentration-function approach yields pharmacology and therapeutic discoveries. Adv Nutr 2 (2): 78-88, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="28810149">Schoenfeld JD, Sibenaller ZA, Mapuskar KA, et al.: O2⋅- and H2O2-Mediated Disruption of Fe Metabolism Causes the Differential Susceptibility of NSCLC and GBM Cancer Cells to Pharmacological Ascorbate. Cancer Cell 32 (2): 268, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="29069637">Schoenfeld JD, Sibenaller ZA, Mapuskar KA, et al.: Redox active metals and H2O2 mediate the increased efficacy of pharmacological ascorbate in combination with gemcitabine or radiation in pre-clinical sarcoma models. Redox Biol 14: 417-422, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="26541605">Yun J, Mullarky E, Lu C, et al.: Vitamin C selectively kills KRAS and BRAF mutant colorectal cancer cells by targeting GAPDH. Science 350 (6266): 1391-6, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="22665050">Hong SW, Lee SH, Moon JH, et al.: SVCT-2 in breast cancer acts as an indicator for L-ascorbate treatment. Oncogene 32 (12): 1508-17, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="21455570">Ong PS, Chan SY, Ho PC: Differential augmentative effects of buthionine sulfoximine and ascorbic acid in As2O3-induced ovarian cancer cell death: oxidative stress-independent and -dependent cytotoxic potentiation. Int J Oncol 38 (6): 1731-9, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="21645609">Martinotti S, Ranzato E, Burlando B: In vitro screening of synergistic ascorbate-drug combinations for the treatment of malignant mesothelioma. Toxicol In Vitro 25 (8): 1568-74, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="22342518">Herst PM, Broadley KW, Harper JL, et al.: Pharmacological concentrations of ascorbate radiosensitize glioblastoma multiforme primary cells by increasing oxidative DNA damage and inhibiting G2/M arrest. Free Radic Biol Med 52 (8): 1486-93, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="18829561">Heaney ML, Gardner JR, Karasavvas N, et al.: Vitamin C antagonizes the cytotoxic effects of antineoplastic drugs. Cancer Res 68 (19): 8031-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="19369963">Perrone G, Hideshima T, Ikeda H, et al.: Ascorbic acid inhibits antitumor activity of bortezomib in vivo. Leukemia 23 (9): 1679-86, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="17785204">Gao P, Zhang H, Dinavahi R, et al.: HIF-dependent antitumorigenic effect of antioxidants in vivo. Cancer Cell 12 (3): 230-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="20554995">Pollard HB, Levine MA, Eidelman O, et al.: Pharmacological ascorbic acid suppresses syngeneic tumor growth and metastases in hormone-refractory prostate cancer. In Vivo 24 (3): 249-55, 2010 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="19671184">Yeom CH, Lee G, Park JH, et al.: High dose concentration administration of ascorbic acid inhibits tumor growth in BALB/C mice implanted with sarcoma 180 cancer cells via the restriction of angiogenesis. J Transl Med 7: 70, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="24500406">Ma Y, Chapman J, Levine M, et al.: High-dose parenteral ascorbate enhanced chemosensitivity of ovarian cancer and reduced toxicity of chemotherapy. Sci Transl Med 6 (222): 222ra18, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Human/Clinical Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Early Case Series Studies and Clinical Trials With Ascorbate Only </Title><Para id="_32">In the early 1970s, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285747" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">consecutive case series</GlossaryTermRef> was conducted in which 50 patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef> were treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ascorbic acid</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/> These patients began ascorbic acid treatment after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conventional therapies</GlossaryTermRef> were deemed unlikely to be effective. Patients received IV ascorbic acid (10 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">g</GlossaryTermRef>/day for 10 consecutive days; some patients received higher doses), oral ascorbic acid (10 g/day), or both. The patients exhibited a wide variety of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">responses</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment, including the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_115" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>No or minimal response.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046039" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regression</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemorrhage</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_116">However, the authors noted that lack of controls prevented definitive assignment of any beneficial responses to the ascorbic acid treatment.<Reference refidx="1"/> A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case report</GlossaryTermRef> published in 1975 detailed one of the patients who had experienced tumor regression.<Reference refidx="2"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> with reticulum <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, the patient exhibited improvement in well-being and resolution of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> masses after being treated with IV and oral ascorbic acid. When the patient's daily dose of ascorbic acid was reduced, some signs of the disease returned; however, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045867" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">remission</GlossaryTermRef> was achieved again after the patient reverted to the higher initial dose.</Para><Para id="_33">A larger <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044006" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case series</GlossaryTermRef> of patients with terminal cancer treated with ascorbate was reported in 1976. In this study, 100 patients with terminal cancer (50 of whom were reported on previously)  <Reference refidx="1"/> were treated with ascorbate (10 g/day for 10 days IV, then orally) and compared with 1,000 matched controls from the same hospital. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285974" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean survival</GlossaryTermRef> time for ascorbate-treated patients was 300 days longer than that of the matched controls.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_34">Two studies tried to reproduce earlier results. These studies were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef> trials in which patients with cancer received either 10 g of oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> daily until signs of cancer progression. No IV vitamin C was given in these studies. At the end of each study, no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">significant</GlossaryTermRef> differences were noted between the two ascorbate-treated and placebo-treated groups for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044174" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">performance status</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survival</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Recent Case Series Studies and Clinical Trials With Ascorbate Only </Title><Para id="_57">One study reported three case reports of patients with cancer who received IV vitamin C as their main <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. During vitamin C therapy, the patients used additional treatments, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044744" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamins</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">minerals</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367458" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">botanicals</GlossaryTermRef>.  According to the authors, the cases were reviewed in accordance with the <ExternalRef xref="https://cam.cancer.gov/indentifying_novel_cam_therapies/best_case_protocol.htm"> NCI Best Case Series guidelines</ExternalRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467841" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Histopathologic</GlossaryTermRef> examination suggested poor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognoses</GlossaryTermRef> for these patients, but they had long survival times after being treated with IV vitamin C.<Reference refidx="7"/> Vitamin C was given at doses ranging from 15 g to 65 g, initially once or twice a week for several months; two patients then received it less frequently for 1 to 4 years.</Para><Para id="_36">One study demonstrated that IV vitamin C treatment resulted in improved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> and a decrease in cancer-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with cancer.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_119">A single-arm <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045838" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pilot study</GlossaryTermRef> of weekly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusions</GlossaryTermRef> of 60 g of ascorbic acid for 9 weeks in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">castration</GlossaryTermRef>-resistant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> failed to observe a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000654999" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reduction</GlossaryTermRef> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serum</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> or tumor regression.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_38">Studies have shown that vitamin C can be safely administered to healthy volunteers or patients with cancer at doses up to 1.5 g/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kg</GlossaryTermRef> and with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> to eliminate treating individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748114" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency</GlossaryTermRef>, renal diseases, or urolithiasis). These studies have also found that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentrations</GlossaryTermRef> of vitamin C are higher with IV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> than with oral administration and are maintained for more than 4 hours.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_39"><Title>Early Phase Ascorbate Trials Combined With Standard Cancer Therapies</Title><Para id="_40">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I</GlossaryTermRef> study published in 2012 examined the safety and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of combining IV ascorbate with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508951" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gemcitabine</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">erlotinib</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage IV pancreatic cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Fourteen patients entered the study and planned to receive IV gemcitabine (1,000 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> over 30 minutes, once a week for 7 weeks), oral erlotinib (100 mg daily for 8 weeks), and IV ascorbate (50 g/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>, 75 g/infusion, or 100 g/infusion 3 times per week for 8 weeks). Minimal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> were reported for ascorbic acid treatment. Five patients received fewer than 18 of the planned 24 ascorbate infusions and thus did not have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046361" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging</GlossaryTermRef> to assess response. Three of those patients had clinically determined <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045850" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progressive disease</GlossaryTermRef>. The other nine patients had repeat imaging to assess tumor size, and each met the criteria for having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045884" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stable disease</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Para id="_62">A 2013 phase I <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical study</GlossaryTermRef> (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01049880">NCT01049880</ProtocolRef>) evaluated the safety of combining pharmacological ascorbate with gemcitabine in treating patients with stage IV pancreatic cancer. During each 4-week cycle, patients received gemcitabine weekly for 3 weeks (1,000 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> over 30 minutes) and twice-weekly ascorbate infusions for 4 weeks (15 g over 30 minutes during the first week, followed by weekly escalations in dose until plasma levels reached at least 350 mg/dL [20 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000659791" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mM</GlossaryTermRef>]). Among nine patients, mean <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044782" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression-free survival</GlossaryTermRef> (PFS) was 26 weeks and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overall survival</GlossaryTermRef> (OS) was 12 months. The combination treatment was well tolerated, and no significant adverse events were reported.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_68">In 2014, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045832" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I/IIA</GlossaryTermRef> clinical trial evaluated the toxicities of combining IV ascorbate with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carboplatin</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045258" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paclitaxel</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045901" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045902" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">IV ovarian cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Twenty-seven patients were randomly assigned to receive either <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> alone or chemotherapy and IV vitamin C concurrently. Chemotherapy was given for 6 months, and IV vitamin C was given for 12 months. The addition of IV vitamin C was associated with  reduced chemotherapy-related toxicities.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_104">A 2015 phase I/II clinical trial of high-dose IV vitamin C (approximately 1.5 g/kg body weight) combined with various chemotherapies, depending on the specific cancer diagnosis, was conducted to do the following:<Reference refidx="15"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_108" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Observe the associated adverse events.</ListItem><ListItem>Assess the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetic</GlossaryTermRef> profiles of vitamin C and  oxalic acid levels prechemotherapy- and postchemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Assess <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> responses.</ListItem><ListItem>Assess changes in mood.</ListItem><ListItem>Assess changes in quality of life.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_109">High-dose IV vitamin C was analyzed in 14 patients and was generally well tolerated and safe. Minor temporary adverse effects included increased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinary</GlossaryTermRef> flow, thirst, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vomiting</GlossaryTermRef>, and chills, some of which could be prevented. Chemotherapy administration did not affect the plasma concentration of vitamin C. Although a few patients experienced temporary stable disease, functional improvement, and increased energy, the sample size is so small that the generalizability of these results is uncertain.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_132">In 2017, a phase I/IIA study reported using IV vitamin C with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard-of-care</GlossaryTermRef> gemcitabine chemotherapy in patients with newly diagnosed pancreatic cancer.<Reference refidx="16"/> Seven participants were initially enrolled. When safety was confirmed, an additional seven participants were enrolled. Twelve of the 14 enrolled participants completed the phase I pharmacokinetic evaluation. The evaluation consisted of IV vitamin C and gemcitabine pharmacokinetic  measurements, each as single <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>,  and then followed by the pharmacokinetic measurement of IV vitamin C combined with gemcitabine. IV vitamin C administration did not interfere with  gemcitabine.</Para><Para id="_105">In May 2019, a phase I study was published that examined the safety, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetics</GlossaryTermRef>, and efficacy of high-dose IV vitamin C  combined with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimens</GlossaryTermRef> mFOLFOX6 (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045465" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxaliplatin</GlossaryTermRef> + leucovorin + <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluorouracil</GlossaryTermRef>) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635807" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FOLFIRI</GlossaryTermRef> (leucovorin + fluorouracil + irinotecan hydrochloride). This study consisted of 36 patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454513" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastric cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The main goal was to determine the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000546597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">maximum-tolerated dose</GlossaryTermRef> and the recommended <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045831" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase II</GlossaryTermRef> dose of ascorbic acid with coadministration of either mFOLFOX6 or FOLFIRI. Patients received chemotherapy treatment on a 14-day cycle with vitamin C infusions occurring for 3 consecutive days for 3 hours at a time. For the dose-escalation portion of the study, ascorbic acid doses ranged from 0.2 g/kg to 1.5 g/kg. To determine the optimal administration rate of ascorbic acid, patient cohorts received infusion rates set at 0.6 g/min, 0.8 g/min, or  1 g/min. The study showed no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044170" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose-limiting</GlossaryTermRef> toxicity for all doses and dosing rates; thus a maximum-tolerated dose was not reached, leading to a recommended phase II dose of 1.5 g/kg for ascorbic acid. Overall, no severe adverse reactions occurred, and the treatments were deemed safe and tolerable. A randomized <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045833" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase III trial</GlossaryTermRef> (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02969681">NCT02969681</ProtocolRef>) is being conducted to determine the clinical efficacy of ascorbic acid with mFOLFOX6 with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bevacizumab</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_158">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045831" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase II clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> published in 2024 evaluated the clinical benefit of combining pharmacologic IV vitamin C with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045382" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">docetaxel</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with progressive metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer. Forty-seven patients were randomly assigned 2:1 to receive docetaxel (75 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> IV) with either pharmacologic IV vitamin C (1 g/kg) or placebo. The study found that the addition of  the vitamin C to docetaxel did not improve PSA response, toxicity, or other clinical outcomes when compared with docetaxel alone.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_159">Another phase  II clinical trial published in 2024 assessed the effect of pharmacological ascorbate (P-AscH-) combined with gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel in patients with stage IV pancreatic cancer. Thirty-four patients were randomly assigned 1:1 to receive gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel only or gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635464" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concomitant</GlossaryTermRef> P-AscH- (75 g  three times weekly). The study found that the  addition of P-AscH− to gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel prolonged OS and PFS in patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer, without detected detriment to quality of life or added toxicity.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><Table id="_101"><Title>Table 1.  Clinical Studies of Ascorbate   with Chemotherapy<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="8"><ColSpec ColName="col01" ColNum="1" ColWidth="18.90%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="2" ColWidth="11.31%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="8.54%"/><ColSpec ColName="col04" ColNum="4" ColWidth="14.31%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="5" ColWidth="13.76%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="6" ColWidth="7.91%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="7" ColWidth="16.06%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="8" ColWidth="9.17%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Condition</GlossaryTermRef> or Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Dose</entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry Align="Center">Results</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Concurrent Therapy</GlossaryTermRef> Used</entry><entry Align="Center">Level of Evidence Score<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col01"/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For additional information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Number of patients treated plus number of patient controls may not equal number of patients enrolled; number of patients enrolled equals number of patients initially recruited/considered by the researchers who conducted a study; number of patients treated equals number of enrolled patients who were given the treatment being studied AND for whom results were reported.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>c</Superscript>For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of evidence</GlossaryTermRef> analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="16"/></entry><entry>Phase I/IIA trial</entry><entry>Newly diagnosed pancreatic cancer</entry><entry> 6 doses of 25–75 g/infusion for phase I and 64 doses of 100 g/infusion for phase II</entry><entry>14; 12; none</entry><entry>Ascorbic acid did not interfere with gemcitabine pharmacokinetics</entry><entry>Gemcitabine</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335136" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Dii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="12"/></entry><entry>Phase I, open label trial</entry><entry>Metastatic stage IV pancreatic cancer</entry><entry>50 g/infusion, 75 g/infusion, or 100 g/infusion 3x/wk for 8 wk</entry><entry>14; 14 (9 analyzed); none</entry><entry>Ascorbic acid was well tolerated with gemcitabine and erlotinib</entry><entry>Gemcitabine, erlotinib</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335136" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Dii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>Phase I, open label trial</entry><entry>Stage IV pancreatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>15 g/wk until the plasma level reached at least 350 mg/dL (20 mM)
</entry><entry>15; 11 (9 completed); none</entry><entry>Ascorbate  acid was well tolerated with gemcitabine</entry><entry>Gemcitabine</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335136" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Dii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry><entry>Pilot phase I/IIA trial</entry><entry>Stage III/IV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445074" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovarian cancer</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Up  to 75 g or 100 g 2x/wk for 12 mo
</entry><entry>27; 14 (chemotherapy), 13 (chemotherapy and intravenous vitamin C); none</entry><entry>Ascorbate acid added to carboplatin and paclitaxel therapy reduced chemotherapy-related toxicities</entry><entry>Carboplatin, paclitaxel</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_41">Trials of high-dose IV vitamin C combined with other drugs are ongoing.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="14"/> A number of studies have included small doses of IV ascorbic acid treatment (1,000 mg) with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046018" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">arsenic trioxide</GlossaryTermRef> regimens, with mixed results. For study results, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742114#_102" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">Table 2</SummaryRef>. </Para><Table id="_102"><Title>Table 2.  Clinical Studies of Ascorbate in Arsenic Trioxide–Containing Regimens<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="8"><ColSpec ColName="col01" ColNum="1" ColWidth="20.46%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="2" ColWidth="10.48%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="15.27%"/><ColSpec ColName="col04" ColNum="4" ColWidth="10.69%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="5" ColWidth="10.59%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="6" ColWidth="11.30%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="7" ColWidth="10.18%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="8" ColWidth="10.99%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design </entry><entry Align="Center">Condition or Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Dose</entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry Align="Center">Results</entry><entry Align="Center">Concurrent Therapy 
Used 
</entry><entry Align="Center">Level of Evidence Score<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col01">N = number of patients; RCT = randomized controlled trial.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For additional information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Number of patients treated plus number of patient controls may not equal number of patients enrolled; number of patients enrolled equals number of patients initially recruited/considered by the researchers who conducted a study; number of patients treated equals number of enrolled patients who were given the treatment being studied AND for whom results were reported.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col01"><Superscript>c</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="20"/></entry><entry>RCT </entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045793" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Multiple myeloma</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>1,000 mg</entry><entry>48; arm 1 (N = 16), arm 2 (N = 17), arm 3 (N = 15); none</entry><entry>The addition of arsenic trioxide and ascorbic acid to high-dose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melphalan</GlossaryTermRef> was reported safe and well tolerated</entry><entry>Melphalan</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335129" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="21"/></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045831" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Phase II</GlossaryTermRef>, open label</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Relapsed</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory</GlossaryTermRef> multiple myeloma</entry><entry>1,000 mg</entry><entry>20; 20; none</entry><entry>Clinical efficacy and tolerability with arsenic trioxide, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045262" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dexamethasone</GlossaryTermRef>, and ascorbic acid was reported</entry><entry> Dexamethasone</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335142" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="22"/></entry><entry>Phase I/II, open label</entry><entry>Relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma</entry><entry>1,000 mg</entry><entry>22; 22; none</entry><entry>Arsenic trioxide, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bortezomib</GlossaryTermRef>, and ascorbic acid was well tolerated with signs of clinical efficacy</entry><entry> Bortezomib</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335142" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="23"/></entry><entry>Phase II</entry><entry>Relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma</entry><entry>1,000 mg</entry><entry>65; 65; none</entry><entry>Melphalan, arsenic trioxide, and ascorbic acid was effective and well tolerated </entry><entry>Melphalan</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335142" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="24"/></entry><entry>Phase II</entry><entry>Refractory metastatic colorectal carcinoma</entry><entry>1,000 mg</entry><entry>5; 5; none</entry><entry>Patients developed moderate to severe toxic side effects without clinical response</entry><entry>None</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335142" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="25"/></entry><entry>Phase II, open label</entry><entry>Metastatic 
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>1,000 mg</entry><entry>11; 10; none</entry><entry>Patients developed  toxic side effects without clinical response</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045387" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Temozolomide</GlossaryTermRef>
</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335142" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iDii</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Para id="_83">Informed by their preclinical data,<Reference refidx="21"/> researchers at the University of Iowa treated patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-small cell lung</GlossaryTermRef> carcinoma (NSCLC)  and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glioblastoma multiforme</GlossaryTermRef> (GBM) in two pilot clinical trials (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02420314">NCT02420314</ProtocolRef> and <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01752491">NCT01752491</ProtocolRef>).<Reference refidx="26"/> Participants in both trials were given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conventional therapy</GlossaryTermRef> plus IV vitamin C, with dosing individualized to achieve a 20 mM peak plasma concentration of ascorbate in each patient. The GBM study was a phase I design with 13 total patients. IV vitamin C was given with both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045387" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">temozolomide</GlossaryTermRef> and toxicity, progression-free survival, and overall survival all compared favorably to the outcomes of historical controls. The NSCLC trial was a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045831" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase II</GlossaryTermRef> design of 14 patients with advanced cancer who received both chemotherapy and IV vitamin C (median maximum plasma concentration,  16.4 mM). The disease control and confirmed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044067" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">objective response</GlossaryTermRef> rates of the study group again compared favorably with those of historical controls.  Limitations of these studies included the use of historical controls and small numbers of enrolled participants.</Para><Para id="_106">Various trials of high-dose IV vitamin C with other drugs are ongoing. There are currently five trials being conducted by researchers at the University of Iowa; four phase II studies and one phase IB/II study. The four phase II clinical trials are investigating the efficacy of high-dose ascorbate combined with standard anticancer regimens. The studies are exploring the combination of high-dose ascorbate with the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_117" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Standard non-small cell lung cancer therapy,  including radiation therapy, carboplatin, and paclitaxel (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02905591">NCT02905591</ProtocolRef>).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Standard therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for metastatic pancreatic adenocarcinoma, including gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02905578">NCT02905578</ProtocolRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>Standard therapy for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">localized</GlossaryTermRef> pancreatic adenocarcinoma with gemcitabine and radiation therapy (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03541486">NCT03541486</ProtocolRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>Standard therapy for glioblastoma multiforme, including temozolomide and radiation therapy (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02344355">NCT02344355</ProtocolRef>). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_118">Another phase IB/II trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03508726">NCT03508726</ProtocolRef>) is studying the safety and efficacy of high-dose ascorbate with preoperative radiation therapy in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_107">Several studies have included IV ascorbic acid treatment at a fixed dose of 1,000 mg  with arsenic trioxide regimens, with mixed results. Researchers using this approach suggested that the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372940" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pro-oxidant</GlossaryTermRef> properties of IV ascorbic acid may have helped to increase the effects of arsenic trioxide  by sensitization of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> cells to arsenic’s cytotoxic effects.<Reference refidx="27"/> The combination therapies were well tolerated and suggested beneficial effects in patients with multiple myeloma, although the specific contribution of vitamin C could not be determined.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/>  However, similar combination regimens resulted in severe side effects, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disease progression</GlossaryTermRef>, and no anticancer effect  in patients with refractory metastatic colorectal cancer <Reference refidx="24"/> and metastatic melanoma.<Reference refidx="25"/> Because these were not placebo-controlled trials, the extent that ascorbate contributed to the toxicity or efficacy demonstrated in these studies is unclear.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_16_sid_5"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_16_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="4430016">Cameron E, Campbell A: The orthomolecular treatment of cancer. II. Clinical trial of high-dose ascorbic acid supplements in advanced human cancer. Chem Biol Interact 9 (4): 285-315, 1974.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="1104207">Cameron E, Campbell A, Jack T: The orthomolecular treatment of cancer. III. Reticulum cell sarcoma: double complete regression induced by high-dose ascorbic acid therapy. Chem Biol Interact 11 (5): 387-93, 1975.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1068480">Cameron E, Pauling L: Supplemental ascorbate in the supportive treatment of cancer: Prolongation of survival times in terminal human cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 73 (10): 3685-9, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="279931">Cameron E, Pauling L: Supplemental ascorbate in the supportive treatment of cancer: reevaluation of prolongation of survival times in terminal human cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 75 (9): 4538-42, 1978.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="384241">Creagan ET, Moertel CG, O'Fallon JR, et al.: Failure of high-dose vitamin C (ascorbic acid) therapy to benefit patients with advanced cancer. A controlled trial. N Engl J Med 301 (13): 687-90, 1979.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="3880867">Moertel CG, Fleming TR, Creagan ET, et al.: High-dose vitamin C versus placebo in the treatment of patients with advanced cancer who have had no prior chemotherapy. A randomized double-blind comparison. N Engl J Med 312 (3): 137-41, 1985.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="16567755">Padayatty SJ, Riordan HD, Hewitt SM, et al.: Intravenously administered vitamin C as cancer therapy: three cases. CMAJ 174 (7): 937-42, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="17297243">Yeom CH, Jung GC, Song KJ: Changes of terminal cancer patients' health-related quality of life after high dose vitamin C administration. J Korean Med Sci 22 (1): 7-11, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="28725594">Nielsen TK, Højgaard M, Andersen JT, et al.: Weekly ascorbic acid infusion in castration-resistant prostate cancer patients: a single-arm phase II trial. Transl Androl Urol 6 (3): 517-528, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="15068981">Padayatty SJ, Sun H, Wang Y, et al.: Vitamin C pharmacokinetics: implications for oral and intravenous use. Ann Intern Med 140 (7): 533-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="18544557">Hoffer LJ, Levine M, Assouline S, et al.: Phase I clinical trial of i.v. ascorbic acid in advanced malignancy. Ann Oncol 19 (11): 1969-74, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="22272248">Monti DA, Mitchell E, Bazzan AJ, et al.: Phase I evaluation of intravenous ascorbic acid in combination with gemcitabine and erlotinib in patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer. PLoS One 7 (1): e29794, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="23381814">Welsh JL, Wagner BA, van't Erve TJ, et al.: Pharmacological ascorbate with gemcitabine for the control of metastatic and node-positive pancreatic cancer (PACMAN): results from a phase I clinical trial. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 71 (3): 765-75, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="24500406">Ma Y, Chapman J, Levine M, et al.: High-dose parenteral ascorbate enhanced chemosensitivity of ovarian cancer and reduced toxicity of chemotherapy. Sci Transl Med 6 (222): 222ra18, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="25848948">Hoffer LJ, Robitaille L, Zakarian R, et al.: High-dose intravenous vitamin C combined with cytotoxic chemotherapy in patients with advanced cancer: a phase I-II clinical trial. PLoS One 10 (4): e0120228, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="29215048">Polireddy K, Dong R, Reed G, et al.: High Dose Parenteral Ascorbate Inhibited Pancreatic Cancer Growth and Metastasis: Mechanisms and a Phase I/IIa study. Sci Rep 7 (1): 17188, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="31096937">Wang F, He MM, Wang ZX, et al.: Phase I study of high-dose ascorbic acid with mFOLFOX6 or FOLFIRI in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer or gastric cancer. BMC Cancer 19 (1): 460, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="39076107">Paller CJ, Zahurak ML, Mandl A, et al.: High-Dose Intravenous Vitamin C Combined with Docetaxel in Men with Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer: A Randomized Placebo-Controlled Phase II Trial. Cancer Res Commun 4 (8): 2174-2182, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="39369582">Bodeker KL, Smith BJ, Berg DJ, et al.: A randomized trial of pharmacological ascorbate, gemcitabine, and nab-paclitaxel for metastatic pancreatic cancer. Redox Biol 77: 103375, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="19041063">Qazilbash MH, Saliba RM, Nieto Y, et al.: Arsenic trioxide with ascorbic acid and high-dose melphalan: results of a phase II randomized trial. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 14 (12): 1401-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="16720927">Abou-Jawde RM, Reed J, Kelly M, et al.: Efficacy and safety results with the combination therapy of arsenic trioxide, dexamethasone, and ascorbic acid in multiple myeloma patients: a phase 2 trial. Med Oncol 23 (2): 263-72, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="17363530">Berenson JR, Matous J, Swift RA, et al.: A phase I/II study of arsenic trioxide/bortezomib/ascorbic acid combination therapy for the treatment of relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Clin Cancer Res 13 (6): 1762-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="17010047">Berenson JR, Boccia R, Siegel D, et al.: Efficacy and safety of melphalan, arsenic trioxide and ascorbic acid combination therapy in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma: a prospective, multicentre, phase II, single-arm study. Br J Haematol 135 (2): 174-83, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="17497326">Subbarayan PR, Lima M, Ardalan B: Arsenic trioxide/ascorbic acid therapy in patients with refractory metastatic colorectal carcinoma: a clinical experience. Acta Oncol 46 (4): 557-61, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="18337652">Bael TE, Peterson BL, Gollob JA: Phase II trial of arsenic trioxide and ascorbic acid with temozolomide in patients with metastatic melanoma with or without central nervous system metastases. Melanoma Res 18 (2): 147-51, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="28810149">Schoenfeld JD, Sibenaller ZA, Mapuskar KA, et al.: O2⋅- and H2O2-Mediated Disruption of Fe Metabolism Causes the Differential Susceptibility of NSCLC and GBM Cancer Cells to Pharmacological Ascorbate. Cancer Cell 32 (2): 268, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="17587338">Campbell RA, Sanchez E, Steinberg JA, et al.: Antimyeloma effects of arsenic trioxide are enhanced by melphalan, bortezomib and ascorbic acid. Br J Haematol 138 (4): 467-78, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><Title>Adverse Effects</Title><Para id="_19"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439436" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ascorbic acid</GlossaryTermRef> has been generally well tolerated in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462925" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Renal failure</GlossaryTermRef> after ascorbic acid treatment has been reported in patients with preexisting renal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disorders</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="10"/> One study reported <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef> overload  related to ascorbic acid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>, but this may be caused by the delivery method and not the product.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><Para id="_42"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Case reports</GlossaryTermRef> have indicated that patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748114" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G-6-PD) deficiency</GlossaryTermRef> should not receive high doses of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> because of the risk of developing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687883" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemolysis</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_124"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Administration</GlossaryTermRef> of IV vitamin C at high doses has been shown to interfere with the measurement of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serum</GlossaryTermRef> biochemical parameters. A study of the administration of high-dose IV vitamin C  has been observed to interfere with certain laboratory tests such as strip-based <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef> meters, showing false elevations in the glucose measurements.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></Para><SummarySection id="_49"><Title>Drug Interactions</Title><Para id="_50">When administered in high doses, vitamin C may result in adverse interactions with some anticancer agents. These interactions have primarily been detected in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">preclinical studies</GlossaryTermRef>. Two early clinical studies evaluated the safety of combining high-dose IV ascorbate with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508951" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gemcitabine</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with stage IV <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The combination therapy was well tolerated by patients, and no significant adverse events were reported.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_51"><Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">In vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> and <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef> have suggested that combining <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> vitamin C with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bortezomib</GlossaryTermRef> interferes with the drug’s ability to act as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000393541" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteasome inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> and blocks bortezomib-initiated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">apoptosis</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/> This interference occurred even with the oral administration of vitamin C (40 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kg</GlossaryTermRef>/day)  to animals. Studies in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556412" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell culture</GlossaryTermRef> and performed by adding <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> from healthy volunteers given  oral vitamin C (1 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">g</GlossaryTermRef>/day) also showed a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">significant</GlossaryTermRef> decrease in bortezomib’s growth inhibitory effect on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045793" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multiple myeloma</GlossaryTermRef> cells. Another study found similar results. Plasma from healthy volunteers who took 1 g of oral vitamin C per day was shown to decrease bortezomib growth inhibition in multiple myeloma cells and to block its inhibitory effect on 20S proteasome activity.<Reference refidx="20"/> However, a study that utilized mice harboring human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cell <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">xenografts</GlossaryTermRef> failed to find any significant effect of oral vitamin C (40 mg/kg/day or 500 mg/kg/day) on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> growth inhibitory action of bortezomib.<Reference refidx="21"/>  Because IV administration of vitamin C is known to produce higher concentrations of ascorbate than oral administration, these results should be a warning for patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> who are receiving treatment with bortezomib. Study results of the co-administration of IV vitamin C and bortezomib in humans would help guide clinical recommendations.</Para><Para id="_55">Several studies have been performed to assess the potential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">synergistic</GlossaryTermRef> or inhibitory action of vitamin C on certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>, with variable results. A series of studies in cell culture and in animals bearing tumors has shown that when given at high concentrations or dosages, dehydroascorbic acid (an oxidized form of vitamin C) can interfere with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic</GlossaryTermRef> effects of several chemotherapy drugs.<Reference refidx="22"/>  However, dehydroascorbic acid is generally present only at low concentrations in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef> and fresh foods.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15068981">Padayatty SJ, Sun H, Wang Y, et al.: Vitamin C pharmacokinetics: implications for oral and intravenous use. Ann Intern Med 140 (7): 533-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="18544557">Hoffer LJ, Levine M, Assouline S, et al.: Phase I clinical trial of i.v. ascorbic acid in advanced malignancy. Ann Oncol 19 (11): 1969-74, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="18678913">Chen Q, Espey MG, Sun AY, et al.: Pharmacologic doses of ascorbate act as a prooxidant and decrease growth of aggressive tumor xenografts in mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 105 (32): 11105-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="22272248">Monti DA, Mitchell E, Bazzan AJ, et al.: Phase I evaluation of intravenous ascorbic acid in combination with gemcitabine and erlotinib in patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer. PLoS One 7 (1): e29794, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="16720927">Abou-Jawde RM, Reed J, Kelly M, et al.: Efficacy and safety results with the combination therapy of arsenic trioxide, dexamethasone, and ascorbic acid in multiple myeloma patients: a phase 2 trial. Med Oncol 23 (2): 263-72, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="17363530">Berenson JR, Matous J, Swift RA, et al.: A phase I/II study of arsenic trioxide/bortezomib/ascorbic acid combination therapy for the treatment of relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Clin Cancer Res 13 (6): 1762-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="19041063">Qazilbash MH, Saliba RM, Nieto Y, et al.: Arsenic trioxide with ascorbic acid and high-dose melphalan: results of a phase II randomized trial. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 14 (12): 1401-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="24500406">Ma Y, Chapman J, Levine M, et al.: High-dose parenteral ascorbate enhanced chemosensitivity of ovarian cancer and reduced toxicity of chemotherapy. Sci Transl Med 6 (222): 222ra18, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="29215048">Polireddy K, Dong R, Reed G, et al.: High Dose Parenteral Ascorbate Inhibited Pancreatic Cancer Growth and Metastasis: Mechanisms and a Phase I/IIa study. Sci Rep 7 (1): 17188, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20628650">Padayatty SJ, Sun AY, Chen Q, et al.: Vitamin C: intravenous use by complementary and alternative medicine practitioners and adverse effects. PLoS One 5 (7): e11414, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="28725594">Nielsen TK, Højgaard M, Andersen JT, et al.: Weekly ascorbic acid infusion in castration-resistant prostate cancer patients: a single-arm phase II trial. Transl Androl Urol 6 (3): 517-528, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="1138591">Campbell GD, Steinberg MH, Bower JD: Letter: Ascorbic acid-induced hemolysis in G-6-PD deficiency. Ann Intern Med 82 (6): 810, 1975.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="1976956">Mehta JB, Singhal SB, Mehta BC: Ascorbic-acid-induced haemolysis in G-6-PD deficiency. Lancet 336 (8720): 944, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="8490379">Rees DC, Kelsey H, Richards JD: Acute haemolysis induced by high dose ascorbic acid in glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency. BMJ 306 (6881): 841-2, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="32506941">Katzman BM, Kelley BR, Deobald GR, et al.: Unintended Consequence of High-Dose Vitamin C Therapy for an Oncology Patient: Evaluation of Ascorbic Acid Interference With Three Hospital-Use Glucose Meters. J Diabetes Sci Technol 15 (4): 897-900, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="16403487">Martinello F, da Silva EL: Ascorbic acid interference in the measurement of serum biochemical parameters: in vivo and in vitro studies. Clin Biochem 39 (4): 396-403, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="23381814">Welsh JL, Wagner BA, van't Erve TJ, et al.: Pharmacological ascorbate with gemcitabine for the control of metastatic and node-positive pancreatic cancer (PACMAN): results from a phase I clinical trial. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 71 (3): 765-75, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="16397052">Zou W, Yue P, Lin N, et al.: Vitamin C inactivates the proteasome inhibitor PS-341 in human cancer cells. Clin Cancer Res 12 (1): 273-80, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="18176107">Llobet D, Eritja N, Encinas M, et al.: Antioxidants block proteasome inhibitor function in endometrial carcinoma cells. Anticancer Drugs 19 (2): 115-24, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="19369963">Perrone G, Hideshima T, Ikeda H, et al.: Ascorbic acid inhibits antitumor activity of bortezomib in vivo. Leukemia 23 (9): 1679-86, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="21400028">Bannerman B, Xu L, Jones M, et al.: Preclinical evaluation of the antitumor activity of bortezomib in combination with vitamin C or with epigallocatechin gallate, a component of green tea. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 68 (5): 1145-54, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="18829561">Heaney ML, Gardner JR, Karasavvas N, et al.: Vitamin C antagonizes the cytotoxic effects of antineoplastic drugs. Cancer Res 68 (19): 8031-8, 2008.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_133"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Intravenous Vitamin C</Title><Para id="_134">To assist readers in evaluating the results of human studies of integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of
evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever
possible.  To qualify for a level of evidence <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef>, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_135" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Be published in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed scientific journal</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Report on a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Describe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> findings in sufficient detail that a meaningful evaluation can be made.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_136">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score. For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis for cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_44"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/13/2025)</Title><Para id="_56">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_160"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000742114#_16" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">Human/Clinical Studies</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_161">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742114#_158" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that a phase II clinical trial published in 2024 evaluated the clinical benefit of combining pharmacologic IV vitamin C with docetaxel in patients with progressive metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer. Forty-seven patients were randomly assigned 2:1 to receive docetaxel with either pharmacologic IV vitamin C  or placebo. The study found that the addition of the   vitamin C to docetaxel did not improve prostate-specific antigen response, toxicity, or other clinical outcomes when compared with docetaxel alone (cited Paller et al. as reference 18).</Para><Para id="_162">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742114#_159" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that a phase  II clinical trial published in 2024 assessed the effect of pharmacological ascorbate (P-AscH-) combined with gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel in patients with stage IV pancreatic cancer. Thirty-four patients were randomly assigned 1:1 to receive gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel only or gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel with concomitant P-AscH-. The study found that the  addition of P-AscH- to gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel prolonged overall survival and progression-free survival in patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer, without detected detriment to quality of life or added toxicity (cited Bodeker et al. as reference 19).</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742114#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of intravenous vitamin C in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Intravenous Vitamin C. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389504]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2013-02-08</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
