<Summary id="CDR0000742253"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Intravenous vitamin C, in some studies, has shown improved quality of life and fewer side effects in some cancer patients. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration has not approved its use as a treatment for cancer. Learn more in this expert-reviewed summary. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq">Intravenous Vitamin C (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">Intravenous Vitamin C (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039737">ascorbic acid</TermRef></MainTopics><SecondaryTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000372898">CAM nutritional therapy</TermRef></SecondaryTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_83">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of intravenous vitamin C in the treatment of people with cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_84">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>ascorbic acid</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>CAM nutritional therapy</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Intravenous Vitamin C (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Intravenous Vitamin C</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Intravenous Vitamin C</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><ItemizedList id="_2" Style="bullet">
   <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrient</GlossaryTermRef> found in food and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>. It is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef> and also plays a key role in making <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collagen</GlossaryTermRef> (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742253#_5" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq">Question 1</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>Vitamin C may be taken by mouth or given by an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000520363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous (IV) infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. When taken by IV infusion, vitamin C can reach higher levels in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> than when the same amount is taken by mouth (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742253#_17" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq">Question 2</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>Some studies of IV vitamin C use in people with cancer showed it improved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> and reduced cancer-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742253#_19" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq">Question 4</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>In general, vitamin C given by IV infusion has caused very few side effects in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>. However, IV vitamin C may cause serious side effects in people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef> disease, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">G6PD deficiency</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446804" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemochromatosis</GlossaryTermRef>  (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742253#_20" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq">Question 5</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) has not approved the use of IV vitamin C as a treatment for cancer (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742253#_21" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq">Question 7</SummaryRef>).</ListItem>
   
   
  </ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Questions and Answers About Intravenous Vitamin C</Title><QandASet id="_4">
   <QandAEntry id="_5">
    <Question>What is vitamin C?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_6"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044697" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutrient</GlossaryTermRef> that is found in food, such as oranges, grapefruit, kiwi, peppers, and broccoli, and in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>. Vitamin C is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef> and helps <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> damage to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044030" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">free radicals</GlossaryTermRef>. It also works with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> to  play a key role in making  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collagen</GlossaryTermRef>. Vitamin C is also called L-ascorbic acid or ascorbate.</Para>
     
    </Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   
   
   <QandAEntry id="_17">
    <Question>How is vitamin C given or taken?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_32">Vitamin C may be given by intravenous (IV) infusion or taken by mouth. When given by IV infusion, vitamin C  can reach much higher levels in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>  than when it  is taken by mouth. </Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_18">
    <Question>Have any laboratory or animal studies
         been done using IV vitamin C?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_85">In laboratory studies, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> cells are used to test a substance to find out if it is likely to have any anticancer effects. In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal studies</GlossaryTermRef>, tests are done to see if a  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef>, procedure, or treatment is safe and effective. Laboratory and animal studies are done in animals before a substance  is tested in people.</Para><Para id="_86">Laboratory and animal studies have tested the effects of IV vitamin C. Laboratory studies suggest that high  levels of vitamin C may kill <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> cells. For information on laboratory and animal studies done using intravenous vitamin C, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742114#_14" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Intravenous Vitamin C.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_19">
    <Question>Have any  studies of IV vitamin C been done in people with cancer?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_49">Several studies of IV vitamin C given alone or in combination with other drugs in people with cancer include the following:</Para><Para id="_50"><Strong>Studies of IV vitamin C alone</Strong></Para><ItemizedList id="_76" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>One study found that people with cancer who received IV vitamin C had better <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> and fewer cancer-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> than those who did not receive it.</ListItem><ListItem>In a single-arm <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045838" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pilot study</GlossaryTermRef> of people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000753525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">castration-resistant prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, IV vitamin C did not lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> levels or stop tumors from growing.</ListItem><ListItem>In a study of healthy volunteers and people with cancer, vitamin C was shown to be safe at doses up to 1.5 g/kg in people who do not have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef> stones,  other kidney diseases, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">G6PD deficiency</GlossaryTermRef>.  Studies have also shown that vitamin C levels in the blood are higher when given by IV than when taken by mouth, and last for more than 4 hours.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_54"><Strong>Studies of IV vitamin C combined with other drugs</Strong></Para><Para id="_77">Studies of IV vitamin C given with other drugs have shown mixed results.</Para><ItemizedList id="_78" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In a  small study of 14 people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, IV vitamin C  was given along with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>  and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">erlotinib</GlossaryTermRef>). Five study participants did not complete the vitamin C treatment because the tumor continued to grow during treatment. The nine participants who completed the treatment had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045884" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stable disease</GlossaryTermRef> as shown by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046361" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging</GlossaryTermRef> studies. Very few side effects were reported from the vitamin C treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>In a study of people newly diagnosed with pancreatic cancer, IV vitamin C did not interfere with  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508951" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gemcitabine</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>In another small study, 9 people with advanced pancreatic cancer were given chemotherapy once a week  for 3 weeks along with  IV vitamin C  twice a week for 4 weeks during each <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">treatment cycle</GlossaryTermRef>. The cancer did not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045850" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progress</GlossaryTermRef> over an average of 6 months in these patients. No serious side effects were reported with the combined treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>In a study of 27 people with advanced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445074" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovarian cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, chemotherapy alone was compared with chemotherapy and IV vitamin C. IV vitamin C was given during chemotherapy and for 6 months after chemotherapy ended. Those who received IV vitamin C had fewer side effects from the chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem>People with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or  metastatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanoma</GlossaryTermRef>  were treated with IV vitamin C given along with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046018" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">arsenic trioxide</GlossaryTermRef> and other drugs. The treatment had no anticancer effect, the tumor continued to grow during treatment, and patients had serious side effects. These studies did not have a comparison group, so it is unclear how much the IV vitamin C affected the side effects.</ListItem><ListItem>In two pilot trials, people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">non-small cell lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glioblastoma multiforme</GlossaryTermRef> were given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard therapy</GlossaryTermRef> plus IV vitamin C. Those who received standard therapy plus IV vitamin C had better <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overall survival</GlossaryTermRef> and fewer side effects than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control groups</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_82">More studies of combining IV vitamin C with other drugs are being done. These include a  number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> combining IV vitamin C with arsenic trioxide, showing mixed results.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_20">
    <Question>Have any side effects or risks been reported from IV vitamin C?</Question>
    <Answer><Para id="_41">IV vitamin C has caused very few side effects in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>. However, IV vitamin C may be harmful in people with certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><ItemizedList id="_79" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In people with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">history</GlossaryTermRef> of kidney disease, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney failure</GlossaryTermRef> has been reported after treatment with IV vitamin C. People who are likely to develop kidney stones should not be treated with IV vitamin C.</ListItem><ListItem>One study reported too much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef> in the body (fluid overload) related to IV vitamin C. This may have been caused by the IV delivery method and not the vitamin C.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Case reports</GlossaryTermRef> have shown that people with an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> disorder called  G6PD deficiency should not be given  high doses of vitamin C because it may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687883" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemolysis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Because vitamin C may make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446805" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iron</GlossaryTermRef>  more easily absorbed and used by the body, high doses of vitamin C are not recommended for people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446804" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemochromatosis</GlossaryTermRef> (a condition in which the body takes up and stores more iron than it needs).</ListItem></ItemizedList></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
   <QandAEntry id="_63"><Question>Have any drug interactions been reported from adding IV vitamin C to treatment with anticancer drugs?</Question><Answer><Para id="_64">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug interaction</GlossaryTermRef> is a change in the way a drug acts in the body when taken with certain other drugs. When IV vitamin C is combined with certain anticancer drugs, the anticancer drugs may not work as well. So far, these effects have been seen only in some laboratory and animal studies. For information on drug interactions while using IV vitamin C, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000742114#_18" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/vitamin-c-pdq">Adverse Effects</SummaryRef> section of the health professional version of Intravenous Vitamin C.</Para></Answer></QandAEntry><QandAEntry id="_21">
    <Question>Is IV vitamin C approved by the FDA for use as a cancer treatment in the United States?</Question>
    <Answer>
     
    <Para id="_35">The FDA has not approved the use of IV vitamin C as a treatment for cancer.</Para><Para id="_87">The FDA regulates dietary supplements separately from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. The FDA's Good Manufacturing Practices require that every finished batch of supplements is safe and that the claims on the label are true and do not mislead the consumer. However, the FDA does not regularly review the way that supplements are made, so  all batches and brands of IV vitamin C may not be the same.</Para></Answer>
   </QandAEntry>
  </QandASet></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the use of intravenous vitamin C in the treatment of people with cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Intravenous Vitamin C. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/vitamin-c-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 26389507]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_2"><Title>General CAM Information</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_3">Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)—also called integrative medicine—includes a broad range of healing philosophies, approaches, and therapies. A therapy is generally called complementary when it is used in addition to conventional treatments; it is often called alternative when it is used instead of conventional treatment. (Conventional treatments are those that are widely accepted and practiced by the mainstream medical community.) Depending on how they are used, some therapies can be considered either complementary or alternative. Complementary and alternative therapies are used in an effort to prevent illness, reduce stress, prevent or reduce side effects and symptoms, or control or cure disease. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_4">Unlike conventional treatments for cancer, complementary and alternative therapies are often not covered by insurance companies. Patients should check with their insurance provider to find out about coverage for complementary and alternative therapies. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_5">Cancer patients considering complementary and alternative therapies should discuss this decision with their doctor, nurse, or pharmacist as they would any type of treatment. Some complementary and alternative therapies may affect their standard treatment or may be harmful when used with conventional treatment. </Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_AboutIACT_6"><Title>Evaluation of CAM Therapies</Title><Para id="_AboutIACT_7">It is important that the same scientific methods used to test conventional therapies are used to test CAM therapies. The National Cancer Institute  and the National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) are sponsoring a number of clinical trials (research studies) at medical centers to test CAM therapies for use in cancer. </Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_8">Conventional approaches to cancer treatment have generally been studied for safety and effectiveness through a scientific process that includes clinical trials with large numbers of patients. Less is known about the safety and effectiveness of complementary and alternative methods. Few CAM therapies have been tested using demanding scientific methods. A small number of CAM therapies that were thought to be purely alternative approaches are now being used in cancer treatment—not as cures, but as complementary therapies that may help patients feel better and recover faster. One example is acupuncture. According to a panel of experts at a National Institutes of Health (NIH) meeting  in November 1997, acupuncture has been found to help control nausea and vomiting caused by chemotherapy and pain related to surgery. However, some approaches, such as the use of laetrile, have been studied and found not to work and to possibly cause harm.</Para><Para id="_AboutIACT_9"><ExternalRef xref="https://cam.cancer.gov/indentifying_novel_cam_therapies/best_case_series_program.htm">The NCI Best Case Series Program</ExternalRef>   which was started  in 1991, is one way CAM approaches that are being used in practice are being studied. The program is overseen by the NCI’s Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM). Health care professionals who offer alternative cancer therapies submit their patients’ medical records and related materials to OCCAM. OCCAM carefully reviews these materials to see if any seem worth further research.</Para></SummarySection> 
  <SummarySection id="_QandA_2"><Title>Questions to Ask Your Health Care Provider About CAM</Title><Para id="_QandA_3">When considering complementary and alternative therapies, patients should ask their health care provider the following questions: </Para><ItemizedList id="_QandA_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>What side effects can be expected?</ListItem><ListItem>What are the risks related to this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>What benefits can be expected from this therapy?</ListItem><ListItem>Do the known benefits outweigh the risks?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy affect conventional treatment?</ListItem><ListItem>Is this therapy part of a clinical trial?</ListItem><ListItem>If so, who is the sponsor of the trial?</ListItem><ListItem>Will the therapy be covered by health insurance?</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
   
  <SummarySection id="_ToLearnMore_2"><Title>To Learn More About CAM</Title><Para id="_ToLearnMore_3"><Strong><Emphasis>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_4">The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) facilitates research and evaluation of complementary and alternative practices, and provides information about a variety of approaches to health professionals and the public.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_5" Style="simple"><ListItem>NCCIH Clearinghouse</ListItem><ListItem>Post Office Box 7923 Gaithersburg, MD 20898–7923</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-644-6226 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and hard of hearing callers): 1-866-464-3615</ListItem><ListItem>E-mail: info@nccih.nih.gov</ListItem><ListItem>Website:  <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/">https://nccih.nih.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_15"><Strong><Emphasis>CAM on PubMed</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_16">NCCIH and the NIH National Library of Medicine (NLM) jointly developed <ExternalRef xref="https://nccih.nih.gov/research/camonpubmed">CAM on PubMed</ExternalRef>, a free and easy-to-use search tool for finding CAM-related journal citations. As a subset of the NLM's PubMed bibliographic database, CAM on PubMed features more than 230,000 references and abstracts for CAM-related articles from scientific journals. This database also provides links to the websites of over 1,800 journals, allowing users to view full-text articles. (A subscription or other fee may be required to access full-text articles.) </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_17"><Strong><Emphasis>Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_18">The NCI Office of Cancer Complementary and Alternative Medicine (OCCAM) coordinates the activities of the NCI in the area of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM). OCCAM supports CAM cancer research and provides information about cancer-related CAM to health providers and the general public via the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/">NCI website</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_19"><Strong><Emphasis>National Cancer Institute (NCI) Cancer Information Service</Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_20">U.S. residents may call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, toll free at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237) Monday through Friday from 9:00 am to 9:00 pm. A trained Cancer Information Specialist is available to answer your questions.</Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_8"><Strong><Emphasis>Food and Drug Administration </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_9">The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulates drugs and medical devices to ensure that they are safe and effective.</Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_10" Style="simple"><ListItem>Food and Drug Administration </ListItem><ListItem>10903 New Hampshire Avenue</ListItem><ListItem>Silver Spring, MD 20993</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-888-463-6332 (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/">http://www.fda.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_ToLearnMore_11"><Strong><Emphasis>Federal Trade Commission </Emphasis></Strong></Para><Para id="_ToLearnMore_12">The Federal Trade Commission (FTC) enforces consumer protection laws. Publications available from the FTC include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_13" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Emphasis>Who Cares: Sources of Information About Health Care Products and Services </Emphasis></ListItem><ListItem><Emphasis>Fraudulent Health Claims: Don’t Be Fooled </Emphasis></ListItem></ItemizedList><ItemizedList id="_ToLearnMore_14" Style="simple"><ListItem>Consumer Response Center</ListItem><ListItem>Federal Trade Commission</ListItem><ListItem>600 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW</ListItem><ListItem>Washington, DC 20580</ListItem><ListItem>Telephone: 1-877-FTC-HELP (1-877-382-4357) (toll free)</ListItem><ListItem>TTY (for deaf and  hard of hearing callers): 202-326-2502</ListItem><ListItem>Website: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ftc.gov/">http://www.ftc.gov</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection> 
  <PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000742114"/><DateFirstPublished>2013-03-21</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-05-28</DateLastModified></Summary>
