<Summary id="CDR0000778578"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Medicinal mushrooms have been used as an addition to standard cancer treatments in Asia. Mushrooms are being studied to find out how they affect the immune system and if they have anticancer effects. Get detailed information about the use of medicinal mushrooms for cancer in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mushrooms-pdq">Medicinal Mushrooms (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/mushrooms-pdq">Medicinal Mushrooms (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000670889">Maitake mushroom extract</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_169">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of  medicinal mushrooms in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_170">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Coriolus versicolor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Ganoderma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Lingzhi</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>mushrooms</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Reishi</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Trametes versicolor</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Turkey Tail</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Medicinal Mushrooms (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Mushrooms (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Mushrooms</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_2">Medicinal mushrooms have been used for hundreds of years, mainly in Asian countries, for treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infections</GlossaryTermRef>. More recently, they have also been used in the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pulmonary diseases</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Medicinal mushrooms have been approved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367454" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuncts</GlossaryTermRef> to standard cancer treatments in Japan and China for more than 30 years and have an extensive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> history of safe use as single agents or combined with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> therapy or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_3">More than 100 species of medicinal mushrooms are used in Asia. Some of the more commonly used species include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_183" Style="bullet"><ListItem> <ScientificName>Ganoderma lucidum</ScientificName> (reishi).</ListItem><ListItem><ScientificName>Trametes versicolor</ScientificName> or <ScientificName>Coriolus versicolor</ScientificName> (turkey tail).</ListItem><ListItem><ScientificName>Lentinus edodes</ScientificName> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285741" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">shiitake</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem><ScientificName>Grifola frondosa</ScientificName> (maitake).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_4">Studies have examined the effects of  mushrooms on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune response</GlossaryTermRef> pathways and on direct <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antitumor</GlossaryTermRef> mechanisms. The immune effects are mediated through the mushroom's stimulation of innate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune cells</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046282" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monocytes</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044062" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">natural killer cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044948" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dendritic cells</GlossaryTermRef>. The activity is generally considered to be caused by the presence of high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecular-weight</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polysaccharides</GlossaryTermRef> (beta-glucans)  in the mushrooms, although other constituents may also be involved. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> in cancer patients have demonstrated that  <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> products are generally well tolerated.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para><Para id="_196">Several companies distribute medicinal mushrooms as  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>. In the United States, dietary supplements are regulated by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) as a separate category from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. Unlike drugs, dietary supplements do not require premarket evaluation and approval by the FDA unless specific disease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> or treatment claims are made. The quality and amount of ingredients in dietary supplements are also regulated by the FDA through Good Manufacturing Practices (GMPs). The FDA GMPs requires that every finished batch of dietary supplement meets each product specification for identity, purity, strength, composition, and limits on contamination that may <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adulterate</GlossaryTermRef> dietary supplements. Because dietary supplements are not formally reviewed for manufacturing consistency every year, ingredients may vary considerably from lot to lot and there is no guarantee that ingredients claimed on product labels are present (or are present in the specified amounts). The FDA has not approved the use of medicinal mushrooms as a treatment for cancer or any other medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_163">Many of the medical and scientific terms used in this summary are hypertext linked (at first use in each section) to the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary   of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>, which is oriented toward nonexperts. When a linked term is clicked, a definition will appear in a separate window.</Para><Para id="_164">Reference citations in some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> cancer information summaries may include links to external websites that are operated by individuals or organizations for the purpose of marketing or advocating the use of specific treatments or products. These reference citations are included for informational purposes only. Their inclusion should not be viewed as an endorsement of the content of the websites, or of any treatment or product, by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="22696372">Jin X, Ruiz Beguerie J, Sze DM, et al.: Ganoderma lucidum (Reishi mushroom) for cancer treatment. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 6: CD007731, 2012.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>Turkey Tail and Polysaccharide-K</Title><SummarySection id="_8"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_9">Turkey tail is a woody bracket polypore <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044571" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fungus</GlossaryTermRef> that grows on dead logs worldwide. The scientific name of turkey tail is <ScientificName>Trametes versicolor</ScientificName> (L.) Lloyd, although it has been known by other names, notably <ScientificName>Coriolus versicolor</ScientificName> (L. ex Fr.) Quel.   It is known as <Emphasis>Yun Zhi</Emphasis> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">traditional Chinese medicine</GlossaryTermRef> and <Emphasis>Kawaratake</Emphasis> (roof tile fungus) in Japan. The name <Emphasis>turkey tail</Emphasis> refers to its concentric rings of brown and tan, which resemble the tail feathers of a turkey.  There are many other species of <ScientificName>Trametes</ScientificName>, some of which are difficult to distinguish from turkey tail. Internal transcribed spacer  sequences alone have been found inadequate to distinguish turkey tail from other species of <ScientificName>Trametes</ScientificName>, so additional molecular characters are required for that task.<Reference refidx="1"/> Another <ScientificName>Trametes</ScientificName> species used primarily in China is <ScientificName>Trametes robiniophila Murr</ScientificName>, also known as Huaier.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>History</Title><Para id="_11">The fungus has been used in traditional Chinese medicine for many years to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pulmonary diseases</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> A purified hot water <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef> prepared from the cultivated fungal mycelium has been used in Japan for its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367426" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunomodulatory</GlossaryTermRef> effects as an adjuvant treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Polysaccharide</GlossaryTermRef>-K (PSK) or krestin, from the mushroom <ScientificName>T. versicolor</ScientificName>, is an approved mushroom product used for cancer treatment in Japan. PSK is a proprietary formulation from the Kureha Corporation. PSK has been used as an adjunctive cancer treatment in thousands of patients since the mid-1970s. The safety record for PSK is well established in Japan. Few <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse events</GlossaryTermRef> have been reported in patients treated with PSK. Polysaccharopeptide (PSP) is another <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef> from <ScientificName>T. versicolor</ScientificName> produced in China.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_97"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_98"><Title>Chemistry</Title><Para id="_99">The best known constituent of turkey tail is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044034" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glycoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> mixture known  as PSK. PSK is not a homogeneous substance, with a range of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecular weights</GlossaryTermRef> averaging 9.4 kDa (range 5–300 kDa). The glycoprotein <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef> are composed of a main chain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044147" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta-(1,4) glucan</GlossaryTermRef> with beta-(1,3)– and beta-(1,6)–linked side chains. Small amounts of galactose, mannose, and arabinose have also been detected in the hydrolysate. Between 25% and 38% of the mass comes from a covalently linked <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> whose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">amino acid</GlossaryTermRef> composition has been reported.<Reference refidx="4"/> </Para><Para id="_100">PSK <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045857" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiolabeled</GlossaryTermRef> with carbon C-14 has been used to study the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef> and distribution of PSK in mice, rats, and rabbits. A fraction of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> appears to be orally absorbed, more or less intact,  and is excreted in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef> over several hours. However, most of the radiolabeled dose is found in exhaled air, suggesting that the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463707" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestion</GlossaryTermRef> of PSK may occur in the gut or the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> of absorbed PSK may occur somewhere else in the body.<Reference refidx="7"/> A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046066" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monoclonal antibody</GlossaryTermRef> (specific for PSK) that neutralizes PSK's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antitumor</GlossaryTermRef> effects has been developed. It has been used to validate the presence of PSK in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">implanted</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_101">PSP, a very similar substance, has also been purified from a different strain of turkey tail; PSP and PSK differ somewhat in sugar composition.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_102">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lipid</GlossaryTermRef> component of PSK has been separated by lipase treatment and found to have toll-like <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">receptor</GlossaryTermRef> 2  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046054" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">agonist</GlossaryTermRef> activity, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">synergistic</GlossaryTermRef> with the protein-bound <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044147" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta-glucan</GlossaryTermRef>. The lipid component was primarily linoleic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acid</GlossaryTermRef>, with smaller amounts of other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045689" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatty acids</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_103">The nonselective <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000486603" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein kinase inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> hypothemycin <Reference refidx="10"/> and the adipocyte fat accumulation–inhibitory cyclic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peptide</GlossaryTermRef> ternatin <Reference refidx="11"/> have also been isolated from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476357" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cultures</GlossaryTermRef> of <ScientificName>T. versicolor</ScientificName>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_104"><Title>Mechanistic studies</Title><Para id="_106">Since the earliest reports of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> benefits, other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">investigators</GlossaryTermRef> have sought to define the mechanism of PSK’s beneficial action. One group hypothesized that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">T-cell</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390268" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dysfunction</GlossaryTermRef>, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">apoptosis</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peripheral blood</GlossaryTermRef> T cells, commonly occurs in patients receiving <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="12"/>  They postulated that reversal of T-cell dysfunction induced by chemotherapy could reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> or enhance the antitumor effect. PSK is reported to enhance <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044062" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">natural killer (NK) cell</GlossaryTermRef>  and T-cell activities by upregulation of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045256" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-2</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interferon-gamma</GlossaryTermRef>. Twenty patients with curatively <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045868" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resected</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045904" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage III gastric cancer</GlossaryTermRef> were randomly assigned to receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with the second-generation dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase–inhibitory oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386207" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluoropyrimidine</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">S-1</GlossaryTermRef> alone (n = 10) or S-1 plus PSK (n = 10). At 5 weeks after adjuvant therapy, T-cell apoptosis was significantly higher in the S-1–alone group than in the S-1–plus-PSK group, leading the authors to conclude that PSK could partially  prevent the T-cell apoptosis induced by S-1.</Para><Para id="_107">Another group of investigators studied the effect of PSK added to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000530325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tegafur-uracil</GlossaryTermRef> (UFT) chemotherapy compared with  that of UFT alone.<Reference refidx="13"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Baseline</GlossaryTermRef> immune parameters were comparable in the two groups. However, CD57-positive T cells decreased more significantly after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> for patients treated with PSK than for those in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control group</GlossaryTermRef> (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0486). These investigators had previously noted that a high CD57-positive cell count was an indicator of poor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> in patients with advanced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454513" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastric cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, leading them to suggest that PSK may improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overall survival</GlossaryTermRef> (OS) partly by inhibiting CD57-positive T cells.</Para><Para id="_108">Noting that hosts become <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045723" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunocompromised</GlossaryTermRef> at the time of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor progression</GlossaryTermRef> and that decreased expression of major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class I by the tumor is one mechanism that allows  it to evade destruction by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic T</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphocytes</GlossaryTermRef>, investigators conducted a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044956" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retrospective study</GlossaryTermRef> to evaluate the expression of MHC class I by immunohistochemical staining in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary lesions</GlossaryTermRef> of patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046037" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage II</GlossaryTermRef> or stage III gastric cancer.<Reference refidx="14"/> They analyzed data from 349 patients who had undergone adjuvant therapy (after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curative</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046565" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">resection</GlossaryTermRef>) between 1995 and 2008; 225 patients received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> with an oral fluoropyrimidine alone, while 124 patients received adjuvant chemotherapy plus PSK 3 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">g</GlossaryTermRef>/d. Although this was not a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized trial</GlossaryTermRef>, baseline characteristics of the patients were well matched. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean</GlossaryTermRef> duration of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> was 49 months.  Three-year <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrence</GlossaryTermRef>-free survival (RFS) rates were the same for both groups (60% for the PSK group and 62% for the chemotherapy-only group).  For MHC expression–negative cases, the 3-year RFS rates were 65% for  the PSK group and  50% for  the chemotherapy-only group; the difference was not considered <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">significant</GlossaryTermRef>. For 82 MHC expression–negative patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> status of pN2 or greater, the RFS rates were 65% for the PSK group and 34% for the chemotherapy-only group—a significant difference with no <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> value offered. The authors concluded that PSK adjuvant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> may be effective in MHC class I–negative patients with advanced lymph node <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef> of pN2 or greater.</Para><Para id="_109">While the mechanism of action for PSK in general and in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> specifically is not clearly defined, the potential activity of PSK as an immunomodulatory adjunct to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306495" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemoradiation</GlossaryTermRef> therapy in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000529764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> has been studied.<Reference refidx="15"/> Thirty patients with stage II or III rectal cancer who were treated with S-1 and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">external-beam radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> were randomly assigned to receive either the standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimen</GlossaryTermRef> or standard regimen plus PSK. A number of cellular and humoral immune parameters were tested. An increase in peripheral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>  NK cells after therapy was observed in the PSK-treated group compared with the  control group. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044041" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunosuppressive</GlossaryTermRef> acidic protein  (IAP) levels have been reported to be elevated in cancer patients and correlated to cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression</GlossaryTermRef> and prognosis. In the study, a more-marked decrease in  IAP level was observed in patients treated with PSK than in those treated in the control group.  In addition, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytotoxic T cells</GlossaryTermRef> increased in the peritumoral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucosa</GlossaryTermRef> and normal mucosa within the radiation field in the PSK-treated group. The authors of the study concluded that PSK treatment may promote local <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468803" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunity</GlossaryTermRef> within the radiation field.</Para><Para id="_123">One review included <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">preclinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> conducted in
<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef> models using either PSK or other <ScientificName>T. versicolor</ScientificName>
preparations.<Reference refidx="16"/> 
 Data from the 15 preclinical studies supported the anticancer effects of PSK by way of immunomodulation and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330176" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">potentiation</GlossaryTermRef> of immune surveillance. In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal models</GlossaryTermRef>, direct antitumor effects resulted in reduced tumor growth and metastases.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_77"><Title>Human Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_78"><Title>Gastric cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_79"><Title> Observational studies</Title><Para id="_80">Gastric cancer is the most common <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045771" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignancy</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> in Korea. Investigators in Korea performed a retrospective <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef> of survival in patients who received PSK in addition to chemotherapy and in those who received  chemotherapy only (control group).<Reference refidx="17"/>  Unfortunately, the chemotherapy regimens differed in that the PSK patients were treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluorouracil</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000713798" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mitomycin-C</GlossaryTermRef> (207 patients), while the controls received fluorouracil with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef>-based chemotherapy (103 patients), introducing a potential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bias</GlossaryTermRef> in the interpretation of the results. Patients with all stages of gastric cancer were included in the analysis. Overall, there was no difference between groups in 5-year <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disease-free survival</GlossaryTermRef> (DFS) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044782" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression-free survival</GlossaryTermRef> (PFS) rates. In a subgroup analysis, PSK recipients with stage IB or stage II disease showed superior 5-year survival (84.4% vs. 67.6%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .019), but no significant benefit was observed in patients with higher-stage disease.</Para><Para id="_81">Another retrospective analysis of nonrandomized data evaluated 254 patients with gastric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045963" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> undergoing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688838" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curative surgery</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043980" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postoperative</GlossaryTermRef> adjuvant treatment in Japan.<Reference refidx="18"/> Researchers compared 139 patients who received chemotherapy  alone with 115 patients who received chemotherapy plus PSK. There were no significant differences between groups in patient demographics or tumor characteristics at baseline.  There were no differences between groups in 5-year RFS rates (52.7% in the PSK group and 52.7% in the control group) or 5-year OS rates (57.1% in the PSK group and 58.3% in the control group). In a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285981" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">subset analysis</GlossaryTermRef> of patients with more than seven involved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> (pN3), the 5-year OS rate was significantly higher in the PSK group (47.8%) than that in the control group (22.8%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0317). Hence, these results contradict the findings from the Korean analysis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_110"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_122">A study published in 1994 first suggested the clinical benefit of adjuvant PSK for patients who underwent curative resection of gastric cancer in Japan.<Reference refidx="19"/> Investigators randomly assigned 262 patients who had undergone curative <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046397" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrectomy</GlossaryTermRef> to receive either <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> mitomycin and oral fluorouracil, or chemotherapy plus protein-bound PSK.  Patients were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454803" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monitored</GlossaryTermRef> for 5 to 7 years.  PSK improved both the 5-year DFS rate (70.7% vs. 59.4%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .047) and 5-year <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survival rate</GlossaryTermRef> (73.0% vs. 60.0%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .044), compared with the standard treatment group. Treatment with PSK was well tolerated, with good <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446112" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compliance</GlossaryTermRef>. The authors concluded that PSK should be added to standard chemotherapy for gastric cancer patients who undergo curative gastrectomy.</Para><Para id="_111">A 2007 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meta-analysis</GlossaryTermRef> included 8,009 patients from eight <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled trials</GlossaryTermRef> (RCTs) of adjuvant PSK in patients after curative resection of gastric cancers:<Reference refidx="20"/>  4,037 patients received  PSK with chemotherapy, and 3,972 patients received  the same chemotherapy alone. The OS <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000618612" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hazard ratio</GlossaryTermRef>  (HR) was 0.88 (95% confidence interval [CI], 0.79–0.98; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .018), indicating improved  survival with the addition of PSK, with no significant heterogeneity between the treatment effects observed in the different studies. The three trials with the best quality supported the findings from the eight studies. The authors concluded that PSK was effective as adjuvant immunotherapy for patients with gastric cancer and suggested that this improvement may well be both statistically and clinically significant.</Para><Para id="_112">One other large study not included in this meta-analysis was a Japanese multicenter comparative trial of adjuvant chemotherapy versus adjuvant chemotherapy and PSK  involving 751 patients undergoing curative resection, conducted from 1978 to 1981.<Reference refidx="21"/> Patients were randomly assigned to receive either  chemotherapy with mitomycin-C  plus oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045201" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tegafur</GlossaryTermRef> (also known as futraful) with (n = 377) or without (n = 374) PSK 3 g/d. After reviewing 20 years of data, the investigators stratified patients on the basis of the ratio of their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">granulocytes</GlossaryTermRef> to lymphocytes (G/L), believing that G/L ratios above 2.0 would predict responders. The 5-year OS rates were 67.9% in the PSK group and 61.8% in the control group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .053). In the subset of 364 patients with G/L ratios above 2.0, 5-year survival rates were 68.7% in the PSK group and 55.4% in the control group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .007). Because the G/L  ratio was not related to stage, the authors suggested that the G/L ratio may be a host-dependent factor and might be useful to predict who might respond best to adjuvant PSK.</Para><Para id="_124">Finally, another small study has been reported since the meta-analysis.<Reference refidx="13"/> Patients received either oral UFT 300 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/d or UFT plus PSK 3 g/d for at least 1 year after undergoing gastric resection for stage II or stage III gastric cancer. The 3-year survival rate was 62.2% in the 10 patients who received PSK and 12.5% in the 11 patients who received UFT alone (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .038).</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_167"><Title>Breast cancer</Title><Para id="_168">So far, studies that have reported on the use of <ScientificName>T. versicolor</ScientificName> products in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> have focused on documenting changes in immune parameters (e.g., changes in T-cell subsets and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045611" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">B-cell</GlossaryTermRef> numbers in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>) as opposed to clinical parameters (e.g., patient survival, resolution of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>, or improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>).<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_114"><Title>Colorectal cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_115"><Title>Observational studies</Title><Para id="_116">A retrospective study was conducted by two groups from Japan. The study examined the impact on survival in patients with colorectal cancer who received adjuvant treatment with oral fluoropyrimidine with the addition of PSK.<Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/> The first study was conducted at a single institution in Japan and analyzed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcomes</GlossaryTermRef> from 101 patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000520509" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Dukes B</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000520510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Dukes C colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> who were treated with UFT or UFT with PSK for 24 months after curative surgery. These patients were monitored for up to 10 years after surgery.<Reference refidx="25"/> The 10-year survival rate was significantly better for patients treated with PSK (HR, 0.3). The second study examined the results of 63 patients with colorectal cancer who were older than 70 years and treated with UFT with or without PSK. The 3-year <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapse-free survival</GlossaryTermRef> rates were 76.2% in the PSK group and 47.8% in the UFT-only group (control). The 3-year OS rates were 80.8% in the PSK group and 52.8% in the control group.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_119"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> of PSK in colorectal cancer have shown reduction in recurrence and improvement in OS with adjuvant use.</Para><Para id="_121">A meta-analysis of randomized, centrally assigned, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prospective</GlossaryTermRef> clinical trials of adjuvant therapy with PSK published between 1980 and 2004 identified three clinical trials that met selection criteria covering 1,094 patients.<Reference refidx="26"/> Combining the data from all three trials, the researchers found that the estimated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000618610" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">odds ratio</GlossaryTermRef> (OR) for the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_184" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year DFS was 0.72 (95% CI, 0.58–0.90; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003, favoring PSK).</ListItem><ListItem>The 5-year OS was 0.71 (95% CI, 0.55–0.90; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006, favoring PSK). </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_85"><Title>Lung cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_90"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_91">Thirty-one reports of 28 studies were included in a systematic review of PSK in lung cancer:<Reference refidx="16"/>  </Para><ItemizedList id="_185" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Seventeen preclinical studies.</ListItem><ListItem>Five nonrandomized controlled trials.</ListItem><ListItem> Six RCTs.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_186">All five nonrandomized controlled trials reported improved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044941" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">median</GlossaryTermRef> survival with the use of PSK in combination with conventional <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and/or chemotherapy. PSK 3 g/d with concurrent chemotherapy was used in all  RCTs, and all six studies showed benefit for at least one of the following endpoints:</Para><ItemizedList id="_187" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Immune function measures.</ListItem><ListItem>Body weight.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044174" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Performance status</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Tumor-related symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem>Survival.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><Table id="_125"><Title>Table 1.  Clinical Studies of Turkey Tail<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="8"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="11.98%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="11.98%"/><ColSpec ColName="col03" ColNum="3" ColWidth="14.17%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="12.21%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="12.32%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="6" ColWidth="13.13%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="7" ColWidth="11.52%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="8" ColWidth="12.67%"/><THead><Row><entry>Reference</entry><entry>Trial Design</entry><entry>Product and Dose</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Condition</GlossaryTermRef> or Cancer Type</entry><entry>Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Placebo</GlossaryTermRef> or No Treatment Control)<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry>Results </entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Concurrent Therapy</GlossaryTermRef> Used</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Level of Evidence</GlossaryTermRef> Score<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1">G/L = granulocyte to lymphocyte count; OR = odds ratio; PSK = polysaccharide-K; RCT = randomized controlled trial; UFT = tegafur-uracil.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For more information and definition of terms, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Number of patients treated plus number of patient controls may not equal number of patients enrolled; number of patients enrolled equals number of patients initially recruited/considered by the researchers who conducted a study; number of patients treated equals number of enrolled patients who were given the treatment being studied AND for whom results were reported.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Strongest evidence reported that the treatment under study has activity or otherwise improves the well-being of cancer patients. For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of evidence</GlossaryTermRef> analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="21"/></entry><entry>RCT
</entry><entry>PSK (3 g/d)
</entry><entry>Gastric cancer</entry><entry>751; 376; 374
(groups were stratified by G/L ratio of &lt;2 vs. &gt;2)</entry><entry>Overall 5-y survival: all patients, 67.9% (PSK) versus 61.8% (control) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .053); 
for G/L ratio ≥2:
68.7% (PSK) versus 55.4% (control) (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .007) 
</entry><entry>Mitomycin-C plus tegafur</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335123" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="19"/></entry><entry>RCT
</entry><entry>PSK (3 g/d)
</entry><entry>Gastric cancer</entry><entry>262; 124; 129</entry><entry>Improved survival in the treatment group was clinically significant</entry><entry>Mitomycin-C plus oral fluorouracil</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335123" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>RCT</entry><entry>PSK (3 g/d)</entry><entry>Gastric cancer</entry><entry>21; 10; 11</entry><entry>Survival was improved significantly in treatment group</entry><entry>UFT 300 mg/d starting 2 wk after surgery and continuing for 1 y or until diagnosis of tumor recurrence</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335123" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="27"/></entry><entry>Meta-analysis summarizing 48 studies</entry><entry>PSK (various doses)</entry><entry>Colorectal cancer</entry><entry>3 trials; 1,094 patients</entry><entry>5-y survival:
79.0% (chemotherapy plus PSK) versus 72.2% (chemotherapy alone) (OR,  0.71; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .006)</entry><entry>Mitomycin-C plus long-term <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> of oral fluorinated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000650574" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pyrimidines</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335120" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iB</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="24898532">Carlson A, Justo A, Hibbett DS: Species delimitation in Trametes: a comparison of ITS, RPB1, RPB2 and TEF1 gene phylogenies. Mycologia 106 (4): 735-45, 2014 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9457474">Ng TB: A review of research on the protein-bound polysaccharide (polysaccharopeptide, PSP) from the mushroom Coriolus versicolor (Basidiomycetes: Polyporaceae). Gen Pharmacol 30 (1): 1-4, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Ying J, Mao X, Ma Q, et al.: Icons of Medicinal Fungi from China. Science Press, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="6238674">Tsukagoshi S, Hashimoto Y, Fujii G, et al.: Krestin (PSK). Cancer Treat Rev 11 (2): 131-55, 1984.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="14499133">Cui J, Chisti Y: Polysaccharopeptides of Coriolus versicolor: physiological activity, uses, and production. Biotechnol Adv 21 (2): 109-22, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2064356">Sakagami H, Aoki T, Simpson A, et al.: Induction of immunopotentiation activity by a protein-bound polysaccharide, PSK (review). Anticancer Res 11 (2): 993-9, 1991 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="3170055">Ikuzawa M, Matsunaga K, Nishiyama S, et al.: Fate and distribution of an antitumor protein-bound polysaccharide PSK (Krestin). Int J Immunopharmacol 10 (4): 415-23, 1988.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="21249323">Hoshi H, Saito H, Iijima H, et al.: Anti-protein-bound polysaccharide-K monoclonal antibody binds the active structure and neutralizes direct antitumor action of the compound. Oncol Rep 25 (4): 905-13, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="25510899">Quayle K, Coy C, Standish L, et al.: The TLR2 agonist in polysaccharide-K is a structurally distinct lipid which acts synergistically with the protein-bound β-glucan. J Nat Med 69 (2): 198-208, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="25399643">Miller RM, Taunton J: Targeting protein kinases with selective and semipromiscuous covalent inhibitors. Methods Enzymol 548: 93-116, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="8307686">Miller R, Galitsky NM, Duax WL, et al.: Molecular structures of two crystalline forms of the cyclic heptapeptide antibiotic ternatin, cyclo[-beta-OH-D-Leu-D-Ile-(NMe)Ala-(NMe)Leu-Leu-(NMe)Ala-D-(NMe)Ala-]. Int J Pept Protein Res 42 (6): 539-49, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="18708731">Kono K, Kawaguchi Y, Mizukami Y, et al.: Protein-bound polysaccharide K partially prevents apoptosis of circulating T cells induced by anti-cancer drug S-1 in patients with gastric cancer. Oncology 74 (3-4): 143-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="20229169">Akagi J, Baba H: PSK may suppress CD57(+) T cells to improve survival of advanced gastric cancer patients. Int J Clin Oncol 15 (2): 145-52, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="22969994">Ito G, Tanaka H, Ohira M, et al.: Correlation between efficacy of PSK postoperative adjuvant immunochemotherapy for gastric cancer and expression of MHC class I. Exp Ther Med 3 (6): 925-930, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="20393026">Sadahiro S, Suzuki T, Maeda Y, et al.: Effects of preoperative immunochemoradiotherapy and chemoradiotherapy on immune responses in patients with rectal adenocarcinoma. Anticancer Res 30 (3): 993-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="25784670">Fritz H, Kennedy DA, Ishii M, et al.: Polysaccharide K and Coriolus versicolor extracts for lung cancer: a systematic review. Integr Cancer Ther 14 (3): 201-11, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="17419278">Choi JH, Kim YB, Lim HY, et al.: 5-fluorouracil, mitomycin-C, and polysaccharide-K adjuvant chemoimmunotherapy for locally advanced gastric cancer: the prognostic significance of frequent perineural invasion. Hepatogastroenterology 54 (73): 290-7, 2007 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="22843926">Tanaka H, Muguruma K, Ohira M, et al.: Impact of adjuvant immunochemotherapy using protein-bound polysaccharide-K on overall survival of patients with gastric cancer. Anticancer Res 32 (8): 3427-33, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="7910230">Nakazato H, Koike A, Saji S, et al.: Efficacy of immunochemotherapy as adjuvant treatment after curative resection of gastric cancer. Study Group of Immunochemotherapy with PSK for Gastric Cancer. Lancet 343 (8906): 1122-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="17106715">Oba K, Teramukai S, Kobayashi M, et al.: Efficacy of adjuvant immunochemotherapy with polysaccharide K for patients with curative resections of gastric cancer. Cancer Immunol Immunother 56 (6): 905-11, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="10948356">Toge T, Yamaguchi Y: Protein-bound polysaccharide increases survival in resected gastric cancer cases stratified with a preoperative granulocyte and lymphocyte count. Oncol Rep 7 (5): 1157-61, 2000 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="16047556">Wong CK, Bao YX, Wong EL, et al.: Immunomodulatory activities of Yunzhi and Danshen in post-treatment breast cancer patients. Am J Chin Med 33 (3): 381-95, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="22701186">Torkelson CJ, Sweet E, Martzen MR, et al.: Phase 1 Clinical Trial of Trametes versicolor in Women with Breast Cancer. ISRN Oncol 2012: 251632, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="19243246">Yoshitani S, Takashima S: Efficacy of postoperative UFT (Tegafur/Uracil) plus PSK therapies in elderly patients with resected colorectal cancer. Cancer Biother Radiopharm 24 (1): 35-40, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="18771350">Sakai T, Yamashita Y, Maekawa T, et al.: Immunochemotherapy with PSK and fluoropyrimidines improves long-term prognosis for curatively resected colorectal cancer. Cancer Biother Radiopharm 23 (4): 461-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="36445793">Pilkington K, Wieland LS, Teng L, et al.: Coriolus (Trametes) versicolor mushroom to reduce adverse effects from chemotherapy or radiotherapy in people with colorectal cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 11 (11): CD012053, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="16133112">Sakamoto J, Morita S, Oba K, et al.: Efficacy of adjuvant immunochemotherapy with polysaccharide K for patients with curatively resected colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis of centrally randomized controlled clinical trials. Cancer Immunol Immunother 55 (4): 404-11, 2006.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><Title>Reishi (<ScientificName>Ganoderma lucidum</ScientificName>)</Title><SummarySection id="_129"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_130"><ScientificName>Ganoderma</ScientificName> is a genus of woody polypore <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044571" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fungi</GlossaryTermRef> which grow on live trees. In the Chinese Pharmacopeia, the official species are <ScientificName>Ganoderma lucidum</ScientificName> (Leyss. ex Fr.) P. Karst and <ScientificName>Ganoderma sinense</ScientificName> Zhao, Xu et Zhang. Another commonly encountered species is <ScientificName>Ganoderma lingzhi Wu</ScientificName>, Cao et Dai. In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">traditional Chinese medicine</GlossaryTermRef>, the fungi are collectively known as Ling Zhi; in Japan, they are known as Reishi. In China, <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> is known  as Chizhi and <ScientificName>G. sinense</ScientificName> is known as Zizhi.</Para><Para id="_131">Recent molecular taxonomic and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef> studies have made it clear that the originally described European species <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> and the East Asian medicinal species are not identical.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> The newly accepted name for the East Asian species traditionally called <ScientificName>G.  lucidum</ScientificName>  is <ScientificName>Ganoderma sichuanense</ScientificName>. 
 However, most research worldwide has been published under the name <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName>.  This includes the full <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044593" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genome</GlossaryTermRef> sequence of <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName>.<Reference refidx="6"/> There are many other species of <ScientificName>Ganoderma</ScientificName>, which are difficult to distinguish from the medicinal species.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_132"><Title>History</Title><Para id="_133"><ScientificName>Ganoderma</ScientificName> has a very long history in East Asia as a medicinal mushroom dating back to the Chinese materia medica “Shen Nung Ben Cao Jing,” written between 206 BC and  8 AD. It was considered a superior tonic for prolonging life, preventing aging, and boosting <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454782" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">qi</GlossaryTermRef>. It has been associated with royalty, perhaps due to its rarity in the wild. It was also revered in Japanese <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476357" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">culture</GlossaryTermRef>. It is used by contemporary Chinese <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physicians</GlossaryTermRef> to support <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045721" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune function</GlossaryTermRef> in patients undergoing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, among other uses.<Reference refidx="7"/> In some parts of the world (e.g., Shanghai), cancer patients commonly use supplements containing <ScientificName>Ganoderma lucidum</ScientificName>.<Reference refidx="8"/> The development of improved <ScientificName>Ganoderma</ScientificName> products is currently under way using biotechnological processes.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_154"><Title>Chemistry</Title><Para id="_158">Among the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biologically</GlossaryTermRef> active components of <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> are triterpenoids, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polysaccharides</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lipids</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Most <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory research</GlossaryTermRef> studies have utilized <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> products obtained via any of several extraction processes, which produce products that contain a mixture of two or more of these molecular species. This lack of purity of the products under study may account for some of the overlap of biological activities attributed to the individual components.</Para><Para id="_156">The best-studied <ScientificName>Ganoderma</ScientificName> polysaccharides possess mostly 1,3- and 1,4-glycosidic linkages, which are of high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecular weight</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="10"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044147" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Beta-glucans</GlossaryTermRef> are known to bind to the complement <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">receptor</GlossaryTermRef> CR3.<Reference refidx="13"/> The activity is considered to be immunomodulatory in nature, similar to many other medicinal fungi. It has recently been pointed out that <ScientificName>Ganoderma</ScientificName> products derived from mycelium grown on different grain substrates contain large amounts of alpha-glucans derived from the substrate, compared with the fruiting body and its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef>, which are entirely beta-glucan in nature.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_157">Many <ScientificName>Ganoderma</ScientificName> species produce large amounts of oxidized lanostane triterpenes in a complex mixture. <ScientificName>Ganoderma</ScientificName> triterpenes are unique to the genus. Some <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> triterpenes have been found to inhibit <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000695994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer cell line</GlossaryTermRef> growth, although many of the major triterpenes are relatively weak inhibitors or inactive.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>
 Analytical studies have examined the relative amounts of the different triterpenes in fruiting bodies, as well as in mycelial preparations.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/>
The mammalian <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> of the triterpenes has been studied singly and in combination, with numerous sites of metabolism identified.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><Title><ScientificName>In vitro</ScientificName> studies</Title><Para id="_141">Several <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName>-derived products have been studied in preclinical models and reported to produce anticancer effects. Both triterpenoids and polysaccharides cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> growth arrest and cytotoxicity.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="26"/><Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/> Studies of the cellular pathway by which <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> triterpenoids produce cytotoxicity have generally implicated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">apoptosis</GlossaryTermRef> pathways, both the intrinsic or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044060" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mitochondrial</GlossaryTermRef> pathway <Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/><Reference refidx="27"/>  and the extrinsic or death receptor pathway.<Reference refidx="29"/> Triterpenoids also inhibit adhesion and migration of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> cells.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/> The lipid and protein components of <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> have been less studied but also have demonstrated <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> cytotoxicity.<Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/></Para><Para id="_142">Polysaccharides from <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> have been shown to induce <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044948" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dendritic cell</GlossaryTermRef> maturation, thus raising the possibility that these products might support or elicit immune-mediated anticancer actions.<Reference refidx="35"/></Para><Para id="_143">Other potential mechanisms of anticancer activity have been demonstrated, including reports of the induction of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">differentiation</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> cells <ScientificName>in vitro</ScientificName> <Reference refidx="36"/>  and the inhibition of cellular secretion of factors associated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>-induced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046529" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">angiogenesis</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vascular endothelial growth factor</GlossaryTermRef> (VEGF) and transforming growth factor (TGF)-beta.<Reference refidx="37"/></Para><Para id="_179">Ganoderenic acid B, a <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> derived triterpene, has been shown to enhance the cytotoxicity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044009" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapeutic agents</GlossaryTermRef> in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000416100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug-resistant</GlossaryTermRef> cell line of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatocellular carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> by inhibiting the transport function of the  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045009" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenosine triphosphate</GlossaryTermRef> (ATP)-binding cassette (ABC) superfamily transporters.<Reference refidx="38"/> This finding led the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">investigators</GlossaryTermRef> to conclude that ganoderenic acid B may have the potential to be developed into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045790" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multidrug resistance</GlossaryTermRef> reversal agent.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_144"><Title><ScientificName>In vivo</ScientificName> studies</Title><Para id="_145">Relatively few studies have explored the <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> effects of <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal models</GlossaryTermRef>, but those available have shown <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antitumor</GlossaryTermRef> activity of triterpenoids in mice bearing Lewis <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045963" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="39"/>  and antitumor effects of polysaccharides in mice bearing S180 cells <Reference refidx="40"/> and Ehrlich ascites cells.<Reference refidx="41"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><Title>Human Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_147"><Title>Lung cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_148"><Title>Mechanistic studies</Title><Para id="_149">There are no studies of <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> with measured cancer outcomes. Building on the preclinical evidence that the polysaccharide fractions of <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> enhance host immune function and have potential antitumor activity, investigators studied an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044696" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">over-the-counter</GlossaryTermRef> product in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="42"/>  Patients received Ganopoly, an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aqueous</GlossaryTermRef> polysaccharide fraction extracted from <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> fruiting bodies. In an open-label trial, 36 patients with advanced lung cancer at a  hospital in China, enrolled and 30 were accessible for immune function after 12 weeks. The patients were treated with chemotherapy or radiation therapy, and other complementary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef>. Ganopoly was administered as 1,800 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsules</GlossaryTermRef> 3 times daily before meals for 12 weeks. Treatment did not significantly alter the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean</GlossaryTermRef> mitogenic reactivity to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467859" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phytohemagglutinin</GlossaryTermRef>; mean counts of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045765" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphocyte</GlossaryTermRef> subsets CD3, CD4, CD8, and CD56; mean <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> concentrations on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045256" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-2</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044045" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-6</GlossaryTermRef>, or interferon-gamma; or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044062" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">natural killer cell</GlossaryTermRef> activity (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &gt; .05). The investigators noted that some patients did experience some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">significant</GlossaryTermRef> changes in the parameters studied, but the group effect was null overall. </Para><Para id="_150">Another mechanistic study in China investigated whether <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> polysaccharides could counteract the immune suppression mediated by the plasma of patients with lung cancer.<Reference refidx="43"/> It is postulated that cancer cells release <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044041" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunosuppressive</GlossaryTermRef> mediators such as PGE2, TGF-beta, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000682069" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">IL-10</GlossaryTermRef>, and VEGF to inhibit the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune response</GlossaryTermRef> and escape from immune <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef>.  <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> polysaccharides had been shown to counteract this immune suppression in an animal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556412" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell culture</GlossaryTermRef> model; therefore,  this experiment was undertaken to evaluate whether the effect could be duplicated in humans. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood</GlossaryTermRef> was obtained from 12 lung cancer patients. The <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> polysaccharides were isolated from a boiling water extract of <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> fruit bodies by ethanol precipitation. CD69 expression on mononuclear lymphocytes after phytohemagglutinin stimulation was inhibited markedly compared with controls (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .05) after a 24-hour incubation with lung cancer patient plasma. <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> polysaccharides at concentrations of 3.2 μg/mL and 12.8 µg/mL significantly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350250" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antagonized</GlossaryTermRef> this inhibition (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .05 for both). Similar results were observed with additional assays leading the investigators to conclude that lung cancer patient plasma-induced suppression of lymphocyte activation by phytohemagglutinin may be fully or partially antagonized by <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> polysaccharides, making them an attractive adjuvant in cancer treatment.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_151"><Title>Colorectal cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_152"><Title>Prevention</Title><Para id="_153">Japanese investigators studied a water-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soluble</GlossaryTermRef> extract from a cultured medium of <ScientificName>G. lucidum</ScientificName> mycelia (MAK) in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046217" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenomas</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="44"/> After being <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef>  with colorectal adenomas on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef>, 123 patients were enrolled in the MAK treatment group, and 102 no-treatment controls were randomly selected from the department’s patients.  The treatment group was administered 1.5 g/d of MAK for 12 months. Both groups underwent repeat colonoscopy at 12 months. The change in the number of adenomas was +0.66 +/- 0.10  in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control group</GlossaryTermRef> and -0.42 +/- 0.10  in the treated group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01). The total size of adenomas increased by 1.73 +/- 0.28 mm in the control group and decreased by -1.40 +/- 0.64 mm in the MAK group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01). These results suggest that MAK may suppress the development of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045846" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">premalignant</GlossaryTermRef> colorectal adenomas.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="27507489">Raja HA, Baker TR, Little JG, et al.: DNA barcoding for identification of consumer-relevant mushrooms: A partial solution for product certification? Food Chem 214: 383-92, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="27044336">Hennicke F, Cheikh-Ali Z, Liebisch T, et al.: Distinguishing commercially grown Ganoderma lucidum from Ganoderma lingzhi from Europe and East Asia on the basis of morphology, molecular phylogeny, and triterpenic acid profiles. Phytochemistry 127: 29-37, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="28056060">Zhang X, Xu Z, Pei H, et al.: Intraspecific Variation and Phylogenetic Relationships Are Revealed by ITS1 Secondary Structure Analysis and Single-Nucleotide Polymorphism in Ganoderma lucidum. PLoS One 12 (1): e0169042, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="26300957">Liao B, Chen X, Han J, et al.: Identification of commercial Ganoderma (Lingzhi) species by ITS2 sequences. Chin Med 10: 22, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21148895">Hong SG, Jung HS: Phylogenetic analysis of Ganoderma based on nearly complete mitochondrial small-subunit ribosomal DNA sequences. Mycologia 96 (4): 742-55, 2004 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="22735441">Chen S, Xu J, Liu C, et al.: Genome sequence of the model medicinal mushroom Ganoderma lucidum. Nat Commun 3: 913, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Upton R, ed.: Reishi Mushroom: Ganoderma Lucidum: Standards of Analysis, Quality Control, and Therapeutics. American Herbal Pharmacopoeia, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="22745737">Bao PP, Lu W, Cui Y, et al.: Ginseng and Ganoderma lucidum use after breast cancer diagnosis and quality of life: a report from the Shanghai Breast Cancer Survival Study. PLoS One 7 (6): e39343, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="23227951">Boh B: Ganoderma lucidum: a potential for biotechnological production of anti-cancer and immunomodulatory drugs. Recent Pat Anticancer Drug Discov 8 (3): 255-87, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="25457487">Ferreira IC, Heleno SA, Reis FS, et al.: Chemical features of Ganoderma polysaccharides with antioxidant, antitumor and antimicrobial activities. Phytochemistry 114: 38-55, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="25975187">Baby S, Johnson AJ, Govindan B: Secondary metabolites from Ganoderma. Phytochemistry 114: 66-101, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="25361420">Xia Q, Zhang H, Sun X, et al.: A comprehensive review of the structure elucidation and biological activity of triterpenoids from Ganoderma spp. Molecules 19 (11): 17478-535, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="10477568">Yan J, Vetvicka V, Xia Y, et al.: Beta-glucan, a "specific" biologic response modifier that uses antibodies to target tumors for cytotoxic recognition by leukocyte complement receptor type 3 (CD11b/CD18). J Immunol 163 (6): 3045-52, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Chilton J: A new analytical fingerprinting system for quality control of medicinal mushroom products. In: Baars JJP, Sonnenberg ASM, eds.: Science and Cultivation of Edible and Medicinal
Fungi: Mushroom Science XIX. Proceedings of the 19th Congress of the International Society
for Mushroom Science. International Society for Mushroom Science, 2016, pp 267-71. <ExternalRef xref="https://library.wur.nl/WebQuery/wurpubs/fulltext/400213">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed April 24, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="20615519">Cheng CR, Yue QX, Wu ZY, et al.: Cytotoxic triterpenoids from Ganoderma lucidum. Phytochemistry 71 (13): 1579-85, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="23790022">Wu GS, Guo JJ, Bao JL, et al.: Anti-cancer properties of triterpenoids isolated from Ganoderma lucidum - a review. Expert Opin Investig Drugs 22 (8): 981-92, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="28052025">Chen S, Li X, Yong T, et al.: Cytotoxic lanostane-type triterpenoids from the fruiting bodies of Ganoderma lucidum and their structure-activity relationships. Oncotarget 8 (6): 10071-10084, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="25212865">Da J, Cheng CR, Yao S, et al.: A reproducible analytical system based on the multi-component analysis of triterpene acids in Ganoderma lucidum. Phytochemistry 114: 146-54, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="22586399">Qi Y, Zhao L, Sun HH: Development of a rapid and confirmatory method to identify ganoderic acids in ganoderma mushrooms. Front Pharmacol 3: 85, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="24189202">Cheng CR, Yang M, Yu K, et al.: Metabolite identification of crude extract from Ganoderma lucidum in rats using ultra-performance liquid chromatography-quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometry. J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci 941: 90-9, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="21109986">Shang D, Li Y, Wang C, et al.: A novel polysaccharide from Se-enriched Ganoderma lucidum induces apoptosis of human breast cancer cells. Oncol Rep 25 (1): 267-72, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="18425349">Jiang J, Grieb B, Thyagarajan A, et al.: Ganoderic acids suppress growth and invasive behavior of breast cancer cells by modulating AP-1 and NF-kappaB signaling. Int J Mol Med 21 (5): 577-84, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="21036023">Liu RM, Zhong JJ: Ganoderic acid Mf and S induce mitochondria mediated apoptosis in human cervical carcinoma HeLa cells. Phytomedicine 18 (5): 349-55, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="26397202">Liang ZE, Yi YJ, Guo YT, et al.: Inhibition of migration and induction of apoptosis in LoVo human colon cancer cells by polysaccharides from Ganoderma lucidum. Mol Med Rep 12 (5): 7629-36, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="24857920">Liang Z, Yi Y, Guo Y, et al.: Chemical characterization and antitumor activities of polysaccharide extracted from Ganoderma lucidum. Int J Mol Sci 15 (5): 9103-16, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="23670292">Hsieh TC, Wu JM: Regulation of cell cycle transition and induction of apoptosis in HL-60 leukemia cells by the combination of Coriolus versicolor and Ganoderma lucidum. Int J Mol Med 32 (1): 251-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="18481862">Hsu CL, Yu YS, Yen GC: Lucidenic acid B induces apoptosis in human leukemia cells via a mitochondria-mediated pathway. J Agric Food Chem 56 (11): 3973-80, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="26292672">Ruan W, Wei Y, Popovich DG: Distinct Responses of Cytotoxic Ganoderma lucidum Triterpenoids in Human Carcinoma Cells. Phytother Res 29 (11): 1744-52, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="17786330">Zaidman BZ, Wasser SP, Nevo E, et al.: Androgen receptor-dependent and -independent mechanisms mediate Ganoderma lucidum activities in LNCaP prostate cancer cells. Int J Oncol 31 (4): 959-67, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="26489631">Wang T, Xie ZP, Huang ZS, et al.: Total triterpenoids from Ganoderma Lucidum suppresses prostate cancer cell growth by inducing growth arrest and apoptosis. J Huazhong Univ Sci Technolog Med Sci 35 (5): 736-41, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="24204647">Wu GS, Song YL, Yin ZQ, et al.: Ganoderiol A-enriched extract suppresses migration and adhesion of MDA-MB-231 cells by inhibiting FAK-SRC-paxillin cascade pathway. PLoS One 8 (10): e76620, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="18024477">Weng CJ, Chau CF, Hsieh YS, et al.: Lucidenic acid inhibits PMA-induced invasion of human hepatoma cells through inactivating MAPK/ERK signal transduction pathway and reducing binding activities of NF-kappaB and AP-1. Carcinogenesis 29 (1): 147-56, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="22179718">Liang C, Li H, Zhou H, et al.: Recombinant Lz-8 from Ganoderma lucidum induces endoplasmic reticulum stress-mediated autophagic cell death in SGC-7901 human gastric cancer cells. Oncol Rep 27 (4): 1079-89, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="22172327">Wang JH, Zhou YJ, Zhang M, et al.: Active lipids of Ganoderma lucidum spores-induced apoptosis in human leukemia THP-1 cells via MAPK and PI3K pathways. J Ethnopharmacol 139 (2): 582-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="18644156">Chan WK, Cheung CC, Law HK, et al.: Ganoderma lucidum polysaccharides can induce human monocytic leukemia cells into dendritic cells with immuno-stimulatory function. J Hematol Oncol 1: 9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="18938219">Pinweha S, Wanikiat P, Sanvarinda Y, et al.: The signaling cascades of Ganoderma lucidum extracts in stimulating non-amyloidogenic protein secretion in human neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y cell lines. Neurosci Lett 448 (1): 62-6, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="15781230">Stanley G, Harvey K, Slivova V, et al.: Ganoderma lucidum suppresses angiogenesis through the inhibition of secretion of VEGF and TGF-beta1 from prostate cancer cells. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 330 (1): 46-52, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="25779097">Liu DL, Li YJ, Yang DH, et al.: Ganoderma lucidum derived ganoderenic acid B reverses ABCB1-mediated multidrug resistance in HepG2/ADM cells. Int J Oncol 46 (5): 2029-38, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="24379669">Qu D, He J, Liu C, et al.: Triterpene-loaded microemulsion using Coix lacryma-jobi seed extract as oil phase for enhanced antitumor efficacy: preparation and in vivo evaluation. Int J Nanomedicine 9: 109-19, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="18695905">Li YB, Wang R, Wu HL, et al.: Serum amyloid A mediates the inhibitory effect of Ganoderma lucidum polysaccharides on tumor cell adhesion to endothelial cells. Oncol Rep 20 (3): 549-56, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="21945912">Joseph S, Sabulal B, George V, et al.: Antitumor and anti-inflammatory activities of polysaccharides isolated from Ganoderma lucidum. Acta Pharm 61 (3): 335-42, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="16117607">Gao Y, Tang W, Dai X, et al.: Effects of water-soluble Ganoderma lucidum polysaccharides on the immune functions of patients with advanced lung cancer. J Med Food 8 (2): 159-68, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="24525691">Sun LX, Li WD, Lin ZB, et al.: Protection against lung cancer patient plasma-induced lymphocyte suppression by Ganoderma lucidum polysaccharides. Cell Physiol Biochem 33 (2): 289-99, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="20518254">Oka S, Tanaka S, Yoshida S, et al.: A water-soluble extract from culture medium of Ganoderma lucidum mycelia suppresses the development of colorectal adenomas. Hiroshima J Med Sci 59 (1): 1-6, 2010.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_199"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Medicinal Mushrooms</Title><Para id="_200">To assist readers in evaluating the results of human studies of integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of
evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever
possible.  To qualify for a level of evidence <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef>, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_201" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Be published in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed scientific journal</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Report on a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Describe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> findings in sufficient detail that a meaningful evaluation can be made.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_202">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score. For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis of integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies for cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/06/2024)</Title><Para id="_34">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_210">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000778578#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mushrooms-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of medicinal mushrooms in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Medicinal Mushrooms. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mushrooms-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/mushrooms-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 27929633]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2016-11-30</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-06</DateLastModified></Summary>
