<Summary id="CDR0000783881" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Financial Toxicity and Cancer Treatment discusses the increased financial burdens and pressures that cancer patients and survivors often experience. Learn more about financial toxicity, risk factors, and ways to reduce financial distress in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs/financial-toxicity-pdq">Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs/financial-toxicity-hp-pdq">Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000636198">cancer survivor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_221">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of cancer and financial toxicity (financial distress). It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_222">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>financial distress</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>financial toxicity</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_223"><Title>General Information About Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment</Title><SummarySection id="_389"><KeyPoint id="_390">Financial toxicity describes problems a patient has related to the cost of medical care.</KeyPoint><Para id="_391">The terms <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790159" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">financial toxicity</GlossaryTermRef>  and financial distress are used to describe how <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000789800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">out-of-pocket costs</GlossaryTermRef> can cause financial problems for a patient. Out-of-pocket costs are what you pay for your medical care that is not covered by your health insurance. Out-of-pocket costs include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_392" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Copayments</GlossaryTermRef>: Amount you pay for each health care service, such as a doctor appointment or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044711" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prescription</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Deductibles</GlossaryTermRef>: Amount you pay for your medical care before your health insurance plan begins to pay.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784322" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Coinsurance</GlossaryTermRef>: Percentage of costs you pay for a service that your health insurance covers after you have paid your deductible; for example, you pay 20% and your insurance pays 80%.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_393">These costs can be for hospital stays, outpatient services (procedures and tests that can be done without staying overnight in the hospital), medical appointments, and prescription drugs.</Para><Para id="_415">Cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> usually report higher out-of-pocket spending than people who have not had cancer. Some cancer survivors report spending more than 20% of their annual income on medical care.</Para><Para id="_394">Financial toxicity may also be called financial distress, financial stress, financial hardship, financial burden, economic burden, and economic hardship.</Para><Para id="_395">There have been no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> studying financial toxicity in people with cancer. The information in this summary is mainly based on studies that only included survivors and people with certain cancers, so it may not apply to all people with cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_396"><KeyPoint id="_397">Several studies show that people with cancer and survivors are more likely to have financial toxicity than are people without cancer. </KeyPoint><Para id="_398">Cancer is one of the most expensive medical conditions to treat in the United States. People with cancer may receive multiple types of treatments, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic treatment</GlossaryTermRef>, and may be hospitalized. People with cancer who have health insurance  are paying higher <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">premiums</GlossaryTermRef> than in the past. They are also paying more for copayments, deductibles, and coinsurance.</Para><Para id="_399">Compared to 10 years ago, patients receive more expensive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, and other new types of treatments. Copayments for prescription drugs covered by health insurance may be more for higher priced drugs or brand name drugs (versus <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044672" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">generic</GlossaryTermRef> drugs) and may increase over time. These copayments and coinsurance for drugs may cause financial toxicity even for people with cancer who have health insurance.</Para><Para id="_400">Cancer survivors may have financial problems many years after they are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef>. This is because they may be paying for ongoing cancer treatment or care for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef> from their treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_401"><KeyPoint id="_402">The level of financial toxicity you may have will depend on several factors in your household. </KeyPoint><Para id="_403">When you are diagnosed with cancer, the following factors in your household may affect your risk of financial toxicity:</Para><ItemizedList id="_404" Style="bullet"><ListItem>whether you make the most money for your household</ListItem><ListItem>how much money other people in your household make</ListItem><ListItem>how much debt you had before you were diagnosed with cancer</ListItem><ListItem>your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790150" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assets</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>costs related to your cancer</ListItem><ListItem>how the cancer and its treatment affect your ability to work</ListItem><ListItem>whether you have health and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790156" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disability insurance</GlossaryTermRef> and what they cover</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_405">You and your family may have the following problems because of your cancer diagnosis:</Para><ItemizedList id="_406" Style="bullet"><ListItem>less income and assets</ListItem><ListItem>debt because of the cost of your cancer care</ListItem><ListItem>trouble paying for housing, food, and bills</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bankruptcy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_407"><KeyPoint id="_408">Cancer treatment can affect your ability to work and pay your bills.</KeyPoint><Para id="_410">Having cancer may make it hard for you to do the physical and mental tasks for your job. You may miss time at work, or not be able to work at all. One study showed that working people who are getting cancer treatment missed about 22 more workdays a year than those who did not have any cancer treatment. Not being able to work may affect your employment-based health insurance (this is when part or all of your premium is paid by your employer).</Para><Para id="_414">You may also worry and have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef> about paying medical bills related to your cancer. People with cancer have reported worrying about wages lost for sick time or going to medical appointments. You may also have difficulty and stress when trying to understand complex medical bills.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_247"><Title>Risk Factors Related to Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress)</Title><SummarySection id="_248"><KeyPoint id="_249">The type of cancer you have, how severe it is, and the treatment you receive can affect your risk of financial toxicity.</KeyPoint><Para id="_416">Patients with the following types of diseases have a higher risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790159" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">financial toxicity</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_417" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>cancer that has a poor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>more than one type of cancer</ListItem><ListItem>a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic</GlossaryTermRef> disease (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748138" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart disease</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044911" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diabetes</GlossaryTermRef>) in addition to cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_418">This is partly because their cancer and treatment may keep them from having a job.</Para><Para id="_419">Patients who have been treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> are more likely to have higher <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000789800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">out-of-pocket costs</GlossaryTermRef> and financial toxicity than patients who have not had those treatments.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_254"><KeyPoint id="_255">Your age, race and ethnicity, income, and whether you have a job can affect your risk of financial toxicity.</KeyPoint><Para id="_420">Studies have shown that younger age at the time of cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> increases the risk of financial toxicity. Younger  people with cancer may have financial toxicity because of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_421" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a lack of savings and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790150" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assets</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>other financial responsibilities, such as raising children</ListItem><ListItem>not having health insurance ( people younger than 65 years are not eligible for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000640052" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Medicare</GlossaryTermRef>) or having a high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">deductible</GlossaryTermRef> health insurance plan with high out-of-pocket costs</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_437"> Survivors of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000728326" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">childhood cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may be more likely to have financial problems. A cancer diagnosis during childhood may disrupt education and limit job opportunities. Childhood cancer survivors may have higher out-of-pocket costs  than their siblings due to the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">second cancers</GlossaryTermRef> and lasting effects of their cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_423">Some studies have shown that people who belong to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000784947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">racial</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000807091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ethnic</GlossaryTermRef> minority groups may be more likely to have financial problems after being diagnosed with cancer. More research needs to be done in this area.</Para><Para id="_424">Patients from lower-income households have a higher risk of financial toxicity than patients from higher-income households. Losing a job has also been shown to be a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef> for debt and bankruptcy.</Para><Para id="_425">Several studies have shown that people with cancer may experience:</Para><ItemizedList id="_426" Style="bullet"><ListItem>loss of a job</ListItem><ListItem>change in job status, such as switching to part-time work or taking extended leave</ListItem><ListItem>difficulty returning to work</ListItem><ListItem>earning less income</ListItem><ListItem>general loss of productivity</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_356"><KeyPoint id="_357">The type of health insurance that you have, or not having health insurance, can affect your risk of financial toxicity.</KeyPoint><Para id="_427">If you do not have health insurance, you have a high risk of financial toxicity, especially because cancer costs are rising. However, even if you have health insurance, you may still have high out-of-pocket costs for your cancer care.</Para><Para id="_428">If you are enrolled in Medicare, you can also enroll in additional plans that can help reduce your out-of-pocket costs. You can choose to get <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000789795" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplemental insurance</GlossaryTermRef> that can help cover medical costs that your regular insurance plan does not cover, and you can enroll in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000789797" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Medicare Part D</GlossaryTermRef>, which is a Medicare plan that covers <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044711" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prescription</GlossaryTermRef> drugs.</Para><Para id="_429">One study found that patients who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790152" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">public health insurance</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000640050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Medicaid</GlossaryTermRef> or Medicare) have a higher risk of financial toxicity compared to patients who have private health insurance. Patients with public health insurance may also have fewer savings and assets, which is a risk factor for financial toxicity.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_273"><Title>Effects of Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) on People with Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_274"><KeyPoint id="_275">Patients may not take their medicine as directed so that they can save money on copayments.</KeyPoint><Para id="_430">Some patients have reported skipping <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> or taking less medicine than prescribed, to make their prescription last longer and save money. Patients have also reported not filling a prescription because of the cost.</Para><Para id="_431">The higher the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">copayment</GlossaryTermRef>, the less likely patients are to take their medicine as directed.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_279"><KeyPoint id="_280">Patients who have financial toxicity may have a lower quality of life.</KeyPoint><Para id="_432">Studies have shown that patients who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790159" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">financial toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> reported having a lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>, more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, and more pain. One study showed that some patients felt financial toxicity was more severe than physical, emotional, social, or family <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">distress</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_361">In addition to lower quality of life, patients who have financial toxicity are also more likely to report:</Para><ItemizedList id="_384" Style="bullet"><ListItem>poor physical health</ListItem><ListItem>poor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mental health</GlossaryTermRef>, including feeling <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depressed</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>being unsatisfied with social activities and relationships</ListItem><ListItem>worrying that their cancer may come back</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_283"><KeyPoint id="_284">Financial toxicity may lead to debt, bankruptcy, and other harmful financial events.</KeyPoint><Para id="_442">One study found that people with cancer experienced more harmful financial events, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_441" Style="bullet"><ListItem>an inability to pay bills</ListItem><ListItem>past-due mortgage payments</ListItem><ListItem>foreclosures or repossessions of property</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_285">In another study, some cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> reported the following problems related to financial toxicity:</Para><ItemizedList id="_385" Style="bullet"><ListItem>worrying about paying large bills related to cancer</ListItem><ListItem>going into debt</ListItem><ListItem>filing for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bankruptcy</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_434">You may have to do some of the following to help pay for your medical care:</Para><ItemizedList id="_435" Style="bullet"><ListItem>use your savings</ListItem><ListItem>borrow money</ListItem><ListItem>spend less on leisure activities, food, clothing, and utilities</ListItem><ListItem>sell your stocks, investments, possessions, or property</ListItem><ListItem>move to lower-cost housing</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_438"><KeyPoint id="_439">Informal caregivers often share in the experience of financial toxicity.</KeyPoint><Para id="_440">Family members and friends may provide informal care for people with cancer.  They often share in the experience of financial toxicity by spending money on food, medicine, and other things the patient needs.  They may also need to take time off from work to provide care for the patient.  These actions may lead to a higher sense of burden, lower quality of life, and poorer mental health for the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648947" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">caregiver</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_314"><Title>Ways to Reduce Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress)</Title><SummarySection id="_321"><KeyPoint id="_367">There may be ways to reduce financial toxicity.</KeyPoint><Para id="_322">The following are being studied as possible ways to reduce <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790159" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">financial toxicity</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_388" Style="bullet"><ListItem>meeting with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000789804" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">financial navigator</GlossaryTermRef> who will teach you about the health insurance plans and cost-saving methods for treatments that you are eligible for</ListItem><ListItem>hospitals posting their prices so that health care professionals and patients know the costs when making decisions about which tests and treatments to use</ListItem><ListItem>introducing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790154" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">value-based pricing</GlossaryTermRef> so that patients can choose higher-value treatments with lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000789800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">out-of-pocket costs</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>reforming health insurance by passing policies that help people with cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_436">See <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs">Managing Costs and Medical Information</ExternalRef> for more information about ways to manage the costs of your cancer care.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of cancer and  financial toxicity (financial distress).  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs/financial-toxicity-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs/financial-toxicity-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 28682576]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000781334"/><DateFirstPublished>2017-06-29</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-06-06</DateLastModified></Summary>
