<Summary id="CDR0000784601" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood nasopharyngeal cancer can start in the nasal cavity and top of the throat. Learn about the symptoms of childhood nasopharyngeal cancer and how it is diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Nasopharyngeal Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_966">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood nasopharyngeal cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_967">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Nasopharyngeal cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Nasopharyngeal Cancer  (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Nasopharyngeal Cancer </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Nasopharyngeal Cancer </AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1702"><Title>What is childhood nasopharyngeal cancer?</Title><Para id="_1703">Childhood nasopharyngeal cancer is a rare type of cancer that forms in the tissue lining the nasopharynx. The nasopharynx is the upper part of the throat behind the nose. The nostrils allow air into the nasopharynx. Air and food pass through the pharynx on the way to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_1704">Nasopharyngeal cancer is more common in children aged 10 to 19 years than in children younger than 10 years.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000791249" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the nasopharynx; drawing shows the three parts of the pharynx (throat): the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and hypopharynx. Also shown are the nasal cavity, oral cavity, larynx, esophagus, and trachea." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1668"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the nasopharynx. The nasopharynx is in the upper part of the pharynx (throat) behind the nose. The nostrils lead into the nasopharynx. An opening on each side of the nasopharynx leads into the ear.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1705"><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1706">Childhood nasopharyngeal cancer is caused by certain changes in the way the cells in the nasal cavity and top part of the throat function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_1707">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. A known risk factor for childhood nasopharyngeal cancer is infection from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Epstein-Barr virus</GlossaryTermRef> (EBV). Not every child with this risk factor will develop nasopharyngeal cancer. And it will develop in some children who don’t have a known risk factor. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1708"><Title>Symptoms of childhood nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1709">Children may not have symptoms of nasopharyngeal cancer until the tumor has grown bigger. It’s important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1577" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a headache</ListItem><ListItem>a blocked or stuffy nose</ListItem><ListItem>nosebleeds</ListItem><ListItem>an earache</ListItem><ListItem>an ear infection</ListItem><ListItem>hearing loss</ListItem><ListItem>problems moving the jaw</ListItem><ListItem>trouble speaking</ListItem><ListItem>trouble seeing or a droopy eyelid</ListItem><ListItem>lumps in the neck that may be painful</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1710">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than nasopharyngeal cancer. The only way to know is for your child to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1711"><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1712">If your child has symptoms that suggest nasopharyngeal cancer, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, the doctor may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with nasopharyngeal cancer, the results of these tests will help plan treatment.</Para><SummarySection id="_1714"><Title>Diagnostic tests</Title><Para id="_1715">The tests used to diagnose nasopharyngeal cancer may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_1716"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_1717"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas of the body, such as the head and neck. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1718"><Title>Nasal endoscopy</Title><Para id="_1719">Nasal endoscopy is a procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas. A flexible or rigid endoscope is inserted through the nose.  An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> for signs of disease. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1720"><Title>Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) tests</Title><Para id="_1721">Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) tests use a sample of blood to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to the Epstein-Barr virus and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> of the Epstein-Barr virus. These are found in the blood of patients who have been infected with EBV. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1722"><Title>Tests to stage nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1723">If your child is diagnosed with nasopharyngeal cancer, they will be referred to a pediatric oncologist. This is a doctor who specializes in staging and treating nasopharyngeal cancer and other cancers. They will recommend tests to determine the extent (stage) of cancer. Sometimes the cancer is only in the nasopharynx. Or, it may have spread to other parts of the body. The process of learning the extent of cancer in the body is called staging. It is important to know the stage of the nasopharyngeal cancer in order to plan the best treatment. </Para><Para id="_1724">Most children with nasopharyngeal cancer are at an advanced stage at the time of diagnosis. Nasopharyngeal cancer spreads most often to the bone, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_1725">For information about a specific stage of nasopharyngeal cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000784601#_1740" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Nasopharyngeal Cancer Stages</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_1726">The following procedures may be used to determine the nasopharyngeal cancer stage:</Para><SummarySection id="_1727"><Title>Neurological exam</Title><Para id="_1728">A neurologic exam is a series of questions and tests done to check the brain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve</GlossaryTermRef> function. The exam checks a person’s mental status, coordination, and ability to walk normally, and how well the muscles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">senses</GlossaryTermRef>, and reflexes work. This may also be called a neuro exam.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1729"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_1730">Chest x-ray is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> that can go through the body and make pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1731"><Title>PET-CT scan</Title><Para id="_1732">PET-CT scan combines the pictures from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">positron emission tomography (PET) scan</GlossaryTermRef> and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">computed tomography (CT) scan</GlossaryTermRef>. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time on the same machine. The combined scans make more detailed pictures than either test would make by itself.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1684" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For the PET scan, a small amount of radioactive sugar (also called radioactive glucose) is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where sugar is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more sugar than normal cells do.</ListItem><ListItem>For the CT scan (CAT scan), a computer linked to an x-ray machine makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body.  The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  Often, a chest CT scan is done. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1737"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_1738">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child’s cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child’s cancer.  </Para><Para id="_1795">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1740"><Title>Stages of childhood nasopharyngeal cancer </Title><Para id="_1741">The cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of nasopharyngeal cancer to plan the best treatment.  </Para><Para id="_1742">There are several staging systems for cancer. Nasopharyngeal cancer staging usually uses the TNM staging system. You may see your child’s cancer described by this staging system in the pathology report. Based on the TNM results, a stage (I, II, III, or IV, also written as 1, 2, 3, or 4) is assigned to your child’s cancer. When talking with you about your child’s cancer, your child’s doctor may describe it as one of these stages.  </Para><Para id="_1743">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_1744">Learn about the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000784601#_1722" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">tests and procedures</SummaryRef> used to determine the stage of nasopharyngeal cancer. </Para><SummarySection id="_1745"><Title>Stage 0 nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1746">In stage 0, abnormal cells are found in the lining of the nasopharynx. These abnormal cells may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. Stage 0 is also called carcinoma in situ.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1747"><Title>Stage I nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1748">In stage I, nasopharyngeal cancer has formed and is found in the nasopharynx only or has spread from the nasopharynx to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046024" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oropharynx</GlossaryTermRef> and/or nasal cavity.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_186"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1749"><Title>Stage II nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1750">Stage II is based on the location of the cancer and whether it has spread. A child may have one of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1751" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Cancer has spread to one or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> on one side of the neck and/or to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the back of the throat. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller. Cancer is found:<ItemizedList id="_1752" Style="bullet"><ListItem>in the nasopharynx only or has spread from the nasopharynx to the oropharynx and/or to the nasal cavity; or</ListItem><ListItem>only in the lymph nodes in the neck. The cancer cells in the lymph nodes are infected with Epstein-Barr virus (a virus linked to nasopharyngeal cancer). Cancer was not found in the nasopharynx.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797784" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">parapharyngeal space</GlossaryTermRef> and/or nearby muscles. Cancer may have also spread to one or more lymph nodes on one side of the neck and/or to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the back of the throat. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1753"><Title>Stage III nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1754">Stage III is based on the location of the cancer and whether it has spread. A child may have one of the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_1755" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Cancer has spread to one or more lymph nodes on both sides of the neck. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller. Cancer is found:<ItemizedList id="_1756" Style="bullet"><ListItem>in the nasopharynx only or has spread from the nasopharynx to the oropharynx and/or to the nasal cavity; or</ListItem><ListItem>only in the lymph nodes in the neck. The cancer cells in the lymph nodes are infected with Epstein-Barr virus (a virus linked to nasopharyngeal cancer). Cancer was not found in the nasopharynx.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to the parapharyngeal space and/or nearby muscles. Cancer has also spread to one or more lymph nodes on both sides of the neck. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to the bones at the bottom of the skull, the bones in the neck, jaw muscles, and/or the sinuses around the nose and eyes. Cancer may have also spread to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the neck and/or the back of the throat. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1757"><Title>Stage IV nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1758">Stage IV is subdivided based on whether the cancer has spread to other tissue.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1759" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In stage IVA:<ItemizedList id="_1760" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Cancer has spread to the brain, the cranial nerves, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046029" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypopharynx</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">salivary gland</GlossaryTermRef> in front of the ear, the bone around the eye, and/or the soft tissues of the jaw. Cancer may have also spread to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the neck and/or the back of the throat. The affected lymph nodes are 6 centimeters or smaller; or</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer has spread to one or more lymph nodes on one or both sides of the neck. The affected lymph nodes are larger than 6 centimeters and/or are found in the lowest part of the neck.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IVB: Cancer has spread beyond the lymph nodes in the neck to distant lymph nodes, such as those between the lungs, below the collarbone, or in the armpit or groin, or to other parts of the body, such as the lung, bone, or liver.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1761">Stage IV nasopharyngeal cancer is also called metastatic nasopharyngeal cancer. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if nasopharyngeal cancer spreads to the lung, the cancer cells in the lung are actually nasopharyngeal cancer cells. The disease is called metastatic nasopharyngeal cancer, not lung cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1762"><Title>Recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1763">Recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. Nasopharyngeal cancer may come back in the nasopharynx, or in other parts of the body, such as the bone, lung, or liver. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned in the body, if it has spread, and how far. The type of treatment that your child will have for recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer will depend on where it has come back.   </Para><Para id="_1764">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.  </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1765"><Title>Types of treatment for childhood nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_1790"><Title>Who treats children with nasopharyngeal cancer?</Title><Para id="_1693">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of nasopharyngeal cancer. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1694" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044444" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ear, nose, and throat specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1796"><Title>Treatment options</Title><Para id="_1766">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with nasopharyngeal cancer. You and your child’s care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child’s overall health and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_1767">Your child’s treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child’s care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, visit our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_1797">The types of treatment your child might have include:</Para><SummarySection id="_1768"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_1769">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cancer cells or stops them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_1770">Chemotherapy for nasopharyngeal cancer is injected into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream to reach cancer cells throughout the body. Chemotherapy used alone or in combination to treat nasopharyngeal cancer in children include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_1771" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537894" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/fluorouracil">fluorouracil (5-FU)</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1772">Other chemotherapy not listed here may also be used.  </Para><Para id="_1773">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1774"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_1618">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Nasopharyngeal cancer is treated with external beam radiation therapy. This type of radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation therapy may be given alone or with other treatments, such as chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_1775">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1776"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_1622">Surgery to remove the tumor is done if the tumor has not spread throughout the nasal cavity and throat at the time of diagnosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1777"><Title>Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_1626">Immunotherapy uses a person's  immune system to fight cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Interferon</GlossaryTermRef> may be used to treat nasopharyngeal cancer.</Para><Para id="_1778">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1779"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_1779_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_1779_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_1779_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1685"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038904">nasopharyngeal cancer</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of childhood nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1687">Treatment of newly diagnosed nasopharyngeal cancer in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1688" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Chemotherapy followed by chemotherapy and radiation therapy given at the same time. Interferon may also be given.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove the tumor.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1691">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045863" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">refractory</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> nasopharyngeal cancer is chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_1685_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1735"><Title>Prognostic factors  for childhood nasopharyngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_1736">If your child has been diagnosed with nasopharyngeal cancer, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child’s chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis. The prognosis can be affected by whether the cancer has spread to other parts of the body at the time of diagnosis and whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has recurred (come back). No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child’s cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child’s prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1605"><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_1794">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_1605_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1669">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1609" Style="bullet"><ListItem>problems with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid gland</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>decreased mouth function</ListItem><ListItem>hearing loss or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045641" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chronic</GlossaryTermRef> ear infections</ListItem><ListItem>dental cavities</ListItem><ListItem>chronic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000799139" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sinusitis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer) or other problems</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1670">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments.  Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1787"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_1787_md_55">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_1787_md_56">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1788"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_1789">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child’s treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1641"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related Resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors-caregivers-advocates">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood nasopharyngeal cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Nasopharyngeal Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/nasopharyngeal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2018-01-08</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-04-10</DateLastModified></Summary>
