<Summary id="CDR0000789047" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood esthesioneuroblastoma is a very rare type of cancer that forms in the tissues of the nose. Learn about the symptoms of esthesioneuroblastoma in children and how it is diagnosed and treated. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/esthesioneuroblastoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Esthesioneuroblastoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/esthesioneuroblastoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Esthesioneuroblastoma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040691">paranasal sinus and nasal cavity esthesioneuroblastoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_966">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood esthesioneuroblastoma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_967">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood olfactory neuroblastoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Esthesioneuroblastoma (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Esthesioneuroblastoma</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Esthesioneuroblastoma</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1699"><Title>What is esthesioneuroblastoma?</Title><Para id="_1700">Childhood esthesioneuroblastoma is a rare type of cancer that forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">olfactory</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve</GlossaryTermRef> endings in the upper part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790106" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasal cavity</GlossaryTermRef>.  The olfactory nerves (sense of smell) pass through the many tiny holes in the bone at the base of the brain to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000698420" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">olfactory bulb</GlossaryTermRef>. Esthesioneuroblastoma is also called olfactory neuroblastoma.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000801515" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows areas of the body where esthesioneuroblastoma tumors may form, including the olfactory nerve endings, olfactory bulb, nasal cavity, nasal sinuses, and brain." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1698"><Caption language="en">Esthesioneuroblastomas form in the olfactory nerve endings in the upper part of the nasal cavity. The olfactory nerves (sense of smell) pass through the many tiny holes in the bone at the base of the brain to the olfactory bulb. Esthesioneuroblastomas may spread from the nasal cavity to the nasal sinuses or to nearby tissue. They may also spread to the brain or to other parts of the body (not shown).</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_1567">Esthesioneuroblastoma affects adults and children. Even though it is very rare, esthesioneuroblastoma is the most common nasal cavity cancer in children and teens.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1701"><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1702">Childhood esthesioneuroblastoma is caused by certain changes to the way the cells in the olfactory nerve endings function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these cell changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_1703">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. There are no known risk factors for childhood esthesioneuroblastoma.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1568"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Symptoms of childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1570">Children may not have symptoms of esthesioneuroblastoma until the tumor has grown bigger. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1572" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a mass in the nose</ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing through the nose</ListItem><ListItem>a change in or loss of the sense of smell</ListItem><ListItem>nosebleeds</ListItem><ListItem>a headache</ListItem><ListItem>bulging of the eye</ListItem><ListItem>trouble seeing</ListItem><ListItem>eye pain</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1704">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than esthesioneuroblastoma. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1573"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1575">If your child has symptoms that suggest esthesioneuroblastoma, their doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or to another condition. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. The doctor will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family health history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with esthesioneuroblastoma, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><SummarySection id="_1705"><Title>Diagnostic tests</Title><Para id="_1706">The following tests may be used to diagnose esthesioneuroblastoma:</Para><SummarySection id="_1707"><Title>Nasal endoscopy</Title><Para id="_1708">Nasal endoscopy is a  procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas. A flexible or rigid endoscope is inserted through the nose. An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> checks under a microscope for signs of disease.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1709"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_1710">MRI uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas of the body, such as the head and neck. This procedure is also called nuclear MRI (NMRI). <MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1754"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1711"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_1712">CT scan uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make  a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the head and neck or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775452" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1654"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck. </Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1713"><Title>PET scan (positron emission tomography scan)</Title><Para id="_1714">PET scan uses a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> sugar (radioactive glucose) that is injected into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body. Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1715"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_1716">Biopsy is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the tumor so that a pathologist can view it under a microscope to check for signs of cancer.</Para><Para id="_1577">The following tests may be done on the sample of cells or tissues that were removed:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1578" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Immunohistochemistry</Strong> uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (markers) in a sample of a patient's tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Genetic analysis</Strong> is a laboratory test in which cells or tissue are analyzed to look for changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosomes</GlossaryTermRef>. These changes may be a sign that a person has or is at risk of having a specific disease or condition. Children with esthesioneuroblastoma may be eligible for genetic analysis and other types of molecular testing through the Molecular Characterization Initiative.<Para id="_md_4">The Molecular Characterization Initiative offers free molecular testing to children, adolescents, and young adults with certain types of newly diagnosed cancer. The program is offered through NCI's Childhood Cancer Data Initiative. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/areas/childhood/childhood-cancer-data-initiative/data-ecosystem/molecular-characterization">About the Molecular Characterization Initiative</ExternalRef>.</Para></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Electron microscopy</Strong> is a laboratory test in which cells in a sample of tissue are viewed under regular and high-powered microscopes to look for certain changes in the cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1717"><Title>Tests to stage childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1718">If your child is diagnosed with esthesioneuroblastoma, they will be referred to a pediatric oncologist. This is a doctor who specializes in staging and treating esthesioneuroblastoma and other cancers. They will recommend tests to determine the extent (stage) of cancer. Sometimes the cancer is only in the olfactory nerve ending in the upper nasal cavity. Or, it may have spread from the nasal cavity to other parts of the body. The process of learning the extent of cancer in the body is called staging. It is important to know the stage of esthesioneuroblastoma to plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_1719">Most children with esthesioneuroblastoma are at an advanced stage at the time of diagnosis. Esthesioneuroblastoma spreads most often to nearby tissue, including the olfactory bulb, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044061" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nasal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000641960" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sinuses</GlossaryTermRef>, or brain. It can also spread to the lymph nodes, lungs, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, bone or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_1720">Learn more about a specific stage of esthesioneuroblastoma at <SummaryRef href="CDR0000789047#_1734" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/esthesioneuroblastoma-treatment-pdq">Stages of childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_1721">The following tests may be used to determine the esthesioneuroblastoma stage:</Para><SummarySection id="_1722"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_1723">An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures. A chest x-ray is one that makes pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1724"><Title>PET-CT scan</Title><Para id="_1725">PET-CT scan combines the pictures from a positron emission tomography (PET) scan and a computed tomography (CT) scan. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time on the same machine. The pictures from both scans are combined to make a more detailed picture than either test would make by itself. If there is any cancer, this increases the chance that it will be found.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1726" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For the PET scan, a small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into a vein. The scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body. Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells.</ListItem><ListItem>For the CT scan, a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, is taken from different angles. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1727"><Title>Fine-needle aspiration (FNA) biopsy</Title><Para id="_1728">Fine-needle aspiration biopsy uses a thin needle to remove tissue or fluid from an enlarged lymph node. A pathologist views the tissue or fluid under a microscope to look for cancer cells.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1729"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_1730">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's cancer.  </Para><Para id="_1731">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1734"><Title>Stages of childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1735">The cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of esthesioneuroblastoma to plan the best treatment.</Para><Para id="_1736">There are several different staging systems for cancer. The Kadish staging system is used for esthesioneuroblastoma. Based on the diagnostic and staging test results, a Kadish stage is assigned to your child's esthesioneuroblastoma, such as stage A, stage B, stage C, or stage D. When talking with you about your child's cancer, your child's doctor may describe it as one of these stages.</Para><SummarySection id="_1596"><Title>Stage A esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1598">In stage A, cancer is found in the nasal cavity only.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1599"><Title>Stage B esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1601">In stage B, cancer has spread from the nasal cavity to the nasal sinuses.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1602"><Title>Stage C esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1604">In stage C, cancer has spread through the nasal sinuses to nearby tissue.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1605"><Title>Stage D esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1607">In stage D, cancer has spread to distant parts of the body, such as the lymph nodes in the neck, or to the brain, bone marrow, or lung.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1608"><Title>Types of treatment for childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><SummarySection id="_1757"><Title>Who treats children with esthesioneuroblastoma?</Title><Para id="_1693">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of esthesioneuroblastoma. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1694" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_1738">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with esthesioneuroblastoma. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_1739">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our downloadable booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_1618"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_1620">Surgery to remove the tumor is one of the main treatments for esthesioneuroblastoma.</Para><Para id="_1621">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, your child may be given chemotherapy or radiation therapy to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after surgery to lower the risk that the cancer will come back is called adjuvant therapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1622"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_1624">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Esthesioneuroblastoma may be treated with external beam radiation therapy. This type of radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation therapy may be given alone or with other treatments, such as chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_1740">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1625"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_1627">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cells or stops them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy. </Para><Para id="_1741">For esthesioneuroblastoma, the chemotherapy is injected into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body.</Para><Para id="_1742">Chemotherapy drugs used alone or in combination to treat esthesioneuroblastoma in children include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1743" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000720376" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dactinomycin">dactinomycin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496383" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/docetaxel">docetaxel</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000542867" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/doxorubicinhydrochloride">doxorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000686471" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ifosfamide">ifosfamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537382" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecanhydrochloride">irinotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599877" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vincristinesulfate">vincristine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1744">Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_1745">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1628"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_1628_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_1628_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_1628_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1674"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040691">paranasal sinus and nasal cavity esthesioneuroblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment options by stage</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of childhood esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1676">Treatment of newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage A esthesioneuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1677" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery to remove the tumor followed by radiation therapy if visible tumor cells remain after surgery</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1680">Treatment of newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790074" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage B esthesioneuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1681" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery to remove the tumor followed by radiation therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1684">Treatment of newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790076" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage C esthesioneuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1685" Style="bullet"><ListItem>chemotherapy followed by surgery to remove the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy followed by surgery to remove the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy and radiation therapy given at the same time followed by surgery to remove the tumor</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1687">Treatment of newly diagnosed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000790078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage D esthesioneuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1688" Style="bullet"><ListItem>chemotherapy given before or after surgery to remove the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy to the tumor and other places in the body where the cancer has spread</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1755">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_1674_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1732"><Title>Prognostic factors for esthesioneuroblastoma</Title><Para id="_1733">If your child has been diagnosed with esthesioneuroblastoma, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis. The prognosis can be affected by whether the cancer is only in the nose or if it has spread to the nasal sinuses, lymph nodes, or other parts of the body and whether the tumor was completely removed by surgery. No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1613"><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_1758">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_1613_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1671">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1615" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer) or other conditions</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1670">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments.  Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1749"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_1750">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to <SummaryRef href="CDR0000789047#_1573" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/esthesioneuroblastoma-treatment-pdq">diagnose</SummaryRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of the these tests.</Para><Para id="_1751">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1752"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_1753">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families When a Child Has Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1651"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck">Head and Neck Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors and Caregivers</ExternalRef>
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood esthesioneuroblastoma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Esthesioneuroblastoma. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/esthesioneuroblastoma-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/esthesioneuroblastoma-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000790381"/><DateFirstPublished>2018-01-09</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-04</DateLastModified></Summary>
