<Summary id="CDR0000789169" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood thyroid cancer starts in the thyroid gland. Learn more about symptoms and risk factors of childhood thyroid cancer and how it is diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/thyroid/patient/child-thyroid-treatment-pdq">Childhood Thyroid Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038801">thyroid cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood thyroid cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Childhood follicular thyroid cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Childhood medullary thyroid cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Childhood papillary thyroid cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Childhood thyroid cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Thyroid Cancer (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Thyroid Cancer</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Thyroid Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_116"><Title>What is childhood thyroid cancer?</Title><Para id="_161">Thyroid cancer in children is a rare cancer that forms in the thyroid, a butterfly-shaped gland at the base of the throat near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044379" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">windpipe</GlossaryTermRef> (also called the trachea). The thyroid gland has a right <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046188" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lobe</GlossaryTermRef> and a left lobe that is connected by a thin piece of tissue called the isthmus. Although thyroid cancer can affect children of all ages, it's more common in adolescents and girls. It also occurs more often in White people than in Black people.</Para><Para id="_225">Children can also have thyroid nodules. A thyroid nodule is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> growth of thyroid cells in the thyroid. The nodules may be solid or fluid-filled. Thyroid nodules usually don't cause symptoms or need treatment unless they become large enough that it is hard to swallow or breathe. Only one in five thyroid nodules become cancer.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000791254" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the thyroid and parathyroid glands; drawing shows the thyroid gland at the base of the throat near the trachea. An inset shows the front and back views. The front view shows that the thyroid is shaped like a butterfly, with the right lobe and left lobe connected by a thin piece of tissue called the isthmus. The back view shows the four pea-sized parathyroid glands. The larynx is also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_125"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the thyroid and parathyroid glands. The thyroid gland lies at the base of the throat near the trachea. It is shaped like a butterfly, with the right lobe and left lobe connected by a thin piece of tissue called the isthmus. The parathyroid glands are four pea-sized organs found in the neck near the thyroid. The thyroid and parathyroid glands make hormones.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_11">The thyroid uses iodine, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mineral</GlossaryTermRef> found in some foods and in iodized salt, to help make several <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef>. Thyroid hormones:</Para><ItemizedList id="_12" Style="bullet"><ListItem>control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart rate</GlossaryTermRef>, body temperature, and how quickly food is changed into energy (metabolism)</ListItem><ListItem>control the amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045632" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">calcium</GlossaryTermRef> in the blood</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_162"><Title>Types of childhood thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_15">There are four types of thyroid cancers:</Para><ItemizedList id="_17" Style="dash"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Papillary</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> thyroid carcinoma is the most common type of thyroid cancer in children, occurring most often in teens. It usually affects both sides of the thyroid and often spreads to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> in the neck and sometimes the lungs.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044544" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Follicular</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> thyroid carcinoma usually forms in one area of the thyroid. It often spreads to the bone and lung but  rarely spreads to the lymph nodes in the neck.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Medullary</GlossaryTermRef></Strong> thyroid cancer forms from parafollicular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">C cells</GlossaryTermRef> in the thyroid. It is usually linked to a certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> change in the <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810835" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RET</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName> gene and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000702087" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2 (MEN 2) syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>. It occurs most often in children aged 4 years and younger and may have spread to other parts of the body at the time of diagnosis. Children who have MEN2 syndrome may also be at risk of developing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322877" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pheochromocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperparathyroidism</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044541" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Anaplastic thyroid cancer</GlossaryTermRef> rarely occurs in children. Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/pediatric-adult-rare-tumor/rare-tumors/rare-endocrine-tumor/anaplastic-thyroid-cancer">Anaplastic Thyroid Cancer (ATC)</ExternalRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18">Papillary and follicular thyroid cancer are sometimes called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">differentiated</GlossaryTermRef> thyroid cancer. Medullary and anaplastic thyroid cancer are sometimes called poorly differentiated or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">undifferentiated</GlossaryTermRef> thyroid cancer. </Para><Para id="_163"> Adenomas are a type of thyroid nodule that can grow very large and sometimes make hormones. Adenomas are not cancer but may rarely become cancer and spread to the lungs or lymph nodes in the neck.
        </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_24"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_164">Thyroid cancer in children is caused by certain changes to the way thyroid cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these cell changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_26">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with one or more of these risk factors will develop thyroid cancer. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor.</Para><Para id="_27">Risk factors for childhood thyroid cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_28" Style="bullet"><ListItem>being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef>, such as from diagnostic tests, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation treatment</GlossaryTermRef>, or radiation in the environment</ListItem><ListItem>having autoimmune thyroiditis</ListItem><ListItem>having certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> syndromes, such as:<ItemizedList id="_112" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000702095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A (MEN2A) syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000702100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2B (MEN2B) syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of thyroid cancer, including:<ItemizedList id="_129" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GeneName>APC</GeneName>-associated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046172" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyposis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000782329" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DICER1 syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Carney complex</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000800505" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PTEN hamartoma tumor syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Werner syndrome</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_166">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk for thyroid cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_167"><Title>Genetic counseling for children with thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_168">It is not always clear from the family medical history whether a condition is inherited. Genetic counseling can assess the likelihood that your child's cancer is inherited and whether genetic testing is needed. Genetic testing may help explain why a child develops a rare cancer or a cancer that is usually seen in adults. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic counselors</GlossaryTermRef> and other specially trained health professionals can discuss your child's diagnosis and your family's medical history to help you understand:</Para><ItemizedList id="_169" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the options for testing for changes in the <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810835" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RET</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName>, <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName>, or <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene </ListItem><ListItem>the risk of other cancers for your child</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of thyroid cancer or other cancers for your child's siblings</ListItem><ListItem>the risks and benefits of learning genetic information</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_170">Genetic counselors can also help you cope with your child's genetic testing results, including how to discuss the results with family members. They can advise you about whether other members of your family should receive genetic testing.</Para><Para id="_171">If your child has been found to have a change in the <GeneName>RET</GeneName> gene, other family members may also be tested to find out if they have an increased risk of medullary thyroid cancer. Family members, including young children, who have the changed gene may have a thyroidectomy (surgery to remove the thyroid). This can decrease the chance of developing medullary thyroid cancer.</Para><Para id="_172">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/genetic-testing-fact-sheet">Genetic Testing for Inherited Cancer Risk</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Symptoms of childhood thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_35">Often thyroid cancer is found when a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> or an imaging test is done for another health problem. Sometimes the cancer can cause symptoms. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_37" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a lump in the neck</ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>trouble swallowing</ListItem><ListItem>hoarseness or a change in the voice</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_126">Children with changes to the <GeneName>RET</GeneName> gene may have symptoms that can lead to an early diagnosis of multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A or 2B syndrome. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_128" Style="bullet"><ListItem>bumps on the lips, tongue, or eyelids that do not hurt</ListItem><ListItem>trouble making tears</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794906" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Marfan syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (being tall and thin, with long arms, legs, fingers, and toes)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_173">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than thyroid cancer. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_130">If your child has symptoms that suggest thyroid cancer, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or to another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a physical exam. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with thyroid cancer, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_40">The tests used to diagnose thyroid cancer may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_175"><Title>Thyroid function test</Title><Para id="_176">A thyroid function test checks the blood for abnormal levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044559" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid-stimulating hormone</GlossaryTermRef> (TSH). TSH is made by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pituitary gland</GlossaryTermRef> in the brain. It stimulates the release of thyroid hormone and controls how fast follicular thyroid cells grow. The blood may also be checked for high levels of calcitonin (a hormone made by the thyroid that decreases the amount of calcium in the blood).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_177"><Title>Thyroglobulin test</Title><Para id="_178">A thyroglobulin test checks the blood for the amount of thyroglobulin, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> made by the thyroid gland. Thyroglobulin levels are low or absent with normal thyroid function but may be higher with thyroid cancer or other conditions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_179"><Title><GeneName>RET</GeneName>, <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName>, or <GeneName>APC</GeneName> genetic testing</Title><Para id="_180">A <GeneName>RET</GeneName>, <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName>, or <GeneName>APC</GeneName> genetic test checks a sample of blood, saliva, or tissue for certain changes in the <GeneName>RET</GeneName>, <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName>, or <GeneName>APC</GeneName> genes.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_181"><Title>Ultrasound exam</Title><Para id="_182">An ultrasound exam uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs in the neck and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. This procedure can show the size of the mass and whether it is solid or a fluid-filled <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046461" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyst</GlossaryTermRef>. Ultrasound may be used to guide a fine-needle aspiration biopsy. A complete ultrasound exam of the neck is done before surgery.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_183"><Title>Thyroid scan</Title><Para id="_184">A thyroid scan uses a small amount of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance that is swallowed or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef>. The radioactive material collects in thyroid gland cells. A special camera linked to a computer detects the radiation given off and makes pictures that show how the thyroid looks and functions and whether the cancer has spread beyond the thyroid gland. If the amount of TSH in the child's blood is low, a scan to make images of the thyroid may be done before surgery.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_185"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_186">A CT scan uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the neck, chest, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, and brain. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775452" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_110"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck. </Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_187"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with gadolinium</Title><Para id="_188">MRI uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the neck and chest. A substance called gadolinium is injected into a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_189"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_190">An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures. A chest x-ray makes pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_191"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_192">A biopsy is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the tumor so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for signs of cancer.</Para><ItemizedList id="_41" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Fine-needle aspiration biopsy</Strong> is the removal of thyroid tissue using a thin needle. The needle is inserted through the skin into the thyroid. Several tissue samples are removed from different parts of the thyroid. A pathologist views the tissue samples under a microscope to look for cancer cells. If it is not clear whether cancer is present, a surgical biopsy may be done.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Surgical biopsy</Strong> is the removal of the thyroid nodule or one lobe of the thyroid during surgery so the cells and tissues can be viewed under a microscope by a pathologist to check for signs of cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_200"><Title>Whole-body thyroid scan</Title><Para id="_201">A whole-body thyroid scan uses a small amount of radioactive substance that is swallowed or injected. The radioactive material collects in any thyroid tissue or cancer cells remaining after surgery. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045855" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radioactive iodine</GlossaryTermRef> is used because only thyroid cells take up iodine. A special camera detects the radiation given off by the thyroid tissue or cancer cells. This procedure is also called radioactive iodine scan or RAI scan.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_202"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_203">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to  share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the genetic test report, pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's cancer.</Para><Para id="_204">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_120"><Title>Types of treatment for childhood thyroid cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_205"><Title>Who treats children with thyroid cancer?</Title><Para id="_206">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of thyroid cancer. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_207" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pathologist</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_208">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with thyroid cancer. You and your child's cancer care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_209">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_210">Treatment for thyroid cancer might include:</Para><SummarySection id="_211"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_68">Surgery is the most common treatment for thyroid cancer. One of the following procedures may be used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_69" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Total thyroidectomy is the removal of the whole thyroid. Lymph nodes near the cancer may also be removed and checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Near-total thyroidectomy is the removal of all but a very small part of the thyroid. Lymph nodes near the cancer may also be removed and checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_154">In children, a total thyroidectomy is usually done.</Para><Para id="_227">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery">Surgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_212"><Title>Radioactive iodine therapy</Title><Para id="_72">Follicular and papillary thyroid cancers are sometimes treated with radioactive iodine (RAI) therapy. RAI therapy may be given to children after surgery to kill any thyroid cancer cells that were not removed or to children whose tumor cannot be removed by surgery. RAI is taken by mouth and collects in any remaining thyroid tissue, including thyroid cancer cells that have spread to other places in the body. Because only thyroid tissue takes up iodine, the RAI destroys thyroid tissue and thyroid cancer cells without harming other tissue. Before a full treatment dose of RAI is given, a small test dose is given to see if the tumor takes up the iodine.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_213"><Title>Targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_75">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to block the action of specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef>, proteins, and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef> involved in the growth and spread of cancer cells. Targeted therapies used to treat thyroid cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_159" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000799054" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/entrectinib">entrectinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000795854" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/larotrectinibsulfate">larotrectinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000801635" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/selpercatinib">selpercatinib</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000698680" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vandetanib">vandetanib </DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_226">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_214"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_215">Joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using existing treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_216">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done.</Para><Para id="_217">Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_131"><Title>Treatment of newly diagnosed childhood papillary and follicular thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_133">Treatment of papillary and follicular thyroid carcinoma in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_134" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to remove all or most of the thyroid gland and sometimes lymph nodes near the thyroid gland. Radioactive iodine  therapy may also be given if any thyroid cancer cells remain after surgery. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046127" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hormone replacement therapy</GlossaryTermRef> (HRT) is given to make up for the lost <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid hormone</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Radioactive iodine therapy alone may be given to children whose tumor cannot be removed by surgery. HRT is given to make up for the lost thyroid hormone.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>Treatment of newly diagnosed childhood medullary thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_140">Treatment of medullary thyroid cancer in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_141" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery to remove the cancer</ListItem><ListItem>targeted therapy (selpercatinib or vandetanib) for cancer that has continued to grow during treatment or has spread to other parts of the body</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_142"><Title>Treatment of progressive or recurrent childhood thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_144">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045850" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progressive</GlossaryTermRef> or  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> papillary and follicular thyroid carcinoma in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_145" Style="bullet"><ListItem>radioactive iodine therapy</ListItem><ListItem>targeted therapy (entrectinib, larotrectinib, or selpercatinib)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_230">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Prognosis and prognostic factors for childhood thyroid cancer</Title><Para id="_218">If your child has been diagnosed with thyroid cancer, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_44">The prognosis depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem>your child's age at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>the type of thyroid cancer</ListItem><ListItem>the size of the cancer</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor has spread to the lymph nodes or other parts of the body at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer was completely removed by surgery</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_219">The prognosis for most children with papillary thyroid cancer and follicular thyroid cancer is very good.</Para><Para id="_220">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment </Title><Para id="_221">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_148_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_150">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment for childhood thyroid cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_151" Style="bullet"><ListItem>changes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">salivary glands</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem> increased risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem> trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_152">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your  child's doctors about the effects cancer treatment can have on your child.  Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_87"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_89">It is common for thyroid cancer to recur (come back), especially in children younger than 10 years and those with cancer in the lymph nodes. Ultrasound, whole-body scan, and thyroglobulin tests may be done from time to time to check if the cancer has recurred. Lifelong follow-up of thyroid hormone levels in the blood is needed to make sure the right amount of hormone replacement therapy (HRT) is being given. Talk with your child's doctor to find out how often these tests need to be done.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_222"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_223">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_101"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_228">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_229" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/thyroid">Thyroid Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/nci/pediatric-adult-rare-tumor/rare-tumors/rare-endocrine-tumor">MyPART - My Pediatric and Adult Rare Tumor Network</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors and Caregivers</ExternalRef>
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood thyroid cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Thyroid Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/thyroid/patient/child-thyroid-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/thyroid/patient/child-thyroid-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2018-01-11</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
