<Summary id="CDR0000789588" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood laryngeal (throat) tumors start in some tissues of the throat. Learn more about symptoms and causes of laryngeal tumors and how they are diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/laryngeal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Laryngeal Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038962">laryngeal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_7">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood laryngeal cancer and papillomatosis. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood laryngeal cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>laryngeal papillomatosis</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Laryngeal Tumors (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Laryngeal Tumors</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Laryngeal Tumors</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>What are childhood laryngeal tumors?</Title><Para id="_18101">Childhood laryngeal tumors form in the voice box, also called the larynx. These tumors may be benign (which means they are not cancer) or cancer. Most laryngeal tumors in children are not cancer and do not spread to other tissues. Both types of tumors need treatment.</Para><Para id="_18102">The most common type of benign laryngeal tumor is papillomatosis of the larynx. In this condition, papillomas (benign tumors that look like warts) form in the lining of the larynx. These tumors may block the airway and cause trouble breathing. They often come back after treatment and, in rare cases, may turn into cancer in the larynx or the lung.</Para><Para id="_13">The larynx is a part of the throat, between the base of the tongue and the trachea (windpipe). The larynx contains the vocal cords, which vibrate and make sound when air is directed against them. The sound echoes through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046061" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharynx</GlossaryTermRef>, mouth, and nose to make a person's voice.</Para><Para id="_14">There are three main parts of the larynx:</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The supraglottis is the upper part of the larynx above the vocal cords, including the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046421" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epiglottis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The glottis is the middle part of the larynx where the vocal cords are located.</ListItem><ListItem>The subglottis is the lower part of the larynx between the vocal cords and the trachea.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000801514" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the larynx; drawing shows the epiglottis, supraglottis, vocal cord, glottis, and subglottis. Also shown are the tongue, trachea, and esophagus." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1682"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the larynx. The larynx is a part of the throat, between the base of the tongue and the trachea. The three main parts of the larynx are the supraglottis (including the epiglottis), the glottis (including the vocal cords), and the subglottis.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18103"><Title>Causes of childhood laryngeal tumors</Title><Para id="_18104">Laryngeal cancer in children is caused by certain changes to the way cells in the larynx function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these cell changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef> </Para><Para id="_18143">Laryngeal papillomatosis is caused by infection with low-risk HPV (human papillomavirus), most often types 6 and 11. Children can get the HPV infection that causes laryngeal papillomatosis from an infected mother during birth. Most children with an HPV infection do not develop laryngeal papillomatosis. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_18144">Getting the HPV vaccine can help protect against HPV infection and reduce the risk of transmitting it during childbirth. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/infectious-agents/hpv-vaccine-fact-sheet">HPV Vaccines</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Symptoms of childhood laryngeal tumors</Title><Para id="_20">Children may not have symptoms of a laryngeal tumor until the tumor has grown bigger. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet"><ListItem>hoarseness or a change in the voice</ListItem><ListItem>trouble or pain when swallowing</ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>a high-pitched sound with breathing</ListItem><ListItem>a lump in the neck or throat</ListItem><ListItem>a sore throat</ListItem><ListItem>a cough that does not go away</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18106">Infants and young children with these tumors may grow slowly and not eat well or meet <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">developmental milestones</GlossaryTermRef> such as sitting, walking, and talking in sentences.</Para><Para id="_18107">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than a laryngeal tumor. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood laryngeal tumors</Title><Para id="_25">If your child has symptoms that suggest a laryngeal tumor, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or some other problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with a laryngeal tumor, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_18108">The tests used to diagnose laryngeal tumors may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_18109"><Title>Oral exam</Title><Para id="_18110">In an oral exam, a doctor or dentist checks the mouth for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas. This exam may be done while under anesthesia. The doctor or dentist will feel the entire inside of the mouth with a gloved finger and examine the area with a small long-handled mirror and lights or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476949" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fiberoptic</GlossaryTermRef> device.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18111"><Title>Neck and chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_18112">An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of the inside of the body. A neck and chest x-ray makes pictures of the organs and bones inside the neck and chest.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18113"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_18114"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas in the body, such as the head and neck. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18115"><Title>CT scan</Title><Para id="_18116">CT scan (CAT scan) uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775452" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_87"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck. </Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18117"><Title>PET scan</Title><Para id="_18118">PET scan  (positron emission tomography scan) uses a small amount of radioactive sugar (also called radioactive glucose) that is injected into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes pictures of where sugar is being used by the body. Cancer cells show up brighter in the pictures because they are more active and take up more sugar than normal cells do.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775456" type="image/jpeg" alt="Positron emission tomography (PET) scan; drawing shows a child lying on table that slides through the PET scanner." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1688"><Caption language="en">Positron emission tomography (PET) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the PET scanner. The head rest and white strap help the child lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the child's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do. </Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18119"><Title>Ultrasound</Title><Para id="_18120">Ultrasound uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18121"><Title>Barium swallow</Title><Para id="_18122"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Barium swallow</GlossaryTermRef> is a series of x-rays of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef> and stomach. For this procedure, the patient drinks a liquid that contains barium (a silver-white metallic compound). The barium coats the esophagus and stomach which helps them show up more clearly in x-rays. This procedure is also called an upper GI series.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18123"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_18124">A biopsy is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the tumor so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for signs of disease, such as cancer or laryngeal papillomatosis.</Para><Para id="_18125">The sample of tissue may be removed during a procedure, such as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_28" Style="dash"><ListItem><Strong>Laryngoscopy</Strong> is a procedure in which the doctor checks the larynx (voice box) with a mirror or a laryngoscope to check for abnormal areas.

A laryngoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing the inside of the throat and voice box. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of disease.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Endoscopy</Strong> is a procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body, such as the throat, esophagus, and trachea to check for abnormal areas. An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing that is inserted through an opening in the body, such as the mouth. A special tool on the endoscope may be used to remove samples of tissue.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18126"><Title>Human papillomavirus (HPV) test</Title><Para id="_18127">An HPV test checks tissue samples from the biopsy for certain types of HPV infection that may be linked to laryngeal papillomatosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18128"><Title>Immunohistochemistry</Title><Para id="_18129">Immunohistochemistry uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (markers) in a sample of a patient's cells or tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to  help diagnose cancer and help tell one type of cancer from another type.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18130"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_1773">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's cancer.</Para><Para id="_1774">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_34"><Title>Treatment of childhood laryngeal tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_18131"><Title>Who treats children with laryngeal tumors?</Title><Para id="_1677">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of laryngeal tumors. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1678" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044444" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ear, nose, and throat specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_18132">There are different types of treatment for children with laryngeal tumors. You and your child's care team will work together to decide on treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_18133">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the tumor, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_18134"><Title>Treatment of childhood laryngeal cancer</Title><Para id="_43">Laser surgery uses a laser beam (a narrow beam of intense light) to destroy the cancer cells.</Para><Para id="_46">For laryngeal cancer that is likely to spread, external radiation therapy is also used. This treatment uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_18135">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18136"><Title>Treatment of childhood laryngeal papillomatosis</Title><Para id="_18137">Laser surgery, which uses a laser beam (a narrow beam of intense light) to destroy cancer cells, may be used to treat newly diagnosed papillomatosis or other benign tumors.</Para><Para id="_74">For laryngeal papillomatosis that comes back after being removed by laser surgery four times in one year, treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_75" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Immunotherapy. Immunotherapy uses the patient's immune system to fight disease.</ListItem><ListItem>Laser surgery combined with targeted therapy. Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to block the action of specific enzymes, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef>, or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef> involved in the growth and spread of cancer cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18138"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_18138_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_18138_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_18138_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18139"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_18139_md_98">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_18139_md_99">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18142"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_1791">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_76"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related Resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck">Head and Neck Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef>
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood laryngeal cancer and papillomatosis.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Laryngeal Tumors. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/laryngeal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/laryngeal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2018-01-11</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-08</DateLastModified></Summary>
