<Summary id="CDR0000789556" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood salivary gland tumors are rare and start in the salivary glands. Learn about the symptoms and risk factors of childhood salivary gland tumors and how they are diagnosed and treated. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/salivary-gland-treatment-pdq">Childhood Salivary Gland Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038946">salivary gland cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_966">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood salivary gland tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_967">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood salivary gland cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood salivary gland tumors</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Salivary Gland Tumors (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Salivary Gland Tumors</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Salivary Gland Tumors</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1775"><Title>What are salivary gland tumors?</Title><Para id="_1712">Salivary gland tumors are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> growths that can form in the salivary glands. They can be benign (not cancer) or malignant (cancerous). Although benign tumors do not spread to other parts of the body, they may require treatment to stop them from continuing to grow and press on nearby tissue. Cancerous tumors can spread to other areas of the body and will be treated to kill the cancer cells. Salivary gland tumors rarely occur in children.</Para><Para id="_1773">The salivary glands make saliva and release it into the mouth. Saliva has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> that help digest food and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> that help protect against mouth and throat infections. There are three pairs of major salivary glands:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1774" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Parotid glands are the largest glands and are found in front of and just below each ear. Most salivary gland tumors begin in this gland.</ListItem><ListItem>Sublingual glands are found under the tongue in the floor of the mouth.</ListItem><ListItem>Submandibular glands are found below the jawbone.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000791244" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the salivary glands; drawing shows a cross section of the head and the three main pairs of salivary glands. The parotid glands are in front of and just below each ear; the sublingual glands are under the tongue in the floor of the mouth; and the submandibular glands are below each side of the jawbone. The tongue and lymph nodes are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1776"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the salivary glands. The three main pairs of salivary glands are the parotid glands, the sublingual glands, and the submandibular glands.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1713"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood salivary gland tumors</Title><Para id="_1714">Salivary gland tumors in children are caused by certain changes to the way salivary gland cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these cell changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_1715">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Past treatment for cancer with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or radiation therapy is a risk factor for childhood salivary gland tumors. Not every child with this risk factor will develop a salivary gland tumor. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1716"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Symptoms of childhood salivary gland tumors</Title><Para id="_1717">Children may not have symptoms of a salivary gland tumor until the tumor has grown bigger. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1718" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a lump near the ear, cheek, jaw, lip, or inside the mouth that may be painless</ListItem><ListItem>numbness or weakness in the face</ListItem><ListItem>pain in the face that does not go away</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1719">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than a salivary gland tumor. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1720"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood salivary gland tumors</Title><Para id="_1721">If your child has symptoms that suggest a salivary gland tumor, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to a salivary gland tumor or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with a salivary gland tumor, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_1757">The tests used to diagnose salivary gland tumors in children may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_1758"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_1759">MRI uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas of the body, such as the head and neck. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1806"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1760"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_1761">A CT scan uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775452" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1777"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan of the head and neck. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of the inside of the head and neck. </Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1762"><Title>Ultrasound exam</Title><Para id="_1763">An ultrasound exam uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) which bounce off internal tissue or organs, such as the pelvis, and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1764"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_1765">A biopsy is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the tumor so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for signs of cancer. Fine-needle aspiration biopsy is used to check for salivary gland cancer. During a fine-needle aspiration biopsy, tissue or fluid is removed using a thin needle.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1724"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_1725">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's tumor.</Para><Para id="_1726">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1789"><Title>Who treats children with salivary gland tumors?</Title><Para id="_1729">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of salivary gland tumors. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1785" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pathologist</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044444" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ear, nose, and throat specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1792"><Title>Treatment of childhood salivary gland tumors</Title><Para id="_1793">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with salivary gland tumors. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_1794">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the tumor, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child’s care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_1795">Treatment of salivary gland tumors may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1796" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery  to remove salivary gland tumors or salivary gland cancer is the most common treatment. If the parotid gland is removed during surgery, special care must be taken to avoid damage to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000799141" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">facial nerve</GlossaryTermRef>. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery">Surgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy may be given after surgery for salivary gland cancer. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Salivary gland cancer may be treated with external beam radiation therapy or internal radiation therapy if the cancer is likely to spread.<ItemizedList id="_1797" Style="bullet"><ListItem> External beam radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Internal radiation therapy, also called brachytherapy, uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheters</GlossaryTermRef> that are placed directly into or near the cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1798"> Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy">Radiation Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>Targeted therapy (<DrugRef href="CDR0000799054" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/entrectinib">entrectinib</DrugRef> or <DrugRef href="CDR0000795854" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/larotrectinibsulfate">larotrectinib</DrugRef>) may be used to treat recurrent childhood salivary gland cancer. Recurrent salivary gland cancer is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to block the action of specific enzymes, proteins, or other molecules involved in the growth and spread of cancer cells. The doctor may suggest biomarker tests to help predict your child's response to certain targeted therapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1799"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_1799_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_1799_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_1799_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1803"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Prognosis and prognostic factors for childhood salivary gland tumors</Title><Para id="_1804">If your child has been diagnosed with salivary gland cancer, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis. The prognosis can be affected by whether the cancer has spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> or other parts of the body at the time of diagnosis and whether the cancer can be completely removed by surgery. The prognosis for salivary gland cancer in children is usually good.</Para><Para id="_1805">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1751"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_1791">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_1751_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1781">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1783" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems, such as:<ItemizedList id="_1696" Style="bullet"><ListItem>dry mouth</ListItem><ListItem>trouble seeing</ListItem><ListItem>numbness or weakness in the face</ListItem><ListItem>changes in the way the bones of the head and face grow</ListItem><ListItem>other changes in the child's appearance</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1786">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1752"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_1807">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to <SummaryRef href="CDR0000789556#_1720" url="/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/salivary-gland-treatment-pdq">diagnose</SummaryRef> the tumor may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_1754">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the tumor has recurred (come back).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1755"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_1756">When a child has a tumor, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child’s treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1787"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors and Caregivers</ExternalRef>
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood salivary gland tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Salivary Gland Tumors. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/salivary-gland-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/patient/child/salivary-gland-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2018-01-10</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-10</DateLastModified></Summary>
