<Summary id="CDR0000790157" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Thyroid cancer screening has not been shown to decrease the chance of dying from the disease. Not all screening tests are helpful, and most have risks. Learn more about thyroid cancer risks and screening in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/thyroid/patient/thyroid-screening-pdq">Thyroid Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/thyroid/hp/thryoid-screening-pdq">Thyroid Cancer (PDQ®): Screening</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028536">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038801">thyroid cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SecondaryTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></SecondaryTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_225">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the screening of thyroid cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_226">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>thyroid cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Thyroid Cancer Screening (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Thyroid Cancer Screening</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Thyroid Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_227"><Title>What Is Screening?</Title><Para id="_228"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Screening</GlossaryTermRef> is looking for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> before a person has any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>. 
         This can help find cancer at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> 
         <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> or cancer is found early, it may be easier to treat. 
         By the time symptoms appear, cancer may have begun to spread.</Para><Para id="_229"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> are trying to better understand which people are 
         more likely to get certain types of cancer. They also study the 
         things we do and the things around us to see if they cause cancer. 
         This information helps doctors recommend who should be screened 
         for cancer, which <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810044" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening tests</GlossaryTermRef> should be used, and how often 
         the tests should be done.</Para><Para id="_230">It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily 
         think you have cancer if he or she suggests a screening test.
         Screening tests are given when you have no cancer symptoms.</Para><Para id="_231">If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more 
         tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called 
         <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689569" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_232"><Title>General Information About Thyroid Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_233"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_234">Thyroid cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells 
         form in the tissues of the thyroid gland.</KeyPoint><Para id="_273">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046036" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid</GlossaryTermRef> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gland</GlossaryTermRef> at the base of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef> near the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> (windpipe).   It is shaped like a butterfly, with a right <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046188" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lobe</GlossaryTermRef> and a left lobe. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044549" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">isthmus</GlossaryTermRef>, a thin piece of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, connects the two lobes. A healthy thyroid is about the size of a walnut. It usually cannot be felt through the skin.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000719086" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the thyroid and parathyroid glands; drawing shows the thyroid gland at the base of the throat near the trachea. An inset shows the front and back views. The front view shows that the thyroid is shaped like a butterfly, with the right lobe and left lobe connected by a thin piece of tissue called the isthmus. The back view shows the four pea-sized parathyroid glands. The larynx is also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_274"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the thyroid and parathyroid glands. The thyroid gland lies at the base of the throat near the trachea. It is shaped like a butterfly, with the right lobe and left lobe connected by a thin piece of tissue called the isthmus. The parathyroid glands are four pea-sized organs found in the neck near the thyroid. The thyroid and parathyroid glands make hormones.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_275">The thyroid uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044548" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iodine</GlossaryTermRef>, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045787" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mineral</GlossaryTermRef> found in some foods and in iodized salt, to help make several  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef>.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044558" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thyroid   hormones</GlossaryTermRef> do the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_276" Style="bullet"><ListItem>control  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart rate</GlossaryTermRef>, body temperature, and how quickly food is changed into energy (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef>)</ListItem><ListItem>control the amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045632" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">calcium</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_235">Learn more about thyroid cancer at  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258038" url="/types/thyroid/patient/thyroid-treatment-pdq">Thyroid Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_236"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Incidence</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_281">Thyroid cancer is found more often in women.</KeyPoint><Para id="_282">Thyroid cancer is most often <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> in men and women aged  55 to  64 years.  Women are about three times more likely than men to have thyroid cancer.</Para><Para id="_289">The number of people diagnosed with thyroid cancer in the United States increased from 1974 to 2013, but the number of deaths from thyroid cancer has stayed the same or decreased slightly. Rates  of thyroid cancer leveled off  from 2013 to 2016, and there was a decrease in the rate of  thyroid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>  less than 1 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354457" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">centimeter</GlossaryTermRef> in size. Most cases of thyroid cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment and are usually <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318813" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cured</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_237"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_238">Being exposed to radiation increases the risk of thyroid cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_239">Anything that increases a person's chance of getting a disease is 
         called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Not every person with one or more of these risk factors will develop thyroid cancer, and it will also develop in some people who don't have any known risk factors. Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_290">Risk factors for thyroid cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_277" Style="bullet"> 
		   
		   
		  <ListItem>Being exposed  to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to the head and neck as an infant or child or being exposed to radiation from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive fallout</GlossaryTermRef>. The cancer may  occur as soon as 5 years after exposure. </ListItem><ListItem>Having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of thyroid disease or thyroid cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">history</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044545" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">goiter</GlossaryTermRef> (enlarged thyroid).</ListItem><ListItem>Having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> such as  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000702087" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2 syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (MEN2), which is caused by a change in the <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810835" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RET</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Being female.</ListItem><ListItem>Being Asian.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_241"><Title>Thyroid Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_242"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Screening methods</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_243">Tests are used to screen for different types of cancer when a person does not have symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_245"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Scientists</GlossaryTermRef> study <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810044" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening tests</GlossaryTermRef> to find those with the fewest 
         harms and most benefits. Cancer screening trials also are meant 
         to show whether early detection (finding cancer before it causes 
         <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>) helps a person live longer or decreases a person's chance of dying from the disease. 
         For some types of cancer, the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454708" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recovery</GlossaryTermRef> is better if 
         the disease is found and treated at an early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_278"><KeyPoint id="_279">There is no standard or routine screening test for thyroid cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_280">There is no standard or routine screening test used for early detection of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Thyroid cancer that does not cause symptoms may be found during:</Para><ItemizedList id="_291" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a routine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> when the doctor checks a person's neck for lumps (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044502" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nodules</GlossaryTermRef>) or swelling in the neck, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000520366" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">voice box</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, or anything else that seems unusual</ListItem><ListItem> a surgery that is done for another condition</ListItem><ListItem>an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> that is done for another condition</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_283"><KeyPoint id="_284">Screening for thyroid cancer may not help a person live longer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_285">Studies have shown that screening for thyroid cancer does not decrease the chance of dying from the disease. No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> have been done in the United States to find out if a neck exam, ultrasound, or other screening test decreases the risk of dying from thyroid cancer. Neck exams and ultrasound are sometimes used to screen for thyroid cancer but do not decrease the risk of dying from the disease.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_292"><KeyPoint id="_293">Screening tests for thyroid cancer are being studied in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_292_md_95">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> supported by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044267" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">NCI</GlossaryTermRef> can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_258"><Title>Risks of Thyroid Cancer Screening</Title><SummarySection id="_259"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risks of screening</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_260">Screening tests have risks.</KeyPoint><Para id="_261">Decisions about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810044" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening tests</GlossaryTermRef> can be difficult. Not all 
         screening tests are helpful, and most have risks. Before having 
         any screening test, you may want to discuss the test with your 
         doctor. It is important to know the risks of the test and whether 
         it has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_262"><KeyPoint id="_263">The risks of thyroid cancer screening include:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_286"><KeyPoint id="_287">Finding thyroid cancer that may never  cause symptoms or become life threatening.</KeyPoint><Para id="_288">When a screening test result leads to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment of a disease that may never have caused <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> or become life-threatening, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000759894" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overdiagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045959" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Diagnostic tests</GlossaryTermRef> (such as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fine-needle aspiration biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>) and cancer treatments (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045855" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive iodine</GlossaryTermRef> therapy) can have serious risks, including physical and emotional problems.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_264"><KeyPoint id="_265">False-negative test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_266">Screening test results may appear to be normal even though <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid 
         cancer</GlossaryTermRef> is present. A person who receives a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340928" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-negative test result</GlossaryTermRef> 
         (one that shows there is no cancer when there really is) may 
         delay seeking medical care even if there are symptoms.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_267"><KeyPoint id="_268">False-positive test results can occur.</KeyPoint><Para id="_269">Screening test results may appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> even though 
         no cancer is present. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">false-positive test result</GlossaryTermRef> (one that 
         shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> 
         and is usually followed by more tests and procedures (such 
         as a fine-needle aspiration biopsy), which also have risks.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the screening of thyroid cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/screening-prevention">PDQ Screening and Prevention Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Screening and Prevention Editorial Board. PDQ Thyroid Cancer Screening. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/thyroid/patient/thyroid-screening-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/thyroid/patient/thyroid-screening-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000790145"/><DateFirstPublished>2018-02-07</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
