<Summary id="CDR0000790385" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatment for children with laryngeal tumors depends upon the type; most are rhabdomyosarcoma and treated with chemotherapy and radiation therapy. Squamous cell carcinoma is managed with surgery and radiation therapy. Get detailed treatment information in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/laryngeal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Laryngeal  Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038962">laryngeal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1556">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood laryngeal  cancer and papillomatosis. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_1557">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood laryngeal cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>laryngeal papillomatosis</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Laryngeal  Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Laryngeal  Tumors Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Laryngeal  Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1840"><Title>Childhood Laryngeal  Cancer</Title><SummarySection id="_2436"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_1905">Tumors of the larynx are rare. In children, the most common benign vascular laryngeal tumor is subglottic hemangioma.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Malignant
laryngeal tumors, which are especially rare, may be associated with benign tumors such as polyps and
papillomas.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2430"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_2431">Laryngeal tumors may present with the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2432" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Hoarseness.</ListItem><ListItem>Difficulty swallowing.</ListItem><ListItem>Stridor.</ListItem><ListItem>Enlargement of the lymph nodes of the neck.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1841"><Title>Histology</Title><Para id="_1842">A review of Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) Program data from 1973 to 2016 identified 23 pediatric patients with laryngeal malignancies. Sixteen of the patients had squamous cell carcinoma. The other identified histologies included small cell carcinoma, mucoepidermoid carcinoma, myxosarcoma, embryonal rhabdomyosarcoma, and synovial sarcoma.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1477"><Title>Treatment of Childhood Laryngeal  Cancer</Title><Para id="_1884"> Squamous cell carcinoma of the larynx in children is managed by surgery and radiation therapy, as in adults with
carcinoma at this site.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>   Laser surgery may be the
initial treatment used for these lesions. Outcomes of pediatric patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the larynx  are similar to those reported for adult patients.<Reference refidx="4"/> For more information about the treatment of laryngeal cancer in adults, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062922" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/laryngeal-treatment-pdq">Laryngeal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1811"><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation for Childhood Laryngeal  Cancer</Title><Para id="_1873">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15692531">Bitar MA, Moukarbel RV, Zalzal GH: Management of congenital subglottic hemangioma: trends and success over the past 17 years. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 132 (2): 226-31, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9052665" MedlineID="97206937">McGuirt WF, Little JP: Laryngeal cancer in children and adolescents. Otolaryngol Clin North Am 30 (2): 207-14, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="8973518" MedlineID="97128978">Bauman NM, Smith RJ: Recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. Pediatr Clin North Am 43 (6): 1385-401, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="33279850">Forsyth AM, Camilon PR, Tracy L, et al.: Pediatric laryngeal tumors and demographics, management, and survival in laryngeal squamous cell carcinoma. Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol 140: 110507, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="12652621" MedlineID="22538839">Siddiqui F, Sarin R, Agarwal JP, et al.: Squamous carcinoma of the larynx and hypopharynx in children: a distinct clinical entity? Med Pediatr Oncol 40 (5): 322-4, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1864"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Unusual Cancers Special Considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Special Considerations for the Treatment of Children With Cancer</Title>

<Para id="_1864_md_3">Cancer in children and adolescents is rare, although the overall incidence has slowly increased since 1975.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Children and adolescents with cancer should be referred to medical centers that have a multidisciplinary team of cancer specialists with experience treating the cancers that occur during childhood and adolescence.  This multidisciplinary team approach incorporates the skills
of the following pediatric specialists and others to ensure that children receive treatment, supportive care, and rehabilitation
to achieve optimal survival and quality of life:</Para>
        <ItemizedList id="_1864_md_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Primary care physicians.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric surgeons.</ListItem><ListItem>Pathologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric radiation
oncologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric medical oncologists and hematologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Ophthalmologists.</ListItem><ListItem> Rehabilitation
specialists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric oncology nurses.</ListItem><ListItem>Social workers.</ListItem><ListItem>Child-life professionals.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Nutritionists.</ListItem></ItemizedList>
 <Para id="_1864_md_5">For specific information about supportive care for children and adolescents with cancer, see the summaries on <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/supportive-care">Supportive and Palliative Care</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1864_md_6">The American Academy of Pediatrics has outlined guidelines for
pediatric cancer centers and their role in the treatment of children and adolescents
with cancer.<Reference refidx="2"/>  At
these centers, clinical trials are available for most  types of cancer that occur in children and adolescents, and the opportunity
to participate is offered to most patients and their families.  Clinical
trials for children and adolescents diagnosed with cancer are generally
designed to compare potentially better therapy with current standard therapy. Other types of clinical trials test novel therapies when there is no standard therapy for a cancer diagnosis.  Most of the progress in identifying curative
therapies for childhood cancers has been achieved through clinical trials. 
Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1864_md_7">Dramatic improvements in survival have been achieved for children and adolescents with cancer. Between 1975 and 2020, childhood cancer mortality decreased by more than 50%.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  Childhood and adolescent cancer survivors require close monitoring because side effects of cancer therapy may persist or develop months or years after treatment.  For information about the incidence, type, and monitoring of late effects in childhood and adolescent cancer survivors, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343584" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-hp-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para>
<Para id="_1864_md_8">Childhood cancer is a rare disease, with about 15,000 cases diagnosed annually in the United States in individuals younger than 20 years.<Reference refidx="6"/> The U.S. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.congress.gov/107/plaws/publ280/PLAW-107publ280.pdf">Rare Diseases Act of 2002</ExternalRef> defines a rare disease as one that affects populations smaller than 200,000 people in the United States. Therefore, all pediatric cancers are considered rare.</Para><Para id="_1864_md_9">The designation of a rare tumor is not uniform among pediatric and adult groups. In adults, rare cancers are defined as those with an annual incidence of fewer than six cases per 100,000 people. They account for up to 24% of all cancers diagnosed in the European Union and about 20% of all cancers diagnosed in the United States.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> In children and adolescents, the designation of a rare tumor is not uniform among international groups, as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1864_md_10" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A consensus effort between the European Union Joint Action on Rare Cancers and the European Cooperative Study Group for Rare Pediatric Cancers estimated that 11% of all cancers in patients younger than 20 years could be categorized as very rare. This consensus group defined very rare cancers as those with annual incidences of fewer than two cases per 1 million people. However, three additional histologies (thyroid carcinoma, melanoma, and testicular cancer) with incidences of more than two cases per 1 million people were also included  in the very rare group due to a lack of knowledge and expertise in the management of these tumors.<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Children's Oncology Group defines rare pediatric cancers as those listed in the International Classification of Childhood Cancer subgroup XI, which includes thyroid cancers, melanomas and nonmelanoma skin cancers, and multiple types of carcinomas (e.g., adrenocortical carcinomas, nasopharyngeal carcinomas, and most adult-type carcinomas such as breast cancers and colorectal cancers).<Reference refidx="10"/>  These diagnoses account for about 5% of the cancers diagnosed in children aged 0 to 14 years and about 27% of the cancers diagnosed in adolescents aged 15 to 19 years.<Reference refidx="4"/><Para id="_11"> Most cancers in subgroup XI are either melanomas or thyroid cancers, with other cancer types accounting for only 2% of the cancers diagnosed in children aged 0 to 14 years and 9.3% of the cancers diagnosed in adolescents aged 15 to 19 years.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1864_md_12">These rare cancers are extremely challenging to study because of the relatively few patients with any individual diagnosis, the predominance of rare cancers in the adolescent population, and the small number of clinical trials for adolescents with rare cancers.</Para><Para id="_1837">Information about these tumors may also be found in sources relevant to
adults with cancer, such as <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062922" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/adult/laryngeal-treatment-pdq">Laryngeal Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20404250">Smith MA, Seibel NL, Altekruse SF, et al.: Outcomes for children and adolescents with cancer: challenges for the twenty-first century. J Clin Oncol 28 (15): 2625-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2">American Academy of Pediatrics: Standards for pediatric cancer centers. Pediatrics  134 (2): 410-4, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/134/2/410">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24853691">Smith MA, Altekruse SF, Adamson PC, et al.: Declining childhood and adolescent cancer mortality. Cancer 120 (16): 2497-506, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4">National Cancer Institute: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://NCCRExplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Surveillance Research Program, National Cancer Institute: SEER*Explorer: An interactive website for SEER cancer statistics. 	Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statistics-network/explorer/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24488779">Ward E, DeSantis C, Robbins A, et al.: Childhood and adolescent cancer statistics, 2014. CA Cancer J Clin 64 (2): 83-103, 2014 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28687376">Gatta G, Capocaccia R, Botta L, et al.: Burden and centralised treatment in Europe of rare tumours: results of RARECAREnet-a population-based study. Lancet Oncol 18 (8): 1022-1039, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28542893">DeSantis CE, Kramer JL, Jemal A: The burden of rare cancers in the United States. CA Cancer J Clin 67 (4): 261-272, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="30785015">Ferrari A, Brecht IB, Gatta G, et al.: Defining and listing very rare cancers of paediatric age: consensus of the Joint Action on Rare Cancers in cooperation with the European Cooperative Study Group for Pediatric Rare Tumors. Eur J Cancer 110: 120-126, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20956621">Pappo AS, Krailo M, Chen Z, et al.: Infrequent tumor initiative of the Children's Oncology Group: initial lessons learned and their impact on future plans. J Clin Oncol 28 (33): 5011-6, 2010.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1486"><Title>Childhood Laryngeal Papillomatosis</Title><SummarySection id="_1845"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_1906">Respiratory papillomatosis is  the most common benign laryngeal tumor in children and is associated with human papillomavirus (HPV) infection, most commonly HPV-6 and HPV-11.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  The presence of HPV-11 appears to correlate with a more aggressive clinical course than the presence of HPV-6.<Reference refidx="3"/> An Australian survey of pediatric otorhinolaryngologists documented a decline in the incidence of laryngeal papillomatosis after the introduction of HPV vaccinations for adolescent girls and young women aged 12 to 26 years.<Reference refidx="4"/> In another study of laryngeal papillomatosis in patients younger than 18 years, the incidence decreased from 165 cases in children born between 2004 and 2005 to 36 cases in children born between 2012 and 2013. The HPV vaccine was released in 2006. The authors attributed the decline to the widespread use of the vaccine.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1907"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_2424">Laryngeal papillomatosis can cause
hoarseness because of the formation of wart-like nodules on the vocal
cords, which may rarely extend into the lung, producing significant morbidity.<Reference refidx="6"/> Malignant
degeneration may occur, with development of laryngeal carcinoma and  squamous cell lung cancer, generally reported at rates of 2% to 10% in the pediatric population.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1908"><Title>Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_2425">Exposure to HPV during a vaginal birth appears to be a risk factor for the development of juvenile-onset recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. A multi-institutional registry study identified children with juvenile-onset recurrent respiratory papillomatosis from 23 states between 2015 and 2020.<Reference refidx="8"/>  Of those children, 88.8% were delivered vaginally. Among 190 mothers, the median age at the time of delivery was 22 years. Of 114 mothers (60.0%) who were age-eligible to receive the HPV vaccine, 16 (14.0%) were vaccinated, 1 (0.9%) of whom was vaccinated before delivery. Of 162 tested biopsy specimens from children undergoing papillomatosis surgery, 157 (96.9%) had detectable HPV. All 157 specimens had a vaccine-preventable HPV type.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1847"><Title>Treatment of Childhood Laryngeal Papillomatosis</Title><Para id="_1848">Primary treatment for papillomatosis is surgical ablation with laser vaporization.<Reference refidx="9"/> Frequent recurrences are common. Lung involvement, although rare, can occur.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_1909">Evidence (surgery):</Para><OrderedList id="_1910" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A single-institution retrospective analysis evaluated 121 children with respiratory papillomatosis.  The age at initial operation was 4.3 years (±2.9 years), and  47.9% of patients (58 of 121) experienced a recurrence and underwent surgical treatment after the age of 14 years.<Reference refidx="10"/><ItemizedList id="_1911" Style="bullet"><ListItem> At follow-up, 5% of the patients (6 of 121) had died, 41.3% of the patients (50 of 121) had been recurrence free for 5 years or longer (cured group), and 53.7% of the patients (65 of 121) experienced a recurrence in the previous 5 years (recurrent group).  </ListItem><ListItem>There were no significant differences in sex, age at initial operation, or adjuvant therapy between the cured and recurrent groups of patients.  </ListItem><ListItem>In the recurrent group, there was a higher incidence of overall operation frequency, aggressive disease, tracheal dissemination of the papilloma, and HPV infection.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_1886">If a patient requires more than four surgical procedures per year, other interventions may be necessary. The following therapies are under investigation:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1849" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Systemic bevacizumab produced good results with minimal toxicity in a report of two patients with aggressive recurrent respiratory papillomatosis.<Reference refidx="11"/> In another report of seven children treated with bevacizumab, continued responses were noted and subsequent surgical debridements were avoided in most patients. Of the seven patients, five did not require surgical debridement after the initiation of bevacizumab. Four of these five patients had previously required between four and ten debridements per year. Follow-up for these patients was between 8 months and 3.5 years. No serious adverse events were reported.<Reference refidx="12"/> In a study of 24 patients with recurrent respiratory papillomatosis, 15 had juvenile-onset disease. Patients were treated with systemic bevacizumab (7.5–10 mg/kg) every 3 to 4 weeks. All patients had a  reduction in the number and size of lesions after three doses, excluding one patient who was lost to follow-up. Voice outcomes were improved in 87.5% of patients, as measured by Voice Handicap Index-30 (VHI) or pediatric VHI. No grade 3 Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events were reported. However, follow-up was limited to a maximum of 14 months after initiation of therapy and 10 months after discontinuation of bevacizumab.<Reference refidx="13"/> In a  study of 17 adult patients (12 with juvenile-onset recurrent or refractory respiratory papillomatosis) who received systemic bevacizumab,  the number of recurrences and surgeries were significantly reduced compared with previous treatments.<Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem>Interferon therapy.<Reference refidx="15"/></ListItem><ListItem>Immunotherapy with HspE7, a recombinant fusion protein that has shown activity in other HPV-related diseases. A pilot study suggested a marked increase in the amount of time between surgeries.<Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem><ListItem>Laser therapy combined with intralesional bevacizumab.<Reference refidx="17"/></ListItem><ListItem>Intralesional cidofovir has been studied. However, its effectiveness has not been conclusively demonstrated.<Reference refidx="18"/></ListItem><ListItem>Checkpoint inhibitors, such as PD-1 inhibitors, are currently being investigated.<Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem><ListItem>Reports with small numbers of patients have documented that in selected cases, the administration of a quadrivalent HPV vaccine was associated with complete remission and an increase in the intersurgical interval.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/> In contrast, other reports have not documented a therapeutic effect of the quadrivalent HPV vaccine.<Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1875"><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation for Childhood Laryngeal Papillomatosis</Title><Para id="_1876">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="28427542">Fortes HR, von Ranke FM, Escuissato DL, et al.: Recurrent respiratory papillomatosis: A state-of-the-art review. Respir Med 126: 116-121, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="18496162">Derkay CS, Wiatrak B: Recurrent respiratory papillomatosis: a review. Laryngoscope 118 (7): 1236-47, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="16847177">Maloney EM, Unger ER, Tucker RA, et al.: Longitudinal measures of human papillomavirus 6 and 11 viral loads and antibody response in children with recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 132 (7): 711-5, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="29136168">Novakovic D, Cheng ATL, Zurynski Y, et al.: A Prospective Study of the Incidence of Juvenile-Onset Recurrent Respiratory Papillomatosis After Implementation of a National HPV Vaccination Program. J Infect Dis 217 (2): 208-212, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="33621333">Meites E, Stone L, Amiling R, et al.: Significant Declines in Juvenile-onset Recurrent Respiratory Papillomatosis Following Human Papillomavirus (HPV) Vaccine Introduction in the United States. Clin Infect Dis 73 (5): 885-890, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="18281102">Gélinas JF, Manoukian J, Côté A: Lung involvement in juvenile onset recurrent respiratory papillomatosis: a systematic review of the literature. Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol 72 (4): 433-52, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26453486">Karatayli-Ozgursoy S, Bishop JA, Hillel A, et al.: Risk Factors for Dysplasia in Recurrent Respiratory Papillomatosis in an Adult and Pediatric Population. Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol 125 (3): 235-41, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="34145881">Amiling R, Meites E, Querec TD, et al.: Juvenile-Onset Recurrent Respiratory Papillomatosis in the United States, Epidemiology and HPV Types-2015-2020. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc 10 (7): 774-781, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="16469660">Andrus JG, Shapshay SM: Contemporary management of laryngeal papilloma in adults and children. Otolaryngol Clin North Am 39 (1): 135-58, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="32815263">Xiao Y, Zhang X, Ma L, et al.: Long-term outcomes of juvenile-onset recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. Clin Otolaryngol 46 (1): 161-167, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="30588638">Carnevale C, Ferrán-De la Cierva L, Til-Pérez G, et al.: Safe use of systemic bevacizumab for respiratory recurrent papillomatosis in two children. Laryngoscope 129 (4): 1001-1004, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="35043981">Ruiz R, Balamuth N, Javia LR, et al.: Systemic Bevacizumab Treatment for Recurrent Respiratory Papillomatosis: Long-Term Follow-Up. Laryngoscope 132 (10): 2071-2075, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="38180605">Zhao X, Wang J, Chen Q, et al.: Systemic bevacizumab for treatment of recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol 281 (4): 1865-1875, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="38525973">So RJ, Rayle C, Joo HH, et al.: Systemic Bevacizumab for Recurrent Respiratory Papillomatosis: A Single Institution's Experience. Laryngoscope 134 (7): 3253-3259, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="7530830" MedlineID="95140434">Avidano MA, Singleton GT: Adjuvant drug strategies in the treatment of recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 112 (2): 197-202, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="16240938">Derkay CS, Smith RJ, McClay J, et al.: HspE7 treatment of pediatric recurrent respiratory papillomatosis: final results of an open-label trial. Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol 114 (9): 730-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="24633948">Sidell DR, Nassar M, Cotton RT, et al.: High-dose sublesional bevacizumab (avastin) for pediatric recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol 123 (3): 214-21, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="23235619">Chadha NK, James A: Adjuvant antiviral therapy for recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 12: CD005053, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="29492465">Ivancic R, Iqbal H, deSilva B, et al.: Current and future management of recurrent respiratory papillomatosis. Laryngoscope Investig Otolaryngol 3 (1): 22-34, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="25619468">Young DL, Moore MM, Halstead LA: The use of the quadrivalent human papillomavirus vaccine (gardasil) as adjuvant therapy in the treatment of recurrent respiratory papilloma. J Voice 29 (2): 223-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="25496821">Mészner Z, Jankovics I, Nagy A, et al.: Recurrent laryngeal papillomatosis with oesophageal involvement in a 2 year old boy: successful treatment with the quadrivalent human papillomatosis vaccine. Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol 79 (2): 262-6, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="28992265">Katsuta T, Miyaji Y, Offit PA, et al.: Treatment With Quadrivalent Human Papillomavirus Vaccine for Juvenile-Onset Recurrent Respiratory Papillomatosis: Case Report and Review of the Literature. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc 6 (4): 380-385, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1851"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (02/26/2025)</Title><Para id="_1852">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_2435">This summary was reformatted.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790385#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/laryngeal-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood laryngeal  cancer and papillomatosis. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Childhood Laryngeal Tumors Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Denise Adams, MD (Children's Hospital Boston)</ListItem><ListItem>Karen J. Marcus, MD, FACR (Dana-Farber of Boston Children's Cancer Center and Blood Disorders Harvard Medical School)</ListItem><ListItem>William H. Meyer, MD</ListItem><ListItem>Paul A. Meyers, MD (Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Thomas A. Olson, MD (Aflac Cancer and Blood Disorders Center of Children's Healthcare of Atlanta - Egleston Campus)</ListItem><ListItem>Arthur Kim Ritchey, MD (Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC)</ListItem><ListItem>Carlos Rodriguez-Galindo, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Stephen J. Shochat, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Laryngeal Tumors Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/laryngeal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/head-and-neck/hp/child/laryngeal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 29337477]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2018-01-09</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-02-26</DateLastModified></Summary>
