<Summary id="CDR0000790962" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood mesothelioma treatment includes surgery, chemotherapy, and radiation therapy. Learn more about the risk factors, symptoms, tests to diagnose, and treatment of childhood mesothelioma in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/patient/child-mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Mesothelioma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/hp/child-mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Mesothelioma (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038142">malignant mesothelioma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood mesothelioma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood mesothelioma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Mesothelioma Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Mesothelioma Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Mesothelioma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_212"><Title>General Information About Childhood Mesothelioma</Title><SummarySection id="_213"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_214">Mesothelioma is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form in
		  the thin layer of tissue that covers organs in the chest or abdomen.</KeyPoint><Para id="_215"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044992" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Malignant mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef> is a disease in which <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> are found in one or more of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_216" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045842" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pleura</GlossaryTermRef>: A thin layer of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> that lines the chest <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef> and covers the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045829" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Peritoneum</GlossaryTermRef>: A thin layer of tissue that lines the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> and covers most of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organs</GlossaryTermRef> in the abdomen.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pericardium</GlossaryTermRef>: A thin layer of tissue that surrounds the heart.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_217">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef> often spread over the surface of organs without spreading into the organ. They may spread to nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> or in other parts of the body. Malignant mesothelioma may also form in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046611" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">testicles</GlossaryTermRef>, but this is rare.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000805930" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows parts of the body where malignant mesothelioma may form, including the pleura (the tissue that lines the chest cavity and covers the lungs), the pericardium (the tissue that surrounds the heart), the peritoneum (the tissue that lines the abdomen and covers most of the organs in the abdomen), and the testicles. The heart and lungs are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_298"><Caption language="en">Malignant mesothelioma forms in the tissue that lines the chest or abdomen, including the pleura (the tissue that lines the chest cavity and covers the lungs), the pericardium (the tissue that surrounds the heart), and the peritoneum (the tissue that lines the abdomen and covers most of the organs in the abdomen). Malignant mesothelioma may also form in the testicles, but this is rare.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_218"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_219">Treatment with radiation therapy increases the risk of childhood mesothelioma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_220">Anything that increases your chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Having a risk factor does not mean that you will get cancer; not having risk factors doesn't mean that you will not get cancer. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_221">Treatment for an earlier cancer, especially <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, increases the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef> in children.</Para><Para id="_222">In adults, mesothelioma is strongly linked to being exposed to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046528" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">asbestos</GlossaryTermRef>, which has been used in the building and textile industries. In children, there is little information about the risk of developing mesothelioma after being exposed to asbestos.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_223"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_224">Signs and symptoms of mesothelioma include trouble breathing and pain in the chest or abdomen.</KeyPoint><Para id="_225">In children, these and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> may be caused by mesothelioma  or by other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_226">Check with your child's doctor if your child has any of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_227" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Trouble breathing.</ListItem><ListItem>Cough for no known reason.</ListItem><ListItem>Pain under the rib cage or pain in the chest and abdomen.</ListItem><ListItem>Weight loss for no known reason. 
</ListItem><ListItem>Feeling very tired.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_228"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_229">Tests that examine the chest, abdomen, and heart are used to diagnose mesothelioma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_230">The following tests and procedures may be used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_231" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health history</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An exam of the body to check general signs of health, including checking for signs of disease, such as lumps or anything else that seems unusual. A history of the patient’s health habits and past illnesses and treatments will also be taken.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> of the organs and bones inside the chest.  An x-ray is a type of energy beam that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the body.</ListItem><ListItem> <Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an x-ray machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find malignant tumor cells in the body.  A small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive glucose</GlossaryTermRef> (sugar) is injected into a vein.  The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body.  Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775456" type="image/jpeg" alt="Positron emission tomography (PET) scan; drawing shows a child lying on table that slides through the PET scanner." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_294"><Caption language="en">Positron emission tomography (PET) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the PET scanner. The head rest and white strap help the child lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the child's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658018" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pulmonary function test</GlossaryTermRef> (PFT):</Strong> A test to see how well the lungs are working. It measures how much air the lungs can hold and how quickly air moves into and out of the lungs. It also measures how much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> is used and how much <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538147" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carbon dioxide</GlossaryTermRef> is given off during breathing. This is also called a lung function test.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fine-needle aspiration (FNA) biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  The removal of  tissue or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef> using a thin needle.  A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the tissue or fluid under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> to look for cancer cells.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046119" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Thoracoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgical</GlossaryTermRef> procedure to look at the organs inside the chest to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas. An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> (cut) is made between two ribs and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thoracoscope</GlossaryTermRef>  is inserted into the chest.  A thoracoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue or lymph node samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.  In some cases, this procedure is used to remove part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046408" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">esophagus</GlossaryTermRef> or lung.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045628" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bronchoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> and large airways in the lung for abnormal areas. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bronchoscope</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted through the nose or mouth into the trachea and lungs. A bronchoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Laparoscopy</GlossaryTermRef>:</Strong> A surgical procedure to look at the organs inside the abdomen to check for abnormal areas. Small incisions (cuts) are made in the wall of the abdomen and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laparoscope</GlossaryTermRef> (thin, lighted tube) is inserted into one of the incisions. Other instruments may be inserted through the same or other incisions to perform procedures such as removing organs or taking tissue samples to be checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cytologic</GlossaryTermRef> exam</Strong>: An exam of cells under a microscope (by a pathologist) to check for anything abnormal. For mesothelioma, fluid is taken from around the lungs or from the abdomen. A pathologist checks the cells in the fluid.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_232"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_233">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery).</KeyPoint><Para id="_234"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> depends on whether the cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_235" Style="bullet"><ListItem>has spread throughout the thin layer of tissue or into organs.</ListItem><ListItem>has just been <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_237"><Title>Stages of Childhood Mesothelioma</Title><Para id="_241">The process used to find out if <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> has spread from where it first began is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. In childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef>, cancer may spread to nearby or distant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>. There is no standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging system</GlossaryTermRef> for childhood mesothelioma. The results of <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790962#_229" url="/types/mesothelioma/patient/child-mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">tests and procedures</SummaryRef> done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> mesothelioma are used to help make decisions about treatment.</Para><Para id="_244">Sometimes childhood mesothelioma <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurs</GlossaryTermRef> (comes back) after it has been treated.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_245"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_246"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_247">There are different types of treatment for children with mesothelioma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_246_md_79">Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.  A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the  standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment.</Para><Para id="_246_md_80">Because cancer in children is rare, taking part in a clinical trial should be considered.  Some clinical trials are open only to patients  who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_248"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_249">Children with mesothelioma should have their treatment planned by a team of doctors who are experts in treating childhood cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_250">Treatment will be overseen by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>, a doctor who specializes in treating children with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The pediatric oncologist works with other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric</GlossaryTermRef> health professionals who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef>. This may include the following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">specialists</GlossaryTermRef> and others:</Para><ItemizedList id="_251" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pathologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Social worker</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Psychologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_252"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_253">Three types of treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_254"><KeyPoint id="_255">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_256"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> may be used to treat childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_257"><KeyPoint id="_258">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_259"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> to stop the growth of cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_260"><KeyPoint id="_261">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_262"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_263"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_264">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_265">This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_266"><KeyPoint id="_267">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_268"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. Targeted therapies usually cause less harm to normal cells than chemotherapy or radiation therapy do.</Para><Para id="_269">Targeted therapy is being studied for the treatment of childhood mesothelioma that has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_295"><KeyPoint id="_296">Immunotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_297"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment that uses the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to fight cancer.  Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the body's natural defenses against cancer. This cancer treatment is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045617" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biologic therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_270"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_271">Treatment for childhood mesothelioma may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_270_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_278">Side effects from cancer treatment that begin after treatment and continue for months or years are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef>. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_279" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Physical problems.</ListItem><ListItem>Changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Second cancers</GlossaryTermRef> (new types of cancer) or other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_280">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_272"><KeyPoint id="_273">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_272_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_272_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_272_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_274"><KeyPoint id="_275">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_274_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_274_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_276"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_277">Follow-up tests may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_276_md_55">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_276_md_56">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_281"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038142">malignant mesothelioma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Childhood Mesothelioma</Title><Para id="_284">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790962#_253" url="/types/mesothelioma/patient/child-mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_282">Treatment of newly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef> in children may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_283" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the part of the chest lining with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and some of the healthy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> around it.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, to relieve pain and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of newer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_281_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_285"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038160">recurrent malignant mesothelioma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Childhood Mesothelioma</Title><Para id="_288">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790962#_253" url="/types/mesothelioma/patient/child-mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_286">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef> in children may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_287" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> that checks a sample of the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> changes. The type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> that will be given to the patient depends on the type of gene change.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_285_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_289"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>To Learn More About Childhood Mesothelioma</Title><Para id="_290">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mesothelioma</GlossaryTermRef>, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_291" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma">Malignant Mesothelioma Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Cancer Therapies</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_289_md_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_289_md_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood mesothelioma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Mesothelioma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/patient/child-mesothelioma-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/mesothelioma/patient/child-mesothelioma-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000799420"/><DateFirstPublished>2019-10-02</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2021-02-18</DateLastModified></Summary>
