<Summary id="CDR0000790953" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood tracheobronchial tumors are rare tumors that start in the lining of the trachea and bronchi. Learn about the symptoms of tracheobronchial tumors and how they are diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/child-tracheobronchial-treatment-pdq">Childhood Tracheobronchial Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040209">lung cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of a type of childhood lung cancer called tracheobronchial tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bronchial carcinoid</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood lung cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>primary tracheobronchial tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>tracheal tumors</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>tracheobronchial tumor</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Tracheobronchial Tumors (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Tracheobronchial Tumors </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Tracheobronchial Tumors </AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1657"><Title>What are childhood tracheobronchial tumors?</Title><Para id="_1788">Tracheobronchial tumors are rare, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> growths that form in the windpipe (trachea) or the large airways in the lungs called the bronchi. They can be benign (not cancerous) or malignant (cancerous). Benign tumors are more common in children. If a child has a benign tumor, they may need treatment to prevent the tumor from growing and putting pressure on nearby tissue in the airway. If the tumor is cancerous, the treatment is aimed at killing the cancer cells and keeping them from spreading to other parts of the body.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000801516" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows areas of the body where tracheobronchial tumors may form, including the trachea and the bronchi (large airways of the lung)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1742"><Caption language="en">Tracheobronchial tumors form in the inside lining of the trachea or bronchi (large airways of the lung). Tracheobronchial tumors are rare and can occur in both children and adults.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_1661">Several types of tracheobronchial tumors may affect children:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1662" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044233" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Carcinoid tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is the most common type of tracheobronchial tumor in children. This type of tumor is usually benign, but some may be cancerous and spread to other parts of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Mucoepidermoid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045963" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a slow-growing cancer that affects the airway.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000782642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is a slow-growing tumor that usually affects the upper trachea. These tumors rarely spread to other parts of the body.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Rhabdomyosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>. Learn more at <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258466" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/patient/rhabdomyosarcoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Rhabdomyosarcoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000785687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Granular cell tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is usually benign, but can be cancerous and spread to nearby tissue.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1747"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood tracheobronchial tumors</Title><Para id="_1748">Tracheobronchial tumors in children are caused by certain changes to the way cells in the lining of the trachea or large bronchi function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these cell changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_1749">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. There are no known risk factors for childhood tracheobronchial tumors.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1663"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Symptoms of childhood tracheobronchial tumors</Title><Para id="_1665">Symptoms of tracheobronchial tumors are a lot like symptoms of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440101" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">asthma</GlossaryTermRef>, which can make it hard to diagnose the tumor. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has any symptoms, such as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1666" Style="bullet"><ListItem>dry cough</ListItem><ListItem>wheezing</ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>coughing up blood</ListItem><ListItem>frequent infections in the lung, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pneumonia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>feeling very tired</ListItem><ListItem>loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef> or weight loss for no known reason</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1667">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than a tracheobronchial tumor. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1668"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood tracheobronchial tumors</Title><Para id="_1670">If your child has symptoms that suggest a tracheobronchial tumor, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or to another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with a tracheobronchial tumor, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_1750">The tests used to diagnose tracheobronchial tumors in children may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_1751"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_1752">An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures. A chest x-ray makes pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1753"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_1754">A CT scan uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the neck and chest. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs.  A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_17924"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1755"><Title>Bronchoscopy</Title><Para id="_1756">Bronchoscopy is a procedure to look for abnormal areas inside the trachea and large airways in the lung. A bronchoscope is inserted through the nose or mouth into the trachea and lungs. A bronchoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1757"><Title>Bronchography</Title><Para id="_1758">Bronchography is a procedure to look for abnormal areas in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046026" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">larynx</GlossaryTermRef>, trachea, and bronchi and to check whether the airways are wider below the level of the tumor. A contrast dye is given through a  bronchoscope to coat the airways and make them show up more clearly on x-ray film. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1759"><Title>Octreotide scan</Title><Para id="_1760">An octreotide scan is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046552" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radionuclide scan</GlossaryTermRef> used to find tracheobronchial tumors or cancer that has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>. A very small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> octreotide (a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef> that attaches to  carcinoid tumors) is injected into a vein and travels through the bloodstream. The radioactive octreotide attaches to the tumor and a special camera that detects radioactivity is used to show where the tumors are in the body. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1761"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_1762">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's tumor.</Para><Para id="_1789">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1778"><Title>Who treats children with tracheobronchial tumors?</Title><Para id="_1691">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of tracheobronchial tumors. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1692" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1686"><Title>Treatment of childhood tracheobronchial tumors</Title><Para id="_1764">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with tracheobronchial tumors. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back after treatment.</Para><Para id="_1766">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the tumor, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_1779">For all tracheobronchial tumors except rhabdomyosarcoma, treatment might include surgery to remove the tumor. The lymph nodes and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vessels</GlossaryTermRef> where cancer has spread are also removed. Sometimes a surgery called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482346" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sleeve resection</GlossaryTermRef> is done. </Para><Para id="_1790">For rhabdomyosarcoma in the trachea or bronchi, treatment might include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1791" Style="bullet"><ListItem> Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cancer cells or stops them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. External beam radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1792">Learn more about  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258466" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/patient/rhabdomyosarcoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Rhabdomyosarcoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_1793">For inflammatory myofibroblastic tumors in the trachea or bronchi, in addition to surgery, treatment may include targeted therapy. Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. <DrugRef href="CDR0000710816" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/crizotinib">Crizotinib</DrugRef> may be used if the tumor has a certain change in the <GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000721252" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ALK</GlossaryTermRef></GeneName> gene. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_17923">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1771"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_1771_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_1771_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_1771_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1672"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Prognosis and prognostic factors for childhood tracheobronchial tumors</Title><Para id="_1775">If your child has been diagnosed with a tracheobronchial tumor, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and about your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_1784">The prognosis depends on many factors, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1785" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the type of tracheobronchial tumor</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor is or has become cancer and spread to other parts of the body</ListItem><ListItem> whether the tumor was completely removed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem> whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back after treatment</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1786">The prognosis for children with tracheobronchial tumors that can be removed by surgery is very good. This is the case for most tracheobronchial tumors except rhabdomyosarcoma, which requires more aggressive treatment.</Para><Para id="_1676">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1713"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_1787">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_1713_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1715">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1716" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer) or other conditions</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1717">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1722"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_1722_md_98">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_1722_md_99">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1776"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_1777">When your child has a tumor, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer </ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1731"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung">Lung Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors and Caregivers</ExternalRef>
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood tracheobronchial tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Tracheobronchial Tumors. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/child-tracheobronchial-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/lung/patient/child-tracheobronchial-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2019-10-02</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-11</DateLastModified></Summary>
