<Summary id="CDR0000790955" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood esophageal cancer is a rare cancer that forms in the esophagus. Learn more about the risk factors and symptoms and how childhood esophageal cancer is diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/child-esophageal-treatment-pdq">Childhood Esophageal Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043615">esophageal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood esophageal cancer. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood esophageal cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Esophageal Cancer (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Esophageal Cancer </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Esophageal Cancer </AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1717"><Title>What is childhood esophageal cancer?</Title><Para id="_1718">Childhood esophageal cancer is a rare type of cancer that forms in the esophagus.</Para><Para id="_872">The esophagus is the hollow, muscular tube that moves food and
		  drink from the throat to the stomach. The wall of the esophagus is made up of several layers of tissue,
		  including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257212" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucous membrane</GlossaryTermRef>, muscle, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000804898" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the esophagus; drawing shows the pharynx (throat), esophagus, and stomach. A pullout shows the mucosa layer, thin muscle layer, submucosa layer, thick muscle layer, and connective tissue layer of the esophagus wall. The lymph nodes are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1713"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the esophagus. The esophagus is a hollow, muscular tube that moves food and liquid from the pharynx (throat) to the stomach. The wall of the esophagus is made up of several layers of tissue, including the mucosa layer, thin muscle layer, submucosa layer, thick muscle layer, and connective tissue layer.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_1714">There are two common forms of esophageal cancer.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1715" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046595" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Squamous cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the esophagus is the most common esophageal  tumor in children. This cancer begins in the thin, flat cells called squamous cells that line the inside of the esophagus.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adenocarcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the esophagus is a less common type of esophageal tumor in children. It begins in the glands that secrete mucus in the esophagus.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1719"><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood esophageal cancer</Title><Para id="_1720">Esophageal cancer in children is caused by certain changes in the way cells in the esophagus function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these cell changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_1721">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with one or more of these risk factors will develop esophageal cancer. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. </Para><Para id="_1722">Known risk factors for childhood esophageal cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_878" Style="bullet"><ListItem>having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastroesophageal reflux</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Barrett esophagus</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>swallowing chemicals, which may burn the esophagus and cause cell changes that may lead to cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1723">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1724"><Title>Symptoms of childhood esophageal cancer</Title><Para id="_1725">Children with esophageal cancer may not have symptoms until the tumor has grown large or spread. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child:</Para><ItemizedList id="_883" Style="bullet"><ListItem>has trouble swallowing</ListItem><ListItem>loses weight</ListItem><ListItem>feels tired and weak</ListItem><ListItem>has indigestion and heartburn</ListItem><ListItem>has reflux</ListItem><ListItem>has nausea or vomiting</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1726">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than cancer. The only way to know is to see your  child's doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1727"><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood esophageal cancer</Title><Para id="_1728">If your child has symptoms that suggest esophageal cancer, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with esophageal cancer, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_1729">The tests used to diagnose esophageal cancer may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_1730"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_1731">An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures. A chest x-ray is one that makes pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1732"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_1733">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest and abdomen. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1734"><Title>PET scan (positron emission tomography scan)</Title><Para id="_1735">A PET scan uses a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> sugar (radioactive glucose) that is injected into a vein.  The PET scanner rotates around the body to make detailed, computerized pictures of areas inside the body where the glucose is taken up.  Because cancer cells often take up more glucose than normal cells, the pictures can be used to find cancer cells in the body.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775456" type="image/jpeg" alt="Positron emission tomography (PET) scan; drawing shows a child lying on table that slides through the PET scanner." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_1711"><Caption language="en">Positron emission tomography (PET) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the PET scanner. The head rest and white strap help the child lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the child's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do. </Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1736"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_1737"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient"> 
		  MRI</GlossaryTermRef> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of the esophagus. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1738"><Title>Ultrasound exam</Title><Para id="_1739">A test that uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs and make  echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1740"><Title>Barium swallow</Title><Para id="_1741"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Barium swallow</GlossaryTermRef> is a series of x-rays of the esophagus and stomach. The patient drinks a liquid that contains barium (a silver-white metallic compound). The liquid coats the esophagus and stomach, and x-rays are taken. This procedure is also called an upper GI series.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1742"><Title>Esophagoscopy</Title><Para id="_1743">An esophagoscopy is a  procedure to look inside the esophagus to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas. An esophagoscope is inserted through the mouth or nose and down the throat into the esophagus. An esophagoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> is usually done during an esophagoscopy. Sometimes a biopsy shows changes in the esophagus that are not cancer but may lead to cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1744"><Title>Bronchoscopy</Title><Para id="_1745">A bronchoscopy is a procedure to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046623" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trachea</GlossaryTermRef> and large airways in the lungs for abnormal areas. A bronchoscope is inserted through the nose or mouth into the trachea and lungs. A bronchoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1746"><Title>Thoracoscopy</Title><Para id="_1747">A thoracoscopy is a surgical procedure to look at the organs inside the chest to check for abnormal areas. A cut (incision) is made between two ribs and a thoracoscope is inserted into the chest. A thoracoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer. Sometimes this procedure is used to remove part of the esophagus or lung.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1748"><Title>Immunohistochemistry</Title><Para id="_1749">Immunohistochemistry is a laboratory test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (markers) in a sample of a patient’s cells. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to the antigen in the sample of the patient’s cells, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1750"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_1751">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's cancer.</Para><Para id="_1752">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1753"><Title>Who treats children with esophageal cancer?</Title><Para id="_1669">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment for esophageal cancer. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1670" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1754"><Title>Treatment of childhood esophageal cancer</Title><Para id="_1755">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with esophageal cancer. To decide on a treatment plan for your child, you and their care team will think about many factors, such as your child's overall health and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_1756">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team about what to expect before treatment begins. For help every step of the way, see our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_1757">Treatment of esophageal cancer in children might include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1758" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Radiation therapy, which uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Internal radiation therapy is used to treat esophageal cancer. For this treatment, a plastic or metal tube is passed through your child's mouth into the esophagus. A machine that is outside the body has a special tool that is placed in the tube to send radiation toward the cancer. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy">Radiation Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy (also called chemo), which uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cancer cells or stops them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given in different ways. To learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1759">If your child's cancer comes back after treatment, their doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1760"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_1760_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_1760_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_1760_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1761"><Title>Prognostic factors for childhood esophageal cancer</Title><Para id="_1762">If your child has been diagnosed with esophageal cancer, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_1650">Your child's prognosis depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1651" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the type of esophageal cancer (squamous cell or adenocarcinoma)</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer was completely removed by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to other areas of the body</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has recurred (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1652">The prognosis is better if the cancer can be completely removed during surgery and if it has not spread to other areas of the body.</Para><Para id="_1763">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1764"><Title>Side effects and late effects of cancer treatment</Title><Para id="_1765">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_63">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects of Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_1766">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1767" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems, such as narrowing of the esophagus</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer) or other problems</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_66">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1768"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_1769">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_1770">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition changes or if the cancer comes back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1771"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_71">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child’s treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1708"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/nutrition">Nutrition During Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors and Caregivers</ExternalRef>
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood esophageal cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Esophageal Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/child-esophageal-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/esophageal/patient/child-esophageal-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2019-10-02</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-02-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
