<Summary id="CDR0000790961" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood heart tumors are rare and may sometimes be cancer. Learn about the symptoms of childhood heart tumors and how they are diagnosed and treated. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cardiac/patient-child-cardiac-treatment-pdq">Childhood Cardiac (Heart) Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cardiac/hp-child-cardiac-treatment-pdq">Childhood Cardiac (Heart) Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043724">childhood cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood heart tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood cardiac cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood heart cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>heart tumors in children</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Heart Tumors (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Cardiac (Heart) Tumors Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Heart Tumors</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>What are childhood heart tumors?</Title><Para id="_181">Heart tumors (also called cardiac tumors) are rare growths that can form in any part of the heart. They can be benign (not cancerous) or malignant (cancerous). Most heart tumors in children are benign. Although benign tumors do not spread to other parts of the body, they may require treatment to stop them from causing problems with the heart's rhythm and blood flow. Cancerous heart tumors are very rare in children. They can spread to other parts of the body and require more intensive treatment than benign tumors.</Para><Para id="_5">Types of benign heart tumors that may occur in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046400" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fetus</GlossaryTermRef>, newborn, or child include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Rhabdomyoma is a tumor that forms in muscle made up of long <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046401" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fibers</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Myxoma is a tumor that may be part of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797792" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hereditary syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Carney complex</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Teratoma is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">germ cell tumor</GlossaryTermRef>.  In the heart, these tumors form most often in the pericardium (the sac that covers the heart). Some teratomas are cancerous.</ListItem><ListItem>Fibroma is a tumor that forms in  fiber-like tissue that holds bones, muscles, and other organs in place.</ListItem><ListItem> Histiocytoid cardiomyopathy tumor is a tumor that forms in the heart cells that control  heart rhythm. </ListItem><ListItem>Hemangioma is a tumor that forms in the cells that line <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Neurofibroma is a tumor that forms in the cells and tissues that cover <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373935" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerves</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_7">The most common benign heart tumors that may occur in a fetus or newborn include rhabdomyoma, myxoma, teratoma, and fibroma. Most rhabdomyomas go away on their own.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000804602" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the heart; a pullout shows the aorta, superior vena cava, pericardium, coronary artery, and inferior vena cava." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_8"><Caption language="en">Heart tumors are rare tumors that form in the tissues of the heart, including muscle tissue, connective tissue, and tissues that line the blood vessels, control heart rhythm, and cover the nerves of the heart. They may also form in the pericardium (the sac around the heart). Most heart tumors are benign (not cancer), but some may be malignant (cancer).</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_9">Types of cancerous heart tumors that may occur in a fetus, newborn, or child include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_10" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Malignant teratoma is a type of germ cell tumor. In the heart, these tumors form most often in the pericardium (the sac that covers the heart). Most teratomas are not cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Primary cardiac <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045368" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphoma</GlossaryTermRef> begins in the heart and/or pericardium (the sac that covers the heart).</ListItem><ListItem>Rhabdomyosarcoma forms in muscle made up of long fibers.</ListItem><ListItem>Angiosarcoma forms in cells that line blood vessels or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Undifferentiated pleomorphic sarcoma usually forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, but it may also form in bone.</ListItem><ListItem>Leiomyosarcoma forms in smooth muscle cells.</ListItem><ListItem>Chondrosarcoma usually forms in bone <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044190" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cartilage</GlossaryTermRef>, but very rarely can begin in the heart.</ListItem><ListItem>Synovial sarcoma usually forms around <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">joints</GlossaryTermRef>, but may very rarely form in the heart or sac around the heart.</ListItem><ListItem>Infantile fibrosarcoma forms in fiber-like tissue that holds bones, muscles, and other organs in place.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood heart tumors</Title><Para id="_13">Heart tumors in children are caused by certain changes to the way heart cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of the cell changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_14">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. A fetus or newborn can have a higher risk of benign heart tumors if they have a genetic condition called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tuberous sclerosis</GlossaryTermRef>. Another condition, called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Carney complex</GlossaryTermRef>, might also increase a child's risk of a type of benign heart tumor called myxoma. Not all children with these risk factors will get a benign heart tumor, and benign heart tumors may develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_182">There are no known risk factors for cancerous heart tumors in children.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><Title>Symptoms of childhood heart tumors</Title><Para id="_16">Most children with a heart tumor will have some signs and symptoms that alert parents of a problem. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_17" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a change in the heart's normal rhythm</ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing, especially when lying down</ListItem><ListItem>pain or tightness in the middle of the chest that feels better when sitting up</ListItem><ListItem>coughing</ListItem><ListItem>fainting</ListItem><ListItem>feeling dizzy, tired, or weak</ListItem><ListItem>fast <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart rate</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>swelling in the legs, ankles, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>signs of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439425" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stroke</GlossaryTermRef>, including sudden:<ItemizedList id="_18" Style="bullet"><ListItem>numbness or weakness of the face, arm, or leg (especially on one side of the body)</ListItem><ListItem>confusion or  trouble speaking or understanding</ListItem><ListItem>trouble seeing with one or both eyes</ListItem><ListItem>trouble walking or  feeling dizzy</ListItem><ListItem>loss of balance or coordination</ListItem><ListItem>severe headache for no known reason</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_19">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than a heart tumor. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood heart tumors</Title><Para id="_21">If your child has symptoms that suggest a heart tumor, the doctor will need to find out the cause. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with a heart tumor, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_22">The tests and procedures used to diagnose heart tumors may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_23"><Title>Echocardiogram</Title><Para id="_24">An echocardiogram uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off the heart and nearby tissues or organs and make echoes. A moving picture is made of the heart and heart valves as blood is pumped through the heart.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_26">A CT scan uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_27"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_29">MRI uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas of the body, such as the head and neck. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_30"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_32">An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures. A chest x-ray is one that makes pictures of the organs and bones inside the chest.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><Title>Electrocardiogram (EKG)</Title><Para id="_34">An EKG is a recording of the heart's electrical activity to check its rate and rhythm. Small pads (electrodes) are placed on the patient's chest, arms, and legs, and are connected by wires to the EKG machine. Heart activity is then recorded as a line graph on paper. Electrical activity that is faster or slower than normal may be a sign of heart disease or damage.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Cardiac catheterization</Title><Para id="_36">Cardiac catheterization is a procedure to look inside the blood vessels and heart for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas or cancer. A long, thin, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted into an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">artery</GlossaryTermRef> or vein in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046375" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">groin</GlossaryTermRef>, neck, or arm and threaded through the blood vessels to the heart. A sample of tissue may be removed using a special tool. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_37"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_38">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's tumor.</Para><Para id="_39">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/services">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><Title>Types of treatment for childhood heart tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_178"><Title>Who treats children with heart tumors?</Title><Para id="_47">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of heart tumors. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_48" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pediatric heart <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044306" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pediatric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cardiologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_46">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with heart tumors. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_50">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the tumor, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_51"><Title>Watchful waiting</Title><Para id="_52">Watchful waiting is closely monitoring a child's condition without giving any treatment until signs or symptoms appear or change. This treatment may be used for rhabdomyoma (a benign tumor).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_54">When possible, the tumor is removed by surgery. Types of surgery that may be done include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_55" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Surgery to remove the tumor and some healthy tissue around it.</ListItem><ListItem>Heart <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef>. If the child is waiting for a donated heart, they may receive other treatment as needed.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_56">Sometimes chemotherapy may be given before surgery to make a cancerous tumor smaller and decrease the amount of tissue that needs to be removed during surgery. This is called neoadjuvant (preoperative) therapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_58">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cancer cells or stops them from dividing. For children with sarcoma, chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment to reduce the size of the tumor before surgery. </Para><Para id="_60">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_62">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Cancerous heart tumors are sometimes treated with external beam radiation therapy. External beam radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation therapy may be used when the cancer cannot be removed by surgery.</Para><Para id="_63">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_64"><Title>Targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_65">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to block the action of specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef>, proteins, or other molecules involved in the growth of tumor cells.</Para><Para id="_66">Targeted therapies used to treat benign heart tumors include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000640318" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/everolimus">everolimus</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045513" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sirolimus</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_69">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_70_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_70_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_70_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_74"><Title>Treatment of childhood heart tumors</Title><Para id="_75">Treatment of newly diagnosed childhood heart tumors may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_76" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045942" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">watchful waiting</GlossaryTermRef> for children with rhabdomyoma (a benign tumor), which sometimes shrinks and goes away on its own</ListItem> <ListItem>targeted therapy (<DrugRef href="CDR0000640318" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/everolimus">everolimus</DrugRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045513" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sirolimus</GlossaryTermRef>) for  children with rhabdomyoma or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tuberous sclerosis</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy followed by surgery (which may include removing some or all of the tumor or a heart <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">transplant</GlossaryTermRef>) for children with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sarcomas</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>surgery to completely remove the tumor for children with other types of heart tumors</ListItem><ListItem>radiation therapy for children with cancerous tumors that cannot be removed by surgery</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_177">If a cancerous tumor comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There may be treatment options that could shrink the tumor or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_81"><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_179">Treatments for heart tumors can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_81_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_82">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef>. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_83" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046658" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">second cancers</GlossaryTermRef> (new types of cancer) or other conditions</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_84">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_85"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_85_md_98">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_85_md_99">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_89">When your child has a heart tumor, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_90"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_91">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, see:</Para><ItemizedList id="_92" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef> 
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors and Caregivers</ExternalRef>
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood cardiac (heart) tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Heart Tumors. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cardiac/patient-child-cardiac-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/cardiac/patient-child-cardiac-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000799419"/><DateFirstPublished>2019-10-02</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-04</DateLastModified></Summary>
