<Summary id="CDR0000791425" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Cognitive impairment (problems with memory and thinking) is often reported by people with cancer and survivors and is sometimes called "chemobrain" or "chemofog." Get detailed information about cognitive impairment and treatment in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/memory/cognitive-impairment-pdq">Cognitive Impairment in Adults with Cancer (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/memory/cognitive-impairment-hp-pdq">Cognitive Impairment in Adults with Cancer (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028579">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000722010">cognitive intervention</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_207">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about cognitive impairment in adults. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_208">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cognitive impairment</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Cognitive Impairment in Adults with Cancer (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Cognitive Impairment in Adults with Cancer</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Cognitive Impairment in Adults with Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_209"><Title>General Information About Cognitive Problems in Cancer Survivors</Title><SummarySection id="_210"><KeyPoint id="_211">Cognition problems can change the way you think and learn.</KeyPoint><Para id="_275"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cognition</GlossaryTermRef> is the process of how you learn, remember, and become aware of what is around you.</Para><Para id="_212">This process includes being able to do the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_255" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Focus on important  information, thoughts, and actions.</ListItem><ListItem>Pay attention to a task or activity for a long period of time.</ListItem><ListItem>Predict what may happen, plan, and solve problems.</ListItem><ListItem>Learn quickly.</ListItem><ListItem>Have a sense of where objects are around you.</ListItem><ListItem>Understand and communicate by speaking and writing.</ListItem><ListItem>Learn and remember new information.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_279">When your cognition changes, you may have problems with daily tasks.</Para><Para id="_276">This summary is about cognitive changes that occur in people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_216"><KeyPoint id="_217">Memory loss and thinking problems  are common in people with cancer and  cancer survivors.</KeyPoint><Para id="_218">Your thought process may change, and it may be hard for you to focus and remember things the same way as you did before your cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_219">Talk to your doctor about memory loss and thinking problems you have during or after treatment.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_215"><Title>Signs of Cognitive Problems</Title><SummarySection id="_213"><KeyPoint id="_214">Signs of cognitive problems include trouble learning or remembering.</KeyPoint><Para id="_259">Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef> may also cause cognitive problems. Talk to your doctor if you have memory loss or are unable to do the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_258" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Focus on what you are doing.</ListItem><ListItem>Complete tasks.</ListItem><ListItem>Understand what people are saying.</ListItem><ListItem>Remember names and common words.</ListItem><ListItem>Recognize familiar objects.</ListItem><ListItem>Follow instructions.</ListItem><ListItem>Manage your money well. For example, you may have trouble paying bills or balancing your checkbook.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_277">You may also notice the following changes:</Para><ItemizedList id="_278" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Disorganized behavior or thinking.</ListItem><ListItem>Loss of interest.</ListItem><ListItem>Problems making sense of the world around you.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_223"><KeyPoint id="_224">Cancer treatments or other diseases may cause cognitive problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_225">Factors that cause cognitive problems in people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_260" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Older age.</ListItem><ListItem>Being weak or frail.</ListItem><ListItem>Cancer treatments, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, or other medications, and their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Being <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmenopausal</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454701" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Distress</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, such as pain, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, or trouble sleeping.</ListItem><ListItem>Other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000811791" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diseases</GlossaryTermRef> or conditions.</ListItem><ListItem>Using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463134" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alcohol</GlossaryTermRef> or other substances that change your mental state.</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer (the size of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>, and whether it has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> or other parts of the body).</ListItem><ListItem>Higher levels of certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_280">The cognitive effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044411" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endocrine therapy</GlossaryTermRef> were studied in   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> survivors. Patients who received 5 years of  treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">exemestane</GlossaryTermRef>  were compared with those who received 2.5 years of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000509341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tamoxifen</GlossaryTermRef> followed by 2.5 years of exemestane, and with healthy participants.  Findings suggested that tamoxifen may have more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse</GlossaryTermRef> cognitive effects than exemestane. More studies are needed to confirm these results.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_226"><KeyPoint id="_227">Your doctor will examine you to better understand your cognitive problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_261">Your doctor will ask about your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health history</GlossaryTermRef> and usual daily activities to find out a cause of your cognitive problems. Your doctor will also do an exam to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> of disease.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_228"><Title>Treatment of Cognitive Problems</Title><SummarySection id="_229"><KeyPoint id="_230">Treatment of cognitive problems may include activities that help your attention, memory, and thinking.</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_231"><KeyPoint id="_232">Cognitive rehabilitation</KeyPoint><Para id="_262">The goal of cognitive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441257" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation</GlossaryTermRef> is to improve your memory and the way you think, organize, and make decisions. Cognitive rehabilitation involves the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_263" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Learning ways to  take in new information and perform new tasks or behaviors.</ListItem><ListItem>Staying organized by using tools, such as  calendars or electronic diaries.</ListItem><ListItem>Doing activities over and over, usually on a computer, that become more challenging over time.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_236"><KeyPoint id="_237">Exercise and physical activity</KeyPoint><Para id="_264">Exercise, physical activity, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000729824" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mind-body practices</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467869" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tai chi</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467860" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">qigong</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000532135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">yoga</GlossaryTermRef>, may improve the way you think and focus.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_238"><KeyPoint id="_239">Attention restoration</KeyPoint><Para id="_266">Activities  that restore attention may help you stay focused on what is around you. These activities may include walking, gardening, bird-watching, and caring for pets.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_240"><KeyPoint id="_241">Meditation</KeyPoint><Para id="_267"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000730354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Meditation</GlossaryTermRef> may help improve cognitive function. Meditation is a mind-body practice in which a person focuses his or her attention on something, such as an object, word, phrase, or breathing. This will help keep you from being distracted or having <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stressful</GlossaryTermRef> thoughts or feelings. Mindfulness-based stress reduction  is a  type of meditation that focuses on bringing attention and awareness to each moment.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_242"><KeyPoint id="_243">Certain drugs are being studied to treat cognitive problems.</KeyPoint><Para id="_274">Several <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> have been studied to treat cognitive problems in people who have or who have had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468800" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychostimulants</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">erythropoietin</GlossaryTermRef>-stimulating agents, but results are mixed. More research is needed.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about expert-reviewed information summary about causes and management of cognitive impairment in people with cancer.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/supportive-care">PDQ Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Supportive and Palliative Care Editorial Board. PDQ Cognitive Impairment in Adults with Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/memory/cognitive-impairment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/memory/cognitive-impairment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000788906"/><DateFirstPublished>2018-03-20</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-25</DateLastModified></Summary>
