<Summary id="CDR0000797948"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Curcumin  is one member of a group of natural compounds called curcuminoids,  contained in an extract commonly called turmeric. Get detailed information about curcumin-containing products studied in clinical trials for the prevention and treatment of cancer and related side effects in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">Curcumin (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/curcumin-pdq">Curcumin (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043115">curcumin</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_281">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of curcumin (curcuma, turmeric) in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_282">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Curcuma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Curcumin</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Turmeric</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Curcumin (Curcuma, Turmeric) and Cancer (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Curcumin and Cancer (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Curcumin and Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_10">This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summary provides an overview of the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curcumin</GlossaryTermRef>  as a treatment for people with cancer.</Para><Para id="_12">This summary contains the following key information:</Para><ItemizedList id="_13" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Curcumin (diarylheptanoid) is one member of a group of natural <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef> called curcuminoids, derived from the rhizome of <ScientificName>Curcuma longa</ScientificName>, an East Indian plant, contained in an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef> commonly called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Turmeric has a long history of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> application in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">traditional Asian medicine</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Extensive research over the past two decades suggests that curcuminoids, the  active ingredient in turmeric (<ScientificName>C. longa</ScientificName>), interfere with multiple <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell signaling</GlossaryTermRef> pathways, providing support for the potential role of curcumin in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390300" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">modulating</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> development and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044078" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>With varying formulations and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, there is evidence of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef> of curcumin and curcumin conjugates in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem> Results from early-phase trials of curcumin-containing products in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045487" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemoprevention</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic</GlossaryTermRef> carcinoma appear promising. However, the findings from these early trials have to be confirmed in well-powered trials evaluating safety and effectiveness as indicated by modulation of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> outcomes.</ListItem><ListItem>Data from early-phase trials of the safety and effectiveness of curcumin-containing products in cancer treatment are at most from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045838" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pilot</GlossaryTermRef> trials that targeted various <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stages</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer and cancer patient populations, and utilized different formulations and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of curcumin and durations of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intervention</GlossaryTermRef>. Thus, the evidence is currently inadequate to recommend curcumin-containing products for the treatment of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Data from early-phase trials of the safety and effectiveness of curcumin-containing products as adjuncts to traditional cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef> are from pilot trials that had small sample sizes, targeted various stages of cancer and cancer patient populations, and utilized different formulations and doses of curcumin and durations of intervention. Thus, the evidence is currently inadequate to recommend curcumin-containing products to be used as adjuncts  for the treatment of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Data from early-phase trials on the use of curcumin formulations to ameliorate cancer treatment–related effects have demonstrated  (a) improved oxidative status in patients who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, (b) delayed onset and severity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045789" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucositis</GlossaryTermRef>, (c) reduced severity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446545" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation dermatitis</GlossaryTermRef>, and (d) improved <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>, without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> with curcumin-containing products at these doses. However, these studies were short in duration and used varying doses and formulations of curcumin. Thus, these results should be interpreted with caution. The findings from these early trials have to be confirmed in well-powered trials evaluating safety or effectiveness.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>General Information and History</Title><Para id="_11"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Curcumin</GlossaryTermRef> is a member of the diarylheptanoid class of natural products (curcuminoids) derived from the rhizome of <ScientificName>Curcuma longa</ScientificName> L., an East Indian plant, commonly called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef>.  The other major curcuminoids present in turmeric are demethoxycurcumin, bisdemethoxycurcumin, and cyclocurcumin; together, they are termed the <Strong>curcuminoid complex</Strong>. The turmeric plant and preparations derived from it have a long history of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> application in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">traditional Asian medicine</GlossaryTermRef>.  The crude and often dried plant material is widely consumed as a food additive, as part of curry spices, which typically contain numerous other ingredients. Turmeric and its preparations also have a long history of use as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicines</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>, primarily to treat various <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disorders</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_55">Significant confusion exists in the scientific biomedical literature, as well as the popular literature, about the meaning of curcumin. Consequently, one group has developed a classification scheme that is described below.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para><Para id="_143">Several companies distribute curcumin as a dietary supplement. In the United States, dietary supplements are regulated by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454786" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">(FDA)</GlossaryTermRef> as a separate category from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. Unlike drugs, dietary supplements do not require premarket evaluation and approval by the FDA unless specific disease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> or treatment claims are made. The quality and amount of ingredients in dietary supplements are also regulated by the FDA through Good Manufacturing Practices (GMPs). The FDA GMPs requires that every finished batch of dietary supplement meets each product specification for identity, purity, strength, composition, and limits on contamination that may <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adulterate</GlossaryTermRef> dietary supplements. The FDA can remove dietary supplements from the market that are deemed unsafe. Because dietary supplements are not formally reviewed for manufacturing consistency every year, ingredients may vary considerably from lot to lot. In addition, there is no guarantee that ingredients claimed on product labels are present at all or are present in the specified amounts. The FDA has not approved the use of curcumin as a treatment for cancer or any other medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_302"><Strong>Caution/Awareness Notice: Several cases of severe liver toxicity have occurred in Europe and the United States after consumption of products that were labeled as containing curcumin.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> These toxic events may be the result of contamination with toxins known to be in some of these products and/or adulteration or individual patient susceptibility. Various organizations, including international government regulatory agencies, have released cautionary safety advisory notices regarding curcumin-containing products.</Strong></Para><SummarySection id="_75"><Title>Categories of Curcumin-Type Products</Title><Para id="_76">The materials that have received the moniker <Strong>curcumin</Strong> may be divided into five categories:</Para><OrderedList id="_77" Style="LRoman">
     <ListItem>Turmeric (T): Raw <ScientificName>C. longa</ScientificName> rhizomes.</ListItem><ListItem>Turmeric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef> (TE): A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463162" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solvent</GlossaryTermRef> extract of dried or fresh <ScientificName>C. longa</ScientificName> rhizomes.</ListItem><ListItem>Curcuminoids-enriched turmeric extract (CTE): Typically the deep-yellow precipitate collected from the solvent extract upon <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentration</GlossaryTermRef> under reduced temperature.</ListItem><ListItem>Curcuminoids-enriched material (CEM): Obtained by additional, often large-scale,  chromatographic purification of CTE.</ListItem><ListItem>Curcumin (CUR): A  single-chemical entity, in a purity that is commensurate with that of a validated and/or metrological reference material.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_78">It is important to note that  materials often referred to as <Strong>curcumin</Strong> are not identical to the pure,  single-chemical entity. Because of the deficiency in the adequate chemical characterization of the immense diversity of crude turmeric (T), extracts (CE), enriched materials (CTE, CEM), and even materials considered <Emphasis>pure</Emphasis>, augmented by the fact that the materials often share the same name (curcumin), the usefulness of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biological</GlossaryTermRef> data acquired from the plethora of these preparations is questionable.<Reference refidx="1"/> Furthermore, attributing biological activity of a complex mixture solely to the major component, however prominent, is problematic.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_79">This summary refers to all turmeric-derived <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intervention</GlossaryTermRef> materials by using the collective term, curcumin-containing products. Tables at the end of each section specify the exact intervention material used in each cited study.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="28074653">Nelson KM, Dahlin JL, Bisson J, et al.: The Essential Medicinal Chemistry of Curcumin. J Med Chem 60 (5): 1620-1637, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="32656820">Lombardi N, Crescioli G, Maggini V, et al.: Acute liver injury following turmeric use in Tuscany: An analysis of the Italian Phytovigilance database and systematic review of case reports. Br J Clin Pharmacol 87 (3): 741-753, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="36252717">Halegoua-DeMarzio D, Navarro V, Ahmad J, et al.: Liver Injury Associated with Turmeric-A Growing Problem: Ten Cases from the Drug-Induced Liver Injury Network [DILIN]. Am J Med 136 (2): 200-206, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="22620854">Pauli GF, Chen SN, Friesen JB, et al.: Analysis and purification of bioactive natural products: the AnaPurNa study. J Nat Prod 75 (6): 1243-55, 2012.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><Title>Laboratory/Preclinical Studies</Title><Para id="_60">Extensive research over the past two decades suggests that curcuminoids belonging to the diferuloylmethane class of natural products, the major constituents in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef>  (<ScientificName>Curcuma longa</ScientificName>), interfere with multiple <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell signaling</GlossaryTermRef> pathways, which provides support for the potential role of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curcumin</GlossaryTermRef> in modulating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046487" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinogenesis</GlossaryTermRef>. These pathways include the following:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_90" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597111" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cell cycle</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000729820" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclin D1</GlossaryTermRef> and cyclin E).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Apoptosis</GlossaryTermRef> (activation of caspases and down-regulation of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390240" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antiapoptotic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> products).</ListItem><ListItem>Proliferation (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793177" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human epidermal growth factor receptor-2</GlossaryTermRef> [HER-2], <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045680" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epidermal growth factor receptor</GlossaryTermRef> [EGFR], and activating protein-1 [AP-1]).</ListItem><ListItem>Survival (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000530323" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phosphoinositide 3-kinase</GlossaryTermRef> [PI3K]/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000653106" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein kinase B</GlossaryTermRef> [AKT]) invasion (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">matrix metallopeptidase-9</GlossaryTermRef> [MMP-9] and adhesion <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046529" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Angiogenesis</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044222" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vascular endothelial growth factor</GlossaryTermRef> [VEGF]).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Metastasis</GlossaryTermRef> (CXC-chemokine receptor-4 [CXCR-4]).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Inflammation</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000773861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nuclear factor-kappa B</GlossaryTermRef> [NF-kappa B], <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor necrosis factor</GlossaryTermRef> [TNF], <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000350231" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin- 1</GlossaryTermRef> [IL-1], interleukin-8 [IL-8], interleukin-12 [IL-12], <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclooxygenase-2</GlossaryTermRef> [COX-2], and 5-lipoxygenase [5-LOX]).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_91">While these reports can possibly  provide support for the potential role of curcumin-containing products in modulating carcinogenesis, definitive conclusions cannot be made, especially in light of the widespread confusion and/or misconception regarding the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef> nature of curcumin-containing products outlined above.</Para><Para id="_61">Because of the abundance of  <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">preclinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> in the past two decades, there has been a  significant increase in the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> investigating the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> potential of curcumin-containing products. These clinical trials have used varying formulations and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of curcuminoids for the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment of cancer and  to ameliorate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> treatment.   This summary will focus on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef>, safety, and effectiveness of curcumin-containing products reported in clinical trials that targeted individuals at high risk of cancer and cancer patients for the prevention and treatment of cancer and ameliorating the symptoms of cancer treatment.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="22156994">Alexandrow MG, Song LJ, Altiok S, et al.: Curcumin:  a novel Stat3 pathway inhibitor for chemoprevention of lung cancer. Eur J Cancer Prev 21 (5): 407-12, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="26774676">Panahi Y, Darvishi B, Ghanei M, et al.: Molecular mechanisms of curcumins suppressing effects on tumorigenesis, angiogenesis and metastasis, focusing on NF-κB pathway. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev 28: 21-9, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="17273796">Cho JW, Lee KS, Kim CW: Curcumin attenuates the expression of IL-1beta, IL-6, and TNF-alpha as well as cyclin E in TNF-alpha-treated HaCaT cells; NF-kappaB and MAPKs as potential upstream targets. Int J Mol Med 19 (3): 469-74, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="16188398">Pal S, Bhattacharyya S, Choudhuri T, et al.: Amelioration of immune cell number depletion and potentiation of depressed detoxification system of tumor-bearing mice by curcumin. Cancer Detect Prev 29 (5): 470-8, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21859361">Sehgal A, Kumar M, Jain M, et al.: Synergistic effects of piperine and curcumin in modulating benzo(a)pyrene induced redox imbalance in mice lungs. Toxicol Mech Methods 22 (1): 74-80, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="19359593">Dance-Barnes ST, Kock ND, Moore JE, et al.: Lung tumor promotion by curcumin. Carcinogenesis 30 (6): 1016-23, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="19793800">Moghaddam SJ, Barta P, Mirabolfathinejad SG, et al.: Curcumin inhibits COPD-like airway inflammation and lung cancer progression in mice. Carcinogenesis 30 (11): 1949-56, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="20426658">Lee JC, Kinniry PA, Arguiri E, et al.: Dietary curcumin increases antioxidant defenses in lung, ameliorates radiation-induced pulmonary fibrosis, and improves survival in mice. Radiat Res 173 (5): 590-601, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15501961">Sharma RA, Euden SA, Platton SL, et al.: Phase I clinical trial of oral curcumin: biomarkers of systemic activity and compliance. Clin Cancer Res 10 (20): 6847-54, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="11712783">Cheng AL, Hsu CH, Lin JK, et al.: Phase I clinical trial of curcumin, a chemopreventive agent, in patients with high-risk or pre-malignant lesions. Anticancer Res 21 (4B): 2895-900, 2001 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="21372035">Carroll RE, Benya RV, Turgeon DK, et al.: Phase IIa clinical trial of curcumin for the prevention of colorectal neoplasia. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 4 (3): 354-64, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="12680238">Aggarwal BB, Kumar A, Bharti AC: Anticancer potential of curcumin: preclinical and clinical studies. Anticancer Res 23 (1A): 363-98, 2003 Jan-Feb.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Human/Clinical Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_172"><Title>Bioavailability of Curcumin-Containing Products (Phase I Clinical Trials)</Title><Para id="_173">At least six <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curcumin</GlossaryTermRef>-containing products  have investigated the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetics</GlossaryTermRef> and pharmacodynamics of pure curcumin (CUR) alone in humans. These studies have shown that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic</GlossaryTermRef> exposure to curcumin-containing products at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of up to 8,000 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/day was safe and tolerable and did not cause serious adverse events. In these studies, the  peak <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serum</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentrations</GlossaryTermRef> ranged from 47 ng/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mL</GlossaryTermRef> (at a dose of 200 mg of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> curcumin daily) to 1,380 ng/mL (at a dose of 8,000 mg of oral curcumin daily).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_174">These concentrations refer to <Strong>total curcumin</Strong>, meaning  that studies do not differentiate between free (unconjugated) curcumin and curcumin conjugated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucuronic acid</GlossaryTermRef> or sulfate. Conjugated curcumin is the more abundant metabolite in circulation. While studies indicate that conjugated curcumin is less bioactive than free curcumin, there are also indications for the enzymatic release of  free curcumin  from the conjugated forms at sites of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inflammation</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_175">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assessment</GlossaryTermRef> of curcuminoid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef>, including that of CUR, is confounded by the pronounced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044056" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolic</GlossaryTermRef> and (photo)chemical instability of these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef>. Because of the varying preparations, formulations, and doses of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intervention</GlossaryTermRef> materials tested in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, it is unclear which curcumin-containing products and doses of CUR and/or other constituents of <ScientificName>Curcuma longa </ScientificName>are required to produce a clinically significant modulation of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biomarkers</GlossaryTermRef> or even <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcomes</GlossaryTermRef>. The general consensus that the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> levels of CUR required to achieve any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biological</GlossaryTermRef> effects in patients are much higher than what has been observed clinically to date. Studies have directly compared  the bioavailability of unformulated curcumin-containing preparations with CUR that is formulated for enhanced bioavailability. These studies have consistently shown   an increase in plasma levels  using formulated CUR; however, these levels are still relatively low and do not exceed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutically</GlossaryTermRef> insufficient concentrations.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Table id="_270"><Title>Table 1.  Curcumin-Containing Products in Phase I Clinical Trials</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Source</entry><entry Align="Center">Description of Curcuminoid-Containing Product</entry><entry Align="Center">Supplier</entry><entry Align="Center">Type of Product<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">CEM = further processed curcuminoid-enriched materials; CUR = curcumin as a single-chemical entity; TE = <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For a more detailed definition of these terms, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_4" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">General Information and History</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="1"/> <Reference refidx="3"/> <Reference refidx="5"/></entry><entry>Standardized turmeric extract formulated in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsules</GlossaryTermRef> (curcumin C3 complex); each capsule contained 450 mg of curcumin, 30 mg of demethoxycurcumin, and 20 mg of bisdemethoxycurcumin</entry><entry>Sabinsa Corp. (Piscataway, NJ, USA 
 and East Windsor, NJ, USA)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="2"/></entry><entry>Theracurmin (200 mg, then escalated to 400 mg)</entry><entry>Theravalues Corp. (Tokyo)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>P54FP formulated in soft gelatin capsules. Each capsule contained 20 mg of curcuminoids (18 mg of curcumin and 2 mg of demethoxycurcumin) suspended in 200 mg of essential oils derived from  <ScientificName>Curcuma</ScientificName> spp. Typical constituents of <ScientificName>Curcuma</ScientificName> essential oils are tumerone, atlantone, and zingiberene.</entry><entry>Phytopharm plc. (Godmanchester, United Kingdom)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="6"/></entry><entry>Diferuloylmethane (99.3% pure; 500 mg per tablet)</entry><entry>Yung-Shin Pharmaceutical Co. (Taiwan)</entry><entry>CUR</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_176"><Title>Cancer Prevention and Treatment of Precancerous Lesions</Title><Para id="_177">Investigations into products that may aid in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> and the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">precancerous</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesions</GlossaryTermRef> are important for the development of early <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intervention</GlossaryTermRef> strategies and treatments. A few studies have investigated the potential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> benefit of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curcumin</GlossaryTermRef>-containing products, and other studies are under way. See <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_178"><Title>Colorectal cancer</Title><Para id="_179">Researchers have explored curcumin’s potential in curcumin-containing products for the prevention of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044237" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon cancer</GlossaryTermRef> through its effects on precancerous lesions.</Para><Para id="_180">Published results (curcumin-containing product for prevention of colon cancer):</Para><OrderedList id="_181" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>One small study (N = 5) assessed patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">familial adenomatous polyposis</GlossaryTermRef> (FAP). The patients, all of whom had previous colectomies (four patients with retained <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectums</GlossaryTermRef> and one patient with an ileal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044185" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anal</GlossaryTermRef> pouch), received 480 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef> of curcumin and 20 mg of quercetin 3 times per day <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">orally</GlossaryTermRef> for 6 months.<Reference refidx="11"/><ItemizedList id="_182" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>At 3 months, four of five patients had a decrease in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyp</GlossaryTermRef> number and size from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">baseline</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>At 6 months, this decrease continued for four of the patients, one  patient was lost to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef> after 3 months of treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>This same group conducted a controlled trial of 100% pure CUR (1,500 mg orally, 2 times/day) in a similar population of individuals with FAP (N = 44; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> = 23; curcumin = 21).<Reference refidx="12"/><ItemizedList id="_183" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Results of this study contradicted previous findings. No significant difference was found between the two treatment arms in this study.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A third study that investigated oral  curcumin used 2 doses (2,000 mg and 4,000 mg) of curcuminoid-containing powder (98%) given orally once daily for 30 days.<Reference refidx="13"/> The study investigated the potential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of curcumin-containing products in reducing the concentrations of prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) and 5-hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acid (5-HETE) (procarcinogenic factors) within <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000524194" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aberrant crypt foci</GlossaryTermRef> (ACF) (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044163" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary endpoint</GlossaryTermRef>) and associated normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucosa</GlossaryTermRef>. The secondary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef> included total ACF number (visible on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef>) and an estimate of proliferation in normal mucosa using the proliferation marker Ki-67. Forty patients were evaluable, with 20 participants in each dose group.<Reference refidx="13"/><ItemizedList id="_184" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>There was no significant decrease in primary or secondary endpoints in either group of patients, except for a 40% decrease in the number of ACF in the group of patients who received 4,000 mg doses.</ListItem><ListItem>The ACF reduction in the 4,000 mg group was associated with a significant, five-fold increase in posttreatment <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> curcumin and conjugate levels.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_185"><Title>Head and neck cancer</Title><Para id="_186">Treatment of patients with oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045954" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukoplakia</GlossaryTermRef> using a curcumin-containing product was investigated in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized trial</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_187">Published results (curcumin-containing product to treat oral leukoplakia):</Para><OrderedList id="_188" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>In one trial, 223 patients with oral leukoplakia were randomly assigned to receive either 3,600 mg of an oral curcumin-containing product (N = 111) or a placebo (N = 112) twice daily after food for 6 months.<Reference refidx="14"/> The intervention material contained a curcuminoid-enriched material (CEM) reconstituted with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef> oil and dispensed in capsules (BCM95–Biocurcumax). Clinical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef> (primary endpoint) was determined by measurement of leukoplakia at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">baseline</GlossaryTermRef> and at 6 months. At 6 months, 213 patients were evaluable (curcumin, N = 105; placebo, N = 108). <ItemizedList id="_189" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Of these patients, complete or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045819" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">partial responses</GlossaryTermRef> were observed in 75 patients from the curcumin-containing product group and in 62 patients from the placebo group (a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef> difference). </ListItem><ListItem>One hundred three patients with a clinical response at 6 months continued the curcumin-containing product or placebo treatment to evaluate long-term treatment effects.</ListItem><ListItem>There was no statistically significant difference between treatment arms at 12 months, suggesting no additional benefits with treatment longer than 6 months.</ListItem><ListItem>Histological response (complete reversal of dysplasia/hyperplasia vs. partial reversal vs. no response vs. increased severity; secondary endpoint) between the groups was not significant, but combined histological and clinical response showed a significantly better response to the curcumin-containing product.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_190"><Title>Multiple myeloma</Title><Para id="_191">The effect of a curcumin-containing product was investigated in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000411379" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance</GlossaryTermRef> (MGUS) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000413932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">smoldering multiple myeloma </GlossaryTermRef>(SMM).</Para><Para id="_192">Published results (effectiveness of curcumin-containing product on MGUS and SMM):</Para><OrderedList id="_193" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045673" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">double-blind</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797424" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">crossover study</GlossaryTermRef> followed by an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">open-label</GlossaryTermRef> extension study explored the effectiveness of a curcumin-containing product in patients with MGUS or SMM. Thirty-six patients (19 with MGUS and 17 with SMM) were randomly assigned to receive either 4,000 mg of the curcumin-containing product (curcumin stick-pack contained 3,600 mg of curcumin, 320 mg of demethoxycurcumin, and 80 mg of bisdemethoxycurcumin; one-half in the morning and  one-half in the evening as a divided dose) or 4,000 mg of placebo, crossing over at 3 months. At completion of the first study, patients were given the option to begin the open-label 8,000 mg dose-extension study. Twenty-five patients (9 with SMM and 16 with MGUS) completed the crossover study and 18 patients (7 with SMM and 11 with MGUS) completed the extension study.<Reference refidx="15"/><ItemizedList id="_194" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Serum <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef> revealed decreases in free light-chain ratio (rFLC); a difference between clonal and nonclonal light-chain (dFLC) and involved free light-chain (iFLC) was observed but not statistically significant in patients who received the curcumin-containing product in the crossover study.</ListItem><ListItem>In patients who received the placebo and then crossed over to receive the curcumin-containing product, no significant changes occurred after crossover.  Urinary deoxypyridinoline (uDPYD), a marker of bone resorption, decreased in the curcumin-containing product arm and increased in the placebo arm.</ListItem><ListItem>Significant decrease in rFLC and uDPYD occurred in the open-label study.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_195"><Title>Hepatoma (liver cancer)</Title><Para id="_196">The efficacy and safety of curcumin-containing products have been studied in patients with nonalcoholic fatty <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> disease (NAFLD).</Para><Para id="_197">Published results (effectiveness of curcumin-containing product on NAFLD):</Para><OrderedList id="_198" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>A study evaluated the efficacy and safety of supplementation with a phytosomal curcumin-containing product in patients with NAFLD (grades 1–3 according to liver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045557" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasonography</GlossaryTermRef>) These patients were randomly assigned to receive either the curcumin-containing product (phytosomal form; 1,000 mg/day in 2 divided doses; N = 50) or the placebo (N = 52) for a period of 8 weeks.<Reference refidx="16"/><ItemizedList id="_199" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Results indicated that supplementation with the curcumin-containing product was associated with a reduction in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455136" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">body mass index</GlossaryTermRef> (-0.99 ± 1.25 in the curcumin-containing product group vs.  -0.15 ± 1.31 in the placebo group; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .003) and waist circumference (1.74 ± 2.58 in the curcumin-containing product group vs. -0.23 ± 3.49 in the placebo group; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .024). </ListItem><ListItem>Ultrasonographic findings were improved in 75.0% of patients in the curcumin-containing product group, while the rate of improvement in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control group</GlossaryTermRef> was 4.7% (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). </ListItem><ListItem>Serum levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372942" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aspartate aminotransferase</GlossaryTermRef> (AST) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000372944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alanine aminotransferase</GlossaryTermRef> (ALT) were reduced by the end of the trial in the patients in the curcumin-containing product group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001) but elevated in the patients in the control group (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001). </ListItem><ListItem>The curcumin-containing product was safe and well-tolerated during the trial.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A 2019 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meta-analysis</GlossaryTermRef> examined four randomized <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled trials</GlossaryTermRef> that included 228 patients.<Reference refidx="17"/><ItemizedList id="_200" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Results indicated a trend toward significant reduction of ALT <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> concentrations in a subgroup of patients who received ≥1,000 mg/day  of curcumin-containing product supplementation (-11.36 IU/L; 95% confidence interval [CI], -22.75 to 0.02; I<Superscript>2</Superscript>: 51%).</ListItem><ListItem>The meta-analysis showed a significant reduction of AST levels in patients who received curcumin-containing products in studies with 8 weeks of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> (-9.22 IU/L; 95% CI, -12.77 to -5.67; I<Superscript>2</Superscript>: 49%). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_201">Based on these findings, the authors suggested that curcumin-containing products, at higher dosages, might have a favorable effect on patients with NAFLD.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Table id="_271"><Title>Table 2.  Curcumin-Containing Products in Cancer Prevention and Treatment of Precancerous Lesions Trials</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Source</entry><entry Align="Center">Description of Curcuminoid-Containing Product</entry><entry Align="Center">Supplier</entry><entry Align="Center">Type of Product<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">CEM = further processed curcuminoid-enriched materials; CUR = curcumin as a single-chemical entity; HPLC = high-performance liquid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655048" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromatography</GlossaryTermRef>; TE = turmeric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For a more detailed definition of these terms, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_4" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">General Information and History</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="11"/></entry><entry>Curcumin-containing product (480 mg) and quercetin (20 mg) using Oxy-Q tablets</entry><entry>Farr Laboratories (Santa Clarita, CA, USA)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="12"/></entry><entry>100% pure curcumin (CUR)</entry><entry>No source given</entry><entry>CUR</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>Pure curcumin (CUR) powder; 98.0% by HPLC</entry><entry>Sabinsa Corp. (East Windsor, NJ, USA)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="14"/></entry><entry>Curcumin-containing product, reconstituted with turmeric oil and dispensed in capsules (BCM95–Biocurcumax)</entry><entry>Arjuna Natural Extracts Ltd. (Kerela, India)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="15"/></entry><entry><Emphasis>C3</Emphasis> curcuminoid granule stick-packs (Allepey finger turmeric); each curcumin-containing product stick-pack contained 4,000 mg of curcuminoids (3,600 mg of curcumin [CUR], 320 mg of demethoxycurcumin, and 80 mg of bisdemethoxycurcumin)</entry><entry>Sabinsa Corp. (Piscataway, NJ, USA)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="16"/></entry><entry>A phytosomal formulation that contained a complex of curcuminoids and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soy</GlossaryTermRef> phosphatidylcholine in a 1:2 weight ratio, and 2 parts of microcrystalline <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476320" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cellulose</GlossaryTermRef>, with an overall content of curcumin  in the final product of around 20%</entry><entry>Meriva; Indena S.p.A, (Milan, Italy)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_202"><Title>Cancer Treatment</Title><SummarySection id="_203"><Title>Biomarker studies</Title><Para id="_204"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045618" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biomarkers</GlossaryTermRef> have long been used to identify and understand the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046410" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">etiology</GlossaryTermRef> of various diseases. In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> research, there are different types of cancer biomarkers.  Prognostic biomarkers determine the likely <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease and if further treatment is warranted and predictive biomarkers ascertain the likelihood the disease will <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> to treatment.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para><Para id="_205">Five <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> have been performed to evaluate the effects of supplementation with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curcumin</GlossaryTermRef>-containing products on predictive biomarkers in patients with different types of cancer. Various biomarkers from these studies were evaluated as potential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> measures to ascertain the usefulness of curcumin-containing products alone and as an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044144" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjunctive therapy</GlossaryTermRef>. Different curcumin-containing products were used. Curcuminoid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> used in these studies ranged from 20 mg/day to 3,000 mg/day. One of the studies did not identify the amount of curcuminoids administered, but used 5 g of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef> powder dissolved in 150 mL of milk 3 times/day.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><Para id="_206">The main biomarkers used in these studies were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serum</GlossaryTermRef> levels of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_207" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> Total <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef> capacity (TAC).<Reference refidx="20"/> </ListItem><ListItem>Superoxide dismutase (SOD).<Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Glutathione</GlossaryTermRef> peroxidase (GPx).<Reference refidx="20"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045290" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumor necrosis factor-alpha</GlossaryTermRef> (TNF-alpha).<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem><ListItem>Transforming growth factor-beta (TGF-beta).<Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044045" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Interleukin-6</GlossaryTermRef>  (IL-6).<Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000559451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cyclooxygenase-2</GlossaryTermRef> (COX-2).<Reference refidx="23"/></ListItem><ListItem>Prostaglandin E2 (PGE2).<Reference refidx="23"/></ListItem><ListItem> Nitric oxide.<Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem><ListItem> Histological expression of p53 on cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells.</GlossaryTermRef><Reference refidx="21"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_208">Results from four of the studies indicated an association between a positive change in a biomarker and patient outcome as follows:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_209" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>TAC increased and SOD decreased.<Reference refidx="20"/> </ListItem><ListItem>p53 expression increased and TNF-alpha decreased.<Reference refidx="21"/> <Reference refidx="22"/> </ListItem><ListItem>TGF-beta and IL-6 decreased.<Reference refidx="22"/> </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000654999" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Reduction</GlossaryTermRef> in nitric oxide.<Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_210">However, another study found no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef> difference between comparison groups when accounting for the observed biomarker, PGE2.<Reference refidx="23"/> Additionally, a different study found no significant change in GPx.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_211">Another study conducted using a proprietary lecithin delivery system of a curcumin-containing product (500 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef> tablet) given 3 times/day found that curcumin-containing product supplementation consistently improved oxidative status in patients who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_212"><Title>Curcumin-containing products alone</Title><Para id="_213">Two studies have been published that suggest a possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antitumor</GlossaryTermRef> effect of curcumin-containing products.</Para><Para id="_214">Published results (possible antitumor effect of curcumin-containing product):</Para><OrderedList id="_215" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>One report described a patient with treatment-resistant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045795" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">myeloma</GlossaryTermRef> who began a daily oral regime of a curcumin-containing product. A single 8,000 mg dose of the curcumin-containing product (containing curcuminoids complexed with bioperine to aid with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">absorption</GlossaryTermRef>)  was taken on an empty <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> each evening. The patient also underwent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045218" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperbaric oxygen</GlossaryTermRef> treatment.<Reference refidx="25"/><ItemizedList id="_216" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Over the course of 60 months, the patient’s cancer remained stable with minor fluctuations in paraprotein levels.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">open-label</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045831" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase II</GlossaryTermRef> trial investigated the efficacy and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> of curcumin-containing products alone in patients with advanced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="26"/>  The study enrolled 25 patients who received 8,000 mg (orally) of a curcuminoid-containing product daily until <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disease progression</GlossaryTermRef>; each 1 g <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsule</GlossaryTermRef> contained 900 mg of curcumin, 80 mg of demethoxycurcumin, and 20 mg of bisdemethoxycurcumin. Of the 25 patients, 21 were evaluable for response and 24 for toxicity. <ItemizedList id="_219" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>No treatment-related toxicity was reported.</ListItem><ListItem>One patient had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045884" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stable disease</GlossaryTermRef> for more than18 months and another patient had a brief tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046039" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regression.</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_220"><Title>Imatinib and curcumin-containing products</Title><Para id="_221"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044893" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Imatinib</GlossaryTermRef> and curcumin-containing products have been studied in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenoid cystic carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> (ACC).</Para><Para id="_222">Published results (treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044329" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">c-kit</GlossaryTermRef>–positive metastatic ACC with imatinib and a curcumin-containing product):</Para><OrderedList id="_223" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>A published <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case report</GlossaryTermRef> described the successful treatment of a patient with a c-kit–positive metastatic ACC using imatinib and a curcumin-containing product. Imatinib was administered orally at 400 mg/day along with 225 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> of a curcumin-containing product in 1,000 mL of normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046152" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">saline</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenously</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) over 2 to 3 hours, twice a week. An oral curcumin-containing product was also administered, two capsules twice daily (42 mg curcumin per capsule). This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045864" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">regimen</GlossaryTermRef> was continued for 6 months.<Reference refidx="27"/><ItemizedList id="_224" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Stable disease was observed after 2 months of treatment, and  a significant reduction in tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638197" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mass</GlossaryTermRef> (80% decrease in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor volume</GlossaryTermRef> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lungs</GlossaryTermRef>) was observed at 6 months. </ListItem><ListItem>After cessation of IV treatment at 6 months, but with steady use of an oral curcumin-containing product and imatinib, the patient showed continuous clinical and radiographic improvements.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_225">Given the known activity of imatinib against c-kit–positive tumors, the contribution of curcumin-containing products to the efficacy of this patient’s treatment regimen is unclear.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_226"><Title>Docetaxel and curcumin-containing products</Title><Para id="_227">Two studies have explored the efficacy, tolerability, and feasibility of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045382" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">docetaxel</GlossaryTermRef> plus curcumin-containing products in the treatment of cancer.<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/></Para><Para id="_228">Published results (efficacy of docetaxel and a curcumin-containing product):</Para><OrderedList id="_229" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>A 2010 study  conducted in France examined docetaxel plus curcumin-containing products in patients with advanced and metastatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="28"/> Six dose levels of oral curcumin-containing products were studied. Doses varied from 500 mg to 8,000 mg daily along with docetaxel (100 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) administered as a 1-hour IV infusion on day 1 of each 3-week cycle for six cycles. Fourteen patients were enrolled in the study, and ten patients completed the treatments of docetaxel plus a curcumin-containing product. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef> and headaches were the main <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044170" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose-limiting</GlossaryTermRef> toxicities, and three patients considered the amount of the curcumin-containing product (16 capsules a day) as unacceptable. A curcumin-containing product dose of 6,000 mg/day for 7 consecutive days every 3 weeks was determined to be the recommended dose for further investigation in combination with a standard dose of docetaxel.<Reference refidx="28"/><ItemizedList id="_230" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Among the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044029" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">evaluable patients</GlossaryTermRef> enrolled on the study, no disease progression was observed with the combination treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>One patient had evaluable bone lesions that were stable after six cycles of treatment. </ListItem><ListItem>Five patients had partial responses, and three patients had stable disease.</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biological</GlossaryTermRef> response was documented with a decrease of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor markers</GlossaryTermRef> in seven patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A randomized phase II study compared docetaxel and curcumin with docetaxel and placebo in patients with metastatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">castration</GlossaryTermRef>-resistant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="29"/> Patients  received 75 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> of docetaxel  on day 1 every 3 weeks for six cycles and  5 mg of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045492" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prednisone</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046155" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prednisolone</GlossaryTermRef>  twice a day. Patients also received either 6 g of curcumin or placebo daily (4 capsules, 500 mg each, 3 times per day:  morning, lunchtime, and evening) for 7 consecutive days every 3 weeks.<ItemizedList id="_283" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>There were no  differences in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044782" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">progression-free survival</GlossaryTermRef> (PFS), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen</GlossaryTermRef> response rate, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">overall survival</GlossaryTermRef> (OS), or quality of life between the groups.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_232">A multicenter, phase II, randomized, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045673" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">double-blind study</GlossaryTermRef> was initiated at the same institution in France and compared docetaxel plus a curcumin-containing product with docetaxel plus <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> in the first-line treatment of patients with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer. The study was terminated for futility in view of results from the interim analysis (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02095717">NCT02095717</ProtocolRef>).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_233"><Title>Gemcitabine and curcumin-containing products</Title><Para id="_234">Three studies investigated the efficacy and safety of variable formulations and doses of curcumin-containing products in combination with gemcitabine. All studies administered gemcitabine 1,000 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> IV weekly for 3 of 4 weeks, but differed in rate of gemcitabine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_235">Two research studies of first-line treatment in patients with advanced and metastatic pancreatic cancer (PC) showed differing results in tolerability and toxicity profiles.</Para><Para id="_236">Published results (gemcitabine and a curcumin-containing product):</Para><OrderedList id="_237" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>A research group from Israel enrolled 17 patients in an open-label, phase II trial.<Reference refidx="30"/> Patients received 8,000 mg of a curcumin-containing product by mouth daily concurrently with chemotherapy.<ItemizedList id="_238" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Five patients discontinued the curcumin component of the combined treatment mostly because of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> toxicity, and 11 evaluable patients received the planned concurrent treatment of the two <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> until progression of disease (median, 2.5 months); one patient died at home from causes unrelated to the study. </ListItem><ListItem>Seven patients reported gastrointestinal toxicity, mostly diarrhea. </ListItem><ListItem>Of the 11 evaluable patients, 1 had a partial response, 4 had stable disease, and 6 had tumor progression. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Median overall survival</GlossaryTermRef> was 5 months.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_239">The authors concluded that this combination of curcumin-containing products and gemcitabine is not feasible in this population of patients.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>Conversely, an Italian study (N = 44) reported good tolerability using 2,000 mg daily of a curcumin-containing product.<Reference refidx="31"/><ItemizedList id="_240" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>A partial response was observed in 27.3% of patients and stable disease was observed in 34.1% of patients; the overall disease control rate was 61.4%. </ListItem><ListItem>The median OS was 10.2 months and median <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044783" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">time to progression</GlossaryTermRef> was 8.4 months, which is reported to be higher than the historically observed OS rates of 5.7 to 6.7 months for gemcitabine as a single agent.</ListItem><ListItem>The  researchers also noted that patients using this combination of a curcumin-containing product and gemcitabine reported lower-than-expected hematological toxicity. Grade 3 to grade 4 diarrhea occurred in only one patient.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of patients with gemcitabine-resistant PC also found this combination to be safe and effective (N = 21). In addition to gemcitabine, this study administered 60 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript> of S-1 orally for 14 consecutive days every 3 weeks.<Reference refidx="32"/> Patients received a mixture of curcuminoids (8,000 mg/day) that they took at their own convenience,  while on a standard chemotherapy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">treatment schedule</GlossaryTermRef>; the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446112" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compliance</GlossaryTermRef> rate was 90%.<ItemizedList id="_241" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>No patients experienced a partial or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045652" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complete response</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Five patients demonstrated stable disease. </ListItem><ListItem>The most common adverse events of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fatigue</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anorexia</GlossaryTermRef>, and diarrhea were attributed to chemotherapy or disease progression. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_242"><Title>FOLFOX and curcumin-containing products</Title><Para id="_243">A group from the United Kingdom conducted a combined phase I <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000802094" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose-escalation study</GlossaryTermRef> and a phase IIA study of daily oral curcumin-containing products with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000613202" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">folinic acid</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluorouracil</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045465" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxaliplatin</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346521" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">FOLFOX</GlossaryTermRef>) (CUFOX) in patients with metastatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal cancer</GlossaryTermRef> to assess safety, tolerability, and a suitable dose of curcumin.<Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/> Both studies used the same curcumin-containing product.</Para><Para id="_244">Published results (FOLFOX and a curcumin-containing product):</Para><OrderedList id="_245" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>In the phase I dose-escalation trial, oral doses of 500 mg, 1,000 mg, or 2,000 mg of curcumin-containing products were given daily with a loading period of 1 week before initiation of FOLFOX chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="33"/><ItemizedList id="_246" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The curcumin-containing product was determined to be a safe and well-tolerated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to FOLFOX at doses up to 2,000 mg/day. </ListItem><ListItem>Of the 12 patients, 11 patients demonstrated stable disease or partial responses to the treatment after six cycles and 8 patients maintained these responses.</ListItem><ListItem>Median PFS was 34 weeks.</ListItem><ListItem>The adverse events (AEs) reported were primarily gastrointestinal, mainly diarrhea, which is consistent with those described with FOLFOX alone and in some curcumin-containing product trials.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In the phase IIA study, 28 patients were accrued, 18 of whom received CUFOX with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046115" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bevacizumab</GlossaryTermRef>, while 9 patients were randomly assigned  to the control arm and received FOLFOX with or without bevacizumab. One patient was deemed ineligible and was excluded from analyses.<Reference refidx="34"/><ItemizedList id="_247" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Grade 1 or grade 2 fatigue, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044705" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peripheral neuropathy</GlossaryTermRef>, and diarrhea were the most reported AEs in both arms.</ListItem><ListItem>Three patients who received CUFOX reported grade 3 or grade 4 thromboembolic events.</ListItem><ListItem>No complete response was observed; however, 22% of patients who received FOLFOX exhibited stable disease and 44% of patients who received FOLFOX exhibited partial responses; 28% of patients who received CUFOX exhibited stable disease and 56% of patients who received CUFOX exhibited partial responses.</ListItem><ListItem>The median PFS was 171 days for patients who received FOLFOX and 320 days for patients who received CUFOX.</ListItem><ListItem>The median OS was 200 days for patients who received FOLFOX and 596 days for patients who received CUFOX.</ListItem><ListItem>The difference in median OS rates between the two arms in this study was statistically significant. However, the small sample size and an imbalance between the two groups regarding the percentage of patients with two or more metastatic sites makes this result difficult to interpret.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Table id="_272"><Title>Table 3.  Clinical Trials of Curcumin-Containing Products for Cancer Treatment</Title><TGroup Cols="7"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.86%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="4.72%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="14.13%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="6.43%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="14.32%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="19.10%"/><ColSpec ColName="col7" ColNum="7" ColWidth="15.41%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Condition</GlossaryTermRef> or Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Type of Chemotherapy</entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Groups</entry><entry Align="Center">Results</entry><entry Align="Center">Level of Evidence Score<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1">CRLM = colorectal liver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastases;</GlossaryTermRef> FOLFOX = folinic acid, fluorouracil, and oxaliplatin.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col7" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of evidence</GlossaryTermRef> analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="26"/></entry><entry>Phase II, open-label trial</entry><entry>Advanced pancreatic cancer</entry><entry>N/A</entry><entry>N = 25 patients enrolled; 24
were evaluable for toxicity and 21 were evaluable for response
</entry><entry>No treatment-related toxicities were observed; one patient remained stable for &gt;18 months and another patient had a dramatic but brief tumor response</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335136" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Dii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="28"/></entry><entry>Phase I, dose-escalation trial</entry><entry>Advanced and metastatic breast cancer</entry><entry>Docetaxel</entry><entry>N = 14</entry><entry>3 dose-limiting toxicities were observed and 2 of 3 patients at these dose levels refused to continue treatment</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="29"/></entry><entry>Randomized, phase II</entry><entry>Castration-resistant prostate cancer</entry><entry>Docetaxel</entry><entry>N = 50; 24 patients received placebo and docetaxel and 26 patients received docetaxel and curcumin</entry><entry>No difference between groups was reported</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335123" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iDii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="30"/></entry><entry>Phase II, open-label trial</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> and metastatic pancreatic cancer</entry><entry>Gemcitabine</entry><entry>N = 17; 4 locally advanced and 11   metastatic</entry><entry>Median time to tumor progression was 2.5 mo </entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335137" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Diii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="31"/></entry><entry>Phase II trial</entry><entry>Locally advanced and metastatic pancreatic cancer</entry><entry>Gemcitabine</entry><entry>N = 44; 13 locally advanced and 34 metastatic</entry><entry>Partial response in 27.3% of patients and stable disease in 34.1% of patients</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335137" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Diii</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="32"/></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045832" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Phase I/II trial</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Gemcitabine-resistant pancreatic cancer</entry><entry>Gemcitabine</entry><entry>N = 21; 19 patients received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688810" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination therapy</GlossaryTermRef> and 2 patients received gemcitabine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monotherapy</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Phase I study outcome showed safety of oral curcumin-containing product. Additionally, no patients withdrew from this study because of curcumin-containing product intolerability, thus meeting the primary endpoint of the phase II study</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="33"/></entry><entry>Phase I, dose-escalation trial</entry><entry>CRLM</entry><entry>FOLFOX</entry><entry>N = 12</entry><entry>This study revealed curcumin-containing products to be safe and tolerable adjuncts to FOLFOX chemotherapy in patients with CRLM at doses up to 2 g/d</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="34"/></entry><entry>Phase IIA trial</entry><entry>Colorectal cancer with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285970" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inoperable</GlossaryTermRef> liver metastases</entry><entry>FOLFOX</entry><entry>N = 28; 9 received FOLFOX alone and 18 received FOLFOX + a curcumin-containing product</entry><entry>Daily oral curcumin-containing product combined with FOLFOX chemotherapy was safe and tolerable</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_273"><Title>Table 4.  Curcumin-Containing Products in Cancer Treatment Trials</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.05%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="26.46%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="23.41%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.05%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Source</entry><entry Align="Center">Description of Curcuminoid-Containing Product</entry><entry Align="Center">Supplier</entry><entry Align="Center">Type of Product<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">CEM = further processed curcuminoid-enriched materials; CTE = curcuminoid-enriched turmeric extract; CUR = curcumin as a single-chemical entity; T = Turmeric; TE = a hybrid of a CEM and Turmeric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">essential oil</GlossaryTermRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For a more detailed definition of these terms, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_4" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">General Information and History</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="19"/></entry><entry>Turmeric powder dissolved in 150 mL of milk</entry><entry>No source given</entry><entry>T</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="20"/></entry><entry>Curcumin-containing product capsules (BCM-95 CURCUGREEN)</entry><entry>Arjuna Natural Extracts Ltd. (Kerela, India)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="21"/></entry><entry>Curcumin-containing product (not further described)</entry><entry>Sigma Aldrich (Shanghai, China)</entry><entry>CUR</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="22"/> <Reference refidx="31"/></entry><entry>Phytosomal preparation of curcuminoids</entry><entry>Meriva; Indena S.p.A (Milan, Italy)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="23"/></entry><entry>P54FP, an extract of Curcuma spp.; a liquid in 220 mg capsules (9% curcumin [CUR]  and 1% demethoxycurcumin with the remainder constituted by essential oils derived from <Emphasis>Curcuma domestica</Emphasis> and <Emphasis>Curcuma xanthorrhiza</Emphasis>)</entry><entry>Sigma Chemical Co. (Poole, United Kingdom); Phytopharm plc (Godmanchester, United Kingdom)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="24"/></entry><entry>Meriva (ratio of curcumin: demethoxycurcumin: bis-demethoxycurcumin, 33:8:1), 200 mg soy lecithin, and 200 mg microcrystalline cellulose</entry><entry>Meriva; Indena S.p.A (Milan, Italy)  </entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="25"/></entry><entry>Curcumin-containing product complexed with bioperine</entry><entry>Patient administered, not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044711" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prescribed</GlossaryTermRef> by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physician</GlossaryTermRef>; no source given</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="35"/></entry><entry>Curcumin-containing product (not specified)</entry><entry>No source given</entry><entry>CUR</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="26"/></entry><entry>A preparation containing CUR (87.2%); demethoxycurcumin (10.5%); and bisdemethoxycurcumin (2.3%)</entry><entry>Sabinsa Corp. (Piscataway, NJ, USA)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="27"/></entry><entry>A proprietary formulation containing 42 mg of CUR in a form that enhances the solubility of CUR in water</entry><entry>Arantal</entry><entry>CTE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="28"/></entry><entry><Emphasis>Curcuma extract</Emphasis> (not specified)</entry><entry>No source given</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="29"/></entry><entry>Each capsule contained 500 mg of CUR</entry><entry>No source given</entry><entry>CUR</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="30"/></entry><entry>Each capsule contained 500 mg of curcuminoids (curcumin [CUR] 450 mg, demethoxycurcumin 40 mg, and bisdemethoxycurcumin 10 mg)</entry><entry>Sabinsa Corp. (Piscataway, NJ, USA)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="32"/> <Reference refidx="33"/><Reference refidx="34"/></entry><entry>Curcumin-containing product in microbead form, containing a mixture of curcuminoids (Curcumin C3 Complex) that contains curcumin (CUR; 73%), demethoxycurcumin (22%), and bisdemethoxycurcumin (4%)</entry><entry>Sabinsa Corp. (Piscataway, NJ, USA) </entry><entry>TE</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_248"><Title>Quality-of-Life Studies</Title><Para id="_249">One study examined the potential effect of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curcumin</GlossaryTermRef> on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef> (QOL) of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> patients (N = 80) with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045301" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">solid tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, predominantly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454513" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastric</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colorectal</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef> cancer.<Reference refidx="22"/>  All patients received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for their respective cancers while enrolled in the study.  Patients were randomly assigned to receive either curcuminoids (180 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/day) or matched <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> for 8 weeks. Curcuminoids were prepared with phosphatidylcholine to boost <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef>. Meriva contains 20% curcuminoids; therefore, each patient was asked to take three 300 mg <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsules</GlossaryTermRef> per day (one capsule tid).</Para><Para id="_250">This study reported an overall increase in self-reported QOL in both groups, with greater improvement in the curcuminoid group. However, because of the  higher <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">baseline</GlossaryTermRef> QOL values in the placebo group when compared with the curcuminoid group, it is difficult to interpret these results.</Para><Table id="_274"><Title>Table 5.  Curcumin-Containing Products in Quality-of-Life Studies</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Source</entry><entry Align="Center">Description of Curcuminoid-Containing Product</entry><entry Align="Center">Supplier</entry><entry Align="Center">Type of Product<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">CEM = further processed curcuminoid-enriched materials.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For a more detailed definition of these terms, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_4" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">General Information and History</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="22"/></entry><entry>Phytosomal preparation of curcuminoids</entry><entry>Meriva; Indena S.p.A, (Milan, Italy)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_251"><Title>Cancer Therapy Side Effects</Title><SummarySection id="_252"><Title>Dermatitis</Title><Para id="_253">The effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curcumin</GlossaryTermRef>-containing products on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446545" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation-induced dermatitis</GlossaryTermRef> were investigated in three studies.<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/> Two of the studies evaluated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> curcumin-containing products while one study assessed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045927" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">topical</GlossaryTermRef> application of a curcumin-containing cream.</Para><Para id="_254">Published results (curcumin-containing products in the treatment of radiation-induced dermatitis):</Para><OrderedList id="_255" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>In a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045673" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">double-blind</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef> study, 30 adult women with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>  alone were randomly assigned to receive either <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">experimental</GlossaryTermRef> treatment (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> curcumin-containing product; 2,000 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>) or  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control</GlossaryTermRef>  treatment  (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef>) 3 times a day.<Reference refidx="36"/><ItemizedList id="_256" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Self-reported pain measures showed no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">significant</GlossaryTermRef> differences between the  treatment arms. However, the severity of radiation dermatitis at the treatment site was reduced in patients who received the oral curcumin-containing product.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A multi-site, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study assessed the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of an oral curcumin-containing product to reduce radiation dermatitis severity. Breast cancer patients (N = 686) were randomly assigned to received an oral curcumin-containing product (2,000 mg) or  placebo 3 times a day.<Reference refidx="37"/><ItemizedList id="_257" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>While curcumin did not reduce radiation dermatitis severity, fewer curcumin-treated patients with a Radiation Dermatitis Severity scale score of &gt;3.0 suggested a trend towards reduced severity; the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> lacked statistical significance.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prospective,</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">investigator</GlossaryTermRef>-blinded study, 40 adult breast cancer patients underwent radiation therapy and received either a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef>-containing cream or baby oil (placebo) for 5 weeks. The skin was treated with 5 g of turmeric-containing cream or baby oil  5 times daily, before and after radiation therapy.<Reference refidx="38"/><ItemizedList id="_258" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Results showed that curcumin was effective in reducing the severity of dermatitis at 2, 3, and 4 weeks, compared with placebo.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_259"><Title>Mucositis</Title><Para id="_260">Several studies evaluated the tolerability and efficacy of a curcuminoid-containing product by oral application (mouthwash) in the treatment of oral <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045789" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mucositis</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="39"/><Reference refidx="40"/> The studies used several objective outcome measures, including the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454794" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">World Health Organization's</GlossaryTermRef>  mucositis scale and Oral Mucositis <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Assessment</GlossaryTermRef> Scale. </Para><Para id="_261">Published results (curcuminoid-containing products in the treatment of oral mucositis):</Para><OrderedList id="_262" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>A study of adult patients who received chemotherapy and radiation therapy aimed to assess the efficacy of turmeric powder with honey on treating oral mucositis. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">experimental group</GlossaryTermRef> of patients (n = 30) were given a mixture of turmeric powder and honey to apply 5 minutes before treatment, maintain during treatment, and then reapplied 5 minutes after treatment. The control group of patients received no supplementation (n = 30).<Reference refidx="40"/><ItemizedList id="_264" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Good tolerability and a reduction in oral mucositis were noted in patients using the turmeric and honey treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>No adverse effects were observed.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In an investigator-blinded, randomized, controlled trial, 80 patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef> underwent combined <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045182" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carboplatin</GlossaryTermRef>/radiation therapy and received turmeric (6 times a day) or povidone-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044548" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iodine</GlossaryTermRef> (twice a day) mouthwash every other day. Oral mucositis was assessed using the  Radiation Therapy Oncology Group (RTOG) grading system.<Reference refidx="41"/><ItemizedList id="_265" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Turmeric mouthwash delayed and reduced the levels of radiation-induced oral mucositis at all time points.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients who used the turmeric mouthwash had decreased intolerable mucositis, fewer treatment breaks during the first  4 weeks of treatment, and reduced weight loss.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a double-blind randomized study, 32 adult patients with head and neck cancer received radiation therapy and either an oral nano-encapsulated curcumin-containing product (80 mg a day) or a placebo. Fifteen patients received the nano-encapsulated curcumin-containing product (study group), and 14 patients received the placebo (control group). Oral mucositis was assessed by the National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria.<Reference refidx="42"/><ItemizedList id="_266" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In the study group of patients,  onset of oral mucositis was delayed.</ListItem><ListItem>Severity of mucositis increased in all patients, but the grade was significantly lower in patients receiving curcumin.</ListItem><ListItem>While 50% of patients in the control group (7 of 14) developed grade 4 mucositis, no patients developed grade 4 mucositis in the study group.</ListItem><ListItem>The study group had reduced weight loss, and no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> were detectable in this group.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In a randomized <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044727" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">single-blind study</GlossaryTermRef>, 61 adult patients with head and neck cancer  who underwent radiation therapy received either an oral curcumin-containing product (500 mg <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsule</GlossaryTermRef>; total dose of 1.5 g a day) or a placebo 3 times a day. Patients were assessed weekly during radiation therapy and 2 months after treatment.<Reference refidx="43"/><ItemizedList id="_267" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Beginning with week 3 of treatment, patients who received curcumin had decreased incidence and severity of oral mucositis. Two months after treatment, these patients experienced less severe oral mucositis.</ListItem><ListItem>Results from the subjective assessment of patients were comparable to those obtained using the objective scale.</ListItem><ListItem>No <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef>  was observed.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_268"><Title>Multiple effects</Title><Para id="_269">A proprietary lecithin delivery system of a curcuminoid-containing product given 3 times/day (500 mg tablet) was evaluated in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled study</GlossaryTermRef>. The study assessed  efficacy in alleviating the side effects of chemotherapy and radiation therapy  in patients undergoing these treatments 1 month after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> for their cancer (N = 160; 80 patients each in the chemotherapy group and the radiation therapy group). These groups were further divided into experimental and control groups, with 40 patients in each subgroup receiving Meriva or a comparable placebo tablet. In both the chemotherapy and radiation therapy groups, frequency and severity of reported symptoms were significantly lower in the Meriva group and no significant changes were reported in the control group.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></SummarySection><Table id="_275"><Title>Table 6.  Clinical Trials of Curcumin-Containing Products for Cancer Therapy Side Effects</Title><TGroup Cols="6"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="16.66%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Condition</GlossaryTermRef> or Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Groups 
(Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)
</entry><entry Align="Center">Results</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Level of Evidence</GlossaryTermRef> Score<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1">RCT = randomized controlled trial.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="36"/></entry><entry>RCT</entry><entry>Radiation dermatitis in breast cancer patients</entry><entry>35; 17; 18</entry><entry>Reduced severity of radiation dermatitis</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="37"/></entry><entry>RCT</entry><entry>Radiation dermatitis in breast cancer patients</entry><entry>695; 344; 342</entry><entry>No difference in severity between the groups</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="38"/></entry><entry>RCT</entry><entry>Radiation dermatitis in breast cancer patients</entry><entry>40; 20; 20</entry><entry>Reduced radiation dermatitis</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="40"/></entry><entry>Nonrandomized trial</entry><entry>Oral mucositis</entry><entry>60; 30; 30</entry><entry>Reduced oral mucositis</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335134" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2C</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="41"/></entry><entry>RCT</entry><entry>Oral mucositis</entry><entry>80; 40; 40</entry><entry>Reduced oral mucositis</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="42"/></entry><entry>RCT</entry><entry>Oral mucositis</entry><entry>32; 15; 14</entry><entry>Reduced oral mucositis</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="43"/></entry><entry>RCT</entry><entry>Oral mucositis</entry><entry>64; 30; 31</entry><entry>Reduced oral mucositis</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_276"><Title>Table 7.  Curcumin-Containing Products in Symptom Management Trials</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="28.44%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="21.55%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Source</entry><entry Align="Center">Description of Curcuminoid-Containing Product</entry><entry Align="Center">Supplier</entry><entry Align="Center">Type of Product<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">CEM = further processed curcuminoid-enriched materials; T = Turmeric; TE = turmeric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef>; w/w = weight per weight.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For a more detailed definition of these terms, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_4" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">General Information and History</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="36"/> <Reference refidx="37"/></entry><entry>Curcumin C3 complex, 500 mg/capsule</entry><entry>Sabinsa Corp. (UT, USA)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="39"/></entry><entry>Curcumall, a liquid formula mouthwash containing a tincture of curcumin (C3 complex), turmeric, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ginger</GlossaryTermRef> dissolved in glycerin and 0.4% of alcohol</entry><entry>Tumron health products (Jerusalem, Israel); Sabinsa Corp. (UT, USA)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="40"/></entry><entry>Mixture of turmeric powder and honey</entry><entry>Made by researchers</entry><entry>T</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="24"/></entry><entry>Meriva (ratio of curcumin: demethoxycurcumin: bis-demethoxycurcumin 33:8:1), 200 mg <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soy</GlossaryTermRef> lecithin and 200 mg microcrystalline <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476320" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cellulose</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Meriva; Indena S.p.A (Milan, Italy)</entry><entry>CEM</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="38"/></entry><entry>Turmeric extract (16% w/w) and  sandalwood oil (0.5% w/w) in a non-greasy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689975" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">base</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Vicco Laboratories, (Maharashtra, India)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="41"/></entry><entry>Turmeric powder, 400 mg suspended in 80 mL water (use of 10 mL for mouthwash)</entry><entry>Himalaya Drug Company (Bangalore, India)</entry><entry>T</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="42"/></entry><entry>SinaCurcumin (nanocurcumin)</entry><entry>Nanotechnology Research Center of Mashhad University of Medical Science (Iran)</entry><entry>Undefined</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="43"/></entry><entry>Turmeric extract capsules (BCM-95/Curcugreen) containing essential oils of turmeric</entry><entry>Arjuna Natural, Aluva (India)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_288"><Title>Pediatric Population and Curcumin-Containing Products</Title><SummarySection id="_289"><Title>Anticancer effects</Title><Para id="_290">A case report has been published that suggests a possible antitumor effect of a curcumin-containing product. The case report described a 6 month-old infant with infantile hemangioendothelioma. The curcuminoid-containing product was given at a dose of 400 mg/day over the course of 9 months.<Reference refidx="35"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_291" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Radiographic improvement was seen within 3 months. </ListItem><ListItem>There was a notable decrease in liver size at 6 months, and an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> showed no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045869" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">residual</GlossaryTermRef> lesions within 1 year.</ListItem><ListItem>The patient was well and thriving with no evidence of disease at the age of 6 years.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_292">Given that this disease is known to frequently undergo spontaneous involution, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> activity of the curcumin-containing product in this case should be questioned. However, the authors  indicated that this patient’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> had some signs of  an adverse <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_293"><Title>Mucositis</Title><Para id="_294">One pediatric study evaluated the tolerability and efficacy of a curcuminoid-containing product by oral application (mouthwash) in the treatment of oral mucositis.<Reference refidx="39"/> The study used several objective outcome measures, including the WHO's  mucositis scale and Oral Mucositis Assessment Scale. Seven patients (four evaluable) used 10 drops of Curcumall in 50 mL of water along with standard oral care (0.2% chlorohexidine mouthwash for 30 seconds) 2 times a day during doxorubicin-containing chemotherapy treatment. Curcumall is a liquid formula mouthwash containing a tincture of curcumin C3 complex, turmeric, and ginger dissolved in glycerin and 0.4% of alcohol to create a serving dose. Compliance was inconsistent as follows:<Reference refidx="39"/>  </Para><ItemizedList id="_295" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Good tolerability and a reduction in oral mucositis were noted in patients using the curcumin/turmeric mouthwash.</ListItem><ListItem>Except for one patient with gastrointestinal upset, no adverse effects were observed.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Table id="_296"><Title>Table 8.  Clinical Studies of Curcumin-Containing Products for Pediatric Population</Title><TGroup Cols="6"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="16.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="16.66%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design</entry><entry Align="Center">Condition or Cancer Type</entry><entry Align="Center">Treatment Groups (Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control)</entry><entry Align="Center">Results</entry><entry Align="Center">Level of Evidence Score<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1">N/A = not applicable.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="35"/></entry><entry>Case report</entry><entry>Infantile hemangioendothelioma</entry><entry>1; none; none</entry><entry>A decrease in liver size at 6 months, and an ultrasound showed no residual lesions within 1 year</entry><entry>N/A</entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="39"/></entry><entry>Case series</entry><entry>Oral mucositis in pediatric patients</entry><entry>7; 4; none</entry><entry>Reduced oral mucositis</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335140" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">3iC</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15668484">Garcea G, Berry DP, Jones DJ, et al.: Consumption of the putative chemopreventive agent curcumin by cancer patients: assessment of curcumin levels in the colorectum and their pharmacodynamic consequences. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 14 (1): 120-5, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="23543271">Kanai M, Otsuka Y, Otsuka K, et al.: A phase I study investigating the safety and pharmacokinetics of highly bioavailable curcumin (Theracurmin) in cancer patients. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 71 (6): 1521-30, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23233733">Irving GR, Howells LM, Sale S, et al.: Prolonged biologically active colonic tissue levels of curcumin achieved after oral administration--a clinical pilot study including assessment of patient acceptability. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 6 (2): 119-28, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11448902">Sharma RA, McLelland HR, Hill KA, et al.: Pharmacodynamic and pharmacokinetic study of oral Curcuma extract in patients with colorectal cancer. Clin Cancer Res 7 (7): 1894-900, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15501961">Sharma RA, Euden SA, Platton SL, et al.: Phase I clinical trial of oral curcumin: biomarkers of systemic activity and compliance. Clin Cancer Res 10 (20): 6847-54, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11712783">Cheng AL, Hsu CH, Lin JK, et al.: Phase I clinical trial of curcumin, a chemopreventive agent, in patients with high-risk or pre-malignant lesions. Anticancer Res 21 (4B): 2895-900, 2001 Jul-Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="30393127">Kunihiro AG, Brickey JA, Frye JB, et al.: Curcumin, but not curcumin-glucuronide, inhibits Smad signaling in TGFβ-dependent bone metastatic breast cancer cells and is enriched in bone compared to other tissues. J Nutr Biochem 63: 150-156, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="30794412">Kunihiro AG, Luis PB, Brickey JA, et al.: Beta-Glucuronidase Catalyzes Deconjugation and Activation of Curcumin-Glucuronide in Bone. J Nat Prod 82 (3): 500-509, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="24402825">Schiborr C, Kocher A, Behnam D, et al.: The oral bioavailability of curcumin from micronized powder and liquid micelles is significantly increased in healthy humans and differs between sexes. Mol Nutr Food Res 58 (3): 516-27, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="29043927">Stohs SJ, Ji J, Bucci LR, et al.: A Comparative Pharmacokinetic Assessment of a Novel Highly Bioavailable Curcumin Formulation with 95% Curcumin: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Crossover Study. J Am Coll Nutr 37 (1): 51-59, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="16757216">Cruz-Correa M, Shoskes DA, Sanchez P, et al.: Combination treatment with curcumin and quercetin of adenomas in familial adenomatous polyposis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 4 (8): 1035-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="29802852">Cruz-Correa M, Hylind LM, Marrero JH, et al.: Efficacy and Safety of Curcumin in Treatment of Intestinal Adenomas in Patients With Familial Adenomatous Polyposis. Gastroenterology 155 (3): 668-673, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="21372035">Carroll RE, Benya RV, Turgeon DK, et al.: Phase IIa clinical trial of curcumin for the prevention of colorectal neoplasia. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 4 (3): 354-64, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="27267893">Kuriakose MA, Ramdas K, Dey B, et al.: A Randomized Double-Blind Placebo-Controlled Phase IIB Trial of Curcumin in Oral Leukoplakia. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 9 (8): 683-91, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="22473809">Golombick T, Diamond TH, Manoharan A, et al.: Monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance, smoldering multiple myeloma, and curcumin: a randomized, double-blind placebo-controlled cross-over 4g study and an open-label 8g extension study. Am J Hematol 87 (5): 455-60, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="28158893">Panahi Y, Kianpour P, Mohtashami R, et al.: Efficacy and Safety of Phytosomal Curcumin in Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Drug Res (Stuttg) 67 (4): 244-251, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="30949432">Mansour-Ghanaei F, Pourmasoumi M, Hadi A, et al.: Efficacy of curcumin/turmeric on liver enzymes in patients with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: A systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Integr Med Res 8 (1): 57-61, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="21862978">La Thangue NB, Kerr DJ: Predictive biomarkers: a paradigm shift towards personalized cancer medicine. Nat Rev Clin Oncol 8 (10): 587-96, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="21844132">Ghalaut VS, Sangwan L, Dahiya K, et al.: Effect of imatinib therapy with and without turmeric powder on nitric oxide levels in chronic myeloid leukemia. J Oncol Pharm Pract 18 (2): 186-90, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="26771294">Hejazi J, Rastmanesh R, Taleban FA, et al.: Effect of Curcumin Supplementation During Radiotherapy on Oxidative Status of Patients with Prostate Cancer: A Double Blinded, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Study. Nutr Cancer 68 (1): 77-85, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="21314329">He ZY, Shi CB, Wen H, et al.: Upregulation of p53 expression in patients with colorectal cancer by administration of curcumin. Cancer Invest 29 (3): 208-13, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="24648302">Panahi Y, Saadat A, Beiraghdar F, et al.: Adjuvant therapy with bioavailability-boosted curcuminoids suppresses systemic inflammation and improves quality of life in patients with solid tumors: a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled trial. Phytother Res 28 (10): 1461-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="11751448">Plummer SM, Hill KA, Festing MF, et al.: Clinical development of leukocyte cyclooxygenase 2 activity as a systemic biomarker for cancer chemopreventive agents. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 10 (12): 1295-9, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="23775598">Belcaro G, Hosoi M, Pellegrini L, et al.: A controlled study of a lecithinized delivery system of curcumin (Meriva®) to alleviate the adverse effects of cancer treatment. Phytother Res 28 (3): 444-50, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="28413157">Zaidi A, Lai M, Cavenagh J: Long-term stabilisation of myeloma with curcumin. BMJ Case Rep 2017: , 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="18628464">Dhillon N, Aggarwal BB, Newman RA, et al.: Phase II trial of curcumin in patients with advanced pancreatic cancer. Clin Cancer Res 14 (14): 4491-9, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="27515884">Demiray M, Sahinbas H, Atahan S, et al.: Successful treatment of c-kit-positive metastatic Adenoid Cystic Carcinoma (ACC) with a combination of curcumin plus imatinib: A case report. Complement Ther Med 27: 108-13, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="19901561">Bayet-Robert M, Kwiatkowski F, Leheurteur M, et al.: Phase I dose escalation trial of docetaxel plus curcumin in patients with advanced and metastatic breast cancer. Cancer Biol Ther 9 (1): 8-14, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="33666378">Passildas-Jahanmohan J, Eymard JC, Pouget M, et al.: Multicenter randomized phase II study comparing docetaxel plus curcumin versus docetaxel plus placebo in first-line treatment of metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer. Cancer Med 10 (7): 2332-2340, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="21058202">Epelbaum R, Schaffer M, Vizel B, et al.: Curcumin and gemcitabine in patients with advanced pancreatic cancer. Nutr Cancer 62 (8): 1137-41, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="29614381">Pastorelli D, Fabricio ASC, Giovanis P, et al.: Phytosome complex of curcumin as complementary therapy of advanced pancreatic cancer improves safety and efficacy of gemcitabine: Results of a prospective phase II trial. Pharmacol Res 132: 72-79, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="20859741">Kanai M, Yoshimura K, Asada M, et al.: A phase I/II study of gemcitabine-based chemotherapy plus curcumin for patients with gemcitabine-resistant pancreatic cancer. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 68 (1): 157-64, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="25979230">James MI, Iwuji C, Irving G, et al.: Curcumin inhibits cancer stem cell phenotypes in ex vivo models of colorectal liver metastases, and is clinically safe and tolerable in combination with FOLFOX chemotherapy. Cancer Lett 364 (2): 135-41, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="31132111">Howells LM, Iwuji COO, Irving GRB, et al.: Curcumin Combined with FOLFOX Chemotherapy Is Safe and Tolerable in Patients with Metastatic Colorectal Cancer in a Randomized Phase IIa Trial. J Nutr 149 (7): 1133-1139, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="20582974">Hassell LA, Roanh le D: Potential response to curcumin in infantile hemangioendothelioma of the liver. Pediatr Blood Cancer 55 (2): 377-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="23745991">Ryan JL, Heckler CE, Ling M, et al.: Curcumin for radiation dermatitis: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial of thirty breast cancer patients. Radiat Res 180 (1): 34-43, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="29192329">Ryan Wolf J, Heckler CE, Guido JJ, et al.: Oral curcumin for radiation dermatitis: a URCC NCORP study of 686 breast cancer patients. Support Care Cancer 26 (5): 1543-1552, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="28930259">Rao S, Hegde SK, Baliga-Rao MP, et al.: Sandalwood Oil and Turmeric-Based Cream Prevents Ionizing Radiation-Induced Dermatitis in Breast Cancer Patients: Clinical Study. Medicines (Basel) 4 (3): , 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="23709456">Elad S, Meidan I, Sellam G, et al.: Topical curcumin for the prevention of oral mucositis in pediatric patients: case series. Altern Ther Health Med 19 (3): 21-4, 2013 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="26182820">Francis M, Williams S: Effectiveness of Indian Turmeric Powder with Honey as Complementary Therapy on Oral Mucositis : A Nursing Perspective among Cancer Patients in Mysore. Nurs J India 105 (6): 258-60, 2014 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="24165896">Rao S, Dinkar C, Vaishnav LK, et al.: The Indian Spice Turmeric Delays and Mitigates Radiation-Induced Oral Mucositis in Patients Undergoing Treatment for Head and Neck Cancer: An Investigational Study. Integr Cancer Ther 13 (3): 201-10, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="30761565">Delavarian Z, Pakfetrat A, Ghazi A, et al.: Oral administration of nanomicelle curcumin in the prevention of radiotherapy-induced mucositis in head and neck cancers. Spec Care Dentist 39 (2): 166-172, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="32029014">Arun P, Sagayaraj A, Azeem Mohiyuddin SM, et al.: Role of turmeric extract in minimising mucositis in patients receiving radiotherapy for head and neck squamous cell cancer: a randomised, placebo-controlled trial. J Laryngol Otol : 1-6, 2020.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_72"><Title>Adverse Effects</Title><Para id="_73">Most <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> of curcuma-containing products have demonstrated few, if any, associated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef>. In one small study (N = 17) of patients who received a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046049" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">curcumin</GlossaryTermRef>-containing product along with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508951" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gemcitabine</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, about 30% of patients (N = 5) who received 8,000 mg/day of the curcumin-containing product discontinued the product because of intractable <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> fullness. Two other patients had a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> reduction to 4,000 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>, also because of abdominal complaints.<Reference refidx="1"/> In this study, seven patients had grade 3 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> and two patients had grade 2 gastrointestinal toxicity.</Para><Table id="_89"><Title>Table 9.  Curcumin-Containing Products With Reported Adverse Effects</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>Source</entry><entry>Description of Curcuminoid-Containing Product</entry><entry>Supplier</entry><entry>Type of Product<Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">TE = <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">turmeric</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extract</GlossaryTermRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For a more detailed definition of these terms, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_4" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">General Information and History</SummaryRef> section.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="1"/></entry><entry>Each <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsule</GlossaryTermRef> contained 500 mg of curcuminoids (curcumin 450 mg, demethoxycurcumin 40 mg, and bisdemethoxycurcumin 10 mg)</entry><entry>Sabinsa Corp. (Piscataway, NJ)</entry><entry>TE</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21058202">Epelbaum R, Schaffer M, Vizel B, et al.: Curcumin and gemcitabine in patients with advanced pancreatic cancer. Nutr Cancer 62 (8): 1137-41, 2010.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_277"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Curcumin (Curcuma, Turmeric)</Title><Para id="_278">To assist readers in evaluating the results of human studies of integrative, alternative, and complementary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever possible. To qualify for a level of evidence <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef>, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_279" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Be published in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed scientific journal</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Report on    <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Describe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> findings in sufficient detail for a meaningful evaluation to be made.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_280">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and scientific strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score. For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis of CAM treatments for cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_7"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/13/2025)</Title><Para id="_8">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_304"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_4" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">General Information and History</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_305">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_302" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state several cases of severe liver toxicity have occurred in Europe and the United States after consumption of products that were labeled as containing curcumin (cited Lombardi et al. and Halegoua-DeMarzio et al. as references 2 and ,3 respectively). These toxic events may be the result of contamination with toxins known to be in some of these products and/or adulteration or individual patient susceptibility. Various organizations, including international government regulatory agencies, have released cautionary safety advisory notices regarding curcumin-containing products.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000797948#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of curcumin in the treatment of people with cancer.. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Curcumin (Curcuma, Turmeric) and Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/curcumin-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 33651529]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2021-02-22</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
