<Summary id="CDR0000798747" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors can form in the appendix or gastrointestinal tract. Learn about the symptoms of childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor and how it is diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/child-gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Childhood Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/hp/pediatric-gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Childhood Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038092">gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>appendiceal carcinoid</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors  (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors </AltTitle><SummarySection id="_109"><Title>What is childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor?</Title><Para id="_180">Childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000810445" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (also called gastrointestinal carcinoid tumor) is a rare cancer that develops in neuroendocrine cells. These cells have features of both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nerve cells</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef>-producing cells and are found throughout the body, most often in the chest and abdomen. In the digestive tract, these cells help control digestion and the movement of food through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomach</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestines</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_181">In children, these tumors most often form in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044753" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appendix</GlossaryTermRef>, a small pouch connected to the beginning of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045097" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">large intestine</GlossaryTermRef>. They are usually found by accident during surgery to remove the appendix. Appendiceal neuroendocrine tumors in children tend to grow slowly and almost never spread to other parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_182">Rarely, neuroendocrine tumors can also form in other parts of the digestive system, such as the stomach, intestines, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer that forms in these areas have a higher chance of spreading and may need more treatment.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000805506" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing of the gastrointestinal tract showing the liver, stomach, pancreas, small intestine, colon, and appendix." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_103"><Caption language="en">Gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors form in the lining of the gastrointestinal tract and other organs in the abdomen. Most gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors in children form in the appendix, but they can also form in the stomach, intestines, pancreas, and liver.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_113"><Title>Causes and risk factors for childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors</Title><Para id="_114">Gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors in children are caused by certain changes to the way gastrointestinal neuroendocrine cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_115">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Children with multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) or von Hipple Lindau (VHL) syndrome may have a higher risk of gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_116"><Title>Genetic counseling for children with gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor that is not in the appendix</Title><Para id="_118">It may not be clear from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> whether your child's gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor is part of an inherited condition. Genetic counseling can assess the likelihood that your child's cancer is inherited and whether <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef> is needed. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic counselors</GlossaryTermRef> and other specially trained health professionals can discuss your child's diagnosis and your family's medical history to help you understand:</Para><ItemizedList id="_119" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the options for testing for changes in the <GeneName>MEN1</GeneName> and <GeneName>VHL</GeneName> genes</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of other cancers for your child</ListItem><ListItem>the risk of gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor or other cancers for your child's siblings</ListItem><ListItem>the risk and benefits of learning genetic information</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_120">Genetic counselors can also help you cope with your child's genetic testing results, including how to discuss the results with family members. They can also advise you about whether other members of your family should receive genetic testing.</Para><Para id="_121">Learn about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/genetic-testing-fact-sheet">Genetic Testing for Inherited Cancer Risk</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_122"><Title>Symptoms of childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor</Title><Para id="_123">The symptoms of a gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor depend on where the tumor forms in the abdomen. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has any symptoms below.</Para><Para id="_124">Neuroendocrine tumors in the appendix are often found during an appendectomy for appendicitis. Appendicitis is a medical emergency that can cause:</Para><ItemizedList id="_125" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> pain, especially on the lower right side of the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>fever</ListItem><ListItem>nausea and vomiting</ListItem><ListItem>diarrhea</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_126">A gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor that is not in the appendix may release hormones and other substances. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339609" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Carcinoid syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> occurs when a neuroendocrine tumor in the digestive tract releases the hormone <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000335511" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serotonin</GlossaryTermRef> and other substances. It may cause:</Para><ItemizedList id="_127" Style="bullet"><ListItem>redness and a warm feeling in the face, neck, and upper chest</ListItem><ListItem>a fast heartbeat</ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>sudden drop in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef> which can cause restlessness, confusion, weakness, dizziness, and pale, cool, and clammy skin</ListItem><ListItem>diarrhea</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_128">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than a gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor. The only way to know is for your child to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_129"><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor</Title><Para id="_130">If your child has symptoms that suggest a gastrointestinal tumor, the doctor will need to find out if they are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. The doctor will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor, the results of these tests will help plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_131">The tests used to diagnose gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_132"><Title>Blood chemistry study</Title><Para id="_133"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry study</GlossaryTermRef> uses a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_135">MRI uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas in the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_91"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_136"><Title>PET scan</Title><Para id="_137">PET scan  (positron emission tomography scan) uses a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> sugar (also called radioactive glucose) that is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes pictures of where sugar is being used by the body. Cancer cells show up brighter in the pictures because they are more active and take up more sugar than normal cells do.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775456" type="image/jpeg" alt="Positron emission tomography (PET) scan; drawing shows a child lying on table that slides through the PET scanner." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_92"><Caption language="en">Positron emission tomography (PET) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the PET scanner. The head rest and white strap help the child lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the child's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do. </Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>CT scan</Title><Para id="_139">CT scan (CAT scan) uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_93"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><Title>Ultrasound</Title><Para id="_141">Ultrasound uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775457" type="image/jpeg" alt="Abdominal ultrasound; drawing shows a child lying on an exam table during an abdominal ultrasound procedure. A technician is shown pressing a transducer (a device that makes sound waves that bounce off tissues inside the body) against the skin of the abdomen. A computer screen shows a sonogram (picture)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_94"><Caption language="en">Abdominal ultrasound. An ultrasound transducer connected to a computer is pressed against the skin of the abdomen. The transducer bounces sound waves off internal organs and tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture).</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_142"><Title>24-hour urine test</Title><Para id="_143">A 24-hour <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef> test collects urine for 24 hours to measure the amounts of certain substances, such as hormones. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the organ or tissue that makes it. The urine sample is checked to see if it contains <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798773" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">5-HIAA</GlossaryTermRef> (a breakdown product of the hormone serotonin which may be made by neuroendocrine tumors). This test is used to help diagnose carcinoid syndrome.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_144"><Title>Somatostatin receptor scintigraphy</Title><Para id="_145">Somatostatin receptor scintigraphy is a type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046552" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radionuclide scan</GlossaryTermRef> that may be used to find tumors. A very small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045141" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">octreotide</GlossaryTermRef> (a hormone that attaches to tumors) is injected into a vein and travels through the blood. The radioactive octreotide attaches to the tumor and a special camera that detects radioactivity is used to show where the tumors are in the body. This procedure is also called octreotide scan and SRS.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_147">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child’s cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the genetic test report, pathology report, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child’s cancer.</Para><Para id="_148">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/services">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_149"><Title>Types of treatment for childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor</Title><SummarySection id="_150"><Title>Who treats children with gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor?</Title><Para id="_151">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor. The pediatric oncologist works with other pediatric health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_47" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>pediatric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046439" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endocrinologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem> <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_179"><Title>Treatment options</Title><Para id="_152">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with a gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor. You and your child's cancer care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_153">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, visit our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_154">Types of treatment your child might have include:</Para><SummarySection id="_155"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_156">Surgery to remove the tumor is the only treatment needed for neuroendocrine tumor in the appendix. Surgery is also used alone or with other therapies to treat neuroendocrine tumors outside the appendix.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_157"><Title>Embolization</Title><Para id="_55">Embolization is a treatment in which <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">contrast dye</GlossaryTermRef> and particles are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic artery</GlossaryTermRef> through a catheter (thin tube). The particles block the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">artery</GlossaryTermRef>, cutting off blood flow to the tumor. Sometimes a small amount of a radioactive substance is attached to the particles. Most of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> is trapped near the tumor to kill the cancer cells. This is called radioembolization.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_158"><Title>Radioactive drug</Title><Para id="_159">A radioactive drug contains a radioactive substance and is used to diagnose or treat disease, including cancer. Lutetium Lu 177-dotatate is a radioactive drug used to treat gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_160"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_160_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_160_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_160_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_161"><Title>Treatment of childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor</Title><Para id="_162">Treatment of neuroendocrine tumor in the appendix in children is surgery to remove the appendix.</Para><Para id="_163">Treatment of neuroendocrine tumor in the large intestine, pancreas, or stomach is usually surgery.</Para><Para id="_164">Treatment of neuroendocrine tumor that cannot be removed by surgery, multiple tumors, or tumors that have spread may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_165" Style="bullet"><ListItem>embolization</ListItem><ListItem>radioactive drug (lutetium Lu 177-dotatate)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_166">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_167"><Title>Prognostic factors for childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor</Title><Para id="_168">If your child has been diagnosed with a gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_169">Prognosis depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_170" Style="bullet"><ListItem>where the tumor first formed in the body</ListItem><ListItem>the size of the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor has spread to other parts of the body</ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor is newly diagnosed or has recurred (come back)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_171">The prognosis for neuroendocrine tumors in the appendix in children is usually excellent after surgery to remove the tumor. Gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors that are not in the appendix may be larger or have spread to other parts of the body at the time of diagnosis and usually do not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">respond</GlossaryTermRef> well to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>. Larger tumors are more likely to recur (come back).</Para><Para id="_172">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_173"><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_174">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_173_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_79">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_80" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer) or other problems</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_81">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_175"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_175_md_98">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_175_md_99">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back).</Para><Para id="_176">To learn more about follow-up tests, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000798747#_129" url="/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/child-gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">Tests to diagnose childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumor</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_177"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_178">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child’s treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-carcinoid-tumors/">Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood gastrointestinal neuroendocrine tumors.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumors. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/child-gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/gi-neuroendocrine-tumors/patient/child-gi-neuroendocrine-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000799718"/><DateFirstPublished>2019-10-25</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-07</DateLastModified></Summary>
