<Summary id="CDR0000799261"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>When cancer drugs are taken with certain foods or dietary supplements,  they may interact causing adverse effects. Get detailed information about cancer therapy interactions   with different foods and dietary supplements in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/dietary-interactions-pdq">Dietary Supplement and Cancer Therapy Interactions (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/dietary-interactions-pdq">Dietary Supplement and Cancer Therapy Interactions (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000372898">CAM nutritional therapy</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_105">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of foods, dietary supplements, and cancer therapy interactions in people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_106">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>foods, dietary supplements, and cancer therapy interactions</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Cancer Therapy Interactions With Foods and Dietary Supplements (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Cancer Therapy Interactions With Foods and Dietary Supplements (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Cancer Therapy Interactions With Foods and Dietary Supplements</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_68"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_69">This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summary provides an overview on cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> interactions with different foods and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_70">This summary contains the following key information:</Para><ItemizedList id="_94" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> The combination of cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> taken by patients and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary and alternative medicine</GlossaryTermRef> used may interact, causing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse outcomes</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem>Research on dietary supplement and cancer drug <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetics</GlossaryTermRef> (PK) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interactions</GlossaryTermRef> is limited, but there is evidence for several possible interactions and adverse reactions.</ListItem><ListItem>For many specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef> supplements, there is insufficient information available to determine if they are safe and effective as a complementary therapy to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> cancer treatment.</ListItem><ListItem>Certain constituents of foods and dietary supplements (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">St. John’s wort</GlossaryTermRef>, grapefruit juice, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687277" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epigallocatechin gallate</GlossaryTermRef> from green tea) can alter the PK of specific types of drugs.</ListItem><ListItem>Some research has shown a dietary supplement/food and drug PK interaction between grapefruit juice and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044893" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imatinib</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_8">For adult <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> patients in the United States, the frequency of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary and alternative medicine</GlossaryTermRef> (CAM) use is approximately 36%.<Reference refidx="1"/> It is possible that the combination of cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> taken by these patients and the CAM they use may interact, causing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse outcomes</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>/herbs and cancer drugs are taken together, there is always a risk of the supplement having an impact on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetics</GlossaryTermRef> (PK) or pharmacodynamics (PD) of the drug. Many <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug interactions</GlossaryTermRef> occur from the effects of the supplement on specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> or on components involved in the PK of the drug, such as how the drug is metabolized and transported. Reporting and studying these interactions is important, so health care professionals can help patients navigate CAM usage with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef>, thus avoiding preventable adverse outcomes. Integrative <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045434" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oncology</GlossaryTermRef> consultations available in a number of cancer care settings can engage patients in evidence-based discussions about recommending or stopping supplements, as well as addressing questions about alternative therapies.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_164">In the United States, dietary supplements are regulated by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) as a separate category from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. Unlike drugs, dietary supplements do not require premarket evaluation and approval by the FDA unless specific disease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> or treatment claims are made. The quality and amount of ingredients in dietary supplements are also regulated by the FDA through Good Manufacturing Practices (GMPs). The FDA GMPs requires that every finished batch of dietary supplement meets each product specification for identity, purity, strength, composition, and limits on contamination that may <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adulterate</GlossaryTermRef> dietary supplements. Because dietary supplements are not formally reviewed for manufacturing consistency every year, ingredients may vary considerably from lot to lot and there is no guarantee that ingredients claimed on product labels are present (or are present in the specified amounts). The FDA has not approved the use of dietary supplements as a treatment for cancer patients.</Para><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Cytochrome P450 Inhibitors/Inducers </Title><Para id="_10">One of the main group of enzymes involved in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> of many cancer drugs is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytochrome P450</GlossaryTermRef> (CYP) superfamily of enzymes. These enzymes play an important role in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043976" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">activation</GlossaryTermRef> and inactivation of various drugs. Another component involved in the metabolism and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476338" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excretion</GlossaryTermRef> of many drugs is the transport <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643067" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">P-glycoprotein</GlossaryTermRef>  (P-gp). P-gp works in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046335" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestine</GlossaryTermRef> as a drug efflux pump regulating the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef> of the drug. Various anticancer drugs are substrates of P-gp; thus, if P-gp or any CYP enzyme is impacted, the drug it is processing will also be impacted.</Para><Para id="_11">The PK of a drug predicts <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> outcomes for the patient. Various <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbs</GlossaryTermRef> and dietary supplements are known to influence the PK of certain drugs, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">St. John’s wort</GlossaryTermRef>. Currently, research on dietary supplement and cancer drug PK interactions is limited, but there is evidence for several possible interactions and adverse reactions.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="27316629">Collado-Borrell R, Escudero-Vilaplana V, Romero-Jiménez R, et al.: Oral antineoplastic agent interactions with medicinal plants and food: an issue to take into account. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 142 (11): 2319-30, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="33864520">Wolf CPJG, Rachow T, Ernst T, et al.: Interactions in cancer treatment considering cancer therapy, concomitant medications, food, herbal medicine and other supplements. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 148 (2): 461-473, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="33524183">Lee RT, Kwon N, Wu J, et al.: Prevalence of potential interactions of medications, including herbs and supplements, before, during, and after chemotherapy in patients with breast and prostate cancer. Cancer 127 (11): 1827-1835, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="34835986">Harrigan M, McGowan C, Hood A, et al.: Dietary Supplement Use and Interactions with Tamoxifen and Aromatase Inhibitors in Breast Cancer Survivors Enrolled in Lifestyle Interventions. Nutrients 13 (11): , 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="36525104">D'Andre SD, Bauer BA, Hofmann MB, et al.: Dietary supplement use and recommendations for discontinuation in an integrative oncology clinic. Support Care Cancer 31 (1): 40, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20701553">He SM, Yang AK, Li XT, et al.: Effects of herbal products on the metabolism and transport of anticancer agents. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol 6 (10): 1195-213, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="16880233">Meijerman I, Beijnen JH, Schellens JH: Herb-drug interactions in oncology: focus on mechanisms of induction. Oncologist 11 (7): 742-52, 2006 Jul-Aug.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_175"><Title>Antioxidants</Title><SummarySection id="_176"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_177">Some common dietary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidants</GlossaryTermRef> include the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_178" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef> (ascorbate).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin E</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Flavonoids</GlossaryTermRef> (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soy</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046660" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">isoflavones</GlossaryTermRef>, green tea <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686469" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catechins</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Beta-carotene</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Glutathione</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_179"> Numerous anticancer agents generate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687227" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reactive oxygen species</GlossaryTermRef>, which cause decreased levels of antioxidants, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044393" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deoxyribonucleic acid</GlossaryTermRef>  damage, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> death. Antioxidants are taken by many cancer patients because it is thought that the substances will protect and repair healthy cells damaged by cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/> There is insufficient information for many specific antioxidant supplements to determine if they are safe and effective as a complementary therapy to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> cancer treatment. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_180"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><Para id="_181">A study published in 2018 examined the pharmacokinetic interactions between <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044893" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imatinib</GlossaryTermRef> (25 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kg</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">orally</GlossaryTermRef>) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin A</GlossaryTermRef> (12 mg <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046057" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retinol</GlossaryTermRef>/kg orally), vitamin E (400 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">IU</GlossaryTermRef>/kg orally), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000427252" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vitamin D3</GlossaryTermRef> (100 IU/kg orally), and vitamin C (500 mg/kg orally) when coadministered in rat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal models</GlossaryTermRef>. The results showed that there was an increase in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef> of imatinib with vitamins A, E , and D, and a decrease in the bioavailability of imatinib with vitamin C.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_182">A study that examined the oxidized form of ascorbate, dehydroascorbate,  as a complementary supplement with chemotherapeutic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000615324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vincristine</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef>, and imatinib) initially found that dehydroascorbate given before doxorubicin treatment caused a reduction of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> in mice with lymphoma  (RL) cell–derived xenogeneic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumors</GlossaryTermRef>. This form of ascorbate is not generally available as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplement</GlossaryTermRef> and is not used clinically, and it has different properties and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacology</GlossaryTermRef> from unoxidized or reduced ascorbate; thus, the potential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> implications of these findings are unknown.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_183">An <ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mouse model</GlossaryTermRef> study observed a possible interaction between vitamin C (40 mg/kg/d) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bortezomib</GlossaryTermRef>. There was a significant reduction in bortezomib’s anticancer activities with consumption of vitamin C.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_184"><Title>Human/Clinical Studies</Title><Para id="_185">A study examined pre- and post-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> antioxidant dietary supplement (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045113" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">selenium</GlossaryTermRef>; multivitamins; zinc; and  vitamins A,  C, and  E) use in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmenopausal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors.</GlossaryTermRef> The results showed an increased risk of total <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496502" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mortality</GlossaryTermRef> and worsened <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrence</GlossaryTermRef>-free survival with antioxidant dietary supplement use during <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="5"/> A similar study investigated the outcomes for breast cancer patients using antioxidant supplements (vitamins A, C, and E; <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046132" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carotenoids</GlossaryTermRef>; and  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">coenzyme Q10)</GlossaryTermRef> before and during treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045253" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cyclophosphamide</GlossaryTermRef>, doxorubicin, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045258" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paclitaxel</GlossaryTermRef>. The results showed an increase in hazards of recurrence and death in these patients. Though these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000618612" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hazard ratios</GlossaryTermRef> are not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef>, they both trended in the same direction as those seen in the previous study.<Reference refidx="6"/> This evidence does give reason to use these supplements with caution and indicates that more research on this topic is needed.</Para><Para id="_186"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691423" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Alpha-tocopherol</GlossaryTermRef>, one of eight vitamin E <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef>, was investigated in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> for its impact on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> from chemotherapy and radiation therapy. Initially, some research suggested that alpha-tocopherol may reduce <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> caused by radiation therapy for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">head and neck cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. Two <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of patients with head and neck cancer who received vitamin E supplementation at a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> of 400 IU/day have shown an  association with a higher risk of tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapse</GlossaryTermRef> and a decrease in cancer-free survival.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25496272">Ozben T: Antioxidant supplementation on cancer risk and during cancer therapy: an update. Curr Top Med Chem 15 (2): 170-8, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="30047806">Maher HM, Alzoman NZ, Shehata SM: Ultra-performance LC-MS/MS study of the pharmacokinetic interaction of imatinib with selected vitamin preparations in rats. Bioanalysis 10 (14): 1099-1113, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="18829561">Heaney ML, Gardner JR, Karasavvas N, et al.: Vitamin C antagonizes the cytotoxic effects of antineoplastic drugs. Cancer Res 68 (19): 8031-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19369963">Perrone G, Hideshima T, Ikeda H, et al.: Ascorbic acid inhibits antitumor activity of bortezomib in vivo. Leukemia 23 (9): 1679-86, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="30668630">Jung AY, Cai X, Thoene K, et al.: Antioxidant supplementation and breast cancer prognosis in postmenopausal women undergoing chemotherapy and radiation therapy. Am J Clin Nutr 109 (1): 69-78, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="31855498">Ambrosone CB, Zirpoli GR, Hutson AD, et al.: Dietary Supplement Use During Chemotherapy and Survival Outcomes of Patients With Breast Cancer Enrolled in a Cooperative Group Clinical Trial (SWOG S0221). J Clin Oncol 38 (8): 804-814, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="15812073">Bairati I, Meyer F, Gélinas M, et al.: A randomized trial of antioxidant vitamins to prevent second primary cancers in head and neck cancer patients. J Natl Cancer Inst 97 (7): 481-8, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="16841333">Bairati I, Meyer F, Jobin E, et al.: Antioxidant vitamins supplementation and mortality: a randomized trial in head and neck cancer patients. Int J Cancer 119 (9): 2221-4, 2006.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_107"><Title>Herbs</Title><SummarySection id="_108"><Title>Ginseng</Title><SummarySection id="_109"><Title>General information</Title><Para id="_110"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044151" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ginseng</GlossaryTermRef> root has commonly been used as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplement</GlossaryTermRef> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000449722" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">traditional Asian medicine</GlossaryTermRef>. There are several types of ginsengs. While there is no conclusive evidence for the health benefits of ginseng, people currently use it for the following reasons:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_111" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>To increase overall well-being and concentration.</ListItem><ListItem>To strengthen the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem> To improve health <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748138" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart disease</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_112"><Title>Laboratory/animal/preclinical studies</Title><Para id="_113">Most <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> research on ginseng’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetic</GlossaryTermRef> (PK) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interactions</GlossaryTermRef> found little evidence of any effects, determining a low risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cytochrome P450</GlossaryTermRef> (CYP)-dependent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herb</GlossaryTermRef>-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef> reactions. Overall, the evidence is mixed and inconclusive.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_114"><Title>Case study</Title><Para id="_115">Ginseng was suspected of being responsible for an incident of hepatotoxicity that occurred in a 26-year-old male taking <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044893" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imatinib</GlossaryTermRef>. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypothesized</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797426" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mechanism</GlossaryTermRef> for this interaction was inhibition of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic</GlossaryTermRef> CYP3A4, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> primarily responsible for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolizing</GlossaryTermRef> imatinib. The ginseng was <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ingested</GlossaryTermRef> through a ginseng energy drink, which creates uncertainty about whether the ginseng or the other ingredients in the drink caused the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effect</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical research</GlossaryTermRef> is needed to confirm if there are any PK interactions between imatinib and ginseng.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_118"><Title>Scutellaria baicalensis/wogonin</Title><SummarySection id="_119"><Title>General information</Title><Para id="_120"><ScientificName>Scutellaria baicalensis</ScientificName>, also known as wogonin, Chinese skullcap, or Huang Qin, is a plant used in traditional Chinese medicine to treat various medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>, such as the following:<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_121" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hepatitis</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Infections</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Inflammation</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_122">In traditional Chinese medicine, there are some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbal</GlossaryTermRef> mixtures that contain <ScientificName>Scutellaria baicalensis</ScientificName>, one being Huang Qin Tang. PHY906, a patented formula derived from Huang Qin Tang, is being studied as a potential adjuvant for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>; there is some evidence that this herbal mixture potentiates the anticancer effects of certain cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000509041" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sorafenib</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="8"/>  Some research has shown the inhibitory effect of wogonin on the activity of CYP, but more research is needed to determine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interactions</GlossaryTermRef> with specific drugs.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_123"><Title>Laboratory/animal/preclinical studies</Title><Para id="_192">A 2016 study investigated the effects of a <ScientificName>Scutellariae</ScientificName> radix decoction on methotrexate pharmacokinetics in rats. The study revealed an increased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic</GlossaryTermRef> methotrexate exposure when given together with the <ScientificName>Scutellariae</ScientificName> radix decoction. Giving them together is thought to have effects on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045790" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multidrug resistance</GlossaryTermRef>–associated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">proteins</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000791448" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer resistance protein</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_124">A 2018 study examined the PK profile and herb-drug interactions of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> wogonin and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045382" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">docetaxel</GlossaryTermRef> in rats with mammary tumors. The investigators  found that in rats receiving oral wogonin and  docetaxel, the area under the concentration versus time curve (AUC), initial peak serum concentration (C<Subscript>max</Subscript>), and half-life  for docetaxel increased.  The investigators speculated that these increases resulted from  the inhibitory effect of wogonin on CYP3A and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643067" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">P-glycoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> (P-gp). More research is needed with human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, but these results suggest a possible interaction between wogonin and docetaxel.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_125"><Title>St. John’s Wort</Title><SummarySection id="_126"><Title>General information</Title><Para id="_127">The flower of the St. John’s wort (SJW) (<ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Hypericum perforatum</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName>) plant is used traditionally for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000441269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">wound</GlossaryTermRef> healing, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044043" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">insomnia</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270740" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lung</GlossaryTermRef> problems, and most commonly today for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>. This flower can be taken through teas, tablets, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000455334" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">capsules</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef>. Currently, the evidence for the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of SJW is varied, but there have been reports of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interactions</GlossaryTermRef> and adverse effects with several <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><Title>Laboratory/animal/preclinical studies</Title><Para id="_129">A 2012 study observed the effects of SJW on the PK of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef> in a rat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal model</GlossaryTermRef>. After coadministration of SJW (300 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kg</GlossaryTermRef> and 150 mg/kg) and methotrexate, animals that received 300 mg/kg of SJW had a 163%  increase in AUC and a 60% increase in C<Subscript>max</Subscript>  for methotrexate. For animals that received 150 mg/kg of SJW, an  increase in AUC (55%) for methotrexate was observed. Overall, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496502" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mortality</GlossaryTermRef> of the rats treated with SJW combined with methotrexate was higher. The researchers suggested using extreme caution if coadministering these two substances.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_130"><Title>Human/clinical studies</Title><Para id="_131">There are two well-known examples of herb-drug interactions impacting drug PK that have clinical evidence. These two interactions are between SJW and both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635811" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">irinotecan</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044893" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imatinib</GlossaryTermRef>. After patients were treated with both irinotecan (350 mg/m<Superscript>2</Superscript>) and SJW (900 mg/d), one study found a 42% decrease in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> levels of SN-38, the active <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolite</GlossaryTermRef> of irinotecan. The researchers hypothesized that components of SJW extract, pseudohypericin and hyperforin, interacted with CYP3A4 isoform and P-gp, causing  reduction in SN-38. This interaction may cause a loss of irinotecan efficacy.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_132">A similar <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> occurred in two studies that examined treatment with imatinib (400 mg) and SJW (300 mg 3 times a day). In one study, SJW caused a 32% decrease in AUC, a 29% decrease in C<Subscript>max</Subscript>, and a 21% decrease in half-life after two weeks of combined treatment with SJW and imatinib.<Reference refidx="15"/> The second study found that SJW use caused a 43% increase in the clearance of imatinib and a 30% decrease in AUC. This interaction is also thought to be caused by the impact of SJW on CYP3A4, the major <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> that metabolizes imatinib.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_133">Another CYP3A4 substrate that may be impacted by SJW is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045382" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">docetaxel</GlossaryTermRef>. A 2014 study with ten <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> patients investigated the PK interactions of docetaxel (135 mg <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046326" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">IV</GlossaryTermRef> for 60 min) in combination with SJW (300 mg <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">orally</GlossaryTermRef> for 14 days). The results showed a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef> decrease of 12% in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean</GlossaryTermRef> AUC and an increased clearance of docetaxel.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_134">Although there is a lack of published research, the use of SJW in patients undergoing treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367463" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ixabepilone</GlossaryTermRef> is not recommended. SJW may cause a decrease in plasma concentrations of ixabepilone. The drug label for ixabepilone states a warning for this possible interaction.<Reference refidx="18"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_135"><Title>Thunder God Vine </Title><SummarySection id="_136"><Title>General information</Title><Para id="_137">Thunder god vine, also known as <ScientificName>Tripterygium wilfordii</ScientificName> Hook f, is an herb traditionally used in Chinese medicine for its possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anti-inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef>, immunosuppressant, and anticancer effects.<Reference refidx="19"/>  Studies have found that triptolide and celastrol, the active components of thunder god vine, are responsible for these possible effects. Clinical observations, mostly from China, reported significant multiorgan <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicities</GlossaryTermRef> from the traditional raw material or the extracts. Deaths associated with ingesting these materials have been frequently reported.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/> Frequency of severe-grade adverse events from the extracts ranged from 5% to 8%,<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/> with the global <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046145" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incidence</GlossaryTermRef> of adverse events at 30.8% (95% confidence interval, 21.2–40.3).<Reference refidx="23"/> The most frequently reported adverse events are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044046" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intestinal</GlossaryTermRef> toxicity (13.9%), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046564" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reproductive</GlossaryTermRef> toxicity (10.2%), hepatotoxicity (6.8%), nephrotoxicity (13.6%), hematotoxicity (5.7%), and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046112" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cutaneous</GlossaryTermRef> toxicity (&lt;5%).<Reference refidx="23"/> Evidence varies for herb-drug interactions and toxicity, which are  potentially caused by inhibiting effects on the activity of the CYP450 enzyme system.<Reference refidx="24"/> Specifically, celastrol inhibits five cytochrome P450 isoenzymes (CYP1A2, CYP2C19, CYP2D6, CYP2E1, and CYP3A4) <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis>.<Reference refidx="25"/>  In addition, a study also found that the coadministration of the CYP3A4 inhibitor, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045535" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ritonavir</GlossaryTermRef>, or the inducer, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045262" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dexamethasone</GlossaryTermRef>, leads to a significant increase or decrease of the plasma concentration levels of triptolide.<Reference refidx="26"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>Laboratory/animal/preclinical studies</Title><Para id="_139">A 2017 study investigated the effects of triptolide (10 mg/kg) on the PKs of three different sorafenib <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> (20, 50, and 100 mg/kg) in rats. The results showed an increase in C<Subscript>max</Subscript> and AUC for each sorafenib dose and a decrease in clearance with pretreatment of triptolide. It is hypothesized that this interaction occurred due to triptolide’s possible inhibiting effects on P-gp and CYP3A4 enzymatic activity.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Wang CZ, Yuan  CS: Ginseng, American. In: Coates PM, Betz JM, Blackman MR, et al., eds.: Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2nd ed. Informa Healthcare, 2010, pp 339-47.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Jia L, Soldati F: Ginseng, Asian. In: Coates PM, Betz JM, Blackman MR, et al., eds.: Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2nd ed. Informa Healthcare, 2010, pp 348-62.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27316629">Collado-Borrell R, Escudero-Vilaplana V, Romero-Jiménez R, et al.: Oral antineoplastic agent interactions with medicinal plants and food: an issue to take into account. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 142 (11): 2319-30, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="23394826">Goey AK, Mooiman KD, Beijnen JH, et al.: Relevance of in vitro and clinical data for predicting CYP3A4-mediated herb-drug interactions in cancer patients. Cancer Treat Rev 39 (7): 773-83, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="24387348">Haefeli WE, Carls A: Drug interactions with phytotherapeutics in oncology. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol 10 (3): 359-77, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20332334">Bilgi N, Bell K, Ananthakrishnan AN, et al.: Imatinib and Panax ginseng: a potential interaction resulting in liver toxicity. Ann Pharmacother 44 (5): 926-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="31070530">Wang ZL, Wang S, Kuang Y, et al.: A comprehensive review on phytochemistry, pharmacology, and flavonoid biosynthesis of Scutellaria baicalensis. Pharm Biol 56 (1): 465-484, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25819872">Lam W, Jiang Z, Guan F, et al.: PHY906(KD018), an adjuvant based on a 1800-year-old Chinese medicine, enhanced the anti-tumor activity of Sorafenib by changing the tumor microenvironment. Sci Rep 5: 9384, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="21713461">Li T, Li N, Guo Q, et al.: Inhibitory effects of wogonin on catalytic activity of cytochrome P450 enzyme in human liver microsomes. Eur J Drug Metab Pharmacokinet 36 (4): 249-56, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="26852865">Yu CP, Hsieh YC, Shia CS, et al.: Increased Systemic Exposure of Methotrexate by a Polyphenol-Rich Herb via Modulation on Efflux Transporters Multidrug Resistance-Associated Protein 2 and Breast Cancer Resistance Protein. J Pharm Sci 105 (1): 343-9, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="29679509">Wang T, Long F, Jiang G, et al.: Pharmacokinetic properties of wogonin and its herb-drug interactions with docetaxel in rats with mammary tumors. Biomed Chromatogr : e4264, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="11209989">Field HL, Monti DA, Greeson JM, et al.: St. John's Wort. Int J Psychiatry Med 30 (3): 203-19, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="22699020">Yang SY, Juang SH, Tsai SY, et al.: St. John's wort significantly increased the systemic exposure and toxicity of methotrexate in rats. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol 263 (1): 39-43, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="12189228">Mathijssen RH, Verweij J, de Bruijn P, et al.: Effects of St. John's wort on irinotecan metabolism. J Natl Cancer Inst 94 (16): 1247-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="15537555">Smith P, Bullock JM, Booker BM, et al.: The influence of St. John's wort on the pharmacokinetics and protein binding of imatinib mesylate. Pharmacotherapy 24 (11): 1508-14, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="15470331">Frye RF, Fitzgerald SM, Lagattuta TF, et al.: Effect of St John's wort on imatinib mesylate pharmacokinetics. Clin Pharmacol Ther 76 (4): 323-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="24068654">Goey AK, Meijerman I, Rosing H, et al.: The effect of St John's wort on the pharmacokinetics of docetaxel. Clin Pharmacokinet 53 (1): 103-10, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="18">IXEMPRA - ixabepilone. Bristol-Myers Squibb Company, 2009. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2009/022065s002lbl.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed May 26, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="27222828">Ziaei S, Halaby R: Immunosuppressive, anti-inflammatory and anti-cancer properties of triptolide: A mini review. Avicenna J Phytomed 6 (2): 149-64, 2016 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="27877128">Zhang C, Sun PP, Guo HT, et al.: Safety Profiles of Tripterygium wilfordii Hook F: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Front Pharmacol 7: 402, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="7628889">Chou WC, Wu CC, Yang PC, et al.: Hypovolemic shock and mortality after ingestion of Tripterygium wilfordii hook F.: a case report. Int J Cardiol 49 (2): 173-7, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="22">Adverse Drug Reaction Information Circular (no. 46) Focuses on the Drug Safety of Triptolide Preparations. National Medical Products Administration, 2012. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nmpa.gov.cn/xxgk/yjjsh/ypblfytb/20120401101301366.html">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed March 10, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="31780926">Ru Y, Luo Y, Zhou Y, et al.: Adverse Events Associated With Treatment of Tripterygium wilfordii Hook F: A Quantitative Evidence Synthesis. Front Pharmacol 10: 1250, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="31181731">Jin C, Wu Z, Wang L, et al.: CYP450s-Activity Relations of Celastrol to Interact with Triptolide Reveal the Reasons of Hepatotoxicity of Tripterygium wilfordii. Molecules 24 (11): , 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="25811791">Jin C, He X, Zhang F, et al.: Inhibitory mechanisms of celastrol on human liver cytochrome P450 1A2, 2C19, 2D6, 2E1 and 3A4. Xenobiotica 45 (7): 571-7, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="29283173">Xu Y, Zhang YF, Chen XY, et al.: CYP3A4 inducer and inhibitor strongly affect the pharmacokinetics of triptolide and its derivative in rats. Acta Pharmacol Sin 39 (8): 1386-1392, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="28614959">Wang X, Zhang X, Liu F, et al.: The effects of triptolide on the pharmacokinetics of sorafenib in rats and its potential mechanism. Pharm Biol 55 (1): 1863-1867, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><Title>Foods</Title><SummarySection id="_141"><Title>Grapefruit</Title><SummarySection id="_142"><Title>General information</Title><Para id="_143">Grapefruit and other similar fruits, such as Seville orange, pomelo, and lime, have been known to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interact</GlossaryTermRef> with a variety of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>, including some anticancer drugs. These <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetic</GlossaryTermRef> interactions may be caused by the furanocoumarin components found in the seeds of grapefruit. These components have been observed impacting the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> of substrates of CYP3A4.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_173"><Title>Laboratory/animal/preclinical studies</Title><Para id="_174">Grapefruit and its furanocoumarin components have been studied for their potential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidative</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anti-inflammatory</GlossaryTermRef>, and anticancer effects in <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> and <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> studies.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_144"><Title>Human/clinical studies</Title><Para id="_145">Some research has shown a dietary supplement/food and drug PK interaction between grapefruit juice and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044893" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imatinib</GlossaryTermRef>. Grapefruit juice may cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> levels of imatinib to increase by inhibiting CYP3A4, in turn triggering <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_146">An interaction has been observed between grapefruit juice and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">etoposide</GlossaryTermRef>. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797424" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">crossover</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045838" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pilot study</GlossaryTermRef> of six participants examined  the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689103" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> drug etoposide after coadministration of grapefruit juice. The data showed a decrease in bioavailability between the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control group</GlossaryTermRef> and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">experimental group</GlossaryTermRef>, who were treated with etoposide and grapefruit juice. The bioavailability of etoposide (50 mg <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">orally</GlossaryTermRef>) reduced  from approximately 73% to   52%  after pretreatment with grapefruit juice (100 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mL</GlossaryTermRef>). This resulted in a decrease in the area under the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentration</GlossaryTermRef> versus time curve (AUC) by 26% for etoposide with grapefruit juice, compared with   etoposide alone.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_147">Other studies have found an increase in the bioavailability of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468779" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sunitinib</GlossaryTermRef> with grapefruit juice exposure,<Reference refidx="7"/> and an increase in AUC by 29% and an increase in peak <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serum</GlossaryTermRef> concentration (C<Subscript>max</Subscript>) by 60% for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000575396" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nilotinib</GlossaryTermRef> (400 mg orally) was also observed when combined with grapefruit juice (240 mL).<Reference refidx="8"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_148"><Title>Green Tea</Title><SummarySection id="_149"><Title>General information</Title><Para id="_150">Green tea, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">green tea extract</GlossaryTermRef>, and products of green tea components are commonly taken as foods, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapies</GlossaryTermRef>. Some of the traditional and modern uses of green tea include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_151" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Preventing and treating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Lowering <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cholesterol</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Promoting weight loss.</ListItem><ListItem>Improving mental alertness.</ListItem><ListItem>Helping with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046446" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">digestive</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_152">Research has been mixed on whether green tea is safe or effective for these uses as well as for coadministration with anticancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="9"/> Current research shows that green tea and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256573" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyphenol</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687277" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epigallocatechin gallate</GlossaryTermRef> (EGCG), an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antioxidant</GlossaryTermRef> component of green tea, can impact the PK or pharmacodynamics (PD) of certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>, thus impacting the metabolism and effectiveness of these drugs.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_153"><Title>Laboratory/animal/preclinical studies</Title><Para id="_154">As seen in the literature, green tea and its constituent EGCG may be involved in both PK and PD interactions. An interaction between green tea and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bortezomib</GlossaryTermRef> was examined in an <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> study with human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045793" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">multiple myeloma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glioblastoma</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044016" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell lines</GlossaryTermRef>. EGCG blocked bortezomib’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045977" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protease inhibitory</GlossaryTermRef> function by binding to the boronic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acid</GlossaryTermRef> structure in bortezomib, causing the inability to induce cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cell</GlossaryTermRef> death and consequently blocking its anticancer abilities. The second portion of this study investigated this interaction within a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046231" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasmacytoma</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">xenograft</GlossaryTermRef> nude <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561606" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mouse model</GlossaryTermRef>. Bortezomib’s cancer cell <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">apoptosis</GlossaryTermRef>-inducing effect was completely prevented with intragastric EGCG <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef> (50 mg/kg).<Reference refidx="11"/> This interaction was also reported in another <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal study</GlossaryTermRef> that examined human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate cancer</GlossaryTermRef> xenografts in immune-deficient mouse models. High <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> of EGCG along with the coadministration of bortezomib resulted in the abrogation of bortezomib’s anticancer effects.<Reference refidx="12"/> Human studies should be conducted to determine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> significance. </Para><Para id="_155">The impact of green tea and EGCG on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluorouracil</GlossaryTermRef> PK was studied in rats. The results of these studies showed a 151% increase in C<Subscript>max</Subscript> and a 425% increase in AUC for fluorouracil. The researchers  concluded that green tea greatly impacted the PK of fluorouracil.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><Para id="_156">A similar study examined the PK of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635811" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">irinotecan</GlossaryTermRef> (10 mg/kg IV) given in combination with EGCG (20 mg/kg IV) in rats and found that  EGCG caused elevated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> levels and reduced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415544" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatobiliary</GlossaryTermRef> excretion of irinotecan and its <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolite</GlossaryTermRef> SN-38. This is possibly because of EGCG’s inhibitory effects on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643067" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">P-glycoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> (P-gp).<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_157">A 2019 study evaluated the effects of green tea extract on the PK of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000768872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palbociclib</GlossaryTermRef> in a rat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043996" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">animal model</GlossaryTermRef>. The data showed a decrease in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef> of palbociclib when it was coadministered with green tea extract, but there was no impact on the elimination of palbociclib. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">altered</GlossaryTermRef> PK was thought to be the result of interference in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">absorption</GlossaryTermRef> of palbociclib. The authors recommended against the coadministration of these <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_158">Research on rat animal models investigated the impact of green tea extract on the oral bioavailability of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">erlotinib</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000539453" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lapatinib</GlossaryTermRef>. A decrease in the oral bioavailability for erlotinib and lapatinib was observed after consumption of green tea extract (200 mg/kg). There was a decrease in AUC by 68% for erlotinib and 70% for lapatinib with short-term administration of green tea extract, and a decrease in AUC by 16% for erlotinib and 14% for lapatinib with long-term administration of green tea extract.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para><Para id="_159">An <Emphasis>in vivo</Emphasis> and <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> study examined the impacts of intragastric coadministration of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468779" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sunitinib</GlossaryTermRef> with EGCG. Coadministration of these two solutions resulted in the formation of a precipitate in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046604" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stomachs</GlossaryTermRef> of the mice, thus decreasing its bioavailability. It was  also reported that a decrease in the AUC and  C<Subscript>max</Subscript> of plasma sunitinib with EGCG administration in rats resulted in reduced sunitinib absorption.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_160">A possible interaction was also found between EGCG and tamoxifen. A 2009 study assessed the bioavailability and PK of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000509341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tamoxifen</GlossaryTermRef> (2 mg/kg) and its metabolite, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">4-hydroxytamoxifen</GlossaryTermRef>, with coadministration of EGCG (0.5 mg/kg, 3 mg/kg, and 10 mg/kg) in Sprague-Dawley rats. The coadministration of EGCG at doses of 3  mg/kg and 10 mg/kg caused a 49% to 78% increase  in the bioavailability of tamoxifen. In addition, EGCG significantly impacted the formation of 4-hydroxytamoxifen. It is believed that this reaction was caused by EGCG’s inhibitory effect on P-gp and CYP3A.<Reference refidx="18"/> However, a  subsequent study analyzed the effect of a green tea extract (1 g twice daily, 300 mg EGCG) on endoxifen (active metabolite of tamoxifen) levels. The study did not demonstrate a PK interaction between the green tea supplement and endoxifen levels.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para><Para id="_161">The findings of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">preclinical studies</GlossaryTermRef> provide a justification and motivation for human studies to determine appropriate clinical recommendations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_162"><Title>Case study</Title><Para id="_163">In addition to the <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> and <Emphasis>in vivo</Emphasis> EGCG and sunitinib study mentioned above, the same researchers published a case study that might demonstrate a possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effect</GlossaryTermRef> of green tea consumption with sunitinib treatment. A male patient with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000661352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> who received sunitinib  reported worsened symptoms of hyperemia and eye swelling near the site of a metastatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lesion</GlossaryTermRef> when drinking green tea; the symptoms improved when he stopped taking green tea. The authors hypothesized that the lack of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269453" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptom control</GlossaryTermRef> may result from EGCG’s effects on sunitinib’s anticancer abilities.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="27693910">Mouly S, Lloret-Linares C, Sellier PO, et al.: Is the clinical relevance of drug-food and drug-herb interactions limited to grapefruit juice and Saint-John's Wort? Pharmacol Res 118: 82-92, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="10511919">Singh BN: Effects of food on clinical pharmacokinetics. Clin Pharmacokinet 37 (3): 213-55, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="16685052">Paine MF, Widmer WW, Hart HL, et al.: A furanocoumarin-free grapefruit juice establishes furanocoumarins as the mediators of the grapefruit juice-felodipine interaction. Am J Clin Nutr 83 (5): 1097-105, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28911545">Hung WL, Suh JH, Wang Y: Chemistry and health effects of furanocoumarins in grapefruit. J Food Drug Anal 25 (1): 71-83, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="20701553">He SM, Yang AK, Li XT, et al.: Effects of herbal products on the metabolism and transport of anticancer agents. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol 6 (10): 1195-213, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12389073">Reif S, Nicolson MC, Bisset D, et al.: Effect of grapefruit juice intake on etoposide bioavailability. Eur J Clin Pharmacol 58 (7): 491-4, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="20512335">van Erp NP, Baker SD, Zandvliet AS, et al.: Marginal increase of sunitinib exposure by grapefruit juice. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 67 (3): 695-703, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="19948946">Yin OQ, Gallagher N, Li A, et al.: Effect of grapefruit juice on the pharmacokinetics of nilotinib in healthy participants. J Clin Pharmacol 50 (2): 188-94, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Sang S, Lambert JD, Ho C, et al.: Green tea polyphenols. In: Coates PM, Betz JM, Blackman MR, et al., eds.: Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2nd ed. Informa Healthcare, 2010, pp 402-10.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="23201840">Du GJ, Zhang Z, Wen XD, et al.: Epigallocatechin Gallate (EGCG) is the most effective cancer chemopreventive polyphenol in green tea. Nutrients 4 (11): 1679-91, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="19190249">Golden EB, Lam PY, Kardosh A, et al.: Green tea polyphenols block the anticancer effects of bortezomib and other boronic acid-based proteasome inhibitors. Blood 113 (23): 5927-37, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="21400028">Bannerman B, Xu L, Jones M, et al.: Preclinical evaluation of the antitumor activity of bortezomib in combination with vitamin C or with epigallocatechin gallate, a component of green tea. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 68 (5): 1145-54, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="21440026">Qiao J, Gu C, Shang W, et al.: Effect of green tea on pharmacokinetics of 5-fluorouracil in rats and pharmacodynamics in human cell lines in vitro. Food Chem Toxicol 49 (6): 1410-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="18579105">Lin LC, Wang MN, Tsai TH: Food-drug interaction of (-)-epigallocatechin-3-gallate on the pharmacokinetics of irinotecan and the metabolite SN-38. Chem Biol Interact 174 (3): 177-82, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="30549069">Paul D, Surendran S, Chandrakala P, et al.: An assessment of the impact of green tea extract on palbociclib pharmacokinetics using a validated UHPLC-QTOF-MS method. Biomed Chromatogr 33 (4): e4469, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="28260629">Maher HM, Alzoman NZ, Shehata SM, et al.: UPLC-ESI-MS/MS study of the effect of green tea extract on the oral bioavailability of erlotinib and lapatinib in rats: Potential risk of pharmacokinetic interaction. J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci 1049-1050: 30-40, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="21331509">Ge J, Tan BX, Chen Y, et al.: Interaction of green tea polyphenol epigallocatechin-3-gallate with sunitinib: potential risk of diminished sunitinib bioavailability. J Mol Med (Berl) 89 (6): 595-602, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="19491656">Shin SC, Choi JS: Effects of epigallocatechin gallate on the oral bioavailability and pharmacokinetics of tamoxifen and its main metabolite, 4-hydroxytamoxifen, in rats. Anticancer Drugs 20 (7): 584-8, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="32803636">Braal CL, Hussaarts KGAM, Seuren L, et al.: Influence of green tea consumption on endoxifen steady-state concentration in breast cancer patients treated with tamoxifen. Breast Cancer Res Treat 184 (1): 107-113, 2020.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><Title>Foods, Dietary Supplements, and Cancer Drug Interaction Tables</Title><Table id="_89"><Title> Table 1. Foods,  Dietary Supplements, and Cancer Drug Interactions</Title> <TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="30.92%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="15.69%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="24.01%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="29.35%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Herbal</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Dietary  Supplement      </GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639945" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Anticancer Therapy</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry Align="Center">Effect</entry><entry Align="Center">Study Type</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">AUC = area under the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentration</GlossaryTermRef> versus time curve; C<Subscript>max</Subscript> = peak <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serum</GlossaryTermRef> concentration; EGCG = epigallocatechin gallate; SJW = St. John's wort.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044957" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">SJW</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000635811" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Irinotecan</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Increased activity of CYP3A4 and decreased AUC of active <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolite</GlossaryTermRef> SN38</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="1"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>SJW</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044893" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Imatinib</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Increased clearance and decreased AUC of imatinib</entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>SJW</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045393" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Methotrexate</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Increased AUC and C<Subscript>max</Subscript> of methotrexate</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454774" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Animal study</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>SJW</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045382" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Docetaxel</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Increased clearance and decreased AUC of docetaxel</entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="4"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>SJW</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367463" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ixabepilone</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>May decrease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">plasma</GlossaryTermRef> concentrations of ixabepilone</entry><entry>Label warning for ixabepilone <Reference refidx="5"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Green tea</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468779" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Sunitinib</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Decreased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">absorption</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044225" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bioavailability</GlossaryTermRef> of sunitinib</entry><entry>Animal study and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case report</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="6"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Green tea</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000768872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Palbociclib</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Decreased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> bioavailability of palbociclib</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="7"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000389271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Green tea extract</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000508929" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Erlotinib</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Decreased AUC and oral bioavailability of erlotinib</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Green tea extract</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000539453" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lapatinib</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Decreased AUC and oral bioavailability of lapatinib</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000687277" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">EGCG</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000509341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tamoxifen</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of tamoxifen</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="9"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>EGCG</entry><entry>Irinotecan</entry><entry>Increased plasma concentration of irinotecan and decreased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415544" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatobiliary</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476338" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">excretion</GlossaryTermRef> of drug and its metabolite SN-38</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="10"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Green tea and EGCG</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fluorouracil</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Increased AUC and C<Subscript>max</Subscript> of fluorouracil</entry><entry>Animal and <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> study <Reference refidx="11"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Grapefruit</entry><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>May increase plasma levels of imatinib by inhibiting CYP3A4</entry><entry>Review <Reference refidx="12"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Grapefruit</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Etoposide</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Decreased AUC and bioavailability of etoposide</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Randomized</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797424" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">crossover</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045838" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pilot study</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="13"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Grapefruit</entry><entry>Sunitinib</entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of sunitinib</entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Grapefruit</entry><entry>Nilotinib</entry><entry>Increased AUC and C<Subscript>max</Subscript>  of nilotinib</entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="15"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045248" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin A</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of imatinib</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045023" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin E</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of imatinib</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000427252" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin D3</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of imatinib</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439435" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Vitamin C</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Decreased bioavailability of imatinib</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Scutellaria baicalensis</entry><entry>Docetaxel</entry><entry>Increased AUC of drug and exposure to both drug and herb</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="16"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_90"><Title>Table 2. Foods, Dietary Supplements, and Cancer Drug Interactions</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="24.63%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="24.45%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="32.66%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="18.24%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Anticancer Therapy </entry><entry Align="Center">Herbal/Dietary Supplement </entry><entry Align="Center">Effect </entry><entry Align="Center">Study Type </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">AUC = area under the concentration versus time curve; C<Subscript>max</Subscript> = peak serum concentration; EGCG = epigallocatechin gallate; SJW = St. John's wort.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry> Docetaxel</entry><entry>Scutellaria baicalensis </entry><entry>Increased AUC of drug and exposure to both drug and herb </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="16"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry>Docetaxel </entry><entry>SJW</entry><entry>Increased clearance and decrease AUC of docetaxel </entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="4"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Erlotinib</entry><entry>Green tea extract</entry><entry>Decreased AUC and oral bioavailability of erlotinib </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Etoposide </entry><entry>Grapefruit </entry><entry>Decreased AUC and bioavailability of etoposide </entry><entry>Randomized, crossover, pilot study <Reference refidx="13"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Fluorouracil</entry><entry>Green tea and EGCG</entry><entry>Increased AUC and C<Subscript>max</Subscript> of fluorouracil </entry><entry>Animal and <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> study <Reference refidx="11"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Grapefruit  </entry><entry>May increase plasma levels of imatinib by inhibiting CYP3A4 </entry><entry>Review <Reference refidx="12"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Vitamin A </entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of imatinib </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Vitamin E </entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of imatinib </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry>Imatinib </entry><entry>Vitamin D3 </entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of imatinib </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Vitamin C </entry><entry>Decreased bioavailability of imatinib </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>SJW</entry><entry>Increased clearance and decreased AUC of imatinib </entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="2"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Irinotecan </entry><entry>SJW </entry><entry>Increased activity of CYP3A4 and decreased AUC of active metabolite SN38 </entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="1"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Irinotecan </entry><entry>EGCG </entry><entry>Increased plasma concentration of irinotecan and decreased hepatobiliary excretion of drug and its metabolite SN-38 </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="10"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Ixabepilone </entry><entry>SJW </entry><entry>May decrease plasma concentrations of ixabepilone </entry><entry>Label warning for ixabepilone <Reference refidx="5"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Lapatinib </entry><entry>Green tea extract </entry><entry>Decreased AUC and oral bioavailability of lapatinib </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="8"/> </entry></Row><Row><entry>Methotrexate </entry><entry>SJW </entry><entry>Increased AUC and C<Subscript>max</Subscript> of methotrexate </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="3"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Nilotinib </entry><entry>Grapefruit </entry><entry>Increased AUC and C<Subscript>max</Subscript> of nilotinib </entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="15"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Palbociclib </entry><entry>Green tea </entry><entry>Decreased oral bioavailability of palbociclib </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="7"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Tamoxifen </entry><entry>EGCG </entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of tamoxifen </entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="9"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Sunitinib </entry><entry>Grapefruit </entry><entry>Increased bioavailability of sunitinib </entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="14"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Sunitinib </entry><entry>Green tea </entry><entry>Decreased drug absorption and bioavailability of sunitinib </entry><entry>Animal study and case report <Reference refidx="6"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><Table id="_91"><Title>Table 3.  Foods, Dietary Supplements, and Cancer Therapies Adverse Reaction</Title><TGroup Cols="4"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="25.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="30.91%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="19.08%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="25.00%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center">Herbal/Dietary Supplement</entry><entry Align="Center">Cancer Therapy</entry><entry Align="Center">Adverse Reaction</entry><entry Align="Center">Study Type</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col1">EGCG = epigallocatechin gallate.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry>Vitamin C</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000560140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Doxorubicin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045230" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cisplatin</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000615324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vincristine</GlossaryTermRef>, methotrexate, and imatinib</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Dose-dependent</GlossaryTermRef> decrease in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046524" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">apoptosis</GlossaryTermRef> with all <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044009" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapeutic drugs</GlossaryTermRef> tested</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="17"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Vitamin C</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Bortezomib</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Decreased bortezomib’s anticancer activities</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="18"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Dl-alpha-tocopherol (vitamin E)</entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Higher risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapse</GlossaryTermRef> and increased all-cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496502" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mortality</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Clinical trial <Reference refidx="19"/><Reference refidx="20"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044151" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ginseng</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>Imatinib</entry><entry>Incident of hepatotoxicity</entry><entry>Case report <Reference refidx="21"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>EGCG or green tea extract</entry><entry>Bortezomib</entry><entry>Decreased anticancer effect by neutralizing effects of bortezomib</entry><entry><Emphasis>In vitro</Emphasis> and animal study <Reference refidx="22"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>EGCG</entry><entry>Bortezomib</entry><entry>Decreased bortezomib’s anticancer effect</entry><entry>Animal study <Reference refidx="23"/></entry></Row><Row><entry>Green tea</entry><entry>Sunitinib</entry><entry>Decreased anticancer effect, worsened <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Preclinical research</GlossaryTermRef> and case report <Reference refidx="6"/></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12189228">Mathijssen RH, Verweij J, de Bruijn P, et al.: Effects of St. John's wort on irinotecan metabolism. J Natl Cancer Inst 94 (16): 1247-9, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15470331">Frye RF, Fitzgerald SM, Lagattuta TF, et al.: Effect of St John's wort on imatinib mesylate pharmacokinetics. Clin Pharmacol Ther 76 (4): 323-9, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="22699020">Yang SY, Juang SH, Tsai SY, et al.: St. John's wort significantly increased the systemic exposure and toxicity of methotrexate in rats. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol 263 (1): 39-43, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="30993543">Clairet AL, Boiteux-Jurain M, Curtit E, et al.: Interaction between phytotherapy and oral anticancer agents: prospective study and literature review. Med Oncol 36 (5): 45, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5">IXEMPRA - ixabepilone. Bristol-Myers Squibb Company, 2009. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2009/022065s002lbl.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed May 26, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="21331509">Ge J, Tan BX, Chen Y, et al.: Interaction of green tea polyphenol epigallocatechin-3-gallate with sunitinib: potential risk of diminished sunitinib bioavailability. J Mol Med (Berl) 89 (6): 595-602, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="30549069">Paul D, Surendran S, Chandrakala P, et al.: An assessment of the impact of green tea extract on palbociclib pharmacokinetics using a validated UHPLC-QTOF-MS method. Biomed Chromatogr 33 (4): e4469, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="30047806">Maher HM, Alzoman NZ, Shehata SM: Ultra-performance LC-MS/MS study of the pharmacokinetic interaction of imatinib with selected vitamin preparations in rats. Bioanalysis 10 (14): 1099-1113, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="19491656">Shin SC, Choi JS: Effects of epigallocatechin gallate on the oral bioavailability and pharmacokinetics of tamoxifen and its main metabolite, 4-hydroxytamoxifen, in rats. Anticancer Drugs 20 (7): 584-8, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="18579105">Lin LC, Wang MN, Tsai TH: Food-drug interaction of (-)-epigallocatechin-3-gallate on the pharmacokinetics of irinotecan and the metabolite SN-38. Chem Biol Interact 174 (3): 177-82, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="21440026">Qiao J, Gu C, Shang W, et al.: Effect of green tea on pharmacokinetics of 5-fluorouracil in rats and pharmacodynamics in human cell lines in vitro. Food Chem Toxicol 49 (6): 1410-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="20701553">He SM, Yang AK, Li XT, et al.: Effects of herbal products on the metabolism and transport of anticancer agents. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol 6 (10): 1195-213, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="12389073">Reif S, Nicolson MC, Bisset D, et al.: Effect of grapefruit juice intake on etoposide bioavailability. Eur J Clin Pharmacol 58 (7): 491-4, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="20512335">van Erp NP, Baker SD, Zandvliet AS, et al.: Marginal increase of sunitinib exposure by grapefruit juice. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 67 (3): 695-703, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="19948946">Yin OQ, Gallagher N, Li A, et al.: Effect of grapefruit juice on the pharmacokinetics of nilotinib in healthy participants. J Clin Pharmacol 50 (2): 188-94, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="29679509">Wang T, Long F, Jiang G, et al.: Pharmacokinetic properties of wogonin and its herb-drug interactions with docetaxel in rats with mammary tumors. Biomed Chromatogr : e4264, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="18829561">Heaney ML, Gardner JR, Karasavvas N, et al.: Vitamin C antagonizes the cytotoxic effects of antineoplastic drugs. Cancer Res 68 (19): 8031-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="19369963">Perrone G, Hideshima T, Ikeda H, et al.: Ascorbic acid inhibits antitumor activity of bortezomib in vivo. Leukemia 23 (9): 1679-86, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="16027437">Bairati I, Meyer F, Gélinas M, et al.: Randomized trial of antioxidant vitamins to prevent acute adverse effects of radiation therapy in head and neck cancer patients. J Clin Oncol 23 (24): 5805-13, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="16841333">Bairati I, Meyer F, Jobin E, et al.: Antioxidant vitamins supplementation and mortality: a randomized trial in head and neck cancer patients. Int J Cancer 119 (9): 2221-4, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="20332334">Bilgi N, Bell K, Ananthakrishnan AN, et al.: Imatinib and Panax ginseng: a potential interaction resulting in liver toxicity. Ann Pharmacother 44 (5): 926-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="19190249">Golden EB, Lam PY, Kardosh A, et al.: Green tea polyphenols block the anticancer effects of bortezomib and other boronic acid-based proteasome inhibitors. Blood 113 (23): 5927-37, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="21400028">Bannerman B, Xu L, Jones M, et al.: Preclinical evaluation of the antitumor activity of bortezomib in combination with vitamin C or with epigallocatechin gallate, a component of green tea. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol 68 (5): 1145-54, 2011.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_187"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Cancer Therapy Interactions With Foods and Dietary Supplements</Title><Para id="_188">To assist readers in evaluating the results of human studies of integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of
evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever
possible.  To qualify for a level of evidence <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef>, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_189" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Be published in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed scientific journal</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Report on a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Describe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> findings in sufficient detail that a meaningful evaluation can be made.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_190">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044724" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scientific</GlossaryTermRef> strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score. For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (04/05/2024)</Title><Para id="_6">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_199"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000799261#_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/dietary-interactions-pdq">General Information</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_200">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799261#_164" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/dietary-interactions-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that in the United States, dietary supplements are regulated by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) as a separate category from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. Unlike drugs, dietary supplements do not require premarket evaluation and approval by the FDA unless specific disease prevention or treatment claims are made. Also added text to state that the quality and amount of ingredients in dietary supplements are also regulated by the FDA through Good Manufacturing Practices (GMPs). The FDA GMPs requires that every finished batch of dietary supplement meets each product specification for identity, purity, strength, composition, and limits on contamination that may adulterate dietary supplements.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799261#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/dietary-interactions-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about cancer therapy interactions with foods and dietary supplements in people with cancer.. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Cancer Therapy Interactions With Foods and Dietary Supplements. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/dietary-interactions-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/dietary-interactions-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 33079503]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2020-10-14</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-04-05</DateLastModified></Summary>
