<Summary id="CDR0000799676" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma treatment options include surgery, chemotherapy, high-dose 131I-MIBG therapy, and targeted therapy. Learn more about the risk factors, symptoms, tests to diagnose, and treatment of childhood pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma in this expert-reviewed summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/pheochromocytoma/patient/child-pheochromocytoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/pheochromocytoma/hp/child-pheochromocytoma-treatment-pdq">Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039816">pheochromocytoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000639696">paraganglioma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood paraganglioma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood pheochromocytoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Pheochromocytoma &amp; Paraganglioma Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Pheochromocytoma &amp; Paraganglioma Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>General Information About Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma</Title><SummarySection id="_10"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_11">Pheochromocytoma forms in the adrenal gland.</KeyPoint><Para id="_12"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322877" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pheochromocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adrenal gland</GlossaryTermRef>. There are two adrenal glands, one on top of each <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidney</GlossaryTermRef> in the back of the upper <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>. Each adrenal gland has two parts. The outer layer of the adrenal gland is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458082" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adrenal cortex</GlossaryTermRef>. The center of the adrenal gland is the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458083" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adrenal medulla</GlossaryTermRef>. Pheochromocytoma is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> of the adrenal medulla.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000805084" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the adrenal gland; drawing of the abdomen showing the left and right adrenal glands, the left and right kidneys, and major blood vessels. Also shown is an inset of an adrenal gland showing the adrenal cortex and the adrenal medulla." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_114"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the adrenal gland. There are two adrenal glands, one on top of each kidney. The outer part of each gland is the adrenal cortex and the inner part is the adrenal medulla.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_71">The adrenal glands make important <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef>  called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catecholamines</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Adrenaline</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045404" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epinephrine</GlossaryTermRef>) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000479003" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">noradrenaline</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">norepinephrine</GlossaryTermRef>) are two types of catecholamines that help control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart rate</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000658770" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood sugar</GlossaryTermRef>, and the way the body reacts to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450122" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stress</GlossaryTermRef>. Some pheochromocytomas release extra adrenaline and noradrenaline into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> and cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><KeyPoint id="_14">Paraganglioma forms in nerve tissue  near the carotid artery, along nerve pathways in the head and neck, and in other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_15">Some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paragangliomas</GlossaryTermRef> make extra catecholamines called adrenaline and noradrenaline. The release of extra adrenaline and noradrenaline into the blood may cause symptoms.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000804042" type="image/jpeg" alt="Paraganglioma of the head and neck; drawing shows a cancerous tumor near the carotid artery in the head and neck." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_113"><Caption language="en">A paraganglioma is a rare tumor that often forms in nerve tissue near the carotid artery. It may also form along nerve pathways in the head and neck and in other parts of the body.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><KeyPoint id="_107">Pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma may be benign (not cancer) or malignant (cancer).</KeyPoint><Para id="_108">About half of all children with pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> 
pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma. This means that the tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> have spread to other parts of the body. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045614" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Benign</GlossaryTermRef> and malignant pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma require treatment because they can cause severe or life-threatening heart problems and affect many body functions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">Inheriting certain gene mutations (changes) increases the risk of pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_18">Anything that increases your chance of getting a disease is called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factor</GlossaryTermRef>. Having a risk factor does not mean that you will get <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>; not having risk factors doesn't mean that you will not get cancer. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_72">Having any of the following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">syndromes</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> changes increases risk of pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_73" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (tumors in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044554" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">parathyroid gland</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pituitary gland</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270855" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">islet cells</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>, and rarely, pheochromocytoma).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000702095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (pheochromocytoma, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medullary thyroid cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, and parathyroid gland disease).  </ListItem> 
		  <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000702100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2B syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (pheochromocytoma, medullary thyroid cancer, parathyroid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045956" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hyperplasia</GlossaryTermRef>, and other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">von Hippel-Lindau disease</GlossaryTermRef> (VHL) (pheochromocytoma, paraganglioma, hemangioblastoma, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444982" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clear cell</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000661352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000753531" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreatic neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, and other conditions).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045096" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Neurofibromatosis type 1</GlossaryTermRef> (NF1) (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurofibromas</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000387264" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">brain tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, pheochromocytoma, and other conditions). 
</ListItem> 
		   
		   
		<ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Carney-Stratakis dyad</GlossaryTermRef> (paraganglioma and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044998" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal stromal tumor</GlossaryTermRef> [GIST]).</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000648576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Carney triad</GlossaryTermRef> (paraganglioma, GIST, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045852" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pulmonary</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000799923" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chondroma</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem><ListItem>Familial pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_74">More than half of the children and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adolescents</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> with pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma have an inherited syndrome  or gene change that increases the risk of cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> (a discussion with a trained professional about inherited diseases) and testing is an important part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">treatment plan</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_20">Signs and symptoms of pheochromocytoma and  paraganglioma occur if  too much adrenaline or noradrenaline is released into the blood.</KeyPoint><Para id="_21">Some tumors do not make extra adrenaline or noradrenaline and do not cause symptoms. These tumors may be found when a lump forms in the neck or when a test is done for another reason. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Signs</GlossaryTermRef> and symptoms of pheochromocytoma and  paraganglioma occur when  too much adrenaline or noradrenaline is released into the blood.  These and other signs and symptoms may be caused by pheochromocytoma, paraganglioma, or other conditions.</Para><Para id="_109">Check with your child's doctor if your child has any of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_75" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">High blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Headache.</ListItem><ListItem>Heavy sweating for no known reason.</ListItem><ListItem>A strong, fast, or irregular heartbeat.</ListItem>
     <ListItem>Feeling shaky.</ListItem><ListItem>Being extremely pale.</ListItem><ListItem>Dizziness.</ListItem><ListItem>Being irritable or nervous.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_76">These signs and symptoms may come and go, but high blood pressure is more likely to occur for long periods of time in  young patients. These signs and symptoms may also occur with physical activity, injury, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046050" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anesthesia</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the tumor, eating foods such as chocolate and cheese, or while passing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef> (if the tumor is in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_77"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_78">Tests and procedures used to diagnose and stage pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma depend on the patient's signs and symptoms and family history.</KeyPoint><Para id="_79"> Tests are done to diagnose and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> cancer. After cancer is diagnosed, more tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread to nearby areas or to other parts of the body. This process is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_80">The following tests and procedures may be used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_81" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health history</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An exam of the body to check general signs of health, including checking for signs of disease, such as lumps or anything else that seems unusual. A history of the patient’s health habits and past illnesses and treatments will also be taken.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045839" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Plasma</GlossaryTermRef>-free metanephrines test</Strong>: A blood test that  measures the amount of metanephrines in the blood.    Metanephrines are substances that are made when the body breaks down adrenaline or noradrenaline. Pheochromocytomas and paragangliomas can make large amounts of adrenaline and noradrenaline and cause  high levels of metanephrines in both the blood and urine. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Blood catecholamine  studies</Strong>: A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amount of certain catecholamines (adrenaline or noradrenaline) released into the blood. Substances caused by the breakdown of these catecholamines are also measured. An unusual (unusual higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organ</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> that makes it. Higher than normal amounts may be a sign of pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Twenty-four-hour urine test</Strong>: A test in which urine is collected for 24 hours to measure the amounts of catecholamines (adrenaline or noradrenaline) or metanephrines in the urine. Substances caused by the breakdown of these catecholamines are also  measured. An unusual (higher than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease in the organ or tissue that makes it. Higher than normal amounts may be a sign of pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure to find malignant tumor cells in the body.  A small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive glucose</GlossaryTermRef> (sugar) is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef>.  The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef> is being used in the body.  Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775456" type="image/jpeg" alt="Positron emission tomography (PET) scan; drawing shows a child lying on table that slides through the PET scanner." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_102"><Caption language="en">Positron emission tomography (PET) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the PET scanner. The head rest and white strap help the child lie still.  A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into the child's vein, and a scanner makes a picture of where the glucose is being used in the body.  Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they take up more glucose than normal cells do. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles.  The pictures are made by a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.  This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_103"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).<MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_104"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000736798" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MIBG scan</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A procedure used to find  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044904" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroendocrine tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, such as pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma. A very small amount of a substance called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> MIBG is injected into a vein and travels through the bloodstream.  Neuroendocrine tumor cells take up the radioactive MIBG and are detected by a  scanner. Scans may be taken over 1-3 days. An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044548" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">iodine</GlossaryTermRef> solution may be given before or during the test to keep the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044751" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid gland</GlossaryTermRef> from absorbing too much of the MIBG.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390250" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Somatostatin receptor scintigraphy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046552" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radionuclide scan</GlossaryTermRef> that may be used to find tumors. A very small amount of radioactive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045141" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">octreotide</GlossaryTermRef> (a hormone that attaches to tumors) is injected into a vein and travels through the blood. The radioactive octreotide attaches to the tumor and a special camera that detects radioactivity is used to show where the tumors are in the body. This procedure is also called octreotide scan and SRS.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory test</GlossaryTermRef> in which cells or tissue are analyzed to look for changes in genes or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosomes</GlossaryTermRef>. These changes may be a sign that a person has or is at risk of having a specific disease or condition. The following are genes that might be tested for in children with pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma: <GeneName>VHL</GeneName>, <GeneName>NF1</GeneName>, <GeneName>RET</GeneName>, <GeneName>SDHD</GeneName>, <GeneName>SDHB</GeneName>, <GeneName>SDHA</GeneName>, <GeneName>MAX</GeneName>, and <GeneName>TMEM127</GeneName> genes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_82"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_83">Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.</KeyPoint><Para id="_84"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Prognosis</GlossaryTermRef> and treatment options depend on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_85" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurred</GlossaryTermRef> (come back).</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><Title>Stages of Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma</Title><SummarySection id="_26"><KeyPoint id="_27">After pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread to nearby areas or to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_28">The process used to find out if <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> has spread to nearby areas or to other parts of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046597" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging</GlossaryTermRef>. There is no standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging system</GlossaryTermRef> for childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322877" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pheochromocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paraganglioma</GlossaryTermRef>. The results of the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799676#_77" url="/types/pheochromocytoma/patient/child-pheochromocytoma-treatment-pdq">tests and procedures</SummaryRef> done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> cancer are used to help make decisions about treatment.</Para><Para id="_112">Sometimes childhood pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurs</GlossaryTermRef> (comes back) after treatment. It may come back in the place it first formed or in other parts of the body.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_29"><KeyPoint id="_30">There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_29_md_69">Cancer can spread through <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph system</GlossaryTermRef>, and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>:</Para><ItemizedList id="_29_md_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.
</ListItem><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000269462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> to other parts of the body.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><KeyPoint id="_33">Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.</KeyPoint><Para id="_32_md_66">When cancer spreads to another part of the body, it is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef>. Cancer cells break away from where they began (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>) and travel through the lymph system or blood.</Para><ItemizedList id="_32_md_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lymph system. The cancer gets into the lymph system, travels through the lymph vessels, and forms a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Blood. The cancer gets into the blood, travels through the blood vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_34">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is the same type of cancer as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. For example, if  pheochromocytoma spreads to the bone, the cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> in the bone are actually pheochromocytoma cells. The disease is metastatic pheochromocytoma, not <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000434562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone cancer</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><EmbeddedVideo id="_105" ref="CDR0000787719" hosting="youtube" unique_id="fQwar_-QdiQ" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>metastasis: how cancer spreads</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Many cancer deaths are caused when cancer moves from the original tumor and spreads to other tissues and organs. This is called metastatic cancer. This animation shows how cancer cells travel from the place in the body where they first formed to other parts of the body.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_36"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_37">There are different types of treatment for children with pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma.</KeyPoint><Para id="_36_md_79">Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.  A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the  standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment.</Para><Para id="_36_md_80">Because cancer in children is rare, taking part in a clinical trial should be considered.  Some clinical trials are open only to patients  who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_39"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_40">Children with pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma should have their treatment planned by a team of doctors who are experts in treating childhood cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_41">Treatment will be overseen by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>, a doctor who specializes in treating children with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The pediatric oncologist works with other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric</GlossaryTermRef> health professionals who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef>. This may include the following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">specialists</GlossaryTermRef> and others:</Para><ItemizedList id="_86" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pathologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046439" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endocrinologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Social worker</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem> <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Psychologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_43">Four types of standard treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_45"><KeyPoint id="_46">Surgery</KeyPoint><Para id="_47"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is the main treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322877" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pheochromocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paraganglioma</GlossaryTermRef>. For several days before surgery, your child may need to take <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef> medicine to lower the risk of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complications</GlossaryTermRef> during and after surgery.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_48"><KeyPoint id="_49">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_50"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> to stop the growth of cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef>, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_51"><KeyPoint id="_52">High-dose 131I-MIBG therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_53"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">131I-MIBG</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a treatment with high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045855" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive iodine</GlossaryTermRef>. The radioactive iodine is given through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intravenous</GlossaryTermRef> (IV) line and enters the bloodstream which carries <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> directly to tumor cells. Radioactive iodine collects in pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma cells and kills them with the radiation that is given off.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_54"><KeyPoint id="_55">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_56"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. Targeted therapies usually cause less harm to normal cells than chemotherapy or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> do.</Para><ItemizedList id="_87" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046739" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Angiogenesis inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef> drugs <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevent</GlossaryTermRef> the growth of new <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045020" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood vessels</GlossaryTermRef> needed for tumors to grow. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000468779" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Sunitinib</GlossaryTermRef> is an angiogenesis inhibitor used to treat pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_58">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_59">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_60"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_61">Treatment of pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma  may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_60_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><KeyPoint id="_89">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_88_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_88_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_88_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_90"><KeyPoint id="_91">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_90_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_90_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_92"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_93">Follow-up tests may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_92_md_55">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_92_md_56">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_110">For patients with pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma that causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537553" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catecholamine</GlossaryTermRef> levels in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef> will be checked on a regular basis. Catecholamine levels that are higher than normal can be a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sign</GlossaryTermRef> that the cancer has come back.
Talk to your child’s doctor about which tests should be done and how often.</Para><Para id="_111"> Patients with pheochromocytoma or paraganglioma need lifelong <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follow-up</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_63"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000039816">pheochromocytoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000639696">paraganglioma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma</Title><Para id="_94">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799676#_42" url="/types/pheochromocytoma/patient/child-pheochromocytoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_64">Treatment of newly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322877" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pheochromocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paraganglioma</GlossaryTermRef> in children may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_95" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Surgery</GlossaryTermRef> to completely remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045650" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Combination chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, high-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">131I-MIBG</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for tumors that have spread to other parts of the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_96">Before surgery, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651195" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alpha-blockers</GlossaryTermRef> to control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood pressure</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta-blockers</GlossaryTermRef> to control <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">heart rate</GlossaryTermRef> are given. If both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adrenal glands</GlossaryTermRef> are removed, life-long <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045110" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to replace  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef> made by the adrenal glands is needed after surgery.</Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_63_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_97"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040119">recurrent pheochromocytoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Recurrent Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma</Title><Para id="_101">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799676#_42" url="/types/pheochromocytoma/patient/child-pheochromocytoma-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef>  section.</Para><Para id="_98">Treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322877" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pheochromocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paraganglioma</GlossaryTermRef> may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_99" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> that checks a sample of the patient's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> changes. The type of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> that will be given to the patient depends on the type of gene change.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390341" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">131I-MIBG</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>A clinical trial of a new <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef>  (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000800168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">guadecitabine</GlossaryTermRef>).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_TrialSearch_97_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_69"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>To Learn More About Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma</Title><Para id="_70">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about childhood <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322877" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pheochromocytoma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390305" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">paraganglioma</GlossaryTermRef>, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_100" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/pheochromocytoma">Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Cancer Therapies</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_69_md_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_69_md_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Pheochromocytoma and Paraganglioma Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/pheochromocytoma/patient/child-pheochromocytoma-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/pheochromocytoma/patient/child-pheochromocytoma-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000800108"/><DateFirstPublished>2019-12-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2022-07-21</DateLastModified></Summary>
