<Summary id="CDR0000799767" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>This evidence-based, expert-reviewed summary discusses the clinical presentation, risk factors, histology, outcomes, and treatment of pediatric bladder cancer.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bladder/hp/child-bladder-treatment-pdq">Childhood Bladder Cancer (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038767">bladder cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1556">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of pediatric bladder cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_1557">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>pediatric bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Bladder Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Bladder Cancer Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Bladder Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_2209"><Title>Clinical Presentation and Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_2210">Urothelial bladder neoplasms are extremely rare in children. The most common presenting symptom of bladder cancer in children is hematuria.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Bladder tumors can present throughout the pediatric age range. In one small series, the mean age was 11.9 years (range, 4–19 years).<Reference refidx="3"/> In another study, patients were aged between 16 months and 19 years. Most of the bladder tumors occurred in males.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_2212">Bladder cancer in adolescents may develop as
a result of exposure to alkylating-agent chemotherapy that was given to treat other childhood tumors
or leukemia.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> The association between cyclophosphamide exposure and bladder
cancer is one of the only established relationships between a specific anticancer drug
and a solid tumor.<Reference refidx="9"/> An excess prevalence of bladder tumors has also been observed in survivors of specific cancer types (e.g., heritable retinoblastoma), supporting the concept that genetic factors contribute to the development of subsequent neoplasms.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="29221636">Saltsman JA, Malek MM, Reuter VE, et al.: Urothelial neoplasms in pediatric and young adult patients: A large single-center series. J Pediatr Surg 53 (2): 306-309, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="31326327">Rezaee ME, Dunaway CM, Baker ML, et al.: Urothelial cell carcinoma of the bladder in pediatric patients: a systematic review and data analysis of the world literature. J Pediatr Urol 15 (4): 309-314, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="35871900">Galiya R, Stanislav K, Jawdat J, et al.: Pediatric urothelial bladder neoplasm. J Pediatr Urol 18 (6): 833.e1-833.e4, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="35970356">Shumaker AD, Harel M, Gitlin J, et al.: Pediatric Bladder Tumors: A Ten-Year Retrospective Analysis. Urology 169: 185-190, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="25545665">Di Carlo D, Ferrari A, Perruccio K, et al.: Management and follow-up of urothelial neoplasms of the bladder in children: a report from the TREP project. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (6): 1000-3, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="18985721">Ritchey M, Ferrer F, Shearer P, et al.: Late effects on the urinary bladder in patients treated for cancer in childhood: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 52 (4): 439-46, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="7707439">Travis LB, Curtis RE, Glimelius B, et al.: Bladder and kidney cancer following cyclophosphamide therapy for non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. J Natl Cancer Inst 87 (7): 524-30, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="14752871">Kersun LS, Wimmer RS, Hoot AC, et al.: Secondary malignant neoplasms of the bladder after cyclophosphamide treatment for childhood acute lymphocytic leukemia. Pediatr Blood Cancer 42 (3): 289-91, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="9259084" MedlineID="97403759">Johansson SL, Cohen SM: Epidemiology and etiology of bladder cancer. Semin Surg Oncol 13 (5): 291-8, 1997 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20184574">Frobisher C, Gurung PM, Leiper A, et al.: Risk of bladder tumours after childhood cancer: the British Childhood Cancer Survivor Study. BJU Int 106 (7): 1060-9, 2010.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2213"><Title>Histology</Title><Para id="_2214">Histological classification of urothelial bladder neoplasms includes the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2305" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Urothelial papillomas.</ListItem><ListItem>Papillary neoplasms of low malignant potential.</ListItem><ListItem>Low-grade urothelial carcinomas.</ListItem><ListItem>High-grade urothelial carcinomas.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2320">An alternative designation is transitional cell carcinoma of the bladder. The most common
histology is papillary urothelial neoplasms of low malignant potential, while high-grade, invasive urothelial carcinomas are extremely rare in young patients.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20015324">Alanee S, Shukla AR: Bladder malignancies in children aged &lt;18 years: results from the Surveillance, Epidemiology and End Results database. BJU Int 106 (4): 557-60, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21169741">Paner GP, Zehnder P, Amin AM, et al.: Urothelial neoplasms of the urinary bladder occurring in young adult and pediatric patients: a comprehensive review of literature with implications for patient management. Adv Anat Pathol 18 (1): 79-89, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24079760">Stanton ML, Xiao L, Czerniak BA, et al.: Urothelial tumors of the urinary bladder in young patients: a clinicopathologic study of 59 cases. Arch Pathol Lab Med 137 (10): 1337-41, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25545665">Di Carlo D, Ferrari A, Perruccio K, et al.: Management and follow-up of urothelial neoplasms of the bladder in children: a report from the TREP project. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (6): 1000-3, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="25305695">Berrettini A, Castagnetti M, Salerno A, et al.: Bladder urothelial neoplasms in pediatric age: experience at three tertiary centers. J Pediatr Urol 11 (1): 26.e1-5, 2015.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_974"><Title>Treatment and Outcome of Childhood Bladder Cancer</Title><Para id="_2215">Treatment options for childhood bladder cancer include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_2216" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Surgery.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_975"> In contrast to adult bladder carcinomas, most pediatric tumors are low grade and superficial. Pediatric patients have an excellent prognosis after transurethral resection.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> In one review of the literature, recurrence risk and mortality rates were low in pediatric patients (8.6% and 3.7%, respectively).<Reference refidx="5"/> Most recurrences were observed within 9 months of treatment, and all recurrences occurred within 32 months of treatment. This finding  suggests that patients should be monitored for at least 3 years. </Para><Para id="_2340">Squamous cell carcinomas and more aggressive carcinomas have been reported in children and may require a more aggressive surgical approach.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/>    </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="16217372">Fine SW, Humphrey PA, Dehner LP, et al.: Urothelial neoplasms in patients 20 years or younger: a clinicopathological analysis using the world health organization 2004 bladder consensus classification. J Urol 174 (5): 1976-80, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21169741">Paner GP, Zehnder P, Amin AM, et al.: Urothelial neoplasms of the urinary bladder occurring in young adult and pediatric patients: a comprehensive review of literature with implications for patient management. Adv Anat Pathol 18 (1): 79-89, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24079760">Stanton ML, Xiao L, Czerniak BA, et al.: Urothelial tumors of the urinary bladder in young patients: a clinicopathologic study of 59 cases. Arch Pathol Lab Med 137 (10): 1337-41, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25305695">Berrettini A, Castagnetti M, Salerno A, et al.: Bladder urothelial neoplasms in pediatric age: experience at three tertiary centers. J Pediatr Urol 11 (1): 26.e1-5, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31326327">Rezaee ME, Dunaway CM, Baker ML, et al.: Urothelial cell carcinoma of the bladder in pediatric patients: a systematic review and data analysis of the world literature. J Pediatr Urol 15 (4): 309-314, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11101751">Sung JD, Koyle MA: Squamous cell carcinoma of the bladder in a pediatric patient. J Pediatr Surg 35 (12): 1838-9, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="15266415">Lezama-del Valle P, Jerkins GR, Rao BN, et al.: Aggressive bladder carcinoma in a child. Pediatr Blood Cancer 43 (3): 285-8, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="22105002">Korrect GS, Minevich EA, Sivan B: High-grade transitional cell carcinoma of the pediatric bladder. J Pediatr Urol 8 (3): e36-8, 2012.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1965"><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation for Childhood Bladder Cancer</Title><Para id="_1966">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2461"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Unusual Cancers Special Considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Special Considerations for the Treatment of Children With Cancer</Title>

<Para id="_2461_md_3">Cancer in children and adolescents is rare, although the overall incidence has slowly increased since 1975.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Children and adolescents with cancer should be referred to medical centers that have a multidisciplinary team of cancer specialists with experience treating the cancers that occur during childhood and adolescence.  This multidisciplinary team approach incorporates the skills
of the following pediatric specialists and others to ensure that children receive treatment, supportive care, and rehabilitation
to achieve optimal survival and quality of life:</Para>
        <ItemizedList id="_2461_md_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Primary care physicians.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric surgeons.</ListItem><ListItem>Pathologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric radiation
oncologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric medical oncologists and hematologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Ophthalmologists.</ListItem><ListItem> Rehabilitation
specialists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric oncology nurses.</ListItem><ListItem>Social workers.</ListItem><ListItem>Child-life professionals.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Nutritionists.</ListItem></ItemizedList>
 <Para id="_2461_md_5">For specific information about supportive care for children and adolescents with cancer, see the summaries on <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/supportive-care">Supportive and Palliative Care</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_2461_md_6">The American Academy of Pediatrics has outlined guidelines for
pediatric cancer centers and their role in the treatment of children and adolescents
with cancer.<Reference refidx="2"/>  At
these centers, clinical trials are available for most  types of cancer that occur in children and adolescents, and the opportunity
to participate is offered to most patients and their families.  Clinical
trials for children and adolescents diagnosed with cancer are generally
designed to compare potentially better therapy with current standard therapy. Other types of clinical trials test novel therapies when there is no standard therapy for a cancer diagnosis.  Most of the progress in identifying curative
therapies for childhood cancers has been achieved through clinical trials. 
Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_2461_md_7">Dramatic improvements in survival have been achieved for children and adolescents with cancer. Between 1975 and 2020, childhood cancer mortality decreased by more than 50%.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  Childhood and adolescent cancer survivors require close monitoring because side effects of cancer therapy may persist or develop months or years after treatment.  For information about the incidence, type, and monitoring of late effects in childhood and adolescent cancer survivors, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000343584" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-hp-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para>
<Para id="_2461_md_8">Childhood cancer is a rare disease, with about 15,000 cases diagnosed annually in the United States in individuals younger than 20 years.<Reference refidx="6"/> The U.S. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.congress.gov/107/plaws/publ280/PLAW-107publ280.pdf">Rare Diseases Act of 2002</ExternalRef> defines a rare disease as one that affects populations smaller than 200,000 people in the United States. Therefore, all pediatric cancers are considered rare.</Para><Para id="_2461_md_9">The designation of a rare tumor is not uniform among pediatric and adult groups. In adults, rare cancers are defined as those with an annual incidence of fewer than six cases per 100,000 people. They account for up to 24% of all cancers diagnosed in the European Union and about 20% of all cancers diagnosed in the United States.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> In children and adolescents, the designation of a rare tumor is not uniform among international groups, as follows:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2461_md_10" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A consensus effort between the European Union Joint Action on Rare Cancers and the European Cooperative Study Group for Rare Pediatric Cancers estimated that 11% of all cancers in patients younger than 20 years could be categorized as very rare. This consensus group defined very rare cancers as those with annual incidences of fewer than two cases per 1 million people. However, three additional histologies (thyroid carcinoma, melanoma, and testicular cancer) with incidences of more than two cases per 1 million people were also included  in the very rare group due to a lack of knowledge and expertise in the management of these tumors.<Reference refidx="9"/></ListItem><ListItem>The Children's Oncology Group defines rare pediatric cancers as those listed in the International Classification of Childhood Cancer subgroup XI, which includes thyroid cancers, melanomas and nonmelanoma skin cancers, and multiple types of carcinomas (e.g., adrenocortical carcinomas, nasopharyngeal carcinomas, and most adult-type carcinomas such as breast cancers and colorectal cancers).<Reference refidx="10"/>  These diagnoses account for about 5% of the cancers diagnosed in children aged 0 to 14 years and about 27% of the cancers diagnosed in adolescents aged 15 to 19 years.<Reference refidx="4"/><Para id="_11"> Most cancers in subgroup XI are either melanomas or thyroid cancers, with other cancer types accounting for only 2% of the cancers diagnosed in children aged 0 to 14 years and 9.3% of the cancers diagnosed in adolescents aged 15 to 19 years.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2461_md_12">These rare cancers are extremely challenging to study because of the relatively few patients with any individual diagnosis, the predominance of rare cancers in the adolescent population, and the small number of clinical trials for adolescents with rare cancers.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20404250">Smith MA, Seibel NL, Altekruse SF, et al.: Outcomes for children and adolescents with cancer: challenges for the twenty-first century. J Clin Oncol 28 (15): 2625-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2">American Academy of Pediatrics: Standards for pediatric cancer centers. Pediatrics  134 (2): 410-4, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/134/2/410">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24853691">Smith MA, Altekruse SF, Adamson PC, et al.: Declining childhood and adolescent cancer mortality. Cancer 120 (16): 2497-506, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4">National Cancer Institute: NCCR*Explorer: An interactive website for NCCR cancer statistics. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://NCCRExplorer.ccdi.cancer.gov/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Surveillance Research Program, National Cancer Institute: SEER*Explorer: An interactive website for SEER cancer statistics. 	Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statistics-network/explorer/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed December 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="24488779">Ward E, DeSantis C, Robbins A, et al.: Childhood and adolescent cancer statistics, 2014. CA Cancer J Clin 64 (2): 83-103, 2014 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28687376">Gatta G, Capocaccia R, Botta L, et al.: Burden and centralised treatment in Europe of rare tumours: results of RARECAREnet-a population-based study. Lancet Oncol 18 (8): 1022-1039, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28542893">DeSantis CE, Kramer JL, Jemal A: The burden of rare cancers in the United States. CA Cancer J Clin 67 (4): 261-272, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="30785015">Ferrari A, Brecht IB, Gatta G, et al.: Defining and listing very rare cancers of paediatric age: consensus of the Joint Action on Rare Cancers in cooperation with the European Cooperative Study Group for Pediatric Rare Tumors. Eur J Cancer 110: 120-126, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20956621">Pappo AS, Krailo M, Chen Z, et al.: Infrequent tumor initiative of the Children's Oncology Group: initial lessons learned and their impact on future plans. J Clin Oncol 28 (33): 5011-6, 2010.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2321"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (09/05/2024)</Title><Para id="_2322">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_2462">This summary was comprehensively reviewed.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799767#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/bladder/hp/child-bladder-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of pediatric bladder cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Childhood Bladder Cancer Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Denise Adams, MD (Children's Hospital Boston)</ListItem><ListItem>Karen J. Marcus, MD, FACR (Dana-Farber of Boston Children's Cancer Center and Blood Disorders Harvard Medical School)</ListItem><ListItem>William H. Meyer, MD</ListItem><ListItem>Paul A. Meyers, MD (Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Thomas A. Olson, MD (Aflac Cancer and Blood Disorders Center of Children's Healthcare of Atlanta - Egleston Campus)</ListItem><ListItem>Alberto S. Pappo, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Arthur Kim Ritchey, MD (Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC)</ListItem><ListItem>Carlos Rodriguez-Galindo, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Stephen J. Shochat, MD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Bladder Cancer Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bladder/hp/child-bladder-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/bladder/hp/child-bladder-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 31846271]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2019-12-12</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-09-05</DateLastModified></Summary>
