<Summary id="CDR0000799748" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Expert-reviewed information summary about the treatment of childhood carcinoma of unknown primary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary/patient/child-unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary/hp/child-unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000040456">carcinoma of unknown primary</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood carcinoma of unknown primary. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood carcinoma of unknown primary</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Treatment (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>General Information About Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><SummarySection id="_7"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_8">Carcinoma of unknown primary is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells are found in the body but the place the cancer began is not known.</KeyPoint><Para id="_9"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cancer</GlossaryTermRef> can form in any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> in the body. The first cancer to form is called the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The process of cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> spreading to other parts of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046710" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastasis</GlossaryTermRef>.  The cancer that has spread to another part of the body is called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> cancer.</Para><Para id="_80">In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> (CUP), metastatic cancer is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef>, but the primary cancer has not been found.</Para><Para id="_22">This type of cancer is also called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">occult primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000804045" type="image/jpeg" alt="Cancer of unknown primary; drawing shows a primary tumor that has spread from an unknown site to other parts of the body (the lung and the brain). An inset shows cancer cells spreading from the primary cancer, through the blood and lymph systems, to another part of the body where a metastatic tumor has formed." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_87"><Caption language="en">In cancer of unknown primary, cancer cells have spread in the body but the place where the primary cancer began is not known.</Caption></MediaLink><EmbeddedVideo id="_88" ref="CDR0000787719" hosting="youtube" unique_id="fQwar_-QdiQ" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>metastasis: how cancer spreads</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Many cancer deaths are caused when cancer moves from the original tumor and spreads to other tissues and organs. This is called metastatic cancer. This animation shows how cancer cells travel from the place in the body where they first formed to other parts of the body.</Caption></EmbeddedVideo></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_14">The signs and symptoms of disease are caused by the metastatic cancer and depend on where the cancer has spread.</KeyPoint><Para id="_81">The primary cancer does not cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> of disease.</Para><Para id="_15"> Check with your doctor if you have any of the following general signs of cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_24" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Lump or thickening in any part of the body.</ListItem><ListItem>Pain that is in one part of the body and does not go away.</ListItem><ListItem>A cough that does not go away or hoarseness in the voice.</ListItem><ListItem>Change in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046500" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bowel</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> habits, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">constipation</GlossaryTermRef>,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000306496" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diarrhea</GlossaryTermRef>, or frequent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urination</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Unusual bleeding or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000443583" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">discharge</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fever</GlossaryTermRef> for no known reason that does not go away.</ListItem><ListItem>Drenching night sweats.</ListItem><ListItem>Weight loss for no known reason or loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_82"><KeyPoint id="_83">Blood and imaging tests are done to learn more about the cause of the signs and symptoms.</KeyPoint><Para id="_84"><SummaryRef href="CDR0000799748#_31" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/child-unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Tests and procedures</SummaryRef> that may be used are described below.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_17">A biopsy is done to diagnose metastatic cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_26">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> is the removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef> by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_28">One of the following types of biopsies may be used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_27" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045691" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Fine-needle aspiration (FNA) biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of tissue or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044669" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluid</GlossaryTermRef> using a thin needle. 
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045657" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Core biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of tissue using a wide needle.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046698" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Incisional biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of part of a lump or a sample of tissue.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046411" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Excisional biopsy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: The removal of an entire lump of tissue.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_85">The pathologist views the tissue to look for cancer cells and to find out the type of cancer. Cancer cells usually look like the cells in the type of tissue in which the cancer began. In CUP, the cancer cells do not look like  the cells of the tissue they were found in.  The pathologist cannot determine the type of primary cancer.</Para><Para id="_29">One or more of the following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046590" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory tests</GlossaryTermRef> may be used to further study the tissue samples:</Para><ItemizedList id="_30" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386202" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic analysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test in which the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> in a sample of cancer cells or tissue is studied to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutations</GlossaryTermRef> (changes) that may help predict the best treatment for CUP.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Histologic</GlossaryTermRef> study</Strong>: A laboratory test in which stains are added to a sample of cancer cells or tissue and viewed under a microscope to look for certain changes in the cells. Certain changes in the cells are linked to certain types of cancer.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000653117" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Immunohistochemistry</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef>) in a sample of a patient’s tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer.  
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783668" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction</GlossaryTermRef> (RT–PCR) test</Strong>: A laboratory test in which the amount of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> substance called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000662001" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mRNA</GlossaryTermRef> made by a specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is measured. An enzyme called reverse transcriptase is used to convert a specific piece of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046568" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">RNA</GlossaryTermRef> into a matching piece of DNA, which can be amplified (made in large numbers) by another enzyme called DNA polymerase. The amplified DNA copies help tell whether a specific mRNA is being made by a gene. RT–PCR can be used to check the activation of certain genes that may indicate the presence of cancer cells. This test may be used to look for certain changes in a gene or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef>, which may help diagnose cancer.
</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Cytogenetic analysis</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test in which the chromosomes of cells in a sample of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> tissue are counted and checked for any changes, such as broken, missing, rearranged, or extra chromosomes. Changes in certain chromosomes may be a sign of cancer. Cytogenetic analysis is used to help diagnose cancer, plan treatment, or find out how well treatment is working. Changes in certain chromosomes are linked to certain types of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044052" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Light</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044025" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electron microscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: A laboratory test in which cells in a sample of tissue are viewed under regular and high-powered microscopes to look for certain changes in the cells.
</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_32">Because the place where the cancer started is not known, more tests and procedures are done to search for the primary cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_33">The following tests and procedures may be done:</Para><ItemizedList id="_34" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Physical exam</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000798522" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">health history</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: An exam of the body to check general signs of health, including checking for signs of disease, such as lumps or anything else that seems unusual. A history of the patient’s health habits and past illnesses and treatments will also be taken.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> (CAT scan)</Strong>: A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>, taken from different angles. The pictures are made by a computer linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> machine. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dye</GlossaryTermRef> may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or swallowed to help the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">organs</GlossaryTermRef> or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> (magnetic resonance imaging)</Strong>: A procedure that uses a magnet, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radio waves</GlossaryTermRef>, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046140" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PET scan</GlossaryTermRef> (positron emission tomography scan)</Strong>: A procedure to find <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignant</GlossaryTermRef> tumor cells in the body. A small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774386" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive glucose</GlossaryTermRef> (sugar) is injected into a vein. The PET <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386220" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scanner</GlossaryTermRef> rotates around the body and makes a picture of where <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glucose</GlossaryTermRef> is being used in the body. Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046157" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ultrasound</GlossaryTermRef> exam</Strong>: A procedure in which high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) are bounced off internal tissues or organs and make echoes.  The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>. The picture can be printed to be looked at later.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Endoscopy</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  A procedure to look at organs and tissues inside the body to check for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> areas.  An <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046428" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endoscope</GlossaryTermRef> is inserted through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046353" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incision</GlossaryTermRef> (cut) in the skin or opening in the body, such as the mouth.  An endoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572035" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lens</GlossaryTermRef> for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of disease. For example, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045648" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colonoscopy</GlossaryTermRef> may be done.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000732562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumor marker test</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>:  A procedure in which a sample of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270735" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef>, or tissue is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances made by organs, tissues, or tumor cells in the body. Certain substances are linked to specific types of cancer when found in increased levels in the body. These are called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor markers</GlossaryTermRef>. The blood may be checked for the levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046490" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CA-125</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000721308" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CgA</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046208" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alpha-fetoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> (AFP), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354453" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta human chorionic gonadotropin</GlossaryTermRef> (beta-hCG), or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046540" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate-specific antigen (PSA)</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><KeyPoint id="_20">When tests are able to find the primary cancer, the cancer is no longer a CUP and treatment is based on the type of primary cancer.</KeyPoint><Para id="_35">When it is not known where the cancer first formed at diagnosis, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046216" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adenocarcinomas</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045135" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">melanomas</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367442" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">embryonal tumors</GlossaryTermRef> (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045872" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rhabdomyosarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>) are tumor types that are often diagnosed later in children and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adolescents</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><KeyPoint id="_11">Sometimes the primary cancer is never found.</KeyPoint><Para id="_12">The primary cancer (the cancer that first formed) may not be found for one of the following reasons:
</Para><ItemizedList id="_23" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The primary cancer is very small and grows slowly.</ListItem><ListItem>The body’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> killed the primary cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>The primary cancer was removed during <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef> for another <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef> and doctors didn’t know cancer had formed. For example, in adults, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef> with cancer may be removed during a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045718" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hysterectomy</GlossaryTermRef> to treat a serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_86">Because the primary cancer is unknown, it may be harder to choose the best treatment.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><Title>Stages of Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><Para id="_37">The extent or spread of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> is usually described as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stages</GlossaryTermRef>. The stage of the cancer is usually used to plan treatment. However, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> (CUP) has already spread to other parts of the body when it is found. There is no standard <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging system</GlossaryTermRef> for CUP.</Para><Para id="_89">Sometimes childhood carcinoma of unknown primary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046556" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurs</GlossaryTermRef> (comes back) after treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><Title>Treatment Option Overview</Title><SummarySection id="_39"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_40">There are different types of treatment for children with carcinoma of unknown primary.</KeyPoint><Para id="_39_md_79">Some treatments are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard</GlossaryTermRef> (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.  A treatment clinical trial is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research study</GlossaryTermRef> meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the  standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment.</Para><Para id="_39_md_80">Because cancer in children is rare, taking part in a clinical trial should be considered.  Some clinical trials are open only to patients  who have not started treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_41"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_42">Children with carcinoma of unknown primary should have their treatment planned by a team of doctors who are experts in treating childhood cancer. </KeyPoint><Para id="_43">Treatment will be overseen by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000693555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>, a doctor who specializes in treating children with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. The pediatric oncologist works with other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046245" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric</GlossaryTermRef> health professionals who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef>. This may include the following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">specialists</GlossaryTermRef> and others:</Para><ItemizedList id="_44" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pathologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Social worker</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Psychologist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_46">Three types of standard treatment are used:</KeyPoint><SummarySection id="_47"><KeyPoint id="_48">Radiation therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_49"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045944" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-rays</GlossaryTermRef> or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> or keep them from growing. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046686" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">External radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><KeyPoint id="_51">Chemotherapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_52"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> is a cancer treatment that uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef> to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476471" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vein</GlossaryTermRef> or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000301626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><KeyPoint id="_54">Targeted therapy</KeyPoint><Para id="_55"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef>
is a treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack cancer cells.Targeted therapies usually cause less harm to normal cells than chemotherapy and radiation therapy do.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_56"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Treatment in clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_57">New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.</KeyPoint><Para id="_58">Information about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_59"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_60">Treatment for childhood carcinoma of unknown primary may cause side effects.</KeyPoint><Para id="_59_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><KeyPoint id="_62">Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.</KeyPoint><Para id="_61_md_23">For some patients, taking part in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef> may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer  treatments are safe and effective or better than the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_61_md_24">Many of today's standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first  to receive a new treatment.</Para><Para id="_61_md_25">Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_63"><KeyPoint id="_64">Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.</KeyPoint><Para id="_63_md_29">Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> of cancer treatment.</Para><Para id="_63_md_30">Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials supported by NCI can be found on NCI’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trials search</ExternalRef> webpage. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_65"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><KeyPoint id="_66">Follow-up tests may be needed.</KeyPoint><Para id="_65_md_55">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some tests that were done to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnose</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_65_md_56">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040456">carcinoma of unknown primary</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><Para id="_69">Treatment of newly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosed</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef> (CUP) in children depends on the following: </Para><ItemizedList id="_70" Style="bullet"><ListItem>What the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> look like under a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000638184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">microscope</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The child's age.</ListItem><ListItem>The child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000750109" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">signs</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The results of tests and procedures.</ListItem><ListItem>Where the cancer has spread in the body.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_68">For information about the treatments listed below, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000799748#_45" url="/types/unknown-primary/patient/child-unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">Treatment Option Overview</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_71">Treatment of newly diagnosed CUP in children may include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_72" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_93">Sometimes childhood carcinoma of unknown primary can recur (come back) after treatment. If your child is diagnosed with a recurrent carcinoma of unknown primary, your child's doctor will work with you to plan treatment. </Para><Para id="_TrialSearch_67_19">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are accepting patients. You can search for trials based on the type of cancer, the age of the patient, and where the trials are being done. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef>  about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_77"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Resources</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>To Learn More About Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</Title><Para id="_78">For more information from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044266" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">National Cancer Institute</GlossaryTermRef> about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527198" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">carcinoma of unknown primary</GlossaryTermRef>, see the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_79" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary">Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Cancer Therapies</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_77_md_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_77_md_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of childhood carcinoma of unknown primary.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Carcinoma of Unknown Primary Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary/patient/child-unknown-primary-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/unknown-primary/patient/child-unknown-primary-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><PatientVersionOf ref="CDR0000800113"/><DateFirstPublished>2019-12-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-01-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
