<Summary id="CDR0000802835" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Genetics of Gastric Cancer includes the hereditary cancer syndromes hereditary diffuse gastric cancer, familial adenomatous polyposis, Lynch syndrome, and other genes. Get comprehensive information on these syndromes in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Gastric Cancer (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039821">gastric cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1337">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of gastric cancers. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_1338">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>gastric cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Genetics of Gastric Cancer (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Genetics of Gastric Cancer (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Genetics of Gastric Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1340"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_1341">Gastric cancer is one of the most commonly diagnosed cancers in the world, with an incidence of over 1 million cases and an estimated 769,000 deaths occurring in 2020. Globally, this cancer ranked fifth for cancer incidence and fourth for cancer mortality in 2020.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> In 2025, there will be an estimated 30,300 new cases of gastric cancer and 10,780 deaths from gastric cancer in the United States.<Reference refidx="3"/> In clinic-based populations, approximately 15% to 20% of patients with gastric cancer are found to have<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional"> pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in hereditary cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_3800">The genes that can predispose individuals to hereditary diffuse gastric cancer (HDGC) include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_3801" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GeneName><SummaryRef href="CDR0000812188#_3761" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hereditary-diffuse-gastric-cancer-hp-pdq">CDH1</SummaryRef></GeneName>.</ListItem><ListItem><GeneName><SummaryRef href="CDR0000812188#_3762" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hereditary-diffuse-gastric-cancer-hp-pdq">CTNNA1</SummaryRef></GeneName>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3812">HDGC is the most common hereditary cancer syndrome that can predispose individuals to gastric cancer. This disease does not have an easily detectable precursor lesion. For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000812188" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hereditary-diffuse-gastric-cancer-hp-pdq">Hereditary Diffuse Gastric Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_3802">There are also hereditary cancer syndromes that can cause other forms of gastric cancer.  These syndromes include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_3803" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Lynch syndrome:</Strong> Lynch syndrome is caused by pathogenic variants  in <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName>. The amount of gastric cancer risk associated with Lynch syndrome and the role of gastric cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> remain unknown, especially since  a Lynch syndrome–associated gastric cancer precursor has not yet been identified.<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Familial</GlossaryTermRef> adenomatous polyposis (FAP)/gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS):</Strong> FAP/GAPPS are caused by pathogenic variants  in <GeneName>APC</GeneName>. Gastric cancer is typically preceded by fundic gland polyps.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Peutz-Jeghers syndrome (PJS):</Strong> PJS is caused by pathogenic variants in <GeneName>STK11</GeneName>. Gastric cancer is typically preceded by hamartomatous polyps.<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Juvenile polyposis syndrome (JPS):</Strong> JPS is caused by pathogenic variants in <GeneName>SMAD4</GeneName> and <GeneName>BMPR1A</GeneName>. Gastric cancer is typically preceded by hamartomatous polyps.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3813">In each of these syndromes, gastric polyps and gastric cancer risk are of secondary importance to colorectal polyps and colorectal cancer. Gastric polyp burden (including polyp count and size) and gastric cancer risk may vary between individuals.</Para><Para id="_3809">For more information on these genetic syndromes, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_3792" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_1342"><Title>Gastric Cancer Risk Factors</Title><SummarySection id="_1462"><Title>Environmental risk factors</Title><Para id="_1458">Incidence rates for gastric cancer are the highest in Eastern Asia and Eastern Europe, while the rates in Northern America, Northern Europe, and Africa are generally low.<Reference refidx="2"/> These regional differences are most likely affected by environmental and hereditary risk factors.</Para><Para id="_1465">Environmental risk factors for gastric cancer include the following:</Para><Para id="_1468">1. <Strong><Emphasis>Helicobacter pylori</Emphasis> (<Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis>) infection</Strong>.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1474" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>This may be most the impactful environmental risk factor for gastric cancer. </ListItem><ListItem>An <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> infection may cause histological changes in the stomach, which can begin with chronic, active gastritis and can progress to gastric atrophy, intestinal metaplasia, gastric dysplasia, and eventually gastric cancer.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem><ListItem>The combination of <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> and germline pathogenic variants in homologous recombination genes (<GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>) increases the risk of gastric cancer in an additive manner. A study of 38,153 controls and 10,426 gastric cancer cases in Japan found that germline pathogenic variants in nine genes (<GeneName>APC</GeneName>, <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, and <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>) were associated with increased gastric cancer risk.<Reference refidx="11"/> The relative risk (RR) of gastric cancer in those with <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> and a pathogenic variant in one of four homologous recombination genes  was 16.01 (confidence interval, 2.22–29.8). Risk persisted after adjusting for environmental risk factors like smoking, obesity, and salt intake. There was no increased risk in those who had <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> and a pathogenic variant  in a mismatch repair gene. The authors noted that results primarily pertain to the Japanese population, since gastric cancer and <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> incidence rates are much higher in East Asian populations than in Western populations.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1469">2. <Strong>Diet</Strong>.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1475" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The regional variation in gastric cancer incidence is influenced by diet.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem><ListItem>Gastric cancer risk may increase when individuals consume foods that are preserved with salt.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></ListItem><ListItem>Low fruit intake and the consumption of a large amount of processed, grilled, or barbequed meats/fish may also increase gastric cancer risk.<Reference refidx="13"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1478">3. <Strong>Migrant effects</Strong>.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1477" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Gastric cancer risk may also be affected by migrant effects (i.e., effects incurred when individuals migrate from a region with high gastric cancer risk to a region with low gastric cancer risk or vice versa). </ListItem><ListItem>Studies have demonstrated that the incidence of gastric cancer in immigrants correlates closely with the incidence of gastric cancer in their new host country after one or two generations.<Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>

 </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1470">4. <Strong>Tobacco use</Strong>.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_1471">5. <Strong>Alcohol use</Strong>.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_1472">6. <Strong>Emerging evidence for obesity and gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD)</Strong>.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1476" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Emerging evidence suggests an association between increased gastric cancer risk, excess body weight, and tissue damage associated with GERD.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1479">7. <Strong>Racial and ethnic disparities</Strong>.</Para><ItemizedList id="_1480" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>There are striking racial and ethnic disparities associated with gastric cancer incidence in the United States.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/></ListItem><ListItem>Studies that examine genetic and nongenetic risk factors, such as social determinants of health, are needed to understand and reduce the disparities in gastric cancer incidence that are seen in different racial and ethnic minority groups.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1460">Intensive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> may be clinically warranted in individuals with hereditary, environmental, or ethnicity-based gastric cancer risk factors. However, more data are needed to show whether these risk factors increase or decrease gastric cancer risk in individuals with hereditary gastric cancer pathogenic variants. For more information about risk factors for gastric cancer in the general population, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062757" url="/types/stomach/hp/stomach-screening-pdq">Stomach (Gastric) Cancer Screening</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1463"><Title>Familial risk factors</Title><Para id="_1481">Individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family histories</GlossaryTermRef> of gastric cancer have an increased risk of developing gastric cancer.<Reference refidx="26"/> For example, when individuals had a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460150" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">first-degree relative</GlossaryTermRef> with gastric cancer, their RRs to develop gastric cancer ranged from 1.5-fold to 3.5-fold in seven different studies.<Reference refidx="27"/><Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/><Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/><Reference refidx="32"/><Reference refidx="33"/> However, these were retrospective studies, and risk estimates may have been confounded by recall bias (i.e., recalling cancers in relatives), shared environmental factors, shared dietary factors, and different countries that studies were conducted in. The most notable environmental/dietary risk factor was <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> infection. When an individual has an  <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> infection, other people in this individual's  family also have an increased chance of developing an <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> infection. Smaller cohort studies have suggested the presence of a residual heritable risk for gastric cancer after correcting for the presence of <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis>. Most of these studies did not account for hereditary gastric cancer pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="34"/> A large retrospective review of Japanese individuals (both with and without gastric cancer) found a strong, additive risk for gastric cancer in individuals  with <Emphasis>H. pylori </Emphasis>infection, especially in those with <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, or <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="11"/> A Scandinavian study demonstrated that the concordance value for gastric cancer was higher in monozygotic twins than it was in dizygotic twins. This suggests that gastric cancer risk may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781848" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heritable</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="35"/>
</Para><Para id="_1482">Families with multiple gastric cancer cases have also been used to study the heritability of gastric cancer. A report in 1964 described a large, native Maori family from New Zealand.<Reference refidx="36"/> Then, in the late 1990s, another study established genetic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460161" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">linkage</GlossaryTermRef> between <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName>, a gene that codes for a cell-adhesion molecule, and gastric cancer cases from the original Maori family (identified in 1964) and two additional Maori families. In this study, researchers found that <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> was downregulated in Maori individuals with advanced gastric cancer.<Reference refidx="36"/><Reference refidx="37"/><Reference refidx="38"/><Reference refidx="39"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> pathogenic variants were first found in affected individuals in these Maori families, and later in families around the world with hereditary diffuse gastric cancer. Subsequently, female lobular breast cancer and orofacial clefts were added to the phenotypic spectrum of <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="40"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1344"><Title>Precancerous Lesions</Title><Para id="_3752">In the stomach, gastric adenocarcinoma can arise from visible lesions, from the histological progression of mucosal atrophy or, less commonly, from invisible lesions (i.e., submucosal infiltration, as seen in diffuse-type gastric adenocarcinoma).  This section reviews both gastric polyps and the histological changes associated with chronic gastritis that can predispose an individual to gastric cancer. </Para><SummarySection id="_3753"><Title>Gastric polyps</Title><Para id="_3754">Gastric polyps are common in the U.S. population and are found in up to 6% of individuals who undergo endoscopy. However, these polyps rarely progress to become gastric cancer.<Reference refidx="41"/> When gastric polyps are isolated, they usually are sporadic in nature.  However, gastric polyps can also be associated with hereditary cancer syndromes, particularly the hamartomatous and polyposis syndromes. Gastric polyps can present with the following pathologies:</Para><ItemizedList id="_3755" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Adenomatous.</ListItem><ListItem>Hyperplastic.</ListItem><ListItem>Inflammatory.</ListItem><ListItem>Hamartomatous (associated with PJS, JPS, and <GeneName>PTEN</GeneName> hamartoma tumor syndromes  [PHTS]).</ListItem><ListItem>Fundic gland.<Reference refidx="42"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><Para id="_3756">In general, the malignant potential of a polyp is determined by the polyp’s histology, size, and degree of dysplasia, if present. Adenomatous and hyperplastic polyps have the highest malignant potentials, especially when <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> is present. In contrast, fundic gland polyps (with or without dysplasia) rarely progress to become gastric cancer, even in individuals who have FAP.<Reference refidx="43"/></Para><Para id="_3757">Fundic gland polyps of the stomach are common and typically associated with long-term proton pump inhibitor (PPI) use.<Reference refidx="44"/> Fundic glands polyps generally do not increase gastric cancer risk because these polyps are not neoplastic in nature. However, GAPPS is an exception to this rule. In GAPPS, gastric cancer risk is strongly correlated with fundic gland polyposis. For more information about GAPPS and FAP, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Colorectal Cancer</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000814294" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gapps-hp-pdq">Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_3758">Inflammatory and hyperplastic polyps can present with many different pathological features. Unlike the colon, in which hyperplastic polyps carry little or no cancer risk, hyperplastic polyps of the stomach can enlarge and develop dysplastic foci.<Reference refidx="45"/> These types of polyps are not clearly associated with known hereditary gastric cancer syndromes.</Para><Para id="_3810">Hamartomatous polyps are seen in the stomachs of patients with PJS, JPS, and PHTS. For more information on these hereditary cancer syndromes, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Genetics of Colorectal Cancer</SummaryRef>. Hamartomatous polyps are typically not dysplastic in nature. However, they can develop dysplastic foci. Consequently, these polyps can be associated with an increased gastric cancer risk, especially in individuals with hereditary gastric cancer syndromes. It is unclear if hamartomatous gastric polyps eventually become gastric cancer or if they are merely indicative of  a high-risk environment in the stomach. The risk of gastric cancer is estimated by the hereditary cancer syndrome.</Para><Para id="_3768">Gastric adenomas make up approximately 10% of all gastric polyps. A gastric adenoma’s malignant potential is determined by its histological subtype and size.<Reference refidx="46"/> For example, pyloric gland adenomas and intestinal-type gastric adenomas have the highest malignant potentials, while foveolar-type gastric adenomas have the lowest malignant potential.<Reference refidx="47"/><Reference refidx="48"/></Para><SummarySection id="_3760"><Title>Chronic gastritis</Title><Para id="_3761">Chronic gastritis, a histological diagnosis defined by the presence of a mononuclear cellular infiltrate in the lamina propria of the stomach, occurs due to environmental exposures or autoimmune gastritis. Chronic gastritis can lead to gastric intestinal metaplasia. <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> is the most common risk factor for intestinal metaplasia. Other risk factors for intestinal metaplasia include pernicious anemia, autoimmune gastritis, ethnicity, a family history of gastric cancer, dietary habits, smoking, and alcohol use.<Reference refidx="49"/> After the development of chronic gastritis, the gastric mucosa may undergo a series of progressive changes, known as Correa’s cascade, which can eventually result in gastric cancer.  </Para><Para id="_3811">The steps of Correa's cascade include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_3762" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Chronic gastritis (most commonly caused by <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis>).</ListItem><ListItem>Gastric mucosal atrophy. </ListItem><ListItem>Gastric intestinal metaplasia.</ListItem><ListItem>Gastric dysplasia (low-grade dysplasia followed by high-grade dysplasia).<Reference refidx="50"/><Reference refidx="51"/></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_3763">Although these histological changes are associated with increased gastric cancer risk in the general population, the prevalence of findings and associated cancer risk in hereditary cancer syndromes is unknown. Each step in Correa's cascade only occurs in  a minority of patients. There is considerable controversy regarding appropriate  surveillance in patients with intestinal metaplasia.<Reference refidx="52"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3764"><Title>Endoscopic assessment</Title><Para id="_3765">Gastric cancer screening is not routinely performed in the United States, where gastric cancer incidence is relatively low. Gastric cancer screening is also not usually performed in individuals with  family histories of gastric cancer in which a hereditary gastric cancer pathogenic variant has not been identified. Large, prospective multicenter studies are needed to determine if gastric cancer screening programs would improve mortality in individuals from the United States with family histories of gastric cancer. In the United States, gastric cancer surveillance guidelines only exist for individuals with  pathogenic variants in <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> or other gastric cancer risk genes (for more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_3792" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="53"/><Reference refidx="54"/> The International Gastric Cancer Linkage Consortium recommends that individuals with family histories of diffuse gastric cancer without identifiable genetic causes (this is known as HDGC-like syndrome) participate in gastric cancer surveillance.<Reference refidx="55"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000812188#_1341" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hereditary-diffuse-gastric-cancer-hp-pdq">Definition and Management of Hereditary Diffuse Gastric Cancer (HDGC)–Like Families</SummaryRef> section in Hereditary Diffuse Gastric Cancer.</Para><Para id="_3766">When evaluating any patient with hereditary gastric cancer risk, endoscopy includes assessment for gastric polyps and <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis>—despite a lack of evidence demonstrating that <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis>  increases gastric cancer risk in the setting of all hereditary cancer syndromes.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><Para id="_3767">A small focus of intestinal metaplasia in the antrum is shown below. Intestinal metaplasia is not always visible on endoscopy. Instead, it is often found when taking random biopsies of the stomach.<Reference refidx="49"/> Emerging research has identified measures to improve endoscopic detection of such foci. Populations with high gastric intestinal metaplasia and gastric dysplasia prevalence rates have high incidence rates of gastric cancer.<Reference refidx="49"/><MediaLink ref="CDR0000812832" type="image/jpeg" alt="Endoscopic image showing a small area of intestinal metaplasia (circled in yellow) in the antrum of the stomach." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_3778"><Caption language="en">Endoscopic image showing a small area of intestinal metaplasia (circled in yellow) in the antrum of the stomach.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="29395269">Allemani C, Matsuda T, Di Carlo V, et al.: Global surveillance of trends in cancer survival 2000-14 (CONCORD-3): analysis of individual records for 37 513 025 patients diagnosed with one of 18 cancers from 322 population-based registries in 71 countries. Lancet 391 (10125): 1023-1075, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="33538338">Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, et al.: Global Cancer Statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN Estimates of Incidence and Mortality Worldwide for 36 Cancers in 185 Countries. CA Cancer J Clin 71 (3): 209-249, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3">American Cancer Society: Cancer Facts and Figures 2025. American Cancer Society, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2025/2025-cancer-facts-and-figures-acs.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 16, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="35122589">Uson PLS, Kunze KL, Golafshar MA, et al.: Germline Cancer Testing in Unselected Patients with Gastric and Esophageal Cancers: A Multi-center Prospective Study. Dig Dis Sci 67 (11): 5107-5115, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="34251444">Ku GY, Kemel Y, Maron SB, et al.: Prevalence of Germline Alterations on Targeted Tumor-Normal Sequencing of Esophagogastric Cancer. JAMA Netw Open 4 (7): e2114753, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="28754778">Møller P, Seppälä TT, Bernstein I, et al.: Cancer risk and survival in path_MMR carriers by gene and gender up to 75 years of age: a report from the Prospective Lynch Syndrome Database. Gut 67 (7): 1306-1316, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="10980114">Abraham SC, Nobukawa B, Giardiello FM, et al.: Fundic gland polyps in familial adenomatous polyposis: neoplasms with frequent somatic adenomatous polyposis coli gene alterations. Am J Pathol 157 (3): 747-54, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="11113065" MedlineID="20565550">Giardiello FM, Brensinger JD, Tersmette AC, et al.: Very high risk of cancer in familial Peutz-Jeghers syndrome. Gastroenterology 119 (6): 1447-53, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="49653">Correa P, Haenszel W, Cuello C, et al.: A model for gastric cancer epidemiology. Lancet 2 (7924): 58-60, 1975.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="28456631">Hooi JKY, Lai WY, Ng WK, et al.: Global Prevalence of Helicobacter pylori Infection: Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Gastroenterology 153 (2): 420-429, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="36988593">Usui Y, Taniyama Y, Endo M, et al.: Helicobacter pylori, Homologous-Recombination Genes, and Gastric Cancer. N Engl J Med 388 (13): 1181-1190, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="17577615">Tsugane S, Sasazuki S: Diet and the risk of gastric cancer: review of epidemiological evidence. Gastric Cancer 10 (2): 75-83, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="35695929">Liu SJ, Huang PD, Xu JM, et al.: Diet and gastric cancer risk: an umbrella review of systematic reviews and meta-analyses of prospective cohort studies. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol 148 (8): 1855-1868, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="35798837">Song Y, Liu X, Cheng W, et al.: The global, regional and national burden of stomach cancer and its attributable risk factors from 1990 to 2019. Sci Rep 12 (1): 11542, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="3468285">Shimizu H, Mack TM, Ross RK, et al.: Cancer of the gastrointestinal tract among Japanese and white immigrants in Los Angeles County. J Natl Cancer Inst 78 (2): 223-8, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="19892547">Mousavi SM, Brandt A, Weires M, et al.: Cancer incidence among Iranian immigrants in Sweden and Iranian residents compared to the native Swedish population. Eur J Cancer 46 (3): 599-605, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="17242674">Lee J, Demissie K, Lu SE, et al.: Cancer incidence among Korean-American immigrants in the United States and native Koreans in South Korea. Cancer Control 14 (1): 78-85, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="35565732">Bouras E, Tsilidis KK, Triggi M, et al.: Diet and Risk of Gastric Cancer: An Umbrella Review. Nutrients 14 (9): , 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="35804824">Poly TN, Lin MC, Syed-Abdul S, et al.: Proton Pump Inhibitor Use and Risk of Gastric Cancer: Current Evidence from Epidemiological Studies and Critical Appraisal. Cancers (Basel) 14 (13): , 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="32771406">Shah SC, McKinley M, Gupta S, et al.: Population-Based Analysis of Differences in Gastric Cancer Incidence Among Races and Ethnicities in Individuals Age 50 Years and Older. Gastroenterology 159 (5): 1705-1714.e2, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="29361173">Anderson WF, Rabkin CS, Turner N, et al.: The Changing Face of Noncardia Gastric Cancer Incidence Among US Non-Hispanic Whites. J Natl Cancer Inst 110 (6): 608-615, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="29902641">Islami F, DeSantis CE, Jemal A: Incidence Trends of Esophageal and Gastric Cancer Subtypes by Race, Ethnicity, and Age in the United States, 1997-2014. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 17 (3): 429-439, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="31420363">Holowatyj AN, Ulrich CM, Lewis MA: Racial/Ethnic Patterns of Young-Onset Noncardia Gastric Cancer. Cancer Prev Res (Phila) 12 (11): 771-780, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="29691758">De B, Rhome R, Jairam V, et al.: Gastric adenocarcinoma in young adult patients: patterns of care and survival in the United States. Gastric Cancer 21 (6): 889-899, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="30267713">Gupta S, Tao L, Murphy JD, et al.: Race/Ethnicity-, Socioeconomic Status-, and Anatomic Subsite-Specific Risks for Gastric Cancer. Gastroenterology 156 (1): 59-62.e4, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="17406355">Hemminki K, Sundquist J, Ji J: Familial risk for gastric carcinoma: an updated study from Sweden. Br J Cancer 96 (8): 1272-7, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="19888225">Yaghoobi M, Bijarchi R, Narod SA: Family history and the risk of gastric cancer. Br J Cancer 102 (2): 237-42, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="10443951">Lissowska J, Groves FD, Sobin LH, et al.: Family history and risk of stomach cancer in Warsaw, Poland. Eur J Cancer Prev 8 (3): 223-7, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="11454685">Palli D, Russo A, Ottini L, et al.: Red meat, family history, and increased risk of gastric cancer with microsatellite instability. Cancer Res 61 (14): 5415-9, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="11391635">Dhillon PK, Farrow DC, Vaughan TL, et al.: Family history of cancer and risk of esophageal and gastric cancers in the United States. Int J Cancer 93 (1): 148-52, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="14529588">Minami Y, Tateno H: Associations between cigarette smoking and the risk of four leading cancers in Miyagi Prefecture, Japan: a multi-site case-control study. Cancer Sci 94 (6): 540-7, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="16762526">Eto K, Ohyama S, Yamaguchi T, et al.: Familial clustering in subgroups of gastric cancer stratified by histology, age group and location. Eur J Surg Oncol 32 (7): 743-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="15233662">Chen MJ, Wu DC, Ko YC, et al.: Personal history and family history as a predictor of gastric cardiac adenocarcinoma risk: a case-control study in Taiwan. Am J Gastroenterol 99 (7): 1250-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="15280918">Yatsuya H, Toyoshima H, Tamakoshi A, et al.: Individual and joint impact of family history and Helicobacter pylori infection on the risk of stomach cancer: a nested case-control study. Br J Cancer 91 (5): 929-34, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="35" PMID="10891514" MedlineID="20331418">Lichtenstein P, Holm NV, Verkasalo PK, et al.: Environmental and heritable factors in the causation of cancer--analyses of cohorts of twins from Sweden, Denmark, and Finland. N Engl J Med 343 (2): 78-85, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="36" PMID="14158754">JONES EG: FAMILIAL GASTRIC CANCER. N Z Med J 63: 287-96, 1964.</Citation><Citation idx="37" PMID="9537325">Guilford P, Hopkins J, Harraway J, et al.: E-cadherin germline mutations in familial gastric cancer. Nature 392 (6674): 402-5, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="38" PMID="10477433">Guilford PJ, Hopkins JB, Grady WM, et al.: E-cadherin germline mutations define an inherited cancer syndrome dominated by diffuse gastric cancer. Hum Mutat 14 (3): 249-55, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="39" PMID="22225527">Corso G, Marrelli D, Pascale V, et al.: Frequency of CDH1 germline mutations in gastric carcinoma coming from high- and low-risk areas: metanalysis and systematic review of the literature. BMC Cancer 12: 8, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="40" PMID="15235021">Brooks-Wilson AR, Kaurah P, Suriano G, et al.: Germline E-cadherin mutations in hereditary diffuse gastric cancer: assessment of 42 new families and review of genetic screening criteria. J Med Genet 41 (7): 508-17, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="41" PMID="19491866">Carmack SW, Genta RM, Schuler CM, et al.: The current spectrum of gastric polyps: a 1-year national study of over 120,000 patients. Am J Gastroenterol 104 (6): 1524-32, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="42" PMID="33179620">Gullo I, Grillo F, Mastracci L, et al.: Precancerous lesions of the stomach, gastric cancer and hereditary gastric cancer syndromes. Pathologica 112 (3): 166-185, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="43" PMID="28185118">Mankaney G, Leone P, Cruise M, et al.: Gastric cancer in FAP: a concerning rise in incidence. Fam Cancer 16 (3): 371-376, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="44" PMID="27634363">Martin FC, Chenevix-Trench G, Yeomans ND: Systematic review with meta-analysis: fundic gland polyps and proton pump inhibitors. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 44 (9): 915-925, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="45" PMID="19037727">Jain R, Chetty R: Gastric hyperplastic polyps: a review. Dig Dis Sci 54 (9): 1839-46, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="46" PMID="7859674">Stolte M, Sticht T, Eidt S, et al.: Frequency, location, and age and sex distribution of various types of gastric polyp. Endoscopy 26 (8): 659-65, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="47" PMID="12920223">Abraham SC, Park SJ, Lee JH, et al.: Genetic alterations in gastric adenomas of intestinal and foveolar phenotypes. Mod Pathol 16 (8): 786-95, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="48" PMID="18830123">Chen ZM, Scudiere JR, Abraham SC, et al.: Pyloric gland adenoma: an entity distinct from gastric foveolar type adenoma. Am J Surg Pathol 33 (2): 186-93, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="49" PMID="31816301">Altayar O, Davitkov P, Shah SC, et al.: AGA Technical Review on Gastric Intestinal Metaplasia-Epidemiology and Risk Factors. Gastroenterology 158 (3): 732-744.e16, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="50" PMID="1458460" MedlineID="93092113">Correa P: Human gastric carcinogenesis: a multistep and multifactorial process--First American Cancer Society Award Lecture on Cancer Epidemiology and Prevention. Cancer Res 52 (24): 6735-40, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="51" PMID="23774773">Neumann WL, Coss E, Rugge M, et al.: Autoimmune atrophic gastritis--pathogenesis, pathology and management. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol 10 (9): 529-41, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="52" PMID="31926996">Dinis-Ribeiro M, Kuipers EJ: How to Manage a Patient With Gastric Intestinal Metaplasia: An International Perspective. Gastroenterology 158 (6): 1534-1537, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="53">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Colorectal. Version 1.2023. Plymouth Meeting, PA: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_colon.pdf">Available with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed June 28, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="54">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic. Version 3.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_bop.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed October 17, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="55" PMID="32758476">Blair VR, McLeod M, Carneiro F, et al.: Hereditary diffuse gastric cancer: updated clinical practice guidelines. Lancet Oncol 21 (8): e386-e397, 2020.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3769"><Title>Genetic Evaluation in Individuals With Personal and/or Family Histories of Gastric Cancer</Title><Para id="_3770">Approximately 15% to 20% of gastric cancers may be caused by hereditary gastric cancer syndromes.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> When providers suspect that an individual has a hereditary gastric cancer syndrome, it is recommended that they obtain a detailed, three-generation <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family history</GlossaryTermRef> and perform genetic testing, if appropriate. The collection of a detailed personal and family history is integral for gastric cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460214" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">risk assessment</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_3779">The following items are important to elicit when collecting a patient's family history:</Para><ItemizedList id="_3783" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Number of relatives with cancers on the same side of the family. </ListItem><ListItem>Types of cancers seen in family members (including each cancer's histological subtype).<Superscript>a</Superscript></ListItem><ListItem>Ages of family members when they were diagnosed with cancer.</ListItem><ListItem>Family members' gastrointestinal polyp histories (including each polyp's histological subtype).</ListItem><ListItem>Number of family members with cleft lip or cleft palate (cleft lip or cleft palate has been linked to <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName>-associated hereditary gastric cancer).<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3794"><Superscript>a</Superscript><Note>It is recommended that family history analysis focus on gastric cancer and other cancers (such as lobular breast cancer) that may be associated with hereditary diffuse gastric cancer (HDGC).</Note></Para><Para id="_3795">For information on collecting a family history, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865#_162" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Documenting the family history</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling. </Para><Para id="_3780">In busy clinical settings, it might not be feasible to obtain a complete family history.<Reference refidx="5"/> Studies have found that people   often have incomplete or inaccurate information about the cancers that occurred in their relatives.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  Furthermore, patients often over- or under-report the number of individuals in their families who have had gastric cancer.</Para><Para id="_3796">Many factors can contribute to inaccurate reporting of a gastric cancer family history. In medicine, the stomach has a distinct definition and anatomical location in the body. The public's definition of the stomach is more ambiguous, which could lead to reporting inaccuracies.<Reference refidx="7"/> There are multiple organs inside the abdominal cavity that patients could confuse with the stomach. Studies have demonstrated that many patients do not know where organs are located in the body.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_3798">The poor validity of self-reported gastric cancer family histories needs to be considered during a patient’s genetic evaluation and when creating an individual's clinical management recommendations. Studies have assessed the accuracy of self-reported family histories by comparing collected information with confirmation sources like death certificates, cancer registries, and histopathological records.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="11"/> One retrospective study from the United Kingdom compared 595 clinical notes   to confirmation sources. This study found increased error when patients reported malignancies located in the abdominal cavity.<Reference refidx="7"/> A systematic review found that only 22% to 67% of reported stomach cancer diagnoses were verified by confirmation sources.<Reference refidx="11"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865#_340" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Accuracy of the family history</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling.</Para><Para id="_3781">Obtaining   pathological documentation of personal/family histories of cancer and polyps is also integral when assessing a patient’s hereditary gastric cancer risk. This documentation is especially important because genetic testing criteria has shifted over the years and has, in turn, broadened clinical criteria.<Reference refidx="12"/> It is important to obtain pathology reports from patients to confirm the histological subtypes of cancers when possible. Signet   ring cell carcinoma, diffuse gastric cancer, and poorly differentiated carcinoma pathologies are characteristic of hereditary gastric cancer syndromes, particularly <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName>-associated HDGC. These histologies are commonly associated with linitis plastica (i.e., diffusely infiltrated, non-distensible stomach). Multiple gastrointestinal polyps (e.g., tubular adenomas, hamartomas) are associated with other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">hereditary cancer syndromes,</GlossaryTermRef> such as Peutz-Jeghers syndrome, juvenile polyposis syndrome,  familial adenomatous polyposis   (FAP)/gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS).<Reference refidx="13"/> Fundic gland polyps are one of the most common findings on routine upper endoscopies.   While these fundic gland polyps are a characteristic finding in individuals with FAP, they are also found often in individuals in the general population who take proton pump inhibitors. Hence,  fundic gland polyps are not usually indicative of an underlying hereditary cancer syndrome.   For more information about the cellular classification of gastric cancers, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062911" url="/types/stomach/hp/stomach-treatment-pdq">Gastric Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_3782">The diagnosis of cancers before age 50 years is a hallmark feature of hereditary cancer syndromes. Attenuated forms of hereditary cancer syndromes also exist  and are increasingly recognized. In these attenuated syndromes, the ages of gastric cancer onset can occur after age 50 years.<Reference refidx="14"/></Para><SummarySection id="_3771"><Title>Genetic Testing Approach</Title><Para id="_3784">Patients who develop gastric cancer usually present at an advanced stage.<Reference refidx="15"/> This is important to consider when selecting a genetic testing approach. Genetic testing is time-sensitive for patients with advanced gastric cancer and should include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044677" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">informed consent</GlossaryTermRef>, sample collection, and an explanation of genetic test results.<Reference refidx="16"/> However, the timing of genetic testing will need to be balanced with the patient's competing treatment priorities and performance status. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865#_313" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Value of testing an affected family member first</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling.</Para><Para id="_3785"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Germline</GlossaryTermRef> genetic testing criteria exists for the following <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> associated with gastric cancer and/or gastric polyps: <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>CTNNA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>APC</GeneName>, <GeneName>STK11</GeneName>, <GeneName>SMAD4</GeneName>, and the Lynch syndrome genes (<GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName>).<Reference refidx="12"/> One  possible genetic testing approach is to first test for gene(s) in which clinical criteria for hereditary cancer syndrome(s) are met. This approach may not be ideal when a patient’s family history includes cancers that can be associated with multiple hereditary gastric cancer syndromes. This can create a lengthy and expensive evaluation process if each suspected gene is tested sequentially after uninformative results. When the cancers in a family history overlap with multiple  hereditary gastric cancer syndromes, providers can first test the gene(s) at the top of the differential diagnosis list. If <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> are not identified, providers can then reflex to a larger hereditary gastric cancer multigene panel. If this single-gene genetic testing approach is preferred, providers may need to identify a lab that offers the option to reflex to other genes before beginning the genetic testing process.</Para><Para id="_3799">When the patient has multiple cancers in the family that overlap with more than one hereditary cancer syndrome, another option is ordering multigene panel testing for all suspected genes. Multigene panel testing is the simultaneous testing of many   genes for pathogenic and likely pathogenic variants, often at costs comparable to single-gene genetic testing.   Hereditary cancer multigene panel testing includes cancer site-specific panels, high- or moderate-risk gene panels, guideline-based panels, and pancancer panels.<Reference refidx="17"/> Given the numerous panel testing options, clinicians must pay special attention to choose the most appropriate panel of genes based on each individual patient’s differential diagnosis.   For instance, genetic testing for pathogenic variants in both <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> and <GeneName>CTNNA1</GeneName> is recommended when testing criteria for HDGC is met. Additionally, analysis of promoter 1B in the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene must be included when testing  for GAPPS.   </Para><Para id="_3787">For more information about selecting the appropriate genetic test, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865#_86" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Determining the Test to be Used</SummaryRef>  section in Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling.</Para><SummarySection id="_3773"><Title>Multigene panel testing implications</Title></SummarySection><Para id="_3788">This section briefly summarizes the implications for patients undergoing multigene panel testing for hereditary gastric cancer syndromes. For more information about multigene panel testing, including genetic education, counseling considerations, and research, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865#_1320" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Multigene (panel) testing</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling.</Para><Para id="_3789">Multigene panel testing can present challenges,  including the unexpected discovery of pathogenic variants in genes that would not have been considered based on the patient’s personal and/or family history.  Pathogenic variants in many  hereditary cancer genes can increase an individual’s risk of developing more than one type of cancer. For instance, <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> pathogenic variants are associated with increased risk for both diffuse gastric cancer and lobular breast cancer.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/> Gastric cancer risk management dilemmas arise when individuals with only a personal and/or family history of breast cancer find an unexpected  <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> pathogenic variant on multigene panel testing. This test result can complicate medical decision-making, since these individuals would not normally participate in enhanced gastric cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> based on their personal or family histories alone. Furthermore, there are no effective gastric cancer screening recommendations for <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> carriers.   Therefore, all individuals with a pathogenic variant in <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> are counseled about the option of  risk-reducing total gastrectomy, a surgery   with postoperative complication rates as high as 10% and a high likelihood of chronic sequelae.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="20"/> The discovery of an unexpected <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> variant on multigene panel testing in the absence of a family history of gastric cancer is a challenging situation that is increasingly encountered in clinical practice.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/> Pretest <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> is recommended when patients undergo multigene panel testing. Pretest genetic counseling may include a discussion about potential unexpected genetic test findings, and the implications of identifying pathogenic variants in genes that are not well understood, including a review of any limitations associated with  cancer risk management recommendations.<Reference refidx="22"/><Reference refidx="23"/></Para><SummarySection id="_3775"><Title>Cascade genetic testing</Title><Para id="_3790"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000799496" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Cascade genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef> identifies relatives who are at risk for a genetic condition by following the logical path of a pathogenic variant in a family. Cascade genetic testing is routinely offered to at-risk relatives once a pathogenic variant is identified. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062865#_1609" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/risk-assessment-hp-pdq">Cascade Genetic Testing of Family Members</SummaryRef> section in Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling. In some cases, the patient will already have advanced gastric cancer when a <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> pathogenic variant is found.   Many patients do not have symptoms of gastric cancer until it has advanced to later stages. Gastric cancer  is often incurable, and only 31% of patients diagnosed with gastric cancer survive 5 years or more.<Reference refidx="15"/> Patients may be declining when they receive their genetic test results and may be unable to  communicate this result to family members. Ideally, probands and clinicians work together to identify at-risk relatives for cascade testing.<Reference refidx="24"/> Since gastric cancer screening is not performed in the general population, cascade genetic testing is critical to identify asymptomatic high-risk individuals who may benefit from personalized gastric cancer management recommendations.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="35122589">Uson PLS, Kunze KL, Golafshar MA, et al.: Germline Cancer Testing in Unselected Patients with Gastric and Esophageal Cancers: A Multi-center Prospective Study. Dig Dis Sci 67 (11): 5107-5115, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="34251444">Ku GY, Kemel Y, Maron SB, et al.: Prevalence of Germline Alterations on Targeted Tumor-Normal Sequencing of Esophagogastric Cancer. JAMA Netw Open 4 (7): e2114753, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25638682">Oliveira C, Pinheiro H, Figueiredo J, et al.: Familial gastric cancer: genetic susceptibility, pathology, and implications for management. Lancet Oncol 16 (2): e60-70, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15831593">Frebourg T, Oliveira C, Hochain P, et al.: Cleft lip/palate and CDH1/E-cadherin mutations in families with hereditary diffuse gastric cancer. J Med Genet 43 (2): 138-42, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18457477">Qureshi N, Wilson B, Santaguida P, et al.: Collection and use of cancer family history in primary care. Evid Rep Technol Assess (Full Rep)  (159): 1-84, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="14724166">Mitchell RJ, Brewster D, Campbell H, et al.: Accuracy of reporting of family history of colorectal cancer. Gut 53 (2): 291-5, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="10227399">Douglas FS, O'Dair LC, Robinson M, et al.: The accuracy of diagnoses as reported in families with cancer: a retrospective study. J Med Genet 36 (4): 309-12, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="22237666">Ozanne EM, O'Connell A, Bouzan C, et al.: Bias in the reporting of family history: implications for clinical care. J Genet Couns 21 (4): 547-56, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="21562245">Mai PL, Garceau AO, Graubard BI, et al.: Confirmation of family cancer history reported in a population-based survey. J Natl Cancer Inst 103 (10): 788-97, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="8902514">Rashid A, Jagger C: Patients' knowledge of anatomical location of major organs within the human body: a comparison between Asians and non-Asians. Fam Pract 13 (5): 450-4, 1996.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="27222437">Fiederling J, Shams AZ, Haug U: Validity of self-reported family history of cancer: A systematic literature review on selected cancers. Int J Cancer 139 (7): 1449-60, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="32758476">Blair VR, McLeod M, Carneiro F, et al.: Hereditary diffuse gastric cancer: updated clinical practice guidelines. Lancet Oncol 21 (8): e386-e397, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="26363540">Colvin H, Yamamoto K, Wada N, et al.: Hereditary Gastric Cancer Syndromes. Surg Oncol Clin N Am 24 (4): 765-77, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="31296550">Xicola RM, Li S, Rodriguez N, et al.: Clinical features and cancer risk in families with pathogenic CDH1 variants irrespective of clinical criteria. J Med Genet 56 (12): 838-843, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="15">National Cancer Institute: SEER Cancer Stat Facts: Stomach Cancer. Bethesda, Md: National Cancer Institute. <ExternalRef xref="https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/stomach.html">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 21, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="25394175">Hampel H, Bennett RL, Buchanan A, et al.: A practice guideline from the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics and the National Society of Genetic Counselors: referral indications for cancer predisposition assessment. Genet Med 17 (1): 70-87, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="23460708">Domchek SM, Bradbury A, Garber JE, et al.: Multiplex genetic testing for cancer susceptibility: out on the high wire without a net? J Clin Oncol 31 (10): 1267-70, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="11729114">Pharoah PD, Guilford P, Caldas C, et al.: Incidence of gastric cancer and breast cancer in CDH1 (E-cadherin) mutation carriers from hereditary diffuse gastric cancer families. Gastroenterology 121 (6): 1348-53, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="26759166">Corso G, Intra M, Trentin C, et al.: CDH1 germline mutations and hereditary lobular breast cancer. Fam Cancer 15 (2): 215-9, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="29341148">van der Kaaij RT, van Kessel JP, van Dieren JM, et al.: Outcomes after prophylactic gastrectomy for hereditary diffuse gastric cancer. Br J Surg 105 (2): e176-e182, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="35172483">Lowstuter K, Espenschied CR, Sturgeon D, et al.: Unexpected CDH1 Mutations Identified on Multigene Panels Pose Clinical Management Challenges. JCO Precis Oncol 1: 1-12, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="31841163">Katona BW, Clark DF, Domchek SM: CDH1 on Multigene Panel Testing: Look Before You Leap. J Natl Cancer Inst 112 (4): 330-334, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="23">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic. Version 3.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_bop.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed October 17, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="26969309">Hampel H: Genetic counseling and cascade genetic testing in Lynch syndrome. Fam Cancer 15 (3): 423-7, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3777"><Title>Major Genes and Genetic Syndromes Associated With Gastric Cancer</Title><Para id="_3791">The major heritable syndromes associated with increased gastric cancer risk are  listed in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_3792" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>, along with their corresponding susceptibility <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef>. For more information on  <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName>- and <GeneName>CTNNA1</GeneName>-associated hereditary gastric cancers, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000812188" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hereditary-diffuse-gastric-cancer-hp-pdq">Hereditary Diffuse Gastric Cancer</SummaryRef>. The gastric cancer risk of the other syndromes in this table are described throughout this summary, and hyperlinks have also been provided to  other  PDQ summaries with additional information.</Para><Table id="_3792"><Title>Table 1.  Hereditary Syndromes Associated With Increased Gastric Cancer Risk</Title><TGroup Cols="6"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="18.97%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="18.47%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="17.22%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="4" ColWidth="12.48%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="5" ColWidth="13.73%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="6" ColWidth="19.10%"/><THead><Row><entry>Syndrome<Superscript>a</Superscript> </entry><entry>Gene </entry><entry>Gastric Cancer Risk </entry><entry>Gastric Cancer Pathology </entry><entry>Gastric Cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> </entry><entry>Other Characteristics </entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1">CNS = central nervous system; CRC = colorectal cancer; EGD = esophagogastroduodenoscopy;  GI = gastrointestinal; GIST = gastrointestinal stromal tumor. </entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>All conditions are inherited in an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> fashion, unless otherwise specified.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>High-risk lesions include tubular adenomas, polyps with high-grade dysplasia, and pyloric gland adenomas. 
</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Prophylactic total gastrectomy is not recommended prior to age 40 y. However, it  may be considered for certain patients, especially those with family histories of gastric cancer prior to age 25 y.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"/></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000812188" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hereditary-diffuse-gastric-cancer-hp-pdq">Hereditary diffuse gastric cancer </SummaryRef> </entry><entry><GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> and <GeneName>CTNNA1</GeneName></entry><entry>33%–83% <Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> </entry><entry>Diffuse type, signet ring cell carcinoma </entry><entry>EGD with multiple random biopsies of the stomach every 6–12 mo <Strong>or</Strong> risk-reducing total gastrectomy between ages 18–40 y<Superscript>c</Superscript> <Reference refidx="6"/> </entry><entry><Strong>For <GeneName>CDH1 </GeneName>only: </Strong>Lobular breast cancer, cleft lip or cleft palate. It is currently unknown whether <GeneName>CTNNA1</GeneName> is associated with lobular breast cancer or cleft lip or cleft palate 
</entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_3205" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Familial adenomatous polyposis syndrome</SummaryRef> (FAP)  
 
</entry><entry><GeneName>APC</GeneName> </entry><entry MoreRows="1"> 1.3%–5% in FAP and AFAP.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> </entry><entry MoreRows="2">Intestinal type </entry><entry MoreRows="2">EGD for duodenal surveillance is also adequate surveillance for gastric cancers. Gastrectomy can be considered for patients with high-risk lesions that cannot be managed endoscopically<Superscript>b</Superscript> <Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry MoreRows="2">Gastric polyps (fundic gland polyps and adenomas), CRC, colorectal polyps (adenomas), desmoid tumors, duodenal tumors and cancer, thyroid cancer, brain cancer, ampullary cancer, pancreatic cancer, hepatoblastoma </entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_118" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Attenuated familial  adenomatous polyposis</SummaryRef>  (AFAP)</entry><entry><GeneName>APC</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000814294" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gapps-hp-pdq">Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach</SummaryRef>  
(GAPPS)</entry><entry><GeneName>APC</GeneName> (pathogenic variants/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803525" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">single nucleotide variant</GlossaryTermRef> in the promoter 1B  region of <GeneName>APC</GeneName> are associated with  GAPPS-7) 
 
 
</entry><entry>In GAPPS, gastric cancer risk is significantly increased, but exact risk numbers are unknown <Reference refidx="10"/></entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_2986" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Lynch syndrome</SummaryRef> (also known as hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancer [HNPCC])</entry><entry><GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName>, <GeneName>EPCAM</GeneName> </entry><entry>0.2%–9% </entry><entry>Intestinal type 
</entry><entry>Upper GI surveillance with EGD (preferably performed in conjunction with colonoscopy) starting at age 30–40 y (or earlier based on the patient's family history). Repeat EGD every 2–4 y <Reference refidx="9"/> </entry><entry>CRC, endometrial cancer, ovarian cancer, breast cancer, pancreatic cancer, bladder cancer, biliary tract cancer, urothelial cancer, small bowel cancer, prostate cancer, brain/CNS tumor </entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_2920" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Peutz-Jeghers syndrome</SummaryRef> </entry><entry><GeneName>STK11</GeneName> (also known as <GeneName>LKB1</GeneName>) 
 
</entry><entry>29% <Reference refidx="9"/> </entry><entry>Intestinal type (arising from dysplasia in hamartomas) </entry><entry>EGD every 2–3 y beginning in the late adolescence <Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry>Hamartomatous GI polyps; breast cancer; CRC; small bowel cancer; pancreatic cancer; Sertoli cell tumors of the ovary and testes; cervical adenoma malignum; endometrial cancer; lung cancer; mucocutaneous hyperpigmentation of the mouth, lips, nose, eyes, genitalia and/or fingers </entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_647" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Juvenile polyposis syndrome</SummaryRef> </entry><entry><GeneName>SMAD4</GeneName>, <GeneName>BMPR1A</GeneName> </entry><entry> 21% if multiple polyps are present 
</entry><entry>Intestinal type (arising from dysplasia in juvenile polyps/hamartomas) 
</entry><entry>EGD  every 2–3 y. If polyps are found, conduct EGD at shorter intervals based on polyp size, number, and pathology <Reference refidx="9"/></entry><entry>Juvenile/hamartomatous 
colorectal polyps, CRC, hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia</entry></Row><Row><entry><SummaryRef href="CDR0000062855#_3755" url="/types/breast/hp/breast-ovarian-genetics-pdq">Li-Fraumeni syndrome</SummaryRef> </entry><entry><GeneName>TP53</GeneName> </entry><entry>2.8% </entry><entry>Possibly intestinal type </entry><entry/><entry>Breast cancer, adrenocortical carcinoma, sarcoma, brain/CNS tumor, leukemia</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="31246251">Roberts ME, Ranola JMO, Marshall ML, et al.: Comparison of CDH1 Penetrance Estimates in Clinically Ascertained Families vs Families Ascertained for Multiple Gastric Cancers. JAMA Oncol 5 (9): 1325-1331, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11729114">Pharoah PD, Guilford P, Caldas C, et al.: Incidence of gastric cancer and breast cancer in CDH1 (E-cadherin) mutation carriers from hereditary diffuse gastric cancer families. Gastroenterology 121 (6): 1348-53, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="26182300">Hansford S, Kaurah P, Li-Chang H, et al.: Hereditary Diffuse Gastric Cancer Syndrome: CDH1 Mutations and Beyond. JAMA Oncol 1 (1): 23-32, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="17545690">Kaurah P, MacMillan A, Boyd N, et al.: Founder and recurrent CDH1 mutations in families with hereditary diffuse gastric cancer. JAMA 297 (21): 2360-72, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31296550">Xicola RM, Li S, Rodriguez N, et al.: Clinical features and cancer risk in families with pathogenic CDH1 variants irrespective of clinical criteria. J Med Genet 56 (12): 838-843, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Gastric Cancer. Version 1.2023. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/gastric.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed October 17, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="31848868">Cannon AR, Keener M, Neklason D, et al.: Surgical Interventions, Malignancies, and Causes of Death in a FAP Patient Registry. J Gastrointest Surg 25 (2): 452-456, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28185118">Mankaney G, Leone P, Cruise M, et al.: Gastric cancer in FAP: a concerning rise in incidence. Fam Cancer 16 (3): 371-376, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Colorectal. Version 1.2023. Plymouth Meeting, PA: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_colon.pdf">Available with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed June 28, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="27087319">Li J, Woods SL, Healey S, et al.: Point Mutations in Exon 1B of APC Reveal Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach as a Familial Adenomatous Polyposis Variant. Am J Hum Genet 98 (5): 830-842, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3805"><Title>Other Genes Associated With Gastric Cancer</Title><Para id="_3806">Preliminary evidence has linked gastric cancer to other  genes that are not typically associated with this type of cancer, such as <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRIP1</GeneName>, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>RAD51D</GeneName>. Studies suggest a possible association between gastric cancer risk and pathogenic variants in both established gastric cancer genes and in moderate- and high-risk genes that are not typically  associated with gastric cancer. However, clinical practice changes are not indicated based on this preliminary evidence.</Para><Para id="_3826">Several studies searched for candidate genes in hereditary gastric cancer cases that were not associated with <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> pathogenic variants. Some of these cases may be explained by pathogenic variants in homologous recombination (HR) DNA repair genes, particularly <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_3827" Style="bullet"><ListItem>One of the first studies to identify variants that may increase gastric cancer risk performed whole-exome sequencing (WES) in 28 patients and sequenced candidate genes in 333 patients.<Reference refidx="1"/> In 11 cases, pathogenic variants were identified in genes that regulate HR, including eight <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants, two <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> pathogenic variants, and one <GeneName>RAD51C</GeneName> pathogenic variant. WES in four tumor samples (from three <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers and one <GeneName>RAD51C</GeneName> carrier) did not find a loss of heterozygosity (LOH). However, all of the tumors (4/4) were enriched for a mutational signature that is characteristic of HR defects, suggesting a causal link between these genes and gastric cancer risk. </ListItem><ListItem>Another study of 28 <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName>-negative individuals with clinical diagnoses of hereditary diffuse gastric cancer used WES.<Reference refidx="2"/> A <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> loss-of-function variant was found in one patient with a history of gastric cancer and breast cancer. Two pathogenic variants were also identified in <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName> (mismatch repair gene), and two variants were identified in  <GeneName>RECQL5</GeneName> (DNA repair gene). </ListItem><ListItem> In a large investigation of cancer predisposition variants, 5 of 443 patients with gastric cancer carried <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> loss-of-function variants with variable LOH (2 of 5 tumors), similar to that seen in other <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>-associated tumors.<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem> However,  a study of 58 patients who met clinical criteria for hereditary diffuse gastric cancer but tested negative for <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName> pathogenic variants reported conflicting findings.<Reference refidx="4"/> Unlike similar studies, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> sequencing did not discover pathogenic variants in these patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3828">In summary,  these findings suggest that defects in HR genes increase risk for gastric cancer and highlight a role for the known cancer predisposition gene, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> as a potential candidate gene for hereditary gastric cancer. However, case-control studies are needed to confirm whether <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> is associated with hereditary gastric cancer susceptibility. Gastric cancer screening is not indicated for <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers.</Para><Para id="_3816">Additional studies investigated potential candidate genes for gastric cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_3807" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Fifty-one adults with gastric cancer (with any type of  histology) were part of an international hereditary cancer research network. These individuals were retrospectively selected to undergo germline genetic testing with a 706–candidate gene genetic testing panel.<Reference refidx="5"/> Twenty pathogenic or likely pathogenic variants were identified in 18 participants (35%). Some of these pathogenic variants were in genes not typically associated with gastric cancer, including <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRIP1</GeneName>, <GeneName>FANCC</GeneName>, and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>.</ListItem><ListItem>Another study of 34 patients with gastric cancer, who were not selected based on their clinical characteristics or family histories of cancer, found a pathogenic variant rate of 17.6% on a genetic testing panel  that examined between 83 and 84 genes.<Reference refidx="6"/> Two pathogenic variants were identified in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, and one pathogenic variant was identified in each of the following genes: <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>CDH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>FH</GeneName>, and <GeneName>SDHA</GeneName>.   </ListItem><ListItem>A cross-sectional study performed at a tertiary cancer center assessed the presence of pathogenic variants on a genetic testing panel that examined 76 or 88 genes in 243 patients with gastric cancer who consented to paired somatic and germline sequencing.<Reference refidx="7"/> A total of 48 patients with gastric cancer (19.8%) had germline pathogenic variants.   In high- and moderate-penetrance genes that are not classically associated with gastric cancer,   pathogenic variants were found most frequently in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>ATM</GeneName>.</ListItem><ListItem>One of the largest studies included 282 patients with gastric cancer who were of Han Chinese descent.<Reference refidx="8"/> These patients were enrolled at medical centers in Beijing and underwent a 69–cancer gene panel, which revealed that 7.1% of patients had pathogenic variants. Pathogenic variants were found most often in <GeneName>ATM</GeneName> (detection rate, 1.1% [3/282 patients]), followed by <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>, <GeneName>BRIP1</GeneName>, and <GeneName>RAD51D</GeneName>, which all had a detection rate of 0.7% (2/282 patients). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3808">Additional studies are warranted to determine if there is a causal relationship between these genes and gastric cancer risk. However, the  rate of pathogenic variants found in these studies  supports the use of multigene panels in patients with gastric cancer undergoing germline genetic  testing. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811356#_3574" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/brca-genes-hp-pdq">Other Cancer Risks</SummaryRef> section in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>: Cancer Risks and Management.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="28024868">Sahasrabudhe R, Lott P, Bohorquez M, et al.: Germline Mutations in PALB2, BRCA1, and RAD51C, Which Regulate DNA Recombination Repair, in Patients With Gastric Cancer. Gastroenterology 152 (5): 983-986.e6, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="29706558">Fewings E, Larionov A, Redman J, et al.: Germline pathogenic variants in PALB2 and other cancer-predisposing genes in families with hereditary diffuse gastric cancer without CDH1 mutation: a whole-exome sequencing study. Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol 3 (7): 489-498, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="29625052">Huang KL, Mashl RJ, Wu Y, et al.: Pathogenic Germline Variants in 10,389 Adult Cancers. Cell 173 (2): 355-370.e14, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="33512806">Carreño M, Pena-Couso L, Mercadillo F, et al.: Investigation on the Role of PALB2 Gene in CDH1-Negative Patients With Hereditary Diffuse Gastric Cancer. Clin Transl Gastroenterol 11 (12): e00280, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="29025585">Slavin T, Neuhausen SL, Rybak C, et al.: Genetic Gastric Cancer Susceptibility in the International Clinical Cancer Genomics Community Research Network. Cancer Genet 216-217: 111-119, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="35122589">Uson PLS, Kunze KL, Golafshar MA, et al.: Germline Cancer Testing in Unselected Patients with Gastric and Esophageal Cancers: A Multi-center Prospective Study. Dig Dis Sci 67 (11): 5107-5115, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="34251444">Ku GY, Kemel Y, Maron SB, et al.: Prevalence of Germline Alterations on Targeted Tumor-Normal Sequencing of Esophagogastric Cancer. JAMA Netw Open 4 (7): e2114753, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="32963463">Ji K, Ao S, He L, et al.: Characteristics of cancer susceptibility genes mutations in 282 patients with gastric adenocarcinoma. Chin J Cancer Res 32 (4): 508-515, 2020.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3751"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (05/07/2025)</Title><Para id="_1182">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3831"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_1340" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">Introduction</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_3832">Updated <SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_1341" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">statistics</SummaryRef> with estimated new cancer cases and deaths for 2025 (cited American Cancer Society as reference 3). </Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of gastric cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Genetics of Gastric Cancer are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Grace-Ann O. Fasaye, ScM, CGC (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Gautam Mankaney, MD (Virginia Mason Franciscan Health)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ Genetics of Gastric Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 37669413]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-08-30</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-07</DateLastModified></Summary>
