<Summary id="CDR0000803263"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Black cohosh has been used as a treatment in breast cancer patients and survivors for the relief of side effects, such as hot flashes. Get detailed information about black cohosh   in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/black-cohosh-pdq">Black Cohosh (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryToggleURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/patient/black-cohosh-pdq">Black Cohosh (PDQ®)</SummaryToggleURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000256158">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000302635">black cohosh</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of black cohosh in the treatment of people with cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>black cohosh</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Black Cohosh (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Black Cohosh (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Black Cohosh</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Overview</Title><Para id="_8">This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summary provides an overview of the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321355" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">black cohosh</GlossaryTermRef> as a treatment in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> patients and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef>, generally for the relief of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef>. The summary provides a brief history of black cohosh research, the results of laboratory and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, and possible side effects of black cohosh use.</Para><Para id="_9">This summary contains the following key information:</Para><ItemizedList id="_10" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The roots and rhizomes of black cohosh are used for various medicinal purposes ranging from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045056" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gynecologic</GlossaryTermRef> to other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disorders</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Black cohosh was first used by American Indian or Alaska Native people. it is now commonly used in Europe.</ListItem><ListItem>Black cohosh is frequently studied as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complementary therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for breast cancer patients and survivors to reduce <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vasomotor</GlossaryTermRef> symptoms associated with treatment-induced <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopause</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Purported estrogenic actions of black cohosh are refuted by current, up-to-date laboratory and clinical studies of commercially available hydroalcoholic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef>. Suggestions of serotonergic activity are well supported.</ListItem><ListItem>Recent findings show that black cohosh contains a large variety of constituents that are chemically related to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046481" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">central nervous system</GlossaryTermRef>–active <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045065" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">molecules</GlossaryTermRef>, which have not been studied in detail yet.</ListItem><ListItem>Commercially available hydroalcoholic extracts of black cohosh have been well tolerated, with very rare serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> reported.</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000286105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Observational</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">open-label</GlossaryTermRef> studies indicate benefits of black cohosh on climacteric symptoms in cancer and noncancer populations, though gold-standard clinical investigations fail to confirm this effect.</ListItem><ListItem>Given both the evidence and variability of previous findings, including the lack of demonstration of a clinical benefit against <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> and underexplored constituents, further <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">preclinical</GlossaryTermRef> and clinical studies of black cohosh are warranted. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>General Information</Title><Para id="_11">Native to eastern and midwestern North America, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321355" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">black cohosh</GlossaryTermRef> (<ScientificName>Actaea racemosa</ScientificName>, also known as <ScientificName>Cimicifuga racemosa</ScientificName>) <Reference refidx="1"/>  is a member of the buttercup family (<ScientificName>Ranunculaceae</ScientificName>).<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Black cohosh has many synonyms, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321357" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">black snakeroot</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bugbane</GlossaryTermRef>, rattleroot, squawroot, and macrotrys or macrotys.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> The roots and rhizomes of the black cohosh plant are used for medicinal preparations.</Para><Para id="_12">Various types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> of black cohosh roots and rhizomes have been studied for their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643008" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemical</GlossaryTermRef> composition and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044510" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biological</GlossaryTermRef> activity. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lipophilic</GlossaryTermRef> extracts have predominantly been used in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044512" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">laboratory studies</GlossaryTermRef> and only infrequently in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="3"/> The most commonly used clinical preparations of black cohosh (e.g., Remifemin® and BNO 1055) are made from hydrophilic (typically hydroalcoholic) extracts.<Reference refidx="4"/>  Lipophilic extracts have <ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName> effects on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046076" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estrogen</GlossaryTermRef>-regulated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef>, whereas hydrophilic extracts generally do not.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para><Para id="_13">Several of the chemical constituents of black cohosh extracts have biological activities that have been demonstrated through <ScientificName>in vitro</ScientificName> studies and are candidate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> for the observed <ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName> and clinical effects. Triterpene glycosides have structures similar to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046601" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">steroids</GlossaryTermRef>,<Reference refidx="4"/>  but no apparent direct binding to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046409" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estrogen receptor</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="3"/> One of the most abundant of such glycosides, 23-epi-26-deoxyactein, is specific for black cohosh and is the constituent usually chosen for standardization of commercial products.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> At least 40 different triterpene glycoside analogues have been identified in black cohosh (<ScientificName>A. racemosa</ScientificName>), including actein and cimicifugoside congeners.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_14">Other chemical constituents of black cohosh extracts include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000462664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acid</GlossaryTermRef> phenolpropanoids related to caffeic and ferulic acid, along with  the black cohosh-specific fukinolic acid.<Reference refidx="5"/> The plant also contains a large variety of guanidine <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alkaloids</GlossaryTermRef>, which have been explored chemically but not studied biologically.</Para><Para id="_15">Various plants that resemble black cohosh have been mistakenly or intentionally included in some commercial black cohosh products or plants. Such <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adulteration</GlossaryTermRef> can be detected by methods such as microscopy, high-performance thin-layer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000655048" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chromatography</GlossaryTermRef>, high-performance liquid chromatography ultraviolet, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> barcoding.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_16">Black cohosh root, rhizome, and associated preparations have gained considerable international market and consumer interest for more than 60 years, particularly gaining U.S. interest within the last 15 years.<Reference refidx="6"/>  A market report released by the American Botanical Council stated that black cohosh extract was among the 15 top-selling <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herbal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef> by the food, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef>, and mass-market channel in the United States in 2019, with total sales nearing $30 million.<Reference refidx="7"/> Growth in market demand for black cohosh has led to an increased need for scientific evidence of  quality, safety, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_65">Companies distribute  black cohosh as a dietary supplement. In the United States, dietary supplements are regulated by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454785" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">U.S. Food and Drug Administration</GlossaryTermRef> (FDA) as a separate category from foods, cosmetics, and drugs. Unlike drugs, dietary supplements do not require premarket evaluation and approval by the FDA unless specific disease <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef> or treatment claims are made. The quality and amount of ingredients in dietary supplements are also regulated by the FDA through Good Manufacturing Practices (GMPs). The FDA GMPs requires that every finished batch of dietary supplement meets each product specification for identity, purity, strength, composition, and limits on contamination that may <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000686042" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adulterate</GlossaryTermRef> dietary supplements. The FDA can remove dietary supplements from the market that are deemed unsafe. Because dietary supplements are not formally reviewed for manufacturing consistency every year, ingredients may vary considerably from lot to lot and  there is no guarantee that ingredients claimed on product labels are present (or are present in the specified amounts). The FDA has not approved the use of black cohosh as a treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> or any other medical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">condition</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">European Union Herbal Monograph on Cimicifuga racemosa (L.) Nutt., rhizoma. London, United Kingdom: Committee on Herbal Medicinal Products, 2018. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/herbal-monograph/final-european-union-herbal-monograph-cimicifuga-racemosa-l-nutt-rhizome-revision-1_en.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Predny ML, De Angelis P, Chamberlain JL: Black cohosh (Actaea racemosa): an annotated bibliography. U.S. Department of Agriculture Forest Service, Southern Research Station, 2006. General Technical Report SRS 97.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Fabricant DS, Krause EC, Farnsworth NR: Black cohosh. In: Coates PM, Blackman MR, Cragg GM: Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2<Superscript>nd</Superscript> ed.  CRC Press, 2015, pp 60-74.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25296437">Qiu F, McAlpine JB, Krause EC, et al.: Pharmacognosy of black cohosh: the phytochemical and biological profile of a major botanical dietary supplement. Prog Chem Org Nat Prod 99: 1-68, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Gafner S: Black Cohosh Laboratory Guidance Document. ABC-AHP-NCNPR Botanical Adulterants Program,  2015.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Foster S: Exploring the peripatetic maze of black cohosh adulteration: a review of the nomenclature, distribution, chemistry, market status, analytical methods, and safety. HerbalGram  (98): 32-51, 2013. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.herbalgram.org/resources/herbalgram/issues/98/table-of-contents/hg98feat-blackcohosh/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Smith T, May G, Eckl V, et al.: US sales of herbal supplements increase by 8.6% in 2019. HerbalGram  (127): 54-69, 2020. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.herbalgram.org/resources/herbalgram/issues/127/table-of-contents/herbalgram-127-herb-market-report/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="8">Gafner S: Botanical adulterants bulletin on adulteration of actaea racemosa. Black Cohosh - Botanical Adulterants Bulletin  1-5, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_17"><Title>History</Title><Para id="_18"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321355" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Black cohosh</GlossaryTermRef> was in use by American Indian or Alaska Native people when Europeans arrived in the New World.<Reference refidx="1"/> Among the reported indications for black cohosh in traditional American Indian or Alaska Native  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef> were various female <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">conditions</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rheumatism</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fever</GlossaryTermRef> (possibly due to malaria), general malaise, sore <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439429" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">throat</GlossaryTermRef>, childbirth, and snakebite.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Early European settlers, and subsequently American eclectic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physicians</GlossaryTermRef>, assimilated the use of black cohosh and began exporting the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herb</GlossaryTermRef> to Europe as early as the 18th century.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_19">Europeans have used black cohosh to treat <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopausal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> for over 50 years. In Germany, the Commission E approved black cohosh as a treatment for dysmenorrhea, menopausal symptoms, heart palpitations, nervousness, irritability, sleep disturbances, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482287" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tinnitus</GlossaryTermRef>, vertigo, perspiration, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430479" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">depression</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_20">Various sources suggested that the recommended <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> of crude drug is 40 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef> per day.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  At least one trial compared two different doses (39 mg and 127.3 mg) <Reference refidx="4"/>  in women with menopausal symptoms and found equivalent beneficial effects at both doses. The lack of long-term safety studies has led some groups to recommend limiting the use of black cohosh to a maximum of 6 months.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Predny ML, De Angelis P, Chamberlain JL: Black cohosh (Actaea racemosa): an annotated bibliography. U.S. Department of Agriculture Forest Service, Southern Research Station, 2006. General Technical Report SRS 97.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25296437">Qiu F, McAlpine JB, Krause EC, et al.: Pharmacognosy of black cohosh: the phytochemical and biological profile of a major botanical dietary supplement. Prog Chem Org Nat Prod 99: 1-68, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Fabricant DS, Krause EC, Farnsworth NR: Black cohosh. In: Coates PM, Blackman MR, Cragg GM: Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2<Superscript>nd</Superscript> ed.  CRC Press, 2015, pp 60-74.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="11975864">Liske E, Hänggi W, Henneicke-von Zepelin HH, et al.: Physiological investigation of a unique extract of black cohosh (Cimicifugae racemosae rhizoma): a 6-month clinical study demonstrates no systemic estrogenic effect. J Womens Health Gend Based Med 11 (2): 163-74, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Cimicifugae Rhizoma. Amsterdam,
The Netherlands: European Medicines Agency, 2018. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/medicines/herbal/cimicifugae-rhizoma">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_21"><Title>Laboratory/Animal/Preclinical Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Mechanism of Action</Title><Para id="_23">Given the apparent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> effects of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321355" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">black cohosh</GlossaryTermRef> on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopausal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, early preclinical investigations searched for an anticipated estrogenic activity. These <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651211" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">research studies</GlossaryTermRef> demonstrated differences between <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lipophilic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef>, which often had evidence of estrogenic activity,<Reference refidx="1"/> and the hydroalcoholic extracts of the type contained in the most commonly used clinical products, which generally  lacked such activity.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_24">Considering the recent discovery of nitrogenous black cohosh constituents,<Reference refidx="2"/> subsequent hypotheses for the activity of black cohosh involve potential effects on hypothalamic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neurotransmitter</GlossaryTermRef> regulation systems,<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/> such as those involving   
the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044026" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endogenous</GlossaryTermRef> central opioid system.<Reference refidx="4"/> This   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044209" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypothesis</GlossaryTermRef> is supported by the observation that while black cohosh treatment alone has no effect on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643019" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">luteinizing hormone</GlossaryTermRef> (LH) activity, induction of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045228" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">naloxone</GlossaryTermRef> blockade of µ-opioid <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044958" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">receptors</GlossaryTermRef> in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmenopausal</GlossaryTermRef> women treated with Remifemin® leads to the suppression of LH activity.<Reference refidx="4"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046218" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Positron emission tomography</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046361" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">imaging</GlossaryTermRef> in women treated with black cohosh indicated selective µ-opioid receptor availability, with increased availability in regions responsible for emotional and cognitive processing, and pronounced reductions observed in areas associated with the human <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="4"/> Given such results, and the comparatively high frequency of placebo responsiveness in black cohosh <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>, both pharmacologic and placebo effects simultaneously affecting the endogenous opioid system are suggested.  </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Fabricant DS, Krause EC, Farnsworth NR: Black cohosh. In: Coates PM, Blackman MR, Cragg GM: Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2<Superscript>nd</Superscript> ed.  CRC Press, 2015, pp 60-74.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25296437">Qiu F, McAlpine JB, Krause EC, et al.: Pharmacognosy of black cohosh: the phytochemical and biological profile of a major botanical dietary supplement. Prog Chem Org Nat Prod 99: 1-68, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="23439657">Fritz H, Seely D, McGowan J, et al.: Black cohosh and breast cancer: a systematic review. Integr Cancer Ther 13 (1): 12-29, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="18521048">Reame NE, Lukacs JL, Padmanabhan V, et al.: Black cohosh has central opioid activity in postmenopausal women: evidence from naloxone blockade and positron emission tomography neuroimaging. Menopause 15 (5): 832-40, 2008 Sep-Oct.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><Title>Human/Clinical Studies</Title><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Mechanism of Action, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics</Title><Para id="_27">Given that the clinically utilized hydrophilic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321355" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">black cohosh</GlossaryTermRef> roots and rhizomes are not estrogenic, alternative mechanisms of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopausal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptom</GlossaryTermRef> relief have been proposed, one of which suggests serotonergic activity by triterpenes to minimize episodes of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256567" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hot flashes</GlossaryTermRef> and bone loss.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> While this finding warrants further investigation, it is currently common practice to standardize the content of  commercially available black cohosh supplements to certain triterpene <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000422394" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">compounds</GlossaryTermRef> related to actein, such as 23-epi-26-deoxyactein. Likewise, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044324" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pharmacokinetic</GlossaryTermRef> (PK) investigations of black cohosh triterpenes are more commonly reported.</Para><Para id="_28">The maximum-tolerated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dose</GlossaryTermRef> and PK  of 23-epi-26-deoxyactein, the  most abundant triterpene found in the plant,<Reference refidx="5"/> has been evaluated in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">phase I clinical trial</GlossaryTermRef>. Single doses of an ethanolic black cohosh extract containing 1.4 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef>, 2.8 mg, or 5.6 mg of 23-epi-26-deoxyactein (32 mg, 64 mg, or 128 mg of black cohosh, respectively) were administered to 15 healthy menopausal women.<Reference refidx="1"/>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Analysis</GlossaryTermRef> of the compound in sera indicates a half-life of about 2 hours for all administered dosages (2.1 ± 0.4, 2.7 ± 0.4, and 3.0 ± 1.0 h, respectively). First-order kinetics is also indicated, with maximum <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000683342" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">concentration</GlossaryTermRef> and area under the curve increasing proportionately with dosage. It is suggested that 23-epi-26-deoxyactein is excreted intact in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef> and degraded in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal tract</GlossaryTermRef>, as no metabolites of the compound were detected in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef> or sera, and only a negligible amount (&lt;0.01%) of the compound was recovered in urine 24 hours after <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044068" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oral</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">administration</GlossaryTermRef>; specific proof of predominant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044970" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biliary</GlossaryTermRef> secretion is needed.<Reference refidx="1"/> In the same study, no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alteration</GlossaryTermRef> in circulating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormone</GlossaryTermRef> levels <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">(estradiol</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643012" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">follicle-stimulating hormone</GlossaryTermRef>, luteinizing hormone) was observed in this population relative to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467830" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">baseline</GlossaryTermRef> (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis>  &lt; .05). Changes have not been observed in similar investigations of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">systemic</GlossaryTermRef> hormone levels or those monitoring for estrogenic effects on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045044" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endometrial</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044308" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vaginal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_29">Although  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case reports</GlossaryTermRef> suggested connections between the use of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373932" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">dietary supplements</GlossaryTermRef> containing black cohosh and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> damage, no evidence of hepatotoxicity—or any other form of serious toxicity—was found in systematic reviews of results from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> of a chemically standardized black cohosh preparation; regardless of dosage administered, no liver function <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045776" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">markers</GlossaryTermRef> were altered.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_30">Reports of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef> include one case of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045585" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">acute</GlossaryTermRef> liver failure, two cases of <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> (without further description), and two cases indicating mild elevation of liver function markers, though many of these patients were taking multiple <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000367458" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">botanical</GlossaryTermRef> products simultaneously.<Reference refidx="6"/> An episode of autoimmune hepatitis is questionably related to the use of black cohosh. Although noteworthy, many of these reports are anecdotal in nature.<Reference refidx="6"/> Furthermore, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000691484" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">meta-analysis</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045858" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">randomized</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045673" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">double-blind</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> does not demonstrate evidence of black cohosh causing adverse effects on liver function.<Reference refidx="7"/> Indications of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">toxicity</GlossaryTermRef> are reportedly caused by manufacturer contamination or adulteration with other toxic products,<Reference refidx="1"/> necessitating mechanisms of botanical authentication and proper methods of manufacturing the product. The not-infrequent adulteration of black cohosh with Asian <ScientificName>Actaea</ScientificName> species that contain significantly different phytoconstituents is the most plausible cause of the reported potential adverse hepatic effects.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_31">Acute toxicity of black cohosh is also purported to occur through interactions with pharmaceutical agents.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="10"/> Though substantial <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">herb</GlossaryTermRef>-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drug</GlossaryTermRef> interactions can occur in this manner with certain herbs   such as St. John’s wort, <ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName> analysis of black cohosh <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> does not suggest this interaction. Black cohosh <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045916" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">supplementation</GlossaryTermRef> does not significantly alter the expression or activity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044056" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> CYP3A4, CYP1A2, or CYP2E1.<Reference refidx="10"/> While a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044167" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">statistically significant</GlossaryTermRef> decrease in the CYP2D6 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef> (approximately 7%; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02) has been observed in a human study, the clinical relevancy of this finding is questionable <Reference refidx="10"/>—especially since a very high dose was used for this particular investigation (1,090 mg bid). Studies have yet to verify this effect;<Reference refidx="2"/> however, given that tamoxifen is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044229" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">selective estrogen receptor modulator</GlossaryTermRef> and is primarily metabolized by CYP2D6, even mild inhibition of the enzyme by black cohosh may warrant consideration.<Reference refidx="2"/>  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><Title>Prevention of Breast Cancer/Recurrence </Title><Para id="_33"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000286105" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Observational studies</GlossaryTermRef> of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045269" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmenopausal</GlossaryTermRef> women without a history of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> indicated no significant association between the use of black cohosh and development of the disease when compared with nonuse (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000618612" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hazard ratio</GlossaryTermRef> = 1.17; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.75–1.82; adjusted <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000618610" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">odds ratio</GlossaryTermRef> [OR], 0.80; 95% CI, 0.63–1.00).<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_34">One study suggested a possible protective effect. This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348989" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case-control trial</GlossaryTermRef> evaluated whether the use of hormone-related supplements, including black cohosh for the management of menopausal symptoms, was associated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> risk or protection.<Reference refidx="11"/> A 53% decreased risk in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046145" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">incidence</GlossaryTermRef> of breast cancer was observed among postmenopausal women taking black cohosh compared with nonusers (adjusted OR, 0.47; 95% CI, 0.27–0.82). In subset analyses, ever-use of tamoxifen or raloxifene prior to cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef> (as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045487" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemopreventive</GlossaryTermRef> agent rather than a treatment for cancer) was not a significant confounder in the protective relationship observed between black cohosh use and breast cancer occurrence.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><Para id="_35"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045861" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Recurrence</GlossaryTermRef>-free survival was also evaluated as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044163" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary endpoint</GlossaryTermRef> measure in a sample of breast cancer patients and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000450125" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">survivors</GlossaryTermRef> (n = 18,861), 1,102 of whom had received a product containing a black cohosh extract (i.e., Remifemin® or Remifemin® plus; R/R+, a 40% isopropanol black cohosh extract, with or without St. John’s wort extract,<Reference refidx="12"/> respectively).<Reference refidx="13"/> This <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000286525" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">retrospective cohort study</GlossaryTermRef> reported a significantly lower risk of recurrence in R/R+ users compared with nonusers over a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mean</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045981" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">observation</GlossaryTermRef> time of 3.6 years.<Reference refidx="13"/> This decrease was observed in patients who also received tamoxifen. These results suggest that R/R+ is not likely to promote breast cancer recurrence or inhibit the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> effect of tamoxifen.<Reference refidx="13"/> No other studies have reported to further explore a potential beneficial effect of black cohosh extracts on breast cancer recurrence.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><Title>Effect on Menopausal Symptoms </Title><Para id="_37">Several studies have investigated black cohosh in treating women suffering from climacteric complaints, including breast cancer patients and survivors.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Analyses of the effect of black cohosh preparations on these symptoms in patients with other cancers have not yet been reported. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_38"><Title>Breast Cancer Patients</Title><Para id="_39">Observational and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000285990" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">open-label</GlossaryTermRef> studies have demonstrated reductions in the number and severity of hot flashes among breast cancer patients undergoing adjuvant <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044411" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endocrine therapy</GlossaryTermRef> complemented with black cohosh; however, randomized, double-blind, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo-controlled</GlossaryTermRef> clinical trials have failed to demonstrate reductions greater than that seen with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_40">Significant declines in hot flash frequency and severity and other menopausal symptoms are reported in a review of observational studies of breast cancer patients and survivors taking Remifemin® (20–40 mg/d), with or without tamoxifen or raloxifene.<Reference refidx="2"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044079" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Prospective</GlossaryTermRef> trials indicated reductions as high as 56% (95% CI = 40%–71%) in hot flash scores (daily frequency times average severity).<Reference refidx="2"/> Self-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assessment</GlossaryTermRef> of menopausal symptoms through the Menopausal Rating Scale (MRS II) has also been evaluated among breast cancer patients on Remifemin® (40 mg/d) plus tamoxifen (10–40 mg/d), indicating significant declines in menopausal symptomology (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .001) from baseline, and after 1, 3, and 6 months of black cohosh treatment.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_41">Statistically significant reductions in hot flash symptomology have also been observed in open-label administration of another black cohosh product, CR BNO 1055 from Bionorica in Germany (40 mg/d), in breast cancer survivors who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adjuvant therapy</GlossaryTermRef> with tamoxifen; however, double-blind studies so far have failed to show this to be a specific effect.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_42">Thus far, two randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trials have assessed the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346517" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">efficacy</GlossaryTermRef> of black cohosh use (one trial used black cohosh extract;<Reference refidx="14"/> the other trial used an uncharacterized black cohosh product <Reference refidx="15"/>)    on hot flashes—or related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256578" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vasomotor</GlossaryTermRef> symptoms—in breast cancer survivors who received a selective estrogen receptor modulator (SERM). Neither study indicated a significant difference in menopausal symptomology between women taking the supplement (20–40 mg/d), or an identical-appearing placebo, with or without the use of tamoxifen (10–40 mg) or raloxifene (dosage not provided).<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_43">One randomized clinical study specifically evaluated the preventative effect of Remifemin® on symptoms of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopause</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045090" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> (MPS) in breast cancer patients who received <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044574" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044919" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analogs</GlossaryTermRef> (LHRH-a).<Reference refidx="3"/> Some patients received LHRH-a treatment in addition to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044232" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">aromatase inhibitor</GlossaryTermRef>  or SERM, though no significant difference in use was found between the treatment group and the control group.<Reference refidx="3"/> Evaluation of MPS was assessed using Kupperman Menopausal Index (KMI) scores. Symptomology increased in both groups throughout the course of study; however, KMI scores of patients on LHRH-a treatment (goserelin, n = 32; leuprorelin, n = 10) with Remifemin® (40 mg/d) were significantly lower than those on adjuvant therapy alone (goserelin, n = 28; leuprorelin, n = 15) at each time point in this 12-week clinical trial (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> &lt; .01). </Para><Para id="_44">Given these conflicting results in observational and randomized clinical trials, a large placebo effect is presumably at play, especially considering the subjective nature of many of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoint</GlossaryTermRef> measures.<Reference refidx="2"/>   Furthermore, the beneficial effect observed through an open-label study left unconfirmed through double-blind studies further obscured the understanding of the true effect of black cohosh in alleviating climacteric symptoms in this patient population; however, given the unlikely negative impact on breast cancer risk or recurrence,<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="13"/> along with evidence of relative safety, more research is warranted.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><Title>Noncancer Patients</Title><Para id="_46">The efficacy of black cohosh supplementation on vasomotor symptoms has also been evaluated in noncancer populations; however,  these findings to date remain inconsistent.</Para><Para id="_72">At least two meta-analyses have addressed questions about the specific effect of black cohosh supplements versus placebo. The first meta-analysis <Reference refidx="16"/> compared the effect of oral black cohosh monopreparations with that of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">control group</GlossaryTermRef>.  Participants in the control group were given <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000330178" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red clover</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045374" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fluoxetine</GlossaryTermRef>, or placebo. In three studies with placebo-control groups, there was no significant difference in hot flash frequency between the black cohosh group and the placebo group.  The second meta-analysis included six different randomized <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044014" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">controlled trials</GlossaryTermRef>  that investigated the efficacy of a single formulation of black cohosh (isopropanolic black cohosh extract [iCR]) in reducing climacteric symptomology (neurovegetative and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454766" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychological</GlossaryTermRef> menopausal symptoms) in perimenopausal and postmenopausal women.<Reference refidx="17"/>  Patients who received  iCR displayed significant reductions in climacteric symptoms when compared with patients who received the placebo. One study used a black cohosh/St. John’s wort <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000688810" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">combination therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, and the other five studies used iCR alone. This meta-analysis also found that women treated with higher doses of black cohosh <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">monotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> demonstrated the greatest improvement in climacteric symptomology.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><Para id="_75">A  comprehensive review of clinical trials that studied the use of black cohosh in noncancer menopausal and/or aging women was published in 2014. The review demonstrated that the overall heterogeneity of clinical evidence was due to major variation in exact <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454757" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intervention</GlossaryTermRef> materials and clinical endpoints.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="18"/>
 Variability in study results are possibly because of differences in extract preparation methods, potentially affecting the concentration of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043994" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alkaloid</GlossaryTermRef> constituents, which have not been previously studied in <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045733" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vitro</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774488" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical research</GlossaryTermRef>. Other factors that contributed to the heterogeneity included doses administered and study group characteristics.</Para><Para id="_48">Similarly, the  Herbal Alternatives for Menopause (HALT) study  investigated  the effect of  black cohosh (CimiPure®, 70% ethanol extract standardized to 2.5% triterpene glycosides, 160 mg/d) and an encapsulated  multibotanical-containing black cohosh (ProGyne; black cohosh, 200 mg/d, along with nine other ingredients),<Reference refidx="19"/> both of which failed to show a benefit greater than that of placebo.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_49">Randomized controlled investigations of black cohosh used as monopreparations <Reference refidx="16"/> or within multibotanical preparations <Reference refidx="20"/> have yet proven effective in reducing climacteric complaints among women without a history of breast cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Management of Other Conditions</Title><SummarySection id="_51"><Title>Bone mineral density</Title><Para id="_52">The therapeutic effects of black cohosh on bone metabolism have also been investigated as a secondary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> measure in a randomized, double-blind clinical trial, comparing results to that of conjugated estrogens (CE) and placebo.<Reference refidx="21"/> Daily administration of the black cohosh extract containing commercial product CR BNO 1055 (40 mg/d) demonstrated an effect equipotent to that of CE (0.6 mg) after 3 months of treatment. Analyses of bone turnover markers indicated a significant improvement above placebo values on bone metabolism  in both the black cohosh and CE groups (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0138,  both groups).<Reference refidx="21"/>  Unlike other groups, women treated with CR BNO 1055 displayed a significant increase in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044088" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">serum</GlossaryTermRef> bone-specific alkaline phosphatase levels (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0358), indicating increases in bone formation. The effect demonstrated with CE supplementation was comparable, though distinct; compared with placebo, women displayed a significant decrease in bone degradation, as measured by serum levels of the C-terminal breakdown product of bone-specific type-1 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044196" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">collagen</GlossaryTermRef> (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0181). Likewise, while the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797426" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mechanism of action</GlossaryTermRef> may be different than that of CE, black cohosh does appear to have an osteoprotective effect in postmenopausal women.<Reference refidx="21"/>  Potential benefits on bone metabolism are further supported in an uncontrolled trial by increases in osteocalcin levels in women receiving the supplement.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><Table id="_62"><Title>Table 1.  Clinical Studies of Black Cohosh in Patients With Cancer<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="7"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="13.17%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="20.06%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="3" ColWidth="13.26%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="4" ColWidth="13.26%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColNum="5" ColWidth="14.83%"/><ColSpec ColName="col5" ColNum="6" ColWidth="8.72%"/><ColSpec ColName="col6" ColNum="7" ColWidth="16.66%"/><THead><Row><entry Align="Center"> Reference</entry><entry Align="Center">Trial Design</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000651193" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Condition</GlossaryTermRef> Treated</entry><entry Align="Center">No. of Patients: Enrolled; Treated; Placebo or No Treatment Control<Superscript>b</Superscript></entry><entry Align="Center">Primary Outcome</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044011" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Concurrent Therapy</GlossaryTermRef> Used</entry><entry Align="Center"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Level of Evidence</GlossaryTermRef> Score<Superscript>c</Superscript></entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1">KMI = Kupperman Menopausal Index; LHRH-a  = luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone analogs; OR = odds ratio.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>For additional information and definition of terms, see text and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/dictionaries/cancer-terms/">NCI Dictionary of Cancer Terms</ExternalRef>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Number of patients treated plus number of patient controls may not equal number of patients enrolled; number of patients enrolled equals number of patients initially recruited/considered by the researchers who conducted a study; number of patients treated equals number of enrolled patients who were given the treatment being studied AND for whom results were reported.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col6" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>For information about levels of evidence analysis and scores, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Reference refidx="14"/> </entry><entry>Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled,  crossover trial</entry><entry>Hot flashes</entry><entry>131; 66; 65 (crossover in treated and placebo groups)</entry><entry>No difference in hot flashes from black cohosh compared with placebo after 8 weeks of treatment (primary outcome)</entry><entry>Various <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046367" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormonal therapies</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="15"/></entry><entry>Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled  trial</entry><entry>Hot flashes</entry><entry>85; 42; 43</entry><entry>No difference in the number of hot flashes from placebo at 57 to 60 days</entry><entry>Tamoxifen</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="3"/></entry><entry>Randomized controlled trial</entry><entry>Menopausal symptoms</entry><entry>85; 42; 43</entry><entry>Menopausal symptoms (measured by KMI) significantly lower in patients treated with black cohosh</entry><entry>LHRH-a</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335127" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iiC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="4"/></entry><entry>Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</entry><entry>Bone metabolism</entry><entry>62; 20 (black cohosh), 22 (conjugated estrogens); 20 (placebo)</entry><entry>Statistically significant increase in bone-specific alkaline phosphatase level</entry><entry>Unknown</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335121" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">1iC</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="11"/></entry><entry>Retrospective case-control</entry><entry>Breast cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000439419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prevention</GlossaryTermRef></entry><entry>101; 25; 76</entry><entry> Statistically significant OR (0.47) for developing breast cancer in women who took black cohosh supplements</entry><entry>Various therapies</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335135" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Di</LOERef></entry></Row><Row><entry><Reference refidx="13"/></entry><entry>Observational retrospective cohort</entry><entry>Breast cancer recurrence</entry><entry>18,861; 1,102; 17,759</entry><entry>Did not promote breast cancer recurrence or inhibit the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> effect of tamoxifen</entry><entry>Tamoxifen</entry><entry><LOERef href="CDR0000335135" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">2Di</LOERef></entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20032972">van Breemen RB, Liang W, Banuvar S, et al.: Pharmacokinetics of 23-epi-26-deoxyactein in women after oral administration of a standardized extract of black cohosh. Clin Pharmacol Ther 87 (2): 219-25, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="23439657">Fritz H, Seely D, McGowan J, et al.: Black cohosh and breast cancer: a systematic review. Integr Cancer Ther 13 (1): 12-29, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="30935866">Wang C, Huang Q, Liang CL, et al.: Effect of cimicifuga racemosa on menopausal syndrome caused by LHRH-a in breast cancer. J Ethnopharmacol 238: 111840, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="16645532">Wuttke W, Gorkow C, Seidlová-Wuttke D: Effects of black cohosh (Cimicifuga racemosa) on bone turnover, vaginal mucosa, and various blood parameters in postmenopausal women: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, and conjugated estrogens-controlled study. Menopause 13 (2): 185-96, 2006 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="5">Gafner S: Black Cohosh Laboratory Guidance Document. ABC-AHP-NCNPR Botanical Adulterants Program,  2015.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15356412">Cohen SM, O'Connor AM, Hart J, et al.: Autoimmune hepatitis associated with the use of black cohosh: a case study. Menopause 11 (5): 575-7, 2004 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21228727">Naser B, Schnitker J, Minkin MJ, et al.: Suspected black cohosh hepatotoxicity: no evidence by meta-analysis of randomized controlled clinical trials for isopropanolic black cohosh extract. Menopause 18 (4): 366-75, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="8">Foster S: Exploring the peripatetic maze of black cohosh adulteration: a review of the nomenclature, distribution, chemistry, market status, analytical methods, and safety. HerbalGram  (98): 32-51, 2013. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.herbalgram.org/resources/herbalgram/issues/98/table-of-contents/hg98feat-blackcohosh/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Gafner S: Botanical adulterants bulletin on adulteration of actaea racemosa. Black Cohosh - Botanical Adulterants Bulletin  1-5, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="16432272">Gurley B, Hubbard MA, Williams DK, et al.: Assessing the clinical significance of botanical supplementation on human cytochrome P450 3A activity: comparison of a milk thistle and black cohosh product to rifampin and clarithromycin. J Clin Pharmacol 46 (2): 201-13, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="17205521">Rebbeck TR, Troxel AB, Norman S, et al.: A retrospective case-control study of the use of hormone-related supplements and association with breast cancer. Int J Cancer 120 (7): 1523-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="25296437">Qiu F, McAlpine JB, Krause EC, et al.: Pharmacognosy of black cohosh: the phytochemical and biological profile of a major botanical dietary supplement. Prog Chem Org Nat Prod 99: 1-68, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="17416109">Henneicke-von Zepelin HH, Meden H, Kostev K, et al.: Isopropanolic black cohosh extract and recurrence-free survival after breast cancer. Int J Clin Pharmacol Ther 45 (3): 143-54, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="16782922">Pockaj BA, Gallagher JG, Loprinzi CL, et al.: Phase III double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled crossover trial of black cohosh in the management of hot flashes: NCCTG Trial N01CC1. J Clin Oncol 24 (18): 2836-41, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="11352967">Jacobson JS, Troxel AB, Evans J, et al.: Randomized trial of black cohosh for the treatment of hot flashes among women with a history of breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 19 (10): 2739-45, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="22972105">Leach MJ, Moore V: Black cohosh (Cimicifuga spp.) for menopausal symptoms. Cochrane Database Syst Rev  (9): CD007244, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="33021111">Castelo-Branco C, Gambacciani M, Cano A, et al.: Review &amp; meta-analysis: isopropanolic black cohosh extract iCR for menopausal symptoms - an update on the evidence. Climacteric 24 (2): 109-119, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="19609225">Geller SE, Shulman LP, van Breemen RB, et al.: Safety and efficacy of black cohosh and red clover for the management of vasomotor symptoms: a randomized controlled trial. Menopause 16 (6): 1156-66, 2009 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="16186076">Newton KM, Reed SD, Grothaus L, et al.: The Herbal Alternatives for Menopause (HALT) Study: background and study design. Maturitas 52 (2): 134-46, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="18257142">Reed SD, Newton KM, LaCroix AZ, et al.: Vaginal, endometrial, and reproductive hormone findings: randomized, placebo-controlled trial of black cohosh, multibotanical herbs, and dietary soy for vasomotor symptoms: the Herbal Alternatives for Menopause (HALT) Study. Menopause 15 (1): 51-8, 2008 Jan-Feb.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="12609561">Wuttke W, Seidlová-Wuttke D, Gorkow C: The Cimicifuga preparation BNO 1055 vs. conjugated estrogens in a double-blind placebo-controlled study: effects on menopause symptoms and bone markers. Maturitas 44 (Suppl 1): S67-77, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="16837890">Raus K, Brucker C, Gorkow C, et al.: First-time proof of endometrial safety of the special black cohosh extract (Actaea or Cimicifuga racemosa extract) CR BNO 1055. Menopause 13 (4): 678-91, 2006 Jul-Aug.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><Title>Adverse Effects</Title><Para id="_54">In general, the hydroalcoholic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321355" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">black cohosh</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">extracts</GlossaryTermRef> that are widely used as components in commercially available products—and those used in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef>—have been very well tolerated, producing rare serious <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044922" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">adverse effects</GlossaryTermRef>, which are likely due to product quality issues (adulteration) rather than black cohosh itself. An overview of the adverse events from a systematic review of the results of several clinical trials, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689749" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">postmarketing  surveillance studies</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044006" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case series</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044007" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">case reports</GlossaryTermRef> found only rare serious adverse events that may not have been induced by black cohosh.<Reference refidx="1"/> The most common minor adverse effects noted in these trials were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef> (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390302" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nausea</GlossaryTermRef>) and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044938" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">musculoskeletal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407758" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">disorders</GlossaryTermRef> (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000458080" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">joint</GlossaryTermRef> pain, rashes).<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><SummarySection id="_55"><Title>Herb-Drug Interactions</Title><Para id="_56">A small number of studies have explored the potential for black cohosh extracts to interfere with the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046173" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metabolism</GlossaryTermRef> or activity of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000348921" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">drugs</GlossaryTermRef>. One group studied the <ScientificName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">in vivo</GlossaryTermRef></ScientificName> effect of black cohosh extracts on cytochrome P450 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef> at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044664" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">doses</GlossaryTermRef> up to 1,090 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mg</GlossaryTermRef> bid (0.2% triterpene glycosides) and found only weak inhibition of CYP2D6 <Reference refidx="2"/>  and no effect on CYP3A4.<Reference refidx="3"/> A single case report suggested a possible effect of a black cohosh extract on reducing the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000407756" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cholesterol</GlossaryTermRef>-lowering effects of statins.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18984078">Borrelli F, Ernst E: Black cohosh (Cimicifuga racemosa): a systematic review of adverse events. Am J Obstet Gynecol 199 (5): 455-66, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15900287">Gurley BJ, Gardner SF, Hubbard MA, et al.: In vivo effects of goldenseal, kava kava, black cohosh, and valerian on human cytochrome P450 1A2, 2D6, 2E1, and 3A4/5 phenotypes. Clin Pharmacol Ther 77 (5): 415-26, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="18214849">Gurley BJ, Swain A, Hubbard MA, et al.: Clinical assessment of CYP2D6-mediated herb-drug interactions in humans: effects of milk thistle, black cohosh, goldenseal, kava kava, St. John's wort, and Echinacea. Mol Nutr Food Res 52 (7): 755-63, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28762712">Asher GN, Corbett AH, Hawke RL: Common Herbal Dietary Supplement-Drug Interactions. Am Fam Physician 96 (2): 101-107, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><Title>Summary of the Evidence for Black Cohosh  </Title><Para id="_58">To assist readers in evaluating the results of human studies of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044964" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">integrative, alternative, and complementary therapies</GlossaryTermRef> for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the strength of the evidence (i.e., the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446533" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">levels of evidence</GlossaryTermRef>) associated with each type of treatment is provided whenever possible. To qualify for a level of evidence <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390238" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">analysis</GlossaryTermRef>, a study must:</Para><ItemizedList id="_59" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Be published in a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000537399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">peer-reviewed scientific journal</GlossaryTermRef> and include sufficient parameters about the quality and reproducibility of the investigated material derived from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000321355" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">black cohosh</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Report on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000043985" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">therapeutic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000467853" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">outcome</GlossaryTermRef> or outcomes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044085" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">response</GlossaryTermRef>, improvement in survival, or measured improvement in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of life</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Describe <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044168" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical</GlossaryTermRef> findings in sufficient detail for a meaningful evaluation to be made.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_60">Separate levels of evidence scores are assigned to qualifying human studies on the basis of statistical strength of the study design and scientific strength of the treatment outcomes (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000346519" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">endpoints</GlossaryTermRef>) measured. The resulting two scores are then combined to produce an overall score. For an explanation of the scores and additional information about levels of evidence analysis of CAM treatments for cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">Levels of Evidence for Human Studies of Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_61">The Committee on Herbal Medicinal Products of the European Medicines Agency describes black cohosh products as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000482419" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">medicine</GlossaryTermRef> that may be used for the treatment of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopausal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045022" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">symptoms</GlossaryTermRef>, based on their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430407" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">assessment</GlossaryTermRef> of the results of around 20 <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045961" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clinical trials</GlossaryTermRef> involving over 6,000 patients who received black cohosh.<Reference refidx="1"/> However, the lack of demonstration of a clinical benefit significantly greater than that of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046688" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">placebo</GlossaryTermRef> and the fact that much less research has been performed with cancer patients should lead to extra caution when its use in such patients is being considered .</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Cimicifugae Rhizoma. Amsterdam,
The Netherlands: European Medicines Agency, 2018. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/medicines/herbal/cimicifugae-rhizoma">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed September 18, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (10/31/2024)</Title><Para id="_79">The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044271" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PDQ</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045333" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cancer</GlossaryTermRef> information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_80">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803263#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/black-cohosh-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of black cohosh in people with cancer.. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/cam">PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000256874" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/cam">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. PDQ Black Cohosh. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/black-cohosh-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/cam/hp/black-cohosh-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 33433969]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2021-01-08</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-31</DateLastModified></Summary>
