<Summary id="CDR0000803507" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Evidence-based, expert-reviewed summary about hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC), including information about the FH gene.  This summary also contains information about screening for HLRCC,  clinical presentation, management, and prognosis of HLRCC.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000599273">hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_782">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC). It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians who care for HLRCC patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_783">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_362"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_594">Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) is characterized by the presence of one or more of the following: <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765494" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cutaneous leiomyomas</GlossaryTermRef> (or leiomyomata), uterine leiomyomas (fibroids) in females, and renal cell cancer (RCC). <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> are responsible for the susceptibility to HLRCC.  <GeneName>FH</GeneName> encodes fumarate hydratase, the enzyme that catalyzes the conversion of fumarate to malate in the tricarboxylic acid cycle  (Krebs cycle).  </Para><SummarySection id="_376"><Title>Nomenclature</Title><Para id="_377">Historically, the predisposition to the development of cutaneous leiomyomas was referred to as multiple cutaneous leiomyomatosis. In 1973, two <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460158" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">kindreds</GlossaryTermRef> were described in which multiple members over three generations exhibited cutaneous leiomyomas and uterine leiomyomas and/or leiomyosarcomas inherited in an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> pattern.<Reference refidx="1"/> That report also described a woman aged 20 years with uterine leiomyosarcoma and metastatic RCC. Subsequently, the association of cutaneous and uterine leiomyomas became known as Reed syndrome. However, the clear association of cutaneous leiomyomas and RCC was not described until 2001, when a study reported two Finnish families in whom cutaneous and uterine leiomyomas and papillary type 2 RCC <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460139" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cosegregated</GlossaryTermRef> <Reference refidx="2"/> and the name hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) was introduced. </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="4127477">Reed WB, Walker R, Horowitz R: Cutaneous leiomyomata with uterine leiomyomata. Acta Derm Venereol 53 (5): 409-16, 1973.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11248088">Launonen V, Vierimaa O, Kiuru M, et al.: Inherited susceptibility to uterine leiomyomas and renal cell cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 98 (6): 3387-92, 2001.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_628"><Title>Genetics</Title><SummarySection id="_378"><Title><GeneName>FH</GeneName> Gene</Title><Para id="_643">The <GeneName>FH</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> consists of ten <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460146" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">exons</GlossaryTermRef> encompassing 22.15 kb of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044393" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef>. The gene is highly conserved across species. The human <GeneName>FH</GeneName> gene is located on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 1q42.3-43.</Para><Para id="_28">Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>. An individual can be predisposed to HLRCC disease manifestations when he/she inherits a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339341" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> gene.<Reference refidx="1"/> Various <GeneName>FH</GeneName> pathogenic variants  have been identified in families with HLRCC. Most are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense variants</GlossaryTermRef>. However,  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783965" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">nonsense variants</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783963" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">frameshift variants</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783968" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">splice-site variants</GlossaryTermRef>, and whole-gene/partial <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deletions</GlossaryTermRef> have also been identified and described.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> </Para><Para id="_380">Renal tumors that develop in individuals who inherit a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781852" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in <GeneName>FH</GeneName>  typically display a  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000464169" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">loss of heterozygosity</GlossaryTermRef> because of a second <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variant. This finding suggests that loss of function of the fumarate hydratase protein is the basis for tumor formation in HLRCC and supports a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046657" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">tumor suppressor</GlossaryTermRef> function for <GeneName>FH</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  </Para><Para id="_3160">Inherited <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">biallelic</GlossaryTermRef>  pathogenic variants in the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> gene (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339342" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">homozygous</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766214" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">compound heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef>) can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339339" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal recessive</GlossaryTermRef> fumarate hydratase deficiency (FHD) (also abbreviated as FMRD), a disorder characterized by rapid, progressive neonatal neurological impairment that includes hypotonia, seizures, and cerebral atrophy.  For more information, see the  <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_442" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Genetically Related Disorders</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_382"><Title>Prevalence</Title><Para id="_3161">Prevalence estimates for HLRCC are evolving. Older estimates suggested a prevalence of 1 in 200,000 individuals.<Reference refidx="8"/> However, an analysis of nonpopulation-based cohorts found an <GeneName>FH</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460226" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carrier frequency</GlossaryTermRef> of 1 in 1,000 individuals, suggesting a larger number of asymptomatic cases than previously thought.<Reference refidx="9"/>  A clinical database analysis of over 120,000 records from individuals undergoing hereditary cancer genetic testing estimated a carrier frequency of 1 in 2,668 (0.04%). These estimates reflect the high rate of <GeneName>FH</GeneName> pathogenic variants that were  detected incidentally in individuals undergoing cancer genetic testing for other indications. This finding suggests that HLRCC may be one of the most common <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">hereditary cancer syndromes</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_384"><Title>Penetrance of <GeneName>FH</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_385">On the basis of the observation that most patients with HLRCC have at least one of the three major clinical manifestations, the  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of HLRCC in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef> of pathogenic <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variants appears to be very high.   However, the estimated cumulative lifetime incidence of renal cell cancer (RCC) varies widely, with most estimates ranging from 15% to 30% in families with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>FH</GeneName> pathogenic variants, depending on ascertainment method and the imaging modalities used.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> A 2020 study showed that <GeneName>FH</GeneName> pathogenic variants have been detected at a higher rate than previously thought, indicating that lifetime risk of kidney cancer in individuals with HLRCC may be significantly lower than current estimates suggest.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_3162">A study that analyzed patients undergoing cancer genetic testing suggested that  RCC may be more common in males with HLRCC than in females with HLRCC.<Reference refidx="10"/> Several studies have also reported an enrichment of  <GeneName>FH</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants in individuals with RCC and African ancestry.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_386"><Title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</Title><Para id="_3163">Correlations between specific <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variants and the occurrence of cutaneous/uterine leiomyomas, RCC, or other primary features of HLRCC have not been reported.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_3164">However, certain <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variants (primarily missense variants) seem to be associated with an increased risk for paraganglioma (PGL)/pheochromocytoma (PHEO) in the absence of other HLRCC features.<Reference refidx="15"/> Three recurrent variants with increased PGL/PHEO risk have been reported in the literature: (1) p.Thr234Ala, (2) p.Ala273Thr, and (3) p.Ala194Thr.  Conversely, <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variants associated with autosomal dominant HLRCC and  autosomal recessive FHD do not seem to correlate with increased PGL/PHEO risk. Although PGL/PHEO <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> is not included in HLRCC guidelines, the authors suggest that surveillance similar to that which is recommended for <GeneName>SDHx</GeneName> carriers may be warranted. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_391" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Surveillance</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_556"><Title>Sequence Analysis</Title><Para id="_437">Using bidirectional DNA sequencing methodology, pathogenic variants in <GeneName>FH</GeneName> have been detected in more than 85% of individuals with HLRCC.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="16"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_442"><Title>Genetically Related Disorders</Title><SummarySection id="_558"><Title>Fumarate hydratase deficiency (fumaric aciduria, FHD)</Title><Para id="_444">  FHD (also abbreviated as FMRD) is an autosomal recessive disorder that results  from the inheritance of biallelic pathogenic variants in the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> gene. This inborn error of metabolism is characterized by rapid, progressive neurological impairment that includes  hypotonia, seizures, and cerebral atrophy. Homozygous or compound heterozygous germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>FH</GeneName> are found in individuals with FHD.<Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>  To date, RCC has not been reported in FHD-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">affected individuals</GlossaryTermRef>, possibly because most individuals with FHD survive only a few months with  very few surviving to early adulthood.<Reference refidx="19"/> However, a parent (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339341" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef> carrier) of an individual with FHD developed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765494" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cutaneous leiomyomas</GlossaryTermRef> similar to those observed in HLRCC.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_3165">Four <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variants are thought to be associated with FHD: (1)  p.Lys477dup, (2) p.Pro174Arg, (3) p.Gln376Pro, and (4) p.Ala308Gly.<Reference refidx="20"/> The most common variant found in individuals with FHD is the in-frame duplication, c.1431_1433dupAAA (also known as p.Lys477dup).  This variant has been observed in 0.5% of the Ashkenazi Jewish population. </Para><Para id="_3166">While multiple studies have demonstrated that certain biallelic <GeneName>FH</GeneName> pathogenic variants  can cause autosomal recessive FHD, these variants are not associated with HLRCC when  in the heterozygous state.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="20"/>  Hence, the common FHD variant, p.Lys477dup, is not thought to be associated with an increased risk of RCC. However, the p.Lys477dup variant is associated with autosomal recessive FHD when found in conjunction with another <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variant (i.e., p.Lys477dup on one <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339337" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">allele</GlossaryTermRef> and a different <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variant on the other allele) and not when it is  in the homozygous state (i.e., when an individual carries two p.Lys477dup variants). This finding suggests that the p.Lys477dup variant has some residual function. Individuals in these studies who carried the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> p.Lys477dup variant and had RCC shared similarities  with individuals who had sporadic forms of kidney cancer, like higher prevalences of clear cell RCC and later ages of RCC onset.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_559"><Title>Somatic <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variants</Title><Para id="_446">Biallelic somatic loss of <GeneName>FH</GeneName> has been identified in two early-onset <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic</GlossaryTermRef> uterine leiomyomas and a soft tissue sarcoma of the lower limb without other associated tumor characteristics of the heritable disease.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/> Few somatic <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variants have been identified in sporadic forms of RCC.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="23"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12761039">Alam NA, Rowan AJ, Wortham NC, et al.: Genetic and functional analyses of FH mutations in multiple cutaneous and uterine leiomyomatosis, hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cancer, and fumarate hydratase deficiency. Hum Mol Genet 12 (11): 1241-52, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11865300">Tomlinson IP, Alam NA, Rowan AJ, et al.: Germline mutations in FH predispose to dominantly inherited uterine fibroids, skin leiomyomata and papillary renal cell cancer. Nat Genet 30 (4): 406-10, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="12772087" MedlineID="22696721">Toro JR, Nickerson ML, Wei MH, et al.: Mutations in the fumarate hydratase gene cause hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer in families in North America. Am J Hum Genet 73 (1): 95-106, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15937070">Wei MH, Toure O, Glenn GM, et al.: Novel mutations in FH and expansion of the spectrum of phenotypes expressed in families with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. J Med Genet 43 (1): 18-27, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18366737">Bayley JP, Launonen V, Tomlinson IP: The FH mutation database: an online database of fumarate hydratase mutations involved in the MCUL (HLRCC) tumor syndrome and congenital fumarase deficiency. BMC Med Genet 9: 20, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="28196407">Vocke CD, Ricketts CJ, Merino MJ, et al.: Comprehensive genomic and phenotypic characterization of germline FH deletion in hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell carcinoma. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 56 (6): 484-492, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="11248088">Launonen V, Vierimaa O, Kiuru M, et al.: Inherited susceptibility to uterine leiomyomas and renal cell cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 98 (6): 3387-92, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="31831373">Forde C, Lim DHK, Alwan Y, et al.: Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer: Clinical, Molecular, and Screening Features in a Cohort of 185 Affected Individuals. Eur Urol Oncol 3 (6): 764-772, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="32413184">Shuch B, Li S, Risch H, et al.: Estimation of the carrier frequency of fumarate hydratase alterations and implications for kidney cancer risk in hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cancer. Cancer 126 (16): 3657-3666, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="34724198">Lu E, Hatchell KE, Nielsen SM, et al.: Fumarate hydratase variant prevalence and manifestations among individuals receiving germline testing. Cancer 128 (4): 675-684, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="16029320">Alam NA, Olpin S, Leigh IM: Fumarate hydratase mutations and predisposition to cutaneous leiomyomas, uterine leiomyomas and renal cancer. Br J Dermatol 153 (1): 11-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="18476789">Pfaffenroth EC, Linehan WM: Genetic basis for kidney cancer: opportunity for disease-specific approaches to therapy. Expert Opin Biol Ther 8 (6): 779-90, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="17509289">Grubb RL, Franks ME, Toro J, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer: a syndrome associated with an aggressive form of inherited renal cancer. J Urol 177 (6): 2074-9; discussion 2079-80, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="33789101">Abou Alaiwi S, Nassar AH, Adib E, et al.: Trans-ethnic variation in germline variants of patients with renal cell carcinoma. Cell Rep 34 (13): 108926, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="36773955">Zavoshi S, Lu E, Boutros PC, et al.: Fumarate Hydratase Variants and Their Association With Paraganglioma/Pheochromocytoma. Urology 176: 106-114, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="15724016">Alam NA, Barclay E, Rowan AJ, et al.: Clinical features of multiple cutaneous and uterine leiomyomatosis: an underdiagnosed tumor syndrome. Arch Dermatol 141 (2): 199-206, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="9635293">Coughlin EM, Christensen E, Kunz PL, et al.: Molecular analysis and prenatal diagnosis of human fumarase deficiency. Mol Genet Metab 63 (4): 254-62, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="8200987">Bourgeron T, Chretien D, Poggi-Bach J, et al.: Mutation of the fumarase gene in two siblings with progressive encephalopathy and fumarase deficiency. J Clin Invest 93 (6): 2514-8, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="19939761">Badeloe S, Frank J: Clinical and molecular genetic aspects of hereditary multiple cutaneous leiomyomatosis. Eur J Dermatol 19 (6): 545-51, 2009 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="34994643">Kamihara J, Horton C, Tian Y, et al.: Different Fumarate Hydratase Gene Variants Are Associated With Distinct Cancer Phenotypes. JCO Precis Oncol 5: 1568-1578, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="12183404">Kiuru M, Lehtonen R, Arola J, et al.: Few FH mutations in sporadic counterparts of tumor types observed in hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer families. Cancer Res 62 (16): 4554-7, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="14695314">Lehtonen R, Kiuru M, Vanharanta S, et al.: Biallelic inactivation of fumarate hydratase (FH) occurs in nonsyndromic uterine leiomyomas but is rare in other tumors. Am J Pathol 164 (1): 17-22, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="26536169">Linehan WM, Spellman PT, Ricketts CJ, et al.: Comprehensive Molecular Characterization of Papillary Renal-Cell Carcinoma. N Engl J Med 374 (2): 135-45, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_629"><Title>Molecular Biology</Title><Para id="_647">The mechanisms by which alterations in <GeneName>FH</GeneName> lead to hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) are currently under investigation. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Biallelic</GlossaryTermRef> inactivation of <GeneName>FH</GeneName> has been shown to result in loss of oxidative phosphorylation and reliance on aerobic glycolysis to meet cellular energy requirements. Interruption of the Krebs cycle because of reduced or absent fumarate hydratase activity results in increased levels of intracellular fumarate. This increase inhibits the activity of hypoxia-inducible factor (HIF) prolyl hydroxylases, resulting in the accumulation of HIF-alpha.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  Inactivating variants of <GeneName>FH</GeneName> also appear to result in the generation of reactive oxygen species, further contributing to the stabilization of HIF-alpha.<Reference refidx="3"/> Activation of the HIF pathway leads to a pseudohypoxic state and an upregulation of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcriptional</GlossaryTermRef> program contributing to aggressive tumor growth.<Reference refidx="4"/> In addition, accumulated fumarate can activate the antioxidant response pathway which enables cancer cells to survive in an environment of oxidative stress. Fumarate, an electrophile, is able to posttranslationally modify KEAP1 by succination on cysteine sulfhydryls,<Reference refidx="5"/> thereby releasing KEAP1 inhibition of NRF2. The resultant stabilization of NRF2 leads to transcriptional upregulation of antioxidant response element–controlled <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> such as <GeneName>AKR1B10</GeneName>, possibly contributing to the neoplastic process.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="16098467">Isaacs JS, Jung YJ, Mole DR, et al.: HIF overexpression correlates with biallelic loss of fumarate hydratase in renal cancer: novel role of fumarate in regulation of HIF stability. Cancer Cell 8 (2): 143-53, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15987702">Pollard PJ, Brière JJ, Alam NA, et al.: Accumulation of Krebs cycle intermediates and over-expression of HIF1alpha in tumours which result from germline FH and SDH mutations. Hum Mol Genet 14 (15): 2231-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="19470762">Sudarshan S, Sourbier C, Kong HS, et al.: Fumarate hydratase deficiency in renal cancer induces glycolytic addiction and hypoxia-inducible transcription factor 1alpha stabilization by glucose-dependent generation of reactive oxygen species. Mol Cell Biol 29 (15): 4080-90, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15586379">Pollard P, Wortham N, Barclay E, et al.: Evidence of increased microvessel density and activation of the hypoxia pathway in tumours from the hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer syndrome. J Pathol 205 (1): 41-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="16624247">Alderson NL, Wang Y, Blatnik M, et al.: S-(2-Succinyl)cysteine: a novel chemical modification of tissue proteins by a Krebs cycle intermediate. Arch Biochem Biophys 450 (1): 1-8, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="22014576">Ooi A, Wong JC, Petillo D, et al.: An antioxidant response phenotype shared between hereditary and sporadic type 2 papillary renal cell carcinoma. Cancer Cell 20 (4): 511-23, 2011.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_630"><Title>Clinical Manifestations</Title><Para id="_364">The clinical characteristics of hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765494" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cutaneous leiomyomas</GlossaryTermRef>, uterine leiomyomas (fibroids), and renal cell cancer (RCC).  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Affected individuals</GlossaryTermRef> may have multiple cutaneous leiomyomas, a single skin leiomyoma, or no cutaneous lesion; an RCC that is typically solitary, or no renal tumors; and/or uterine leiomyomas.  HLRCC is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotypically</GlossaryTermRef> variable; disease severity shows significant intrafamilial and interfamilial variation.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><SummarySection id="_542"><Title>Cutaneous Leiomyomas</Title><Para id="_366">Cutaneous leiomyomas present as firm papules or nodules that appear pink or reddish-brown. These lesions usually appear on the trunk, on the extremities, and occasionally on the face. These  lesions occur at a mean age of 25 years (age range, 10–47 y) and often increase in size and number with age. Lesions are sensitive to light touch and/or cold temperature. They can also be painful.  Pain is correlated with severity of cutaneous involvement.<Reference refidx="3"/> The presence of multiple cutaneous leiomyomas is often indicative of HLRCC, and  therefore, warrants a genetic workup. One series reported the presence of cutaneous leiomyomas in 22 of 48 patients (46%) with a pathogenic or likely <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in <GeneName>FH</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="4"/> The same series demonstrated that 18 of 19 individuals (95%) with multiple leiomyomas had a pathogenic variant in <GeneName>FH</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="4"/> Therefore, the presence of a solitary leiomyoma  requires careful analysis of an individual's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family history</GlossaryTermRef>.  For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_453" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Clinical diagnosis</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_458" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Differential diagnosis</SummaryRef> sections.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_543"><Title>Uterine Leiomyomas</Title><Para id="_368">The onset of uterine leiomyomas in women with HLRCC occurs at a younger age than in women in the general population. The age at diagnosis ranges from 18 to 63 years (mean age, 30 y). One series reported uterine leiomyomas in 18 of 29 women (62%) with a pathogenic or likely pathogenic variant in <GeneName>FH</GeneName>; the ages of the women ranged from 24 to 63 years.<Reference refidx="4"/> Uterine leiomyomas are usually large and numerous.  Most women with HLRCC experience irregular or heavy menstruation and pelvic pain; thus, they require treatment for leiomyomas at a younger age than women in the general population.  Women with HLRCC undergo hysterectomy or myomectomy for symptomatic uterine leiomyomas at a younger age (&lt;30 y) than women in the general population (median age, 45 y).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_544"><Title>Renal Cell Cancers (RCCs)</Title><Para id="_370">The symptoms of RCC may include hematuria, lower back pain, and a palpable mass. However, a large number of individuals with RCC are asymptomatic. Furthermore, not all individuals with HLRCC present with or develop RCC.  Most RCCs are unilateral and solitary; in a few individuals, they are multifocal.  The exact incidence of RCC in affected individuals remains to be determined, and widely varying estimates have been provided by different groups (1%–60%).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="8"/> The incidence appears to vary on the basis of where the study was performed, the referral patterns of individual groups, and the extent to which individuals were screened for RCC. In studies from the National Cancer Institute (NCI), RCC was identified in approximately 32% of families evaluated.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/> The median age at detection of RCC was 37 years,<Reference refidx="9"/> although some cases have been reported to occur as early as age 10 years.<Reference refidx="10"/> Another large series of 135 patients estimated that the lifetime risk was 20.8% by age 85 years.<Reference refidx="11"/> In contrast to other hereditary RCC syndromes, RCCs associated with HLRCC are aggressive,<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> with a Fuhrman nuclear grade of 3 or 4 in many cases and 9 of 13 individuals dying from metastatic disease within 5 years of diagnosis.<Reference refidx="3"/> <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_801" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Figure 1</SummaryRef> depicts RCCs in a patient with HLRCC.</Para><Para id="_801"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000778864" type="image/jpeg" alt="Axial view of an individual’s midsection showing tumors in both kidneys. The left kidney has a small tumor and the right kidney has a larger tumor. A retroperitoneal lymph node is shown beside the larger tumor." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_796"><Caption language="en">Figure 1.  Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer–associated renal tumors are commonly unilateral and solitary; in a few individuals, they are multifocal. Red arrow indicates a retroperitoneal lymph node. White arrow indicates a left renal mass.</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_545"><Title>Uterine Leiomyosarcomas</Title><Para id="_373">It is unclear whether women with HLRCC have a higher risk of developing uterine leiomyosarcomas than women of similar age in the general population. In the original description of HLRCC, it was reported that 2 of 11 women with uterine leiomyomas also had a uterine leiomyosarcoma, a cancer that may be clinically aggressive if not detected and treated at an early stage.<Reference refidx="2"/> To date, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781852" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in <GeneName>FH</GeneName> have been reported in six women with uterine leiomyosarcoma.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> It seems that most <GeneName>FH</GeneName> pathogenic variant–positive families are not highly predisposed to uterine cancer, but a few individuals and families appear to be at high risk. In North American studies, no uterine leiomyosarcomas in HLRCC  individuals or families have been reported.<Reference refidx="3"/> Therefore, the risk of uterine leiomyosarcoma in women with HLRCC is uncertain. This is a question in urgent need of a definitive answer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_546"><Title>Other Manifestations</Title><Para id="_375">Four <GeneName>FH</GeneName>-positive cases with breast cancer, one case of bladder cancer, and one case of bilateral macronodular adrenocortical disease with Cushing syndrome have been reported. A series from the NCI found that 20 of 255 patients (7.8%) with HLRCC had adrenal nodules, some  of which did not appear to be adenomas based on imaging characteristics. Resections were performed on  many of these lesions since they were fluorodeoxyglucose avid. All of the lesions showed evidence of both micronodular  and macronodular adrenal hyperplasia, suggesting that adrenal nodules could be an additional manifestation of HLRCC.<Reference refidx="16"/> It remains to be determined if these manifestations are truly part of the HLRCC <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="17"/> Similarly, pheochromocytomas (PHEOS) have been reported in the adrenal glands of individuals with HLRCC.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="18"/> However, one of the largest cohorts from the United Kingdom did not report PHEOs in individuals with HLRCC. Therefore, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> of PHEOs is not recommended unless further evidence shows that this tumor  is part of the HLRCC phenotype.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15937070">Wei MH, Toure O, Glenn GM, et al.: Novel mutations in FH and expansion of the spectrum of phenotypes expressed in families with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. J Med Genet 43 (1): 18-27, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11248088">Launonen V, Vierimaa O, Kiuru M, et al.: Inherited susceptibility to uterine leiomyomas and renal cell cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 98 (6): 3387-92, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="12772087" MedlineID="22696721">Toro JR, Nickerson ML, Wei MH, et al.: Mutations in the fumarate hydratase gene cause hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer in families in North America. Am J Hum Genet 73 (1): 95-106, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="29423582">Bhola PT, Gilpin C, Smith A, et al.: A retrospective review of 48 individuals, including 12 families, molecularly diagnosed with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC). Fam Cancer 17 (4): 615-620, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="11814502">Farquhar CM, Steiner CA: Hysterectomy rates in the United States 1990-1997. Obstet Gynecol 99 (2): 229-34, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15724016">Alam NA, Barclay E, Rowan AJ, et al.: Clinical features of multiple cutaneous and uterine leiomyomatosis: an underdiagnosed tumor syndrome. Arch Dermatol 141 (2): 199-206, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="19075141">Stewart L, Glenn GM, Stratton P, et al.: Association of germline mutations in the fumarate hydratase gene and uterine fibroids in women with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. Arch Dermatol 144 (12): 1584-92, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28300276">Muller M, Ferlicot S, Guillaud-Bataille M, et al.: Reassessing the clinical spectrum associated with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell carcinoma syndrome in French FH mutation carriers. Clin Genet 92 (6): 606-615, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="24378414">Shuch B, Vourganti S, Ricketts CJ, et al.: Defining early-onset kidney cancer: implications for germline and somatic mutation testing and clinical management. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 431-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="24526232">Wong MH, Tan CS, Lee SC, et al.: Potential genetic anticipation in hereditary leiomyomatosis-renal cell cancer (HLRCC). Fam Cancer 13 (2): 281-9, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="31831373">Forde C, Lim DHK, Alwan Y, et al.: Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer: Clinical, Molecular, and Screening Features in a Cohort of 185 Affected Individuals. Eur Urol Oncol 3 (6): 764-772, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="17509289">Grubb RL, Franks ME, Toro J, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer: a syndrome associated with an aggressive form of inherited renal cancer. J Urol 177 (6): 2074-9; discussion 2079-80, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="20059341">Linehan WM, Bratslavsky G, Pinto PA, et al.: Molecular diagnosis and therapy of kidney cancer. Annu Rev Med 61: 329-43, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="16155190">Lehtonen HJ, Kiuru M, Ylisaukko-Oja SK, et al.: Increased risk of cancer in patients with fumarate hydratase germline mutation. J Med Genet 43 (6): 523-6, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="16477632">Ylisaukko-oja SK, Kiuru M, Lehtonen HJ, et al.: Analysis of fumarate hydratase mutations in a population-based series of early onset uterine leiomyosarcoma patients. Int J Cancer 119 (2): 283-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="22982371">Shuch B, Ricketts CJ, Vocke CD, et al.: Adrenal nodular hyperplasia in hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. J Urol 189 (2): 430-5, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="15741255">Matyakhina L, Freedman RJ, Bourdeau I, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis associated with bilateral, massive, macronodular adrenocortical disease and atypical cushing syndrome: a clinical and molecular genetic investigation. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 90 (6): 3773-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="25004247">Clark GR, Sciacovelli M, Gaude E, et al.: Germline FH mutations presenting with pheochromocytoma. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 99 (10): E2046-50, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_577"><Title>Histopathology</Title><SummarySection id="_651"><Title>Cutaneous Leiomyomas</Title><Para id="_652"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765494" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Cutaneous leiomyomas</GlossaryTermRef> are believed to arise from the arrectores pilorum muscles attached to the hair follicles. Histologically, these are dermal tumors that spare the epidermis. Morphologically, these tumors have interlacing smooth muscle fibers interspersed with collagen fibers.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_649"><Title>Uterine Leiomyomas</Title><Para id="_650">A review of the National Cancer Institute's experience with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC)-associated uterine leiomyomas reported that most of these cases were well-circumscribed fascicular tumors with occasional cases showing increased cellularity and atypia. The hallmark feature of these cases was similar to those observed in HLRCC kidney cancer: the presence of orangeophilic, prominent nucleoli that are surrounded by a perinuclear halo. While some cases had atypical features, no cases had tumor necrosis or atypical mitosis suggestive of malignancy or leiomyosarcoma.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_648"><Title>RCC</Title><Para id="_371">The renal cell cancers (RCCs) associated with HLRCC have unique histological features, including the presence of cells with abundant amphophilic cytoplasm and large nuclei with large inclusion-like eosinophilic nucleoli. These cytologic features were attributed to type 2 papillary tumors in the original description.<Reference refidx="3"/> However, early studies reported that HLRCC is associated with a spectrum of renal tumors ranging from type 2 papillary to tubulopapillary to collecting duct carcinoma.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>   RCC associated with HLRCC may constitute a new renal pathologic entity or a unique HLRCC type. Two studies reported the morphologic spectrum of RCC in HLRCC syndrome after histological examinations of 40 RCCs from 38 patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>FH</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> and HLRCC family histories.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>   A number of histological patterns were seen, including cystic, tubulopapillary, tubulo-solid, and often mixed patterns.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10671972">Fearfield LA, Smith JR, Bunker CB, et al.: Association of multiple familial cutaneous leiomyoma with a uterine symplastic leiomyoma. Clin Exp Dermatol 25 (1): 44-7, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="23211287">Sanz-Ortega J, Vocke C, Stratton P, et al.: Morphologic and molecular characteristics of uterine leiomyomas in hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cancer (HLRCC) syndrome. Am J Surg Pathol 37 (1): 74-80, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11248088">Launonen V, Vierimaa O, Kiuru M, et al.: Inherited susceptibility to uterine leiomyomas and renal cell cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 98 (6): 3387-92, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15937070">Wei MH, Toure O, Glenn GM, et al.: Novel mutations in FH and expansion of the spectrum of phenotypes expressed in families with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. J Med Genet 43 (1): 18-27, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="17895761">Merino MJ, Torres-Cabala C, Pinto P, et al.: The morphologic spectrum of kidney tumors in hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell carcinoma (HLRCC) syndrome. Am J Surg Pathol 31 (10): 1578-85, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Merino MJ, Torres-Cabala CA, Zbar B, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell carcinoma syndrome (HLRCC): Clinical histopathological and molecular features of the first American families described. [Abstract] Mod Pathol  16 (Suppl): A-739, 162A, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_632"><Title>Management</Title><SummarySection id="_504"><Title>Diagnosis and Testing</Title><Para id="_505">Genetic testing for the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is clinically available and performed by Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)-certified laboratories. <GeneName>FH</GeneName> currently is the only gene known to be associated with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC). Most patients with HLRCC have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781852" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in <GeneName>FH</GeneName>.</Para><Para id="_654">Because the genetic analysis of HLRCC is complex, any interpretation of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556493" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant of unknown significance</GlossaryTermRef> result needs to be performed with consultation by clinical cancer geneticists, ideally in a center that has significant experience with this disease.</Para><SummarySection id="_453"><Title>Clinical diagnosis</Title><Para id="_454">There is no current consensus on the diagnostic criteria for HLRCC.<Reference refidx="1"/> Available guidelines were created during a previous era of histological classification when FH-deficient papillary renal cell carcinoma (RCC) was classified as type 2 papillary RCC. Suggested guidelines may need to be updated based on this RCC classification change, the availability of immunohistochemical stains to identify loss of FH, and the presence of 2SC in tissue manifestations.</Para><Para id="_455">Some experts suggest that a clinical dermatologic diagnosis of HLRCC requires <Strong>one</Strong> of the following:<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_456" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Multiple <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000765494" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cutaneous leiomyomas</GlossaryTermRef> with at least one histologically confirmed leiomyoma.</ListItem><ListItem>A single leiomyoma in the presence of a positive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of HLRCC.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_655">More recent comprehensive criteria for diagnosis have been suggested and are often used by experts in the field. Suggested criteria include dermatologic manifestations like multiple cutaneous leiomyomas (histologically confirmed). At least two of the following manifestations must also be present:<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_3000" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgical treatment for symptomatic uterine leiomyomas before age 40 years.</ListItem><ListItem>A diagnosis of type 2 papillary RCC before age 40 years (now referred to as FH-deficient papillary RCC).</ListItem><ListItem>A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460150" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">first-degree relative</GlossaryTermRef> who meets one of these criteria.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3002">Since FH-deficient RCC can resemble collecting duct RCC, the presence of FH-deficient RCC before age 40 years has been suggested as an additional criterion.<Reference refidx="5"/> Patients with seemingly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic</GlossaryTermRef> tumors who have a negative family history and a single, histologically confirmed cutaneous leiomyoma may test positive for the presence of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>FH</GeneName> pathogenic variant. Although the percentage of germline pathogenic variants in these patient populations is unknown, many centers may refer patients with a single cutaneous leiomyoma for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> and testing, regardless of family history.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_458"><Title>Differential diagnosis</Title><SummarySection id="_659"><Title>Cutaneous lesions</Title><Para id="_660">Cutaneous leiomyomas are rare. The detection of multiple lesions is specific to HLRCC. Because leiomyomas are clinically similar to various cutaneous lesions, histological diagnosis is required to objectively prove the nature of the lesion.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_661"><Title>Uterine leiomyomas</Title><Para id="_662">Uterine leiomyoma is the most common benign pelvic tumor in women in the general population. Most uterine leiomyomas are sporadic and nonsyndromic.<Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_663"><Title>RCCs</Title><Para id="_464">  Diagnostic clues of HLRCC may rely on the presence of several <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotypic</GlossaryTermRef> features in different organs (cutaneous, uterine, and renal). One or more of these characteristic features may be present in the patient or in one or more of their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">affected</GlossaryTermRef> biologic relatives.</Para><Para id="_571">Although <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> RCCs are associated with rather specific renal pathology, the rarity of these syndromes results in few pathologists gaining sufficient experience to recognize their histological features. </Para><Para id="_507">The differential diagnoses may include other rare familial RCC syndromes with specific renal pathology, including:</Para><ItemizedList id="_465" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC)</Strong>. Predisposition to papillary RCC (formerly known as type 1 papillary RCC). Inheritance is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome (BHD)</Strong>. A spectrum of renal tumors including renal oncocytoma (benign), chromophobe renal cell cancer (malignant), and a combination of both cell types (so-called oncocytic hybrid tumor).<Reference refidx="9"/> Individuals with BHD can present with cutaneous <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000771540" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">fibrofolliculomas</GlossaryTermRef>/trichodiscomas and/or with multiple lung cysts and spontaneous pneumothorax. Inheritance is autosomal dominant.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_636"><Title>Genetic testing</Title><Para id="_481">Genetic testing is used clinically for diagnostic confirmation of at-risk individuals. It is recommended that both pretest and posttest genetic counseling be offered to persons contemplating germline pathogenic variant testing.<Reference refidx="12"/>  Laboratories offering genetic testing for use in clinical decision making must be certified under CLIA laws.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para><SummarySection id="_438"><Title>Testing strategy</Title><Para id="_439">Genetic testing for a germline <GeneName>FH</GeneName> pathogenic variant is indicated for all individuals with HLRCC and for all individuals  who are suspected of having HLRCC, regardless of family history. This includes individuals with cutaneous leiomyomas, as described in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_453" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Clinical diagnosis</SummaryRef> section of this summary, and individuals who have renal tumors with histological characteristics consistent with HLRCC.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_577" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Histopathology</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_410"><Title>Risk to family members</Title><Para id="_142">HLRCC is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.<Reference refidx="16"/>  If a parent of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460211" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">proband</GlossaryTermRef> is clinically affected or has a disease-causing variant, the siblings of the proband have a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenic variant. Each child of an individual with HLRCC has a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenic variant. The degree of clinical severity is not predictable. Prenatal genetic testing may be available in laboratories offering custom prenatal testing for families in which a pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member.</Para><ItemizedList id="_412" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>Parents of a proband</ListTitle><ListItem>Some individuals diagnosed with HLRCC have an affected parent, while others have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460224" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">unaffected</GlossaryTermRef> parents, suggesting that some individuals have HLRCC as the result of a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783882" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">de novo pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> or parental <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460197" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">mosaicism</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>The proportion of cases caused by de novo pathogenic variants is unknown, as subtle manifestations in parents have not been systematically evaluated; similarly, not all unaffected parents have undergone <GeneName>FH</GeneName> testing.</ListItem><ListItem>Evaluation of parents of a proband with a suspected de novo pathogenic variant may include genetic testing if the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> disease-causing variant in the proband has been identified.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_413">Although some individuals diagnosed with HLRCC have an affected parent, the family history may appear to be negative because of limited family history, failure to recognize the disorder in family members, early death of the affected parent before the onset of syndrome-related symptoms, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339332" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">late onset</GlossaryTermRef> of the disease in the affected parent.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_415" Style="bullet"><ListTitle>Siblings of a proband</ListTitle><ListItem>The risk to the siblings of the proband depends upon the genetic status of the proband's parents.</ListItem><ListItem>If a parent of a proband is clinically affected or has a disease-causing variant, each sibling of the proband is at a 50% risk of inheriting the variant.</ListItem><ListItem>If the disease-causing variant cannot be detected in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> of either parent, the risk to siblings is low. However, risk will be greater than that of the general population because there is a possibility of germline mosaicism.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_417"><Title>Testing of at-risk family members</Title><Para id="_418">Use of genetic testing for early identification of at-risk family members improves diagnostic certainty. It reduces the number of unnecessary  costly and stressful <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> procedures in at-risk members who have not inherited their family's disease-causing variant.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/></Para><Para id="_419">Early recognition of clinical manifestations may allow timely intervention, which could, in theory, improve outcome. Therefore, clinical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> of asymptomatic at-risk relatives for early RCC detection is reasonable, but additional objective data regarding the impact of screening on syndrome-related mortality are needed.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_420"><Title>Related genetic counseling issues</Title><SummarySection id="_551"><Title>Predicting the phenotype in individuals who have inherited a pathogenic variant</Title><Para id="_422">It is not possible to predict whether HLRCC-related symptoms will occur or, if they do, what the age at onset, type, severity, or clinical characteristics will be in individuals who have a pathogenic variant.  In an in-depth characterization of clinical and genetic features analyzed within 21 new families, the phenotypes displayed a wide range of clinical presentations and no apparent <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660739" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genotype</GlossaryTermRef>-phenotype correlations were found.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_423">When neither parent of a proband with an autosomal dominant condition has the disease-causing variant or clinical evidence of the disorder, it is likely that the proband has a de novo pathogenic variant. However, nonmedical explanations include the possibility of alternate paternity or undisclosed adoption.  Genetic testing of at-risk family members is appropriate in order to identify the need for continued lifelong clinical surveillance. Interpretation of the pathogenic variant test result is most accurate when a disease-causing variant has been identified in an affected family member. Those who have a disease-causing variant are recommended to undergo lifelong periodic surveillance. Meanwhile, family members and offspring who have not inherited the pathogenic variant are thought to have RCC risks similar to those in the general population; no special management of these individuals is recommended.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_852"><Title>Early detection of at-risk individuals affects medical management</Title><Para id="_2953">Screening for early disease manifestations in HLRCC is an important aspect of clinical care of affected individuals. Although there are no prospective studies comparing specific renal cancer screening practices, the aggressive nature of HLRCC-associated RCC <Reference refidx="3"/> justifies efforts directed at the early identification of cancer. When tumors are small and localized, partial nephrectomy may be a feasible option; however, the infiltrative nature of these tumors has led some groups to suggest a wide margin must be taken to achieve complete resection.<Reference refidx="21"/> </Para><Para id="_3158">Uterine fibroids often cause significant symptoms related to bleeding and the presence of a large mass, but small fibroids may be asymptomatic. As HLRCC fibroids can lead to hysterectomies and loss of the ability to bear children in affected young women, the goal of screening in women interested in preserving fertility is to limit some of these irreversible complications. Although there are no specific management recommendations related to HLRCC-associated fibroids, various management strategies have proven effective in the treatment of sporadic fibroids. These strategies include use of hormonal therapies, pain medications, percutaneous and endovascular procedures, and surgical options. Early referral to a fertility specialist may be useful to assist with family planning. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_391"><Title>Surveillance</Title><Para id="_393">It has been suggested that individuals with a suspected or confirmed diagnosis of HLRCC, individuals with heterozygous pathogenic variants in <GeneName>FH</GeneName> regardless of clinical manifestations, and at-risk family members who have not undergone genetic testing undertake the following regular surveillance, performed by physicians familiar with the clinical manifestations of HLRCC.</Para><ItemizedList id="_394" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Skin.</Strong> There are some published recommendations to perform skin exams on a regular basis, but there is no consensus regarding frequency of skin exams, and recommendations have not been prospectively validated.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Uterine.</Strong>  For women with an intact uterus, annual gynecologic consultation is recommended, accompanied by periodic imaging. Imaging may include magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the pelvis  or ultrasound to assess the severity of uterine leiomyomas and to search for changes suggestive of developing leiomyosarcoma.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="22"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Paraganglioma (PGL)/Pheochromocytoma (PHEO). </Strong>Although PGL/PHEO surveillance is not included in suggested HLRCC guidelines, one study suggested that surveillance similar to that which is recommended for <GeneName>SDHx</GeneName> carriers could be considered for individuals with  unique <GeneName>FH</GeneName> variants associated with increased PGL/PHEO risk (i.e., p.Thr234Ala, p.Ala273Thr, and p.Ala194Thr).<Reference refidx="23"/> This surveillance regimen includes annual biochemical screening (urine or plasma metanephrines), careful physical exam with a focus on the neck and abdominal areas, and whole-body cross-sectional imaging.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Renal.</Strong>  In view of the aggressive nature of this disease, annual imaging with either computed tomography (CT) scan with contrast or MRI with gadolinium is warranted even if the initial (baseline) evaluation reveals normal kidneys. Special attention to imaging is warranted in this population because subtle findings, such as a complex cyst, may sometimes represent an aggressive malignancy. The age to initiate renal screening is uncertain, however, because HLRCC has been described in children as young as 10 years. The <ExternalRef xref="http://hlrccinfo.org/">HLRCC Family Alliance</ExternalRef> recommends annual imaging beginning at age 8 years in children at risk of HLRCC and those with HLRCC.<Reference refidx="1"/> MRI has the advantage of sparing the patient radiation exposure and for this reason it may be preferred over CT for lifetime surveillance of HLRCC patients.<Para id="_395">Any suspicious renal lesion (indeterminate, questionable, or complex cysts) at a previous examination should be closely followed with periodic imaging, preferably using the same modality to allow for comparisons. The use of renal ultrasound examination may be helpful in the characterization of cystic lesions identified on cross-sectional imaging. It should be cautioned that ultrasound examination alone is never sufficient.  Renal tumors should be evaluated by a clinician familiar with HLRCC-related renal cancer.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="24"/></Para><Para id="_396">Because of the aggressive growth of these tumors, patients warrant regular surveillance with a low threshold for early surgical intervention for solid renal lesions. This strategy differs from that described for several other hereditary RCC syndromes, in which the tumor behavior is more indolent, and for which observation may be a viable option.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/></Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_687"><LOERef href="CDR0000526280" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence (skin surveillance): 5</LOERef></Para><Para id="_688"><LOERef href="CDR0000531827" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence (uterine surveillance): 4</LOERef></Para><Para id="_689"><LOERef href="CDR0000531827" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence (renal surveillance): 4</LOERef></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_397"><Title>Treatment of Manifestations</Title><SummarySection id="_547"><Title>Cutaneous lesions</Title><Para id="_399">Cutaneous leiomyomas are most appropriately examined by a dermatologist. Generally, asymptomatic cutaneous leiomyomas require no treatment. Treatment of symptomatic cutaneous leiomyomas may be difficult if a patient has diffuse disease in a wide distribution. Surgical excision may be performed for a solitary painful lesion. Lesions can be treated by cryoablation and/or lasers. Several medications, including calcium channel blockers, alpha blockers, nitroglycerin, antidepressants, and antiepileptic drugs, reportedly reduce leiomyoma-related pain.<Reference refidx="26"/> A small,  randomized clinical trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00971620">09-C-0072</ProtocolRef> [NCT00971620])   showed that intralesional injection of botulinum toxin A (Botox) may improve quality of life.<Reference refidx="27"/></Para><Para id="_690"><LOERef href="CDR0000531846" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: 5</LOERef></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_548"><Title>Uterine leiomyomas</Title><Para id="_401">Uterine leiomyomas are best evaluated by a gynecologist. HLRCC-associated leiomyomas are treated in the same manner as sporadic leiomyomas. However, because of the multiplicity, size, and potential rapid growth observed in HLRCC-related uterine leiomyomas, most women may require medical and/or surgical intervention earlier and more often than would be expected in the general population. Medical therapy (currently including gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonists, anti-hormonal medications, and pain relievers) may be used to initially treat uterine leiomyomas, both to decrease their size in preparation for surgical removal and  to provide temporary relief from leiomyoma-related pain. When women desire fertility preservation, myomectomy can be used to remove leiomyomas and simultaneously preserve the uterus. Hysterectomy should be performed only when necessary.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_691"><LOERef href="CDR0000531845" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: 4</LOERef></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_549"><Title>RCCs</Title><Para id="_403">Efforts aimed at early detection of HLRCC-related RCC are prudent,  given its biological aggressiveness. However, studies do not currently show that early detection is clearly associated with improved survival. Surgical excision of these malignancies at the first sign of disease is recommended, unlike management of other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">hereditary cancer syndromes</GlossaryTermRef>. The propensity for lymph node involvement, even with small renal tumors, may necessitate a lymph node dissection for more appropriate staging.<Reference refidx="21"/>  Radical nephrectomy or partial nephrectomy with wide margins should be considered in individuals with detectable renal masses, including small, subcentimetric tumors.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="24"/><Reference refidx="25"/></Para><Para id="_692"><LOERef href="CDR0000531845" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: 4</LOERef></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_550"><Title>Therapies under investigation</Title><Para id="_405">It has been suggested that hypoxia-inducible factor (HIF1)-alpha overexpression is involved in HLRCC tumorigenesis.<Reference refidx="28"/><Reference refidx="29"/> Therefore, potential targeted therapies for HLRCC-associated tumors may include HIF1-alpha targeting agents, when such agents become clinically available.</Para><Para id="_656">Loss of oxidative phosphorylation resulting from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">biallelic</GlossaryTermRef> inactivation of <GeneName>FH</GeneName> renders HLRCC tumors almost entirely reliant on aerobic glycolysis for meeting cellular adenosine triphosphate and other bioenergetics requirements. Consequently, targeting aerobic glycolysis is being explored as a therapeutic strategy.<Reference refidx="30"/><Reference refidx="31"/> A phase II study (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01130519">10-C-0114</ProtocolRef> [NCT01130519]) examining the combination of bevacizumab and erlotinib for the treatment of advanced HLRCC is ongoing and is based partly on the premise that this combination might inhibit effective glucose delivery to tumor cells.<Reference refidx="32"/></Para><Para id="_779">Other investigations <Reference refidx="33"/> evaluating the known consequences of  FH inactivation in HLRCC kidney cancer have confirmed that there are very high levels of  NAD(P)H dehydrogenase quinine 1 (NQO1) expression in HLRCC kidney tumors. Expression of this compound is lower in other types of hereditary RCC, including the clear cell RCC associated with von Hippel-Lindau disease  and the papillary RCC associated with HPRC. The activation of an oxidative stress response pathway mediated by NRF2, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef> factor that regulates the transcription of NQO1, could explain NQO1 overexpression in these tumors. Vandetanib, an oral VEGFR2 and EGFR inhibitor with additional activity against Abl-1 kinase, has potent activity against FH-deficient cells <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> and induces regression of HLRCC-derived xenografts in mice. The activity of vandetanib in this model is mediated, at least in part, by its ability to disrupt the NRF2-mediated cytoprotective oxidative stress response pathway in an Abl-dependent fashion. Furthermore, metformin, an activator of 5’–AMP activated protein kinase (AMPK), was synergistic with vandetanib both <Emphasis>in vitro</Emphasis> and in mouse xenografts derived from FH-deficient human renal cancer.<Reference refidx="34"/> These data provided the basis for a clinical trial (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02495103">NCT02495103</ProtocolRef>) to evaluate the efficacy of this combination in HLRCC patients with advanced kidney cancer.</Para><Para id="_570">General information about clinical trials is also available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">HLRCC Family Alliance: The HLRCC Handbook. Version 2.0. Boston, MA: HLRCC Family Alliance, 2013. <ExternalRef xref="http://hlrccinfo.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/HLRCC-HANDBOOK.pdf">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed November 6, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25018647">Schmidt LS, Linehan WM: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell carcinoma. Int J Nephrol Renovasc Dis 7: 253-60, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="20618355">Smit DL, Mensenkamp AR, Badeloe S, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer in families referred for fumarate hydratase germline mutation analysis. Clin Genet 79 (1): 49-59, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25012257">Menko FH, Maher ER, Schmidt LS, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC): renal cancer risk, surveillance and treatment. Fam Cancer 13 (4): 637-44, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21404119">Lehtonen HJ: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer: update on clinical and molecular characteristics. Fam Cancer 10 (2): 397-411, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12772087" MedlineID="22696721">Toro JR, Nickerson ML, Wei MH, et al.: Mutations in the fumarate hydratase gene cause hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer in families in North America. Am J Hum Genet 73 (1): 95-106, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="19075141">Stewart L, Glenn GM, Stratton P, et al.: Association of germline mutations in the fumarate hydratase gene and uterine fibroids in women with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. Arch Dermatol 144 (12): 1584-92, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="8308957">Zbar B, Tory K, Merino M, et al.: Hereditary papillary renal cell carcinoma. J Urol 151 (3): 561-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="12459621" MedlineID="22346902">Pavlovich CP, Walther MM, Eyler RA, et al.: Renal tumors in the Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome. Am J Surg Pathol 26 (12): 1542-52, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20059341">Linehan WM, Bratslavsky G, Pinto PA, et al.: Molecular diagnosis and therapy of kidney cancer. Annu Rev Med 61: 329-43, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="26334087">Schmidt LS, Linehan WM: Molecular genetics and clinical features of Birt-Hogg-Dubé syndrome. Nat Rev Urol 12 (10): 558-69, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="22134580">Riley BD, Culver JO, Skrzynia C, et al.: Essential elements of genetic cancer risk assessment, counseling, and testing: updated recommendations of the National Society of Genetic Counselors. J Genet Couns 21 (2): 151-61, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="17441260">Update: information about obtaining a CLIA certificate. Jt Comm Perspect 26 (12): 6-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="28171700">Kopp RP, Stratton KL, Glogowski E, et al.: Utility of prospective pathologic evaluation to inform clinical genetic testing for hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell carcinoma. Cancer 123 (13): 2452-2458, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="17895761">Merino MJ, Torres-Cabala C, Pinto P, et al.: The morphologic spectrum of kidney tumors in hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell carcinoma (HLRCC) syndrome. Am J Surg Pathol 31 (10): 1578-85, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="11248088">Launonen V, Vierimaa O, Kiuru M, et al.: Inherited susceptibility to uterine leiomyomas and renal cell cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 98 (6): 3387-92, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="17392716">Refae MA, Wong N, Patenaude F, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer: an unusual and aggressive form of hereditary renal carcinoma. Nat Clin Pract Oncol 4 (4): 256-61, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="12692171" MedlineID="22689272">American Society of Clinical Oncology: American Society of Clinical Oncology policy statement update: genetic testing for cancer susceptibility. J Clin Oncol 21 (12): 2397-406, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="20065170">Robson ME, Storm CD, Weitzel J, et al.: American Society of Clinical Oncology policy statement update: genetic and genomic testing for cancer susceptibility. J Clin Oncol 28 (5): 893-901, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="15937070">Wei MH, Toure O, Glenn GM, et al.: Novel mutations in FH and expansion of the spectrum of phenotypes expressed in families with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. J Med Genet 43 (1): 18-27, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="22487757">Shuch B, Singer EA, Bratslavsky G: The surgical approach to multifocal renal cancers: hereditary syndromes, ipsilateral multifocality, and bilateral tumors. Urol Clin North Am 39 (2): 133-48, v, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="28314682">Patel VM, Handler MZ, Schwartz RA, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer syndrome: An update and review. J Am Acad Dermatol 77 (1): 149-158, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="36773955">Zavoshi S, Lu E, Boutros PC, et al.: Fumarate Hydratase Variants and Their Association With Paraganglioma/Pheochromocytoma. Urology 176: 106-114, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="17509289">Grubb RL, Franks ME, Toro J, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer: a syndrome associated with an aggressive form of inherited renal cancer. J Urol 177 (6): 2074-9; discussion 2079-80, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="18476789">Pfaffenroth EC, Linehan WM: Genetic basis for kidney cancer: opportunity for disease-specific approaches to therapy. Expert Opin Biol Ther 8 (6): 779-90, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="16319483">Ritzmann S, Hanneken S, Neumann NJ, et al.: Type 2 segmental manifestation of cutaneous leiomyomatosis in four unrelated women with additional uterine leiomyomas (Reed's Syndrome). Dermatology 212 (1): 84-7, 2006.</Citation><Citation idx="27" PMID="26244563">Naik HB, Steinberg SM, Middelton LA, et al.: Efficacy of Intralesional Botulinum Toxin A for Treatment of Painful Cutaneous Leiomyomas: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Dermatol 151 (10): 1096-102, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="28" PMID="16098467">Isaacs JS, Jung YJ, Mole DR, et al.: HIF overexpression correlates with biallelic loss of fumarate hydratase in renal cancer: novel role of fumarate in regulation of HIF stability. Cancer Cell 8 (2): 143-53, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="29" PMID="15987702">Pollard PJ, Brière JJ, Alam NA, et al.: Accumulation of Krebs cycle intermediates and over-expression of HIF1alpha in tumours which result from germline FH and SDH mutations. Hum Mol Genet 14 (15): 2231-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="30" PMID="19276158">Xie H, Valera VA, Merino MJ, et al.: LDH-A inhibition, a therapeutic strategy for treatment of hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. Mol Cancer Ther 8 (3): 626-35, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="31" PMID="21304509">Yamasaki T, Tran TA, Oz OK, et al.: Exploring a glycolytic inhibitor for the treatment of an FH-deficient type-2 papillary RCC. Nat Rev Urol 8 (3): 165-71, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="32" PMID="23972715">Linehan WM, Srinivasan R, Garcia JA: Non-clear cell renal cancer: disease-based management and opportunities for targeted therapeutic approaches. Semin Oncol 40 (4): 511-20, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="33" PMID="17255292">Linehan WM, Pinto PA, Srinivasan R, et al.: Identification of the genes for kidney cancer: opportunity for disease-specific targeted therapeutics. Clin Cancer Res 13 (2 Pt 2): 671s-679s, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="34" PMID="25490448">Sourbier C, Ricketts CJ, Matsumoto S, et al.: Targeting ABL1-mediated oxidative stress adaptation in fumarate hydratase-deficient cancer. Cancer Cell 26 (6): 840-50, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_633"><Title>Prognosis</Title><Para id="_644">Prognosis is quite good for cutaneous and uterine manifestations of hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC). Local management of cutaneous manifestations, when required, and hysterectomy, where indicated, address these sites fairly effectively and with minimal long-term consequences.  The incidence of uterine leiomyosarcomas is likely quite low and is unlikely to substantively affect median survival at a cohort level.  Renal cell cancer (RCC) in the context of HLRCC is a considerably more ominous manifestation, and the HLRCC patients who develop RCC <Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> are at high risk of developing metastatic disease.<Reference refidx="6"/>  Metastatic RCC associated with HLRCC is characterized by an aggressive clinical course. There are no sufficiently large patient cohorts or databases that provide a  precise estimate of survival in this population; however, retrospective cohorts demonstrate that these cancers have worse outcomes than other conventional forms of RCC.<Reference refidx="7"/>  </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="24378414">Shuch B, Vourganti S, Ricketts CJ, et al.: Defining early-onset kidney cancer: implications for germline and somatic mutation testing and clinical management. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 431-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="11248088">Launonen V, Vierimaa O, Kiuru M, et al.: Inherited susceptibility to uterine leiomyomas and renal cell cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 98 (6): 3387-92, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="12772087" MedlineID="22696721">Toro JR, Nickerson ML, Wei MH, et al.: Mutations in the fumarate hydratase gene cause hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer in families in North America. Am J Hum Genet 73 (1): 95-106, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="15724016">Alam NA, Barclay E, Rowan AJ, et al.: Clinical features of multiple cutaneous and uterine leiomyomatosis: an underdiagnosed tumor syndrome. Arch Dermatol 141 (2): 199-206, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31831373">Forde C, Lim DHK, Alwan Y, et al.: Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer: Clinical, Molecular, and Screening Features in a Cohort of 185 Affected Individuals. Eur Urol Oncol 3 (6): 764-772, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="17509289">Grubb RL, Franks ME, Toro J, et al.: Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer: a syndrome associated with an aggressive form of inherited renal cancer. J Urol 177 (6): 2074-9; discussion 2079-80, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26947078">Chen F, Zhang Y, Şenbabaoğlu Y, et al.: Multilevel Genomics-Based Taxonomy of Renal Cell Carcinoma. Cell Rep 14 (10): 2476-89, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_634"><Title>Future Directions</Title><Para id="_645">There are two major unmet needs, other than the availability of effective medical therapy for metastatic disease, in the management of patients with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC). The first is the ability to predict who will develop renal cell cancer to allow detection earlier and with a higher degree of precision.  The development of diagnostic blood-based tests or imaging tools that permit cost-effective <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> of the kidneys of patients with HLRCC would have a major positive effect on the outcomes of these individuals. The second major unmet need is for a more accurate determination of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660739" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genotype</GlossaryTermRef>-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef> correlations for various genetic lesions found in the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>.  New <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044805" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">polymorphisms</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>FH</GeneName> gene are frequently of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556495" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">uncertain significance</GlossaryTermRef>, and considerable effort needs to be expended to determine their clinical significance.  Devising in silico prediction tools and linking these to robust patient databases and registries will expand our understanding of specific <GeneName>FH</GeneName> gene <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3155"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/06/2024)</Title><Para id="_3157">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3183"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_632" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Management</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_3184">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_454" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that available guidelines were created during a previous era of histological classification when FH-deficient papillary renal cell carcinoma (RCC) was classified as type 2 papillary RCC. Suggested guidelines may need to be updated based on this RCC classification change, the availability of immunohistochemical stains to identify loss of FH, and the presence of 2SC in tissue manifestations.</Para><Para id="_3185">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_655" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> about suggested criteria for a hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) diagnosis.</Para><Para id="_3186">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_3002" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that since FH-deficient renal cancer can resemble collecting duct RCC, the presence of FH-deficient RCC before age 40 years has been suggested as an additional criterion for HLRCC diagnosis.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803507#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Alexandra Perez Lebensohn, MS, CGC (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Brian Matthew Shuch, MD (UCLA Health)</ListItem><ListItem>Ramaprasad Srinivasan, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ Hereditary Leiomyomatosis and Renal Cell Cancer. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hlrcc-syndrome-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 33724749]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2021-03-08</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-06</DateLastModified></Summary>
