<Summary id="CDR0000803600" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Evidence-based, expert-reviewed summary about the hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC), including information about the MET gene.  This summary also contains information about screening for HPRC,  clinical presentation, management, and prognosis of HPRC.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Hereditary Papillary Renal Carcinoma (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000544837">hereditary papillary renal cell carcinoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_782">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC). It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians who care for HPRC patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_783">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>hereditary papillary renal carcinoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Hereditary Papillary Renal Carcinoma (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Hereditary Papillary Renal Carcinoma (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Hereditary Papillary Renal Carcinoma</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_285"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_68">Hereditary papillary renal  carcinoma (HPRC) is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> that predisposes individuals to bilateral and multifocal papillary renal cell carcinoma (RCC) (formerly known as type 1 papillary RCC).<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_3158">Individuals are at the greatest risk of developing HPRC if they have a biological relative with bilateral, multifocal papillary RCC and/or a known activating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in the tyrosine kinase <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460145" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">domain</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GeneName>MET</GeneName> proto-oncogene.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_534">No specific environmental risk factors have been reported to cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809370" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">hereditary</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic</GlossaryTermRef> papillary RCC. </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="8308957">Zbar B, Tory K, Merino M, et al.: Hereditary papillary renal cell carcinoma. J Urol 151 (3): 561-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9140397">Schmidt L, Duh FM, Chen F, et al.: Germline and somatic mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the MET proto-oncogene in papillary renal carcinomas. Nat Genet 16 (1): 68-73, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="7853572">Zbar B, Glenn G, Lubensky I, et al.: Hereditary papillary renal cell carcinoma: clinical studies in 10 families. J Urol 153 (3 Pt 2): 907-12, 1995.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_671"><Title>Genetics</Title><SummarySection id="_295"><Title><GeneName>MET</GeneName> Gene</Title><Para id="_774">The  <GeneName>MET</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is located on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 7q31.2 and encodes a protein with 1,390 amino-acids.<Reference refidx="1"/>
  The functional MET receptor is a heterodimer made of an alpha chain (50 kDa) and a beta chain (145 kDa). The primary single-chain precursor protein is posttranslationally cleaved to produce the alpha and beta subunits,<Reference refidx="2"/> which are disulfide-linked to form the mature receptor. Two <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcript</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef>, which encode  different isoforms, have been found for this gene.</Para><Para id="_775">The beta subunit of MET possesses tyrosine kinase activity and was identified as the cell-surface receptor for hepatocyte growth factor (HGF).<Reference refidx="3"/> MET transduces signals from the extracellular matrix into the cytoplasm by binding to the HGF ligand; it also regulates cell proliferation, scattering, morphogenesis, and survival.<Reference refidx="4"/>
 Ligand binding at the cell surface induces autophosphorylation of MET on its intracellular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460145" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">domain</GlossaryTermRef>, which provides docking sites for downstream signaling molecules. After activation by its ligand, MET interacts with the PI3K subunit PI3KR1, PLCG1, SRC, GRB2, or STAT3, or the adapter GAB1. Recruitment of these downstream effectors by MET leads to the activation of several signaling cascades, including RAS-ERK, PI3K/AKT, and PLC-gamma/PKC.<Reference refidx="4"/> The RAS-ERK activation is associated with morphogenetic effects, while PI3K/AKT coordinates cell survival activities.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_298"><Title>Prevalence and Founder Effects</Title><Para id="_299"> A novel <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> was identified in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460146" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">exon</GlossaryTermRef> 16 of the <GeneName>MET</GeneName> gene in two large <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">hereditary</GlossaryTermRef> papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC) families in North America.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Affected</GlossaryTermRef> members of the two families shared the same <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000485392" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">haplotype</GlossaryTermRef> located within and immediately distal to the <GeneName>MET</GeneName> gene, suggesting a common ancestor (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783962" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">founder effect</GlossaryTermRef>).<Reference refidx="5"/>  However, HPRC families with identical <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>MET</GeneName> pathogenic variants who do not share a common ancestral haplotype have also been reported.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_300"><Title>Penetrance of <GeneName>MET</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_301">HPRC is highly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrant</GlossaryTermRef> (approaching 100%).<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_303"><Title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</Title><Para id="_304">All cases of HPRC have presented with papillary renal cell carcinoma, and no other histological subtypes have been detected.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> The papillary RCC seen in HPRC (previously known as type 1 papillary RCC) has a distinct morphology, including the presence of small cells with basophilic cytoplasms arranged in a single layer on thin papillae. Extrarenal manifestations associated with this condition have not been reported.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="2819873">Park M, Dean M, Kaul K, et al.: Sequence of MET protooncogene cDNA has features characteristic of the tyrosine kinase family of growth-factor receptors. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 84 (18): 6379-83, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="8344430">Komada M, Hatsuzawa K, Shibamoto S, et al.: Proteolytic processing of the hepatocyte growth factor/scatter factor receptor by furin. FEBS Lett 328 (1-2): 25-9, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1846706">Bottaro DP, Rubin JS, Faletto DL, et al.: Identification of the hepatocyte growth factor receptor as the c-met proto-oncogene product. Science 251 (4995): 802-4, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="22270953">Gherardi E, Birchmeier W, Birchmeier C, et al.: Targeting MET in cancer: rationale and progress. Nat Rev Cancer 12 (2): 89-103, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="9563489">Schmidt L, Junker K, Weirich G, et al.: Two North American families with hereditary papillary renal carcinoma and identical novel mutations in the MET proto-oncogene. Cancer Res 58 (8): 1719-22, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="15371818">Schmidt LS, Nickerson ML, Angeloni D, et al.: Early onset hereditary papillary renal carcinoma: germline missense mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the met proto-oncogene. J Urol 172 (4 Pt 1): 1256-61, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="24378414">Shuch B, Vourganti S, Ricketts CJ, et al.: Defining early-onset kidney cancer: implications for germline and somatic mutation testing and clinical management. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 431-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="7853572">Zbar B, Glenn G, Lubensky I, et al.: Hereditary papillary renal cell carcinoma: clinical studies in 10 families. J Urol 153 (3 Pt 2): 907-12, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="8308957">Zbar B, Tory K, Merino M, et al.: Hereditary papillary renal cell carcinoma. J Urol 151 (3): 561-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="9140397">Schmidt L, Duh FM, Chen F, et al.: Germline and somatic mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the MET proto-oncogene in papillary renal carcinomas. Nat Genet 16 (1): 68-73, 1997.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_296"><Title>Molecular Biology</Title><Para id="_302">All <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>MET</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC) reported to date are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the tyrosine kinase <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460145" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">domain</GlossaryTermRef>;  this leads to constitutive activation of the MET  kinase and drives the development of papillary renal cell carcinoma (RCC).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_297">   Renal tumors from HPRC-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">affected</GlossaryTermRef> patients commonly show polysomy of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 7 upon <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cytogenetic</GlossaryTermRef> analysis.<Reference refidx="4"/>
  Polysomy 7 in the HPRC renal tumor tissue results from nonrandom duplication of the chromosome bearing the
wild-type <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339337" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">allele</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="5"/> Approximately 15% to 20%  of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic</GlossaryTermRef> papillary RCCs (which all shared what was previously called type 1 papillary RCC morphology)  have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>MET</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460164" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense mutations</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10327054">Schmidt L, Junker K, Nakaigawa N, et al.: Novel mutations of the MET proto-oncogene in papillary renal carcinomas. Oncogene 18 (14): 2343-50, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9140397">Schmidt L, Duh FM, Chen F, et al.: Germline and somatic mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the MET proto-oncogene in papillary renal carcinomas. Nat Genet 16 (1): 68-73, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="11354004">Miller M, Ginalski K, Lesyng B, et al.: Structural basis of oncogenic activation caused by point mutations in the kinase domain of the MET proto-oncogene: modeling studies. Proteins 44 (1): 32-43, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="2819873">Park M, Dean M, Kaul K, et al.: Sequence of MET protooncogene cDNA has features characteristic of the tyrosine kinase family of growth-factor receptors. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 84 (18): 6379-83, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="9731534">Zhuang Z, Park WS, Pack S, et al.: Trisomy 7-harbouring non-random duplication of the mutant MET allele in hereditary papillary renal carcinomas. Nat Genet 20 (1): 66-9, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="26536169">Linehan WM, Spellman PT, Ricketts CJ, et al.: Comprehensive Molecular Characterization of Papillary Renal-Cell Carcinoma. N Engl J Med 374 (2): 135-45, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28592388">Pal SK, Ali SM, Yakirevich E, et al.: Characterization of Clinical Cases of Advanced Papillary Renal Cell Carcinoma via Comprehensive Genomic Profiling. Eur Urol 73 (1): 71-78, 2018.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_672"><Title>Clinical Manifestations</Title><SummarySection id="_776"><Title>Kidney Cancer</Title><Para id="_777">The only recognized manifestation of hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC) is kidney cancer. The mean and median age at onset are 42 and 41 years, respectively.<Reference refidx="1"/>
 The age at onset may vary widely between families (range,  19–66 y), perhaps influenced by specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660739" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genotypes</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/>
 Unlike <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic tumors</GlossaryTermRef>, which occur more frequently in males, both sexes appear to be similarly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">affected</GlossaryTermRef> by HPRC-associated renal cell carcinoma (RCC). Renal tumors in HPRC are most commonly bilateral and multifocal.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>
In contrast with many other RCC syndromes, renal cysts are less common in HPRC.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> However, the presentation of HPRC is similar to other forms of kidney cancer in that small tumors may present incidentally, whereas large lesions can cause the classic triad of flank pain, hematuria, and an abdominal mass.  When HPRC renal tumors become large, they can metastasize, most commonly to the lungs.<Reference refidx="5"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="24378414">Shuch B, Vourganti S, Ricketts CJ, et al.: Defining early-onset kidney cancer: implications for germline and somatic mutation testing and clinical management. J Clin Oncol 32 (5): 431-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15371818">Schmidt LS, Nickerson ML, Angeloni D, et al.: Early onset hereditary papillary renal carcinoma: germline missense mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the met proto-oncogene. J Urol 172 (4 Pt 1): 1256-61, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="7853572">Zbar B, Glenn G, Lubensky I, et al.: Hereditary papillary renal cell carcinoma: clinical studies in 10 families. J Urol 153 (3 Pt 2): 907-12, 1995.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="8308957">Zbar B, Tory K, Merino M, et al.: Hereditary papillary renal cell carcinoma. J Urol 151 (3): 561-6, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="10433944">Lubensky IA, Schmidt L, Zhuang Z, et al.: Hereditary and sporadic papillary renal carcinomas with c-met mutations share a distinct morphological phenotype. Am J Pathol 155 (2): 517-26, 1999.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_535"><Title>Histopathology</Title><Para id="_536">Papillary renal cell carcinomas (RCCs) often have heterogenous morphological features. Type 1 papillary RCC was a unique classification within the papillary RCC family, but recent World Health Organization pathology updates have removed this designation.  All hereditary papillary renal carcinomas (HPRCs) share type 1 papillary morphology, which is defined by small basophilic cells with pale cytoplasm, small oval nuclei, and inconspicuous nucleoli organized in single layers in papillae and tubular structures.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  The HPRC <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef> is only seen in individuals with this distinct type 1 papillary renal carcinoma histopathology. Incipient microscopic lesions, including adenomas and papillary lesions, are commonly found in the adjacent renal parenchyma. It has been estimated that patients with HPRC may develop up to 3,400 renal tumors or incipient lesions per kidney.<Reference refidx="3"/> These pathological findings should raise suspicion for a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781852" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline variant</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>MET</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Hereditary and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic</GlossaryTermRef> type 1 papillary RCCs with <GeneName>MET</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> have similar, distinctive type 1 papillary morphological phenotypes, which include the presence of macrophages and psammoma bodies.<Reference refidx="6"/> In HPRC, papillary tumors are often well differentiated/low grade. However, high-grade tumors can also be observed in HPRC patients.<Reference refidx="7"/>  </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="9195569">Delahunt B, Eble JN: Papillary renal cell carcinoma: a clinicopathologic and immunohistochemical study of 105 tumors. Mod Pathol 10 (6): 537-44, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9307203">Störkel S, Eble JN, Adlakha K, et al.: Classification of renal cell carcinoma: Workgroup No. 1. Union Internationale Contre le Cancer (UICC) and the American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC). Cancer 80 (5): 987-9, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="10647647">Ornstein DK, Lubensky IA, Venzon D, et al.: Prevalence of microscopic tumors in normal appearing renal parenchyma of patients with hereditary papillary renal cancer. J Urol 163 (2): 431-3, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="9563489">Schmidt L, Junker K, Weirich G, et al.: Two North American families with hereditary papillary renal carcinoma and identical novel mutations in the MET proto-oncogene. Cancer Res 58 (8): 1719-22, 1998.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="15371818">Schmidt LS, Nickerson ML, Angeloni D, et al.: Early onset hereditary papillary renal carcinoma: germline missense mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the met proto-oncogene. J Urol 172 (4 Pt 1): 1256-61, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="10433944">Lubensky IA, Schmidt L, Zhuang Z, et al.: Hereditary and sporadic papillary renal carcinomas with c-met mutations share a distinct morphological phenotype. Am J Pathol 155 (2): 517-26, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="12511666">Choyke PL, Glenn GM, Walther MM, et al.: Hereditary renal cancers. Radiology 226 (1): 33-46, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_305"><Title>Management</Title><SummarySection id="_306"><Title>Surveillance </Title><Para id="_537">It is important that patients with known hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC) undergo regular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef>. Papillary renal cell carcinomas (RCCs) possess specific imaging characteristics that differ from clear cell RCCs. Papillary renal tumors are generally hypovascular and enhance only 10 to 30 Hounsfield units after intravenous administration of contrast material. Papillary renal tumors can be mistaken for renal cysts, unless evaluated by careful attenuation measurements before and after contrast enhancement. Ultrasonography can be particularly misleading if no other imaging tests are used because the small renal tumors in HPRC are often isoechoic and may be missed on repeat examinations.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_538">If kidney function is normal and the patient is not allergic to contrast, cross-sectional imaging with computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is considered the best initial imaging technique for identifying these hypovascular renal tumors. Renal ultrasonography is often inadequate for detecting papillary tumors, even when the tumor is clearly present on CT or MRI.<Reference refidx="2"/> Occasionally, ultrasonography may complement cross-sectional imaging by aiding in the identification of cystic structures.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_470">At-risk individuals are generally recommended to undergo periodic kidney imaging throughout their lifetimes, even when renal tumors are not present. Therefore, MRI is typically recommended to minimize the lifetime dose of radiation. One approach that has been used is to perform initial cross-sectional imaging at baseline. If there are no renal tumors present, imaging can be performed periodically. If a renal tumor smaller than 3 cm is found, imaging is repeated within the first year to assess the growth rate of the tumor.<Reference refidx="4"/> Imaging frequency can be adapted to prevent the largest tumor from exceeding  3 cm depending on the growth characteristics of the tumor and the current tumor size.</Para><Para id="_780">Generally, patients with HPRC-associated renal tumors are candidates for radiological surveillance until one or more of the tumors reach 3 cm.  At that point, surgical intervention is recommended. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_681" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_309"><Title>Genetic Testing</Title><Para id="_310">Genetic testing for HPRC is available at Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)-certified laboratories.  A health professional (usually a physician, geneticist, or genetic counselor) intermediary between the patient and the laboratory is chosen.  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> is performed, and  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044677" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">informed consent</GlossaryTermRef> obtained. The genetic counselor will contact the laboratory and coordinate genetic testing.</Para><Para id="_307">Genetic testing for HPRC may be recommended if an individual has one or more of the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_474" Style="bullet"><ListItem>A family history of HPRC.</ListItem><ListItem>A biologically related  family member who tested positive for a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in the tyrosine kinase <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460145" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">domain</GlossaryTermRef> of <GeneName>MET</GeneName>.</ListItem><ListItem>A personal history of greater than one papillary RCC (especially with the previously designated type 1 papillary RCC morphology), a papillary RCC with incipient lesions of the surrounding parenchyma, or a papillary RCC diagnosed before age 45 years.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3160">One report suggested that it may be beneficial to expand  testing for HPRC beyond familial cases.<Reference refidx="5"/> In a series of 158 patients from France, 5% of nonfamilial papillary RCC cases had a germline <GeneName>MET</GeneName> pathogenic variant.</Para><SummarySection id="_311"><Title><GeneName>MET</GeneName> genetic testing</Title><Para id="_312">Bidirectional <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> sequencing of the <GeneName>MET</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> using amplified genomic DNA is done to identify sequence <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the coding <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460146" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">exons</GlossaryTermRef> of <GeneName>MET</GeneName>. All HPRC-associated <GeneName>MET</GeneName> pathogenic variants identified to date are located in the four exons encompassing the tyrosine kinase domain. Therefore, initially analyzing only these four exons may identify most sequence variants while reducing the cost and time involved in analyzing the entire 21-exon gene.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> Some CLIA-approved genetic testing laboratories now offer diagnostic cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763019" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene panels</GlossaryTermRef>,  which use <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763024" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">next-generation sequencing</GlossaryTermRef> technology to examine the entire <GeneName>MET</GeneName> gene.</Para><Para id="_313">Genetic testing enables early definitive diagnosis of the HPRC syndrome, after which at-risk individuals can be guided to regular surveillance for syndrome-associated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotypes</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_3161">Individuals with variants of unknown significance (VUS) in the <GeneName>MET</GeneName> tyrosine kinase domain warrant special consideration. A recent genotype-phenotype study demonstrated that three <GeneName>MET</GeneName> VUS exhibited oncogenic MET signaling in preclinical models, suggesting pathogenicity.<Reference refidx="5"/> Families with papillary RCC and these <GeneName>MET </GeneName>VUS could benefit from a discussion about these findings and their implications.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_681"><Title>Treatment</Title><Para id="_778">
Once HPRC renal tumors reach 3 cm in size, a nephron-sparing partial nephrectomy is usually recommended to minimize the risk of metastasis. There are no curative options available for patients with unresectable extrarenal spread of disease. However, there has been significant interest in developing MET-directed systemic therapy for patients with HPRC. Foretinib, a dual MET/VEGFR2 kinase inhibitor with additional activity against a variety of other tyrosine kinases, was evaluated in a multicenter phase II trial in patients with metastatic papillary RCC or bilateral multifocal papillary RCC. The overall response rate in patients with papillary RCC was 13.5%.<Reference refidx="9"/> However, patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>MET</GeneName> pathogenic variants were particularly sensitive to this agent, with 5 of 10 patients demonstrating a partial response, as assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria. In patients without germline <GeneName>MET</GeneName> pathogenic variants, only 5 of 57 demonstrated  a partial response to foretinib. Cabozantinib was approved for the treatment of metastatic kidney cancer in 2016.<Reference refidx="10"/> In a randomized phase II trial from the Southwest Oncology Group (SWOG), patients with metastatic papillary RCC had improved outcomes with cabozantinib when compared with  sunitinib in the S1500 trial. Ongoing research will evaluate the role of MET activation in RCC treatment response.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12511666">Choyke PL, Glenn GM, Walther MM, et al.: Hereditary renal cancers. Radiology 226 (1): 33-46, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="19448113">Vikram R, Ng CS, Tamboli P, et al.: Papillary renal cell carcinoma: radiologic-pathologic correlation and spectrum of disease. Radiographics 29 (3): 741-54; discussion 755-7, 2009 May-Jun.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9294565">Choyke PL, Walther MM, Glenn GM, et al.: Imaging features of hereditary papillary renal cancers. J Comput Assist Tomogr 21 (5): 737-41, 1997 Sep-Oct.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="10210376">Walther MM, Choyke PL, Glenn G, et al.: Renal cancer in families with hereditary renal cancer: prospective analysis of a tumor size threshold for renal parenchymal sparing surgery. J Urol 161 (5): 1475-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="34882875">Sebai M, Tulasne D, Caputo SM, et al.: Novel germline MET pathogenic variants in French patients with papillary renal cell carcinomas type I. Hum Mutat 43 (3): 316-327, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="2819873">Park M, Dean M, Kaul K, et al.: Sequence of MET protooncogene cDNA has features characteristic of the tyrosine kinase family of growth-factor receptors. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 84 (18): 6379-83, 1987.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9140397">Schmidt L, Duh FM, Chen F, et al.: Germline and somatic mutations in the tyrosine kinase domain of the MET proto-oncogene in papillary renal carcinomas. Nat Genet 16 (1): 68-73, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="9380410">Duh FM, Scherer SW, Tsui LC, et al.: Gene structure of the human MET proto-oncogene. Oncogene 15 (13): 1583-6, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="23213094">Choueiri TK, Vaishampayan U, Rosenberg JE, et al.: Phase II and biomarker study of the dual MET/VEGFR2 inhibitor foretinib in patients with papillary renal cell carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 31 (2): 181-6, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="26406150">Choueiri TK, Escudier B, Powles T, et al.: Cabozantinib versus Everolimus in Advanced Renal-Cell Carcinoma. N Engl J Med 373 (19): 1814-23, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="33592176">Pal SK, Tangen C, Thompson IM, et al.: A comparison of sunitinib with cabozantinib, crizotinib, and savolitinib for treatment of advanced papillary renal cell carcinoma: a randomised, open-label, phase 2 trial. Lancet 397 (10275): 695-703, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_673"><Title>Prognosis</Title><Para id="_321">Hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC)-related papillary renal cell carcinomas, particularly small tumors confined to the kidneys, tend to be indolent. Consequently, patients present later in life or die of other syndrome-unrelated causes before a renal tumor is diagnosed.<Reference refidx="1"/>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Surveillance</GlossaryTermRef>, presymptomatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> of individuals at risk of HPRC, and specialized cancer management (tailored to the biology of syndrome-associated kidney cancer) are expected to improve disease outcome.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12511666">Choyke PL, Glenn GM, Walther MM, et al.: Hereditary renal cancers. Radiology 226 (1): 33-46, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15285561">Kiuru M, Kujala M, Aittomäki K: Inherited forms of renal cell carcinoma. Scand J Surg 93 (2): 103-11, 2004.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_674"><Title>Future Directions</Title><Para id="_781">Development of blood-based early detection assays, and effective systemic therapy for either prevention or treatment of overt disease might provide new options for individuals with hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC).  Because the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of tumors in HPRC is nearly 100%, this patient population might provide an exciting avenue to study chemoprevention using MET-directed strategies. There are currently no systemic therapy options approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) that specifically  address the needs of patients with HPRC-associated metastatic renal cell carcinoma (RCC).  On the basis of limited data from the foretinib study,<Reference refidx="1"/> agents such as cabozantinib (a multitargeted tyrosine kinase inhibitor with activity against MET, which was approved by the FDA for use in patients with metastatic RCC who have progressed on VEGFR-targeted therapy) may be considered. Newer MET inhibitors with a more-selective target profile may be clinically active, while limiting off-target side effects, in patients with HPRC-associated RCC, and such agents are currently under evaluation (<ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02019693">NCT02019693</ProtocolRef>). Because redundant signaling pathways are often activated with targeted therapy, the mechanisms of resistance to MET inhibition should be further investigated.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="23213094">Choueiri TK, Vaishampayan U, Rosenberg JE, et al.: Phase II and biomarker study of the dual MET/VEGFR2 inhibitor foretinib in patients with papillary renal cell carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 31 (2): 181-6, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3155"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (02/16/2024)</Title><Para id="_3156">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3172"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_285" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Introduction</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_3173">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_68" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that the bilateral and multifocal papillary renal cell carcinoma (RCC) seen in hereditary papillary renal carcinoma (HPRC) was formerly known as type 1 papillary RCC.</Para><Para id="_3174"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_671" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Genetics</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_3179">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_304" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that the papillary RCC seen in HPRC was previously known as type 1 papillary RCC  and has distinct morphology, including the presence of small cells with basophilic cytoplasms arranged in a single layer on thin papillae.</Para><Para id="_3175"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_296" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Molecular Biology</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_3176">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_297" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that the RCC seen in 15% to 20% of sporadic papillary RCCs was previously called type 1 papillary RCC.</Para><Para id="_3177"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_305" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">Management</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_3178">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_474" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that genetic testing for HPRC may be recommended if an individual has a personal history of greater than one papillary RCC, especially those with the previously designated type 1 papillary RCC morphology.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000803600#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of hereditary papillary renal carcinoma. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Hereditary Papillary Renal Carcinoma are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Alexandra Perez Lebensohn, MS, CGC (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Brian Matthew Shuch, MD (UCLA Health)</ListItem><ListItem>Ramaprasad Srinivasan, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ Hereditary Papillary Renal Carcinoma. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/hprc-syndrome-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 33724750]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2021-03-08</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-02-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
