<Summary id="CDR0000805706" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Pediatric hematopoietic stem cell transplant involves the infusion of blood stem cells into a patient to reconstitute the blood system. Get detailed information about chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T-cell therapy in this summary for clinicians.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/car-t-cell-therapy">Pediatric Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T-Cell Therapy (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000579886">hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of CAR T-cell therapy in treating pediatric cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>CAR T-cell therapy</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>hematopoietic stem cell transplant</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Pediatric Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T-Cell Therapy (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Pediatric CAR T-Cell Therapy (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Pediatric CAR T-Cell Therapy</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_96"><Title>Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T-Cell Therapy for Pediatric Cancer</Title><Para id="_97">T cells attack cellular targets (viruses or cancer cells) by binding to class I major histocompatibility complex (MHC) molecules on the surface of the target cells. T cells also have to avoid suppressor signals sent by regulatory T cells and other surface molecule interactions.  Gene transfer technologies can modify T cells to express MHC-independent, antibody-binding domains (CAR molecules) on the surface of the modified T cells. The CAR molecules aim at specific target proteins on the surface of tumors.  Lymphodepleting chemotherapy is generally given before CAR T-cell infusions to minimize the chance of suppressor mechanisms (affecting CAR T-cell function) and to create a cytokine milieu favorable for CAR T-cell expansion.<Reference refidx="1"/> CAR T-cell–mediated responses are further enhanced by adding intracellular costimulatory domains (e.g., CD28, 4-1BB), which cause significant CAR T-cell expansion and may increase the lifespan of these cells in the recipient.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><SummarySection id="_644"><Title>CAR T-Cell Therapy Indications for Pediatric Cancer</Title><Para id="_98">  Investigators using this technology have targeted a variety of tumors/surface molecules, but the best-studied example in pediatric patients is CAR T cells aimed at CD19, a surface receptor on B cells.  Several research groups have reported significant rates of remission (70%–90%) in children and adults with refractory B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL),<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> with some groups reporting persistence of CAR T cells and remission beyond 6 months in most patients studied.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> Early loss of the CAR T cells is associated with relapse, and the best use of this therapy (bridge to transplant vs. definitive therapy) is under study. </Para><Para id="_643">Indications for hematopoietic stem cell transplant vary over time as risk classifications for a given malignancy change and the efficacy of primary therapy improves.  It is best to include specific indications in the context of complete therapy for any given disease.  With this in mind, links to sections in specific summaries that cover the most common pediatric CAR T-cell therapy indications are provided below.</Para><OrderedList id="_641" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><Strong>B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia.</Strong> <ItemizedList id="_653" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062923#_1205" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-all-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Relapsed Childhood ALL</SummaryRef> section in Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma.</Strong> <ItemizedList id="_654" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062808#_797" url="/types/lymphoma/hp/child-nhl-treatment-pdq">Treatment options for recurrent or refractory Burkitt lymphoma</SummaryRef> section in Childhood Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_645"><Title>CAR T-Cell Toxicities</Title><SummarySection id="_646"><Title>Cytokine release syndrome (CRS)</Title><Para id="_99">  Responses to CAR T-cell therapies have been associated with a significant increase in inflammatory cytokines, termed <Strong>cytokine release syndrome (CRS)</Strong>. CRS can be successfully treated with anti–interleukin-6 receptor (IL-6R) therapies (e.g., tocilizumab), often in combination with steroids.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> CRS presents as a sepsis-like situation, with fever, headache, myalgias, hypotension, capillary leak, hypoxia, and renal dysfunction.  The severity of the CRS determines whether patients require therapy. The progression of CRS can be measured by staging. The American Society for Transplantation and Cellular Therapy Consensus guidelines for CRS have  been broadly adopted (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000805706#_100" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/car-t-cell-therapy">Table 1</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="9"/> While treatment of grade 1 and early grade 2 CRS is generally not offered, patients with some forms of grade 2 and all patients with grades 3 and 4 CRS receive therapy.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Table id="_100"><Title>Table 1.  ASTCT CRS Consensus Grading<Superscript>a,b</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColWidth="20.00%"/><ColSpec ColName="col4" ColWidth="20.00%"/><THead><Row><entry>CRS Parameter</entry><entry>Grade 1</entry><entry>Grade 2</entry><entry>Grade 3</entry><entry>Grade 4</entry></Row></THead><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0">ASTCT = American Society for Transplantation and Cellular Therapy; BiPAP = bilevel positive airway pressure; CPAP = continuous positive airway pressure; CRS = cytokine release syndrome; CTCAE = Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Reprinted from <ExternalRef xref="https://www.sciencedirect.com/journal/biology-of-blood-and-marrow-transplantation">Biology of Blood and Marrow Transplantation</ExternalRef>, Volume 25, Issue 4, Daniel W. Lee, Bianca D. Santomasso, Frederick L. 
Locke et al., ASTCT Consensus Grading for Cytokine Release 
Syndrome and Neurologic Toxicity Associated 
with Immune Effector Cells, Pages 625–638, Copyright 2019, with permission from Elsevier.<Reference refidx="9"/></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Organ toxicities associated with CRS may be graded according to CTCAE v5.0 but they do not influence CRS grading.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Fever is defined as temperature ≥38°C not attributable to any other cause. In patients who have CRS then receive antipyretic or anticytokine therapy such as tocilizumab or steroids, fever is no longer required to grade subsequent CRS severity. In this case, CRS grading is driven by hypotension and/or hypoxia.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>d</Superscript>CRS grade is determined by the more severe event: hypotension or hypoxia not attributable to any other cause. For example, a patient with temperature of 39.5°C, hypotension requiring 1 vasopressor, and hypoxia requiring low-flow nasal cannula is classified as grade 3 CRS.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>e</Superscript>Low-flow nasal cannula is defined as oxygen delivered at ≤6L/minute. Low flow also includes blow-by oxygen delivery, sometimes used in pediatrics. High-flow nasal cannula is defined as oxygen delivered at &gt;6L/minute.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry><Strong>Fever</Strong><Superscript>c</Superscript></entry><entry>Temperature ≥38°C</entry><entry>Temperature ≥38°C</entry><entry>Temperature ≥38°C</entry><entry>Temperature ≥38°C</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0"><Strong>With</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong>Hypotension</Strong></entry><entry>None</entry><entry>Not requiring vasopressors</entry><entry>Requiring a vasopressor with or without vasopressin</entry><entry>Requiring multiple vasopressors (excluding vasopressin)</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col4" NameSt="col0"><Strong>And/or</Strong><Superscript>d</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry><Strong>Hypoxia</Strong></entry><entry>None</entry><entry>Requiring low-flow nasal cannula<Superscript>e</Superscript> or blow-by</entry><entry>Requiring high-flow nasal cannula<Superscript>e</Superscript>, facemask, nonrebreather mask, or Venturi mask</entry><entry>Requiring positive pressure (e.g., CPAP, BiPAP, intubation and mechanical ventilation)</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><SummarySection id="_655"><Title>Approaches to mitigating CRS toxicities</Title><Para id="_656">Early studies of CD19-targeted CAR T cells using both CD28 and 4-1BB costimulatory domains varied in approach. The use of tocilizumab or steroids was limited to patients who experienced severe toxicities because of concern about the loss of CAR T-cell persistence (with excessive use of immune suppressive agents). These toxicities included hypotension requiring high-dose vasopressors, severe hypoxia, or intubation. After one early study showed similar efficacy in patients treated with and without tocilizumab,<Reference refidx="11"/> investigators designed approaches aimed at early treatment of CRS to limit organ damage secondary to grade 4 CRS. Some approaches have decreased toxicity without obvious effects on efficacy.</Para><Para id="_657">Evidence (early interventions for CRS):</Para><OrderedList id="_658" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Investigators at Seattle Children’s Hospital compared a strategy of early intervention versus standard practice. Early intervention included treatment with tocilizumab for patients with a fever  higher than 39°C that was unresponsive to acetaminophen, persistent hypotension after a 10 mL/kg bolus, or initiation of oxygen. Steroids were given after tocilizumab if symptoms persisted or worsened 6 to 12 hours later.<Reference refidx="12"/><ItemizedList id="_659" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The early intervention approach doubled the number of patients requiring tocilizumab or steroids but did not affect the overall minimal residual disease–negative remission rate, infection rate, long-term persistence of CAR T cells, or overall survival (OS).</ListItem><ListItem>In addition, early intervention for patients with CRS resulted in a decreased need for intubation or inotropic support, from 30% to 15%. However, this finding was not statistically significant (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .29), possibly because of the small number of patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Investigators at Children's Hospital of Philadelphia performed a prospective trial of a different strategy of early intervention. Because of earlier findings that showed that high disease burden at the time of CAR T-cell treatment was associated with severe CRS,<Reference refidx="6"/> they defined a high–tumor burden cohort as patients with 40% or more marrow blasts before infusion. Planned early intervention for this cohort was tocilizumab, given for two fevers of 38.5°C or higher, at least 4 hours apart, in a 24-hour period.<Reference refidx="13"/><ItemizedList id="_660" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Grade 4 CRS decreased from 50% (in a comparator cohort) to 27% in the high–tumor burden cohort (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .18), with no change in efficacy and long-term CAR T-cell persistence.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_647"><Title>Immune effector cell–associated neurotoxicity syndrome (ICANS)</Title><Para id="_101">Neurological toxicities, including aphasia, altered mental status, and seizures, have also been observed with CAR T-cell therapy. This clinical syndrome (ICANS) is graded according to the most severe event of the following five measures that are not attributable to any other cause:<Reference refidx="9"/> </Para><OrderedList id="_102" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Standardized neurological responsiveness score (tests vary by age: Immune Effector Cell-Associated Encephalopathy [ICE] score for children aged ≥12 years and Cornell Assessment of Pediatric Delirium [CAPD]  for children aged &lt;12 years).</ListItem><ListItem> Level of consciousness.</ListItem><ListItem>Seizure activity.</ListItem><ListItem>Motor weakness.</ListItem><ListItem>Elevated intracranial pressure/cerebral edema.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_103">Most neurological toxicities after CD19-targeted CAR T-cell therapy have been short lived (1–5 days). However, rare, fatal events such as severe cerebral edema have been reported.<Reference refidx="14"/> The pathophysiology of central nervous system (CNS) toxicity is likely related to disruption of the blood-brain barrier secondary to systemic cytokine release,<Reference refidx="14"/> high levels of cytokines in the cerebrospinal fluid,<Reference refidx="14"/> and/or direct attack of CD19-positive brain mural cells in the CNS tissue by the CAR T cells.<Reference refidx="15"/> CNS symptoms have not responded well to IL-6R–targeting agents and have generally been treated with high-dose steroids or other approaches. The exact timing of required treatment for ICANS is controversial, but concerns about its rare, fatal form have led to near-uniform recommendations for the treatment of patients with grade 3 or higher ICANS.<Reference refidx="16"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_661"><Title>Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis (HLH)–like toxicities</Title><Para id="_662">A portion of patients undergoing CAR T-cell therapy will have HLH-like toxicities associated with CRS (hyperferritinemia with organ dysfunction). Severity of symptoms and outcomes vary by CAR construct. It is not known whether early or preventive treatment  can improve patient outcomes.</Para><Para id="_663">Evidence (effect of HLH-like toxicities on patient outcomes):</Para><OrderedList id="_664" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>Investigators at the National Cancer Institute noted increased HLH-like toxicities in a trial of CD22-targeted CAR T-cell therapy.<Reference refidx="17"/><ItemizedList id="_665" Style="bullet"><ListItem>HLH-like toxicity was seen in 19 of 58 patients (32.8%). The average time to onset of HLH-like toxicity was 14 days after CAR T-cell therapy. CRS had resolved or was resolving before the onset of HLH-like features.</ListItem><ListItem>CD4/CD8 T-cell selection of the apheresis product improved CAR T-cell manufacturing feasibility. However, after this modification, patients experienced heightened HLH-like toxicities, which led to dose de-escalation.</ListItem><ListItem>HLH-like toxicity did not alter survival outcomes but often required intense interventions such as anakinra.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Investigators from the Pediatric Real World CAR Consortium analyzed 183 evaluable children and adolescent and young adult patients treated with tisagenlecleucel for B-cell ALL and found that 14% had HLH-like toxicities.<Reference refidx="18"/><ItemizedList id="_666" Style="bullet"><ListItem>HLH-like toxicity was associated with poor OS (hazard ratio [HR], 4.61; 95% confidence interval [CI], 2.41–8.83) and relapse-free survival (RFS) (HR, 3.68; 95% CI, 2.15–6.32). The 1-year RFS and OS rates were 25.7% and 4.7%, respectively, for patients with HLH-like toxicities, compared with 80.1% and 57.6%, respectively, for patients without HLH-like toxicities.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients who developed HLH-like toxicity had higher pre-infusion disease burden, ferritin levels, and C-reactive protein levels, compared with patients who did not develop HLH-like toxicity. Patients who developed HLH-like toxicity also had lower pre-infusion platelet  and absolute neutrophil counts.</ListItem><ListItem>Patients who developed HLH-like toxicity subsequently had higher rates of infection, relapse, and nonrelapse mortality. </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_648"><Title>Other side effects of CAR T-cell therapy</Title><Para id="_104">Other CAR T-cell therapy side effects include the following:    </Para><ItemizedList id="_649" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Coagulopathy.</ListItem><ListItem> Cardiac dysfunction.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_650">Early studies of patients with high levels of disease and delayed CRS therapy resulted in 20% to 40% of patients requiring treatment in the intensive care unit (ICU) (mostly vasopressor support, with 10%  to 20% of patients requiring intubation and/or dialysis).<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> However, current real-world data show that ICU requirements are now approximately 10% to 20%.<Reference refidx="19"/></Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_651"><Title>Approved CAR T-Cell Therapies</Title><Para id="_105">  An international trial in children led to U.S. Food and Drug Administration approval of tisagenlecleucel for patients aged 1 to 25 years  with CD19-positive B-cell ALL that is refractory or in second or later relapse.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_652">  Tisagenlecleucel has also been approved for adults with relapsed or refractory B-cell lymphoma, as has axicabtagene ciloleucel, brexucabtagene autoleucel, and lisocabtagene maraleucel.<Reference refidx="21"/><Reference refidx="22"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21832238">Kalos M, Levine BL, Porter DL, et al.: T cells with chimeric antigen receptors have potent antitumor effects and can establish memory in patients with advanced leukemia. Sci Transl Med 3 (95): 95ra73, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="23527958">Grupp SA, Kalos M, Barrett D, et al.: Chimeric antigen receptor-modified T cells for acute lymphoid leukemia. N Engl J Med 368 (16): 1509-18, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25319501">Lee DW, Kochenderfer JN, Stetler-Stevenson M, et al.: T cells expressing CD19 chimeric antigen receptors for acute lymphoblastic leukaemia in children and young adults: a phase 1 dose-escalation trial. Lancet 385 (9967): 517-28, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="24553386">Davila ML, Riviere I, Wang X, et al.: Efficacy and toxicity management of 19-28z CAR T cell therapy in B cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Sci Transl Med 6 (224): 224ra25, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="28408462">Gardner RA, Finney O, Annesley C, et al.: Intent-to-treat leukemia remission by CD19 CAR T cells of defined formulation and dose in children and young adults. Blood 129 (25): 3322-3331, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="25317870">Maude SL, Frey N, Shaw PA, et al.: Chimeric antigen receptor T cells for sustained remissions in leukemia. N Engl J Med 371 (16): 1507-17, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="24876563">Lee DW, Gardner R, Porter DL, et al.: Current concepts in the diagnosis and management of cytokine release syndrome. Blood 124 (2): 188-95, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="24667956">Maude SL, Barrett D, Teachey DT, et al.: Managing cytokine release syndrome associated with novel T cell-engaging therapies. Cancer J 20 (2): 119-22, 2014 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="30592986">Lee DW, Santomasso BD, Locke FL, et al.: ASTCT Consensus Grading for Cytokine Release Syndrome and Neurologic Toxicity Associated with Immune Effector Cells. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 25 (4): 625-638, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="37821079">McNerney KO, Hsieh EM, Shalabi H, et al.: INSPIRED Symposium Part 3: Prevention and Management of Pediatric Chimeric Antigen Receptor T Cell-Associated Emergent Toxicities. Transplant Cell Ther 30 (1): 38-55, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="30190371">Mueller KT, Waldron E, Grupp SA, et al.: Clinical Pharmacology of Tisagenlecleucel in B-cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia. Clin Cancer Res 24 (24): 6175-6184, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="31697826">Gardner RA, Ceppi F, Rivers J, et al.: Preemptive mitigation of CD19 CAR T-cell cytokine release syndrome without attenuation of antileukemic efficacy. Blood 134 (24): 2149-2158, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="33417474">Kadauke S, Myers RM, Li Y, et al.: Risk-Adapted Preemptive Tocilizumab to Prevent Severe Cytokine Release Syndrome After CTL019 for Pediatric B-Cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia: A Prospective Clinical Trial. J Clin Oncol 39 (8): 920-930, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="33391257">Gust J, Ponce R, Liles WC, et al.: Cytokines in CAR T Cell-Associated Neurotoxicity. Front Immunol 11: 577027, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="32961131">Parker KR, Migliorini D, Perkey E, et al.: Single-Cell Analyses Identify Brain Mural Cells Expressing CD19 as Potential Off-Tumor Targets for CAR-T Immunotherapies. Cell 183 (1): 126-142.e17, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="33608690">Ragoonanan D, Khazal SJ, Abdel-Azim H, et al.: Diagnosis, grading and management of toxicities from immunotherapies in children, adolescents and young adults with cancer. Nat Rev Clin Oncol 18 (7): 435-453, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="32286905">Shah NN, Highfill SL, Shalabi H, et al.: CD4/CD8 T-Cell Selection Affects Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T-Cell Potency and Toxicity: Updated Results From a Phase I Anti-CD22 CAR T-Cell Trial. J Clin Oncol 38 (17): 1938-1950, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="36857419">McNerney KO, Si Lim SJ, Ishikawa K, et al.: HLH-like toxicities predict poor survival after the use of tisagenlecleucel in children and young adults with B-ALL. Blood Adv 7 (12): 2758-2771, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="33147337">Pasquini MC, Hu ZH, Curran K, et al.: Real-world evidence of tisagenlecleucel for pediatric acute lymphoblastic leukemia and non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Blood Adv 4 (21): 5414-5424, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="29385370">Maude SL, Laetsch TW, Buechner J, et al.: Tisagenlecleucel in Children and Young Adults with B-Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia. N Engl J Med 378 (5): 439-448, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="29914976">Chow VA, Shadman M, Gopal AK: Translating anti-CD19 CAR T-cell therapy into clinical practice for relapsed/refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. Blood 132 (8): 777-781, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="29226797">Neelapu SS, Locke FL, Bartlett NL, et al.: Axicabtagene Ciloleucel CAR T-Cell Therapy in Refractory Large B-Cell Lymphoma. N Engl J Med 377 (26): 2531-2544, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_124"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (06/13/2024)</Title><Para id="_125">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available. This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_669">This summary was comprehensively reviewed.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000805706#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/car-t-cell-therapy">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the use of CAR T-cell therapy in treating pediatric cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Pediatric Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T-Cell Therapy are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Thomas G. Gross, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Michael A. Pulsipher, MD (Huntsman Cancer Institute at University of Utah)</ListItem><ListItem>Sarah K. Tasian, MD (Children's Hospital of Philadelphia)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Pediatric Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T-Cell Therapy. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/car-t-cell-therapy">https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/hp-stem-cell-transplant/car-t-cell-therapy</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 35133769]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-02-04</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-06-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
