<Summary id="CDR0000809680" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Hepatoblastoma is the most common type of childhood liver cancer. Learn about causes, risk factors, signs, symptoms, diagnosis, and treatment options.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/childhood-liver-cancer/hepatoblastoma">Hepatoblastoma</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043722">childhood hepatoblastoma</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043714">childhood liver cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood hepatoblastoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood liver cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Hepatoblastoma</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Hepatoblastoma</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Hepatoblastoma</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">Hepatoblastoma is a cancer that forms in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissues</GlossaryTermRef> of the liver. It is the most common type of childhood liver cancer and usually affects children younger than 3 years of age.</Para><Para id="_3">The liver is one of the largest organs in the body. It has two lobes and fills the upper right side of the abdomen inside the rib cage. Three of the many important functions of the liver are:</Para><ItemizedList id="_4" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>to make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef> to help digest fats from food  </ListItem><ListItem>to store glycogen (sugar), which the body uses for energy  </ListItem><ListItem>to filter harmful substances from the blood so they can be passed from the body in stools and urine</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000659745" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the liver; drawing shows the right and left lobes of the liver. Also shown are the bile ducts, gallbladder, stomach, spleen, pancreas, small intestine, and colon." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_114"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the liver. The liver is in the upper abdomen near the stomach, intestines, gallbladder, and pancreas. The liver has a right lobe and a left lobe. Each lobe is divided into two sections (not shown). </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_6">In hepatoblastoma, the histology (how the cancer cells look under a microscope) affects the way the cancer is treated. The histology for hepatoblastoma includes: </Para><ItemizedList id="_7" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774690" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">well-differentiated</GlossaryTermRef> fetal (pure fetal) histology </ListItem><ListItem>small cell <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044775" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">undifferentiated</GlossaryTermRef> histology hepatoblastoma and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046139" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rhabdoid tumors</GlossaryTermRef> of the liver </ListItem><ListItem>mixed <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045682" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">epithelial</GlossaryTermRef> and fetal histology (non–well-differentiated fetal histology, non-small cell undifferentiated histology)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Causes and risk factors for hepatoblastoma</Title><Para id="_118">Hepatoblastoma is caused by certain changes in the way the liver cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. Often, the exact cause of these changes is unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_12">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with one or more of these risk factors will develop hepatoblastoma. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor.  </Para><Para id="_13">The following syndromes or conditions are risk factors for hepatoblastoma: </Para><ItemizedList id="_14" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000764137" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Aicardi syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304689" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000785255" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemihyperplasia</GlossaryTermRef> </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000805530" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">familial adenomatous polyposis</GlossaryTermRef> (FAP) </ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748984" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glycogen storage disease</GlossaryTermRef> </ListItem><ListItem>premature birth with a very low weight at birth </ListItem><ListItem>Simpson-Golabi-Behmel syndrome </ListItem><ListItem>certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046391" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic</GlossaryTermRef> changes, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775143" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">trisomy 18</GlossaryTermRef> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_171">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_172"><Title>Monitoring children at risk of hepatoblastoma</Title><Para id="_15">Children with Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome, hemihyperplasia, Simpson-Golabi-Behmel syndrome, and trisomy 18 may have tests done to check for cancer before any symptoms appear. These tests may help find cancer early and improve your child's chance of survival.</Para><Para id="_173">Children at risk of developing hepatoblastoma have an abdominal ultrasound exam every 3 months from birth (or diagnosis of a risk factor) until they are 4 years old.  They also have blood tests to check the level of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046208" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">alpha-fetoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> (AFP). </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Symptoms of hepatoblastoma </Title><Para id="_119">Children may not have symptoms of hepatoblastoma until the tumor has grown bigger. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_10" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>a lump in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>swelling in the abdomen </ListItem><ListItem>pain in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason </ListItem><ListItem>loss of appetite </ListItem><ListItem>nausea and vomiting </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_120">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than hepatoblastoma. The only way to know is for your child to see a doctor. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose hepatoblastoma  </Title><Para id="_121">If your child has symptoms that suggest hepatoblastoma, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Based on these results, the doctor may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with hepatoblastoma, the results of these tests will also help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_18">The tests used to diagnose hepatoblastoma may include: </Para><SummarySection id="_122"><Title>Serum tumor marker test</Title><Para id="_123">Serum <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor marker</GlossaryTermRef> tests measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs, tissues, or tumor cells in the body. Certain substances are linked to specific types of cancer when found in increased levels in the blood. These are called tumor markers. The blood of children who have liver cancer may have increased amounts of a hormone called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354453" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">beta-human chorionic gonadotropin</GlossaryTermRef> (beta-hCG) or a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> called AFP. Other cancers, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045614" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">benign</GlossaryTermRef> liver tumors, and certain noncancer conditions, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045478" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cirrhosis</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis</GlossaryTermRef>, can also increase AFP levels. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_124"><Title><GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> gene testing</Title><Para id="_125"><GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> gene testing is a laboratory test in which a sample of blood or tissue is tested for certain changes in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> gene.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_126"><Title>Complete blood count (CBC)</Title><Para id="_127">A CBC checks a sample of blood for:</Para><ItemizedList id="_20" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef> </ListItem><ListItem>the amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemoglobin</GlossaryTermRef> (the protein that carries oxygen) in the red blood cells </ListItem><ListItem>the portion of the blood sample made up of red blood cells </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_128"><Title>Liver function tests</Title><Para id="_129">Liver function tests measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by the liver. A higher-than-normal amount of a substance can be a sign of liver damage or cancer. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_130"><Title>Blood chemistry studies</Title><Para id="_131"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef> measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044518" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilirubin</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lactate dehydrogenase</GlossaryTermRef> (LDH), released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.   </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_132"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with gadolinium</Title><Para id="_133">MRI uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the liver. A substance called gadolinium is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. This procedure is also called nuclear MRI.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_21"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_134"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_135">A CT scan  uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. </Para><Para id="_136">A CT scan of the chest and abdomen is usually done to help diagnose childhood liver cancer. </Para><Para id="_137">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_103"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_138"><Title>Ultrasound exam</Title><Para id="_139">An ultrasound exam is a procedure in which high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) are bounced off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. An ultrasound exam of the abdomen to check the large blood vessels is usually done to help diagnose childhood liver cancer. </Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775457" type="image/jpeg" alt="Abdominal ultrasound; drawing shows a child lying on an exam table during an abdominal ultrasound procedure. A technician is shown pressing a transducer (a device that makes sound waves that bounce off tissues inside the body) against the skin of the abdomen. A computer screen shows a sonogram (picture)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_23"><Caption language="en">Abdominal ultrasound. An ultrasound transducer connected to a computer is pressed against the skin of the abdomen. The transducer bounces sound waves off internal organs and tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture).</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_140"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_141">An x-ray is a type of high-energy radiation that can go through the body and make pictures. A chest x-ray is one that makes pictures of the lungs. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_142"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_143">Biopsy is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the tumor so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for cancer. The doctor may remove as much tumor as safely possible during the same biopsy procedure. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_144"><Title>Immunohistochemistry</Title><Para id="_145">Immunohistochemistry uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (markers) in a sample of a patient's tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to check for a certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046063" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">mutation</GlossaryTermRef>, to help diagnose cancer, and to help tell one type of cancer from another type of cancer. This test may be used to look for changes in the <GeneName>INI1</GeneName> gene.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_146"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_147">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's  diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>, slides, and scans before giving a recommendation. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's cancer.</Para><Para id="_148">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor</ExternalRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Prognostic factors for hepatoblastoma  </Title><Para id="_27">If your child has been diagnosed with hepatoblastoma, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis. </Para><Para id="_165">The prognosis for hepatoblastoma depends on:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_28" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>whether the cancer has spread throughout the liver</ListItem><ListItem>the size of the tumor </ListItem><ListItem>whether the type of hepatoblastoma is well-differentiated fetal (pure fetal) or small cell undifferentiated histology</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to other places in the body, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diaphragm</GlossaryTermRef>, lungs, or certain large blood vessels </ListItem><ListItem>whether there is more than one tumor in the liver </ListItem><ListItem>whether the outer covering around the tumor has broken open </ListItem><ListItem>how the cancer responds to chemotherapy </ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer can be removed completely by surgery</ListItem><ListItem>whether your child can have a liver transplant </ListItem><ListItem>whether the AFP blood levels go down after treatment </ListItem><ListItem>your child's age  </ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has come back after treatment  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_29">For hepatoblastoma that comes back after initial treatment, the prognosis depends on: </Para><ItemizedList id="_30" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>where in the body the tumor recurred </ListItem><ListItem>the type of treatment used to treat the initial cancer </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_31">Hepatoblastoma may be cured if the tumor is small and can be completely removed by surgery. </Para><Para id="_166">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><Title>Stages of hepatoblastoma  </Title><Para id="_149">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, especially whether the cancer has spread from where it first formed to other parts of the body.</Para><Para id="_33">In hepatoblastoma, the PRETEXT and POSTTEXT groups are used instead of stage to plan treatment. The results of the tests and procedures done to detect, diagnose, and find out whether the cancer has spread are used to determine the PRETEXT and POSTTEXT groups. </Para><Para id="_34">Two grouping systems are used for hepatoblastoma to decide whether the tumor can be removed by surgery: </Para><ItemizedList id="_35" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The PRETEXT group describes the tumor <Emphasis>before</Emphasis> the patient has any treatment. </ListItem><ListItem>The POSTTEXT group describes the tumor <Emphasis>after</Emphasis> the patient has had treatment such as neoadjuvant chemotherapy. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_36">The liver is divided into four sections for the two grouping systems. The PRETEXT and POSTTEXT groups depend on which sections of the liver have cancer. There are four PRETEXT and POSTTEXT groups. </Para><SummarySection id="_104"><Title>PRETEXT and POSTTEXT group I </Title><MediaLink ref="CDR0000686670" type="image/jpeg" alt="Liver PRETEXT and POSTTEXT I; drawing shows two livers. Dotted lines divide each liver into four vertical sections of about the same size. In the first liver, cancer is shown in the section on the far left. In the second liver, cancer is shown in the section on the far right." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_37"><Caption language="en">Liver PRETEXT and POSTTEXT I. Cancer is found in one section of the liver. Three sections of the liver that are next to each other do not have cancer in them.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_105">In group I, the cancer is found in one section of the liver. Three sections of the liver that are next to each other do not have cancer in them.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><Title>PRETEXT and POSTTEXT group II </Title><MediaLink ref="CDR0000686671" type="image/jpeg" alt="Liver PRETEXT and POSTTEXT II; drawing shows five livers. Dotted lines divide each liver into four vertical sections that are about the same size. In the first liver, cancer is shown in the two sections on the left. In the second liver, cancer is shown in the two sections on the right. In the third liver, cancer is shown in the far left and far right sections. In the fourth liver, cancer is shown in the second section from the left. In the fifth liver, cancer is shown in the second section from the right." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_38"><Caption language="en">Liver PRETEXT and POSTTEXT II. Cancer is found in one or two sections of the liver. Two sections of the liver that are next to each other do not have cancer in them.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_107">In group II, cancer is found in one or two sections of the liver. Two sections of the liver that are next to each other do not have cancer in them.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_108"><Title>PRETEXT and POSTTEXT group III </Title><MediaLink ref="CDR0000686673" type="image/jpeg" alt="Liver PRETEXT and POSTTEXT III; drawing shows seven livers. Dotted lines divide each liver into four vertical sections that are about the same size. In the first liver, cancer is shown in three sections on the left. In the second liver, cancer is shown in the two sections on the left and the section on the far right. In the third liver, cancer is shown in the section on the far left and the two sections on the right. In the fourth liver, cancer is shown in three sections on the right. In the fifth liver, cancer is shown in the two middle sections. In the sixth liver, cancer is shown in the section on the far left and in the second section from the right. In the seventh liver, cancer is shown in the section on the far right and in the second section from the left." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_39"><Caption language="en">Liver PRETEXT and POSTTEXT III. Cancer is found in three sections of the liver and one section does not have cancer in it, or cancer is found in two sections of the liver and two sections that are not next to each other do not have cancer in them.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_40">In group III, one of the following is true: </Para><ItemizedList id="_41" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Cancer is found in three sections of the liver, and one section does not have cancer. </ListItem><ListItem>Cancer is found in two sections of the liver, and two sections that are not next to each other do not have cancer in them. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_109"><Title>PRETEXT and POSTTEXT group IV </Title><MediaLink ref="CDR0000686674" type="image/jpeg" alt="Liver PRETEXT and POSTTEXT IV; drawing shows two livers. Dotted lines divide each liver into four vertical sections that are about the same size. In the first liver, cancer is shown across all four sections. In the second liver, cancer is shown in the two sections on the left and spots of cancer are shown in the two sections on the right." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_42"><Caption language="en">Liver PRETEXT and POSTTEXT IV. Cancer is found in all four sections of the liver.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_43">In group IV, cancer is found in all four sections of the liver.  </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_150"><Title>Progressive and recurrent hepatoblastoma</Title><Para id="_151">Hepatoblastoma can be a progressive or refractory disease. Progressive hepatoblastoma is cancer that continues to grow, spread, or worsen. Refractory hepatoblastoma is cancer that no longer responds to treatment.</Para><Para id="_152">Recurrent hepatoblastoma is cancer that has recurred (come back) after it has been treated. The cancer may come back in the liver or as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> tumors in other  parts of the body. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned in the body, if it has spread, and how far. The type of treatment that your child will have for recurrent hepatoblastoma will depend on how far it has spread.</Para><Para id="_153">Learn more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_52"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Types of treatment for hepatoblastoma </Title><Para id="_154">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with hepatoblastoma. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_48">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of hepatoblastoma. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with hepatoblastoma and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. It is especially important to have a pediatric surgeon with experience in liver surgery who can send patients to a liver transplant program if needed. </Para><Para id="_170">Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_49" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutritionist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_155">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, visit our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_54"><Title>Surgery  </Title><Para id="_55">When possible, the cancer is removed by surgery. The types of surgery that may be done are: </Para><ItemizedList id="_56" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Partial hepatectomy</Strong> is surgery to remove the part of the liver where cancer is found. The part removed may be a wedge of tissue, an entire lobe, or a larger part of the liver, along with a small amount of normal tissue around it.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Liver transplant</Strong> is the removal of the entire liver by surgery, followed by a transplant of a healthy liver from a donor. A liver transplant may be possible when cancer has not spread beyond the liver, and a donated liver can be found. If the patient has to wait for a donated liver, other treatment is given as needed.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Resection of metastases</Strong> is surgery to remove cancer that has spread outside of the liver, such as to nearby tissues, the lungs, or the brain.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_57">The type of surgery that can be done depends on: </Para><ItemizedList id="_58" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the PRETEXT group and POSTTEXT group </ListItem><ListItem>the size of the primary tumor </ListItem><ListItem>whether there is more than one tumor in the liver </ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to nearby large blood vessels </ListItem><ListItem>the level of AFP in the blood </ListItem><ListItem>whether the tumor can be shrunk by chemotherapy, so that it can be removed by surgery </ListItem><ListItem>whether a liver transplant is needed </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_59">Chemotherapy is sometimes given before surgery to shrink the tumor and make it easier to remove. This is called neoadjuvant therapy. </Para><Para id="_60">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some patients may be given chemotherapy or radiation therapy to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after the surgery to lower the risk that the cancer will come back is called adjuvant therapy. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_61"><Title>Watchful waiting </Title><Para id="_62">Watchful waiting is closely monitoring a patient's condition without giving any treatment until signs or symptoms appear or change. In hepatoblastoma, this treatment is only used for small well-differentiated fetal (pure fetal) histology tumors that have been completely removed by surgery. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_63"><Title>Chemotherapy </Title><Para id="_64">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cancer cells or stops them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_156">There are two ways to give chemotherapy to treat hepatoblastoma:</Para><ItemizedList id="_117" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Systemic chemotherapy</Strong> is chemotherapy that is injected into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Regional chemotherapy</Strong> is chemotherapy that is placed directly into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046483" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cerebrospinal fluid</GlossaryTermRef>, an organ, or a body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef> such as the abdomen. When given this way, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas. <Para id="_65">Chemoembolization of the hepatic artery (the main artery that supplies blood to the liver) is a type of regional chemotherapy used to treat hepatoblastoma that cannot be removed by surgery. The anticancer drug is injected into the hepatic artery through a catheter (thin tube). The drug is mixed with a substance that blocks the artery, cutting off blood flow to the tumor. Most of the anticancer drug is trapped near the tumor, and only a small amount of the drug reaches other parts of the body. The blockage may be temporary or permanent, depending on the substance used to block the artery. The tumor is prevented from getting the oxygen and nutrients it needs to grow. The liver continues to receive blood from the hepatic portal vein, which carries blood from the stomach and intestine to the liver. This procedure is also called transarterial chemoembolization, or TACE. </Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_157">Chemotherapy drugs used alone or in combination to treat hepatoblastoma include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_158" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000542867" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/doxorubicinhydrochloride">doxorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537894" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/fluorouracil">fluorouracil</DrugRef> (5-FU)</ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000686471" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ifosfamide">ifosfamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537382" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecanhydrochloride">irinotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599877" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vincristinesulfate">vincristine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_159">Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_160">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_68"><Title>Radiation therapy  </Title><Para id="_69">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. The way the radiation therapy is given depends on the type of cancer being treated and the PRETEXT or POSTTEXT group. </Para><Para id="_70">Hepatoblastoma may be treated with external beam radiation therapy or internal radiation therapy:</Para><ItemizedList id="_71" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>External radiation therapy</Strong> uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. External radiation therapy is used to treat hepatoblastoma that cannot be removed by surgery or has spread to other parts of the body. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal radiation therapy</Strong> uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or catheters that are placed directly into or near the cancer. <Para id="_72">Radioembolization is a type of internal radiation therapy used to treat hepatoblastoma. A very small amount of a radioactive substance is attached to tiny beads that are injected into the hepatic artery (the main artery that supplies blood to the liver) through a thin tube called a catheter. The beads are mixed with a substance that blocks the artery, cutting off blood flow to the tumor. Most of the radiation is trapped near the tumor to kill the cancer cells. This is done to shrink the tumor or to relieve symptoms and improve quality of life for children with hepatoblastoma. </Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_115">Learn more about radiation therapy and its side effects at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_73"><Title>Radiofrequency ablation therapy </Title><Para id="_161">Radiofrequency ablation uses needles inserted directly through the skin or through an incision in the abdomen to reach the tumor. High-energy radio waves heat the needles and tumor, which kills cancer cells. Radiofrequency ablation is being used to treat recurrent hepatoblastoma. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_79"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Clinical trials  </Title><Para id="_79_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_79_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_79_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_91"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043722">childhood hepatoblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of newly diagnosed hepatoblastoma </Title><Para id="_92">Treatment of newly diagnosed hepatoblastoma that can be removed by surgery at the time of diagnosis may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_93" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>surgery to remove the tumor, followed by combination chemotherapy, for hepatoblastoma that is mixed epithelial and fetal histology (not well-differentiated fetal histology) or aggressive chemotherapy for small cell undifferentiated histology</ListItem><ListItem>surgery to remove the tumor, followed by watchful waiting or chemotherapy, for hepatoblastoma with well-differentiated fetal histology </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_94">Treatment of newly diagnosed hepatoblastoma that cannot be removed by surgery or is not removed at the time of diagnosis may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_95" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>combination chemotherapy to shrink the tumor, followed by surgery to remove the tumor </ListItem><ListItem>combination chemotherapy, followed by a liver transplant </ListItem><ListItem>chemoembolization or radioembolization of the hepatic artery to shrink the tumor, followed by surgery to remove the tumor </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_96">For newly diagnosed hepatoblastoma that has spread to other parts of the body at the time of diagnosis, combination chemotherapy is given to shrink the tumors in the liver and cancer that has spread to other parts of the body. After chemotherapy, imaging tests are done to check whether the tumors can be removed by surgery. 

</Para><Para id="_110">Treatment may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_97" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>if the tumors in the liver and other parts of the body (usually nodules in the lung) can be removed, surgery will be done to remove the tumors, followed by chemotherapy to kill any cancer cells that may remain </ListItem><ListItem>if the tumor in other parts of the body cannot be removed, or a liver transplant is not possible, chemotherapy, chemoembolization or radioembolization of the hepatic artery, or radiation therapy may be given </ListItem><ListItem>if the tumor in other parts of the body cannot be removed, or the patient does not want surgery, radiofrequency ablation may be given </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_100"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000043722">childhood hepatoblastoma</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment of progressive or recurrent hepatoblastoma </Title><Para id="_101">Treatment of progressive or recurrent hepatoblastoma may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_102" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>surgery to remove isolated (single and separate) metastatic tumors with or without chemotherapy </ListItem><ListItem>radiofrequency ablation </ListItem><ListItem>combination chemotherapy </ListItem><ListItem>liver transplant </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_83"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_174">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_162">To learn more about side effects that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_85">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of treatment may include:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_86" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>physical problems that affect liver function or hearing</ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory  </ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer) </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_87">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the long-term effects cancer treatment can have on your child. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_88"><Title>Follow-up care  </Title><Para id="_89">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer or to find out the treatment group may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests. </Para><Para id="_90">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed, or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_175">To learn more about follow-up tests, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809680#_16" url="/types/liver/childhood-liver-cancer/hepatoblastoma">Tests to diagnose hepatoblastoma</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_163"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_164">When a child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.   </Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-05-19</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-02-21</DateLastModified></Summary>
