<Summary id="CDR0000809695" SVPC="Yes" SuppressOnThisPageSection="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Stages</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>There are several staging systems for liver cancer. Staging is used to predict a person's chance of recovery and plan treatment. Learn more about liver cancer staging. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/what-is-liver-cancer/stages">Liver Cancer Stages</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038756">adult primary liver cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>liver cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Liver Cancer Stages</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Liver Cancer Stages</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Liver Cancer Stages</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">This page describes the stages of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver cancer</GlossaryTermRef> for adults. The stage describes the extent of cancer in the body. Knowing the stage of liver cancer helps the doctor plan the best treatment.</Para><Para id="_14">To learn about liver cancer stages for children, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809680#_32" url="/types/liver/childhood-liver-cancer/hepatoblastoma">Stages of hepatoblastoma</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_3">To learn about the tests and procedures used to diagnose and stage primary liver cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809694" url="/types/liver/what-is-liver-cancer/diagnosis">Liver Cancer Diagnosis</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_5">There are several staging systems for liver cancer. The Barcelona Clinic Liver Cancer (BCLC) Staging System is widely used to stage primary liver cancer. The system is used to predict the patient’s chance of recovery and to plan treatment, based on the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_6" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>whether the cancer has spread within the liver or to other parts of the body</ListItem><ListItem>how well the liver is working</ListItem><ListItem>the general health and wellness of the patient</ListItem><ListItem>the symptoms caused by the cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_7">The BCLC staging system has five stages:</Para><ItemizedList id="_8" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>stage 0: very early</ListItem><ListItem>stage A: early</ListItem><ListItem>stage B: intermediate</ListItem><ListItem>stage C: advanced</ListItem><ListItem>stage D: end-stage</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_9">For liver cancer in adults, stages are also grouped according to how the cancer may be treated:</Para><ItemizedList id="_10" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045754" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Localized</GlossaryTermRef> liver cancer has not spread outside the liver and can be removed by surgery. This includes BCLC stages 0, A, and B.</ListItem><ListItem> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> liver cancer has not spread from the liver to distant parts of the body but cannot be safely removed by surgery. This includes BCLC stage C.</ListItem><ListItem> Metastatic liver cancer is cancer that has spread from the liver to distant parts of the body. Metastatic liver cancer cannot be completely removed by surgery. This includes BCLC stage D. To learn more about metastatic cancer, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</ListItem><ListItem>Recurrent liver cancer is cancer that came back after treatment. The cancer may come back in the liver or in other parts of the body. To learn more about recurrent cancer, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_26">To learn about other ways cancer stages can be described, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_17">To learn about treatment options, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809696" url="/types/liver/what-is-liver-cancer/treatment">Liver Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-05-19</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-05-15</DateLastModified></Summary>
