<Summary id="CDR0000809670" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>There are standard bile duct cancer (cholangiocarcinoma) treatments and new treatments being tested in clinical trials. Learn more about bile duct cancer treatments.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/bile-duct-cancer/treatment">Bile Duct Cancer Treatment</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000774341">bile duct cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bile duct cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Bile Duct Cancer Treatment</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Bile Duct Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Bile Duct Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">This page describes the different types of treatment for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527370" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile duct cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (cholangiocarcinoma). Which of these treatments a person receives will depend on whether the cancer can be completely removed with surgery (resectable) or not (unresectable). To learn more, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809670#_37" url="/types/liver/bile-duct-cancer/treatment">treatment of resectable</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809670#_46" url="/types/liver/bile-duct-cancer/treatment">treatment of unresectable</SummaryRef> bile duct cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Types of treatment</Title><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>Surgery </Title><Para id="_5">The following types of surgery are used to treat bile duct cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_6" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Removal of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile duct</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: This surgical procedure is done to remove part of the bile duct if the tumor is small and is in the bile duct only. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> are removed and tissue from the lymph nodes is viewed under a microscope to see if there is cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Partial hepatectomy</Strong>: This is a surgical procedure to remove the part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef> where cancer is found. The part removed may be a wedge of tissue, an entire <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046188" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lobe</GlossaryTermRef>, or a larger part of the liver, along with some normal tissue around it.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Whipple procedure</Strong>: During this surgical procedure the head of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046254" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pancreas</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallbladder</GlossaryTermRef>, part of the stomach, part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046582" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">small intestine</GlossaryTermRef>, and the bile duct are removed. Enough of the pancreas is left to make digestive juices and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046187" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">insulin</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_7">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, some people may receive chemotherapy or radiation therapy to kill any cancer cells that are left. Treatment given after surgery to lower the risk that the cancer will come back is called adjuvant therapy. It is not yet known whether chemotherapy or radiation therapy given after surgery helps keep the cancer from coming back.</Para><Para id="_8">The following types of palliative surgery may be done to relieve symptoms caused by a blocked bile duct and improve quality of life:</Para><ItemizedList id="_9" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775967" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biliary bypass</GlossaryTermRef></Strong>: If cancer is blocking the bile duct and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef> is building up in the gallbladder, a biliary bypass may be done. During this operation, the doctor will cut the gallbladder or bile duct in the area before the blockage and sew it to the part of the bile duct that is past the blockage or to the small intestine. This type of surgery creates a new pathway around the blocked area.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Endoscopic stent placement</Strong>: If the tumor is blocking the bile duct, surgery may be done to put in a stent (a thin, flexible tube) to drain bile that has built up in the area. The doctor may place the stent through a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> that drains the bile into a bag on the outside of the body or the stent may go around the blocked area and drain the bile into the small intestine.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage</Strong>: This procedure is used to x-ray the liver and bile ducts. A thin needle is inserted through the skin below the ribs and into the liver. Dye is injected into the liver or bile ducts and an x-ray is taken. If the bile duct is blocked, a stent may be left in the liver to drain bile into the small intestine or a collection bag outside the body.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>Radiation therapy    </Title><Para id="_11">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. These are the main ways radiation might be given to treat bile duct cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_12" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>External radiation therapy</Strong>: A machine outside the body sends radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation is given in a series of treatments to allow healthy cells to recover and to make radiation more effective. The number of treatments is based on details about the cancer, such as the size and location of the tumor. <Para id="_13">It is not known whether external radiation therapy helps in the treatment of resectable bile duct cancer. In <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045936" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">unresectable</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045862" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">recurrent</GlossaryTermRef> bile duct cancer, new ways to improve the effect of external radiation therapy on cancer cells are being studied:</Para><ItemizedList id="_14" Style="dash">
     <ListItem><Strong>Hyperthermia therapy</Strong>: Body tissue is exposed to high temperatures to make cancer cells more sensitive to the effects of radiation therapy and certain anticancer drugs.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Radiosensitizers</Strong>: Drugs called radiosensitizers make cancer cells more sensitive to radiation therapy. Combining radiation therapy with radiosensitizers may kill more cancer cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Internal radiation therapy</Strong>: A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance is sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or catheters that are placed directly into or near the bile duct.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_52">External and internal radiation therapy are used to treat bile duct cancer and may also be used as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve symptoms and improve quality of life.</Para><Para id="_15">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy">Radiation Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Chemotherapy     </Title><Para id="_17">Chemotherapy uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. There are two main types of chemotherapy used to treat bile duct cancer.</Para><ItemizedList id="_53" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Systemic chemotherapy</Strong>: When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or injected into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body. <Para id="_54">Systemic chemotherapy is used to treat unresectable, metastatic, or recurrent bile duct cancer. The following chemotherapy drugs may be used:</Para><ItemizedList id="_55" Style="dash">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000632971" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/GEMCITABINE-CISPLATIN">gemcitabine and cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000716081" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/XELOX">capecitabine and oxaliplatin (XELOX)</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000750865" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/GEMCITABINE-OXALIPLATIN">gemcitabine and oxaliplatin</DrugRef> (GEMOX)</ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495426" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemcitabinehydrochloride">gemcitabine</DrugRef> and <DrugRef href="CDR0000496354" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/capecitabine">capecitabine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Regional chemotherapy</Strong>: When chemotherapy is placed directly into an organ, or a body <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef> such as the abdomen, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas.<Para id="_19">Intra-arterial embolization is being studied in the treatment of unresectable, metastatic, or recurrent bile duct cancer. It is a procedure in which the blood supply to a tumor is blocked after anticancer drugs are given in blood vessels near the tumor. Sometimes, the anticancer drugs are attached to small beads that are injected into an artery that feeds the tumor. The beads block blood flow to the tumor as they release the drug. This allows a higher amount of drug to reach the tumor for a longer period of time, which may kill more cancer cells.</Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18">It is not known whether systemic chemotherapy helps in the treatment of resectable bile duct cancer. </Para><Para id="_20">To learn about the different ways chemotherapy works against cancer, what to expect when receiving chemotherapy, and how to manage chemotherapy side effects, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_21"><Title>Liver transplant</Title><Para id="_22">In a liver transplant, the entire liver is removed and replaced with a healthy donated liver. A liver transplant may be done in people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792694" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">perihilar bile duct</GlossaryTermRef> cancer. If the person has to wait for a donated liver, other treatment is given as needed.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><Title>Targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_24">Targeted therapy is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. Your doctor may suggest <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000805418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biomarker tests</GlossaryTermRef> to help predict your response to certain targeted therapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_58">The following targeted therapy drugs may be used to treat bile duct cancer: </Para><ItemizedList id="_25" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000794061" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ivosidenib">ivosidenib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000801476" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pemigatinib">pemigatinib</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_26">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><Title>Immunotherapy   </Title><Para id="_28">Immunotherapy helps a person’s immune system fight cancer. </Para><Para id="_29">The following immunotherapy drugs may be used to treat bile duct cancer: </Para><ItemizedList id="_30" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000788795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/durvalumab">durvalumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_32">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy/side-effects">Immunotherapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><Title>Clinical trials   </Title><Para id="_33_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_33_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_33_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_37"><Title>Treatment of resectable (localized) bile duct cancer  </Title><Para id="_56">If the cancer has not spread and is in a place where surgery can be safely done, the tumor and some of the tissue around it will be removed. This lowers the chance of the cancer coming back. Chemotherapy with or without radiation therapy may be given after surgery.</Para><Para id="_38">Treatment of resectable <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000770184" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrahepatic bile duct cancer</GlossaryTermRef> may include surgery to remove the cancer. A partial hepatectomy with or without embolization may be done before the surgery.</Para><Para id="_40">Treatment of resectable perihilar bile duct cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_41" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>surgery to remove the cancer, which may include partial hepatectomy</ListItem><ListItem>stent placement or percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage, as palliative therapy to         relieve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046328" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">jaundice</GlossaryTermRef> and other symptoms and improve     <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of    life</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_42">Treatment of resectable distal bile duct cancer may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_43" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>surgery to remove the cancer, which may include a Whipple procedure</ListItem><ListItem>stent placement or percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage, as palliative therapy to relieve jaundice and other symptoms and improve quality of life   </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_44">Adjuvant therapy for resectable bile duct cancer may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>external-beam radiation therapy  </ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of adjuvant therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_46"><Title>Treatment of unresectable bile duct cancer (including metastatic or recurrent disease)  </Title><Para id="_57">Most people with bile duct cancer cannot have their cancer completely removed with surgery. This may be the case if the cancer has spread too far, the cancer is in a place that is too difficult to completely remove with surgery, or the patient is not healthy enough for surgery.</Para><Para id="_47">Treatment of unresectable bile duct cancer (including metastatic or recurrent disease) may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_48" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>stent placement or biliary bypass, as palliative treatment to relieve symptoms and improve <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045417" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">quality of   life</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>external or internal radiation therapy, as palliative treatment to relieve symptoms and improve quality of life</ListItem><ListItem>systemic chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>immunotherapy (<DrugRef href="CDR0000788795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/durvalumab">durvalumab</DrugRef> or <DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef>) and systemic chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem> targeted therapy with <DrugRef href="CDR0000801476" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pemigatinib">pemigatinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of various combinations of chemotherapy</ListItem><ListItem>a clinical trial of immunotherapy or targeted therapy in people with mutations (changes) in certain genes</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-05-19</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-05-24</DateLastModified></Summary>
