<Summary id="CDR0000809682" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver is a rare type of childhood liver cancer. Learn about causes, risk factors, signs, symptoms, diagnosis, and treatment options.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/childhood-liver-cancer/undifferentiated-embryonal-sarcoma">Childhood Undifferentiated Embryonal Sarcoma of the Liver</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043714">childhood liver cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood liver cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Undifferentiated Embryonal Sarcoma of the Liver</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Undifferentiated Embryonal Sarcoma of the Liver</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Undifferentiated Embryonal Sarcoma of the Liver</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType><SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType><SectionType>Organ description</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">Childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver is a rare cancer that usually forms in the tissues of the right lobe of the liver. This type of liver cancer usually occurs in children between 5 and 10 years but can also occur in adolescence. It often spreads throughout the liver and/or to the lungs. </Para><Para id="_3">The liver is one of the largest organs in the body. It has two lobes and fills the upper right side of the abdomen inside the rib cage. Three of the many important functions of the liver include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_4" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>to make <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef> to help digest fats from food  </ListItem><ListItem>to store glycogen (sugar), which the body uses for energy  </ListItem><ListItem>to filter harmful substances from the blood so they can be passed from the body in stools and urine</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000659745" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the liver; drawing shows the right and left lobes of the liver. Also shown are the bile ducts, gallbladder, stomach, spleen, pancreas, small intestine, and colon." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_65"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the liver. The liver is in the upper abdomen near the stomach, intestines, gallbladder, and pancreas. The liver has a right lobe and a left lobe. Each lobe is divided into two sections (not shown). </Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Symptoms of childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver </Title><Para id="_7">Children may not have symptoms of undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver until the tumor has grown bigger. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has: </Para><ItemizedList id="_8" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>a lump in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>abdominal pain</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>loss of appetite</ListItem><ListItem>fatigue or loss of energy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_68">These symptoms may be caused by problems other than undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver. The only way to know is to see your child's doctor. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver  </Title><Para id="_10">If your child has symptoms that suggest undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. They will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Based on these results, the doctor may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with liver cancer, the results of these tests will help you and your child's doctor plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_11">The tests used to diagnose undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver may include: </Para><SummarySection id="_69"><Title>Complete blood count (CBC)</Title><Para id="_70">A CBC checks a sample of blood for:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_13" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef> </ListItem><ListItem>the amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemoglobin</GlossaryTermRef> (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> that carries oxygen) in the red blood cells </ListItem><ListItem>the portion of the blood sample made up of red blood cells </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_71"><Title>Liver function tests</Title><Para id="_72">Liver function tests measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by the liver. A higher-than-normal amount of a substance can be a sign of liver damage or cancer. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_73"><Title>Blood chemistry studies</Title><Para id="_74">Blood chemistry studies measure the amounts of certain substances, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044518" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bilirubin</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lactate dehydrogenase</GlossaryTermRef> (LDH), released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign of disease. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_75"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with gadolinium</Title><Para id="_76">MRI uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to take a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the liver. A substance called gadolinium is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. The procedure is also called nuclear MRI.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_14"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_77"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_78">A CT scan uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles.  A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. </Para><Para id="_79">A CT scan of the chest and abdomen is usually done to help diagnose childhood liver cancer.</Para><Para id="_80">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_15"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_81"><Title>Ultrasound exam</Title><Para id="_82">An ultrasound exam uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. An ultrasound exam of the abdomen to check the large blood vessels is usually done to help diagnose childhood liver cancer.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775457" type="image/jpeg" alt="Abdominal ultrasound; drawing shows a child lying on an exam table during an abdominal ultrasound procedure. A technician is shown pressing a transducer (a device that makes sound waves that bounce off tissues inside the body) against the skin of the abdomen. A computer screen shows a sonogram (picture)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_16"><Caption language="en">Abdominal ultrasound. An ultrasound transducer connected to a computer is pressed against the skin of the abdomen. The transducer bounces sound waves off internal organs and tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture).</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_83"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_84">An x-ray is a type of high-energy radiation that can go through the body onto film, making a picture of areas inside the body. A chest x-ray is one that makes pictures of the lungs. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_85"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_86">Biopsy is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the tumor so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for cancer. The doctor may remove as much tumor as safely possible during the same biopsy procedure. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_87"><Title>Immunohistochemistry</Title><Para id="_88">Immunohistochemistry uses <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044918" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antibodies</GlossaryTermRef> to check for certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046086" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">antigens</GlossaryTermRef> (markers) in a sample of a patient's tissue. The antibodies are usually linked to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzyme</GlossaryTermRef> or a fluorescent dye. After the antibodies bind to a specific antigen in the tissue sample, the enzyme or dye is activated, and the antigen can then be seen under a microscope. This type of test is used to help diagnose cancer and to help tell one type of cancer from another type. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_89"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_90">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child's diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>, slides, and scans. This doctor may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child's cancer.  </Para><Para id="_91">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Prognostic factors</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Prognostic factors for childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver  </Title><Para id="_20">If your child has been diagnosed with undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child's chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis. </Para><Para id="_101">The prognosis for undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver depends on:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the size of the tumor </ListItem><ListItem>how the cancer responds to chemotherapy </ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer can be removed completely by surgery </ListItem><ListItem>whether your child can have a liver transplant </ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to other places in the body, such as the lungs</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has come back after treatment  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_22">For childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver that comes back after initial treatment, the prognosis depends on: </Para><ItemizedList id="_23" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>where in the body the tumor came back </ListItem><ListItem>the type of treatment used to treat the initial cancer </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_102">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_29"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Standard treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Types of treatment for childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver </Title><Para id="_92">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver. You and your child's care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child's overall health and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_25">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, will oversee treatment of undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. It is especially important to have a pediatric surgeon with experience in liver surgery who can send patients to a liver transplant program if needed. Other specialists may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_26" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044662" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nutritionist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_93">Your child's treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child's care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, visit our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Surgery  </Title><Para id="_66">When possible, the cancer is removed by surgery. The following types of surgery may be done:</Para><ItemizedList id="_67" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Partial hepatectomy</Strong> is surgery to remove the part of the liver where cancer is found. The part removed may be a wedge of tissue, an entire lobe, or a larger part of the liver, along with some of the healthy tissue around it. The remaining liver tissue takes over the functions of the liver and may regrow. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Liver transplant</Strong> is the removal of the entire liver  by surgery,  followed by a transplant of a healthy liver from a donor. A liver transplant may be done when the cancer is in the liver only, and a donated liver can be found. If the patient has to wait for a donated liver, other treatment is given as needed.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_109">Chemotherapy is sometimes given before surgery to shrink the tumor and make it easier to remove. This is called neoadjuvant therapy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Chemotherapy </Title><Para id="_36">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cancer cells or stops them from dividing.  

</Para><Para id="_94">For childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver, the chemotherapy is injected into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body. </Para><Para id="_95">Chemotherapy drugs used alone or in combination to treat undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver in children include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_96" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000720376" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dactinomycin">dactinomycin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000542867" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/doxorubicinhydrochloride">doxorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000686471" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ifosfamide">ifosfamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599877" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vincristinesulfate">vincristine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_97">Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_58">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_39"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Current clinical trials</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_39_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_39_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_39_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Treatment of childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver </Title><Para id="_51">Treatment of newly diagnosed childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver may include:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_52" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>surgery to remove the tumor</ListItem><ListItem>chemotherapy before surgery, after surgery, or both</ListItem><ListItem>liver transplant if surgery to remove the tumor is not possible</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_111">If the first surgery is unable to remove the entire tumor, a second surgery may be done to remove the remaining tumor cells.</Para><Para id="_108">Sometimes childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver continues to grow or recurs (comes back) after treatment. The cancer may come back in the liver or in other parts of the body. Your child's doctor will work with you to plan treatment if your child is diagnosed with recurrent undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_110">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_98">To learn more about side effects that begin during treatment, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_44">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later  after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:  </Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>physical problems  </ListItem><ListItem>changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer) </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_46">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the long-term effects cancer treatment can have on your child. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_47"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_48">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer or to find out the treatment group may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.  </Para><Para id="_49">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has come back. To learn more about follow-up tests, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809682#_9" url="/types/liver/childhood-liver-cancer/undifferentiated-embryonal-sarcoma">Tests to diagnose childhood undifferentiated embryonal sarcoma of the liver</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_99"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_100">When your child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child's treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.   </Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-05-19</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-12-19</DateLastModified></Summary>
