<Summary id="CDR0000809693" SVPC="Yes" SuppressOnThisPageSection="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Certain medical tests are used to screen for liver cancer.   Not all screening tests are helpful, and many have risks. Learn more about screening tests for liver cancer and their risks.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/what-is-liver-cancer/screening">Liver Cancer Screening</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038756">adult primary liver cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>liver cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Liver Cancer Screening</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Liver Cancer Screening</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Liver Cancer Screening</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">Screening is looking for cancer before a person has any symptoms. This can help find cancer at an early stage. When <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> tissue or cancer is found early, it may be easier to treat.</Para><Para id="_24">It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily think you have cancer if he or she suggests a screening test. Screening tests are given when you have no cancer symptoms.

If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called diagnostic tests.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Tests to screen for liver cancer</Title><Para id="_4">Although there is no standard or routine screening tests for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, the following tests are being used or studied to screen for it:</Para><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Ultrasound</Title><Para id="_10">Ultrasound is a procedure in which high-energy waves (ultrasound) are bounced off the liver and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of the liver called a sonogram.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><Title>CT scan</Title><Para id="_12"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> is a procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of the liver, taken from different angles. The pictures are made by a computer linked to an x-ray machine. A dye may be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the liver show up more clearly. This procedure is also called CAT scan or computed tomography.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>Alpha-fetoprotein tumor marker</Title><Para id="_6"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Tumor markers</GlossaryTermRef>, also called biomarkers, are substances made by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> that may be found in the blood, other body fluids, or tissues. A high level of a specific tumor marker may mean that a certain type of cancer is present in the body.</Para><Para id="_7"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046208" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Alpha-fetoprotein</GlossaryTermRef> (AFP) is the most widely used tumor marker for detecting liver cancer. However, other cancers and certain conditions, including pregnancy, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046371" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatitis</GlossaryTermRef>, and other types of cancer, may also increase AFP levels.</Para><Para id="_8">Specific tumor markers that may lead to early detection of liver cancer are being studied.</Para></SummarySection><Para id="_25">Doctors use these screening tests to find, or diagnose, liver cancer. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809694" url="/types/liver/what-is-liver-cancer/diagnosis">Liver Cancer Diagnosis</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><Title>Risks of liver cancer screening</Title><Para id="_16">Decisions about screening tests can be difficult. Not all screening tests are helpful and most have risk of harms associated with them. Before having any screening test, you may want to discuss the test with your doctor. It is important to be aware of any possible harms of the test and whether the test has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from cancer.</Para><Para id="_17">The risks of liver cancer screening include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>False-negative test results can occur.</Strong> Screening test results may appear to be normal even though liver cancer is present. A person who receives a false-negative test result (one that shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical care even if there are symptoms.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>False-positive test results can occur.</Strong> Screening test results may appear to be abnormal even though no cancer is present. A false-positive test result (one that shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and is usually followed by diagnostic tests and procedures, such as a liver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef>, which also have risks.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Procedures to diagnose liver cancer can cause complications.</Strong> Abnormal screening results may be followed up with a liver biopsy to diagnose liver cancer. Liver biopsy may cause the following rare, but serious, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463706" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">complications</GlossaryTermRef>:<ItemizedList id="_22" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000373015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hemorrhage</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>trouble breathing</ListItem><ListItem>leakage of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046508" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile</GlossaryTermRef>, which can cause an infection of the lining of the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>a small puncture (hole) in an organ in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>spread of cancer cells along the needle path where the biopsy needle is inserted and withdrawn (taken out)</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_23">Your doctor can advise you about your risk for liver cancer and your need for screening tests.</Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-05-19</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-05-15</DateLastModified></Summary>
