<Summary id="CDR0000809669" SVPC="Yes" SuppressOnThisPageSection="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Stages</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Staging for bile duct cancer (cholangiocarcinoma) is used to predict a person's chance of recovery and plan treatment.  Learn more about bile duct cancer stages.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/liver/bile-duct-cancer/stages">Bile Duct Cancer Stages</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000774341">bile duct cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bile duct cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Bile Duct Cancer Stages</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Bile Duct Cancer Stages</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Bile Duct Cancer Stages</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">This page describes the stages of  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000527370" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bile duct cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (cholangiocarcinoma) for adults. The stage describes the extent of cancer in the body. Knowing the stage helps the doctor plan the best treatment. Bile duct cancer stages are described using the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. To learn more about TNM and how cancer stages are described, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer   Staging</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_4">To learn about the tests and procedures used to diagnose and stage bile duct cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809668" url="/types/liver/bile-duct-cancer/diagnosis">Bile Duct Cancer Diagnosis</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Intrahepatic bile duct cancer</Title><ItemizedList id="_5" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Stage 0:</Strong> In stage 0 intrahepatic bile duct cancer (carcinoma in situ), abnormal cells are found in the innermost layer of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> lining   the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intrahepatic bile duct</GlossaryTermRef>. These abnormal cells are not actually cancer but may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage I:</Strong> Stage I intrahepatic bile duct cancer is divided into stages IA and IB.   <ItemizedList id="_7" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>In stage IA, cancer has formed in an intrahepatic bile duct and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is 5 centimeters or smaller.  </ListItem><ListItem>In stage IB, cancer has formed in an intrahepatic bile duct and the tumor is larger than 5 centimeters.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000415526" type="image/jpeg" alt="Drawing shows different sizes of a tumor in centimeters (cm) compared to the size of a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm). Also shown is a 10-cm ruler and a 4-inch ruler." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_6"><Caption language="en">Tumor sizes are often measured in centimeters (cm) or inches. Common food items that can be used to show tumor size in cm include: a pea (1 cm), a peanut (2 cm), a grape (3 cm), a walnut (4 cm), a lime (5 cm or 2 inches), an egg (6 cm), a peach (7 cm), and a grapefruit (10 cm or 4 inches).</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage II:</Strong> In stage II intrahepatic bile duct cancer, either of the following is found:  <ItemizedList id="_8" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>the tumor has spread through the wall of an intrahepatic bile duct and into a blood vessel; or </ListItem><ListItem>more than one tumor has formed in the intrahepatic bile duct and may have spread into a blood vessel.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage III:</Strong> Stage III intrahepatic bile duct cancer is divided into stages IIIA and IIIB.  <ItemizedList id="_9" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>In stage IIIA, the tumor has spread through the capsule (outer lining) of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>.  </ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIB, cancer has spread to organs or tissues near the liver, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046443" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">duodenum</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>, stomach, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046466" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">common bile duct</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046684" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdominal</GlossaryTermRef> wall, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046451" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diaphragm</GlossaryTermRef>, or the part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792054" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vena cava</GlossaryTermRef> behind the liver, or the cancer has spread to nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem> <Strong>Stage IV:</Strong> In stage IV intrahepatic bile duct cancer, cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the bone, lungs, distant lymph nodes, or tissue lining the wall of the abdomen and most organs in the abdomen. </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>Perihilar bile duct cancer   </Title><ItemizedList id="_11" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Stage 0:</Strong> In stage 0 perihilar bile duct cancer (carcinoma in situ), abnormal cells are found in the innermost layer of tissue lining the perihilar bile duct. These abnormal cells are not actually cancer but may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. Stage 0 is also called high-grade dysplasia.</ListItem><ListItem> <Strong>Stage I:</Strong> In stage I perihilar bile duct cancer, cancer has formed in the innermost layer of tissue lining the perihilar bile duct and has spread into the muscle layer or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000344349" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fibrous</GlossaryTermRef> tissue layer of the perihilar bile duct wall.</ListItem><ListItem> <Strong>Stage II:</Strong> In stage II perihilar bile duct cancer, cancer has spread through the wall of the perihilar bile duct to nearby fatty tissue or to liver tissue. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage III:</Strong> Stage III perihilar bile duct cancer is divided into stages IIIA, IIIB, and IIIC.  <ItemizedList id="_12" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Stage IIIA: Cancer has spread to branches on one side of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic artery</GlossaryTermRef> or of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045093" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">portal vein</GlossaryTermRef>. </ListItem><ListItem> Stage IIIB: Cancer has spread to one or more of the following:   <ItemizedList id="_13" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>the main part of the portal vein or its branches on both sides</ListItem><ListItem>the common hepatic artery</ListItem><ListItem>the right <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045709" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hepatic</GlossaryTermRef> duct and the left branch of the hepatic artery or of the portal vein</ListItem><ListItem>the left hepatic duct and the right branch of the hepatic artery or of the portal vein</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem> Stage IIIC: Cancer has spread to 1 to 3 nearby lymph nodes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage IV:</Strong> Stage IV perihilar bile duct cancer is divided into stages IVA and IVB.  <ItemizedList id="_14" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Stage IVA: Cancer has spread to 4 or more nearby lymph nodes.</ListItem><ListItem>Stage IVB: Cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the liver, lung, bone, brain, skin, distant lymph nodes, or tissue lining the wall of the abdomen and most organs in the abdomen.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><Title>Distal bile duct cancer</Title><ItemizedList id="_16" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Stage 0:</Strong> In stage 0 distal bile duct cancer (carcinoma in situ), abnormal cells are found in the innermost layer of tissue lining the distal bile duct. These abnormal cells are not actually cancer but may become cancer and spread into nearby normal tissue. Stage 0 is also called high-grade dysplasia.  <MediaLink ref="CDR0000578121" type="image/jpeg" alt="Millimeters; drawing shows millimeters (mm) using everyday objects. A sharp pencil point shows 1 mm, a new crayon point shows 2 mm, and a new pencil-top eraser shows 5 mm." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_17"><Caption language="en">Millimeters (mm). A sharp pencil point is about 1 mm, a new crayon point is about 2 mm, and a new pencil eraser is about 5 mm.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage I:</Strong> In stage I distal bile duct cancer, cancer has formed and spread fewer than 5 millimeters into the wall of the distal bile duct.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage II:</Strong> Stage II distal bile duct cancer is divided into stages IIA and IIB.  <ItemizedList id="_18" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Stage IIA: Cancer has spread <ItemizedList id="_19" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>fewer than 5 millimeters into the wall of the distal bile duct and has spread to 1 to 3 nearby lymph nodes; or </ListItem><ListItem>5 to 12 millimeters into the wall of the distal bile duct.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIB: Cancer has spread 5 millimeters or more into the wall of the distal bile duct. Cancer may have spread to 1 to 3 nearby lymph nodes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage III:</Strong> Stage III distal bile duct cancer is divided into stages IIIA and IIIB.<ItemizedList id="_20" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>Stage IIIA: Cancer has spread into the wall of the distal bile duct and to 4 or more nearby lymph nodes.</ListItem><ListItem>Stage IIIB: Cancer has spread to the large vessels that carry blood to the organs in the abdomen. Cancer may have spread to 1 or more nearby lymph nodes.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage IV:</Strong> In stage IV distal bile duct cancer, cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the liver, lungs, or tissue lining the wall of the abdomen and most organs in the abdomen.</ListItem>    </ItemizedList><Para id="_21">For bile duct cancer, the following groups are used to plan treatment:  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Resectable (localized) bile duct cancer </Title><Para id="_23">The cancer is in an area, such as the lower part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046466" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">common bile duct</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792694" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">perihilar</GlossaryTermRef> area, where it can be removed completely by surgery.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><Title>Unresectable (including metastatic and recurrent) bile duct cancer </Title><Para id="_31">Unresectable cancer cannot be removed completely by surgery. Most people with bile duct cancer cannot have their cancer completely removed by surgery.</Para><Para id="_32">Metastasis is the spread of cancer from the primary site (place where it started) to other places in the body. Metastatic bile duct cancer may have spread to the liver, other parts of the abdominal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000463703" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cavity</GlossaryTermRef>, or to distant parts of the body. To learn more about metastatic cancer, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_33">Recurrent bile duct cancer is cancer that has come back after treatment. The cancer may come back in the bile ducts, liver, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046395" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gallbladder</GlossaryTermRef>. Less often, it may come back in distant parts of the body.  

To learn more about recurrent cancer, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_34">To learn about treatment options, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000809670" url="/types/liver/bile-duct-cancer/treatment">Bile Duct Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-05-19</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-05-24</DateLastModified></Summary>
