<Summary id="CDR0000810192" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Screening</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Learn what HPV and Pap test results mean and next steps if a test result is abnormal.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">HPV and Pap Test Results: Next Steps after an Abnormal Cervical Cancer Screening Test </SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037892">cervical cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038613">disease screening</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cervical cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>disease screening</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>HPV test</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>Pap test</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>HPV and Pap Test Results: Next Steps after an Abnormal Cervical Cancer Screening Test</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">HPV and Pap Test Results: Next Steps after an Abnormal Test</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">HPV and Pap Test Results: Next Steps after an Abnormal Test</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">People who have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical cancer</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">screening</GlossaryTermRef> at regular intervals are rarely found to have cancer. Most people who receive abnormal cervical cancer screening results either have <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human papillomavirus</GlossaryTermRef> (HPV) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infections</GlossaryTermRef> or have early cell changes that can be monitored (since they often go away on their own) or treated early (to prevent the development of cervical cancer). </Para><Para id="_48">See <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810140" url="/types/cervical/screening">Cervical Cancer Screening</SummaryRef> for information about when to get screened and what to expect during the tests.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>HPV test results: What positive and negative results on a screening test mean</Title><Para id="_4"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000752848" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HPV test</GlossaryTermRef> results show whether <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000753083" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high-risk HPV</GlossaryTermRef> types were found in cervical cells. An HPV test will come back as a negative test result or a positive test result.</Para><ItemizedList id="_5" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Negative HPV test result:</Strong> High-risk HPV was not found. You should have the next test in 5 years. You may need to come back sooner if you had abnormal results in the past. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Positive HPV test result:</Strong> High-risk HPV was found. Your health care provider will recommend <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_17" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">follow-up steps you need to take</SummaryRef>, based on your specific test result.   </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_6"><Strong>What does it mean if you have a positive HPV test after years of negative tests?</Strong></Para><Para id="_7">Sometimes, after several negative HPV tests, a woman may have a positive HPV test result. This is not necessarily a sign of a new HPV infection. Sometimes an HPV infection can become active again after many years. Some other viruses behave this way. For example, the virus that causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chickenpox</GlossaryTermRef> can reactivate later in life to cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">shingles</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_8">Researchers don’t know whether a reactivated HPV infection has the same risk of causing cervical cell changes or cervical cancer as a new HPV infection.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Pap test results: What normal, abnormal, and unsatisfactory screening test results mean</Title><Para id="_10"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045978" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pap test</GlossaryTermRef> results show whether cervical cells are normal or abnormal. A Pap test may also come back as unsatisfactory. </Para><Para id="_11"><Strong>Normal Pap test results:</Strong> No abnormal cervical cells were found. A normal test result may also be called a negative test result or negative for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046336" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">intraepithelial</GlossaryTermRef> lesion (area of abnormal growth) or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045771" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">malignancy</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_12"><Strong>Unsatisfactory Pap test results:</Strong> The lab sample may not have had enough cells, or the cells may have been clumped together or hidden by blood or mucus. Your health care provider will ask you to come in for another Pap test in 2 to 4 months.</Para><Para id="_13"><Strong>Abnormal Pap test results:</Strong> An abnormal test result may also be called a positive test result. Some of the cells of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef> look different from the normal cells. An abnormal test result does not mean you have cancer. Your health care provider will recommend monitoring, more testing, or treatment. </Para><Para id="_14">Abnormal Pap test results include</Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Atypical squamous cells of undetermined significance (ASC-US):</Strong> This is the most common abnormal Pap test finding. It means that some cells don't look completely normal, but it's not clear if the changes are caused by HPV infection. Other things can cause cells to look abnormal, including irritation, some infections (such as a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000773856" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">yeast infection</GlossaryTermRef>), growths (such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045844" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">polyps</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>), and changes in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045713" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hormones</GlossaryTermRef> that occur during pregnancy or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046296" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menopause</GlossaryTermRef>. Although these things may make cervical cells look abnormal, they are not related to cancer. Your health care provider will usually do an HPV test to see if the changes may be caused by an HPV infection. If the HPV test is negative, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000753376" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">estrogen cream</GlossaryTermRef> may be prescribed to see if the cell changes are caused by low hormone levels. If the HPV test is positive, you may need <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_17" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">additional follow-up tests</SummaryRef>.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Atypical glandular cells (AGC):</Strong> Some <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000752837" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">glandular cells</GlossaryTermRef> were found that do not look normal. This can be a sign of a more serious problem up inside the uterus, so your health care provider will likely ask you to <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_17" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">come back for a colposcopy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions (LSIL):</Strong> There are low-grade changes that are usually caused by an HPV infection. Your health care provider will likely ask you to come back for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_17" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">additional testing</SummaryRef> to make sure that there are not more serious (high-grade) changes. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Atypical squamous cells, cannot exclude high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion (ASC-H):</Strong> Some abnormal squamous cells were found that may be a high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion (HSIL), although it's not certain. Your health care provider will likely ask you to <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_17" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">come back for a colposcopy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>High-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions (HSIL):</Strong> There are moderately or severely abnormal cervical cells that could become cancer in the future if not treated. Your health care provider will likely ask you to <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_17" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">come back for a colposcopy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS):</Strong> An advanced lesion (area of abnormal growth) was found in the glandular tissue of the cervix. AIS lesions may be referred to as precancer and may become cancer (cervical adenocarcinoma) if not treated. Your health care provider will likely ask you to <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_17" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">come back for a colposcopy</SummaryRef>. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Cervical cancer cells (squamous cell carcinoma or adenocarcinoma):</Strong> Cancer cells were found; this finding is very rare for people who have been screened at regular intervals. If a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045164" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biopsy</GlossaryTermRef> shows that cervical cancer is present, your doctor will order certain tests to find out if cancer cells have spread within the cervix or to other parts of the body. See the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810229" url="/types/cervical/diagnosis">Cervical Cancer Diagnosis</SummaryRef> page for information about tests that may be used to diagnose and stage cervical cancer.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000752234" type="image/jpeg" alt="Cervical changes; drawing shows a cross-section of the uterus, cervix, and vagina. Also shown are four panels showing cell changes inside the cervix. The first panel shows normal cells. The second and third panels show abnormal cells called LSIL and HSIL. The fourth panel shows cervical cancer cells. Arrows are used between the panels to show that normal cells may become LSIL or HSIL, which may or may not become cancer." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_16"><Caption language="en">Cervical changes. The cervix is the lower, narrow end of the uterus that forms a canal between the uterus and vagina.  Before cancer cells form in tissues of the cervix, the cells of the cervix go through abnormal changes called dysplasia. There are different types of dysplasia. Mild dysplasia, called low-grade intraepithelial lesion   (LSIL) is one type. Moderate or severe dysplasia, called high-grade intraepithelial lesion   (HSIL) is another type of dysplasia. LSIL and HSIL may or may not become cancer. </Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_17"><Title>Follow-up tests and procedures after an abnormal Pap test (Pap smear) or HPV test </Title><Para id="_18">Keep in mind that most people with abnormal cervical screening test results do not have cancer. However, if you have an abnormal test result, it’s important to get the follow-up care that your health care provider recommends. </Para><Para id="_19">Until recently, follow-up recommendations were based on the results of a person's most recent cervical screening test. However, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.asccp.org/guidelines">updated ASCCP risk-based management consensus guidelines</ExternalRef> advise a more tailored approach to follow-up care. </Para><Para id="_20">What these updated guidelines mean is that, in addition to your current Pap, HPV, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000752850" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cotest</GlossaryTermRef> screening result, your health care provider will consider additional factors when recommending follow-up care, including </Para><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>previous screening test results</ListItem><ListItem>previous treatments for precancerous cervical cell changes</ListItem><ListItem>personal health factors, such as your age</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_22">Based on your individual risk of developing severe cervical cell changes that could become cervical cancer, you may be advised to</Para><ItemizedList id="_23" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>return for a repeat HPV test or HPV/Pap cotest in 1 or 3 years</ListItem><ListItem>have a colposcopy and biopsy</ListItem><ListItem>receive treatment; see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_35" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">Treatment for high-grade cervical cell changes</SummaryRef> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_24">These updated guidelines focus on detecting and treating severe cervical cell changes that could develop into cervical cancer while also decreasing testing and treatment for less severe conditions (low-grade cervical cell changes). </Para><SummarySection id="_25"><Title>Colposcopy</Title><Para id="_26">During a colposcopy, your doctor inserts a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046588" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">speculum</GlossaryTermRef> to gently open the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef> and see the cervix. A vinegar solution is applied to the cervix to help show abnormal areas. Your doctor then places an instrument called a colposcope close to the vagina. It has a bright light and a magnifying lens and allows your doctor to look closely at your vagina and cervix for abnormal areas. </Para><Para id="_27">A colposcopy usually includes a biopsy, so that the cells or tissues can be checked under a microscope for signs of disease, including cervical cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><Title>Cervical biopsy</Title><Para id="_29">A biopsy is a procedure used to remove cervical cells or tissue to be checked under a microscope for abnormal cervical cells, including cancer. In addition to removing a sample for further testing, some types of biopsies may be used as treatment, to remove abnormal cervical tissue or lesions.</Para><Para id="_30">Talk with your doctor to learn what to expect during and after your biopsy procedure. Bleeding and/or discharge after a biopsy may occur. Some people have pain that feels like cramps during <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046297" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menstruation</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Biopsy findings: cervical intraepithelial neoplasia (CIN)</Title><Para id="_32">Biopsy samples are checked by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> for CIN. CIN is the term used to describe abnormal cervical cells that were found on the surface of the cervix after a biopsy. </Para><Para id="_33">CIN is graded on a scale of 1 to 3, based on how abnormal the cells look under a microscope and how much of the cervical tissue is affected. LSIL changes seen on a Pap test are generally CIN 1. HSIL changes seen on a Pap test can be CIN 2, CIN2/3, or CIN 3.   </Para><ItemizedList id="_34" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>CIN 1 changes are mild, or low grade. They usually go away on their own and do not require treatment. </ListItem><ListItem>CIN 2 changes are moderate and are typically treated by removing the abnormal cells. However, CIN 2 can sometimes go away on its own. Some people, after consulting with their health care provider, may decide to have a colposcopy with biopsy every 6 months. CIN 2 must be treated if it progresses to CIN 3 or does not go away in 1 to 2 years. </ListItem><ListItem>CIN 3 changes are severely abnormal. Although CIN 3 is not cancer, it may become cancer and spread to nearby normal tissue if not treated. Doctors do not yet have a way to tell which cases of CIN 3 will become cancer and which will not. CIN 3 should be treated right away, unless you are pregnant. See <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_41" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">Pregnancy and Treatment for High-Grade Cervical Cell Changes</SummaryRef> for more information.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_35"><Title>Treatment for high-grade cervical cell changes  </Title><Para id="_36">The goal of treating high-grade cervical cell changes is to remove or destroy abnormal cervical cells that have a high chance of becoming cancer. Some of these treatments are also used for early-stage cervical cancer.   </Para><Para id="_37">The most common treatment for high-grade cervical cell changes is conization, the removal of a cone-shaped piece of tissue from the cervix and cervical canal. There are two types of conization.</Para><ItemizedList id="_38" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Loop electrosurgical excision procedure (LEEP)</Strong> uses a thin wire loop, through which an electrical current is passed, to remove abnormal tissue. This procedure is typically done in a doctor’s office. It usually takes only a few minutes, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local anesthesia</GlossaryTermRef> is used to numb the area. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Cold knife conization</Strong> uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257527" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scalpel</GlossaryTermRef> to remove the abnormal tissue. This procedure is done at the hospital under <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044561" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">general anesthesia</GlossaryTermRef>.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_39">Several other treatments may also be used. </Para><ItemizedList id="_40" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Laser therapy</Strong> uses a laser (narrow beam of intense light) to remove or destroy abnormal tissue. This is an outpatient procedure that may be done under local or general anesthesia. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Cryotherapy</Strong> uses a special cold probe to destroy abnormal tissue by freezing it. This procedure is done at a doctor’s office. It takes only a few minutes and usually does not require anesthesia. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Total hysterectomy</Strong> is the surgical removal of the uterus and cervix. It is often used to treat AIS. It is used to treat CIN3 only if the abnormal cells were not completely removed by other treatments.</ListItem></ItemizedList><SummarySection id="_41"><Title>Pregnancy and treatment for high-grade cervical cell changes </Title><Para id="_42">Rarely, procedures to treat cervical cell abnormalities can weaken the cervix, increasing the risk of premature birth or miscarriage.</Para><Para id="_43">If you are pregnant or plan to become pregnant, your health care provider will talk with you about procedures that are recommended for you and the timing of these procedures. Depending on your specific diagnosis, you may be treated postpartum, or after delivery.</Para></SummarySection><Para id="_44">For a downloadable booklet about cervical cancer screening, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results/understanding-cervical-changes.pdf">Understanding Cervical Changes: A Health Guide</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-10-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-06-06</DateLastModified></Summary>
