<Summary id="CDR0000810229" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Diagnosis</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Learn about the tests that are used to diagnose and stage cervical cancer. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cervical/diagnosis">Cervical Cancer Diagnosis</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037892">cervical cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cervical cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>cervical cancer diagnosis</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Cervical Cancer Diagnosis</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Cervical Cancer Diagnosis</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Cervical Cancer Diagnosis</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">If you have symptoms or screening test results that suggest the possibility of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor will do follow-up tests to find out if it is due to cancer or some other cause. They will usually start by asking about your personal and family medical history and by doing a physical exam, which will include a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvic exam</GlossaryTermRef> and rectovaginal exam. They may recommend diagnostic tests to find out if you have cervical cancer, and if so, whether it has spread to another part of the body. The results of these tests will also help you and your doctor plan treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>How cervical cancer is diagnosed</Title><Para id="_4">The following procedures are used to diagnose cervical cancer:</Para><SummarySection id="_29"><Title>Colposcopy</Title><Para id="_30">Colposcopy is a procedure in which the health care provider inserts a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046588" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">speculum</GlossaryTermRef> to gently open the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef> and view the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef>. A vinegar solution will be applied to the cervix to help show abnormal areas. The health care provider then places an instrument called a colposcope close to the vagina. It has a bright light and a magnifying lens and allows the health care provider to look closely at the cervix. A colposcopy usually includes a biopsy.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_6">Biopsy is a procedure in which a sample of tissue is removed from the cervix so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for signs of cancer. The following types of biopsies are used to check for cervical cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_7" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Punch biopsy</Strong> is a procedure in which a small, round piece of tissue is removed using a sharp, hollow circular instrument. Sometimes several different areas of the cervix will be checked with punch biopsy. This procedure is usually done in the doctor’s office.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Endocervical curettage</Strong> is a procedure to collect cells or tissue from the cervical canal using a curette (spoon-shaped instrument). This procedure removes only a small amount of tissue and is usually done in the doctor’s office.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Loop electrosurgical excision procedure (LEEP)</Strong> uses a thin wire loop, through which an electrical current is passed, to remove tissue from the cervix. LEEP may be used to diagnose cervical cancer. It also may be used to remove precancer or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000561398" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">early-stage cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. This procedure is typically done in a doctor’s office. It usually takes only a few minutes, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044523" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">local anesthesia</GlossaryTermRef> is used to numb the area.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Cone biopsy</Strong> is surgery to remove a larger, cone-shaped piece of tissue from the cervix and cervical canal. A cone biopsy may be used to diagnose cervical cancer. It also may be used to remove precancer or early-stage cancer. This procedure is also called conization. A cone biopsy is done at the hospital under <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044561" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">general anesthesia</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_8">Talk with your health care provider to learn what to expect during and after your biopsy procedure. Some people have bleeding and/or discharge after a biopsy. Others have pain that feels like cramps during <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046297" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">menstruation</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><Para id="_9">To learn about the type of information that can be found in a pathologist’s report about the cells or tissue removed during a biopsy, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/diagnosis/pathology-reports-fact-sheet">Pathology Reports</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>Tests and procedures used to stage cervical cancer</Title><Para id="_11">If you are diagnosed with cervical cancer, you will be referred to a gynecologic oncologist. This is a doctor who specializes in staging and treating cervical cancer and other cancers of the female <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046564" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reproductive system</GlossaryTermRef>. They will recommend tests to determine the extent (stage) of cancer. Sometimes the cancer is only in the cervix. Or, it may have spread from the cervix to other parts of the body. The process of learning the extent of cancer in the body is called staging. It is important to know the stage of the cervical cancer in order to plan the best treatment. </Para><Para id="_32">For information about a specific stage of cervical cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810161" url="/types/cervical/stages">Cervical Cancer Stages</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_12">The following procedures may be used to determine the cervical cancer stage:</Para><SummarySection id="_15"><Title>Imaging tests</Title><ItemizedList id="_14" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>PET-CT scan</Strong>  combines the pictures from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046218" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">positron emission tomography (PET) scan</GlossaryTermRef> and a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045560" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">computed tomography (CT) scan</GlossaryTermRef>. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time on the same machine. The pictures from both scans are combined to make a more detailed picture than either test would make by itself.<ItemizedList id="_33" Style="dash"><ListItem>For the PET scan, a small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. The scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045772" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Malignant</GlossaryTermRef> tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells. </ListItem><ListItem> For the CT scan, a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body is taken from different angles. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Magnetic resonance imaging</GlossaryTermRef> (MRI)</Strong> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Ultrasound</Strong> uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound), which bounce off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Chest x-ray</Strong> is an x-ray of the organs and bones inside the chest. An x-ray is a type of high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the chest.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Lab tests</Title><ItemizedList id="_17" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Complete blood count (CBC)</Strong> is a blood test that measures the following in a sample of blood:<ItemizedList id="_18" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the amount of hemoglobin (the protein that carries oxygen) in the red blood cells</ListItem><ListItem>the portion of the blood sample made up of red blood cells</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Blood chemistry study</Strong> is a blood test that measures the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044338" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">electrolytes</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000354462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lactate dehydrogenase</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000393536" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uric acid</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000572242" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood urea nitrogen</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044337" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">creatinine</GlossaryTermRef>, and liver function values. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of cancer spread or other diseases.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><Title>Visual examination </Title><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Cystoscopy</Strong> is a procedure to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046640" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urethra</GlossaryTermRef> to check for abnormal areas. A cystoscope is inserted through the urethra into the bladder. A cystoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Sigmoidoscopy</Strong> uses a sigmoidoscope to look inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef> and sigmoid (lower) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef> for abnormal areas. A sigmoidoscope is inserted through the rectum into the sigmoid colon. A sigmoidoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove tissue samples, which are checked under a microscope for signs of cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_23">Some people want to get a second opinion to confirm their cervical cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you choose to seek a second opinion, you will need to get important medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans before giving a recommendation. The doctor who gives the second opinion may agree with your first doctor, suggest changes or another approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_24">For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_25">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can also contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI’s Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion.</Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-10-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-03-01</DateLastModified></Summary>
