<Summary id="CDR0000810279" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Learn about the different ways cervical cancer can be treated. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cervical/treatment">Cervical Cancer Treatment</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037892">cervical cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cervical cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>cervical cancer treatment</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Cervical Cancer Treatment</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Cervical Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Cervical Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">Different types of treatment are available for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444973" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervical cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your treatment plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, the treatment options and possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment.</Para><Para id="_3">If you are concerned about whether treatment will affect your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility</GlossaryTermRef>, talk with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect. To learn about fertility preservation options and ways to find support, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/fertility-women">Fertility Issues in Girls and Women with Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_4">For information about treatments by stage of cervical cancer, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810282" url="/types/cervical/treatment/by-stage">Cervical Cancer Treatment by Stage</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_5">For information about treatment during pregnancy, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810337" url="/types/cervical/treatment/cancer-treatment-during-pregnancy">Cervical Cancer Treatment during Pregnancy</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_7">Surgery (also called an operation) is sometimes used to treat cervical cancer. The type of surgery depends on where the cancer is located. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery">Surgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_8">The following surgical procedures may be used:</Para><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Cold knife conization</Title><Para id="_65">Cold knife conization uses a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257527" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">scalpel</GlossaryTermRef> to remove a cone-shaped piece of tissue from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046133" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cervix</GlossaryTermRef> and cervical canal. Sometimes all the cancer can be removed during this procedure. Cold knife conization is done in the hospital under <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044561" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">general anesthesia</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_11">Conization may also be used to treat <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810192#_35" url="/types/cervical/screening/abnormal-hpv-pap-test-results">high-grade cervical cell changes</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><Title>Sentinel lymph node biopsy  </Title><Para id="_13">Sentinel lymph node biopsy removes the sentinel lymph node during surgery. The sentinel lymph node is the first <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph node</GlossaryTermRef> in a group of lymph nodes to receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045760" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic drainage</GlossaryTermRef> from the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045847" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">primary tumor</GlossaryTermRef>. It is therefore the   first lymph node the cancer is likely to spread to from the primary tumor. To identify the sentinel lymph node, a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> substance and/or blue dye is injected near the tumor. The substance or dye flows through the lymph ducts to the lymph nodes. The first lymph node to receive the substance or dye is removed. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells.  If cancer cells are   found, more lymph nodes will be removed through a separate incision (cut). This is called a lymph node dissection. After the sentinel lymph node biopsy, the surgeon removes the cancer.</Para><Para id="_14">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging/sentinel-node-biopsy-fact-sheet">Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><Title>Hysterectomy</Title><Para id="_16">A   hysterectomy is surgery to remove the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>. As a treatment for cervical cancer, the cervix, and sometimes the surrounding structures, are removed. Several types of hysterectomy may be used to treat cervical cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_17" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Total hysterectomy</Strong> removes the uterus and the cervix. When the surgery is done entirely through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef> (with no incisions on the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef>) and the uterus and cervix are removed through the vagina, the operation is called a total vaginal hysterectomy. If the surgery is done through a large incision on the abdomen (either vertical or horizontal) and the uterus and cervix are removed through this incision, the operation is called a total abdominal hysterectomy. If the surgery is done through small   incisions on the abdomen, the operation is called a total laparoscopic hysterectomy. The uterus and cervix are usually taken out through the vagina, although sometimes an abdominal incision is made to remove the uterus and cervix.<MediaLink ref="CDR0000612116" type="image/jpeg" alt="Hysterectomy; drawing shows the female reproductive anatomy, including the ovaries, uterus, vagina, fallopian tubes, and cervix. Dotted lines show which organs and tissues are removed in a total hysterectomy, a total hysterectomy with salpingo-oophorectomy, and a radical hysterectomy. An inset shows the location of two possible incisions on the abdomen: a low transverse incision is just above the pubic area and a vertical incision is between the navel and the pubic area." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_18"><Caption language="en">Hysterectomy. The uterus is surgically removed with or without other organs or tissues. In a total hysterectomy, the uterus and cervix are removed. In a total hysterectomy with salpingo-oophorectomy, (a) the uterus plus one (unilateral) ovary and fallopian tube are removed; or (b) the uterus plus both (bilateral) ovaries and fallopian tubes are removed. In a radical hysterectomy, the uterus, cervix, both ovaries, both fallopian tubes, and nearby tissue are removed. These procedures are done using a low transverse incision or a vertical incision.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Radical hysterectomy</Strong> removes the uterus, cervix, part of the vagina, and a wide area of ligaments and tissues around these organs. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fallopian tubes</GlossaryTermRef>, or nearby lymph nodes may also be removed. </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Modified radical hysterectomy</Strong> removes the uterus, cervix, upper part of the vagina, and ligaments and tissues that closely surround these organs. This type of surgery removes fewer tissues and/or organs than radical hysterectomy. The ovaries, fallopian tubes, or nearby lymph nodes may also be removed.   </ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><Title>Radical trachelectomy</Title><Para id="_20">Radical trachelectomy (also called radical cervicectomy) removes the cervix, nearby tissue, and the upper part of the vagina. Lymph nodes may also be removed. After the surgeon removes the cervix, they attach the uterus to the remaining part of the vagina. A special stitch or band is placed on the uterus (in a procedure called a cerclage) to help keep the uterus closed during pregnancy. If you have this surgery, you may still be able to become pregnant.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_21"><Title>Bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy      </Title><Para id="_22">Bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy removes both ovaries and both fallopian tubes. This is done when the cancer has spread to these organs.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_23"><Title>Total pelvic exenteration</Title><Para id="_24">Total pelvic exenteration removes the lower <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046555" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rectum</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef>. The cervix, vagina, ovaries, and nearby lymph nodes are also removed. Artificial openings (stoma) are made for urine and stool to flow from the body to a collection bag. Plastic surgery may be needed to make an artificial vagina after this operation.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_27">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing by damaging their <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef>. The two main types of radiation therapy are external radiation therapy and internal radiation therapy (also called brachytherapy).</Para><Para id="_28">Both external and internal radiation therapy are used to treat cervical cancer and may also be used as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045815" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">palliative therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to relieve symptoms and improve quality of life in people with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced</GlossaryTermRef> cervical cancer.</Para><SummarySection id="_29"><Title>External radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_30">External beam radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) is a way of giving external radiation therapy that can help keep radiation from damaging nearby healthy tissue.</Para><Para id="_31">IMRT is a type of 3-dimensional (3-D) radiation therapy that uses a computer to make pictures of the size and shape of the tumor. Thin beams of radiation of different intensities (strengths) are aimed directly at the tumor from many angles. IMRT is being studied for the treatment of cervical cancer.</Para><Para id="_32">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><Title>Internal radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_34">Internal radiation therapy uses a radioactive substance sealed in needles, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000257219" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seeds</GlossaryTermRef>, wires, or catheters that are placed directly into or near the cancer. Internal radiation therapy is also called brachytherapy.</Para><Para id="_35">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/brachytherapy">Brachytherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_36"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_37">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment.</Para><Para id="_38">Chemotherapy drugs used to treat cervical cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_39" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495426" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemcitabinehydrochloride">gemcitabine</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000686471" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ifosfamide">ifosfamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537382" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecanhydrochloride">irinotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000502187" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/paclitaxel">paclitaxel</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495675" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/topotecanhydrochloride">topotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000695633" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vinorelbinetartrate">vinorelbine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_40">Combinations of these drugs may be used. Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_41">Learn more about how chemotherapy works against cancer, how it is given, common side effects, and more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_42"><Title>Targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_43">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to block the action of specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef>, proteins, or other molecules involved in the growth and spread of cancer cells.</Para><Para id="_44">Targeted therapies used to treat cervical cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_61" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000487564" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/bevacizumab">bevacizumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000806188" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/tisotumabvedotin-tftv">tisotumab vedotin</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_45">Learn more about how targeted therapy works against cancer, how it is given, possible side effects, and more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_46"><Title>Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_47">Immunotherapy helps a person's immune system fight cancer. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000805418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Biomarker tests</GlossaryTermRef> can be used to help predict your response to certain immunotherapy drugs.   Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_48"><DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">Pembrolizumab</DrugRef>  is an immunotherapy drug used to treat certain patients whose cervical cancer has the biomarker <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000797389" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PD-L1</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_49">Learn more about how immunotherapy works against cancer, how it is given, possible side effects, and more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_50_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_50_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_50_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_54"><Title>Follow-up care during and after treatment</Title><Para id="_55">As you go through treatment, you will have follow-up tests or checkups. Some of the tests that were done to diagnose cervical cancer or to find out the stage of the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_56">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). </Para><Para id="_57">Tell your doctor if you have any of the following signs or symptoms, which may mean the cancer has come back:</Para><ItemizedList id="_58" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>vaginal bleeding or discharge</ListItem><ListItem>pain in the abdomen, back, or leg</ListItem><ListItem>swelling in the leg</ListItem><ListItem>trouble urinating</ListItem><ListItem>change in your bowel movements</ListItem><ListItem>cough</ListItem><ListItem>feeling tired</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_59">For cervical cancer, follow-up tests are usually done every 3 to 4 months for the first 2 years, followed by checkups every 6 months. The checkup includes a current health history and exam of the body to check for signs and symptoms of recurrent cervical cancer and for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390292" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">late effects</GlossaryTermRef> of treatment. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045978" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Pap test</GlossaryTermRef> may or may not be done during your visits.</Para><Para id="_60">Learn more about what to expect <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/survivorship">when treatment ends</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-10-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-04-03</DateLastModified></Summary>
