<Summary id="CDR0000810339" SVPC="Yes" SuppressOnThisPageSection="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Certain aspects of cervical cancer diagnosis and treatment are of special concern. Gain a greater sense of control by knowing what to expect and what resources are available to help you cope.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cervical/coping">Coping with Cervical Cancer</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037892">cervical cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cervical cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>coping with cervical cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>coping with cervical cancer treatment side effects</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Coping with Cervical Cancer</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Coping with Cervical Cancer</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Coping with Cervical Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_3">When you first learn that you have cervical cancer, it is normal to feel a mix of emotions. You may wonder how you will cope with the upcoming changes in your life. One step you can take is to be informed of the changes that may occur and what resources are available to help you cope. Doing so can give you a greater sense of control. </Para><Para id="_4">Resources on the common physical side effects of treatment for cervical cancer are provided in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810279" url="/types/cervical/treatment">Cervical Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef> section. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">side effects caused by cancer treatment</ExternalRef> and ways to manage them. </Para><Para id="_5">Because cervical cancer tends to occur in people of reproductive age, and because of where it forms in the body, certain aspects of your diagnosis and treatment are of special concern. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>Fertility issues</Title><Para id="_7">For some people, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infertility</GlossaryTermRef> can be one of the most difficult and upsetting long-term effects of cervical cancer treatment. Although it might feel overwhelming to think about, you may benefit from talking with you doctor about how treatment may affect your fertility and about options to preserve fertility. If you choose to take steps to preserve your fertility, your doctor and a fertility specialist will work together to develop a treatment plan that includes fertility preservation, whenever possible. </Para><Para id="_8">Learn more about which cancer treatments may affect fertility and about fertility-sparing treatment options in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/fertility-women">Fertility Issues in Girls and Women with Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Sexual problems</Title><Para id="_10">Some treatments for cervical cancer can cause short-term or long-term problems with sex after treatment. Sexual problems are often caused by changes to your body. These changes result from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045570" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">surgery</GlossaryTermRef>, or certain medicines.  </Para><Para id="_11">Learn more about the sexual problems some cancer treatments can cause and ways to cope and share your concerns with your health care team in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/sexuality-women">Sexual Health Issues in Women with Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><Title>Body changes</Title><Para id="_13">Cervical cancer and its treatment can change how you look and feel about yourself. Know you aren't alone in how you feel. Coping with these changes can be hard. But, over time, most people learn to adjust to them and move forward. </Para><Para id="_14">Learn more about how body changes may affect your self-image and sex life after treatment and ways to cope and communicate your feelings in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/self-image">Self-Image and Sexuality</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2"><Title>Stigma and guilt</Title><Para id="_15">Because cervical cancer results from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803838" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sexually transmitted infection</GlossaryTermRef> with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045714" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">human papillomavirus</GlossaryTermRef> (HPV), you may worry that some people assume your behavior caused your cancer. Or you may blame yourself for lifestyle choices you think could have led to your cancer. It is important to remember almost everyone will have an HPV infection at some point in their lives and that most HPV infections of the cervix will not cause cervical cancer. Having cervical cancer is not your fault. It may help you to share your feelings with someone. Let your doctor know if you would like to talk with a counselor or go to a support group. </Para><Para id="_16">Learn more about the emotions many people with cancer feel and ways to cope in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings">Feelings and Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/adjusting-to-cancer/support-groups">Cancer Support Groups</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_17"><Title>Financial toxicity</Title><Para id="_18">Cancer is one of the most costly diseases to treat in the United States. You may face major financial challenges and need help dealing with the costs of cervical cancer treatment, even if you have insurance. The problems a person has related to the cost of treatment is known as financial toxicity. Find out if you are at risk and learn about ways to cope in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000783881" url="/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs/financial-toxicity-pdq">Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs">Managing Costs and Medical Information</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2022-10-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2022-10-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
