<Summary id="CDR0000810728" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatment for children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML) includes stem cell transplant. Supportive care is also used. Get detailed information for JMML in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038439">juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_773">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_774">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_786"><Title>Incidence</Title><Para id="_787">Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML) is a rare
leukemia that occurs approximately ten times less frequently than acute myeloid leukemia in children. The annual incidence is about 1 to 2 cases per 1 million people.<Reference refidx="1"/>  JMML is the most common myeloproliferative neoplasm observed in young children, presenting at a median age of approximately 1.8 years. It
occurs more commonly in boys (male-to-female ratio, approximately 2.5:1).</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12780790">Passmore SJ, Chessells JM, Kempski H, et al.: Paediatric myelodysplastic syndromes and juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia in the UK: a population-based study of incidence and survival. Br J Haematol 121 (5): 758-67, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_788"><Title>Clinical Presentation </Title><Para id="_789"> Common clinical features at diagnosis include the following:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_790" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Hepatosplenomegaly (97%).</ListItem><ListItem>Lymphadenopathy (76%).</ListItem><ListItem>Pallor (64%).</ListItem><ListItem>Fever (54%).</ListItem><ListItem>Skin rash (36%).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1992">Patients may also present with an elevated white blood cell count and increased circulating monocytes.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="9160658" MedlineID="97304295">Niemeyer CM, Arico M, Basso G, et al.: Chronic myelomonocytic leukemia in childhood: a retrospective analysis of 110 cases. European Working Group on Myelodysplastic Syndromes in Childhood (EWOG-MDS) Blood 89 (10): 3534-43, 1997.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1996"><Title>World Health Organization Classification</Title><Para id="_2003">The World Health Organization (WHO) classifies juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML) as a RAS pathway activation–driven myeloproliferative neoplasm (MPN) of early childhood.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para><Para id="_791">For information about the classification system for acute myeloid leukemia (AML), see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062896#_144" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq">World Health Organization (WHO) Classification System for Childhood AML</SummaryRef> section in Childhood Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="35732831">Khoury JD, Solary E, Abla O, et al.: The 5th edition of the World Health Organization Classification of Haematolymphoid Tumours: Myeloid and Histiocytic/Dendritic Neoplasms. Leukemia 36 (7): 1703-1719, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1997"><Title>Diagnostic Criteria</Title><Para id="_2004">In children presenting with clinical features suggestive of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML), current criteria for a definitive diagnosis are described in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_2008" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Table id="_2008"><Title>Table 1.  Diagnostic Criteria for JMML According to the 5th Edition of the WHO Classification of Hematolymphoid Tumors</Title><TGroup Cols="3"><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="1" ColWidth="3.68%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="2" ColWidth="6.71%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="3" ColWidth="89.59%"/><TFoot><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1">GM-CSF = granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor; JMML = juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia; WHO = World Health Organization.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Germline variants in <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName>, <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName>, or <GeneName>NRAS</GeneName> (which cause Noonan syndrome) may lead to JMML-like transient myeloproliferative disorder.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Occasional cases have heterozygous splice-site variants.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>c</Superscript>Such as <GeneName>RRAS</GeneName> or <GeneName>RRAS2</GeneName>.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Superscript>d</Superscript>For cases that do not meet the genetic criteria or if genetic testing is not available. These individuals must meet the following criteria in addition to the clinical, hematologic, and laboratory criteria.</entry></Row></TFoot><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Clinical, Hematologic, and Laboratory Criteria (All Criteria Are Required for Diagnosis)</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">1.    Peripheral blood monocyte count is ≥1 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">2.    Blasts and promonocytes constitute &lt;20% of peripheral blood and bone marrow</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">3.    Clinical evidence of organ infiltration, most commonly splenomegaly
</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">4.    Absence of the <GeneName>BCR</GeneName>::<GeneName>ABL1</GeneName> fusion
gene</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">5.    Absence of a <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> rearrangement</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Genetic Criteria (1 Criterion is Sufficient for Diagnosis)</Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">1.    A variant in a component or a regulator of the canonical RAS pathway:
</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>a)    A clonal somatic variant in <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName>, <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName>, or <GeneName>NRAS</GeneName><Superscript>a</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>b)    A clonal somatic or germline variant in <GeneName>NF1</GeneName> and a loss of heterozygosity or compound heterozygosity in <GeneName>NF1</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry/><entry>c)    A clonal somatic or germline variant in <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> and a loss of heterozygosity in <GeneName>CBL</GeneName><Superscript>b</Superscript></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">2.     A noncanonical clonal RAS pathway pathogenic variant<Superscript>c</Superscript> or fusions that activate genes located upstream of the RAS pathway, such as <GeneName>ALK</GeneName>, <GeneName>PDGFRB</GeneName>, and <GeneName>ROS1</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col1"><Strong>Other Criteria (2 or More Are Required for Diagnosis)<Superscript>d</Superscript></Strong></entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">1.    Circulating myeloid (promyelocytes, myelocytes, metamyelocytes) and erythroid precursors</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">2.    Increased hemoglobin F for age
</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">3.    Thrombocytopenia with hypercellular bone marrow, often with megakaryocytic hypoplasia; dysplastic features may or may not be evident</entry></Row><Row><entry/><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col2">4.     Myeloid progenitors are hypersensitive to GM-CSF (detected by clonogenic assays or by measuring STAT5 phosphorylation in the absence or with low dose of exogenous GM-CSF)</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="35732831">Khoury JD, Solary E, Abla O, et al.: The 5th edition of the World Health Organization Classification of Haematolymphoid Tumours: Myeloid and Histiocytic/Dendritic Neoplasms. Leukemia 36 (7): 1703-1719, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_792"><Title>Pathogenesis and Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_512">The pathogenesis of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML)  has been closely linked to activation of the <GeneName>RAS</GeneName> oncogene pathway, along with related syndromes (see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_563" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">Figure 1</SummaryRef>).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  In addition, distinctive RNA expression and DNA methylation patterns have been reported. These patterns are correlated with clinical factors such as age and appear to be associated with prognosis.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_562"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000712808" type="image/jpeg" alt="Schematic diagram showing ligand-stimulated Ras activation, the Ras-Erk pathway, and gene mutations contributing to the neuro-cardio-facio-cutaneous congenital disorders and JMML." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_563"><Caption language="en">Figure 1.  Schematic diagram showing ligand-stimulated Ras activation, the Ras-Erk pathway, and the gene mutations found to date contributing to the neuro-cardio-facio-cutaneous congenital disorders and JMML. NL/MGCL: Noonan-like/multiple giant cell lesion; CFC: cardia-facio-cutaneous; JMML: juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Reprinted from Leukemia Research, 33 (3), Rebecca J. Chan, Todd Cooper, Christian P. Kratz, Brian Weiss, Mignon L. Loh, Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: A report from the 2nd International JMML Symposium, Pages 355-62, Copyright 2009, with permission from Elsevier.</Caption></MediaLink></Para><Para id="_793">Syndromes and genetic features associated with an increased risk of developing JMML include the following:<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_794" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Neurofibromatosis type
1 (NF1).</Strong> Up to 14% of cases of
JMML occur in children with NF1.<Reference refidx="7"/>  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Noonan syndrome.</Strong> Noonan syndrome is usually inherited as an autosomal dominant condition but can also arise spontaneously. It is characterized by facial dysmorphism, short stature, webbed neck, and neurocognitive and cardiac abnormalities.  Germline variants in <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName> are observed in children with Noonan syndrome and in children with  JMML.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> <Para id="_795">Importantly, some children with Noonan syndrome have hematologic features indistinguishable from JMML that self-resolve during infancy, similar to what happens in children with Down syndrome and transient myeloproliferative disorder.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_1193">In a large prospective cohort of 641 patients with Noonan syndrome and a germline <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName> variant, 36 patients (approximately 6%) showed myeloproliferative features, with 20 patients (approximately 3%) meeting the consensus diagnostic criteria for JMML.<Reference refidx="10"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_1998" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Of the 20 patients meeting the criteria for JMML, 12 patients had severe neonatal manifestations (e.g., life-threatening complications related to congenital heart defects, pleural effusion, leukemia infiltrates, and/or thrombocytopenia), and 10 of 20 patients died during the first month of life. </ListItem><ListItem>Among the remaining eight patients, none required intensive therapy at diagnosis or during follow-up. </ListItem><ListItem>All 16 patients with myeloproliferative features that did not meet JMML criteria were alive, with a median follow-up of 3 years, and no patient received chemotherapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Variants in the <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> gene.</Strong> CBL is an E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase that is involved in targeting proteins, particularly tyrosine kinases, for proteasomal degradation. Variants in the <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> gene occur  in 10% to 15% of JMML cases,<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> with many of these cases occurring in children with germline <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> variants.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Para id="_1993"><GeneName>CBL</GeneName> germline variants result in an autosomal dominant developmental disorder that is often characterized by impaired growth, developmental delay, cryptorchidism, and a predisposition to JMML.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="15"/>  Some individuals with <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> germline variants experience spontaneous regression of their JMML but develop vasculitis later in life,<Reference refidx="13"/>   whereas patients with only somatic <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> variants require therapy.<Reference refidx="15"/> JMML arising from germline variants is clinically indistinguishable from JMML arising from somatic variants, which necessitates studies of both normal and leukemic tissue.<Reference refidx="15"/> <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> variants are nearly always mutually exclusive of <GeneName>RAS</GeneName> and <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName> variants.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para></ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="18954903">Chan RJ, Cooper T, Kratz CP, et al.: Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a report from the 2nd International JMML Symposium. Leuk Res 33 (3): 355-62, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21623760">Loh ML: Recent advances in the pathogenesis and treatment of juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia. Br J Haematol 152 (6): 677-87, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="20231685">Bresolin S, Zecca M, Flotho C, et al.: Gene expression-based classification as an independent predictor of clinical outcome in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. J Clin Oncol 28 (11): 1919-27, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="21406719">Olk-Batz C, Poetsch AR, Nöllke P, et al.: Aberrant DNA methylation characterizes juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia with poor outcome. Blood 117 (18): 4871-80, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="7947106" MedlineID="95034068">Stiller CA, Chessells JM, Fitchett M: Neurofibromatosis and childhood leukaemia/lymphoma: a population-based UKCCSG study. Br J Cancer 70 (5): 969-72, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="10598665" MedlineID="20065724">Choong K, Freedman MH, Chitayat D, et al.: Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia and Noonan syndrome. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 21 (6): 523-7, 1999 Nov-Dec.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="9160658" MedlineID="97304295">Niemeyer CM, Arico M, Basso G, et al.: Chronic myelomonocytic leukemia in childhood: a retrospective analysis of 110 cases. European Working Group on Myelodysplastic Syndromes in Childhood (EWOG-MDS) Blood 89 (10): 3534-43, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12717436">Tartaglia M, Niemeyer CM, Fragale A, et al.: Somatic mutations in PTPN11 in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia, myelodysplastic syndromes and acute myeloid leukemia. Nat Genet 34 (2): 148-50, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15928039">Kratz CP, Niemeyer CM, Castleberry RP, et al.: The mutational spectrum of PTPN11 in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia and Noonan syndrome/myeloproliferative disease. Blood 106 (6): 2183-5, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="25097206">Strullu M, Caye A, Lachenaud J, et al.: Juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia and Noonan syndrome. J Med Genet 51 (10): 689-97, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="19571318">Loh ML, Sakai DS, Flotho C, et al.: Mutations in CBL occur frequently in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Blood 114 (9): 1859-63, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="20008299">Muramatsu H, Makishima H, Jankowska AM, et al.: Mutations of an E3 ubiquitin ligase c-Cbl but not TET2 mutations are pathogenic in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Blood 115 (10): 1969-75, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="20694012">Niemeyer CM, Kang MW, Shin DH, et al.: Germline CBL mutations cause developmental abnormalities and predispose to juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Nat Genet 42 (9): 794-800, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="20543203">Pérez B, Mechinaud F, Galambrun C, et al.: Germline mutations of the CBL gene define a new genetic syndrome with predisposition to juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia. J Med Genet 47 (10): 686-91, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="33375775">Hecht A, Meyer JA, Behnert A, et al.: Molecular and phenotypic diversity of CBL-mutated juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Haematologica 107 (1): 178-186, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_797"><Title>Genomics of Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia (JMML)</Title><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000778658_797"><Title>Molecular Features of JMML</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000778658_798">The genomic landscape of JMML is characterized by variants in one of five genes of the RAS pathway: <GeneName>NF1</GeneName>, <GeneName>NRAS</GeneName>, <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName>, <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName>, and <GeneName>CBL</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> In a series of 118 consecutively diagnosed JMML cases with RAS pathway–activating variants, <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName> was the most commonly altered gene, accounting for 51% of cases (19% germline and 32% somatic) (see Figure 2).<Reference refidx="1"/> Patients with <GeneName>NRAS</GeneName>  variants accounted for 19% of cases, and patients with <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName> variants accounted for 15% of cases. <GeneName>NF1</GeneName> variants accounted for 8% of cases, and <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> variants accounted for 11% of cases.  Although variants among these five genes are generally mutually exclusive, 4% to 17% of cases have variants in two of these RAS pathway genes,<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> a finding that is associated with poorer prognosis.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000778658_799">The variant rate in JMML leukemia cells is very low, but additional variants beyond those of the five RAS pathway genes described above are observed.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Secondary genomic alterations are observed for genes of the transcriptional repressor complex PRC2 (e.g., <GeneName>ASXL1</GeneName> was altered in 7%–8% of cases). Some genes associated with myeloproliferative neoplasms in adults are also altered at low rates in JMML (e.g., <GeneName>SETBP1</GeneName> was altered in 6%–9% of cases).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> <GeneName>JAK3</GeneName> variants are also observed in a small percentage (4%–12%) of JMML cases.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Cases with germline <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName> and germline <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> variants showed low rates of additional variants (see Figure 2).<Reference refidx="1"/> The presence of variants beyond disease-defining RAS pathway variants is associated with an inferior prognosis.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000778658_817">A report describing the genomic landscape of JMML found that 16 of 150 patients (11%) lacked canonical RAS pathway variants. Among these 16 patients, 3 were observed to have in-frame fusions involving receptor tyrosine kinases (<GeneName>DCTN1</GeneName>::<GeneName>ALK</GeneName>, <GeneName>RANBP2</GeneName>::<GeneName>ALK</GeneName>, and <GeneName>TBL1XR1</GeneName>::<GeneName>ROS1</GeneName> gene fusions). These patients all had monosomy 7 and were aged 56 months or older. One patient with an <GeneName>ALK</GeneName> gene fusion was treated with crizotinib plus conventional chemotherapy and achieved a complete molecular remission and proceeded to allogeneic bone marrow transplant.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000778658_812"><MediaLink ref="CDR0000778293" type="image/jpeg" alt="Chart showing alteration profiles in individual JMML cases." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_sm_CDR0000778658_813"><Caption language="en">Figure 2.  Alteration profiles in individual JMML cases. Germline and somatically acquired alterations with recurring hits in the RAS pathway and PRC2 network are shown for 118 patients with JMML who underwent detailed genetic analysis. Blast excess was defined as a blast count ≥10% but &lt;20% of nucleated cells in the bone marrow at diagnosis. Blast crisis was defined as a blast count ≥20% of nucleated cells in the bone marrow. NS, Noonan syndrome. Reprinted by permission from Macmillan Publishers Ltd: <ExternalRef xref="http://www.nature.com/ng/index.html">Nature Genetics</ExternalRef> (Caye A, Strullu M, Guidez F, et al.: Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia displays mutations in components of the RAS pathway and the PRC2 network. Nat Genet 47 [11]: 1334-40, 2015), copyright (2015).</Caption></MediaLink></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000778658_822"><Title>Genomic and Molecular Prognostic Factors</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000778658_823">Several genomic factors affect the prognosis of patients with JMML, including the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_sm_CDR0000778658_824" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><Strong>Number of non–RAS pathway variants.</Strong> A predictor of prognosis for children with JMML is the number of variants beyond the disease-defining RAS pathway variants.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000778658_825" Style="bullet"><ListItem>One study observed that zero or one somatic alteration (pathogenic variant or monosomy 7) was identified in 64 patients (65.3%) at diagnosis, whereas two or more alterations were identified in 34 patients (34.7%).<Reference refidx="2"/> In multivariate analysis, variant number (2 or more vs. 0 or 1) maintained significance as a predictor of inferior event-free survival (EFS) and overall survival (OS). A higher proportion of patients diagnosed with two or more alterations were older and male, and these patients also demonstrated a higher rate of monosomy 7 or somatic <GeneName>NF1</GeneName> variants.<Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem>Another study observed that approximately 60% of patients had one or more additional variants beyond their disease-defining RAS pathway variant. These patients had an inferior OS compared with patients who had no additional variants (3-year OS rate, 61% vs. 85%, respectively).<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem>A third study observed a trend for an inferior OS for patients with two or more variants compared with patients with zero or one variant.<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>RAS pathway double variants.</Strong> Although variants in the five canonical RAS pathway genes associated with JMML (<GeneName>NF1</GeneName>, <GeneName>NRAS</GeneName>, <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName>, <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName>, and <GeneName>CBL</GeneName>) are generally mutually exclusive, 4% to 17% of cases have variants in two of these RAS pathway genes.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> This finding has been associated with a poorer prognosis.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000778658_826" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Two RAS pathway variants were identified in 11% of JMML patients in one report, and these patients had a significantly inferior EFS rate (14%) compared with patients who had a single RAS pathway variant (62%). Patients with Noonan syndrome were excluded from the analyses.<Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem>Similar findings for RAS pathway variants were reported in a second study. This study observed that patients with RAS pathway double variants (15 of 96 patients) had lower survival rates than did patients with either no additional variants or with additional variants beyond the RAS pathway variant.<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>DNA methylation profile.</Strong> <ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000778658_827" Style="bullet"><ListItem>One study applied DNA methylation profiling to a discovery cohort of 39 patients with JMML and to a validation cohort of 40 patients. Distinctive subsets of JMML with either high, intermediate, or low methylation levels were observed in both cohorts. Patients with the lowest methylation levels had the highest survival rates, and all but 1 of 15 patients experienced spontaneous resolution in the low methylation cohort. High methylation status was associated with lower EFS rates.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem>Another study applied DNA methylation profiling to a cohort of 106 patients with JMML. The study observed one subgroup of patients with a hypermethylation profile and one subgroup of patients with a hypomethylation profile. Patients in the hypermethylation group had a significantly lower OS rate than did patients in the hypomethylation group (5-year OS rate, 46% vs. 73%, respectively). Patients in the hypermethylation group also had a significantly poorer 5-year transplant-free survival rate than did patients in the hypomethylation group (2.2%; 95% CI, 0.2%–10.1% vs. 41.2%; 95% CI, 27.1%–54.8%).  Hypermethylation status was associated with two or more variants, higher fetal hemoglobin levels, older age, and lower platelet count at diagnosis. All patients with Noonan syndrome were in the hypomethylation group.<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem>A study examined 33 patients with JMML who had <GeneName>CBL</GeneName> variants. The study identified 31 patients with low methylation and 2 patients with intermediate methylation.  Both of the children with intermediate methylation relapsed after undergoing HSCT.   Because treatment, which included observation only, varied among the 31 patients with low methylation, the impact of the methylation profile on therapeutic decisions and outcomes could not be fully assessed. However, the methylation status was not prognostic of spontaneous resolution.<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>LIN28B</GeneName> overexpression.</Strong> <GeneName>LIN28B</GeneName> overexpression, which is present in approximately one-half of children with JMML, identifies a biologically distinctive subset of JMML. LIN28B is an RNA-binding protein that regulates stem cell renewal.<Reference refidx="7"/><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000778658_828" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GeneName>LIN28B</GeneName> overexpression was positively correlated with high blood fetal hemoglobin level and age (both of which are associated with poor prognosis), and it was negatively correlated with presence of monosomy 7 (also associated with inferior prognosis). Although <GeneName>LIN28B</GeneName> overexpression identifies a subset of patients with increased risk of treatment failure, it was not found to be an independent prognostic factor when other factors such as age and monosomy 7 status are considered.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem><ListItem>Another study also observed a subset of JMML patients with elevated <GeneName>LIN28B</GeneName> expression. The study identified <GeneName>LIN28B</GeneName> as the gene for which expression was most strongly associated with hypermethylation status.<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem></ItemizedList> </ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26457648">Caye A, Strullu M, Guidez F, et al.: Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia displays mutations in components of the RAS pathway and the PRC2 network. Nat Genet 47 (11): 1334-40, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="26457647">Stieglitz E, Taylor-Weiner AN, Chang TY, et al.: The genomic landscape of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Nat Genet 47 (11): 1326-33, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="29437595">Murakami N, Okuno Y, Yoshida K, et al.: Integrated molecular profiling of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Blood 131 (14): 1576-1586, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="23832011">Sakaguchi H, Okuno Y, Muramatsu H, et al.: Exome sequencing identifies secondary mutations of SETBP1 and JAK3 in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Nat Genet 45 (8): 937-41, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="29259179">Stieglitz E, Mazor T, Olshen AB, et al.: Genome-wide DNA methylation is predictive of outcome in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Nat Commun 8 (1): 2127, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="33375775">Hecht A, Meyer JA, Behnert A, et al.: Molecular and phenotypic diversity of CBL-mutated juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Haematologica 107 (1): 178-186, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26712910">Helsmoortel HH, Bresolin S, Lammens T, et al.: LIN28B overexpression defines a novel fetal-like subgroup of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Blood 127 (9): 1163-72, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_800"><Title>Clinical Prognostic Factors</Title><Para id="_801"> Historically, more than 90% of patients with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML)  died despite the use of chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="1"/> However, with the application of hematopoietic stem cell transplant, survival rates of approximately 50% are now observed.<Reference refidx="2"/> Patients appeared to follow  three distinct clinical courses:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1332" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Rapidly progressive disease and early demise.</ListItem><ListItem>Transiently stable disease followed by progression and death.</ListItem><ListItem>Clinical improvement that lasted up to 9 years before progression or, rarely, long-term survival.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1333">Favorable prognostic factors for survival after any therapy include the following:<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_1994" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Age younger than 2 years.</ListItem><ListItem>Platelet count greater than 33 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L.</ListItem><ListItem>Low age-adjusted fetal hemoglobin levels.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1995">In contrast, being older than 2 years and having high blood fetal hemoglobin levels at diagnosis are predictors of poor outcome.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="3052147" MedlineID="89023840">Freedman MH, Estrov Z, Chan HS: Juvenile chronic myelogenous leukemia. Am J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 10 (3): 261-7, 1988 Fall.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15353481">Locatelli F, Nöllke P, Zecca M, et al.: Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) in children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML): results of the EWOG-MDS/EBMT trial. Blood 105 (1): 410-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9160658" MedlineID="97304295">Niemeyer CM, Arico M, Basso G, et al.: Chronic myelomonocytic leukemia in childhood: a retrospective analysis of 110 cases. European Working Group on Myelodysplastic Syndromes in Childhood (EWOG-MDS) Blood 89 (10): 3534-43, 1997.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12780790">Passmore SJ, Chessells JM, Kempski H, et al.: Paediatric myelodysplastic syndromes and juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia in the UK: a population-based study of incidence and survival. Br J Haematol 121 (5): 758-67, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2011"><Title>Special Considerations for the Treatment of Children With Cancer</Title><Para id="_2011_md_3">Cancer in children and adolescents is rare, although the overall incidence has slowly increased since 1975.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Children and adolescents with cancer should be referred to medical centers that have a multidisciplinary team of cancer specialists with experience treating the cancers that occur during childhood and adolescence.<Reference refidx="2"/>  This multidisciplinary team approach incorporates the skills
of the following pediatric specialists and others to ensure that children receive treatment, supportive care, and rehabilitation
to achieve optimal survival and quality of life:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2011_md_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Primary care physicians.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric surgeons.</ListItem><ListItem>Pathologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric radiation
oncologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric medical oncologists and hematologists.</ListItem><ListItem> Rehabilitation
specialists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric oncology nurses.</ListItem><ListItem>Social workers.</ListItem><ListItem>Child-life professionals.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Nutritionists.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2011_md_5">For specific information about supportive care for children and adolescents with cancer, see the summaries on <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/supportive-care">Supportive and Palliative Care</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_2011_md_6">The American Academy of Pediatrics has outlined guidelines for
pediatric cancer centers and their role in the treatment of children and adolescents
with cancer.<Reference refidx="3"/>  At
these centers, clinical trials are available for most  types of cancer that occur in children and adolescents, and the opportunity
to participate is offered to most patients and their families.  Clinical
trials for children and adolescents diagnosed with cancer are generally
designed to compare potentially better therapy with current standard therapy.  Other types of clinical trials test novel therapies when there is no standard therapy for a cancer diagnosis. Most of the progress in identifying curative
therapies for childhood cancers has been achieved through clinical trials.
Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20404250">Smith MA, Seibel NL, Altekruse SF, et al.: Outcomes for children and adolescents with cancer: challenges for the twenty-first century. J Clin Oncol 28 (15): 2625-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="28209594">Wolfson J, Sun CL, Wyatt L, et al.: Adolescents and Young Adults with Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia and Acute Myeloid Leukemia: Impact of Care at Specialized Cancer Centers on Survival Outcome. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 26 (3): 312-320, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3">American Academy of Pediatrics: Standards for pediatric cancer centers. Pediatrics  134 (2): 410-4, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/134/2/410">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_803"><Title>Treatment of JMML</Title><Para id="_804">Treatment options for juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML)  include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_2006" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_2017" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">Chemotherapy before hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT)</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_2007" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">HSCT</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_2017"><Title>Chemotherapy Before HSCT</Title><Para id="_2018">Previous efforts to use chemotherapy before curative-intent HSCT have had a mixed and overall unsatisfactory impact on survival. However, control of symptoms has been aided by various lower- and higher-intensity regimens.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_2024">Evidence (chemotherapy before HSCT):</Para><OrderedList id="_2021" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>In an attempt to cytoreduce leukemic burden, the combination of fludarabine and cytarabine with isotretinoin alone was given for two cycles before planned HSCT in 34 of 87 evaluable children with JMML in the Children's Oncology Group (COG) <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT00025038">AAML0122</ProtocolRef> trial.<Reference refidx="3"/><ItemizedList id="_2027" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In this group, the overall response rate (partial response [PR] and complete response [CR]) was 68%. However, achieving a CR before HSCT did not significantly improve overall survival, event-free survival (EFS), or  relapse risk.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A phase II, single-arm, open-label trial included 18 children with newly diagnosed JMML who received single-agent azacitidine, given for 7 days in 28-day cycles.<Reference refidx="4"/> <ItemizedList id="_2022" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The study found that 61% of patients had partial remissions after three cycles of treatment. </ListItem><ListItem>Responding patients, defined using the International JMML response criteria,<Reference refidx="5"/> tended to be younger and had low-to-medium methylation classifications. </ListItem><ListItem>Six patients became platelet-transfusion independent, and all responders had reductions in splenomegaly. </ListItem><ListItem>Seventeen of the 18 patients received an HSCT at a median of 5.5 months after diagnosis. Of these 17 patients, 14 remained leukemia-free at last follow-up (median, 23.8 months after HSCT).<Reference refidx="4"/> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2023">Partially based on this trial, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration expanded the approved indications for azacitidine to include children with newly diagnosed JMML.</Para></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2007"><Title>HSCT</Title><Para id="_807">HSCT currently offers the best chance of cure for JMML.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_808">Evidence (HSCT):</Para><OrderedList id="_809" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>A report from the European Working Group on Childhood Myelodysplastic Syndromes included 100 transplant recipients at multiple centers treated with a common preparative regimen of busulfan, cyclophosphamide, and melphalan, with or without antithymocyte globulin. Recipients had been treated with varying degrees of pretransplant chemotherapy or differentiating agents, and some patients had a splenectomy.<Reference refidx="7"/>  <ItemizedList id="_810" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year EFS rate was 55%  for children with JMML who underwent HSCT using HLA-identical matched family donor cells and 49% for children with JMML who underwent HSCT using  unrelated donor cells.</ListItem><ListItem>The multivariate analysis showed no effect on survival of previous acute myeloid leukemia–like chemotherapy versus low-dose chemotherapy or no chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem> No effect on survival was observed for splenectomy pretransplant or difference in spleen size.</ListItem><ListItem>No difference in outcomes was found based on related versus unrelated donors.</ListItem><ListItem>Only  age older than 4 years and female sex were shown to be poor prognostic factors for outcome and increased risk of relapse (relative risk [RR], 2.24 [1.07–4.69]; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .032 for older age; RR, 2.22 [1.09–4.50]; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .028 for females).<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In one study, cord blood transplant produced the following results:<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]   <ItemizedList id="_1999" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The 5-year disease-free survival rate was 44%.</ListItem><ListItem> Outcomes were improved in children younger than 1.4 years at diagnosis, those with nonmonosomy 7 karyotype, and those receiving 5/6 to 6/6 HLA-matched cord units.</ListItem><ListItem>This suggests that cord blood can provide an additional donor pool for this group of children.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>The use of reduced-intensity preparative regimens to decrease the adverse side effects of transplant have also been reported in small numbers of patients, generally for patients ineligible for myeloablative HSCT.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><OrderedList id="_1990" Style="LAlpha"><ListItem>The COG conducted a randomized trial in children with JMML that compared a standard-intensity preparative regimen (busulfan/cyclophosphamide/melphalan) with a reduced-intensity regimen (busulfan/fludarabine).<Reference refidx="13"/><ItemizedList id="_1991" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The trial closed to enrollment early when an interim analysis revealed a higher frequency of relapse/disease persistence (7 of 9 patients) in children who received the reduced-intensity regimen than in children who received the standard-intensity regimen (1 of 6 patients).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList> </ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection><Para id="_806">The role of conventional antileukemia therapy in the treatment of JMML is not defined.  Determining the role of specific agents in the treatment of JMML is complicated because of the absence of consensus response criteria.<Reference refidx="14"/> Some agents that have shown antileukemia activity against JMML include etoposide, cytarabine, thiopurines (thioguanine and mercaptopurine), isotretinoin, and farnesyl inhibitors, but none of these have been shown to improve outcome.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/><Reference refidx="18"/>; <Reference refidx="3"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810033" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence B4</LOERef>]</Para><SummarySection id="_2025"><Title>Approaches to Recurrence After HSCT or Refractory JMML</Title><Para id="_811">Disease recurrence is the primary cause of treatment failure for children with JMML after HSCT and occurs in 30% to 40% of cases.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> While the role of donor lymphocyte infusions is uncertain,<Reference refidx="19"/> reports indicate that approximately 50% of patients with relapsed JMML can be successfully treated with a second HSCT.<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><Para id="_2012">In a prospective study, four children with relapsed JMML after stem cell transplant were treated with azacitidine. Three patients responded to azacitidine and were able to proceed to a second transplant.<Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_2026">In a prospective study, ten children with relapsed or refractory JMML were treated with oral trametinib (an MEK inhibitor) daily for up to 12 28-day cycles. Five patients had objective responses (three clinical PRs and two clinical CRs) within five cycles. Two patients had stable disease. All seven patients remained alive at a median follow-up of 24 months, including three who continued to receive trametinib off study (for 6, 24, and 24 months, respectively) without proceeding to HSCT. The four patients who underwent HSCT remained in CR at a median of 24 months of follow-up. The RAS pathway variants were no longer detected in the four patients who underwent HSCT, whereas the three other patients continued to have detectable variants without progressive disease while receiving trametinib. No severe adverse events were reported.<Reference refidx="22"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25564399">Locatelli F, Niemeyer CM: How I treat juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Blood 125 (7): 1083-90, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="34525182">Wintering A, Dvorak CC, Stieglitz E, et al.: Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia in the molecular era: a clinician's guide to diagnosis, risk stratification, and treatment. Blood Adv 5 (22): 4783-4793, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25704135">Stieglitz E, Ward AF, Gerbing RB, et al.: Phase II/III trial of a pre-transplant farnesyl transferase inhibitor in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (4): 629-36, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="34297046">Niemeyer CM, Flotho C, Lipka DB, et al.: Response to upfront azacitidine in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia in the AZA-JMML-001 trial. Blood Adv 5 (14): 2901-2908, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="25552679">Niemeyer CM, Loh ML, Cseh A, et al.: Criteria for evaluating response and outcome in clinical trials for children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Haematologica 100 (1): 17-22, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11849238" MedlineID="21838089">Smith FO, King R, Nelson G, et al.: Unrelated donor bone marrow transplantation for children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia. Br J Haematol 116 (3): 716-24, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="15353481">Locatelli F, Nöllke P, Zecca M, et al.: Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) in children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML): results of the EWOG-MDS/EBMT trial. Blood 105 (1): 410-9, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="14755311">Yusuf U, Frangoul HA, Gooley TA, et al.: Allogeneic bone marrow transplantation in children with myelodysplastic syndrome or juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: the Seattle experience. Bone Marrow Transplant 33 (8): 805-14, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="15125615">Baker D, Cole C, Price J, et al.: Allogeneic bone marrow transplantation in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia without total body irradiation. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 26 (3): 200-3, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="23926304">Locatelli F, Crotta A, Ruggeri A, et al.: Analysis of risk factors influencing outcomes after cord blood transplantation in children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a EUROCORD, EBMT, EWOG-MDS, CIBMTR study. Blood 122 (12): 2135-41, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="18397212">Yabe M, Sako M, Yabe H, et al.: A conditioning regimen of busulfan, fludarabine, and melphalan for allogeneic stem cell transplantation in children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Pediatr Transplant 12 (8): 862-7, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="15968292">Koyama M, Nakano T, Takeshita Y, et al.: Successful treatment of JMML with related bone marrow transplantation after reduced-intensity conditioning. Bone Marrow Transplant 36 (5): 453-4; author reply 454, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29528181">Dvorak CC, Satwani P, Stieglitz E, et al.: Disease burden and conditioning regimens in ASCT1221, a randomized phase II trial in children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: A Children's Oncology Group study. Pediatr Blood Cancer 65 (7): e27034, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="16991133">Bergstraesser E, Hasle H, Rogge T, et al.: Non-hematopoietic stem cell transplantation treatment of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a retrospective analysis and definition of response criteria. Pediatr Blood Cancer 49 (5): 629-33, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="7605422" MedlineID="95059326">Castleberry RP, Emanuel PD, Zuckerman KS, et al.: A pilot study of isotretinoin in the treatment of juvenile chronic myelogenous leukemia. N Engl J Med 331 (25): 1680-4, 1994.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="11786571" MedlineID="21646457">Woods WG, Barnard DR, Alonzo TA, et al.: Prospective study of 90 children requiring treatment for juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia or myelodysplastic syndrome: a report from the Children's Cancer Group. J Clin Oncol 20 (2): 434-40, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="21239819">Loh ML: Childhood myelodysplastic syndrome: focus on the approach to diagnosis and treatment of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program 2010: 357-62, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="17224655">Hasle H: Myelodysplastic and myeloproliferative disorders in children. Curr Opin Pediatr 19 (1): 1-8, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="15800672">Yoshimi A, Bader P, Matthes-Martin S, et al.: Donor leukocyte infusion after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in patients with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Leukemia 19 (6): 971-7, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="17268527">Yoshimi A, Mohamed M, Bierings M, et al.: Second allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) results in outcome similar to that of first HSCT for patients with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Leukemia 21 (3): 556-60, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="37695474">Rubio-San-Simón A, van Eijkelenburg NKA, Hoogendijk R, et al.: Azacitidine (Vidaza®) in Pediatric Patients with Relapsed Advanced MDS and JMML: Results of a Phase I/II Study by the ITCC Consortium and the EWOG-MDS Group (Study ITCC-015). Paediatr Drugs 25 (6): 719-728, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="38867349">Stieglitz E, Lee AG, Angus SP, et al.: Efficacy of the Allosteric MEK Inhibitor Trametinib in Relapsed and Refractory Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia: a Report from the Children's Oncology Group. Cancer Discov 14 (9): 1590-1598, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1241"><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation</Title><Para id="_1242">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_2009">The following is an example of a national and/or institutional clinical trial that is currently being conducted:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2010" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT05849662">NCT05849662</ProtocolRef></Strong> (A Phase I/II Study of Trametinib and Azacitidine for Patients With Newly Diagnosed Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia [JMML])<Strong>:</Strong> This clinical trial will test the safety and efficacy of combining trametinib and azacitidine in patients with JMML.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_857"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (12/10/2024)</Title><Para id="_858">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_2028"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_803" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia (JMML)</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_2030">Revised <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_2018" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that previous efforts to use chemotherapy before curative-intent hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) have had a mixed and overall unsatisfactory impact on survival. However, control of symptoms has been aided by various lower- and higher-intensity regimens (cited Wintering et al. as reference 2).</Para><Para id="_2031">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_2021" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">text</SummaryRef> to state that in an attempt to cytoreduce leukemic burden, the combination of fludarabine and cytarabine with isotretinoin alone was given for two cycles before planned HSCT in 34 of 87 evaluable children with JMML in the Children's Oncology Group AAML0122 trial. In this group, the overall response rate was 68%. However, achieving a complete response before HSCT did not significantly improve overall survival, event-free survival, or  relapse risk.</Para><Para id="_2029">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_2025" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">Approaches to Recurrence After HSCT or Refractory JMML</SummaryRef> as a new subsection.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Alan Scott Gamis, MD, MPH (Children's Mercy Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Karen J. Marcus, MD, FACR (Dana-Farber of Boston Children's Cancer Center and Blood Disorders Harvard Medical School)</ListItem><ListItem>Jessica Pollard, MD (Dana-Farber/Boston Children's Cancer and Blood Disorders Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Michael A. Pulsipher, MD (Huntsman Cancer Institute at University of Utah)</ListItem><ListItem>Rachel E. Rau, MD (University of Washington School of Medicine, Seatle Children’s)</ListItem><ListItem>Lewis B. Silverman, MD (Dana-Farber Cancer Institute/Boston Children's Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Malcolm A. Smith, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Sarah K. Tasian, MD (Children's Hospital of Philadelphia)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 38630974]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2024-03-05</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-12-10</DateLastModified></Summary>
