<Summary id="CDR0000810727" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Treatments for children with myelodysplastic neoplasms include stem cell transplant and other therapies. Supportive care is also used. Get detailed information for this disease in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">Childhood Myelodysplastic Neoplasms (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000559318">childhood myelodysplastic syndromes</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_773">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood myelodysplastic neoplasms. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_774">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>childhood myelodysplastic neoplasms</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Myelodysplastic Neoplasms Treatment (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Myelodysplastic Neoplasms Treatment (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Myelodysplastic Neoplasms Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_859"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000559318">childhood myelodysplastic syndromes</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Childhood Myelodysplastic Neoplasms (MDS) </Title><Para id="_499">The myelodysplastic neoplasms (MDS) and myeloproliferative neoplasms (MPN) represent between 5% and 10% of all myeloid malignancies in children. They are a heterogeneous group of disorders. MDS usually presents with cytopenias and is characterized by ineffective hematopoiesis and increased cell death. MPN presents with increased peripheral white blood cell, red blood cell, or platelet counts, and it is associated with increased progenitor cell proliferation and survival.  Because both types of syndromes represent disorders of very primitive, multipotential hematopoietic stem cells, curative therapeutic approaches nearly always require allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant.</Para><Para id="_2166">For information about therapy-related MDS, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062896#_607" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq">Therapy-Related AML and Therapy-Related Myelodysplastic Neoplasms</SummaryRef> section in Childhood Acute Myeloid Leukemia Treatment.</Para><Para id="_2173">For information about MDS associated with <GeneName>GATA1</GeneName> variants  in children with Down syndrome who are aged 4 years or younger, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810726" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-proliferations-down-syndrome-treatment-pdq">Childhood Myeloid Proliferations Associated with Down Syndrome Treatment</SummaryRef>. </Para><Para id="_2174">For information about MPN, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810729" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-cml-treatment-pdq">Childhood Chronic Myeloid Leukemia Treatment</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810728" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/childhood-jmml-treatment-pdq">Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_980"><Title>Clinical Presentation</Title><Para id="_500">Patients with myelodysplastic neoplasms (MDS) often present with signs of cytopenias, including pallor, infection, or bruising.</Para><Para id="_1187">The bone marrow is usually characterized by hypercellularity and dysplastic changes of 10% or more in one or more precursor lineages.  Clonal evolution can eventually lead to the development of acute myeloid leukemia (AML). The percentage of abnormal blasts is less than 20%, and they lack common AML recurrent cytogenetic abnormalities (e.g., t(8;21), inv(16), t(15;17), or <GeneName>KMT2A</GeneName> translocations).</Para><Para id="_1188">The less common hypocellular MDS can be distinguished from aplastic anemia in part by its marked dysplasia, clonal nature, and higher percentage of CD34-positive precursors.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12100146">Kasahara S, Hara T, Itoh H, et al.: Hypoplastic myelodysplastic syndromes can be distinguished from acquired aplastic anaemia by bone marrow stem cell expression of the tumour necrosis factor receptor. Br J Haematol 118 (1): 181-8, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="17587881">Orazi A: Histopathology in the diagnosis and classification of acute myeloid leukemia, myelodysplastic syndromes, and myelodysplastic/myeloproliferative diseases. Pathobiology 74 (2): 97-114, 2007.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_982"><Title>Risk Factors</Title><Para id="_719">Patients with the following germline variants or inherited disorders have a significantly increased risk of developing myelodysplastic neoplasms (MDS):</Para><ItemizedList id="_737" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Fanconi anemia:</Strong> Caused by germline pathogenic variants in DNA repair genes.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Telomere biology disorders (e.g., dyskeratosis congenita):</Strong> Resulting from variants in genes that regulate telomere length. Genes altered in dyskeratosis congenita include <GeneName>ACD</GeneName>, <GeneName>CTC1</GeneName>, <GeneName>DKC1</GeneName>, <GeneName>NHP2</GeneName>, <GeneName>NOP10</GeneName>, <GeneName>PARN</GeneName>, <GeneName>RTEL1</GeneName>, <GeneName>TERC</GeneName>, <GeneName>TERT</GeneName>, <GeneName>TINF2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>WRAP53</GeneName>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Shwachman-Diamond syndrome, Diamond-Blackfan anemia, and other bone marrow failure syndromes:</Strong> Resulting from variants in genes encoding ribosome-associated proteins.<Reference refidx="1"/>  <Reference refidx="2"/> <GeneName>GATA1</GeneName> variants have been linked to Diamond-Blackfan anemia and MDS predisposition.<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Severe congenital neutropenia:</Strong> Caused by variants in the gene encoding elastase. The 15-year cumulative risk of MDS in patients with severe congenital neutropenia, also known as Kostmann syndrome, has been estimated to be 15%, with an annual risk of MDS/acute myeloid leukemia (AML) of 2% to 3%. It is unclear how variants affecting this protein and how the chronic exposure of granulocyte colony-stimulating factor  (G-CSF) contribute to the development of MDS.<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Trisomy 21 syndrome:</Strong> <GeneName>GATA1</GeneName> variants are nearly always present in the transient leukemia associated with Trisomy 21 and MDS in children younger than 3 years with Down syndrome.<Reference refidx="5"/>  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Congenital amegakaryocytic thrombocytopenia (CAMT):</Strong> Inherited variants in the <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> or <GeneName>CEPBA</GeneName> genes are associated with CAMT.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> Variants in the <GeneName>MPL</GeneName> gene are the underlying genetic cause of CAMT. The risk of developing MDS/AML in patients with CAMT is less than 10%.<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variants:</Strong> Germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> have been reported in patients with MDS/AML in conjunction with monocytopenia, B cell and natural killer cell deficiency, pulmonary alveolar proteinosis, and susceptibility to opportunistic infections.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/> For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000814082" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gata2">GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> or <GeneName>CEPBA</GeneName> variants:</Strong> Inherited variants in the <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> or <GeneName>CEPBA</GeneName> genes are associated with familial MDS/AML.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> For more information, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000813233" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/runx1-hp-pdq">RUNX1-Familial Platelet Disorder</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000813802" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/cebpa-hp-pdq">CEBPA-Associated Familial Acute Myeloid Leukemia</SummaryRef>.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> variants:</Strong> Inherited variants in <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> are associated with familial MDS.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_1206">A retrospective analysis was performed on genomic DNA from peripheral blood mononuclear cell samples from patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplant for MDS and aplastic anemia. The analysis used a capture assay to target variants known to predispose individuals to bone marrow failure and MDS. Among the 46 children aged 18 years and younger with MDS, 10 patients (22%) harbored constitutional variants in hematologic predisposition genes (5 <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>, 1 each of <GeneName>MPL</GeneName>, <GeneName>RTEL1</GeneName>, <GeneName>SBDS</GeneName>, <GeneName>TINF2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>). Only two of these patients were clinically suspected of having genetic variants before their transplants. Children in this study had a higher incidence of genetic variants (22%) than  adults aged 18 to 40 years (8%).<Reference refidx="17"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20507306">Alter BP, Giri N, Savage SA, et al.: Malignancies and survival patterns in the National Cancer Institute inherited bone marrow failure syndromes cohort study. Br J Haematol 150 (2): 179-88, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15059844">Rosenberg PS, Huang Y, Alter BP: Individualized risks of first adverse events in patients with Fanconi anemia. Blood 104 (2): 350-5, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24952648">Ludwig LS, Gazda HT, Eng JC, et al.: Altered translation of GATA1 in Diamond-Blackfan anemia. Nat Med 20 (7): 748-53, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="20456363">Rosenberg PS, Zeidler C, Bolyard AA, et al.: Stable long-term risk of leukaemia in patients with severe congenital neutropenia maintained on G-CSF therapy. Br J Haematol 150 (2): 196-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="12172547">Wechsler J, Greene M, McDevitt MA, et al.: Acquired mutations in GATA1 in the megakaryoblastic leukemia of Down syndrome. Nat Genet 32 (1): 148-52, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="21606161">Liew E, Owen C: Familial myelodysplastic syndromes: a review of the literature. Haematologica 96 (10): 1536-42, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="18173751">Owen C, Barnett M, Fitzgibbon J: Familial myelodysplasia and acute myeloid leukaemia--a review. Br J Haematol 140 (2): 123-32, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="24709246">Ghauri RI, Naveed M, Mannan J: Congenital amegakaryocytic thrombocytopenic purpura (CAMT). J Coll Physicians Surg Pak 24 (4): 285-7, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="24777453">Auer PL, Teumer A, Schick U, et al.: Rare and low-frequency coding variants in CXCR2 and other genes are associated with hematological traits. Nat Genet 46 (6): 629-34, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="20040766">Vinh DC, Patel SY, Uzel G, et al.: Autosomal dominant and sporadic monocytopenia with susceptibility to mycobacteria, fungi, papillomaviruses, and myelodysplasia. Blood 115 (8): 1519-29, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="29146900">Schwartz JR, Ma J, Lamprecht T, et al.: The genomic landscape of pediatric myelodysplastic syndromes. Nat Commun 8 (1): 1557, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="28487541">Schwartz JR, Wang S, Ma J, et al.: Germline SAMD9 mutation in siblings with monosomy 7 and myelodysplastic syndrome. Leukemia 31 (8): 1827-1830, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="29535429">Davidsson J, Puschmann A, Tedgård U, et al.: SAMD9 and SAMD9L in inherited predisposition to ataxia, pancytopenia, and myeloid malignancies. Leukemia 32 (5): 1106-1115, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="27182967">Narumi S, Amano N, Ishii T, et al.: SAMD9 mutations cause a novel multisystem disorder, MIRAGE syndrome, and are associated with loss of chromosome 7. Nat Genet 48 (7): 792-7, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="27259050">Chen DH, Below JE, Shimamura A, et al.: Ataxia-Pancytopenia Syndrome Is Caused by Missense Mutations in SAMD9L. Am J Hum Genet 98 (6): 1146-1158, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="30046003">Wong JC, Bryant V, Lamprecht T, et al.: Germline SAMD9 and SAMD9L mutations are associated with extensive genetic evolution and diverse hematologic outcomes. JCI Insight 3 (14): , 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="27418648">Keel SB, Scott A, Sanchez-Bonilla M, et al.: Genetic features of myelodysplastic syndrome and aplastic anemia in pediatric and young adult patients. Haematologica 101 (11): 1343-1350, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_981"><Title>Molecular Abnormalities</Title><SummarySection id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1929"><Title>Molecular features of myelodysplastic neoplasms (MDS)</Title><Para id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1920">Compared with MDS in adults, pediatric MDS is associated with a distinctive constellation of genetic alterations. In adults, MDS often evolves from clonal hematopoiesis and is characterized by variants in <GeneName>TET2</GeneName>, <GeneName>DNMT3A</GeneName>, <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>. In contrast, variants in these genes are rare in pediatric MDS, while variants in <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>, <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName>, <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName>, <GeneName>ETV6</GeneName>, <GeneName>SETBP1</GeneName>, <GeneName>ASXL1</GeneName>, and RAS/MAPK pathway genes are observed in subsets of children with MDS.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1921">A report of the genomic landscape of pediatric MDS described the results of whole-exome sequencing for 32 pediatric patients with primary MDS and targeted sequencing for another 14 cases.<Reference refidx="1"/> These 46 cases were equally divided between childhood MDS with low blasts (cMDS-LB) (previously called refractory cytopenia of childhood) and childhood MDS with  increased blasts (cMDS-IB) (previously called MDS with excess blasts [MDS-EB)]). The results from the report include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1922" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Variants in RAS/MAPK pathway genes were observed in 43% of primary MDS cases, with variants most commonly involving the <GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName> and <GeneName>NRAS</GeneName> genes. However, variants were also observed in other RAS/MAPK pathway genes (e.g., <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> [non–<GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> V600E], <GeneName>CBL</GeneName>, and <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName>). RAS/MAPK variants were more common in patients with cMDS-IB (65%) than in patients with cMDS-LB (17%). </ListItem><ListItem>Germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> (n = 4) or <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> (n = 4) were observed in 17% of patients with primary MDS, with seven  of eight variants occurring in patients with cMDS-LB. These cases all showed loss of material on chromosome 7. Approximately 40% of patients with deletions of part or all of chromosome 7 had germline <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> or <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> variants. </ListItem><ListItem><GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>  pathogenic variants were observed in three cases (7%), and all cases were confirmed or presumed to be germline. </ListItem><ListItem>Deletions involving chromosome 7 were the most common copy number alteration and were observed in 41% of cases. Loss of part or all of chromosome 7 was most commonly observed in <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> cases (100%) and in cMDS-IB patients with a RAS/MAPK variant (71%).</ListItem><ListItem>In more than 1 of the 46 cases, other genes were altered (<GeneName>SETBP1</GeneName>, <GeneName>ETV6</GeneName>, and <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1923">A second report described the application of a targeted sequencing panel of 105 genes to 50 pediatric patients with MDS (cMDS-LB = 31 and cMDS-IB = 19) and was enriched for cases with monosomy 7 (48%).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> were not included in the gene panel. The second report described the following results:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1924" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Germline <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were observed in 30% of patients, and germline <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> pathogenic variants were observed in 6% of patients.</ListItem><ListItem>Somatic variants were observed in 34% of patients and were more common in patients with cMDS-IB than in patients with cMDS-LB (68% vs. 13%).</ListItem><ListItem>The most commonly altered gene was <GeneName>SETBP1</GeneName> (18%). Less commonly altered genes included <GeneName>ASXL1</GeneName>, <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>, and RAS/MAPK pathway genes (<GeneName>PTPN11</GeneName>, <GeneName>NRAS</GeneName>, <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName>, <GeneName>NF1</GeneName>). Twelve percent of cases had variants in RAS/MAPK pathway genes.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1925">Patients with germline <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants, in addition to MDS, show a wide range of hematopoietic and immune defects as well as nonhematopoietic manifestations.<Reference refidx="3"/> The former defects include monocytopenia with susceptibility to atypical mycobacterial infection and DCML deficiency (loss of dendritic cells, monocytes, and B and natural killer lymphoid cells). The resulting immunodeficiency leads to increased susceptibility to warts, severe viral infections, mycobacterial infections, fungal infections, and human papillomavirus–related cancers. The nonhematopoietic manifestations include deafness and lymphedema. </Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1933">Germline <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were studied in 426 pediatric patients with primary MDS and 82 cases with secondary MDS who were enrolled in consecutive studies of the European Working Group of MDS in Childhood (EWOG-MDS).<Reference refidx="4"/> The study had the following results:</Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1926" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Germline <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were identified in 7% of pediatric patients with primary MDS. While the median age of patients presenting with <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variants was 12.3 years in the EWOG-MDS pediatric population, most cases of germline <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>-related myeloid neoplasms occur during adulthood.<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem><GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variants were more common in patients with cMDS-IB (15%) than in patients with cMDS-LB (4%).</ListItem><ListItem>Among patients with <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variants, 46% presented with cMDS-IB, and 70% showed monosomy 7.</ListItem><ListItem>Familial MDS/acute myeloid leukemia (AML) was identified in 12 of 53 patients with <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variants for whom detailed family histories were available.</ListItem><ListItem>Nonhematologic phenotypes of <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> deficiency were present in 51% of patients with MDS who had <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variants and included deafness (9%), lymphedema/hydrocele (23%), and immunodeficiency (39%).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1927"><GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants are both associated with pediatric MDS cases in which there is an additional loss of all or part of chromosome 7.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>   </Para><Para id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1934">In 2016, <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> was identified as the cause of the MIRAGE syndrome (myelodysplasia, infection, restriction of growth, adrenal hypoplasia, genital phenotypes, and enteropathy), which is associated with early-onset MDS with monosomy 7.<Reference refidx="8"/> Subsequently, variants in <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> were identified in patients with ataxia pancytopenia syndrome (ATXPC; <ExternalRef xref="https://www.omim.org/entry/159550">OMIM 159550</ExternalRef>). <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> variants were also identified as the cause of the myelodysplasia and leukemia syndrome with monosomy 7 (MLSM7; <ExternalRef xref="https://www.omim.org/entry/252270">OMIM 252270</ExternalRef>),<Reference refidx="9"/>  a syndrome first identified in phenotypically normal siblings who developed MDS or AML associated with monosomy 7 during childhood.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1928" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Causative variants in both <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> are gain-of-function variants and enhance the growth-suppressing activity of <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem><ListItem>Both <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> are located at chromosome 7q21.2. Cases of MDS in patients with <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> or <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> variants often show monosomy 7, with the remaining chromosome 7 having wild-type <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> and <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName>. This results in the loss of the enhanced growth-suppressing activity of the altered gene. </ListItem><ListItem>Phenotypically normal patients with <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> or <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> variants and monosomy 7 may progress to develop MDS or AML or, alternatively, may show loss of their monosomy 7 with a return of normal hematopoiesis.<Reference refidx="10"/> The former outcome is associated with the acquisition of variants in genes associated with MDS/AML (e.g., <GeneName>ETV6</GeneName> or <GeneName>SETBP1</GeneName>). The latter outcome is associated with genetic alterations (e.g., revertant variants or copy-neutral loss of heterozygosity with retention of the wild-type allele) that result in normalization of <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> or <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> activity. These observations suggest that monitoring patients with <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName>- or <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName>-related monosomy 7, using clinical sequencing for acquired somatic variants in genes associated with progression to AML, may identify those at high risk of leukemic transformation. Such patients may benefit most from hematopoietic stem cell transplant.<Reference refidx="10"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_sm_CDR0000796536_1935">The presence of an isolated monosomy 7 is the most common cytogenetic abnormality, although it does not appear to portend a poor prognosis, compared with its presence in overt AML.  However, the presence of monosomy 7 in combination with other cytogenetic abnormalities is associated with a poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>  The relatively common abnormalities of -Y, 20q-, and 5q- in adults with MDS are rare in childhood MDS. The presence of cytogenetic abnormalities that are found in AML (t(8;21)(q22;q22.1), inv(16)(p13.1;q22) or t(16;16)(p13.1;q22), and APL with <GeneName>PML</GeneName>::<GeneName>RARA</GeneName> gene fusions) defines disease that should be treated as AML and not MDS, regardless of blast percentage.  The World Health Organization (WHO) notes that whether this should also apply to other recurring genetic abnormalities remains controversial.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="29146900">Schwartz JR, Ma J, Lamprecht T, et al.: The genomic landscape of pediatric myelodysplastic syndromes. Nat Commun 8 (1): 1557, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="27876779">Pastor V, Hirabayashi S, Karow A, et al.: Mutational landscape in children with myelodysplastic syndromes is distinct from adults: specific somatic drivers and novel germline variants. Leukemia 31 (3): 759-762, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25707267">Collin M, Dickinson R, Bigley V: Haematopoietic and immune defects associated with GATA2 mutation. Br J Haematol 169 (2): 173-87, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="26702063">Wlodarski MW, Hirabayashi S, Pastor V, et al.: Prevalence, clinical characteristics, and prognosis of GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndromes in children and adolescents. Blood 127 (11): 1387-97; quiz 1518, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="28637621">Wlodarski MW, Collin M, Horwitz MS: GATA2 deficiency and related myeloid neoplasms. Semin Hematol 54 (2): 81-86, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="29535429">Davidsson J, Puschmann A, Tedgård U, et al.: SAMD9 and SAMD9L in inherited predisposition to ataxia, pancytopenia, and myeloid malignancies. Leukemia 32 (5): 1106-1115, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28487541">Schwartz JR, Wang S, Ma J, et al.: Germline SAMD9 mutation in siblings with monosomy 7 and myelodysplastic syndrome. Leukemia 31 (8): 1827-1830, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="27182967">Narumi S, Amano N, Ishii T, et al.: SAMD9 mutations cause a novel multisystem disorder, MIRAGE syndrome, and are associated with loss of chromosome 7. Nat Genet 48 (7): 792-7, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="27259050">Chen DH, Below JE, Shimamura A, et al.: Ataxia-Pancytopenia Syndrome Is Caused by Missense Mutations in SAMD9L. Am J Hum Genet 98 (6): 1146-1158, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="30046003">Wong JC, Bryant V, Lamprecht T, et al.: Germline SAMD9 and SAMD9L mutations are associated with extensive genetic evolution and diverse hematologic outcomes. JCI Insight 3 (14): , 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="20802024">Göhring G, Michalova K, Beverloo HB, et al.: Complex karyotype newly defined: the strongest prognostic factor in advanced childhood myelodysplastic syndrome. Blood 116 (19): 3766-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="17726160">Haase D, Germing U, Schanz J, et al.: New insights into the prognostic impact of the karyotype in MDS and correlation with subtypes: evidence from a core dataset of 2124 patients. Blood 110 (13): 4385-95, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Arber DA, Vardiman JW, Brunning RD: Acute myeloid leukaemia with recurrent genetic abnormalities. In: Swerdlow SH, Campo E, Harris NL, et al., eds.: WHO Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. 4th ed. International Agency for Research on Cancer, 2008, pp 110-23.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><Title>World Health Organization (WHO) Classification of Bone Marrow and Peripheral Blood Findings for MDS </Title><Para id="_1289">Pediatric myelodysplastic neoplasms (MDS) can be grouped into several general categories, each with distinctive clinical and biological characteristics, as follows:<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_1290" Style="bullet"><ListItem>MDS arising from an inherited bone marrow failure syndrome, such as Fanconi anemia, severe congenital neutropenia, and Shwachman-Diamond syndrome, or a germline predisposition syndrome that confers higher risk of myeloid malignancy.</ListItem><ListItem>MDS arising from severe aplastic anemia.</ListItem><ListItem>Secondary MDS arising from cytotoxic exposures, such as high-dose alkylating chemotherapy.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2132">Primary MDS includes cases of MDS beyond those listed above, acknowledging that some of the cases characterized as primary MDS are also associated with predisposition syndromes.</Para><Para id="_1089">Distinguishing MDS from similar-appearing, reactive causes of dysplasia and/or cytopenias can be difficult.  In general, the finding of ≥10% dysplasia in a cell lineage is a diagnostic criterion for MDS. However, the 2016 WHO guidelines caution that reactive etiologies, rather than clonal ones, may have ≥10% dysplasia and should be excluded, especially when dysplasia is subtle and/or restricted to a single lineage.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_31">The French-American-British (FAB) classification of MDS was not completely applicable to children.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Traditionally, MDS classification systems have been divided into several distinct categories based on the presence of the following:<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  
</Para><ItemizedList id="_709" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Myelodysplasia.</ListItem><ListItem>Types of cytopenia.</ListItem><ListItem>Specific chromosomal abnormalities.</ListItem><ListItem>Percentage of myeloblasts.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_123">A modified classification schema for MDS and myeloproliferative disorders (MPDs) that included subsections on pediatric MDS and MPD was initially proposed in 2003 <Reference refidx="8"/> and then published by the WHO in 2008.<Reference refidx="9"/> A 2016 revision to the WHO classification removed focus on the specific lineage (anemia, thrombocytopenia, or neutropenia) and distinguished cases with dysplasia in single versus multiple lineages. </Para><Para id="_2159">The 5th edition of the WHO Classification of Hematolymphoid Tumors includes a separate category for childhood MDS because MDS in children (aged &lt;18 years) are biologically distinct from those in adults.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> The WHO classification and defining features of MDS are summarized in <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_2177" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">Table 1</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><Table id="_2177"><Title>Table 1.  World Health Organization Classification and Defining Features of Myelodysplastic Neoplasms (MDS)<Superscript>a</Superscript></Title><TGroup Cols="5"><ColSpec ColName="col0" ColNum="1" ColWidth="4.57%"/><ColSpec ColName="col02" ColNum="2" ColWidth="38.44%"/><ColSpec ColName="col1" ColNum="3" ColWidth="17.07%"/><ColSpec ColName="col2" ColNum="4" ColWidth="19.03%"/><ColSpec ColName="col3" ColNum="5" ColWidth="20.86%"/><THead><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">Classification</entry><entry>Blasts</entry><entry>Cytogenetics</entry><entry>Variants</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">MDS with defining genetic abnormalities:</entry><entry/><entry/><entry/></Row></THead><TBody><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">MDS with low blasts and isolated 5q deletion (MDS-5q)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">&lt;5% BM and &lt;2% PB</entry><entry>5q deletion alone, or with 1 other abnormality other than monosomy 7 or 7q deletion</entry><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">MDS with low blasts and <GeneName>SF3B1</GeneName> variant<Superscript>b</Superscript> (MDS-<GeneName>SF3B1</GeneName>)</entry><entry>Absence of 5q deletion, monosomy 7, or complex karyotype</entry><entry><GeneName>SF3B1</GeneName></entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">MDS with biallelic <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> inactivation (MDS-bi<GeneName>TP53</GeneName>)</entry><entry>&lt;20% BM and PB</entry><entry>Usually complex</entry><entry>Two or more <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variants, or 1 <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> variant with evidence of <GeneName>TP53</GeneName> copy number loss or cnLOH</entry></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0"><Strong>MDS, morphologically defined:</Strong></entry><entry/><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">MDS with low blasts (MDS-LB)</entry><entry MoreRows="1">&lt;5% BM and &lt;2% PB</entry><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">MDS, hypoplastic<Superscript>c</Superscript> (MDS-h)</entry><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">MDS with increased blasts (MDS-IB):</entry><entry/><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry>            </entry><entry> MDS-IB1</entry><entry>5%–9% BM or 2%–4% PB</entry><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry>              </entry><entry>MDS-IB2</entry><entry>10%–19% BM or 5%–19% PB or Auer rods</entry><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry>           </entry><entry>MDS with fibrosis (MDS-f)</entry><entry>5%–19% BM; 2%–19% PB</entry><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry Align="Center" NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0"><Strong>Childhood MDS (cMDS):</Strong></entry><entry/><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">cMDS with low blasts (cMDS-LB):</entry><entry/><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry>cMDS-LB, hypoplastic </entry><entry MoreRows="1">&lt;5% BM and &lt;2% PB</entry><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry/><entry>cMDS-LB, not otherwise specified</entry><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col02" NameSt="col0">cMDS with increased blasts (cMDS-IB)</entry><entry>5%–19% BM and 2%–19% PB</entry><entry/><entry/></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0">BM = bone marrow; cnLOH = copy neutral loss of heterozygosity; PB = peripheral blood.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>a</Superscript>Credit: Adapted from Khoury, J.D., Solary, E., Abla, O. et al. The 5th edition of the World Health Organization Classification of Haematolymphoid Tumours: Myeloid and Histiocytic/Dendritic Neoplasms. Leukemia 36, 1703–1719 (2022). <ExternalRef xref="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41375-022-01613-1">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41375-022-01613-1</ExternalRef>.<Reference refidx="12"/> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ExternalRef xref="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons CC BY license</ExternalRef>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>b</Superscript>Detection of ≥15% ring sideroblasts may substitute for <GeneName>SF3B1</GeneName> variant. Acceptable related terminology: MDS with low blasts and ring sideroblasts.</entry></Row><Row><entry NameEnd="col3" NameSt="col0"><Superscript>c</Superscript>By definition, ≤25% bone marrow cellularity, age adjusted.</entry></Row></TBody></TGroup></Table><ItemizedList id="_2176" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Childhood MDS with low blasts (cMDS-LB) includes cases with less than 5% blasts in the bone marrow and less than 2% blasts in the peripheral blood. This group replaces  the prior category of refractory cytopenia of childhood. Patients with cMDS-LB can be further categorized as hypocellular (80% of childhood cases; defined as &lt;25% cellularity, adjusted for age) or not otherwise specified (20% of childhood cases).<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> </ListItem><ListItem>As in the 2016 WHO guidelines, reactive etiologies, rather than clonal ones, may have more than 10% dysplasia and should be excluded. Childhood MDS with increased blasts (cMDS-IB) includes the patients with 5% to 19% blasts in the bone marrow or 2% to 19% blasts in the peripheral blood. When children present with dysplasia and blast count &lt;20% but genetic testing reveals recurrent cytogenetic abnormalities that are usually associated with acute myeloid leukemia (AML), a diagnosis of AML is made, and patients are treated accordingly.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2178">A third classification system, the International Consensus Classification (ICC) of Myeloid Neoplasms and Acute Leukemias, has been published and is primarily used as a tool for clinical trial development instead of clinical use. It further incorporates the growing number of discovered germline predisposition syndromes in children with myeloid neoplasms. For more information, see the sections on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_982" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">Risk Factors</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_981" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">Molecular Abnormalities</SummaryRef>.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_712">The International Prognostic Scoring System (IPSS) is used to determine the risk of progression to AML and the outcome in adult patients with MDS.  When this system was applied to children with MDS or juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML), only a blast count of less than 5% and a platelet count of more than 100 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L were associated with a better survival in MDS, and  a platelet count  of more than 40 × 10<Superscript>9</Superscript>/L predicted a better outcome in JMML.<Reference refidx="16"/> These results suggest that MDS and JMML in children may be significantly different disorders than adult-type MDS. </Para><Para id="_2160">The median survival for children with high-risk MDS remains substantially better than for adults, and the presence of monosomy 7 in children has not had the same adverse prognostic impact as in adults with MDS.<Reference refidx="17"/> However, the presence of monosomy 7 in combination with other cytogenetic abnormalities is associated with a poor prognosis.<Reference refidx="18"/><Reference refidx="19"/>  In one retrospective analysis, only the revised IPSS (R-IPSS)  very poor–risk subgroup, defined as having complex cytogenetics (i.e., &gt;3 abnormalities), was found to have a significant adverse prognostic impact on overall survival and relapse risk after transplant.<Reference refidx="20"/> The relatively common abnormalities of -Y, 20q-, and 5q- in adults with MDS are rare in childhood MDS. Patients with recurrent cytogenetic abnormalities that are found in AML should be treated for AML and not MDS, regardless of blast percentage.  </Para><Para id="_2170">The R-IPSS prognostic groups and associated cytogenetic abnormalities include the following:<Reference refidx="20"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_2171" Style="bullet"><ListItem><Strong>Very good prognostic group:</Strong>	-Y; del(11q).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Good	prognostic group:</Strong> Normal; del(5q); del(20q); del(12p); double	including del(5q).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Intermediate prognostic group:</Strong>	del(7q); +8; i(17q); +19; any other single or double independent clones.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Poor	prognostic group:</Strong> -7; inv(3)/t(3q)/del(3q); double	including -7/del(7q); complex:	3 abnormalities.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Very poor prognostic group:</Strong>	Complex: &gt;3 abnormalities.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2163">The IPSS can help to distinguish low-risk from high-risk MDS. However, its utility in children with MDS is more limited than in adults because many characteristics differ between children and adults.<Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="21"/></Para><Para id="_1291">Genomic characterization of pediatric primary MDS has identified specific subsets defined by alterations in selected genes. For example, germline pathogenic variants in either <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>,<Reference refidx="22"/> <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName>, or <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> <Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="23"/><Reference refidx="24"/> are especially common in children with deletions of all or part of chromosome 7.  Spontaneous remission of MDS in young children with <GeneName>SAMD9</GeneName> or <GeneName>SAMD9L</GeneName> variants led to the discovery that somatic genetic rescue can lead to phenotypic correction.<Reference refidx="25"/> Genomic characterization has also shown that primary MDS in children differs from adult MDS at the molecular level.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> For more information about MDS, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_981" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">Molecular Abnormalities</SummaryRef> section.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="30047423">Wlodarski MW, Sahoo SS, Niemeyer CM: Monosomy 7 in Pediatric Myelodysplastic Syndromes. Hematol Oncol Clin North Am 32 (4): 729-743, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="27069254">Arber DA, Orazi A, Hasserjian R, et al.: The 2016 revision to the World Health Organization classification of myeloid neoplasms and acute leukemia. Blood 127 (20): 2391-405, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="6952920" MedlineID="82206527">Bennett JM, Catovsky D, Daniel MT, et al.: Proposals for the classification of the myelodysplastic syndromes. Br J Haematol 51 (2): 189-99, 1982.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="12368708" MedlineID="22255252">Mandel K, Dror Y, Poon A, et al.: A practical, comprehensive classification for pediatric myelodysplastic syndromes: the CCC system. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 24 (7): 596-605, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="11039659" MedlineID="20492803">Bennett JM: World Health Organization classification of the acute leukemias and myelodysplastic syndrome. Int J Hematol 72 (2): 131-3, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="11790975" MedlineID="21650461">Head DR: Proposed changes in the definitions of acute myeloid leukemia and myelodysplastic syndrome: are they helpful? Curr Opin Oncol 14 (1): 19-23, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="11698274" MedlineID="21554787">Nösslinger T, Reisner R, Koller E, et al.: Myelodysplastic syndromes, from French-American-British to World Health Organization: comparison of classifications on 431 unselected patients from a single institution. Blood 98 (10): 2935-41, 2001.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="12592323" MedlineID="22479947">Hasle H, Niemeyer CM, Chessells JM, et al.: A pediatric approach to the WHO classification of myelodysplastic and myeloproliferative diseases. Leukemia 17 (2): 277-82, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="9">Brunning RD, Porwit A, Orazi A, et al.: Myelodysplastic syndromes/neoplasms overview. In: Swerdlow SH, Campo E, Harris NL, et al., eds.: WHO Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. 4th ed. International Agency for Research on Cancer, 2008, pp 88-93.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="29146900">Schwartz JR, Ma J, Lamprecht T, et al.: The genomic landscape of pediatric myelodysplastic syndromes. Nat Commun 8 (1): 1557, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="27876779">Pastor V, Hirabayashi S, Karow A, et al.: Mutational landscape in children with myelodysplastic syndromes is distinct from adults: specific somatic drivers and novel germline variants. Leukemia 31 (3): 759-762, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="35732831">Khoury JD, Solary E, Abla O, et al.: The 5th edition of the World Health Organization Classification of Haematolymphoid Tumours: Myeloid and Histiocytic/Dendritic Neoplasms. Leukemia 36 (7): 1703-1719, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="37865508">Chisholm KM, Bohling SD: Childhood Myelodysplastic Syndrome. Clin Lab Med 43 (4): 639-655, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="35767897">Arber DA, Orazi A, Hasserjian RP, et al.: International Consensus Classification of Myeloid Neoplasms and Acute Leukemias: integrating morphologic, clinical, and genomic data. Blood 140 (11): 1200-1228, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="36445482">Rudelius M, Weinberg OK, Niemeyer CM, et al.: The International Consensus Classification (ICC) of hematologic neoplasms with germline predisposition, pediatric myelodysplastic syndrome, and juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Virchows Arch 482 (1): 113-130, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="15496981">Hasle H, Baumann I, Bergsträsser E, et al.: The International Prognostic Scoring System (IPSS) for childhood myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) and juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML). Leukemia 18 (12): 2008-14, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="21554264">Hasle H, Niemeyer CM: Advances in the prognostication and management of advanced MDS in children. Br J Haematol 154 (2): 185-95, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="20802024">Göhring G, Michalova K, Beverloo HB, et al.: Complex karyotype newly defined: the strongest prognostic factor in advanced childhood myelodysplastic syndrome. Blood 116 (19): 3766-9, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="17726160">Haase D, Germing U, Schanz J, et al.: New insights into the prognostic impact of the karyotype in MDS and correlation with subtypes: evidence from a core dataset of 2124 patients. Blood 110 (13): 4385-95, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="34508178">Yamamoto S, Kato M, Watanabe K, et al.: Prognostic value of the revised International Prognostic Scoring System five-group cytogenetic abnormality classification for the outcome prediction of hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in pediatric myelodysplastic syndrome. Bone Marrow Transplant 56 (12): 3016-3023, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="15039286">Cutler CS, Lee SJ, Greenberg P, et al.: A decision analysis of allogeneic bone marrow transplantation for the myelodysplastic syndromes: delayed transplantation for low-risk myelodysplasia is associated with improved outcome. Blood 104 (2): 579-85, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="26702063">Wlodarski MW, Hirabayashi S, Pastor V, et al.: Prevalence, clinical characteristics, and prognosis of GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndromes in children and adolescents. Blood 127 (11): 1387-97; quiz 1518, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="27182967">Narumi S, Amano N, Ishii T, et al.: SAMD9 mutations cause a novel multisystem disorder, MIRAGE syndrome, and are associated with loss of chromosome 7. Nat Genet 48 (7): 792-7, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="29535429">Davidsson J, Puschmann A, Tedgård U, et al.: SAMD9 and SAMD9L in inherited predisposition to ataxia, pancytopenia, and myeloid malignancies. Leukemia 32 (5): 1106-1115, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="34621053">Sahoo SS, Pastor VB, Goodings C, et al.: Clinical evolution, genetic landscape and trajectories of clonal hematopoiesis in SAMD9/SAMD9L syndromes. Nat Med 27 (10): 1806-1817, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2179"><Title>Special Considerations for the Treatment of Children With Cancer</Title><Para id="_2179_md_3">Cancer in children and adolescents is rare, although the overall incidence has slowly increased since 1975.<Reference refidx="1"/>    Children and adolescents with cancer should be referred to medical centers that have a multidisciplinary team of cancer specialists with experience treating the cancers that occur during childhood and adolescence.<Reference refidx="2"/>  This multidisciplinary team approach incorporates the skills
of the following pediatric specialists and others to ensure that children receive treatment, supportive care, and rehabilitation
to achieve optimal survival and quality of life:</Para><ItemizedList id="_2179_md_4" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Primary care physicians.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric surgeons.</ListItem><ListItem>Pathologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric radiation
oncologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric medical oncologists and hematologists.</ListItem><ListItem> Rehabilitation
specialists.</ListItem><ListItem>Pediatric oncology nurses.</ListItem><ListItem>Social workers.</ListItem><ListItem>Child-life professionals.</ListItem><ListItem>Psychologists.</ListItem><ListItem>Nutritionists.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2179_md_5">For specific information about supportive care for children and adolescents with cancer, see the summaries on <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/supportive-care">Supportive and Palliative Care</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_2179_md_6">The American Academy of Pediatrics has outlined guidelines for
pediatric cancer centers and their role in the treatment of children and adolescents
with cancer.<Reference refidx="3"/>  At
these centers, clinical trials are available for most  types of cancer that occur in children and adolescents, and the opportunity
to participate is offered to most patients and their families.  Clinical
trials for children and adolescents diagnosed with cancer are generally
designed to compare potentially better therapy with current standard therapy.  Other types of clinical trials test novel therapies when there is no standard therapy for a cancer diagnosis. Most of the progress in identifying curative
therapies for childhood cancers has been achieved through clinical trials.
Information about ongoing clinical trials is available from the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI website</ExternalRef>.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20404250">Smith MA, Seibel NL, Altekruse SF, et al.: Outcomes for children and adolescents with cancer: challenges for the twenty-first century. J Clin Oncol 28 (15): 2625-34, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="28209594">Wolfson J, Sun CL, Wyatt L, et al.: Adolescents and Young Adults with Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia and Acute Myeloid Leukemia: Impact of Care at Specialized Cancer Centers on Survival Outcome. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 26 (3): 312-320, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3">American Academy of Pediatrics: Standards for pediatric cancer centers. Pediatrics  134 (2): 410-4, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/134/2/410">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_984"><Title>Treatment of Childhood MDS</Title><Para id="_1159">Treatment options for children with myelodysplastic neoplasms (MDS) include the following:</Para><OrderedList id="_1160" Style="Arabic"><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_1161" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">Hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT)</SummaryRef> with or without chemotherapy.</ListItem><ListItem><SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_1162" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">Other therapies</SummaryRef>.</ListItem></OrderedList><SummarySection id="_1161"><Title>HSCT</Title><Para id="_508">MDS and associated disorders usually involve a primitive hematopoietic stem cell.  Thus, allogeneic HSCT is considered the optimal approach to treatment for pediatric patients with MDS.  Although matched sibling donor transplant is preferred, similar survival has been noted with well-matched, unrelated cord blood and haploidentical approaches.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_1190">Because survival after HSCT is improved in children with early forms of MDS (refractory anemia), transplant before progression to late MDS or acute myeloid leukemia (AML) should be considered. HSCT should especially be considered when transfusions or other treatments are required, as is usually the case in patients with severe symptomatic cytopenias.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/> The 8-year disease-free survival (DFS) rates for children with various stages of MDS has been reported to be 65% for those treated with HLA matched donor transplants and 40% for those treated with mismatched unrelated donor transplants.<Reference refidx="6"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]  A 3-year DFS rate of 50% was reported with the use of unrelated cord blood donor transplants for children with MDS when the transplants were done after the year 2001.<Reference refidx="7"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810037" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C2</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_985">When making treatment decisions, certain data should be considered, including the question of whether chemotherapy should be used in high-risk MDS.  For example, survival rates as high as 80% have been reported for patients with early-stage MDS who proceeded to transplant within a few months of diagnosis. Additionally, early transplant and no pretransplant chemotherapy have been associated with improved survival in children with MDS.<Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]; <Reference refidx="9"/> A retrospective analysis suggested that azacitidine and venetoclax may have a role in the cytoreduction of disease before HSCT in children with MDS. To date, reports of patients with advanced MDS who received venetoclax-based therapy are anecdotal.<Reference refidx="10"/> While results differ in published series, this regimen might prove to be an effective bridge to HSCT. Azacitidine and venetoclax are being prospectively studied as treatment options for children with MDS. </Para><Para id="_2185">DFS rates have been estimated to be 50% to 70% for pediatric patients with advanced MDS using myeloablative transplant preparative regimens.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/>  While nonmyeloablative preparative transplant regimens are being tested in patients with MDS and AML, such regimens are still investigational for children with these disorders. However, these regimens may be reasonable in the setting of a clinical trial or when a patient’s organ function is compromised in such a way that a myeloablative regimen would be intolerable.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/>; <Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_1076">Evidence (HSCT):</Para><OrderedList id="_1077" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>The Children's Cancer Group 2891 trial accrued patients between 1989 and 1995, including children with
MDS.<Reference refidx="11"/>  There were 77 patients enrolled, including patients with refractory anemia (n = 2), refractory anemia with excess blasts (RAEB) (n = 33),
refractory anemia with excess blasts in transformation (RAEB-T) (n = 26), or AML with antecedent MDS (n = 16). Patients were randomly assigned
to receive either standard or intensively timed induction. Subsequently, patients were allocated to
allogeneic HSCT if there was a suitable family donor or
randomly assigned to either autologous HSCT or chemotherapy.<ItemizedList id="_989" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Patients with
refractory anemia or RAEB had a lower remission rate (45%). Patients with RAEB-T (69%) or AML
with a history of MDS (81%) had similar remission rates compared with those with de novo AML (77%).</ListItem><ListItem>The 6-year survival rates were lower for those with refractory anemia or RAEB (28%) and RAEB-T (30%).</ListItem><ListItem>Patients with AML and
antecedent MDS had a similar outcome to those with de novo AML (survival rates, 50% vs.
45%, respectively).</ListItem><ListItem>Allogeneic HSCT appeared to improve survival (<Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .08).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>Based on the results of the EWOG-MDS 98 study, HSCT was verified as an important  therapeutic approach necessary to achieve prolonged survival. For many patients, HSCT is the sole therapy received.<Reference refidx="19"/> Children with RAEB (n = 53), RAEB-T (n = 29), and myelodysplasia-related AML (n = 15) were treated with an HSCT from various sources (related and unrelated) using the preparative regimen of busulfan, cyclophosphamide, and melphalan. Among this group, 73 were treated without the use of intensive therapy before the HSCT preparative regimen.<ItemizedList id="_2105" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Children with a diagnosis of RAEB and RAEB-T had equivalent event-free survival (EFS) rates of 63% (95% confidence interval [CI], 49%–77%) and 64% (95% CI, 46%–82%), respectively.</ListItem><ListItem>For those with a morphological marrow blast percentage before HSCT of less than 5%, 5% to 20%, or 20% or higher, the EFS rates were 62% (95% CI, 41%–83%), 65% (95% CI, 50%–80%) and 45% (95% CI, 23%–67%), respectively.</ListItem><ListItem>In the entire cohort (n = 97), patients who received low-dose therapy or no therapy before the preparative regimen (n = 73) had similar EFS rates compared with those who received prior intensive chemotherapy (58% [95% CI, 46%–70%] vs. 62% [95% CI, 42%–82%]).</ListItem><ListItem>The outcomes of patients who received unrelated donor cells were like the outcomes of patients who received matched-family donor cells.</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A single-institution retrospective analysis reported on 37 consecutive children with various types of MDS who underwent HSCT using various donor types. Some patients were treated with pre-HSCT chemotherapy (n = 7).<Reference refidx="8"/><ItemizedList id="_2175" Style="bullet"><ListItem>In multivariate analysis, improved DFS was associated with avoiding pre-HSCT chemotherapy (relative risk [RR], 0.30; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .03) and a shorter interval (&lt;140 days) between diagnosis and HSCT (RR, 0.27; <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .02).</ListItem><ListItem> In the 16 children who did not receive pre-HSCT chemotherapy and underwent transplant fewer than 140 days from diagnosis, the 3-year overall survival (OS) and DFS rates were both 80% (95% CI, 51%–93%).</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_510">When analyzing these results, it is important to consider that the subtype RAEB-T is likely to represent patients with overt AML, while refractory anemia and RAEB represents MDS. The World Health Organization classification has omitted the category of RAEB-T, concluding that it is essentially AML.</Para><Para id="_721">Because MDS in children is often associated with inherited predisposition syndromes, reports of transplant in small numbers of patients with these disorders have been documented.  For example, in patients with Fanconi anemia and AML or advanced MDS, the 5-year OS rate has been reported to be 33% to 55%.<Reference refidx="20"/><Reference refidx="21"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]  </Para><Para id="_2104">While some patients with inherited predisposition syndromes require significant modification of their transplant approaches because of excess toxicity (e.g., Fanconi anemia), other syndromes have no detectable excessive toxicity associated with the transplant process.  Inherited <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> deficiency is a good example of the latter.  One study compared HSCT outcomes of 65 children with <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants and MDS with the outcomes of 404 children with MDS and wild-type germline <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>.  Rates of DFS, relapse, and nonrelapse mortality were similar in the two populations.<Reference refidx="22"/> </Para><Para id="_2106">Second transplants have also been used in pediatric patients with MDS/myeloproliferative disorders who experience relapse or graft failure.  The 3-year OS rates were 33% for those who underwent a second transplant after relapse and 57% for those who underwent a second transplant after initial graft failure.<Reference refidx="23"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810035" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C1</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_511">For patients with clinically significant cytopenias, supportive care that includes transfusions and prophylactic antibiotics are considered the standard of care.  The use of hematopoietic growth factors can improve the hematopoietic status, but there are concerns that such treatment could accelerate conversion to AML.<Reference refidx="24"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_1162"><Title>Other Therapies</Title><Para id="_1083">In general, the primary aim for children with newly diagnosed MDS is to rule out AML-associated somatic variants, which would indicate the need to treat according to AML guidelines. Thereafter, the objective should be to provide supportive care while looking for an appropriate donor for HSCT. During this time, close monitoring for the emergence of AML is imperative.<Reference refidx="25"/> Therapies used in adult MDS have not been shown to be beneficial in childhood MDS, likely owing to differences in underlying variant etiologies. </Para><Para id="_2172">Other therapies for MDS that have been studied and may be applicable include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1084" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Agents such as lenalidomide, an analogue of thalidomide, have been tested based on findings that demonstrated increased activity in the bone marrow of patients with MDS.  Lenalidomide has shown the most efficacy in patients with 5q- syndrome, especially those with thrombocytosis. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration approved lenalidomide for use in adults with this finding.<Reference refidx="26"/></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="20400989">Uberti JP, Agovi MA, Tarima S, et al.: Comparative analysis of BU and CY versus CY and TBI in full intensity unrelated marrow donor transplantation for AML, CML and myelodysplasia. Bone Marrow Transplant 46 (1): 34-43, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="20685259">Nemecek ER, Guthrie KA, Sorror ML, et al.: Conditioning with treosulfan and fludarabine followed by allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation for high-risk hematologic malignancies. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 17 (3): 341-50, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="20671124">Shaw PJ, Kan F, Woo Ahn K, et al.: Outcomes of pediatric bone marrow transplantation for leukemia and myelodysplasia using matched sibling, mismatched related, or matched unrelated donors. Blood 116 (19): 4007-15, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="19589484">Parikh SH, Mendizabal A, Martin PL, et al.: Unrelated donor umbilical cord blood transplantation in pediatric myelodysplastic syndrome: a single-center experience. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 15 (8): 948-55, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="28588018">Locatelli F, Merli P, Pagliara D, et al.: Outcome of children with acute leukemia given HLA-haploidentical HSCT after αβ T-cell and B-cell depletion. Blood 130 (5): 677-685, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="20813197">Woodard P, Carpenter PA, Davies SM, et al.: Unrelated donor bone marrow transplantation for myelodysplastic syndrome in children. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 17 (5): 723-8, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21135856">Madureira AB, Eapen M, Locatelli F, et al.: Analysis of risk factors influencing outcome in children with myelodysplastic syndrome after unrelated cord blood transplantation. Leukemia 25 (3): 449-54, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="23152304">Smith AR, Christiansen EC, Wagner JE, et al.: Early hematopoietic stem cell transplant is associated with favorable outcomes in children with MDS. Pediatr Blood Cancer 60 (4): 705-10, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="37369986">Wachter F, Hebert K, Pikman Y, et al.: Impact of cytoreduction and remission status on hematopoietic cell transplantation outcomes in pediatric myelodysplastic syndrome and related disorders. Pediatr Blood Cancer : e30530, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="38701350">Masetti R, Baccelli F, Leardini D, et al.: Venetoclax: a new player in the treatment of children with high-risk myeloid malignancies? Blood Adv 8 (13): 3583-3595, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="11786571" MedlineID="21646457">Woods WG, Barnard DR, Alonzo TA, et al.: Prospective study of 90 children requiring treatment for juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia or myelodysplastic syndrome: a report from the Children's Cancer Group. J Clin Oncol 20 (2): 434-40, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="21492354">Andolina JR, Kletzel M, Tse WT, et al.: Allogeneic hematopoetic stem cell transplantation in pediatric myelodysplastic syndromes: improved outcomes for de novo disease. Pediatr Transplant 15 (3): 334-43, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="21982885">Al-Seraihy A, Ayas M, Al-Nounou R, et al.: Outcome of allogeneic stem cell transplantation with a conditioning regimen of busulfan, cyclophosphamide and low-dose etoposide for children with myelodysplastic syndrome. Hematol Oncol Stem Cell Ther 4 (3): 121-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="21195312">Champlin R: Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for treatment of myleodysplastic syndromes. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 17 (1 Suppl): S6-8, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="20062092">Nelson RP, Yu M, Schwartz JE, et al.: Long-term disease-free survival after nonmyeloablative cyclophosphamide/fludarabine conditioning and related/unrelated allotransplantation for acute myeloid leukemia/myelodysplasia. Bone Marrow Transplant 45 (8): 1300-8, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="20010295">Warlick ED: Optimizing stem cell transplantation in myelodysplastic syndromes: unresolved questions. Curr Opin Oncol 22 (2): 150-4, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="19528536">Pulsipher MA, Boucher KM, Wall D, et al.: Reduced-intensity allogeneic transplantation in pediatric patients ineligible for myeloablative therapy: results of the Pediatric Blood and Marrow Transplant Consortium Study ONC0313. Blood 114 (7): 1429-36, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="24054720">Gao L, Gao L, Gong Y, et al.: Reduced-intensity conditioning therapy with fludarabine, idarubicin, busulfan and cytarabine for allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in acute myeloid leukemia and myelodysplastic syndrome. Leuk Res 37 (11): 1482-7, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="19" PMID="21212791">Strahm B, Nöllke P, Zecca M, et al.: Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for advanced myelodysplastic syndrome in children: results of the EWOG-MDS 98 study. Leukemia 25 (3): 455-62, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="20" PMID="24172081">Mitchell R, Wagner JE, Hirsch B, et al.: Haematopoietic cell transplantation for acute leukaemia and advanced myelodysplastic syndrome in Fanconi anaemia. Br J Haematol 164 (3): 384-95, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="21" PMID="23547077">Ayas M, Saber W, Davies SM, et al.: Allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation for fanconi anemia in patients with pretransplantation cytogenetic abnormalities, myelodysplastic syndrome, or acute leukemia. J Clin Oncol 31 (13): 1669-76, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="22" PMID="34244664">Bortnick R, Wlodarski M, de Haas V, et al.: Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in children and adolescents with GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndrome. Bone Marrow Transplant 56 (11): 2732-2741, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="23" PMID="24976435">Kato M, Yoshida N, Inagaki J, et al.: Salvage allogeneic stem cell transplantation in patients with pediatric myelodysplastic syndrome and myeloproliferative neoplasms. Pediatr Blood Cancer 61 (10): 1860-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="24" PMID="16151466">Zwierzina H, Suciu S, Loeffler-Ragg J, et al.: Low-dose cytosine arabinoside (LD-AraC) vs LD-AraC plus granulocyte/macrophage colony stimulating factor vs LD-AraC plus Interleukin-3 for myelodysplastic syndrome patients with a high risk of developing acute leukemia: final results of a randomized phase III study (06903) of the EORTC Leukemia Cooperative Group. Leukemia 19 (11): 1929-33, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="25" PMID="29438960">Locatelli F, Strahm B: How I treat myelodysplastic syndromes of childhood. Blood 131 (13): 1406-1414, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="26" PMID="12931212">Yazji S, Giles FJ, Tsimberidou AM, et al.: Antithymocyte globulin (ATG)-based therapy in patients with myelodysplastic syndromes. Leukemia 17 (11): 2101-6, 2003.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_217"><Title>Treatment Options Under Clinical Evaluation </Title><Para id="_1147">Information about National Cancer Institute (NCI)–supported clinical trials can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">NCI website</ExternalRef>. For information about clinical trials sponsored by other organizations, see the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov website</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_857"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (12/05/2024)</Title><Para id="_858">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_2186"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_984" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">Treatment of Childhood Myelodysplastic Neoplasms (MDS)</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_2187">Added Wachter et al. as <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_985" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">reference 9</SummaryRef>. Added text to state that a retrospective analysis suggested that azacitidine and venetoclax may have a role in the cytoreduction of disease before hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) in children with MDS. To date, reports of patients with advanced MDS who received venetoclax-based therapy are anecdotal (cited Masetti et al. as reference 10). While results differ in published series, this regimen might prove to be an effective bridge to HSCT. Azacitidine and venetoclax are being prospectively studied as treatment options for children with MDS.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810727#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of childhood myelodysplastic neoplasms. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Childhood Myelodysplastic Neoplasms Treatment are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Alan Scott Gamis, MD, MPH (Children's Mercy Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Karen J. Marcus, MD, FACR (Dana-Farber of Boston Children's Cancer Center and Blood Disorders Harvard Medical School)</ListItem><ListItem>Jessica Pollard, MD (Dana-Farber/Boston Children's Cancer and Blood Disorders Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Michael A. Pulsipher, MD (Huntsman Cancer Institute at University of Utah)</ListItem><ListItem>Rachel E. Rau, MD (University of Washington School of Medicine, Seatle Children’s)</ListItem><ListItem>Lewis B. Silverman, MD (Dana-Farber Cancer Institute/Boston Children's Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Malcolm A. Smith, MD, PhD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Sarah K. Tasian, MD (Children's Hospital of Philadelphia)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Childhood Myelodysplastic Neoplasms Treatment. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/leukemia/hp/child-aml-treatment-pdq/myeloid-dysplastic-neoplasms-treatment-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 38630971]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2024-03-05</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-12-05</DateLastModified></Summary>
