<Summary id="CDR0000810926" SVPC="Yes" SuppressOnThisPageSection="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Causes, risk factors, and prevention</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Using tobacco, especially smoking cigarettes, is a major risk factor for bladder cancer. Learn about tobacco use and other risk factors for bladder cancer and what you can do to lower your risk.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bladder/causes-risk-factors">Bladder Cancer Causes and Risk Factors</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038767">bladder cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Bladder Cancer Causes and Risk Factors</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Bladder Cancer Causes and Risk Factors</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Bladder Cancer Causes and Risk Factors</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">Bladder cancer is caused by certain changes in how <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cells</GlossaryTermRef> function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. There are many risk factors for bladder cancer, but many do not directly cause cancer. Instead, they increase the chance of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">DNA</GlossaryTermRef>  damage in cells that may lead to bladder cancer. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_3">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Some risk factors for bladder cancer, like using tobacco, can be changed. Risk factors also include things people cannot change, like their age and family history. It's important to learn about risk factors for bladder cancer because it can help you make choices that might lower your risk of getting it.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>Risk factors  for bladder cancer</Title><Para id="_5">In the United States, bladder cancer occurs more often in men than in women, and more often in White individuals than in Black individuals. Bladder cancer can be diagnosed at any age, but the risk increases as a person gets older.</Para><Para id="_6">Using tobacco, especially smoking cigarettes, is a major  risk factor for bladder cancer. Tobacco contains harmful chemicals called carcinogens. When you use tobacco, these chemicals get absorbed into the bloodstream, are filtered by the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef>, and then collect in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046642" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urine</GlossaryTermRef>. This exposes your bladder to high levels of these chemicals, which can damage  the DNA in the cells lining your bladder. <ExternalRef xref="https://smokefree.gov/">Learn about different tools to help you quit smoking and how to use them.</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_7">Other risk factors for bladder cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_8" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family history</GlossaryTermRef> of bladder cancer</ListItem><ListItem>having certain changes in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genes</GlossaryTermRef> that are linked to bladder cancer, such as <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000661987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">HRAS</GlossaryTermRef></Emphasis>, <Emphasis>RB1</Emphasis>, <Emphasis><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803426" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">PTEN</GlossaryTermRef>/MMAC1</Emphasis>, <Emphasis>NAT2</Emphasis>, and <Emphasis>GSTM1</Emphasis></ListItem><ListItem>being exposed to paints, dyes, metals, or petroleum products in the workplace</ListItem><ListItem>past treatment with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> or with certain <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639945" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anticancer</GlossaryTermRef> drugs, such as <DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef> or <DrugRef href="CDR0000686471" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ifosfamide">ifosfamide</DrugRef>   </ListItem><ListItem>taking the Chinese herb <Emphasis>Aristolochia fangchi</Emphasis></ListItem><ListItem>drinking water from a well that has high levels of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044303" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">arsenic</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>drinking water that has been treated with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044424" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chlorine</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>having a bladder <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045364" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infection</GlossaryTermRef> caused by a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044310" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">parasite</GlossaryTermRef> called <Emphasis>Schistosoma haematobium</Emphasis>, which is common in Africa and the Middle East but rare in the United States</ListItem><ListItem>using urinary <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheters</GlossaryTermRef> for a long time</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_9">Having one or more of these risk factors does not necessarily mean you will get bladder cancer. Many people with risk factors never develop bladder cancer, while others with no known risk factors do. Talk with your doctor if you think you might be at risk of bladder cancer. Bladder cancer <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811026" url="/types/bladder/screening">screening</SummaryRef>  options may be available to you.</Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-02-16</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
