<Summary id="CDR0000811027" SVPC="Yes" SuppressOnThisPageSection="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Diagnosis</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Learn about the tests that are used to diagnose and stage bladder cancer.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bladder/diagnosis">Bladder Cancer Diagnosis</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038767">bladder cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer diagnosis</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Bladder Cancer Diagnosis</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Bladder Cancer Diagnosis</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Bladder Cancer Diagnosis</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">If you have symptoms or lab test results that suggest <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, your doctor will need to find out if they’re due to cancer or another condition. Your doctor may</Para><ItemizedList id="_3" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>ask about your personal and family medical history to learn more about your symptoms and possible <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">risk factors</GlossaryTermRef> for bladder cancer</ListItem><ListItem>ask for a sample of your urine so it can be checked in the lab for blood, abnormal cells, or infection</ListItem><ListItem> do a physical exam, which for women, may include a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322873" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvic exam</GlossaryTermRef>, to check for signs of cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_4">Depending on your symptoms, medical history, and results of your urine lab tests and physical exam, your doctor may recommend more tests to find out if you have bladder cancer, and if so, its extent (stage).</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>Tests to diagnose bladder cancer</Title><Para id="_6">The following tests and procedures are used to diagnose bladder cancer. The results will also help you and your doctor plan treatment.</Para><SummarySection id="_7"><Title>Cystoscopy</Title><Para id="_8">Cystoscopy is a procedure in which the doctor looks inside the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> and urethra (the tube that carries urine out of your body) to check for abnormal areas. A cystoscope is slowly inserted through the urethra into the bladder to allow the doctor to see inside. A cystoscope is a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing. It may also have a tool to remove very small bladder tumors or tissue samples for biopsy. Cystoscopy helps to diagnose, and sometimes treat, bladder cancer and other conditions.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000649521" type="image/jpeg" alt="Cystoscopy; drawing shows a side view of the lower pelvis containing the bladder, uterus, vagina, rectum, and anus. A cystoscope (a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing) is shown passing through the urethra and into the bladder. Fluid is used to fill the bladder. An inset shows a woman lying on an examination table with her knees bent and legs apart. She is covered by a drape. The doctor is looking at an image of the inner wall of the bladder on a computer monitor to check for abnormal areas." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_9"><Caption language="en">Cystoscopy. A cystoscope (a thin, tube-like instrument with a light and a lens for viewing) is inserted through the urethra into the bladder. Fluid is used to fill the bladder. The doctor looks at an image of the inner wall of the bladder on a computer monitor to check for abnormal areas.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_11">A biopsy is usually done during a cystoscopy procedure. Biopsy is a procedure in which a sample of cells or tissue is removed from the bladder so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for signs of cancer. It may be possible to remove the entire tumor at the time of the biopsy.</Para><Para id="_12">Talk with your doctor to learn what to expect during and after your cystoscopy and biopsy. Some people have blood in the urine or discomfort and a burning sensation while urinating for a day or two.</Para><Para id="_13">To learn about the type of information that can be found in a pathologist’s report about the cells or tissue removed during a biopsy, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/diagnosis/pathology-reports-fact-sheet">Pathology Reports</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><Title>Computed tomography (CT) urogram or intravenous pyelogram (IVP)</Title><Para id="_15">CT urogram is a test that takes a CT scan of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urinary tract</GlossaryTermRef> using a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000409764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">contrast dye</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. To begin the procedure, a CT machine takes a series of detailed pictures of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef>. The contrast dye is then injected, and another CT scan of the kidneys, bladder, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046638" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ureters</GlossaryTermRef> is done. About 10 minutes later, a final scan is taken as the contrast dye drains from the kidneys into the bladder. CT urogram also captures detailed pictures of nearby bones, soft tissues, and blood vessels. This allows the doctor to see how well your urinary tract is working and to check for signs of disease.</Para><Para id="_16">IVP is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000804077" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">x-ray imaging</GlossaryTermRef> test of your urinary tract. After a contrast dye is injected into a vein, a series of x-ray pictures of the kidneys, ureters, and bladder are taken to find out if cancer is present in these organs. As the contrast dye moves through the kidneys, ureters, and bladder, more x-ray pictures are taken at specific times. This allows your doctor to see how well your urinary tract is working and to check for signs of disease.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_17"><Title>Urine tumor marker test</Title><Para id="_18">Urinary tumor markers are substances found in the urine that are either made by bladder cancer cells or that the body makes in response to bladder cancer. For this test, a sample of urine is checked in the lab to detect the presence of these substances. Urine tumor marker tests may be used to help diagnose some types of bladder cancer.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><Title>Tests to stage bladder cancer</Title><Para id="_21">If you’re diagnosed with bladder cancer, you will be referred to a urologic oncologist. This is a doctor who specializes in diagnosing and treating cancers of the male and female urinary tract and the male <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046564" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">reproductive</GlossaryTermRef> organs. They will recommend tests to determine the extent of cancer. Sometimes the cancer is only in the bladder. Or, it may have spread from the bladder to other parts of the body. The process of learning the extent of cancer in the body is called staging. It is important to know the stage of the bladder cancer to plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_22">For information about a specific stage of bladder cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811057" url="/types/bladder/stages">Bladder Cancer Stages</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_23">The following imaging tests may be used to determine the bladder cancer stage.</Para><SummarySection id="_24"><Title>Computed tomography (CT) scan</Title><Para id="_25">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046033" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">CT scan</GlossaryTermRef> uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body from different angles. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_27"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the bladder. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging. Images may be taken at three different times after the dye is injected, to get the best picture of abnormal areas in the bladder. This is called triple-phase MRI.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_28"><Title>Chest x-ray</Title><Para id="_29">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chest x-ray</GlossaryTermRef> is an x-ray of the organs and bones inside the chest. An x-ray is a type of high-energy <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the chest.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><Title>Bone scan</Title><Para id="_31">A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046499" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone scan</GlossaryTermRef> is a procedure that checks to see if there are rapidly dividing cells, such as cancer cells, in the bone. A very small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> material is injected into a vein and travels through the bloodstream. The radioactive material collects in the bones with cancer and is detected by a scanner.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_32"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_33">Some people may want to get a second opinion to confirm their bladder cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you choose to seek a second opinion, you will need to get important medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans before giving a recommendation. The doctor who gives the second opinion may agree with your first doctor, suggest changes or another approach, or provide more information about your cancer.</Para><Para id="_34">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI’s Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor, hospital, or getting a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-02-16</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-03-01</DateLastModified></Summary>
