<Summary id="CDR0000811057" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Stages</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Stage refers to the extent of your cancer, such as how large the tumor is and if it has spread. Learn about bladder cancer stages, an important factor in deciding your treatment plan. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bladder/stages">Bladder Cancer Stages</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038767">bladder cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer stages</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Bladder Cancer Stages</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Bladder Cancer Stages</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Bladder Cancer Stages</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef>, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It’s important to know the stage of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder cancer</GlossaryTermRef> to plan treatment.  </Para><Para id="_3">There are several different <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging systems</GlossaryTermRef> for cancer. Bladder cancer is usually staged using the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef>. Your cancer may be described by this staging system in your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>. Based on the TNM results, a stage is assigned to your cancer, such as stage I, stage II, stage III, or stage IV (may also be written as stage 1, stage 2, stage 3, or stage 4). When talking with you about your cancer, your doctor may describe it as one of these stages.  </Para><Para id="_4">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_5">Learn about the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811027#_19" url="/types/bladder/diagnosis">tests and procedures doctors use to stage bladder cancer</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>Stage 0 (noninvasive papillary carcinoma and carcinoma in situ)  </Title><MediaLink ref="CDR0000747928" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage 0 bladder cancer (noninvasive bladder cancer); drawing shows the bladder, lumen (the space where urine collects), ureter, prostate, and urethra. The first inset shows stage 0a (also called noninvasive papillary carcinoma) on the inner lining of the bladder. The second inset shows stage 0is (also called carcinoma in situ) on the inner lining of the bladder. Also shown are the connective tissue and muscle layers of the bladder and the layer of fat around the bladder." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_7"><Caption language="en">Stage 0 bladder cancer (noninvasive bladder cancer). Cancer cells are found in tissue lining the inside of the bladder but have not invaded into the bladder wall. Stage 0a (also called noninvasive papillary carcinoma) may look like long, thin growths extending into the bladder lumen (the space where urine collects). Stage 0is (also called carcinoma in situ) is a flat tumor on the tissue lining the inside of the bladder. </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_8">Stage 0 refers to noninvasive bladder cancer. This means that cancer cells are found in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046683" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tissue</GlossaryTermRef> lining the inside of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> but have not invaded the bladder wall. Stage 0 is divided into stages 0a and 0is, depending on the type of tumor: </Para><ItemizedList id="_9" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Stage 0a</Strong> is also called noninvasive papillary carcinoma, which may look like long, thin growths extending into the bladder lumen (the space where urine collects). Stage 0a can be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">low grade</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386205" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">high grade</GlossaryTermRef>, depending on how <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044636" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abnormal</GlossaryTermRef> the cells look under the microscope (see the section on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811057#_33" url="/types/bladder/stages">Bladder cancer grade</SummaryRef>).</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Stage 0is</Strong> is also called carcinoma in situ, which is a flat tumor on the tissue lining the inside of the bladder. Stage 0is is always high grade (see the section on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811057#_33" url="/types/bladder/stages">Bladder cancer grade</SummaryRef>). </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_10">Learn about treatment for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811128#_3" url="/types/bladder/treatment/by-stage">stage 0 bladder cancer</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><Title>Stage I bladder cancer </Title><Para id="_12">Stage I is a form of non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer that has spread into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044013" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">connective tissue</GlossaryTermRef> but has not reached the muscle layers of the bladder.  </Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000749301" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage I bladder cancer (non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer); drawing shows the bladder, ureter, prostate, and urethra. An inset shows cancer in the inner lining of the bladder and in the layer of connective tissue next to it. Also shown are the muscle layers of the bladder and the layer of fat around the bladder." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_13"><Caption language="en">Stage I bladder cancer (non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer). Cancer has spread into the connective tissue but has not reached the muscle layers of the bladder.</Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_14">Learn about treatment for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811128#_3" url="/types/bladder/treatment/by-stage">stage I bladder cancer</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><Title>Stage II bladder cancer </Title><Para id="_16">Stage II may also be described as muscle-invasive bladder cancer. In stage II, cancer has spread through the connective tissue into the muscle layers of the bladder.  </Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000749308" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage II bladder cancer (muscle-invasive bladder cancer); drawing shows the bladder, ureter, prostate, and urethra. An inset shows cancer in the inner lining of the bladder and in the layer of connective tissue and the muscle layers of the bladder. Also shown is the layer of fat around the bladder." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_17"><Caption language="en">Stage II bladder cancer (muscle-invasive bladder cancer). Cancer has spread through the connective tissue into the muscle layers of the bladder. </Caption></MediaLink><Para id="_18">Learn about treatment for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811128#_14" url="/types/bladder/treatment/by-stage">stage II bladder cancer</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_19"><Title>Stage III bladder cancer </Title><Para id="_20">Stage III may also be described as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045955" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">locally advanced</GlossaryTermRef> bladder cancer. Stage III is divided into stages IIIA and IIIB. </Para><ItemizedList id="_21" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In stage IIIA <ItemizedList id="_22" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>cancer has grown all the way through the bladder muscles and bladder wall into the layer of fat surrounding the bladder and may have spread to the reproductive organs (<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seminal vesicles</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef>) but has not spread to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>; or </ListItem><ListItem>cancer has spread to one lymph node in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef> that is not near the major <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000440100" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">arteries</GlossaryTermRef> in the pelvis, called the common iliac arteries. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000749310" type="image/jpeg" alt="Two-panel drawing showing stage IIIA bladder cancer in a male (left panel) and a female (right panel); both panels show cancer in the bladder and in (a) the layer of fat around the bladder and (b) one lymph node in the pelvis. Also shown are the right and left common iliac arteries, the prostate (left panel), and the uterus (right panel)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_23"><Caption language="en">Stage IIIA bladder cancer. Cancer (a) has grown all the way through the bladder muscles and bladder wall into the layer of fat around the bladder and may have spread to the prostate and/or seminal vesicles in men or the uterus and/or vagina in women but has not spread to lymph nodes; or (b) has spread to one lymph node in the pelvis that is not near the common iliac arteries.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IIIB, cancer has spread to more than one lymph node in the pelvis that is not near the common iliac arteries or to at least one lymph node that is near the common iliac arteries.  <MediaLink ref="CDR0000791435" type="image/jpeg" alt="Two-panel drawing showing stage IIIB bladder cancer in a male (left panel) and a female (right panel); both panels show cancer in the bladder and in (a) more than one lymph node in the pelvis that is not near the common iliac artery and (b) one lymph node near the common iliac artery. Also shown are the right and left common iliac arteries, the prostate (left panel), and the uterus (the right panel)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_24"><Caption language="en">Stage IIIB bladder cancer. Cancer has spread to (a) more than one lymph node in the pelvis that is not near the common iliac arteries; or (b) at least one lymph node that is near the common iliac arteries.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_25">Learn about treatment for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811128#_14" url="/types/bladder/treatment/by-stage">stage III bladder cancer</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_26"><Title>Stage IV bladder cancer </Title><Para id="_27">Stage IV is divided into stages IVA and IVB. </Para><ItemizedList id="_28" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In stage IVA <ItemizedList id="_29" Style="dash">
     <ListItem>cancer has spread to the abdominal wall or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000410631" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvic wall</GlossaryTermRef>; or </ListItem><ListItem>cancer has spread to lymph nodes that are above the major arteries in the pelvis, called the common iliac arteries.  </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>In stage IVB, cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the lung, bone, or liver. <MediaLink ref="CDR0000749892" type="image/jpeg" alt="Stage IVA and IVB bladder cancer; drawing shows cancer that has spread from the bladder to (a) the abdominal or pelvic wall and (b) lymph nodes above the common iliac arteries. Also shown is cancer that has spread to (c) other parts of the body, including the lung, liver, and bone." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_30"><Caption language="en">Stage IVA and IVB bladder cancer. In stage IVA, cancer has spread to (a) the abdominal or pelvic wall; or (b) lymph nodes above the common iliac arteries. In stage IVB, cancer has spread to (c) other parts of the body, such as the lung, liver, or bone.</Caption></MediaLink></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_31">Stage IV bladder cancer is also called metastatic bladder cancer. Metastatic cancer happens when cancer cells travel through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045764" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymphatic system</GlossaryTermRef> or blood and form tumors in other parts of the body. The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if bladder cancer spreads to the lung, the cancer cells in the lung are actually bladder cancer cells. The disease is called metastatic bladder cancer, not lung cancer. Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/metastatic-cancer">Metastatic Cancer: When Cancer Spreads</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_32">Learn about treatment for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811128#_22" url="/types/bladder/treatment/by-stage">stage IV bladder cancer</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_33"><Title>Bladder cancer grade </Title><Para id="_34">Cancer grade describes how abnormal the bladder cancer cells look under a microscope and how quickly the cancer cells are likely to grow and spread. Your doctor uses grade and other factors about your cancer, such as its stage, to form a treatment plan and in some cases, to estimate your <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045849" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prognosis</GlossaryTermRef>. </Para><ItemizedList id="_35" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Low-grade bladder cancer</Strong> cells look more like normal cells and tend to grow and spread more slowly than high-grade cancer cells.  </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>High-grade bladder cancer</Strong> tends to grow and spread more quickly than low-grade bladder cancer. High-grade cancers usually have a worse prognosis than low-grade cancers and may need treatment right away or treatment that is more aggressive.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_36">To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/diagnosis/tumor-grade">Tumor Grade</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_37"><Title>Recurrent bladder cancer </Title><Para id="_38">Recurrent bladder cancer is cancer that has recurred (come back) after it has been treated. Bladder cancer tends to recur after treatment, even when it is noninvasive at the time of diagnosis. Low-grade bladder cancer mainly recurs in the bladder lining. High-grade bladder cancer is more likely to have spread to the muscle layers or other parts of the body when it recurs. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned in your body, if it has spread, and how far. The type of treatment that you have for recurrent bladder cancer will depend on where it has come back.</Para><Para id="_39">Learn more in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_40">Learn about treatment for <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811128#_320" url="/types/bladder/treatment/by-stage">recurrent bladder cancer</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-02-16</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-16</DateLastModified></Summary>
