<Summary id="CDR0000811132" SVPC="Yes" SuppressOnThisPageSection="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Supportive care</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Coping with bladder cancer and the effects of treatment can feel overwhelming. Learn about resources to help you cope and gain a sense of control.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bladder/coping">Coping with Bladder Cancer</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038767">bladder cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>coping with bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>coping with bladder cancer treatment</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Coping with Bladder Cancer </SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Coping with Bladder Cancer</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Coping with Bladder Cancer</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">When you first learn that you have bladder cancer, you may wonder how you’re going to cope with the upcoming changes in your life. One step you can take is to be informed of the physical and emotional changes that may occur and what resources are available to help you. Talking with your health care team about your concerns can give you a greater sense of control. Family and friends  can also be  important sources of support. </Para><Para id="_3">For resources on the common physical side effects of treatment for bladder cancer, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811102" url="/types/bladder/treatment">Bladder Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>. For help with emotional side effects, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/feelings">Emotions and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_55">For help after your cancer treatment has ended, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/survivorship">Cancer Survivorship</ExternalRef> and our booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/facing-forward">Facing Forward: Life After Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><Title>Adjusting after urostomy </Title><Para id="_14">For those who have  a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045104" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stoma</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046644" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urostomy</GlossaryTermRef> bag, getting used to them takes time. Some people need to learn how to use a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheter</GlossaryTermRef> to empty their bladder, which is another big change. And if you have incontinence or problems controlling your bladder, it can be frustrating to deal with.  </Para><Para id="_15">Know that you aren't alone in how you feel. Adjusting to these changes can be hard. But, over time, many people are able to do a lot of what they did before surgery.  Support from family members and your health care team can help you get used to life after urostomy surgery. Ask your nurse for resources and support groups that may be helpful. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ostomy.org/emotional-issues/">Patient’s Concerns About Surgery</ExternalRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Self-image and sexual problems</Title><Para id="_10">Body changes may affect your self-image and sex life after treatment. Some treatments for bladder cancer, including <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, surgery, or certain medicines, can cause short-term or long-term problems with sex. For example, having a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045986" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cystectomy</GlossaryTermRef> may affect the nerves and make it harder for men to have an erection. Women may have pain during sex or problems with lubrication and orgasm.  </Para><Para id="_11">It’s important to discuss any issues and concerns you have about sex with your health care team before treatment. Knowing your thoughts ahead of time may help them plan your treatment.   </Para><Para id="_12">Learn more about the sexual problems some cancer treatments can cause and ways to cope in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/sexuality-women">Sexual Health Issues in Women with Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/sexuality-men">Sexual Health Issues in Men with Cancer</ExternalRef>. For help communicating your feelings, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/self-image">Self-Image and Sexuality</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>The stress of follow-up care </Title><Para id="_51">It’s common for bladder cancer to come back, even after successful treatment. As a result, it is important for people who have been treated for bladder cancer to visit their doctor regularly to get certain follow-up exams or tests. This can be hard for a number of reasons, such as:</Para><ItemizedList id="_56" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Planning and scheduling these appointments can be stressful and time-consuming. </ListItem><ListItem>Waiting for test results can cause <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000430405" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anxiety</GlossaryTermRef> and an ongoing fear of recurrence.</ListItem><ListItem>The added costs of things such as copays, medicines, and parking and transportation fees only add to the stress.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_57">For information about how to prepare for follow-up appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/survivorship/follow-up-care">Follow-Up Medical Care</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_52">For tips on how to deal with the fear of cancer coming back, see the section <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/survivorship/new-normal">Coping with Fear of Recurrence</ExternalRef> on our New Normal page.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_53"><Title>Cost of cancer treatment </Title><Para id="_54">Cancer is one of the most costly diseases to treat in the United States. Even if you have health insurance, you may face major financial challenges and need help dealing with the costs of bladder cancer treatment.  Having cancer may also make it hard for you to work and pay your bills. The problems a person has related to the cost of treatment is known as financial toxicity. For ways to cope, see  <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs">Managing Costs and Medical Information</ExternalRef>. To learn about financial toxicity and find out if you are at risk, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000783881" url="/about-cancer/managing-care/track-care-costs/financial-toxicity-pdq">Financial Toxicity (Financial Distress) and Cancer Treatment</SummaryRef>. </Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-02-16</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2023-04-27</DateLastModified></Summary>
