<Summary id="CDR0000811102" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Learn about the different ways bladder cancer can be treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/bladder/treatment">Bladder Cancer Treatment</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038767">bladder cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>bladder cancer treatment</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Bladder Cancer Treatment</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Bladder Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Bladder Cancer Treatment</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">Different types of treatment are available for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444968" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. You and your cancer care team will work together to decide your treatment plan, which may include more than one type of treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774694" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">grade</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer, your overall health, and your preferences. Your plan will include information about your cancer, the goals of treatment, your treatment options and the possible side effects, and the expected length of treatment.  </Para><Para id="_3">It will be helpful to talk with your cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect. Some things you'll want to learn about include what you need to do before treatment begins, how you'll feel while going through it, and what kind of help you will need. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor About Your Treatment</ExternalRef>.  
For treatment by stage, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811128" url="/types/bladder/treatment/by-stage">Treatment of Bladder Cancer by Stage</SummaryRef>. 
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_5">Surgery is the main treatment for bladder cancer. The type of surgery depends on where the cancer is located.  
Other treatments may be given in addition to surgery: 
</Para><ItemizedList id="_6" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Treatment given before surgery is called preoperative therapy or neoadjuvant therapy. Chemotherapy may be given before surgery to shrink the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046634" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tumor</GlossaryTermRef> and reduce the amount of tissue that needs to be removed during surgery.  </ListItem><ListItem>Treatment given after surgery, to lower the risk that the cancer will come back, is called adjuvant therapy. After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen, some patients may be given chemotherapy, radiation therapy, immunotherapy, and/or targeted therapy to kill any cancer cells that are left.  </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_7">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery">Surgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para><Para id="_8">The types of surgery done to treat bladder cancer are:  </Para><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Transurethral resection (TUR) with fulguration </Title><Para id="_10">During TUR with fulguration, the doctor inserts a cystoscope (a thin lighted tube) into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046501" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bladder</GlossaryTermRef> through the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046640" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urethra</GlossaryTermRef>. A tool with a small wire loop on the end is then used to remove the cancer or to burn the tumor away with high-energy electricity. This is known as fulguration. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><Title>Partial cystectomy </Title><Para id="_12">Partial cystectomy is surgery to remove part of the bladder. This may be done for patients who have a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000386213" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">low-grade</GlossaryTermRef> tumor that has invaded the wall of the bladder but is limited to one area of the bladder. Because only a part of the bladder is removed, patients are able to urinate normally after recovering from this surgery. This is also called segmental cystectomy. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><Title>Radical cystectomy with urinary diversion </Title><Para id="_14">Radical cystectomy is surgery to remove the bladder and any <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef> and nearby organs that contain cancer. This surgery may be done when the bladder cancer invades the muscle layers or when non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer involves a large part of the bladder: </Para><ItemizedList id="_15" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>In men, the nearby organs that are removed are the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046539" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">prostate</GlossaryTermRef> and the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046576" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">seminal vesicles</GlossaryTermRef>.  </ListItem><ListItem>In women, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef>, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046687" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">ovaries</GlossaryTermRef>, and part of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046646" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">vagina</GlossaryTermRef> are removed.  
</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_16">Sometimes, when the cancer has spread outside the bladder and can't be completely removed, surgery to remove only the bladder may be done to reduce urinary symptoms caused by the cancer.</Para><Para id="_17">When the bladder must be removed, the surgeon performs a procedure called urinary diversion to create another way for the body to store and pass urine. It may involve redirecting urine into the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046462" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">colon</GlossaryTermRef>, using <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045637" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">catheters</GlossaryTermRef> to drain the bladder, or making an opening in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045070" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">abdomen</GlossaryTermRef> that connects to a bag outside the body for collecting urine. To learn more, visit the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases page on <ExternalRef xref="https://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/urologic-diseases/urinary-diversion">Urinary Diversion</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><Title>Radiation therapy  </Title><Para id="_19">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Bladder cancer is sometimes treated with external beam radiation therapy. This type of radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation therapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment, such as chemotherapy. </Para><Para id="_20">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_21"><Title>Chemotherapy  </Title><Para id="_22">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment. The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the type and stage of the cancer being treated. </Para><SummarySection id="_23"><Title>Systemic chemotherapy </Title><Para id="_24">Systemic chemotherapy for bladder cancer is when chemotherapy drugs are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream to reach cancer cells throughout the body.  Systemic chemotherapy drugs that may be used to treat bladder cancer are: </Para><ItemizedList id="_25" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000542867" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/doxorubicinhydrochloride">doxorubicin</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537894" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/fluorouracil">fluorouracil</DrugRef> (5-FU) </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000495426" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/gemcitabinehydrochloride">gemcitabine</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000586940" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/methotrexate-sodium">methotrexate</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000712481" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/mitomycin">mitomycin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000502187" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/paclitaxel">paclitaxel</DrugRef> </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000688288" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vinblastinesulfate">vinblastine</DrugRef> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_26">Combinations of these drugs may be used. Other chemotherapy drugs not listed here may also be used. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_27"><Title>Intravesical chemotherapy </Title><Para id="_28">For bladder cancer, chemotherapy may be intravesical, meaning it is put into the bladder through a tube inserted into the urethra. Intravesical treatments flush the bladder with drugs that kill cancer cells that remain after surgery. This lowers the chance of the cancer coming back.  </Para><Para id="_29">Mitomycin and gemcitabine are two chemotherapy drugs given as intravesical chemotherapy to treat bladder cancer. These drugs can also be given systemically. 
</Para><Para id="_52">To learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_30"><Title>Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_31">Immunotherapy helps a person's immune system fight cancer. Your doctor may suggest <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000805418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">biomarker tests</GlossaryTermRef> to help predict your response to certain immunotherapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef>.  
</Para><SummarySection id="_53"><Title>Systemic immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_54">Systemic immunotherapy drugs used to treat urothelial cancer (a type of bladder cancer) include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_55" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000781156" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/atezolizumab">atezolizumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000787910" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/avelumab">avelumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000767749" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nivolumab">nivolumab</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000764622" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/pembrolizumab">pembrolizumab</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_56">These drugs work in more than one way to kill cancer cells. They are also considered <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef> because they target specific changes or substances in cancer cells (visit the section on <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811102#_37" url="/types/bladder/treatment">Targeted therapy</SummaryRef>).  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_57"><Title>Intravesical immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_58"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045987" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">BCG (bacillus Calmette-Guérin)</GlossaryTermRef>, <DrugRef href="CDR0000811177" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nadofaragene-firadenovec-vncg">nadofaragene firadenovec-vncg</DrugRef>, and <DrugRef href="CDR0000815439" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/nogapendekin-alfa-inbakicept-pmln">nogapendekin alfa inbakicept-pmln</DrugRef> are intravesical immunotherapy drugs used to treat bladder cancer. They are given in a solution that is placed directly into the bladder using a catheter (thin tube). Intravesical treatments flush the bladder with drugs that kill cancer cells that remain after surgery. This lowers the chance of the cancer coming back.</Para></SummarySection><EmbeddedVideo id="_35" ref="CDR0000795516" hosting="youtube" unique_id="zKgCtZ4Sz7w" language="en" audience="Patients" template="Video75NoTitle"><VideoTitle>nonspecific immune stimulation</VideoTitle><Caption language="en">Immunotherapy uses the body’s immune system to fight cancer. This animation explains one type of immunotherapy called nonspecific immune stimulation that is used to treat cancer.
</Caption></EmbeddedVideo><Para id="_36">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy/side-effects">Immunotherapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_37"><Title>Targeted therapy </Title><Para id="_38">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to block the action of specific <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046081" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">enzymes</GlossaryTermRef>, proteins, or other molecules involved in the growth and spread of cancer cells. Your doctor may suggest biomarker tests to help predict your response to certain targeted therapy drugs. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/biomarker-testing-cancer-treatment">Biomarker Testing for Cancer</ExternalRef>.  
</Para><Para id="_51">Targeted therapies used to treat bladder cancer include: 
</Para><ItemizedList id="_39" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000800196" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/enfortumabvedotin-ejfv">enfortumab vedotin</DrugRef>  </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000797598" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/erdafitinib">erdafitinib</DrugRef>  </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000760376" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ramucirumab">ramucirumab</DrugRef>   </ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000801533" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/sacituzumabgovitecan-hziy">sacituzumab govitecan-hziy</DrugRef> </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_40">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_41"><Title>Clinical trials </Title><Para id="_41_md_3">For some people, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for people with cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_41_md_4">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_41_md_5">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_45"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_46">Some of the tests that were done to <SummaryRef href="CDR0000811027" url="/types/bladder/diagnosis">diagnose or stage</SummaryRef> the cancer may be repeated. Some tests will be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests. These tests are sometimes called follow-up tests or check-ups. </Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-02-16</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-09-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
