<Summary id="CDR0000812061" SVPC="Yes"><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Cervical cancer and vaginal cancer are very rare in children. Learn about the signs and symptoms, diagnosis, and treatment options.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/cervical/childhood-cervical-vaginal-cancer">Childhood Cervical and Vaginal Cancers</SummaryURL><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000037892">cervical cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038035">vaginal cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cervical cancer in children</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood cervical cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood vaginal cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>vaginal cancer in children</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Childhood Cervical and Vaginal Cancers</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Childhood Cervical and Vaginal Cancers</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Childhood Cervical and Vaginal Cancers</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Introductory Text</SectionType></SectMetaData><Para id="_2">Childhood cervical and vaginal cancers are very rare types of cancer. Cervical cancer forms in the cells of the cervix, and vaginal cancer forms in the cells of the vagina. The cervix is the lower, narrow end of the uterus (the hollow, pear-shaped organ where a fetus grows). The cervix leads from the uterus to the vagina (birth canal). The vagina is the canal leading from the cervix to the outside of the body. At birth, a baby passes out of the body through the vagina. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000609921" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the female reproductive system; drawing shows the uterus, myometrium (muscular outer layer of the uterus), endometrium (inner lining of the uterus), ovaries, fallopian tubes, cervix, and vagina." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_3"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the female reproductive system. The organs in the female reproductive system include the uterus, ovaries, fallopian tubes, cervix, and vagina. The uterus has a muscular outer layer called the myometrium and an inner lining called the endometrium. </Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_4"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Symptoms</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Childhood cervical cancer and vaginal cancer symptoms</Title><Para id="_5">The most common symptom of cervical cancer and vaginal cancer in children is bleeding from the vagina. Other conditions may also cause vaginal bleeding. If your child has vaginal bleeding, it is important that you tell their doctor. The doctor will ask you when it started and how often it occurs as a first step in making a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046450" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">diagnosis</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Diagnostic tests</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Tests to diagnose childhood cervical cancer and vaginal cancer</Title><Para id="_7">If your child has symptoms that suggest vaginal or cervical cancer, their doctor will need to find out if they are due to cancer or another problem. They may ask about your child’s personal and family medical history and do a physical exam.</Para><Para id="_8">Depending on your child’s symptoms and medical history and the results of their physical exam, the doctor may recommend more tests to find out if your child has vaginal or cervical cancer, and if so, its extent (stage). The results of tests and procedures done to diagnose vaginal and cervical cancers are used to help make decisions about treatment.</Para><Para id="_9">The following tests and procedures may be used to diagnose and stage childhood cervical or vaginal cancers:</Para><SummarySection id="_10"><Title>Pap test</Title><Para id="_11">The Pap test  (also called a Pap smear or cervical cytology) collects cervical cells from the surface of the cervix and vagina using a soft, narrow brush or tiny spatula. The cells are viewed under a microscope to find out if they are abnormal.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_13">Transvaginal needle biopsy is the removal of tissue using a needle that is guided by ultrasound. A <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> views the tissue under a microscope to check for signs of cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><Title>Serum tumor marker test</Title><Para id="_15">Serum tumor markers are substances found in the blood that are either made by vaginal or cervical cancer cells or that the body makes in response to vaginal or cervical cancer. For this test, a sample of blood is checked in the lab to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs, tissues, or tumor cells in the body.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Ultrasound exam</Title><Para id="_17">An ultrasound exam uses high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) that bounce off internal tissues or organs, such as the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>, and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</Title><Para id="_19"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045788" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">MRI</GlossaryTermRef> uses a magnet and radio waves to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the pelvis. The pictures are made by a computer. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_21">A CT scan uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the pelvis. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_75"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_23">You may want to get a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000774692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">second opinion</GlossaryTermRef> to confirm your child’s cervical or vaginal cancer diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044702" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathology report</GlossaryTermRef>, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child’s cancer.</Para><Para id="_24">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI’s Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef>  via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child's appointments, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><Title>Cervical cancer and vaginal cancer stages</Title><Para id="_26">Cancer stage describes the extent of cancer in the body, such as the size of the tumor, whether it has spread, and how far it has spread from where it first formed. It is important to know the stage of the cervical or vaginal cancer to plan the best treatment.</Para><Para id="_27">There are several <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689095" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">staging systems</GlossaryTermRef> for cancer that describe the extent of the cancer. The International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) staging system is used for cervical and vaginal cancers. You may see your child’s cancer described by this staging system in the pathology report. Based on the FIGO results, a stage is assigned to the cancer, ranging from stage I, stage II, stage III, or stage IV (may also be written as stage 1, stage 2, stage 3, or stage 4). When talking with you, your child’s doctor may describe it as one of these stages.</Para><Para id="_28">Learn about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000812061#_6" url="/types/cervical/childhood-cervical-vaginal-cancer">tests and procedures used to diagnose and stage cervical and vaginal cancer in children</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_29">Learn about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000810161" url="/types/cervical/stages">Cervical Cancer Stages</SummaryRef> and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000258349#_26" url="/types/vaginal/patient/vaginal-treatment-pdq">Vaginal Cancer Stages</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_31"><Title>Recurrent cervical cancer or vaginal cancer</Title><Para id="_32">Recurrent cancer is cancer that has come back after it has been treated. Cervical or vaginal cancer may come back in the cervix or vagina or as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044058" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">metastatic</GlossaryTermRef> tumors in other parts of the body. Tests will be done to help determine where the cancer has returned in the body, if it has spread, and how far. The type of treatment that your child will have for recurrent cancer will depend on how far it has spread.</Para><Para id="_33">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/recurrent-cancer">Recurrent Cancer: When Cancer Comes Back</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_34"><Title>Types of treatment for childhood cervical and vaginal cancer</Title><Para id="_35">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with cervical cancer or vaginal cancer. You and your child’s cancer care team will work together to decide treatment. Many factors will be considered, such as your child’s overall health and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_36">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, will oversee treatment for childhood cervical and vaginal cancers. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with cancer and who specialize in certain areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_37" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046378" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gynecologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_38">Your child’s treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals of treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child’s cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, see our downloadable booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_39">A cervical cancer diagnosis can raise concerns about whether treatment will affect your child’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046399" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility</GlossaryTermRef>. Talk with your child’s cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For more information and support, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/fertility-women">Fertility Issues in Girls and Women with Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_77">Types of treatment your child might have include:</Para><SummarySection id="_40"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_41">Surgery is used to remove as much cancer as possible from the cervix or vagina. If cancer cells remain after surgery or cancer has spread to the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>, more treatment may be needed.</Para><Para id="_42">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/surgery">Surgery to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_44">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045072" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation</GlossaryTermRef> to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Cervical cancer and vaginal cancer are sometimes treated with external beam radiation therapy. This type of radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation therapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment, such as chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_45">Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_46"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_47">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells. Chemotherapy either kills the cells or stops them from dividing. Chemotherapy for vaginal cancer or cervical cancer is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein. When given this way, the drugs enter the bloodstream to reach cancer cells throughout the body.</Para><Para id="_48">It is not known if chemotherapy is an effective treatment for childhood cervical cancer or vaginal cancer, although drugs commonly used to treat these cancers in adults, such as <DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef> and <DrugRef href="CDR0000502187" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/paclitaxel">paclitaxel</DrugRef>, may be used.</Para><Para id="_49">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/chemo-and-you">Chemotherapy and You: Support for People With Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_50"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_50_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_50_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_50_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_55"><Title>Treatment of newly diagnosed childhood cervical cancer and vaginal cancer</Title><Para id="_57">Treatment of newly diagnosed cervical cancer and vaginal cancer in children may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_58" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Surgery will be done to remove as much of the cancer as possible, followed by radiation therapy, if cancer cells remain after surgery or cancer has spread to the lymph nodes.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy may also be used, but it is not yet known how well this treatment works.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_76">Sometimes childhood cervical cancer and vaginal cancer can recur (come back) after treatment. If your child is diagnosed with a recurrent cervical cancer or vaginal cancer, your child's doctor will work with you to plan treatment.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_63"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Side effects of cancer treatment</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_78">Cancer treatment can cause side effects. Which side effects your child might have depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_64">For information about side effects that begin during treatment for cancer, see our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects of Cancer Treatment</ExternalRef> page.</Para><Para id="_65">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Physical problems, such as problems with fertility, may be a late effect of treatment.</Para><Para id="_66">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the possible late effects caused by some treatments. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_67"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Post-treatment considerations</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_68">Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer may be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_69">Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). These tests are sometimes called follow-up tests or check-ups.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_70"><Title>Coping with your child's cancer</Title><Para id="_71">When a child has cancer, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is also important. Reach out to your child’s treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, see <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-06-15</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-09</DateLastModified></Summary>
