<Summary id="CDR0000813233" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>RUNX1-familial platelet disorder (RUNX1-FPD) is a hereditary hematologic malignancy syndrome associated with the RUNX1 gene. Learn about RUNX1-FPD’s clinical features and management. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/runx1-hp-pdq">RUNX1-familial Platelet Disorder (RUNX1-FPD) (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_2824">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of RUNX1-FPD. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2825">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>RUNX1</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>RUNX1 familial platelet disorder </SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle><GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-Familial Platelet Disorder  (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">RUNX1-familial Platelet Disorder (RUNX1-FPD) (PDQ®) </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">RUNX1-familial Platelet Disorder</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_3751"><Title>Introduction and Clinical Manifestations of <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>–Familial Platelet Disorder (<GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD) </Title><Para id="_3756">RUNX1   (Runt-related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef> factor 1) is a key transcription factor involved in hematopoietic differentiation, and it is one of the most commonly mutated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> in myeloid malignancies.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_3757"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809371" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Inherited</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> gene lead to an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">hereditary cancer syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>   called <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> platelet disorder (<GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD) (also referred to as FPD with a propensity towards myeloid malignancies [FPD/MM] or acute myeloid leukemia [FPD/AML]).<Reference refidx="2"/>  Familial platelet functional defects have been clinically recognized for several decades.<Reference refidx="3"/> In 1999, <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> was the first gene found to be associated with FPD/MM. <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD was the first germline predisposition syndrome associated with myeloid malignancies. In 2016, the World Health Organization (WHO) incorporated germline <GeneName>RUNX1 </GeneName>pathogenic variants  under a newly created subcategory of myeloid neoplasms called, “myeloid neoplasms with germline predisposition and preexisting platelet disorders.”<Reference refidx="4"/> The WHO's inclusion of <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD  in its classification guidelines has increased public awareness of this disorder.</Para><Para id="_3758">Germline <GeneName>RUNX1 </GeneName>pathogenic variants leading to <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD are associated with the following:<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_3759" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Lifetime mild to moderate thrombocytopenia associated with aspirin-like functional platelet defects.</ListItem><ListItem>Approximately a 44% lifetime risk of developing myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS), AML, or T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3760">Although these are the most commonly reported hematologic cancers seen in individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD, other cancers  have also been reported, including B-cell malignancies and myeloproliferative neoplasms.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  There  is a high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of thrombocytopenia and underlying platelet dysfunction in individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD. Thrombocytopenia is often recognized during childhood, although it has  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339331" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variable expressivity</GlossaryTermRef>, even within affected families. Hematologic malignancies are diagnosed at a median age of  33 years.  However, the reported age range for an MDS or leukemia diagnosis is broad (range, 5 y to 76 y).<Reference refidx="5"/>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660750" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Genetic anticipation</GlossaryTermRef> (which can lead to disease manifestations occurring at earlier ages in successive generations) has also been described in <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_3761">More than 200 families with germline <GeneName>RUNX1 </GeneName>pathogenic variants have been described in the literature.<Reference refidx="11"/>  However, it is estimated that 5,515 families with <GeneName>RUNX1 </GeneName>pathogenic variants exist worldwide, based on population incidence and a survey conducted by FPD/AML centers of excellence.<Reference refidx="12"/> Importantly,   a <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> database (RUNX1db) and registry is now available as a public resource.<Reference refidx="13"/> <GeneName> RUNX1</GeneName>   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic variants</GlossaryTermRef> have been detected in approximately 10% of AML cases, and the vast majority of these variants are somatic in nature. However, some studies have suggested that  in an AML cohort, as many as 16% of <GeneName>RUNX1 </GeneName> variants  that were identified by somatic testing could be germline in nature.<Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/></Para><Para id="_3762">Phenotypic criteria proposed by the ClinGen Myeloid Malignancy Variant Curation Expert Panel (MM-VCEP)   state that an individual should exhibit at least one of the following to fit the FPD/AML phenotype:<Reference refidx="12"/></Para><OrderedList id="_3763" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Mild to moderate thrombocytopenia with normal platelet size and volume (in the absence of other causative factors like autoimmune- or drug-related thrombocytopenias).</ListItem><ListItem>Platelet ultra-structural and/or functional defects, including  platelet alpha granule secretion defects, platelet dense granule secretion defects, and impaired platelet aggregation. </ListItem><ListItem>Diagnosis  of a hematologic malignancy (most commonly affecting the myeloid lineage and manifesting as AML or MDS, or less frequently involving the lymphoid lineage and manifesting as T-ALL  or other cancers).  </ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_3764">In addition to thrombocytopenia and hematologic malignancies, <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD may also be associated with the following features: eczema, psoriasis, arthritis, and other autoimmune disorders.<Reference refidx="11"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21148331">Schnittger S, Dicker F, Kern W, et al.: RUNX1 mutations are frequent in de novo AML with noncomplex karyotype and confer an unfavorable prognosis. Blood 117 (8): 2348-57, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Johns Hopkins University: Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man: Platelet Disorder, Familial, with Associated Myeloid Malignancy; FPDMM. Johns Hopkins University, 2014. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.omim.org/entry/601399">Available online.</ExternalRef> Last accessed October 4, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="5349805">Weiss HJ, Chervenick PA, Zalusky R, et al.: A familialdefect in platelet function associated with imapired release of adenosine diphosphate. N Engl J Med 281 (23): 1264-70, 1969.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27069254">Arber DA, Orazi A, Hasserjian R, et al.: The 2016 revision to the World Health Organization classification of myeloid neoplasms and acute leukemia. Blood 127 (20): 2391-405, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="27899193">Feurstein S, Drazer MW, Godley LA: Genetic predisposition to leukemia and other hematologic malignancies. Semin Oncol 43 (5): 598-608, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="18723428">Owen CJ, Toze CL, Koochin A, et al.: Five new pedigrees with inherited RUNX1 mutations causing familial platelet disorder with propensity to myeloid malignancy. Blood 112 (12): 4639-45, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="20880108">Linden T, Schnittger S, Groll AH, et al.: Childhood B-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukaemia in a patient with familial thrombocytopenia and RUNX1 mutation. Br J Haematol 151 (5): 528-30, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="22138511">Shiba N, Hasegawa D, Park MJ, et al.: CBL mutation in chronic myelomonocytic leukemia secondary to familial platelet disorder with propensity to develop acute myeloid leukemia (FPD/AML). Blood 119 (11): 2612-4, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="32060405">DiFilippo EC, Coltro G, Carr RM, et al.: Spectrum of abnormalities and clonal transformation in germline RUNX1 familial platelet disorder and a genomic comparative analysis with somatic RUNX1 mutations in MDS/MPN overlap neoplasms. Leukemia 34 (9): 2519-2524, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="31124578">Duarte BKL, Yamaguti-Hayakawa GG, Medina SS, et al.: Longitudinal sequencing of RUNX1 familial platelet disorder: new insights into genetic mechanisms of transformation to myeloid malignancies. Br J Haematol 186 (5): 724-734, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="32208489">Brown AL, Arts P, Carmichael CL, et al.: RUNX1-mutated families show phenotype heterogeneity and a somatic mutation profile unique to germline predisposed AML. Blood Adv 4 (6): 1131-1144, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="31648317">Luo X, Feurstein S, Mohan S, et al.: ClinGen Myeloid Malignancy Variant Curation Expert Panel recommendations for germline RUNX1 variants. Blood Adv 3 (20): 2962-2979, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="34233450">Homan CC, King-Smith SL, Lawrence DM, et al.: The RUNX1 database (RUNX1db): establishment of an expert curated RUNX1 registry and genomics database as a public resource for familial platelet disorder with myeloid malignancy. Haematologica 106 (11): 3004-3007, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="32315381">Simon L, Spinella JF, Yao CY, et al.: High frequency of germline RUNX1 mutations in patients with RUNX1-mutated AML. Blood 135 (21): 1882-1886, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="33075818">Ernst MPT, Kavelaars FG, Löwenberg B, et al.: RUNX1 germline variants in RUNX1-mutant AML: how frequent? Blood 137 (10): 1428-1431, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3753"><Title>Genetics and Molecular Biology of <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-Familial Platelet Disorder (FPD)</Title><Para id="_3767">Many of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> seem to be unique to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460211" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">probands</GlossaryTermRef> or families.<Reference refidx="1"/> The majority of <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> germline  pathogenic  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef> described in the literature are inherited, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783882" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">de novo</GlossaryTermRef> germline <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> variants have been rarely reported.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>   The  following types of germline pathogenic variants have been reported in the <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>: <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense variants</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783965" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">nonsense variants</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783968" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">splice-site variants</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803525" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">single nucleotide variants</GlossaryTermRef>, small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781204" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">insertions</GlossaryTermRef>, small <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deletions</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000600383" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">copy number variants</GlossaryTermRef> (including intragenic and whole-gene deletions).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> Pathogenic variants can happen at any location along the <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> gene, but these variants are most often located within the conserved runt-homology <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460145" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">domain</GlossaryTermRef> (RHD) or the transactivation domain (TAD).<Reference refidx="7"/></Para><Para id="_3768"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339333" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Genomic  heterogeneity</GlossaryTermRef> (in terms of somatic clonal evolution) is common, even among asymptomatic individuals with germline <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> More than 80% of evaluated individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD demonstrate clonal evolution by age 50 years. Secondary  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in genes involved in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000717443" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">epigenetic</GlossaryTermRef> regulation (i.e., <GeneName>TET2</GeneName> and <GeneName>DNMT3A</GeneName>) comprise most <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef> identified in individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD who are undergoing <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef>. These secondary variants are commonly associated with age-related clonal hematopoiesis.  Many individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD–associated hematologic malignancies have evidence of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cytogenetic</GlossaryTermRef> abnormalities (e.g., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460223" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">trisomy</GlossaryTermRef> 21, trisomy 8, monosomy 7). These individuals can also have secondary somatic variants   in active signaling pathways (i.e., RAS pathway, KIT   pathway) or in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046657" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">tumor suppressor genes</GlossaryTermRef> (i.e., <GeneName>WT1</GeneName>, <GeneName>PHF6</GeneName>, <GeneName>TP53</GeneName>). Individuals can also have additional somatic variants in the <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> gene.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_3769">Notably, baseline morphological and immunophenotypic abnormalities are often present in the bone marrow of asymptomatic individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD who do not have myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)/acute myeloid leukemia.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> These abnormalities can include low-for-age bone marrow cellularity and dysplastic megakaryopoiesis, which is often characterized by small, hypolobated megakaryocytes. When mild dysplasia is already present, it can be a challenge to define when an individual's condition progresses to MDS.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="28179279">Sood R, Kamikubo Y, Liu P: Role of RUNX1 in hematological malignancies. Blood 129 (15): 2070-2082, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="35764482">Feurstein S, Luo X, Shah M, et al.: Revision of RUNX1 variant curation rules. Blood Adv 6 (16): 4726-4730, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="31648317">Luo X, Feurstein S, Mohan S, et al.: ClinGen Myeloid Malignancy Variant Curation Expert Panel recommendations for germline RUNX1 variants. Blood Adv 3 (20): 2962-2979, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="27899193">Feurstein S, Drazer MW, Godley LA: Genetic predisposition to leukemia and other hematologic malignancies. Semin Oncol 43 (5): 598-608, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="18478040">Béri-Dexheimer M, Latger-Cannard V, Philippe C, et al.: Clinical phenotype of germline RUNX1 haploinsufficiency: from point mutations to large genomic deletions. Eur J Hum Genet 16 (8): 1014-8, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="26175287">Ouchi-Uchiyama M, Sasahara Y, Kikuchi A, et al.: Analyses of Genetic and Clinical Parameters for Screening Patients With Inherited Thrombocytopenia with Small or Normal-Sized Platelets. Pediatr Blood Cancer 62 (12): 2082-8, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="32208489">Brown AL, Arts P, Carmichael CL, et al.: RUNX1-mutated families show phenotype heterogeneity and a somatic mutation profile unique to germline predisposed AML. Blood Adv 4 (6): 1131-1144, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="26492932">Churpek JE, Pyrtel K, Kanchi KL, et al.: Genomic analysis of germ line and somatic variants in familial myelodysplasia/acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 126 (22): 2484-90, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="32060405">DiFilippo EC, Coltro G, Carr RM, et al.: Spectrum of abnormalities and clonal transformation in germline RUNX1 familial platelet disorder and a genomic comparative analysis with somatic RUNX1 mutations in MDS/MPN overlap neoplasms. Leukemia 34 (9): 2519-2524, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="19357396">Preudhomme C, Renneville A, Bourdon V, et al.: High frequency of RUNX1 biallelic alteration in acute myeloid leukemia secondary to familial platelet disorder. Blood 113 (22): 5583-7, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="30600763">Chisholm KM, Denton C, Keel S, et al.: Bone Marrow Morphology Associated With Germline RUNX1 Mutations in Patients With Familial Platelet Disorder With Associated Myeloid Malignancy. Pediatr Dev Pathol 22 (4): 315-328, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="28659335">Kanagal-Shamanna R, Loghavi S, DiNardo CD, et al.: Bone marrow pathologic abnormalities in familial platelet disorder with propensity for myeloid malignancy and germline RUNX1 mutation. Haematologica 102 (10): 1661-1670, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3754"><Title>Management and Prognosis for <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-Familial Platelet Disorder (FPD)</Title><Para id="_3765"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> recommendations for individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD are based on expert opinion and typically include blood work (including a complete blood count [CBC] with differential conducted once or twice annually), in addition to a physical exam.<Reference refidx="1"/>  A bone marrow evaluation is suggested when an individual is first diagnosed with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD. It is suggested that bone marrow evaluation be repeated when changes are found in the individual’s blood counts or when new, concerning medical findings (such as recurrent infections) occur. While annual bone marrow evaluations are often recommended for research purposes, there are no current clinical or pathological criteria that can reliably predict the development of hematologic malignancies in individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD. </Para><Para id="_3766">Clinical outcomes and management decisions for individuals with <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-FPD who experience malignant transformation are rarely reported. In general, standard treatment for the underlying malignancy (i.e., myelodysplastic syndrome, acute myeloid leukemia, or T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia directed-therapies) and consideration of an allogeneic stem cell transplant are recommended. Potential related donors should be evaluated for the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> to avoid transplanting stem cells with the same underlying genetic defect whenever possible. This approach can help avoid risks of graft failure and donor-derived leukemias.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="22691122">Churpek JE, Lorenz R, Nedumgottil S, et al.: Proposal for the clinical detection and management of patients and their family members with familial myelodysplastic syndrome/acute leukemia predisposition syndromes. Leuk Lymphoma 54 (1): 28-35, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3755"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/25/2024)</Title><Para id="_1182">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3771">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000813233#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/runx1-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about RUNX1-familial platelet disorder (RUNX1-FPD). It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for RUNX1-Familial Platelet Disorder are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Julia Cooper, MS, CGC (Ohio State University)</ListItem><ListItem>Courtney DiNardo, MD, MSC (University of Texas, M.D. Anderson Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Marcin  Wlodarski, MD, PhD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ RUNX1-Familial Platelet Disorder. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/runx1-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/runx1-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 38113349]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-12-14</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-25</DateLastModified></Summary>
