<Summary id="CDR0000813836" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 1 (RTPS1) is a hereditary cancer syndrome associated with the SMARCB1 gene. Learn about RTPS1's clinical features and management.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/rtps1-hp-pdq">Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
1 (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000725407">rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_2838">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics, cancer risks, and management of  rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 1. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines for recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2839">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board and PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which are editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
1</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>SMARCB1 gene</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
1 (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
1 (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
1</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_1"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_2">
Rhabdoid   tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809371" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">predisposition syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> type 1 (RTPS1) is caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef>, or hereditary, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339341" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef> loss-of-function <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 22q11.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Individuals with RTPS1 are at an increased risk of developing both central nervous system (CNS) and non-CNS rhabdoid tumors, including atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (AT/RTs), malignant rhabdoid tumors (MRTs) of the kidney, and extrarenal rhabdoid tumors. These tumors tend to require multimodal treatment such as surgery, chemotherapy, and possibly radiation therapy. These tumors occur most frequently in early childhood, often before the age of 3 years.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="10521299" MedlineID="99452595">Sévenet N, Sheridan E, Amram D, et al.: Constitutional mutations of the hSNF5/INI1 gene predispose to a variety of cancers. Am J Hum Genet 65 (5): 1342-8, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="9892189" MedlineID="99107207">Biegel JA, Zhou JY, Rorke LB, et al.: Germ-line and acquired mutations of INI1 in atypical teratoid and rhabdoid tumors. Cancer Res 59 (1): 74-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="9671307" MedlineID="98334382">Versteege I, Sévenet N, Lange J, et al.: Truncating mutations of hSNF5/INI1 in aggressive paediatric cancer. Nature 394 (6689): 203-6, 1998.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>Nomenclature</Title><Para id="_4">Individuals who harbor a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> are said to have rhabdoid tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809371" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">predisposition syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> type 1 (RTPS1).<Reference refidx="1"/> Individuals who harbor a germline pathogenic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant</GlossaryTermRef> in <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> are said to have rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 2 (RTPS2).<Reference refidx="2"/> Nomenclature in genetic disorders continues to evolve, and future terminology for these disorders may reflect the proposed dyadic naming approach, incorporating both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Samples, Phenotypes and Ontologies Team: Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome 1. Ontology Lookup Service  European Molecular Biology Laboratory-European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI), 2023. <ExternalRef xref="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/MONDO_0012252">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed October 17, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Samples, Phenotypes and Ontologies Team: Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome 2. Ontology Lookup Service  European Molecular Biology Laboratory-European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI), 2023. <ExternalRef xref="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/MONDO_0013224">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed October 17, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="33417889">Biesecker LG, Adam MP, Alkuraya FS, et al.: A dyadic approach to the delineation of diagnostic entities in clinical genomics. Am J Hum Genet 108 (1): 8-15, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>Genetics</Title><SummarySection id="_6"><Title>Molecular Genetics</Title><Para id="_7">The <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> encodes the SMARCB1 protein (also called INI1 or BAF47), a member of the SWI/SNF chromatin remodeling complex, which helps control gene <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Rhabdoid tumors develop when both copies of the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> gene are inactivated, or in some cases, when both copies of the <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> gene are inactivated. Individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef> have a diagnosis of rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 2. Loss of SMARCB1/INI1 expression (detected by immunohistochemistry) is included in the diagnostic criteria for rhabdoid tumors.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_8">In individuals with rhabdoid   tumor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809371" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">predisposition syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> type 1 (RTPS1), tumor development follows the Knudsen two-hit hypothesis. The first hit is caused by the inactivation of one copy of <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName>, typically by a truncating variant, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000600383" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">copy-number change</GlossaryTermRef>, or structural variant. The second hit is typically due to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosomal</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deletion</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000464169" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">loss of heterozygosity</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="4"/>  It is estimated that approximately 25% to 35% of rhabdoid tumor cases are associated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781852" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline variant</GlossaryTermRef> in <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>   Higher rates have been reported in certain subgroups, including patients diagnosed at younger than 6 months (55%) and patients with multifocal tumors (78%).<Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/> It is recommended that all patients diagnosed with rhabdoid tumors consider genetic evaluation.<Reference refidx="10"/> Whole- and partial-gene deletions, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783965" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">nonsense</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783963" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">frameshift variants</GlossaryTermRef> are seen most commonly, frequently affecting <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460146" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">exons</GlossaryTermRef> 2 through 7 of the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> gene.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="11"/>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000803525" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Single nucleotide variants</GlossaryTermRef>, duplications, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783968" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">splice-site variants</GlossaryTermRef> occur more rarely.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> A case of ring chromosome 22 has also been reported in an individual with RTPS1.<Reference refidx="13"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_9"><Title>Inheritance </Title><Para id="_10">RTPS1 is inherited in an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal  dominant</GlossaryTermRef> manner. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> is reported as greater than 90% for most types of truncating variants in <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="7"/> However, these estimates are based on a modest number of observations and ascertainment of affected individuals and families. Most cases appear to be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460142" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">de novo</GlossaryTermRef>, and individuals with rhabdoid tumors are often the  first person in the family to be affected.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="14"/><Reference refidx="15"/> This may be due to the aggressive nature of rhabdoid tumors. However, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792352" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">incomplete penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339332" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">late-onset</GlossaryTermRef> tumors, including schwannoma and meningioma, have been reported in a small subset of families who are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460224" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">unaffected</GlossaryTermRef> by rhabdoid tumors and carry a germline <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> variant.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="11"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000813317" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Gonadal mosaicism</GlossaryTermRef> in a parent has been well documented in RTPS1. Therefore, negative genetic testing of parental blood cannot rule out the risk that more than one child may inherit the pathogenic variant and have a diagnosis of RTPS1.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="16"/><Reference refidx="17"/> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> has been suggested to discuss topics like prenatal testing and potential reproductive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460213" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">recurrence risk</GlossaryTermRef> relevant to gonadal mosaicism.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_11"><Title>Related Disorders</Title><Para id="_12">Germline alterations in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> gene are primarily associated with two additional <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809370" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">hereditary conditions</GlossaryTermRef>, schwannomatosis and Coffin-Siris syndrome (CSS). Cases of schwannoma have been reported in RTPS1 kindreds. However, rhabdoid tumors have not been reported in individuals with CSS. Generally, <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> variants associated with CSS are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense variants</GlossaryTermRef> that cluster in the first and last exons of the gene.<Reference refidx="11"/> In patients with schwannomatosis, variants are often nontruncating and occur in the 3’ untranslated (UTR) region of <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="18"/> However, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783965" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">nonsense</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> variants or deletions/duplications of the whole gene/multiple exons are more often associated with rhabdoid tumors.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="18"/> While these patterns represent the common <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660739" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genotype</GlossaryTermRef>-<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef> correlations, they are not final, and overlap can be seen. However, exon-spanning deletions appear to occur exclusively in patients with RTPS1.<Reference refidx="11"/> While genotype-phenotype correlations exist across these three disorders, there is limited information regarding genotype-phenotype correlations specific to RTPS1. </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="19305156">Roberts CW, Biegel JA: The role of SMARCB1/INI1 in development of rhabdoid tumor. Cancer Biol Ther 8 (5): 412-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="19234488">Reisman D, Glaros S, Thompson EA: The SWI/SNF complex and cancer. Oncogene 28 (14): 1653-68, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="28620006">Foulkes WD, Kamihara J, Evans DGR, et al.: Cancer Surveillance in Gorlin Syndrome and Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome. Clin Cancer Res 23 (12): e62-e67, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="9892189" MedlineID="99107207">Biegel JA, Zhou JY, Rorke LB, et al.: Germ-line and acquired mutations of INI1 in atypical teratoid and rhabdoid tumors. Cancer Res 59 (1): 74-9, 1999.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21108436">Eaton KW, Tooke LS, Wainwright LM, et al.: Spectrum of SMARCB1/INI1 mutations in familial and sporadic rhabdoid tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 56 (1): 7-15, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="21208904">Bourdeaut F, Lequin D, Brugières L, et al.: Frequent hSNF5/INI1 germline mutations in patients with rhabdoid tumor. Clin Cancer Res 17 (1): 31-8, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="33532948">Frühwald MC, Nemes K, Boztug H, et al.: Current recommendations for clinical surveillance and genetic testing in rhabdoid tumor predisposition: a report from the SIOPE Host Genome Working Group. Fam Cancer 20 (4): 305-316, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="35565313">Nemes K, Johann PD, Steinbügl M, et al.: Infants and Newborns with Atypical Teratoid Rhabdoid Tumors (ATRT) and Extracranial Malignant Rhabdoid Tumors (eMRT) in the EU-RHAB Registry: A Unique and Challenging Population. Cancers (Basel) 14 (9): , 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="29428974">Pinto EM, Hamideh D, Bahrami A, et al.: Malignant rhabdoid tumors originating within and outside the central nervous system are clinically and molecularly heterogeneous. Acta Neuropathol 136 (2): 315-326, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="28674117">Druker H, Zelley K, McGee RB, et al.: Genetic Counselor Recommendations for Cancer Predisposition Evaluation and Surveillance in the Pediatric Oncology Patient. Clin Cancer Res 23 (13): e91-e97, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="29706634">Holsten T, Bens S, Oyen F, et al.: Germline variants in SMARCB1 and other members of the BAF chromatin-remodeling complex across human disease entities: a meta-analysis. Eur J Hum Genet 26 (8): 1083-1093, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="34101994">Kordes U, Mautner VF, Oyen F, et al.: Evidence for a low-penetrant extended phenotype of rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 1 from a kindred with gain of SMARCB1 exon 6. Pediatr Blood Cancer 68 (10): e29185, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="27734605">Byers HM, Adam MP, LaCroix A, et al.: Description of a new oncogenic mechanism for atypical teratoid rhabdoid tumors in patients with ring chromosome 22. Am J Med Genet A 173 (1): 245-249, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="12429635">Biegel JA, Tan L, Zhang F, et al.: Alterations of the hSNF5/INI1 gene in central nervous system atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors and renal and extrarenal rhabdoid tumors. Clin Cancer Res 8 (11): 3461-7, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="29418059">Nemes K, Clément N, Kachanov D, et al.: The extraordinary challenge of treating patients with congenital rhabdoid tumors-a collaborative European effort. Pediatr Blood Cancer 65 (6): e26999, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="26342593">Gigante L, Paganini I, Frontali M, et al.: Rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome caused by SMARCB1 constitutional deletion: prenatal detection of new case of recurrence in siblings due to gonadal mosaicism. Fam Cancer 15 (1): 123-6, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="20848638">Bruggers CS, Bleyl SB, Pysher T, et al.: Clinicopathologic comparison of familial versus sporadic atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (AT/RT) of the central nervous system. Pediatr Blood Cancer 56 (7): 1026-31, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="24933152">Smith MJ, Wallace AJ, Bowers NL, et al.: SMARCB1 mutations in schwannomatosis and genotype correlations with rhabdoid tumors. Cancer Genet 207 (9): 373-8, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_13"><Title>Cancer Risks, Spectrum, and Characteristics </Title><Para id="_14">As a class, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000600383" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">copy-number</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">(deletion)</GlossaryTermRef> and truncating variants in <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> are associated with increased risk of tumor predisposition, although there are no known <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660739" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genotypes</GlossaryTermRef> that can predict whether a tumor (or type of tumor) will develop.<Reference refidx="1"/> A meta-analysis of 185 carriers of <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef> found that the most common tumor type was atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (AT/RTs), followed by rhabdoid tumors of the kidney and soft tissue.<Reference refidx="1"/> Multifocal tumors were common. Other tumors found included meningiomas, malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumors, chondrosarcomas, epithelioid sarcomas, leiomyosarcomas, leiomyomas, and myoepitheliomas. Anatomical locations of the tumors varied, especially in the brain.<Reference refidx="2"/> Tumors can also be <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000815374" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">synchronous</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000815372" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">metachronous</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_2840">In patients with rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 1 (RTPS1), tumor onset typically occurs in very early childhood (often in infancy), and tumors may even be detected pre- or perinatally. There are rare case reports of adults developing <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName>-associated tumors.  As <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763024" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">next-generation sequencing</GlossaryTermRef> of tumors has become more prevalent, alterations in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> may require investigation for an underlying <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> predisposition.  However, the absence of a genetic alteration in the <GeneName>SMARBC1</GeneName> gene does not rule out an underlying <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cancer predisposition syndrome</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="3"/> Second primary tumors have developed up to 15 years after the first primary tumor diagnosis, suggesting that lifetime <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> is needed for patients with this syndrome.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="29706634">Holsten T, Bens S, Oyen F, et al.: Germline variants in SMARCB1 and other members of the BAF chromatin-remodeling complex across human disease entities: a meta-analysis. Eur J Hum Genet 26 (8): 1083-1093, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="35565313">Nemes K, Johann PD, Steinbügl M, et al.: Infants and Newborns with Atypical Teratoid Rhabdoid Tumors (ATRT) and Extracranial Malignant Rhabdoid Tumors (eMRT) in the EU-RHAB Registry: A Unique and Challenging Population. Cancers (Basel) 14 (9): , 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="33532948">Frühwald MC, Nemes K, Boztug H, et al.: Current recommendations for clinical surveillance and genetic testing in rhabdoid tumor predisposition: a report from the SIOPE Host Genome Working Group. Fam Cancer 20 (4): 305-316, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="35678633">Bruggers CS, Linscott L, Lee JC, et al.: Molecular characterization of metachronous atypical teratoid rhabdoid tumors occurring in a young man 15 years apart. Pediatr Blood Cancer 70 (1): e29836, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="30393974">Bhatt MD, Al-Karmi S, Druker H, et al.: Second rhabdoid tumor 8 years after treatment of atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor in a child with germline SMARCB1 mutation. Pediatr Blood Cancer 66 (3): e27546, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_15"><Title>Management</Title><SummarySection id="_16"><Title>Genetic Counseling</Title><Para id="_17">Experts in the field of cancer genetics recommend a referral for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> or genetic evaluation  for children who have been diagnosed with atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (AT/RTs), malignant rhaboid tumors (MRTs), or any other SMARCB1-deficient tumors. These recommendations are based on the American Association for Cancer Research's (AACR) Childhood Cancer Predisposition Workshop and  the European Society for Paediatric Oncology's (SIOPE) Host Genome Working Group guidelines.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>  In the event that a child with an AT/RT or MRT died before completing the evaluation, counseling may be provided to parents and siblings.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><Title>Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition and Fertility Preservation</Title><Para id="_19">Treatments for AT/RTs and MRTs may reduce fertility in boys and girls.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> Therefore, the medical team may offer fertility preservation to these patients.  Parents of children with AT/RTs and MRTs who undergo fertility preservation should be advised that if a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> truncating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant</GlossaryTermRef> is found, 50% of children derived from preserved gonadal tissue will inherit a <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> pathogenic variant and have a risk of developing rhabdoid tumors.  Prenatal genetic counseling is advised for individuals with RTPS1.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_20"><Title>Outcomes and Treatment Modification</Title><Para id="_21">In patients with  AT/RTs or extracranial rhabdoid tumors, germline <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> variants are associated with poor outcomes. The risk of metastasis may also be associated with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781852" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline variant</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/>  Despite intensive therapy, fewer than half of children with rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 1 (RTPS1) become long-term survivors.  There are no data suggesting that treatment of patients with AT/RTs or MRTs should be modified because of a germline  RTPS1 diagnosis. </Para><Para id="_2844">For information about the treatment of AT/RTs, see <SummaryRef href="CDR0000587224" url="/types/brain/hp/child-cns-atrt-treatment-pdq">Childhood Central Nervous System Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor Treatment</SummaryRef>. For information about the treatment of MRTs, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062789#_17" url="/types/kidney/hp/wilms-treatment-pdq">Rhabdoid Tumors of the Kidney</SummaryRef> section in Wilms Tumor and Other Childhood Kidney Tumors Treatment and the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062934#_628" url="/types/soft-tissue-sarcoma/hp/child-soft-tissue-treatment-pdq">Rhabdoid Tumor NOS (Extrarenal)</SummaryRef> section in Childhood Soft Tissue Sarcoma Treatment.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_22"><Title>Surveillance</Title><Para id="_23">In 2017, a group of experts in childhood cancer genetics created the first recommendations for cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> for patients with RTPS1.<Reference refidx="7"/>  Since children with germline <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> truncating variants have an increased risk of developing AT/RTs in early childhood, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> recommendations include brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) every 3 months until age 5 years, after which surveillance ceases.  Because of the risk of MRTs of the kidney, abdominal ultrasonography is recommended every 3 months from birth, with no upper age limit to stop surveillance.  Whole-body MRI may also be considered until age 5 years.  Screening is not recommended for children with a germline <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> because the risk of tumor development is very low.</Para><Para id="_24">In 2021, the SIOPE Host Genome Working Group published guidelines for clinical surveillance and genetic testing in patients with RTPS1.<Reference refidx="2"/>  These guidelines recommend an age-based approach to surveillance. Central nervous system (CNS) and abdominal imaging  occur every 1 to 3 months  for patients younger than 6 months, every 2 to 3 months for patients aged 7 to 18 months, and every 3 months for patients aged  19 months to 5 years. Yearly whole-body MRI is recommended for patients aged 5 years and older.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_25"><Title>Surveillance in Survivorship</Title><Para id="_26">For children with tumors and <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> truncating variants, surveillance should be ongoing to detect primary disease recurrence.  Survivors of AT/RTs will continue to require abdominal ultrasonography to screen for MRTs.  Conversely, children with MRTs of the kidney will continue  to undergo CNS surveillance for AT/RTs until age 5 years if they have a germline truncating variant in <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_27"><LOERef href="CDR0000526280" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: 5</LOERef></Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="28674117">Druker H, Zelley K, McGee RB, et al.: Genetic Counselor Recommendations for Cancer Predisposition Evaluation and Surveillance in the Pediatric Oncology Patient. Clin Cancer Res 23 (13): e91-e97, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="33532948">Frühwald MC, Nemes K, Boztug H, et al.: Current recommendations for clinical surveillance and genetic testing in rhabdoid tumor predisposition: a report from the SIOPE Host Genome Working Group. Fam Cancer 20 (4): 305-316, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="33539754">Mulder RL, Font-Gonzalez A, Green DM, et al.: Fertility preservation for male patients with childhood, adolescent, and young adult cancer: recommendations from the PanCareLIFE Consortium and the International Late Effects of Childhood Cancer Guideline Harmonization Group. Lancet Oncol 22 (2): e57-e67, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="33539753">Mulder RL, Font-Gonzalez A, Hudson MM, et al.: Fertility preservation for female patients with childhood, adolescent, and young adult cancer: recommendations from the PanCareLIFE Consortium and the International Late Effects of Childhood Cancer Guideline Harmonization Group. Lancet Oncol 22 (2): e45-e56, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="32105509">Reddy AT, Strother DR, Judkins AR, et al.: Efficacy of High-Dose Chemotherapy and Three-Dimensional Conformal Radiation for Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor: A Report From the Children's Oncology Group Trial ACNS0333. J Clin Oncol 38 (11): 1175-1185, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="33249395">Nemes K, Bens S, Kachanov D, et al.: Clinical and genetic risk factors define two risk groups of extracranial malignant rhabdoid tumours (eMRT/RTK). Eur J Cancer 142: 112-122, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28620006">Foulkes WD, Kamihara J, Evans DGR, et al.: Cancer Surveillance in Gorlin Syndrome and Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome. Clin Cancer Res 23 (12): e62-e67, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2841"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/05/2024)</Title><Para id="_2842">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_2845">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef> and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000813836#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/rtps1-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics, cancer risks, and management of  rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 1. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef> and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which are editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 1 are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Julia Meade, MD (UPMC Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh)</ListItem><ListItem>Sarah Scollon, MS, CGC (Baylor College of Medicine &amp; Texas Children's Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Douglas Stewart, MD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board and the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board use a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board and PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 1. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/rtps1-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/rtps1-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 38630976]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2024-03-05</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-05</DateLastModified></Summary>
