<Summary id="CDR0000813802" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>CEBPA-Associated Familial AML is a hereditary hematologic malignancy syndrome associated with the CEBPA gene. Learn about CEBPA-associated familial AML's clinical features and management. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/cebpa-hp-pdq">CEBPA-Associated Familial AML  (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_2824">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of CEBPA-associated familial AML. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2825">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>CEBPA-associated familial AML</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle><GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-Associated Familial Acute Myeloid Leukemia  (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">CEBPA-associated Familial AML (PDQ®) </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">CEBPA-associated Familial AML</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_2826"><Title>Introduction and Clinical Manifestations of <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-Associated Familial Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML)</Title><Para id="_2828">The <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is a granulocytic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef> factor (C/EBPα) that serves an important role in myeloid cell differentiation. Somatic mutations  in <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> occur in approximately 10% to 15% of all AML cases.   The presence of two somatic mutations in <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> (also known as <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>dm)   is recognized as a unique clinical entity associated with favorable outcomes, even in the event of relapse.<Reference refidx="1"/> Germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> were reported in 2004 in a family with hereditary, nonsyndromic AML.<Reference refidx="2"/> <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-associated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> AML (also known as familial AML with a <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant</GlossaryTermRef>) became the second <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> AML <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">predisposition syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> described (<GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName>-familial platelet disorder was the first).<Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_3752">Features of <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-associated familial AML include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_3753" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Highly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrant</GlossaryTermRef>:</Strong> Unlike several other myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS)/AML predisposition syndromes, germline <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants appear to be highly penetrant, conferring greater than a 90% lifetime risk to develop AML.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> </ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Early-onset AML: </Strong>Germline <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants are associated with early-onset AML that can occur in childhood.<Reference refidx="7"/> Published research on families with <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants have reported that AML onset can occur between the ages of 1.75 to 46 years.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>De novo AML: </Strong>Inherited <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants can predispose individuals to de novo  AML without prior prolonged antecedent cytopenias or multilineage dysplasia.<Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>AML similar to somatic <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> variant(s): </Strong>The characteristics of AML arising from a germline <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variant are strikingly similar to the characteristics seen in patients with somatic <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> mutation(s). These include the following: normal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cytogenetics</GlossaryTermRef>, French-American-British (FAB) AML subtypes M1 and M2, numerous Auer rods seen in peripheral blood and bone marrow blasts, and aberrant CD7 expression detected by flow cytometry.<Reference refidx="8"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21177436">Taskesen E, Bullinger L, Corbacioglu A, et al.: Prognostic impact, concurrent genetic mutations, and gene expression features of AML with CEBPA mutations in a cohort of 1182 cytogenetically normal AML patients: further evidence for CEBPA double mutant AML as a distinctive disease entity. Blood 117 (8): 2469-75, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="15575056">Smith ML, Cavenagh JD, Lister TA, et al.: Mutation of CEBPA in familial acute myeloid leukemia. N Engl J Med 351 (23): 2403-7, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="3">Johns Hopkins University: Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man: CCAAT/Enhancer-Binding Protein, Alpha; CEBPA. Johns Hopkins University, 2022. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.omim.org/entry/116897">Available online.</ExternalRef> Last accessed October 9, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="18173751">Owen C, Barnett M, Fitzgibbon J: Familial myelodysplasia and acute myeloid leukaemia--a review. Br J Haematol 140 (2): 123-32, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="19277035">Pabst T, Eyholzer M, Fos J, et al.: Heterogeneity within AML with CEBPA mutations; only CEBPA double mutations, but not single CEBPA mutations are associated with favourable prognosis. Br J Cancer 100 (8): 1343-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="18288131">Renneville A, Roumier C, Biggio V, et al.: Cooperating gene mutations in acute myeloid leukemia: a review of the literature. Leukemia 22 (5): 915-31, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26162409">Tawana K, Wang J, Renneville A, et al.: Disease evolution and outcomes in familial AML with germline CEBPA mutations. Blood 126 (10): 1214-23, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="23926458">Nickels EM, Soodalter J, Churpek JE, et al.: Recognizing familial myeloid leukemia in adults. Ther Adv Hematol 4 (4): 254-69, 2013.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2827"><Title>Genetics and Molecular Biology of <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-Associated Familial Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML)</Title><Para id="_2829">The <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> gene is located on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 19q13.1. Leukemia arising from an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809371" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> follows a two-hit mechanism of leukemogenesis.  Germline <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef>   cluster in the N-terminus (5’ end) of the <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>. The second <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic variant</GlossaryTermRef> (at the C-terminus; 3’ end) is acquired on the other <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339337" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">allele</GlossaryTermRef> (in trans) when leukemia develops.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Interestingly, while the same germline pathogenic variants are present in multiple family members, individuals within families acquire distinct somatic variants in the C-terminus region of <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>. In some cases, more than one C-terminus variant can be acquired, suggesting two distinct episodes of AML in one individual.<Reference refidx="3"/>  Patients with <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants often acquire <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> somatic variants when they develop AML.<Reference refidx="4"/></Para><Para id="_3754">The prevalence of <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-associated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> AML, like that of many other inherited AML <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">predisposition syndromes</GlossaryTermRef>, is unknown. However, germline <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variants may account for up to 1% of all AML cases, as extrapolated from somatic testing data.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> In one series, 2 of 18 patients  (11%) with AML and a somatic <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> variant (also called <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-mutated AML) were found to carry germline pathogenic variants in the N-terminus of <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="7"/> In a second study, 5 of 71 patients (7%) with <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-mutated AML carried a <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> germline pathogenic variant, suggesting that approximately 10% of individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">biallelic</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-mutated AML harbor germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="8"/> Therefore, genetic testing for <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants is indicated  in any patient who presents with AML and <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> somatic variants (particularly biallelic <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> somatic variants).</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="15674366">Leroy H, Roumier C, Huyghe P, et al.: CEBPA point mutations in hematological malignancies. Leukemia 19 (3): 329-34, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="33236764">Kraft IL, Godley LA: Identifying potential germline variants from sequencing hematopoietic malignancies. Blood 136 (22): 2498-2506, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="15902292">Sellick GS, Spendlove HE, Catovsky D, et al.: Further evidence that germline CEBPA mutations cause dominant inheritance of acute myeloid leukaemia. Leukemia 19 (7): 1276-8, 2005.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="23560626">Green CL, Tawana K, Hills RK, et al.: GATA2 mutations in sporadic and familial acute myeloid leukaemia patients with CEBPA mutations. Br J Haematol 161 (5): 701-705, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="19277035">Pabst T, Eyholzer M, Fos J, et al.: Heterogeneity within AML with CEBPA mutations; only CEBPA double mutations, but not single CEBPA mutations are associated with favourable prognosis. Br J Cancer 100 (8): 1343-6, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12351377">Preudhomme C, Sagot C, Boissel N, et al.: Favorable prognostic significance of CEBPA mutations in patients with de novo acute myeloid leukemia: a study from the Acute Leukemia French Association (ALFA). Blood 100 (8): 2717-23, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="18768433">Pabst T, Eyholzer M, Haefliger S, et al.: Somatic CEBPA mutations are a frequent second event in families with germline CEBPA mutations and familial acute myeloid leukemia. J Clin Oncol 26 (31): 5088-93, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="21177436">Taskesen E, Bullinger L, Corbacioglu A, et al.: Prognostic impact, concurrent genetic mutations, and gene expression features of AML with CEBPA mutations in a cohort of 1182 cytogenetically normal AML patients: further evidence for CEBPA double mutant AML as a distinctive disease entity. Blood 117 (8): 2469-75, 2011.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2830"><Title>Management and Prognosis for <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-Associated Familial Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML)</Title><Para id="_2831"><GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-associated <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> AML is similar to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic AML</GlossaryTermRef> with somatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">biallelic</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef> in that both often have a favorable prognosis and preclude the need for hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT). However, in individuals with AML arising from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant,</GlossaryTermRef> the HSCT’s purpose is to both treat the AML and to replace the constitutional stem cell population  that harbors the AML susceptibility.<Reference refidx="1"/> Like in all <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809371" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">inherited predispositions</GlossaryTermRef> to AML, great care needs to  be taken to avoid use of a stem cell donor who carries a germline <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> pathogenic variant. Donor-derived leukemia has been reported in individuals with <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName>-associated familial AML who received a transplant, unknowingly, from a donor who carried a <GeneName>CEBPA</GeneName> germline pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="2"/> </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21455213">Stelljes M, Corbacioglu A, Schlenk RF, et al.: Allogeneic stem cell transplant to eliminate germline mutations in the gene for CCAAT-enhancer-binding protein α from hematopoietic cells in a family with AML. Leukemia 25 (7): 1209-10, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21403128">Xiao H, Shi J, Luo Y, et al.: First report of multiple CEBPA mutations contributing to donor origin of leukemia relapse after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Blood 117 (19): 5257-60, 2011.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3751"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/25/2024)</Title><Para id="_1182">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3757">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000813802#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/cebpa-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about CEBPA-associated familial AML. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for CEBPA-Associated Familial Acute Myeloid Leukemia are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Julia Cooper, MS, CGC (Ohio State University)</ListItem><ListItem>Courtney DiNardo, MD, MSC (University of Texas, M.D. Anderson Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Marcin  Wlodarski, MD, PhD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ CEBPA-Associated Familial Acute Myeloid Leukemia. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/cebpa-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/cebpa-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 38113348]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-12-14</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-25</DateLastModified></Summary>
