<Summary id="CDR0000813806" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>DDX41-Associated Myeloid Malignancies is a hereditary hematologic malignancy syndrome associated with the DDX41 gene. Learn about DDX41's clinical features and management. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/ddx41-hp-pdq">DDX41-Associated Myeloid Malignancies (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_2824">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of DDX41-associated myeloid malignancies. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2825">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>DDX41-associated myeloid malignancies</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle><GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>-Associated Myeloid Malignancies (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">DDX41-Associated Myeloid Malignancies (PDQ®) </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">DDX41-Associated Myeloid Malignancies</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_2826"><Title>Introduction and Clinical Manifestations of <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>-Associated Myeloid Malignancies</Title><Para id="_2828">Germline <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the RNA helicase, <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>, are associated with an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> predisposition to myeloid malignancies  and other cancers. The prevalence of <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants is not clearly defined. However, these variants are thought to underlie 1% to 1.5% of all acute myeloid leukemia (AML) diagnoses,<Reference refidx="1"/> making it one of the most commonly <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809371" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">inherited predispositions</GlossaryTermRef> to adult-onset myeloid malignancies.<Reference refidx="2"/> Individuals who inherit <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> pathogenic variants have an increased lifetime risk to develop myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) and AML. However, lymphoid malignancies such as non-Hodgkin lymphoma and myeloproliferative neoplasm (MPN)   have also been reported in individuals with <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_3752"><GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants are associated with a later median age of MDS/AML  diagnosis  than other inherited hematologic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">predisposition syndromes</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="6"/> For <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef>, the age of MDS/AML diagnosis can range from 61 to 69 years. This age range is similar to the typical age of diagnosis in patients with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic</GlossaryTermRef> MDS/AML in the general population. The myeloid malignancies that occur in individuals with <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> germline pathogenic variants are almost always diploid and harbor lower somatic mutational burdens than those seen in individuals without <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> germline  pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="6"/> The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>  pathogenic variants is incomplete and variable. <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>  pathogenic variants are associated with a mild to moderate predisposition to hematologic malignancies (lifetime risk of hematologic malignancies ranges from 20% to 30% in <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> carriers). Nearly half of reported <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> carriers develop long-standing asymptomatic  cytopenias  (most commonly leukopenia) prior to malignancy development. However, some <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> carriers will only ever develop stable cytopenias that never progress to become hematologic malignancies. In these cases, individuals are typically transfusion-independent.<Reference refidx="2"/> </Para><Para id="_3753">Since  <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> pathogenic variants have low penetrance and <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>-related hematologic malignancies are often diagnosed at later ages, <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> carriers can be difficult to identify using the typical age– or family history–related <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> criteria. </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25920683">Polprasert C, Schulze I, Sekeres MA, et al.: Inherited and Somatic Defects in DDX41 in Myeloid Neoplasms. Cancer Cell 27 (5): 658-70, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="31484648">Sébert M, Passet M, Raimbault A, et al.: Germline DDX41 mutations define a significant entity within adult MDS/AML patients. Blood 134 (17): 1441-1444, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="26712909">Lewinsohn M, Brown AL, Weinel LM, et al.: Novel germ line DDX41 mutations define families with a lower age of MDS/AML onset and lymphoid malignancies. Blood 127 (8): 1017-23, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="35671390">Li P, Brown S, Williams M, et al.: The genetic landscape of germline DDX41 variants predisposing to myeloid neoplasms. Blood 140 (7): 716-755, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="33929502">Goyal T, Tu ZJ, Wang Z, et al.: Clinical and Pathologic Spectrum of DDX41-Mutated Hematolymphoid Neoplasms. Am J Clin Pathol 156 (5): 829-838, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="30963592">Quesada AE, Routbort MJ, DiNardo CD, et al.: DDX41 mutations in myeloid neoplasms are associated with male gender, TP53 mutations and high-risk disease. Am J Hematol 94 (7): 757-766, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2827"><Title>Genetics and Molecular Biology of <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>-Associated Myeloid Malignancies</Title><Para id="_2829"><GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic variants</GlossaryTermRef>  occur in myeloid and lymphoid malignancies and are increasingly included as part of somatic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763024" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">next-generation sequencing</GlossaryTermRef> (NGS) panels. Studies have shown that molecular profiling is a useful and feasible   tool to <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screen</GlossaryTermRef> patients with hematologic malignancies for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Two common Northern European <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783962" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">founder pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef>, p.Asp140Glyfs*2 and p.Met1Ile, account for most <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> germline pathogenic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef>  identified in individuals with European ancestry. As genetic testing becomes more routine, testing in additional populations indicates that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense variants</GlossaryTermRef>, like <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> p.Val152Gly (p.V152G) and <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> p.Tyr259Cys (p.Y259C), may be more common in non-European populations.<Reference refidx="3"/> When these missense and founder variants are found on   somatic  testing, they are present in the germline nearly 100% of the time. However, multiple <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783965" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">nonsense</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783963" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">frameshift</GlossaryTermRef> germline variants have been reported throughout the <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>. Therefore, full <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> gene sequencing  is indicated when evaluating for a germline pathogenic variant.</Para><Para id="_3754">In nearly 80% of cases, a second, somatically-acquired variant (often the <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> p.Arg525His [p.R525H] variant), is acquired on the other <GeneName>DDX41 </GeneName><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339337" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">allele</GlossaryTermRef>. This second hit is associated with progression to hematologic malignancy.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> Likewise, if the <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> p.Arg525His variant is detected on somatic testing, even in absence of an additional <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> variant (presumably on the other allele), germline testing is warranted. Germline pathogenic variants on the other <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> allele could be present, especially when full somatic sequencing of the gene is not performed. </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="31484648">Sébert M, Passet M, Raimbault A, et al.: Germline DDX41 mutations define a significant entity within adult MDS/AML patients. Blood 134 (17): 1441-1444, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="33585199">Bannon SA, Routbort MJ, Montalban-Bravo G, et al.: Next-Generation Sequencing of DDX41 in Myeloid Neoplasms Leads to Increased Detection of Germline Alterations. Front Oncol 10: 582213, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="33626862">Choi EJ, Cho YU, Hur EH, et al.: Unique ethnic features of DDX41 mutations in patients with idiopathic cytopenia of undetermined significance, myelodysplastic syndrome, or acute myeloid leukemia. Haematologica 107 (2): 510-518, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25920683">Polprasert C, Schulze I, Sekeres MA, et al.: Inherited and Somatic Defects in DDX41 in Myeloid Neoplasms. Cancer Cell 27 (5): 658-70, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="35443031">Duployez N, Largeaud L, Duchmann M, et al.: Prognostic impact of DDX41 germline mutations in intensively treated acute myeloid leukemia patients: an ALFA-FILO study. Blood 140 (7): 756-768, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2830"><Title>Management and Prognosis for <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName>-Associated Myeloid Malignancies</Title><Para id="_2831">Emerging data suggest that <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef> who develop acute myeloid leukemia (AML) have higher complete remission rates and longer mean overall survival rates than individuals who do not carry a <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> In addition, individuals with <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> pathogenic variants who develop myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)/AML may show responses to treatment with lenalidomide.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_3755">At   least  two cases of donor-derived leukemias have occurred in <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> carriers post–hematopoietic stem cell transplant  (HSCT) from a matched-related donor carrying the same germline <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> pathogenic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> This highlights the need for systematic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> of germline <GeneName>DDX41</GeneName> pathogenic variants in MDS/AML patients prior to HSCT. This will allow for appropriate donor selection and donor screening.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="35671390">Li P, Brown S, Williams M, et al.: The genetic landscape of germline DDX41 variants predisposing to myeloid neoplasms. Blood 140 (7): 716-755, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="35443031">Duployez N, Largeaud L, Duchmann M, et al.: Prognostic impact of DDX41 germline mutations in intensively treated acute myeloid leukemia patients: an ALFA-FILO study. Blood 140 (7): 756-768, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="34644397">Alkhateeb HB, Nanaa A, Viswanatha D, et al.: Genetic features and clinical outcomes of patients with isolated and comutated DDX41-mutated myeloid neoplasms. Blood Adv 6 (2): 528-532, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25920683">Polprasert C, Schulze I, Sekeres MA, et al.: Inherited and Somatic Defects in DDX41 in Myeloid Neoplasms. Cancer Cell 27 (5): 658-70, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31400013">Abou Dalle I, Kantarjian H, Bannon SA, et al.: Successful lenalidomide treatment in high risk myelodysplastic syndrome with germline DDX41 mutation. Am J Hematol 95 (2): 227-229, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="27560106">Negoro E, Radivoyevitch T, Polprasert C, et al.: Molecular predictors of response in patients with myeloid neoplasms treated with lenalidomide. Leukemia 30 (12): 2405-2409, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28194039">Kobayashi S, Kobayashi A, Osawa Y, et al.: Donor cell leukemia arising from preleukemic clones with a novel germline DDX41 mutation after allogenic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Leukemia 31 (4): 1020-1022, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="27795557">Berger G, van den Berg E, Sikkema-Raddatz B, et al.: Re-emergence of acute myeloid leukemia in donor cells following allogeneic transplantation in a family with a germline DDX41 mutation. Leukemia 31 (2): 520-522, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3751"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (11/25/2024)</Title><Para id="_1182">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3757">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000813806#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/ddx41-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about DDX41-associated myeloid malignancies. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for DDX41-Associated Myeloid Malignancies are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Julia Cooper, MS, CGC (Ohio State University)</ListItem><ListItem>Courtney DiNardo, MD, MSC (University of Texas, M.D. Anderson Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Marcin  Wlodarski, MD, PhD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ DDX41-Associated Myeloid Malignancies. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/ddx41-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/ddx41-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 38113347]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2023-12-14</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-11-25</DateLastModified></Summary>
