<Summary id="CDR0000814082" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>GATA2 deficiency syndrome is a hereditary hematologic malignancy syndrome associated with the GATA2 gene. Learn about GATA2's clinical features and management. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gata2">GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_2824">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of GATA2 deficiency syndrome. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2825">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>GATA2 deficiency syndrome</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome (PDQ®) </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_3752"><Title>Introduction to GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome</Title><Para id="_3753">Germline loss-of-function variants in the master hematopoietic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef> factor, <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>,  can cause cellular deficiencies that have a high propensity to develop into myeloid malignancies. Initial reports identified GATA2 deficiency in cohorts of patients with the following conditions: </Para><ItemizedList id="_3760" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Familial</GlossaryTermRef> myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)/acute myeloid leukemia (AML).<Reference refidx="1"/></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> and sporadic monocytopenias and mycobacterial infection (MonoMAC) syndrome.<Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem><Strong>D</Strong>endritic <Strong>c</Strong>ell, <Strong>m</Strong>onocyte, and B and natural killer (NK)   <Strong>l</Strong>ymphoid (DCML) deficiency.<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem>Lymphedema and anogenital dysplasia (WILD) syndrome.<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem><ListItem>Primary lymphedema associated with a predisposition to AML (Emberger syndrome).<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem>Unexplained chronic neutropenia.<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem><ListItem>Primary childhood MDS.<Reference refidx="7"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3761">Following  these initial reports, it became well accepted that all of these clinical phenotypes represent the broad spectrum of GATA2 deficiency, a single genetic disease.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="21892162">Hahn CN, Chong CE, Carmichael CL, et al.: Heritable GATA2 mutations associated with familial myelodysplastic syndrome and acute myeloid leukemia. Nat Genet 43 (10): 1012-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21670465">Hsu AP, Sampaio EP, Khan J, et al.: Mutations in GATA2 are associated with the autosomal dominant and sporadic monocytopenia and mycobacterial infection (MonoMAC) syndrome. Blood 118 (10): 2653-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="21765025">Dickinson RE, Griffin H, Bigley V, et al.: Exome sequencing identifies GATA-2 mutation as the cause of dendritic cell, monocyte, B and NK lymphoid deficiency. Blood 118 (10): 2656-8, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="28373026">Dorn JM, Patnaik MS, Van Hee M, et al.: WILD syndrome is GATA2 deficiency: A novel deletion in the GATA2 gene. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract 5 (4): 1149-1152.e1, 2017 Jul - Aug.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="21892158">Ostergaard P, Simpson MA, Connell FC, et al.: Mutations in GATA2 cause primary lymphedema associated with a predisposition to acute myeloid leukemia (Emberger syndrome). Nat Genet 43 (10): 929-31, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="23223431">Pasquet M, Bellanné-Chantelot C, Tavitian S, et al.: High frequency of GATA2 mutations in patients with mild chronic neutropenia evolving to MonoMac syndrome, myelodysplasia, and acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 121 (5): 822-9, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="26702063">Wlodarski MW, Hirabayashi S, Pastor V, et al.: Prevalence, clinical characteristics, and prognosis of GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndromes in children and adolescents. Blood 127 (11): 1387-97; quiz 1518, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3754"><Title>Genetics and Molecular Biology of GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome</Title><Para id="_3755">GATA2 deficiency is caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783882" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">de novo</GlossaryTermRef> or inherited, heterozygous, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>, which result in a loss of GATA2  expression or abnormal GATA2 transcription factor  function.<Reference refidx="1"/> Most patients with GATA2 deficiency carry null <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variants (i.e., <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783968" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">splice-site variants</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783965" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">nonsense variants</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783963" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">frameshift variants</GlossaryTermRef>, whole-gene <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deletions</GlossaryTermRef>, or synonymous variants that affect <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">RNA splicing</GlossaryTermRef>) or <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense variants</GlossaryTermRef> that affect the zinc finger 2  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460145" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">domain</GlossaryTermRef>. Approximately 10% of patients   have noncoding substitutions in the EBOX-GATA-ETS enhancer element in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660737" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">intron</GlossaryTermRef> 4 of <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName>, or occasionally, tandem duplications of the entire <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460162" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">locus</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_3762"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339331" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Variable expressivity</GlossaryTermRef> is common in GATA2 deficiency. Some patients present early in life with one of the following: 1) cytopenias and bone marrow failure that progress to myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)/acute myeloid leukemia (AML), or 2)  severe   immunodeficiency with recurrent    bacterial, viral, and fungal infections.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/>  Other patients with GATA2 deficiency develop MDS with excess blasts  without preexisting clinical features.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> Immunodeficiency is common in patients with GATA2 deficiency and manifests with mycobacterial infections, human papillomavirus (HPV) infections (i.e., generalized warts, intraepithelial neoplasia), Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)–related disease, herpes virus–related disease, and fungal infections. Some patients may also develop pulmonary disease (anti-granulocyte–macrophage colony stimulating factor [GM-CSF] antibody-negative pulmonary alveolar proteinosis), thrombosis, and autoimmune features like autoimmune cytopenias, hepatitis, colitis, panniculitis, and arthritis. Immunological   laboratory findings can include deficiencies of the following: dendritic cells, monocytes, transitional B cells, and natural killer cells.  Patients with GATA2 deficiency can also have inverted CD4:CD8 ratios and hypogammaglobulinemia. Loss of B cells and their precursors was shown to be the most common feature in GATA2-deficient patients with MDS.<Reference refidx="12"/> Although not all patients with GATA2 deficiency present with immunological changes, a history of immunodeficiency in a patient with MDS/AML may be a strong indicator that a germline <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> pathogenic variant is present.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="13"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="34387894">Homan CC, Venugopal P, Arts P, et al.: GATA2 deficiency syndrome: A decade of discovery. Hum Mutat 42 (11): 1399-1421, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="34638133">Singh P, Heer M, Resteu A, et al.: GATA2 deficiency phenotype associated with tandem duplication of GATA2 and overexpression of GATA2-AS1. Blood Adv 5 (24): 5631-5635, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="21670465">Hsu AP, Sampaio EP, Khan J, et al.: Mutations in GATA2 are associated with the autosomal dominant and sporadic monocytopenia and mycobacterial infection (MonoMAC) syndrome. Blood 118 (10): 2653-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="23223431">Pasquet M, Bellanné-Chantelot C, Tavitian S, et al.: High frequency of GATA2 mutations in patients with mild chronic neutropenia evolving to MonoMac syndrome, myelodysplasia, and acute myeloid leukemia. Blood 121 (5): 822-9, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="24345756">Dickinson RE, Milne P, Jardine L, et al.: The evolution of cellular deficiency in GATA2 mutation. Blood 123 (6): 863-74, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="22147895">Kazenwadel J, Secker GA, Liu YJ, et al.: Loss-of-function germline GATA2 mutations in patients with MDS/AML or MonoMAC syndrome and primary lymphedema reveal a key role for GATA2 in the lymphatic vasculature. Blood 119 (5): 1283-91, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="25619630">Mir MA, Kochuparambil ST, Abraham RS, et al.: Spectrum of myeloid neoplasms and immune deficiency associated with germline GATA2 mutations. Cancer Med 4 (4): 490-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="21508125">Calvo KR, Vinh DC, Maric I, et al.: Myelodysplasia in autosomal dominant and sporadic monocytopenia immunodeficiency syndrome: diagnostic features and clinical implications. Haematologica 96 (8): 1221-5, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="25359990">Ganapathi KA, Townsley DM, Hsu AP, et al.: GATA2 deficiency-associated bone marrow disorder differs from idiopathic aplastic anemia. Blood 125 (1): 56-70, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="21892162">Hahn CN, Chong CE, Carmichael CL, et al.: Heritable GATA2 mutations associated with familial myelodysplastic syndrome and acute myeloid leukemia. Nat Genet 43 (10): 1012-7, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="26702063">Wlodarski MW, Hirabayashi S, Pastor V, et al.: Prevalence, clinical characteristics, and prognosis of GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndromes in children and adolescents. Blood 127 (11): 1387-97; quiz 1518, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="27013649">Nováková M, Žaliová M, Suková M, et al.: Loss of B cells and their precursors is the most constant feature of GATA-2 deficiency in childhood myelodysplastic syndrome. Haematologica 101 (6): 707-16, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="21765025">Dickinson RE, Griffin H, Bigley V, et al.: Exome sequencing identifies GATA-2 mutation as the cause of dendritic cell, monocyte, B and NK lymphoid deficiency. Blood 118 (10): 2656-8, 2011.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3756"><Title>Clinical Phenotypes in GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome</Title><Para id="_3757">Approximately half of reported  patients with <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> have  constitutional features   of GATA2 deficiency. Constitutional features of GATA2 deficiency include the following:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_3763" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460137" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Congenital</GlossaryTermRef> sensorineural deafness.</ListItem><ListItem>Lymphedema.</ListItem><ListItem>Hydrocele.</ListItem><ListItem>Urogenital malformations.</ListItem><ListItem>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) spectrum disorders.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3764">GATA2  deficiency prevalence is dependent upon several factors, including a patient's age and clinical manifestations. A myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) cohort study estimated that <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were present in approximately 0.5% of adults and 7% of children.<Reference refidx="1"/> Commonly acquired genetic lesions in GATA2 deficiency-related MDS include the following:<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> </Para><ItemizedList id="_3765" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Abnormal karyotypes   (monosomy 7, der(1;7)    <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000470251" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">translocation</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460223" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">trisomy</GlossaryTermRef> 8).</ListItem><ListItem>Somatic variants, particularly in the <GeneName>ASXL1</GeneName>, <GeneName>SETBP1</GeneName>, <GeneName>STAG2</GeneName>, and <GeneName>RUNX1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3766">In children with GATA2-related MDS, monosomy 7 has been reported in up to 70% to 80% of cases. However, in adults, the frequencies of both trisomy 8 and monosomy 7 were  approximately 20% to 40%.<Reference refidx="9"/> It is recommended that  monosomy 7 in a young patient trigger <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> germline testing, since up to 72% of adolescents with an MDS diagnosis and monosomy 7  carry germline <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="1"/> The der (1;7) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosomal</GlossaryTermRef> abnormality is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cytogenetic</GlossaryTermRef> lesion that is also enriched in patients with GATA2 deficiency.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_3767">The lifetime risk of developing myeloid neoplasms (MDS, myeloproliferative neoplasms, acute myeloid leukemia [AML]) is very high in individuals with GATA2 deficiency. The median age  of myeloid neoplasm diagnosis was estimated to be 12 years in pediatric cohorts <Reference refidx="1"/> and 35 years in adult cohorts.<Reference refidx="5"/>  Consolidated data from several studies suggest that the average age of myeloid neoplasm diagnosis was  20 years,<Reference refidx="9"/> and the median age of diagnosis is  17 years (range,  0–78 y).<Reference refidx="11"/> Infants  and young children  are typically not affected with myeloid malignancy or clinically relevant immunodeficiencies. However, these symptoms can manifest as early as age 4 to 5 years.<Reference refidx="1"/> The lifetime <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of GATA2 deficiency is high (estimated as &gt;80%), and thus far, only a small proportion of <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> carriers reported not having symptoms. </Para><Para id="_3768"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660739" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Genotype</GlossaryTermRef>/<GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef>  correlative studies found that lymphedema is associated with <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> null pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="11"/> However,  correlations between  <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variant type and hematopoietic malignancy development have not yet been established. Additional research is required to investigate whether different types of <GeneName>GATA2</GeneName> variants have differing penetrance rates.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26702063">Wlodarski MW, Hirabayashi S, Pastor V, et al.: Prevalence, clinical characteristics, and prognosis of GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndromes in children and adolescents. Blood 127 (11): 1387-97; quiz 1518, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="24227816">Spinner MA, Sanchez LA, Hsu AP, et al.: GATA2 deficiency: a protean disorder of hematopoiesis, lymphatics, and immunity. Blood 123 (6): 809-21, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="37406166">Homan CC, Drazer MW, Yu K, et al.: Somatic mutational landscape of hereditary hematopoietic malignancies caused by germline variants in RUNX1, GATA2, and DDX41. Blood Adv 7 (20): 6092-6107, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="36727400">Largeaud L, Collin M, Monselet N, et al.: Somatic genetic alterations predict hematological progression in GATA2 deficiency. Haematologica 108 (6): 1515-1529, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="24077845">West RR, Hsu AP, Holland SM, et al.: Acquired ASXL1 mutations are common in patients with inherited GATA2 mutations and correlate with myeloid transformation. Haematologica 99 (2): 276-81, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="27876779">Pastor V, Hirabayashi S, Karow A, et al.: Mutational landscape in children with myelodysplastic syndromes is distinct from adults: specific somatic drivers and novel germline variants. Leukemia 31 (3): 759-762, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="29296959">Fisher KE, Hsu AP, Williams CL, et al.: Somatic mutations in children with GATA2-associated myelodysplastic syndrome who lack other features of GATA2 deficiency. Blood Adv 1 (7): 443-448, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="30578959">McReynolds LJ, Yang Y, Yuen Wong H, et al.: MDS-associated mutations in germline GATA2 mutated patients with hematologic manifestations. Leuk Res 76: 70-75, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="28637621">Wlodarski MW, Collin M, Horwitz MS: GATA2 deficiency and related myeloid neoplasms. Semin Hematol 54 (2): 81-86, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="34469508">Kozyra EJ, Göhring G, Hickstein DD, et al.: Association of unbalanced translocation der(1;7) with germline GATA2 mutations. Blood 138 (23): 2441-2445, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="34387894">Homan CC, Venugopal P, Arts P, et al.: GATA2 deficiency syndrome: A decade of discovery. Hum Mutat 42 (11): 1399-1421, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3758"><Title>Management and Prognosis for GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome</Title><Para id="_3759">Consensus guidelines on the management of GATA2 deficiency do not yet exist, and hence, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> strategies are individually tailored for each patient. Most patients are followed by hematologists, immunologists, or   transplant physicians. General  GATA2 deficiency management recommendations include the following: periodic analysis of peripheral blood counts and immune status,  yearly bone marrow evaluation with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270737" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cytogenetics</GlossaryTermRef> and somatic variant testing, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> for human papillomavirus (HPV)–related cancers.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Patients   with severe cellular deficiencies   may require antimicrobial prophylaxis.<Reference refidx="3"/> Due to the risk of clonal evolution, treatment with  granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) is generally avoided in neutropenic patients with GATA2 deficiency.</Para><Para id="_3769">It  is widely accepted that timely hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) is the only curative approach for symptomatic GATA2-deficient patients. HSCT outcomes are influenced by several patient factors, including myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) subtype and the presence of a preexisting immunodeficiency. Overall survival (OS) rates for patients who underwent HSCT for various indications were reported as follows: 54% for MDS/acute myeloid leukemia (AML) or immunodeficiency,<Reference refidx="4"/>  66% in children with MDS and monosomy 7,<Reference refidx="5"/> 88% in children with refractory cytopenia of childhood (RCC)   and normal karyotypes,<Reference refidx="6"/> and 86% in young adults with immunodeficiency.<Reference refidx="7"/> Difficulty in predicting the disease’s course complicates decision making regarding  the optimal timing of HSCT. In 2021, researchers examined HSCT outcomes in 65 patients with GATA2-related MDS.<Reference refidx="8"/> Five years after HSCT, the probability of OS and disease-free survival (DFS) was 75% and 70%, respectively. Nonrelapse mortality and relapse equally contributed to treatment failure. There was no evidence of increased graft-versus-host-disease incidence, excessive rates of infections, or organ toxicities. Advanced MDS   and monosomy 7 were associated with worse outcomes. Patients who had RCC with normal karyotypes had better outcomes (DFS rate, 90%) when compared with those who had RCC and monosomy 7   (DFS rate, 67%).  </Para><Para id="_3770">HSCT  is indicated in GATA2-deficient patients  with the following: recurrent infections, transfusion dependency, or clonal evolution into a myeloid malignancy.<Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> Several  cases of donor-derived MDS/AML have been reported after HSCT in families with GATA2 deficiency.<Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> This emphasizes the need for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef>, assessment for the presence of GATA2-specific clinical features,    and genetic testing in potential <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef>    donors.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25707267">Collin M, Dickinson R, Bigley V: Haematopoietic and immune defects associated with GATA2 mutation. Br J Haematol 169 (2): 173-87, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="31808891">Davies SM: Monitoring and treatment of MDS in genetically susceptible persons. Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program 2019 (1): 105-109, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25397911">Hsu AP, McReynolds LJ, Holland SM: GATA2 deficiency. Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol 15 (1): 104-9, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="24227816">Spinner MA, Sanchez LA, Hsu AP, et al.: GATA2 deficiency: a protean disorder of hematopoiesis, lymphatics, and immunity. Blood 123 (6): 809-21, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="26702063">Wlodarski MW, Hirabayashi S, Pastor V, et al.: Prevalence, clinical characteristics, and prognosis of GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndromes in children and adolescents. Blood 127 (11): 1387-97; quiz 1518, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="34621053">Sahoo SS, Pastor VB, Goodings C, et al.: Clinical evolution, genetic landscape and trajectories of clonal hematopoiesis in SAMD9/SAMD9L syndromes. Nat Med 27 (10): 1806-1817, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="29412158">Parta M, Shah NN, Baird K, et al.: Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for GATA2 Deficiency Using a Busulfan-Based Regimen. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant 24 (6): 1250-1259, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="34244664">Bortnick R, Wlodarski M, de Haas V, et al.: Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in children and adolescents with GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndrome. Bone Marrow Transplant 56 (11): 2732-2741, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="36775010">Förster A, Davenport C, Duployez N, et al.: European standard clinical practice - Key issues for the medical care of individuals with familial leukemia. Eur J Med Genet 66 (4): 104727, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="36786081">Clark A, Thomas S, Hamblin A, et al.: Management of patients with germline predisposition to haematological malignancies considered for allogeneic blood and marrow transplantation: Best practice consensus guidelines from the UK Cancer Genetics Group (UKCGG), CanGene-CanVar, NHS England Genomic Laboratory Hub (GLH) Haematological Malignancies Working Group and the British Society of Blood and Marrow Transplantation and cellular therapy (BSBMTCT). Br J Haematol 201 (1): 35-44, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="33965189">Parta M, Cole K, Avila D, et al.: Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation and Outcomes Related to Human Papillomavirus Disease in GATA2 Deficiency. Transplant Cell Ther 27 (5): 435.e1-435.e11, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="30232126">Galera P, Hsu AP, Wang W, et al.: Donor-derived MDS/AML in families with germline GATA2 mutation. Blood 132 (18): 1994-1998, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="32865708">Sakata N, Okano M, Masako R, et al.: Donor-derived myelodysplastic syndrome after allogeneic stem cell transplantation in a family with germline GATA2 mutation. Int J Hematol 113 (2): 290-296, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3751"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to this Summary (08/22/2024)</Title><Para id="_1182">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3750">This is a new summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000814082#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gata2">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about GATA2 deficiency syndrome. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Julia Cooper, MS, CGC (Ohio State University)</ListItem><ListItem>Courtney DiNardo, MD, MSC (University of Texas, M.D. Anderson Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Marcin  Wlodarski, MD, PhD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ GATA2 Deficiency Syndrome. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gata2">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gata2</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2024-08-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-08-22</DateLastModified></Summary>
