<Summary id="CDR0000814294" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) is a hereditary gastric polyposis and cancer syndrome associated with the APC gene. Learn about GAPPS’ polyposis risk, cancer risks, and management. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gapps-hp-pdq">Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000039821">gastric cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1337">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS). It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_1338">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach (GAPPS) (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach (GAPPS) (PDQ®) </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach (GAPPS)</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_3751"><Title>Introduction to Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach (GAPPS)</Title><Para id="_3752">Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> syndrome caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in promoter 1B of the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Of note, large <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deletions</GlossaryTermRef> involving promoter 1B of the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene are associated with a different syndrome called familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/> GAPPS  was first described in 2012.<Reference refidx="2"/> This syndrome is characterized by numerous stomach polyps (predominantly fundic gland polyps in the body and fundus of the stomach, sparing the antrum), with regions of dysplasia.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="5"/> GAPPS is not  typically associated with colorectal polyposis.  The risk of intestinal-type gastric adenocarcinoma appears to be significantly elevated in GAPPS, but the exact risk of this is currently unknown.</Para><Para id="_3762">GAPPS  and FAP are both caused by pathogenic or likely pathogenic variants in the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene, but they are distinct syndromes with different clinical characteristics. In GAPPS, polyposis and cancer risk are primarily confined to the stomach, while in FAP, polyposis and cancer risk are elevated in the colon. FAP is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000754220" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">hereditary cancer syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> characterized by colorectal polyposis and a 93% risk of colorectal adenocarcinoma.    Pathogenic or likely pathogenic variants in promoter 1B of the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene are <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454769" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathognomonic</GlossaryTermRef> of GAPPS and do not lead to FAP. In contrast, FAP is caused by germline pathogenic variants elsewhere in the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene or large deletions in promoter 1B. For more information about FAP, refer to the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_3205" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">FAP</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer.</Para><Para id="_3763">Environmental risk factors have not been reported to cause or modify the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of GAPPS. Although studies have speculated that there is an inverse relationship between gastric neoplasia and <Emphasis>Helicobacter pylori</Emphasis> infection, further  research is warranted to clarify how <Emphasis>H. pylori</Emphasis> impacts gastric neoplasia in individuals with GAPPS.<Reference refidx="6"/>  </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="27087319">Li J, Woods SL, Healey S, et al.: Point Mutations in Exon 1B of APC Reveal Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach as a Familial Adenomatous Polyposis Variant. Am J Hum Genet 98 (5): 830-842, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21813476">Worthley DL, Phillips KD, Wayte N, et al.: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS): a new autosomal dominant syndrome. Gut 61 (5): 774-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25941542">Lin Y, Lin S, Baxter MD, et al.: Novel APC promoter and exon 1B deletion and allelic silencing in three mutation-negative classic familial adenomatous polyposis families. Genome Med 7 (1): 42, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25243319">Snow AK, Tuohy TM, Sargent NR, et al.: APC promoter 1B deletion in seven American families with familial adenomatous polyposis. Clin Genet 88 (4): 360-5, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="22027476">Yanaru-Fujisawa R, Nakamura S, Moriyama T, et al.: Familial fundic gland polyposis with gastric cancer. Gut 61 (7): 1103-4, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="33975682">Tacheci I, Repak R, Podhola M, et al.: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) - A Helicobacter-opposite point. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 50-51: 101728, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3753"><Title>Genetics of GAPPS</Title><Para id="_3754">Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) is caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in promoter 1B (regulatory region) of the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046657" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">tumor suppressor gene</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Of note, large <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deletions</GlossaryTermRef> involving promoter 1B result in a familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef>. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_3205" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">FAP</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></Para><Para id="_3764">The <GeneName>APC</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is located on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 5q21 and encodes a 2,843–amino acid protein that is important for cell adhesion and signal transduction processes.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> The APC protein regulates intracellular concentrations of beta-catenin, a major mediator of the Wnt signal transduction pathway.<Reference refidx="6"/>  For more information about the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_3253" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Genetics of FAP</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer.</Para><Para id="_3765">A 2016 study identified that germline pathogenic variants in promoter 1B of the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene cause GAPPS.<Reference refidx="1"/> The study included six families who all previously tested negative for germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>APC</GeneName>. However, regulatory regions in <GeneName>APC</GeneName>,  like promoter 1B, were not included in  their original  testing.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Whole genome sequencing</GlossaryTermRef> was also performed in these families, and it failed to identify novel or rare genetic variants that cosegregated with GAPPS. After a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000464169" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">loss of heterozygosity</GlossaryTermRef> was identified in fundic gland polyps on chromosome 5 in a 46-Mb region containing the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene, the researchers  pursued <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763028" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Sanger sequencing</GlossaryTermRef> of the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene's promoter 1A and promoter 1B in family members affected with GAPPS.<Reference refidx="1"/> Sanger sequencing identified several pathogenic variants in the promoter 1B region of <GeneName>APC</GeneName>, including   <GeneName>APC</GeneName> c.-191T&gt;C variants in four families with GAPPS, an <GeneName>APC</GeneName> c.-192A&gt;G variant in one family with GAPPS, and an <GeneName>APC</GeneName> c.-195A&gt;C variant in one family with GAPPS.  These  <GeneName>APC</GeneName> pathogenic variants reside within the Ying Yang 1 binding motif of promoter 1B, and hence,  reduce   <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcriptional</GlossaryTermRef> activity of <GeneName>APC</GeneName>. The study  also reported that a second <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic</GlossaryTermRef> hit in  <GeneName>APC</GeneName> occurred in most fundic gland polyps in relatives with GAPPS, either via loss of the wild-type <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339337" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">allele</GlossaryTermRef> or acquisition of protein-truncating variants.</Para><Para id="_3766">Since GAPPS was first described in the literature, over 20 families with the syndrome have been identified in Australia, North America, Europe, and Japan.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/>  However, the population prevalence and geographic distribution of GAPPS is elusive. This phenomenon may be due to the following: 1) disparate access to diagnostic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> modalities that can identify gastric lesions, and 2) few   laboratories offer sequencing analysis of <GeneName>APC</GeneName>'s promoter 1B.<Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="27087319">Li J, Woods SL, Healey S, et al.: Point Mutations in Exon 1B of APC Reveal Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach as a Familial Adenomatous Polyposis Variant. Am J Hum Genet 98 (5): 830-842, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25941542">Lin Y, Lin S, Baxter MD, et al.: Novel APC promoter and exon 1B deletion and allelic silencing in three mutation-negative classic familial adenomatous polyposis families. Genome Med 7 (1): 42, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25243319">Snow AK, Tuohy TM, Sargent NR, et al.: APC promoter 1B deletion in seven American families with familial adenomatous polyposis. Clin Genet 88 (4): 360-5, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="1651562" MedlineID="91335210">Kinzler KW, Nilbert MC, Su LK, et al.: Identification of FAP locus genes from chromosome 5q21. Science 253 (5020): 661-5, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="1651563">Nishisho I, Nakamura Y, Miyoshi Y, et al.: Mutations of chromosome 5q21 genes in FAP and colorectal cancer patients. Science 253 (5020): 665-9, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="8259518">Rubinfeld B, Souza B, Albert I, et al.: Association of the APC gene product with beta-catenin. Science 262 (5140): 1731-4, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21813476">Worthley DL, Phillips KD, Wayte N, et al.: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS): a new autosomal dominant syndrome. Gut 61 (5): 774-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="22027476">Yanaru-Fujisawa R, Nakamura S, Moriyama T, et al.: Familial fundic gland polyposis with gastric cancer. Gut 61 (7): 1103-4, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="27343414">Repak R, Kohoutova D, Podhola M, et al.: The first European family with gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach: case report and review of the literature. Gastrointest Endosc 84 (4): 718-25, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="34581903">Grossman A, Colavito J, Levine J, et al.: Filling in the "GAPPS": an unusual presentation of a child with gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach. Gastric Cancer 25 (2): 468-472, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="31409086">Foretová L, Navrátilová M, Svoboda M, et al.: GAPPS - Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach Syndrome in 8 Families Tested at Masaryk Memorial Cancer Institute - Prevention and Prophylactic Gastrectomies. Klin Onkol 32 (Supplementum2): 109-117, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="35435526">Iwakawa Y, Yoshikawa K, Okamoto K, et al.: Four cases of gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach treated by robotic total gastrectomy. Surg Case Rep 8 (1): 70, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="25439075">Herrero R, Park JY, Forman D: The fight against gastric cancer - the IARC Working Group report. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 28 (6): 1107-14, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="14">National Library of Medicine: Genetic Testing Registry. Bethesda, MD: National Library of Medicine. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gtr/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 23, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3755"><Title>Genetic Testing for GAPPS</Title><Para id="_3756">Consensus genetic testing guidelines specific to gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) do  not yet exist. Proposed diagnostic criteria for GAPPS include a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339341" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef>  <GeneName>APC</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef> in promoter 1B <Strong>and</Strong> all of the following:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_3767" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>More than 100 proximal gastric polyps with antral sparing in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460211" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">proband</GlossaryTermRef> <Strong>or</Strong> more than 30 gastric polyps in an individual who has  a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460150" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">first-degree relative</GlossaryTermRef> with GAPPS.</ListItem><ListItem>The proband's gastric polyps primarily have fundic gland pathology  (some with dysplasia), <Strong>or</Strong> the proband has  a family member with a history of dysplastic fundic gland polyps or  gastric adenocarcinoma.</ListItem><ListItem>Proband does not have a history of duodenal or colorectal polyposis.</ListItem><ListItem>Gastric polyps and gastric adenocarcinoma in the family follow an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> inheritance pattern.</ListItem><ListItem>Other causes of gastric polyposis have been ruled out (i.e., other <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781848" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heritable</GlossaryTermRef> gastric polyposis syndromes and the use of proton pump inhibitors).</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_3768">However, GAPPS should be suspected in patients with 100 or more proximal gastric polyps with antral sparing, the absence of colorectal polyposis, and the presence of a germline pathogenic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant</GlossaryTermRef> in the promoter 1B region of the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>. Individuals are at the greatest risk for GAPPS if they have a biological relative with clinical features of GAPPS and/or a known germline pathogenic variant in promoter 1B of the <GeneName>APC</GeneName> gene. Clinical-grade, diagnostic genetic testing for GAPPS is available at Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)-certified laboratories. Although many laboratories in the United States offer germline <GeneName>APC</GeneName> genetic testing, only a few perform sequence analysis of promoter 1B for the pathogenic variants that cause GAPPS.<Reference refidx="3"/> Therefore, when patients have personal and/or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family histories</GlossaryTermRef> that are suggestive of GAPPS, <GeneName>APC</GeneName> genetic testing must be ordered from one of these laboratories.</Para><Para id="_3769">Primary differential diagnoses for GAPPS include the following:</Para><ItemizedList id="_3770" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><Strong>Classic and attenuated familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP)</Strong>. In both classic and attenuated FAP, fundic gland polyps are observed in up to 89% of cases (fundic gland polyps carpet the stomach in 25% of cases).<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> The hallmark feature of both classic and attenuated FAP is colonic polyposis followed by duodenal polyposis. In GAPPS, affected individuals notably lack duodenal and colorectal polyposis. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_3205" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Familial Adenomatous Polyposis</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong><GeneName>MUTYH</GeneName>-associated polyposis (MAP)</Strong>. The gastric manifestations of MAP are attenuated when compared with those associated with FAP. However, more research on MAP-related gastric manifestations is necessary. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_433" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq"><GeneName>MUTYH</GeneName>-Associated Polyposis</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Proton pump inhibitor–induced gastric polyposis</Strong>. Sporadic fundic gland polyps can be seen in 3% to 5% of patients in the general population who use proton pump inhibitors.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> These polyps tend to be isolated, are less than 5 mm in size, and do not show signs of  dysplasia. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_1340" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">Introduction</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Gastric Cancer.</ListItem><ListItem><Strong>Hamartomatous polyposis syndromes</Strong>. The hamartomatous polyposis syndromes include <GeneName>PTEN</GeneName> tumor hamartoma syndromes, juvenile polyposis syndrome, and Peutz-Jeghers syndrome. Patients with these syndromes can present with gastric polyposis (including fundic gland polyps), although pathology usually includes hamartomatous polyps as well. Furthermore, gastric polyposis occurs in the antrum —an area of the stomach that  is spared in individuals with GAPPS.<Reference refidx="1"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_2559" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq"><GeneName>PTEN</GeneName> hamartoma tumor syndromes (including Cowden syndrome)</SummaryRef>, <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_2920" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Peutz-Jeghers syndrome</SummaryRef>, and <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062863#_647" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colorectal-genetics-pdq">Juvenile polyposis syndrome</SummaryRef> sections in Genetics of Colorectal Cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="30584346">Rudloff U: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach: diagnosis and clinical perspectives. Clin Exp Gastroenterol 11: 447-459, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="21813476">Worthley DL, Phillips KD, Wayte N, et al.: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS): a new autosomal dominant syndrome. Gut 61 (5): 774-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="3">National Library of Medicine: Genetic Testing Registry. Bethesda, MD: National Library of Medicine. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gtr/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 23, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="18237868">Bianchi LK, Burke CA, Bennett AE, et al.: Fundic gland polyp dysplasia is common in familial adenomatous polyposis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 6 (2): 180-5, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="28185118">Mankaney G, Leone P, Cruise M, et al.: Gastric cancer in FAP: a concerning rise in incidence. Fam Cancer 16 (3): 371-376, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="12118109">Torbenson M, Lee JH, Cruz-Correa M, et al.: Sporadic fundic gland polyposis: a clinical, histological, and molecular analysis. Mod Pathol 15 (7): 718-23, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="18322941">Freeman HJ: Proton pump inhibitors and an emerging epidemic of gastric fundic gland polyposis. World J Gastroenterol 14 (9): 1318-20, 2008.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25187299">Huang CZ, Lai RX, Mai L, et al.: Relative risk factors associated with the development of fundic gland polyps. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 26 (11): 1217-21, 2014.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3757"><Title>Clinical Features of GAPPS</Title><SummarySection id="_3771"><Title>Gastric Manifestations in GAPPS</Title><Para id="_3772">A key feature of gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) is extensive fundic gland polyposis in the proximal regions of the stomach with antral (distal) sparing. For more information,  see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_3753" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">Gastric polyps</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Gastric Cancer.<Reference refidx="1"/> Since GAPPS is rare, literature on this syndrome primarily exists in the form of case reports and case series.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> The incidence of gastric adenocarcinoma (intestinal or mixed types) in patients with GAPPS  is 12% to  25% with age of diagnosis ranging from 23 years to 75 years.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>  Fundic gland polyposis (which precedes gastric adenocarcinoma) has occurred as early as 8 years in patients with GAPPS.<Reference refidx="8"/> Gastric polyps range in size, with most polyps measuring less than  1 cm.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> However, in GAPPS, gastric polyps can grow up to 4 cm in size. These polyps  can be densely packed with extensive  carpeting that covers the gastric mucosa without any visible normal mucosa. Most gastric polyps in GAPPS have fundic gland pathology with or without dysplasia. However, other pathologies are also seen, including hyperplastic polyps, adenomas, and hyperproliferative aberrant crypts. In a histological review of 25 patients, 15 patients had  abnormal endoscopic biopsies.<Reference refidx="6"/> Of these 15 individuals, 10 had hyperproliferative aberrant crypts, 10  had fundic gland polyps, 6 had gastric adenomas, 1 had an adenoma associated with gastric adenocarcinoma, and 1 had gastric adenocarcinoma. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of fundic gland polyposis and gastric adenocarcinoma can vary  between different families and among family members with the same <GeneName>APC</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef>. In a study of 24 Czech patients from 8 families (all had the same <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> c.-191T&gt;C  <GeneName>APC</GeneName> promotor 1B <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant</GlossaryTermRef>), some developed gastric polyposis in their 20s while others had not yet  developed polyposis at age 65 years.<Reference refidx="5"/> Five individuals in this study developed gastric adenocarcinoma between the ages of 29 years and 64 years.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3773"><Title>Colorectal Manifestations in GAPPS</Title><Para id="_3774">Individuals with GAPPS may also have a propensity to develop colon polyps, although polyps are not thought to develop at an earlier age than those seen in the general population.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="9"/> It has been postulated that <GeneName>APC</GeneName>'s promoter 1A compensates for  promoter 1B's dysfunction in the colonic mucosa, likely sparing  the colorectum of polyposis.  However, promoter 1A is methylated in the gastric mucosa, resulting in isolated gastric polyposis.<Reference refidx="10"/> Nevertheless, GAPPS is caused by pathogenic variants in the same <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> (<GeneName>APC</GeneName>) that causes familial adenomatous polyposis  and can therefore, theoretically  increase risk of colonic neoplasia.</Para><Para id="_3775">Clinicopathologic evaluation of two families with GAPPS <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotypes</GlossaryTermRef> (based on clinical criteria) demonstrated  that seven of nine affected individuals had colon pathology.<Reference refidx="9"/> In contrast, the six <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460150" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">first-degree relatives</GlossaryTermRef> (FDRs) in the study without GAPPS diagnoses had normal colonoscopies.  In this study, the average age of individuals with GAPPS was 43.9 years (range, 20–71 y), whereas the average age of FDRs without GAPPS was 32.2 years (range, 18–51 y). In the GAPPS group, four of nine individuals had tubular adenomas in the colon, the youngest of whom was 48 years old. The colorectal polyps in individuals with GAPPS had increased beta-catenin, Ki67, and p53 expression. This expression pattern was also noted in the fundic gland polyps of these individuals, suggesting that  GAPPS may be responsible. In the first paper that described GAPPS, 13 individuals with GAPPS underwent colonoscopy,  in which six individuals (age, 18–37 y) did not have polyps,  three individuals (age, 31–56 y) had tubular adenomas (including a 46-year-old individual who developed eight tubular adenomas over 4 years), and  four individuals had  hyperplastic polyps  (one was located in the proximal colon, and the rest were located  in the rectosigmoid colon).<Reference refidx="7"/> Notably, none of the individuals had colonic polyposis. Colonoscopy findings were available for  eight family members who did not have GAPPS. Three of these individuals (age, 55–77 y) had a single tubular adenoma with or without villous features. The other five individuals were less than 45 years old (age, 29–36 y) and had normal colonoscopies. In contrast to these studies, a report from eight French families with an <GeneName>APC</GeneName> pathogenic variant in promoter 1B revealed colonic polyposis in multiple members, which required colectomy.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/> When these data are taken together, it is unclear whether individuals with GAPPS develop colonic neoplasia any earlier than individuals in the general population. However, there appears to be a trend in which individuals with GAPPS develop more polyps than individuals in the general population.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25187299">Huang CZ, Lai RX, Mai L, et al.: Relative risk factors associated with the development of fundic gland polyps. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 26 (11): 1217-21, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="27343414">Repak R, Kohoutova D, Podhola M, et al.: The first European family with gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach: case report and review of the literature. Gastrointest Endosc 84 (4): 718-25, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="29968043">Mitsui Y, Yokoyama R, Fujimoto S, et al.: First report of an Asian family with gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) revealed with the germline mutation of the APC exon 1B promoter region. Gastric Cancer 21 (6): 1058-1063, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="29141268">Beer A, Streubel B, Asari R, et al.: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) - a rare recently described gastric polyposis syndrome - report of a case. Z Gastroenterol 55 (11): 1131-1134, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="31409086">Foretová L, Navrátilová M, Svoboda M, et al.: GAPPS - Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach Syndrome in 8 Families Tested at Masaryk Memorial Cancer Institute - Prevention and Prophylactic Gastrectomies. Klin Onkol 32 (Supplementum2): 109-117, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="29112017">de Boer WB, Ee H, Kumarasinghe MP: Neoplastic Lesions of Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis Syndrome (GAPPS) Are Gastric Phenotype. Am J Surg Pathol 42 (1): 1-8, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="21813476">Worthley DL, Phillips KD, Wayte N, et al.: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS): a new autosomal dominant syndrome. Gut 61 (5): 774-9, 2012.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="34581903">Grossman A, Colavito J, Levine J, et al.: Filling in the "GAPPS": an unusual presentation of a child with gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach. Gastric Cancer 25 (2): 468-472, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="27406052">McDuffie LA, Sabesan A, Allgäeuer M, et al.: β-Catenin activation in fundic gland polyps, gastric cancer and colonic polyps in families afflicted by 'gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach' (GAPPS). J Clin Pathol 69 (9): 826-33, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="27087319">Li J, Woods SL, Healey S, et al.: Point Mutations in Exon 1B of APC Reveal Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach as a Familial Adenomatous Polyposis Variant. Am J Hum Genet 98 (5): 830-842, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="20685668">Lagarde A, Rouleau E, Ferrari A, et al.: Germline APC mutation spectrum derived from 863 genomic variations identified through a 15-year medical genetics service to French patients with FAP. J Med Genet 47 (10): 721-2, 2010.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3759"><Title>Management for GAPPS</Title><Para id="_3760">Consensus guidelines for management of gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) do not exist, given the rarity of this syndrome and the dearth of GAPPS literature (aside from case reports or case series). Furthermore, the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000792352" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">incomplete penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of GAPPS and its large age range of polyposis onset/gastric adenocarcinoma incidence makes creating uniform management recommendations challenging. The literature frequently recommends that providers use an individualized management approach for patients with GAPPS, with frequent upper endoscopic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> and extensive sampling of gastric polyps.<Reference refidx="1"/> The literature also suggests discussing gastrectomy planning early with a   multidisciplinary team.</Para><Para id="_3776">The goal of gastric endoscopic surveillance is to detect morphological or histological changes that increase risk for gastric adenocarcinoma. Generally, the detection of fundic gland dysplasia in GAPPS  prompts heightened gastric cancer surveillance with more frequent endoscopic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> and discussions about risk-reducing gastrectomy with a multidisciplinary team. However, the natural progression in histology from fundic gland polyp to adenocarcinoma (including the precursor lesion to adenocarcinoma) is unknown.  It has been hypothesized that hyperproliferative crypts found on pathology may  be precursors to fundic gland polyps and adenomas in patients with GAPPS.<Reference refidx="2"/> In addition to understanding the histological precursors of gastric adenocarcinoma, endoscopically identifying them is challenging, since they may easily be hidden or missed in the setting of dense polyp carpeting. For example, in a study, four members of a European family had GAPPS and developed gastric adenocarcinoma while under endoscopic surveillance.<Reference refidx="3"/> In two of these individuals, gastric adenocarcinoma was identified in their gastrectomy specimens.</Para><Para id="_3777">Given the variable <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of GAPPS, the correlation between gastric adenocarcinoma and clinical features (such as age, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family history</GlossaryTermRef>, degree of polyposis, and pathology of polyps) is unknown. However, given the high incidence of gastric adenocarcinoma seen in those with GAPPS (even when patients participate in gastric surveillance), discussion about risk-reducing gastrectomy with a multidisciplinary team may be warranted. Risk-reducing gastrectomy has been recommended when dysplasia is present.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_3778">There are no consensus guidelines for colorectal surveillance in patients with GAPPS. Therefore, patients are managed based on their family histories of colorectal polyps/cancer with consideration of a baseline colonoscopy  to exclude colonic polyposis.<Reference refidx="6"/></Para><Para id="_3779"><LOERef href="CDR0000526280" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence: 5</LOERef></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="30584346">Rudloff U: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach: diagnosis and clinical perspectives. Clin Exp Gastroenterol 11: 447-459, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="29112017">de Boer WB, Ee H, Kumarasinghe MP: Neoplastic Lesions of Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis Syndrome (GAPPS) Are Gastric Phenotype. Am J Surg Pathol 42 (1): 1-8, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27343414">Repak R, Kohoutova D, Podhola M, et al.: The first European family with gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach: case report and review of the literature. Gastrointest Endosc 84 (4): 718-25, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="33975682">Tacheci I, Repak R, Podhola M, et al.: Gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS) - A Helicobacter-opposite point. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol 50-51: 101728, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="34554346">Matsumoto C, Iwatsuki M, Iwagami S, et al.: Prophylactic laparoscopic total gastrectomy for gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach (GAPPS): the first report in Asia. Gastric Cancer 25 (2): 473-478, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="6">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Colorectal. Version 2.2023 . Plymouth Meeting, PA: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_colon.pdf">Available with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed March 13, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3761"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (01/03/2025)</Title><Para id="_1182">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_3780">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000814294#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gapps-hp-pdq ">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of gastric adenocarcinoma and proximal polyposis of the stomach. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach (GAPPS) are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Grace-Ann O. Fasaye, ScM, CGC (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Gautam Mankaney, MD (Virginia Mason Franciscan Health)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ Gastric Adenocarcinoma and Proximal Polyposis of the Stomach (GAPPS). Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gapps-hp-pdq ">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/gapps-hp-pdq </ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 38630970]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2024-04-10</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-01-03</DateLastModified></Summary>
