<Summary id="CDR0000815191" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Tissue-agnostic targeted therapies are a promising treatment strategy tailored to the specific tumor genomic profile, leading to improved patient survival outcomes. Get comprehensive information on agnostic cancer therapies in this clinician summary.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/agnostic-cancer-therapies-hp-pdq">Agnostic Cancer Therapies (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038974">unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about agnostic therapies for cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Agnostic Cancer Therapies (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Agnostic Cancer Therapies (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Agnostic Cancer Therapies</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_3"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038974">unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_4">The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved both gene- and immune-targeted drugs for tissue-agnostic, genomic biomarker–based indications in patients with lethal solid tumors and blood cancers. High response rates were the basis for these approvals.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para><Para id="_21">Precision medicine has rapidly changed the oncology field. Next-generation sequencing can identify patients with specific gene alterations or immune markers for which there are targeted therapies. Biomarker-based treatments are increasingly emerging, and the FDA has approved the following  tissue-agnostic therapies:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_285" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Pembrolizumab.</ListItem><ListItem>Dostarlimab.</ListItem><ListItem>Entrectinib.</ListItem><ListItem>Larotrectinib.</ListItem><ListItem>Repotrectinib.</ListItem><ListItem>Dabrafenib in combination with trametinib.</ListItem><ListItem>Selpercatinib.</ListItem><ListItem>Pemigatinib.</ListItem><ListItem>Trastuzumab deruxtecan.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_22">Precision medicine is constantly evolving, and improved diagnostic tools allow for  more comprehensive genomic definition of the tumor. Tissue-agnostic targeted therapies are a promising treatment strategy tailored to the specific tumor genomic profile, leading to improved patient survival outcomes.</Para><Para id="_23">The list of drugs approved for tumors with genomic alterations will likely expand as understanding of the science driving these cancers continues to advance. As oncology drug development continues to move rapidly, the location where the cancer originated will become less critical.</Para><Para id="_24">Companion tests can determine the presence of specific genomic alterations or immune markers. These tests may have been approved by the FDA as part of the agnostic drug approval. Most insurance companies have not required these specific tests before covering the prescribed medications.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="38102355">Adashek JJ, Kato S, Sicklick JK, et al.: Considering molecular alterations as pan-cancer tissue-agnostic targets. Nat Cancer 4 (12): 1622-1626, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="37111371">Tateo V, Marchese PV, Mollica V, et al.: Agnostic Approvals in Oncology: Getting the Right Drug to the Right Patient with the Right Genomics. Pharmaceuticals (Basel) 16 (4): , 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_5"><Title>Microsatellite Instability–High or Mismatch Repair–Deficient Solid Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_25"><Title>	Pembrolizumab</Title><Para id="_208"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> Pembrolizumab is indicated for adult and pediatric patients with unresectable or metastatic, microsatellite instability–high (MSI-H)/microsatellite unstable or mismatch repair–deficient (dMMR) solid tumors whose disease progressed after prior treatment and who have no satisfactory alternative treatment options.  The MSI-H phenotype is associated with germline defects in the <GeneName>MLH1</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH2</GeneName>, <GeneName>MSH6</GeneName>, and <GeneName>PMS2</GeneName> genes and is the primary phenotype observed in tumors from patients with hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancer or Lynch syndrome. Patients can also have the MSI-H phenotype because one of these genes was silenced via DNA methylation. Molecular genetic tests look for microsatellite instability in the tumor tissue, and immunohistochemistry tests for the loss of mismatch repair proteins. For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062687#_645" url="/types/colorectal/hp/colon-treatment-pdq">Immunotherapy</SummaryRef> section in Colon Cancer Treatment.</Para><Para id="_209"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approval was based on data from the following five uncontrolled, multicohort, multicenter, single-arm clinical trials that included 149 patients with MSI-H or dMMR cancers:<Reference refidx="1"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_286" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01876511">KEYNOTE-016</ProtocolRef> (NCT01876511) (median follow-up, 5.3 months).<Reference refidx="2"/></ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02460198">KEYNOTE-164</ProtocolRef> (NCT02460198) (median follow-up, 31.3 months).<Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01848834">KEYNOTE-012</ProtocolRef> (NCT01848834) (median follow-up, 9 months).<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02054806">KEYNOTE-028</ProtocolRef> (NCT02054806) (median follow-up, 9.8 months).<Reference refidx="5"/></ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02628067">KEYNOTE-158</ProtocolRef> (NCT02628067) (median follow-up, 13.4 months).<Reference refidx="6"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_287"> These trials included 90 patients with colorectal cancer and 59 patients with other cancers who were diagnosed with one of 14 other cancer types. Patients received either 200 mg of pembrolizumab every 3 weeks or 10 mg/kg of pembrolizumab every 2 weeks.</Para><Para id="_210"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> The major efficacy outcome measures were objective response rate, assessed by blinded independent central radiologist review according to RECIST 1.1, and response duration. The pooled objective response rate was 39.6%. A total of 11 patients (7.4%) had a complete response and 48 patients (32.2%) had a  partial response. The objective response rate was 36% in patients with colorectal cancer, and 46% in patients with other cancers (95% confidence interval [CI], 33%–59%).<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/> Responses lasted 6 months or longer for 78% of patients who responded to pembrolizumab.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_211"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> For most patients (135 of 149), tumor status was prospectively determined using local laboratory-developed, investigational polymerase chain reaction (PCR) (for MSI-H) or immunohistochemistry (for dMMR).<Reference refidx="9"/> For 14 of the 149 patients, MSI-H status was determined in a retrospective assessment of tumor samples from 415 patients using a central laboratory-developed PCR test.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_43"><Title>	Dostarlimab</Title><Para id="_214"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> Dostarlimab is indicated for adult patients with dMMR recurrent or advanced solid tumors, as determined by an FDA-approved test, whose disease progressed during or after prior treatment and who have no satisfactory alternative treatment options. This indication is not approved in the pediatric population. </Para><Para id="_215"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02715284">GARNET</ProtocolRef> (NCT02715284) was a nonrandomized, multicenter, open-label, multicohort trial that evaluated the efficacy of dostarlimab.<Reference refidx="10"/> The expansion cohorts were as follows:<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><OrderedList id="_268" Style="Arabic"><ListItem>dMMR/MSI-H endometrial cancers.</ListItem><ListItem>Mismatch repair–proficient or microsatellite stable endometrial cancers.</ListItem><ListItem>Non-small cell lung cancers.</ListItem><ListItem>Non-endometrial dMMR/MSI-H and <GeneName>POLE</GeneName>-mutated cancers.</ListItem><ListItem>High-grade serous, endometrioid, or clear cell ovarian, fallopian tube, or primary peritoneal cancer without <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> variants.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_216"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> The efficacy population consisted of 209 patients with dMMR recurrent or advanced solid tumors whose disease progressed after systemic therapy and who had no satisfactory alternative treatment options. The objective response rate was 41.6% (95% CI, 34.9%–48.6%), with a 9.1% complete response rate and a 32.5% partial response rate. The median follow-up was 27.7 months.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_217"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> The VENTANA MMR RxDx Panel is a companion diagnostic device to select patients with dMMR solid tumors for treatment with dostarlimab.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="30787022">Marcus L, Lemery SJ, Keegan P, et al.: FDA Approval Summary: Pembrolizumab for the Treatment of Microsatellite Instability-High Solid Tumors. Clin Cancer Res 25 (13): 3753-3758, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="29284010">O'Neil BH, Wallmark JM, Lorente D, et al.: Safety and antitumor activity of the anti-PD-1 antibody pembrolizumab in patients with advanced colorectal carcinoma. PLoS One 12 (12): e0189848, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="31725351">Le DT, Kim TW, Van Cutsem E, et al.: Phase II Open-Label Study of Pembrolizumab in Treatment-Refractory, Microsatellite Instability-High/Mismatch Repair-Deficient Metastatic Colorectal Cancer: KEYNOTE-164. J Clin Oncol 38 (1): 11-19, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="29955135">Mehra R, Seiwert TY, Gupta S, et al.: Efficacy and safety of pembrolizumab in recurrent/metastatic head and neck squamous cell carcinoma: pooled analyses after long-term follow-up in KEYNOTE-012. Br J Cancer 119 (2): 153-159, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="28813164">Ott PA, Elez E, Hiret S, et al.: Pembrolizumab in Patients With Extensive-Stage Small-Cell Lung Cancer: Results From the Phase Ib KEYNOTE-028 Study. J Clin Oncol 35 (34): 3823-3829, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="31682550">Marabelle A, Le DT, Ascierto PA, et al.: Efficacy of Pembrolizumab in Patients With Noncolorectal High Microsatellite Instability/Mismatch Repair-Deficient Cancer: Results From the Phase II KEYNOTE-158 Study. J Clin Oncol 38 (1): 1-10, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="29020592">Lemery S, Keegan P, Pazdur R: First FDA Approval Agnostic of Cancer Site - When a Biomarker Defines the Indication. N Engl J Med 377 (15): 1409-1412, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="29754585">Boyiadzis MM, Kirkwood JM, Marshall JL, et al.: Significance and implications of FDA approval of pembrolizumab for biomarker-defined disease. J Immunother Cancer 6 (1): 35, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="33747906">Ren XY, Song Y, Wang J, et al.: Mismatch Repair Deficiency and Microsatellite Instability in Triple-Negative Breast Cancer: A Retrospective Study of 440 Patients. Front Oncol 11: 570623, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="37917058">André T, Berton D, Curigliano G, et al.: Antitumor Activity and Safety of Dostarlimab Monotherapy in Patients With Mismatch Repair Deficient Solid Tumors: A Nonrandomized Controlled Trial. JAMA Netw Open 6 (11): e2341165, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="35729005">Moreno V, Roda D, Pikiel J, et al.: Safety and Efficacy of Dostarlimab in Patients With Recurrent/Advanced Non-small Cell Lung Cancer: Results from Cohort E of the Phase I GARNET Trial. Clin Lung Cancer 23 (7): e415-e427, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="35064011">Oaknin A, Gilbert L, Tinker AV, et al.: Safety and antitumor activity of dostarlimab in patients with advanced or recurrent DNA mismatch repair deficient/microsatellite instability-high (dMMR/MSI-H) or proficient/stable (MMRp/MSS) endometrial cancer: interim results from GARNET-a phase I, single-arm study. J Immunother Cancer 10 (1): , 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="13">Berton D, Banerjee SN, Curigliano G, et al.: Antitumor activity of dostarlimab in patients with mismatch repair-deficient/microsatellite instability–high tumors: A combined analysis of two cohorts in the GARNET study. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  39 (Suppl 15): A-2564, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="14">Andre T, Berton D, Curigliano G, et al.: Efficacy and safety of dostarlimab in patients (pts) with mismatch repair deficient (dMMR) solid tumors: Analysis of 2 cohorts in the GARNET study. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  40 (Suppl 16): A-2587, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_6"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038974">unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Tumor Mutational Burden–High (≥10 Mutations/Megabase) Solid Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_64"><Title>	Pembrolizumab</Title><Para id="_220"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> Pembrolizumab is indicated for adult and pediatric patients with unresectable or metastatic tumor mutational burden–high (TMB-H) solid tumors, whose disease progressed after prior treatment and who have no satisfactory alternative treatment options. TMB-H is defined as ≥10 mutations/megabase (mut/Mb), as determined by a U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved test. </Para><Para id="_221"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> FDA approval was based on a retrospective analysis of 10 cohorts of patients with various previously treated unresectable or metastatic TMB-H solid tumors enrolled in <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02628067">KEYNOTE-158</ProtocolRef> (NCT02628067), a multicenter, nonrandomized, open-label trial. Patients received 200 mg of pembrolizumab intravenously every 3 weeks until unacceptable toxicity or documented disease progression.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_222"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> A total of 102 patients (13%) had TMB-H tumors (defined as TMB ≥10 mut/Mb). The objective response rate for these patients was 29% (95% confidence interval, 21%–39%), with a 4% complete response rate and 25% partial response rate.<Reference refidx="1"/> The median follow-up was 13.4 months.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_223"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> The FoundationOne CDx assay is a companion diagnostic test for pembrolizumab.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="32919526">Marabelle A, Fakih M, Lopez J, et al.: Association of tumour mutational burden with outcomes in patients with advanced solid tumours treated with pembrolizumab: prospective biomarker analysis of the multicohort, open-label, phase 2 KEYNOTE-158 study. Lancet Oncol 21 (10): 1353-1365, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="31682550">Marabelle A, Le DT, Ascierto PA, et al.: Efficacy of Pembrolizumab in Patients With Noncolorectal High Microsatellite Instability/Mismatch Repair-Deficient Cancer: Results From the Phase II KEYNOTE-158 Study. J Clin Oncol 38 (1): 1-10, 2020.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_8"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038974">unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title><GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> Gene Fusion–Positive Solid Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_85"><Title>	Entrectinib</Title><Para id="_226"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> Entrectinib is indicated for adult and pediatric patients with solid tumors and an <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> gene fusion without a known acquired resistance variant; with disease that is metastatic or where surgical resection is likely to result in severe morbidity; and who have disease progression after treatment or have no satisfactory standard therapy.</Para><Para id="_227"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> Five multicenter single-arm clinical trials evaluated the efficacy of entrectinib in patients with <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName>-positive tumors. Three of these trials evaluated a total of 54 adult patients who received entrectinib at various doses and schedules. Two of these trials evaluated a total of 33 pediatric patients.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_290" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02097810">ALKA-372-001</ProtocolRef>; adult patients.</ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02097810">STARTRK-1</ProtocolRef> (NCT02097810); adult patients.</ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02568267">STARTRK-2</ProtocolRef> (NCT02568267); adult patients.</ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02650401">STARTRK-NG</ProtocolRef> (NCT02650401); pediatric patients.</ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04589845">TAPISTRY</ProtocolRef> (NCT04589845); pediatric patients.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_228"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> Among the 54 adult patients, the overall response rate, as determined by independent review, was 57% (95% confidence interval [CI], 43%–71%). The median follow-up was 15 months.<Reference refidx="1"/> Among the 33 pediatric patients, the objective response rate was 70% (95% CI, 51%–84%), and the median duration of response was 25.4 months (95% CI, 14.3–not evaluable). The median follow-up was not defined.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_229"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> Identification of positive <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> gene fusion status was determined at local laboratories or a central laboratory using nucleic acid-based tests prior to enrollment. Not all <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> variants are gene fusions. Entrectinib has not shown clinical efficacy in patients with nonfusion <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> variants..</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_106"><Title>	Larotrectinib</Title><Para id="_232"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> Larotrectinib is indicated for adult and pediatric patients with solid tumors and an <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> gene fusion without a known acquired resistance variant; with disease that is metastatic or where surgical resection is likely to result in severe morbidity; and who have disease progression after treatment and have no satisfactory alternative treatment options.</Para><Para id="_233">	<Strong>Evidence.</Strong> U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approval was based on data from three multicenter, open-label, single-arm clinical trials: <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02122913">LOXO-TRK-14001</ProtocolRef> (NCT02122913), <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02637687">SCOUT</ProtocolRef> (NCT02637687), and <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02576431">NAVIGATE</ProtocolRef> (NCT02576431).<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_234"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> Among 55 patients with unresectable or metastatic solid tumors harboring an <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> gene fusion enrolled across the three trials, the overall response rate was 75% (95% CI, 61%–85%). The complete response rate was 22%, and the partial response rate was 53%. The median follow-up was 8.3 months.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_235"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> gene fusion status was prospectively determined at local laboratories using next-generation sequencing (NGS) or fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization (FISH). Not all <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> variants are gene fusions. Entrectinib has not shown clinical efficacy in patients with nonfusion <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> variants..</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_299"><Title>Repotrectinib</Title><Para id="_300"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> Repotrectinib is indicated for adult and pediatric patients with an <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> gene fusion and solid tumors that are locally advanced or metastatic for which surgical resection may cause severe morbidity.</Para><Para id="_301"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> FDA approval was based on data from <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03093116">TRIDENT-1</ProtocolRef> (NCT03093116), a multicenter, single-arm, open-label, multicohort trial.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><Para id="_302"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> In 88 adult patients with locally advanced or metastatic <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> gene fusion–positive solid tumors, the overall response rate was 58% (95% CI, 41%–73%) for patients who had not received prior NTRK tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs) (n = 40) and 50% (95% CI, 35%–65%) for patients who had previously received NTRK TKIs (n = 48). The median duration of response was not estimable in the TKI-naïve group and was 9.9 months (95% CI, 7.4–13.0) in the TKI-pretreated group. The median follow-up was 24.0 months.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para><Para id="_303"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> gene fusion status was prospectively determined at local laboratories using NGS, Sanger sequencing, reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction, or FISH. Not all <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> variants are gene fusions. Repotrectinib has not shown clinical efficacy in patients with nonfusion <GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> variants.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="28183697">Drilon A, Siena S, Ou SI, et al.: Safety and Antitumor Activity of the Multitargeted Pan-TRK, ROS1, and ALK Inhibitor Entrectinib: Combined Results from Two Phase I Trials (ALKA-372-001 and STARTRK-1). Cancer Discov 7 (4): 400-409, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="35395680">Desai AV, Robinson GW, Gauvain K, et al.: Entrectinib in children and young adults with solid or primary CNS tumors harboring NTRK, ROS1, or ALK aberrations (STARTRK-NG). Neuro Oncol 24 (10): 1776-1789, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="29466156">Drilon A, Laetsch TW, Kummar S, et al.: Efficacy of Larotrectinib in TRK Fusion-Positive Cancers in Adults and Children. N Engl J Med 378 (8): 731-739, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="29606586">Laetsch TW, DuBois SG, Mascarenhas L, et al.: Larotrectinib for paediatric solid tumours harbouring NTRK gene fusions: phase 1 results from a multicentre, open-label, phase 1/2 study. Lancet Oncol 19 (5): 705-714, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="5">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: FDA approves larotrectinib for solid tumors with NTRK gene fusions. U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2018. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/fda-approves-larotrectinib-solid-tumors-ntrk-gene-fusions">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 30, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="38197815">Drilon A, Camidge DR, Lin JJ, et al.: Repotrectinib in ROS1 Fusion-Positive Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer. N Engl J Med 390 (2): 118-131, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="7">Solomon BJ, Drilon A, Lin JJ, et al.: Repotrectinib in patients (pts) with NTRK fusion-positive (NTRK+) advanced solid tumors, including NSCLC: Update from the phase I/II TRIDENT-1 trial. [Abstract] Ann Oncol  34 (Suppl 2): A-787-788, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="8">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: FDA grants accelerated approval to repotrectinib for adult and pediatric patients with NTRK gene fusion-positive solid tumors. U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/resources-information-approved-drugs/fda-grants-accelerated-approval-repotrectinib-adult-and-pediatric-patients-ntrk-gene-fusion-positive">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 23, 2025.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_10"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038974">unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title><GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> V600E Variant–Positive Solid Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_139"><Title>	Dabrafenib in Combination With Trametinib</Title><Para id="_238"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> The combination of dabrafenib and trametinib is indicated for adult and pediatric patients aged 6 years or older with unresectable or metastatic solid tumors and a <GeneName>BRAF</GeneName> V600E variant. Patients must have progressive disease after prior treatment and have no satisfactory alternative treatment options. Dabrafenib in combination with trametinib is not indicated for patients with colorectal cancer because of known intrinsic resistance to BRAF inhibition.</Para><Para id="_239"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> The U.S. Food and Drug Administration approval was based on data from the following populations:<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_288" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Two open-label multiple cohort trials included 131 adult patients: <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02034110">BRF117019</ProtocolRef> (NCT02034110) (median follow-up, 47 weeks), and <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02465060">NCI-MATCH</ProtocolRef> (NCT02465060) protocol H (median follow-up, 23.0 months).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/></ListItem><ListItem> One trial included 36 pediatric patients: <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT02124772">CTMT212X2101</ProtocolRef> (NCT02124772) (median follow-up, not defined).<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_289">The approval was also supported by results from <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01072175">COMBI-d</ProtocolRef> (NCT01072175), <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01597908">COMBI-v</ProtocolRef> (NCT01597908), and <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT01336634">BRF113928</ProtocolRef> (NCT01336634).<Reference refidx="6"/> </Para><Para id="_240"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> For the 131 adult patients, the overall response rate was 41% (95% confidence interval [CI], 33%–50%). For the 36 pediatric patients, the overall response rate was 25% (95% CI, 12%–42%).<Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_241"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> Biomarker status was determined at a Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) or CLIA-equivalent laboratory.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="32818466">Subbiah V, Lassen U, Élez E, et al.: Dabrafenib plus trametinib in patients with BRAFV600E-mutated biliary tract cancer (ROAR): a phase 2, open-label, single-arm, multicentre basket trial. Lancet Oncol 21 (9): 1234-1243, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="34838156">Wen PY, Stein A, van den Bent M, et al.: Dabrafenib plus trametinib in patients with BRAFV600E-mutant low-grade and high-grade glioma (ROAR): a multicentre, open-label, single-arm, phase 2, basket trial. Lancet Oncol 23 (1): 53-64, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="32758030">Salama AKS, Li S, Macrae ER, et al.: Dabrafenib and Trametinib in Patients With Tumors With BRAFV600E Mutations: Results of the NCI-MATCH Trial Subprotocol H. J Clin Oncol 38 (33): 3895-3904, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="36884302">Whitlock JA, Geoerger B, Dunkel IJ, et al.: Dabrafenib, alone or in combination with trametinib, in BRAF V600-mutated pediatric Langerhans cell histiocytosis. Blood Adv 7 (15): 3806-3815, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="5">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: FDA grants accelerated approval to dabrafenib in combination with trametinib for unresectable or metastatic solid tumors with BRAF V600E mutation. U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2022. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/resources-information-approved-drugs/fda-grants-accelerated-approval-dabrafenib-combination-trametinib-unresectable-or-metastatic-solid">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 30, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="31166680">Robert C, Grob JJ, Stroyakovskiy D, et al.: Five-Year Outcomes with Dabrafenib plus Trametinib in Metastatic Melanoma. N Engl J Med 381 (7): 626-636, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_12"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038974">unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title><GeneName>RET</GeneName> Gene Fusion–Positive Solid Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_160"><Title>	Selpercatinib</Title><Para id="_244"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> Selpercatinib is indicated for adult patients with locally advanced or metastatic solid tumors with a <GeneName>RET</GeneName> gene fusion whose disease meets either of the following criteria: disease progressed during or after prior systemic treatment, or disease with no satisfactory alternative treatment options. This indication is not approved for the pediatric population. </Para><Para id="_245"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> Forty-one patients with <GeneName>RET</GeneName> gene fusion–positive tumors (other than non-small cell lung cancer [NSCLC] and thyroid cancer) with disease progression during or after prior systemic treatment or who had no satisfactory alternative treatment options were evaluated in the multicenter, open-label, multicohort <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03157128">LIBRETTO-001</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT03157128).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </Para><Para id="_246"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> For the 41 evaluable patients with cancers other than NSCLC or thyroid cancer, the objective response rate was 44% (95% confidence interval, 28%–60%). A total of 16 patients had a partial response and 2 patients had a complete response, with a median follow-up of 14.9 months.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/></Para><Para id="_247"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) or CLIA-equivalent locally obtained molecular testing was performed at a certified laboratory, with the use of either next-generation sequencing, fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization, or polymerase chain reaction assay.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Subbiah V, Wolf J, Konda B, et al.: Tumor agnostic efficacy of selpercatinib in patients with RET fusion+ solid tumors: A global, multicenter, registrational trial update (LIBRETTO-001). [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  40 (Suppl 16): A-3094, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="36108661">Subbiah V, Wolf J, Konda B, et al.: Tumour-agnostic efficacy and safety of selpercatinib in patients with RET fusion-positive solid tumours other than lung or thyroid tumours (LIBRETTO-001): a phase 1/2, open-label, basket trial. Lancet Oncol 23 (10): 1261-1273, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_14"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038974">unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title><GeneName>FGFR1</GeneName>-Rearranged Myeloid/Lymphoid Neoplasms</Title><SummarySection id="_181"><Title>	Pemigatinib</Title><Para id="_183"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> Pemigatinib is indicated for adult patients with relapsed or refractory myeloid/lymphoid neoplasms (MLNs) with an <GeneName>FGFR1</GeneName> rearrangement. This indication is not approved for the pediatric population.</Para><Para id="_250"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> Twenty-eight patients with relapsed or refractory MLNs with <GeneName>FGFR1</GeneName> rearrangement were evaluated in the multicenter open-label, single-arm <ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03011372">FIGHT-203</ProtocolRef> trial (NCT03011372). Eligible patients were either not candidates for, or had relapsed disease after, allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant or a disease-modifying therapy (e.g., chemotherapy).<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </Para><Para id="_251"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> For all 28 patients (including three patients without evidence of morphologic disease), the complete cytogenetic response rate was 79% (95% confidence interval [CI], 59%–92%). Among the 18 patients with chronic phase disease in the marrow with or without extramedullary disease (EMD), 14 achieved a complete response (78%; 95% CI, 52%–94%). Among the four patients with blast-phase disease in the marrow with or without EMD, two achieved a complete response (duration, 1+ and 94 days). For the three patients with EMD only, one achieved a complete response (duration, 64+ days) with a median follow-up of 25.3 months.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> </Para><Para id="_252"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> Biomarker identification was performed using local cytogenetics and both local and central fluorescence <Emphasis>in situ</Emphasis> hybridization results.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Verstovsek S, Gotlib J, Vannucchi AM, et al.: FIGHT-203, an ongoing phase 2 study of pemigatinib in patients with myeloid/lymphoid neoplasms (MLNs) with fibroblast growth factor receptor 1 (FGFR1) rearrangement (MLNFGFR1): A focus on centrally reviewed clinical and cytogenetic responses in previously treated patients. [Abstract] Blood  140 (Suppl 1): A-624, 3980-2, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="2">Gotlib J, Kiladjian J, Vannucchi A, et al.: A phase 2 study of pemigatinib (FIGHT-203; INCB054828) in patients with myeloid/lymphoid neoplasms (MLNs) with fibroblast growth factor receptor 1 (FGFR1) rearrangement (MLNFGFR1). [Abstract] Blood  138 (Suppl 1): A-634, 385, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_291"><Title>HER2–Expressing Solid Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_292"><Title>Trastuzumab Deruxtecan (T-DXd)</Title><Para id="_293"><Strong>Indication.</Strong> T-DXd is indicated for adult patients with unresectable or metastatic HER2-positive (immunohistochemistry [IHC] 3+) solid tumors who have received prior systemic treatment and have no satisfactory alternative treatment options.<Reference refidx="1"/> This indication is not approved in the pediatric population. </Para><Para id="_294"><Strong>Evidence.</Strong> One hundred ninety-two adult patients with previously treated unresectable or metastatic HER2-positive (IHC 3+) solid tumors were enrolled in one of the following three multicenter trials:<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para><ItemizedList id="_295" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04482309">DESTINY-PanTumor02</ProtocolRef> (NCT04482309).<Reference refidx="2"/> </ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT03505710">DESTINY-Lung01</ProtocolRef> (NCT03505710).<Reference refidx="3"/> </ListItem><ListItem><ProtocolRef nct_id="NCT04744831">DESTINY-CRC02</ProtocolRef> (NCT04744831).<Reference refidx="4"/></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_296"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> The objective response rates were as follows: </Para><ItemizedList id="_297" Style="bullet"><ListItem>51.4% (95% confidence interval [CI], 41.7%–61.0%) for patients in the DESTINY-PanTumor02 trial. </ListItem><ListItem>52.9% (95% CI, 27.8%–77.0%) for patients in the DESTINY-Lung01 trial. </ListItem><ListItem>46.9% (95% CI, 34.3%–59.8%) for patients in the DESTINY-CRC02 trial. </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_298"><Strong>Identification of biomarker.</Strong> Eligible patients had centrally confirmed HER2 positivity (IHC 3+).</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">U.S. Food and Drug Administration: FDA grants accelerated approval to fam-trastuzumab deruxtecan-nxki for unresectable or metastatic HER2-positive solid tumors. U.S. Food and Drug Administration, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/resources-information-approved-drugs/fda-grants-accelerated-approval-fam-trastuzumab-deruxtecan-nxki-unresectable-or-metastatic-her2">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 30, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="37870536">Meric-Bernstam F, Makker V, Oaknin A, et al.: Efficacy and Safety of Trastuzumab Deruxtecan in Patients With HER2-Expressing Solid Tumors: Primary Results From the DESTINY-PanTumor02 Phase II Trial. J Clin Oncol 42 (1): 47-58, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="34534430">Li BT, Smit EF, Goto Y, et al.: Trastuzumab Deruxtecan in HER2-Mutant Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer. N Engl J Med 386 (3): 241-251, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="4">Raghav KPS, Siena S, Takashima A, et al.: Trastuzumab deruxtecan (T-DXd) in patients (pts) with HER2-overexpressing/amplified (HER2+) metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC): Primary results from the multicenter, randomized, phase 2 DESTINY-CRC02 study. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  41 (Suppl 16): A-3501, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_16"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000038974">unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</SpecificDiagnosis></SectMetaData><Title>Potential Emerging Agnostic Targets Not Yet Approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration</Title><SummarySection id="_277"><Title>Tumor Mutational Burden–High (TMB-H) (≥16 Mutations/Megabase [mut/Mb]) Solid Tumors</Title><SummarySection id="_278"><Title>Atezolizumab</Title><Para id="_279"><Strong>Target and mechanism.</Strong> Atezolizumab blocks the interaction of programmed death-ligand 1 (PD-L1) with programmed cell death 1 (PD-1) and CD80 receptors (B7-1Rs).</Para><Para id="_280"><Strong>Current approvals.</Strong> Atezolizumab is approved for non-small cell lung cancer,<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> small-cell lung cancer,<Reference refidx="6"/> hepatocellular carcinoma,<Reference refidx="7"/> melanoma,<Reference refidx="8"/> and alveolar soft part sarcoma.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para><Para id="_281"><Strong>	Supporting study.</Strong> Atezolizumab was evaluated in a phase IIa, multibasket, MyPathway study. The preplanned primary end point was objective response rate in patients with TMB-H (≥16 mut/Mb) tumors by FoundationOne TMB testing.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_282"><Strong>	Study population.</Strong> This study included 120 patients with advanced solid tumors with TMB ≥10 mut/Mb by any Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)-certified assay. Among patients with local or central FoundationOne TMB testing results, 42 had TMB ≥16 mut/Mb tumors, comprising the primary efficacy population, and 49 had TMB ≥10 and &lt;16 mut/Mb tumors, of whom 48 were efficacy evaluable.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_283"><Strong>Efficacy.</Strong> In the primary analysis population of 42 patients with TMB ≥16 mut/Mb tumors, the confirmed objective response rate was 38.1% (95% confidence interval [CI], 23.6%–54.4%) and the disease-control rate (the best response of complete response, partial response, or stable disease &gt;4 months) was 61.9% (95% CI, 45.6%–76.4%), with a median follow-up of 9.9 months.<Reference refidx="10"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="34555333">Felip E, Altorki N, Zhou C, et al.: Adjuvant atezolizumab after adjuvant chemotherapy in resected stage IB-IIIA non-small-cell lung cancer (IMpower010): a randomised, multicentre, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet 398 (10308): 1344-1357, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="32997907">Herbst RS, Giaccone G, de Marinis F, et al.: Atezolizumab for First-Line Treatment of PD-L1-Selected Patients with NSCLC. N Engl J Med 383 (14): 1328-1339, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="29863955">Socinski MA, Jotte RM, Cappuzzo F, et al.: Atezolizumab for First-Line Treatment of Metastatic Nonsquamous NSCLC. N Engl J Med 378 (24): 2288-2301, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="31122901">West H, McCleod M, Hussein M, et al.: Atezolizumab in combination with carboplatin plus nab-paclitaxel chemotherapy compared with chemotherapy alone as first-line treatment for metastatic non-squamous non-small-cell lung cancer (IMpower130): a multicentre, randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 20 (7): 924-937, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="27979383">Rittmeyer A, Barlesi F, Waterkamp D, et al.: Atezolizumab versus docetaxel in patients with previously treated non-small-cell lung cancer (OAK): a phase 3, open-label, multicentre randomised controlled trial. Lancet 389 (10066): 255-265, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="30280641">Horn L, Mansfield AS, Szczęsna A, et al.: First-Line Atezolizumab plus Chemotherapy in Extensive-Stage Small-Cell Lung Cancer. N Engl J Med 379 (23): 2220-2229, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="32402160">Finn RS, Qin S, Ikeda M, et al.: Atezolizumab plus Bevacizumab in Unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma. N Engl J Med 382 (20): 1894-1905, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="36460017">Ascierto PA, Stroyakovskiy D, Gogas H, et al.: Overall survival with first-line atezolizumab in combination with vemurafenib and cobimetinib in BRAFV600 mutation-positive advanced melanoma (IMspire150): second interim analysis of a multicentre, randomised, phase 3 study. Lancet Oncol 24 (1): 33-44, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="37672694">Chen AP, Sharon E, O'Sullivan-Coyne G, et al.: Atezolizumab for Advanced Alveolar Soft Part Sarcoma. N Engl J Med 389 (10): 911-921, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="34876409">Friedman CF, Hainsworth JD, Kurzrock R, et al.: Atezolizumab Treatment of Tumors with High Tumor Mutational Burden from MyPathway, a Multicenter, Open-Label, Phase IIa Multiple Basket Study. Cancer Discov 12 (3): 654-669, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (02/12/2025)</Title><Para id="_19">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly and updated as
new information becomes available.  This section describes the latest
changes made to this summary as of the date above.</Para><Para id="_304"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000815191#_3" url="/about-cancer/treatment/types/agnostic-cancer-therapies-hp-pdq">Introduction</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_305">Revised the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000815191#_21" url="/about-cancer/treatment/types/agnostic-cancer-therapies-hp-pdq">list</SummaryRef> of U.S. Food and Drug Administration–approved tissue-agnostic therapies to include repotrectinib.</Para><Para id="_306"><Strong><SummaryRef href="CDR0000815191#_8" url="/about-cancer/treatment/types/agnostic-cancer-therapies-hp-pdq"><GeneName>NTRK</GeneName> Gene Fusion–Positive Solid Tumors</SummaryRef></Strong></Para><Para id="_307">Added <SummaryRef href="CDR0000815191#_299" url="/about-cancer/treatment/types/agnostic-cancer-therapies-hp-pdq">Repotrectinib</SummaryRef> as a new subsection.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000815191#_AboutThis_1" url="/about-cancer/treatment/types/agnostic-cancer-therapies-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about tissue-agnostic therapy for cancer. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewer for Agnostic Cancer Therapies is:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Jacob Adashek, DO (Consultant)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Agnostic Cancer Therapies. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/agnostic-cancer-therapies-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/agnostic-cancer-therapies-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 38771926]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2024-05-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-02-12</DateLastModified></Summary>
