<Summary id="CDR0000815943" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2 (RTPS2) is a hereditary cancer syndrome associated with the SMARCA4 gene. Learn about RTPS2's clinical features and management.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/rtps2-hp-pdq">Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
2 (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000725407">rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_2838">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics, cancer risks, and management of  rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 2. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines for recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2839">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board and PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which are editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
2</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>SMARCA4 gene</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2 (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
2 (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 
2</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_2840"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_2841">Rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 2 (RTPS2) is caused by <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> (or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045983" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hereditary</GlossaryTermRef>) loss-of-function <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> in the <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef>, which is located on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 19p13.<Reference refidx="1"/> RTPS2 is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> disorder. Individuals with <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants  have an increased risk to develop small cell carcinoma of the ovary hypercalcemic type (SCCOHT) and, rarely, atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (AT/RT). The risk of developing extracranial rhabdoid tumors and other rare tumors is currently unknown. Germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic or likely pathogenic variants have been identified in individuals with neuroblastoma, suggesting that <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> could also be a neuroblastoma <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460209" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">susceptibility gene</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/> </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Nemes K, Bens S, Bourdeaut F, et al.: Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome. In: Adam MP, Feldman J, Mirzaa GM, et al., eds.: GeneReviews. University of Washington, Seattle, 1993-2024, pp. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK469816/">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed February 25, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="36813544">Witkowski L, Nichols KE, Jongmans M, et al.: Germline pathogenic SMARCA4 variants in neuroblastoma. J Med Genet 60 (10): 987-992, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2842"><Title>Nomenclature  for Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2</Title><Para id="_2843">Individuals who harbor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef>  <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> have rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 2 (RTPS2).<Reference refidx="1"/> Nomenclature for genetic disorders continues to evolve. Future terminology for these disorders may reflect the proposed dyadic naming approach, incorporating <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">Samples, Phenotypes and Ontologies Team: Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome 2. Ontology Lookup Service  European Molecular Biology Laboratory-European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI), 2023. <ExternalRef xref="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/MONDO_0013224">Available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed October 17, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="33417889">Biesecker LG, Adam MP, Alkuraya FS, et al.: A dyadic approach to the delineation of diagnostic entities in clinical genomics. Am J Hum Genet 108 (1): 8-15, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2844"><Title>Genetics  of Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2</Title><SummarySection id="_3751"><Title>Molecular Genetics  of Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2 (RTPS2)</Title><Para id="_3752">The <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> encodes the SMARCA4 protein (also called BRG1), a member of the SWI/SNF chromatin remodeling complex, which helps control gene <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000390290" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">transcription</GlossaryTermRef>. Individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000556486" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deleterious</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional"> germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef> (typically loss-of-function variants) are diagnosed with RTPS2.  In RTPS2, tumor development follows the Knudson two-hit hypothesis, in which tumors are driven by the inactivation of both copies of the <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> gene. Inactivation of <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> nearly always results in loss of SMARCA4/BRG1 protein expression. Rare cases of small cell carcinoma of the ovary hypercalcemic type (SCCOHT) have been described with retained SMARCA4 immunoreactivity, despite the presence of <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000464169" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">loss of heterozygosity</GlossaryTermRef> detected via molecular testing.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><Para id="_3772">While most hereditary non-SCCOHT rhabdoid tumor cases are caused by <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> pathogenic variants and lead  to rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 1 (RTPS1), approximately 2% to 3% of rhabdoid tumor cases are caused by <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="2"/> Intracranial atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (AT/RTs)  are seen more often than extracranial rhabdoid tumors  in people with RTPS2.<Reference refidx="3"/> Data are scarce, given the rarity of <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-associated AT/RTs. However, it has been suggested that the rate of germline cases is higher in <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-associated AT/RTs than in those with loss of SMARCB1.<Reference refidx="4"/> Germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants  associated with RTPS2 lead to a loss of function, most often via <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783965" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">nonsense variants</GlossaryTermRef> and intragenic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deletions</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_3753">On the other hand, germline  <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants are detected in approximately 40% of women with SCCOHT, a rare and aggressive tumor.  Somatic variation in these tumors is typically caused by nonsense or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783963" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">frameshift</GlossaryTermRef> variants. However, loss of the short arm of chromosome 19 and  <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense variants</GlossaryTermRef> have also been seen.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/> Some investigators have suggested that SCCOHT be called malignant rhabdoid tumor of the ovary (MRTO) and be included in the group of RTPS2-associated tumors.<Reference refidx="3"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3754"><Title>Inheritance  of RTPS2</Title><Para id="_3755">RTPS2 is an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000793860" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal dominant</GlossaryTermRef> cancer predisposition disorder. The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of RTPS2 appears to be incomplete. Studies using population-scale genomic ascertainment have not been conducted. Data suggest  that <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants in RTPS2 are inherited more often  than <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> variants in RTPS1. In a small cohort study, six of seven patients inherited  <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants from an unaffected parent.<Reference refidx="4"/> It is recommended that family members of <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> carriers consider genetic testing. Testing is also recommended for affected patients.<Reference refidx="7"/>  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3756"><Title>Related Conditions</Title><Para id="_3757">Germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants have also been identified in individuals with Coffin-Siris syndrome (CSS).<Reference refidx="8"/>  However, unlike loss-of-function <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants in RTPS2, individuals with CSS typically have nontruncating missense <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants. In a patient with a germline nonsense <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variant, a mild CSS presentation and a SCCOHT diagnosis were described.<Reference refidx="8"/> However, individuals with CSS who carry nontruncating <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants are not at risk of developing rhabdoid tumors. </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="37345679">Mazibrada J, Jayatunge N, Domecq C, et al.: Unusual Aspects of Small Cell Carcinoma of the Ovary of Hypercalcaemic Type: Retained SMARCA4 Immunohistochemical Staining and Positive Staining With TLE1. Am J Surg Pathol 47 (11): 1261-1266, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="33692948">Del Baldo G, Carta R, Alessi I, et al.: Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome: From Clinical Suspicion to General Management. Front Oncol 11: 586288, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="24752781">Foulkes WD, Clarke BA, Hasselblatt M, et al.: No small surprise - small cell carcinoma of the ovary, hypercalcaemic type, is a malignant rhabdoid tumour. J Pathol 233 (3): 209-14, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="25060813">Hasselblatt M, Nagel I, Oyen F, et al.: SMARCA4-mutated atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors are associated with inherited germline alterations and poor prognosis. Acta Neuropathol 128 (3): 453-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="27241105">Witkowski L, Goudie C, Foulkes WD, et al.: Small-Cell Carcinoma of the Ovary of Hypercalcemic Type (Malignant Rhabdoid Tumor of the Ovary): A Review with Recent Developments on Pathogenesis. Surg Pathol Clin 9 (2): 215-26, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="6">Weyandt JD, Young C, Carraway C, et al.: Small-cell carcinoma of the ovary, hypercalcemic type (SCCOHT) has approximately 20-30% penetrance in individuals carrying loss-of-function mutations in SMARCA4. [Abstract] Fam Cancer  22: A-P063, 373, 2023. <ExternalRef xref="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10689-023-00332-5#Sec211">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed January 28, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="28620006">Foulkes WD, Kamihara J, Evans DGR, et al.: Cancer Surveillance in Gorlin Syndrome and Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome. Clin Cancer Res 23 (12): e62-e67, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28608987">Errichiello E, Mustafa N, Vetro A, et al.: SMARCA4 inactivating mutations cause concomitant Coffin-Siris syndrome, microphthalmia and small-cell carcinoma of the ovary hypercalcaemic type. J Pathol 243 (1): 9-15, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2846"><Title>Cancer Risks, Spectrum, and Characteristics  of Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2</Title><Para id="_2847">Up to 40% of females with small cell carcinoma of the ovary hypercalcemic type (SCCOHT) harbor <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Multiple family members can be affected.<Reference refidx="3"/> In women with SCCOHT who did not have germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants, one <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000781854" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">somatic</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variant was almost always found.<Reference refidx="2"/> A retrospective review of 48 SCCOHT tumors sequenced at a diagnostic lab found 18  tumors (37.5%) with germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants. The remainder were somatic <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants, indeterminate, or unknown. The ages of the 48 women ranged from 8 years to 56 years (median age, 28.5 y).<Reference refidx="4"/> A retrospective review of the Slovenian Cancer Registry identified seven SCCOHT cases from 1991 to 2021 in a country with about 2 million people, giving a minimal SCCOHT incidence of 0.12 cases per 1 million people per year. Of the seven cases, four harbored germline loss-of-function <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants. Three tumors harbored somatic <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> loss-of-function variants. Six of the seven women died of SCCOHT  within 27 months of their diagnoses.<Reference refidx="5"/> Ages of people diagnosed with  SCCOHT ranged from infancy to 56 years, with an average age of 23.9 years. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> was uncertain but may be considerable. There are known unpublished and published cases of women in their 50s (and older) with germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants who remain cancer free.<Reference refidx="2"/> </Para><Para id="_3758">Inactivating <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants have been reported in a rare, aggressive form of uterine sarcoma seen in young women, called <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-deficient undifferentiated uterine sarcoma (<GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-DUS), also known as a malignant rhabdoid tumor of the uterus.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/> A retrospective review of 17 <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-DUS tumors sequenced at a diagnostic lab found two tumors  (11.8%) with germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants. The remainder were somatic <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants, indeterminate, or unknown. The ages of the two women were 40 years and 55 years.<Reference refidx="4"/> </Para><Para id="_3759">Germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants are rarely found in individuals with atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (AT/RTs). <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-altered AT/RTs may be associated with worse prognoses.<Reference refidx="8"/> Risk of other rhabdoid tumors is unknown but likely low.<Reference refidx="9"/> At least one case report described an unusual lung cancer in a child with a <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variant.<Reference refidx="10"/></Para><Para id="_3760">Clinically aggressive <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-deficient thoracic sarcomas (<GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-DTS) have been described in adults (typically male smokers), but  germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants have not been reported.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/><Reference refidx="14"/></Para><Para id="_3761"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339341" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef> germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants were reported in 11 individuals with neuroblastoma (eight previously reported cases and four new cases). Nine of these individuals were male. The median age of diagnosis was 5 years (range, 2 mo–26 y), and all but one patient presented in the pediatric age range. Of the 11 patients, one child aged 4 years presented with bilateral neuroblastoma.  This child also had a germline <GeneName>CHEK2</GeneName> pathogenic variant. Eight of nine <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants were expected to result in a loss-of-function variant. The remaining four <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> variants were <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783964" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">missense</GlossaryTermRef>. There was no clear difference in age of diagnosis between individuals with missense and loss-of-function variants. In the four patients who had <GeneName>MYCN</GeneName> status tested, none showed <GeneName>MYCN</GeneName> amplification. None of the 11 individuals were known to have family histories of <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName>-related tumors.  In eight cases where somatic testing was performed, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000464169" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">loss of heterozygosity</GlossaryTermRef> was observed, which provides additional support that <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046657" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">tumor suppressor.</GlossaryTermRef><Reference refidx="15"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="24752781">Foulkes WD, Clarke BA, Hasselblatt M, et al.: No small surprise - small cell carcinoma of the ovary, hypercalcaemic type, is a malignant rhabdoid tumour. J Pathol 233 (3): 209-14, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="32156746">Tischkowitz M, Huang S, Banerjee S, et al.: Small-Cell Carcinoma of the Ovary, Hypercalcemic Type-Genetics, New Treatment Targets, and Current Management Guidelines. Clin Cancer Res 26 (15): 3908-3917, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="27866340">Witkowski L, Donini N, Byler-Dann R, et al.: The hereditary nature of small cell carcinoma of the ovary, hypercalcemic type: two new familial cases. Fam Cancer 16 (3): 395-399, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="31954538">Connor YD, Miao D, Lin DI, et al.: Germline mutations of SMARCA4 in small cell carcinoma of the ovary, hypercalcemic type and in SMARCA4-deficient undifferentiated uterine sarcoma: Clinical features of a single family and comparison of large cohorts. Gynecol Oncol 157 (1): 106-114, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="37270804">Blatnik A, Dragoš VŠ, Blatnik O, et al.: A Population-Based Study of Patients With Small Cell Carcinoma of the Ovary, Hypercalcemic Type, Encompassing a 30-Year Period. Arch Pathol Lab Med 148 (3): 299-309, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="29700418">Kolin DL, Dong F, Baltay M, et al.: SMARCA4-deficient undifferentiated uterine sarcoma (malignant rhabdoid tumor of the uterus): a clinicopathologic entity distinct from undifferentiated carcinoma. Mod Pathol 31 (9): 1442-1456, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="31190001">Lin DI, Allen JM, Hecht JL, et al.: SMARCA4 inactivation defines a subset of undifferentiated uterine sarcomas with rhabdoid and small cell features and germline mutation association. Mod Pathol 32 (11): 1675-1687, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="25060813">Hasselblatt M, Nagel I, Oyen F, et al.: SMARCA4-mutated atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors are associated with inherited germline alterations and poor prognosis. Acta Neuropathol 128 (3): 453-6, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="33692948">Del Baldo G, Carta R, Alessi I, et al.: Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome: From Clinical Suspicion to General Management. Front Oncol 11: 586288, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="29874541">de Kock L, Fahiminiya S, Fiset PO, et al.: Infantile Pulmonary Teratoid Tumor. N Engl J Med 378 (23): 2238-2240, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="26343384">Le Loarer F, Watson S, Pierron G, et al.: SMARCA4 inactivation defines a group of undifferentiated thoracic malignancies transcriptionally related to BAF-deficient sarcomas. Nat Genet 47 (10): 1200-5, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="30451731">Perret R, Chalabreysse L, Watson S, et al.: SMARCA4-deficient Thoracic Sarcomas: Clinicopathologic Study of 30 Cases With an Emphasis on Their Nosology and Differential Diagnoses. Am J Surg Pathol 43 (4): 455-465, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="28256572">Yoshida A, Kobayashi E, Kubo T, et al.: Clinicopathological and molecular characterization of SMARCA4-deficient thoracic sarcomas with comparison to potentially related entities. Mod Pathol 30 (6): 797-809, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="28643792">Sauter JL, Graham RP, Larsen BT, et al.: SMARCA4-deficient thoracic sarcoma: a distinctive clinicopathological entity with undifferentiated rhabdoid morphology and aggressive behavior. Mod Pathol 30 (10): 1422-1432, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="36813544">Witkowski L, Nichols KE, Jongmans M, et al.: Germline pathogenic SMARCA4 variants in neuroblastoma. J Med Genet 60 (10): 987-992, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2848"><Title>Management  of Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2</Title><SummarySection id="_3762"><Title>Genetic Counseling  of Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2 (RTPS2)</Title><Para id="_3763">It is recommended that any female with (1) a personal diagnosis or family history of small cell carcinoma of the ovary hypercalcemic type (SCCOHT) or (2) a personal diagnosis or family history of other rhabdoid tumors receive <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044961" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genetic counseling</GlossaryTermRef> and be offered <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> genetic testing.  Related boys younger than 5 years are recommended to undergo rhabdoid tumor screening and <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000799496" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">cascade genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef>. It is also appropriate to offer <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> genetic testing to unaffected males older than 5 years who have family histories of rhabdoid tumors or SCCOHT in female family members. These men may be obligate carriers, and screening recommendations would apply to  their children.<Reference refidx="1"/> Shared decision making can be considered (regarding the timing of genetic testing) for boys between the ages of 5  and 18 years, since screening recommendations do not exist for boys older than 5 years. Clinicians must respect the individual's right to choose <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional"> germline</GlossaryTermRef> genetic testing. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3764"><Title>Surveillance  of RTPS2</Title><Para id="_3765">In 2017, experts in childhood cancer genetics created the first recommendations for cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> in rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndromes. These recommendations were updated in 2024.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/>  </Para><Para id="_3766">Optimal surveillance recommendations for children with RTPS2 have not been established and may be burdensome for many families.  For boys and girls younger than 5 years, surveillance of the craniospinal axis is recommended every 4 to 6 weeks from birth  to 6 months, then every 3 months until age 5 years, after which surveillance ceases.  Clinical examination and abdominal ultrasound  are conducted every 3 months until the age of 5 years, when abdominal surveillance stops for boys. For girls, abdominal and pelvic ultrasounds are recommended every 6 months, with no age limit. Abdominal/pelvic ultrasound is a limited  surveillance strategy for detecting low-stage SCCOHT that is amenable to curative surgical resection. This surveillance technique has not been validated in patients with <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/>  Alternative recommendations have been made for risk-reducing bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy in first-degree relatives of women diagnosed with SCCOHT. However, timing of such surgeries in girls and young women is challenging to determine.<Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>    Case reports indicated that when young women or girls were affected by SCCOHT, there was a greater impetus for risk-reducing salpingo-oophorectomy, particularly in siblings.<Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3767"><Title>Surveillance in Survivorship  of RTPS2</Title><Para id="_3768">For women and girls with SCCOHT, the overall survival rate is approximately 51% for patients with Fédération Internationale de Gynécologie et d’Obstétrique (FIGO) stage I disease and decreases to 24% for patients with stage II to stage IV disease.<Reference refidx="9"/>  Since treatment for SCCOHT is surgical removal of the ovary, it is recommended that female patients with germline <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> pathogenic variants have all ovarian tissue removed (removal of both ovaries plus any localized/metastatic disease, like omental studding) and receive adjuvant chemotherapy.<Reference refidx="10"/>  Surveillance imaging would therefore default to long-term follow-up guidelines for survivors of ovarian cancer, as outlined by the National Comprehensive Cancer Network.<Reference refidx="11"/>  </Para><Para id="_3769">For children younger than 5 years who have been diagnosed with atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor or malignant rhabdoid tumor, surveillance of unaffected organs can be continued during primary cancer treatment and posttherapy surveillance.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_3770"><Title>Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition and Fertility Preservation</Title><Para id="_3771">RTPS2 presents unique challenges for fertility preservation in women or girls affected by SCCOHT. Prophylactic risk-reducing bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy is recommended for individuals with a high risk of developing SCCOHT. Women or girls with RTPS2 may engage with their institutional fertility preservation program to determine eligibility for egg or ovarian tissue banking. However, published data suggest that the cell of origin for SCCOHT may be a germ cell, raising uncertainty about this approach.<Reference refidx="12"/> Genetic counseling and consideration of preimplantation genetic testing of embryos is advisable.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="31954538">Connor YD, Miao D, Lin DI, et al.: Germline mutations of SMARCA4 in small cell carcinoma of the ovary, hypercalcemic type and in SMARCA4-deficient undifferentiated uterine sarcoma: Clinical features of a single family and comparison of large cohorts. Gynecol Oncol 157 (1): 106-114, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="28620006">Foulkes WD, Kamihara J, Evans DGR, et al.: Cancer Surveillance in Gorlin Syndrome and Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome. Clin Cancer Res 23 (12): e62-e67, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="38573059">Hansford JR, Das A, McGee RB, et al.: Update on Cancer Predisposition Syndromes and Surveillance Guidelines for Childhood Brain Tumors. Clin Cancer Res 30 (11): 2342-2350, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="33532948">Frühwald MC, Nemes K, Boztug H, et al.: Current recommendations for clinical surveillance and genetic testing in rhabdoid tumor predisposition: a report from the SIOPE Host Genome Working Group. Fam Cancer 20 (4): 305-316, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="33907931">Pastorczak A, Krajewska K, Urbanska Z, et al.: Ovarian carcinoma in children with constitutional mutation of SMARCA4: single-family report and literature review. Fam Cancer 20 (4): 355-362, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="32382648">Podwika SE, Jenkins TM, Khokhar JK, et al.: Optimal age for genetic cancer predisposition testing in hereditary SMARCA4 Ovarian Cancer Families: How young is too young? Gynecol Oncol Rep 32: 100569, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="37663174">Vu JA, Thompson WS, Klinkner DB, et al.: Risk reduction for small cell cancer of the ovary, hypercalcemic type in prepubertal patient: A clinical and bioethical perspective. Gynecol Oncol Rep 49: 101261, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="30886884">Pejovic T, McCluggage WG, Krieg AJ, et al.: The dilemma of early preventive oophorectomy in familial small cell carcinoma of the ovary of hypercalcemic type. Gynecol Oncol Rep 28: 47-49, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="37568608">Wens FSPL, Hulsker CCC, Fiocco M, et al.: Small Cell Carcinoma of the Ovary, Hypercalcemic Type (SCCOHT): Patient Characteristics, Treatment, and Outcome-A Systematic Review. Cancers (Basel) 15 (15): , 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="32654763">Pressey JG, Dandoy CE, Pater LE, et al.: Small cell carcinoma of the ovary hypercalcemic type (SCCOHT): Comprehensive management of a newly diagnosed young adult. Gynecol Oncol 158 (3): 538-546, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="11">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Ovarian Cancer Including Fallopian Tube Cancer
and Primary Peritoneal Cancer. Version 3.2024. Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/ovarian.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed January 27, 2025.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="28130795">McCluggage WG, Witkowski L, Clarke BA, et al.: Clinical, morphological and immunohistochemical evidence that small-cell carcinoma of the ovary of hypercalcaemic type (SCCOHT) may be a primitive germ-cell neoplasm. Histopathology 70 (7): 1147-1154, 2017.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2850"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (03/03/2025)</Title><Para id="_2851">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly
         and updated as new information becomes available.  This section
         describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the
         date above.</Para><Para id="_3750">This is a new summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef> and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000815943#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/rtps2-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics, cancer risks, and management of  rhabdoid tumor predisposition syndrome type 2. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef> and the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which are editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2 are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Julia Meade, MD (UPMC Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh)</ListItem><ListItem>Sarah Scollon, MS, CGC (Baylor College of Medicine &amp; Texas Children's Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Douglas Stewart, MD (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board and the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board use a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board and PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Rhabdoid Tumor Predisposition Syndrome Type 2. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/rtps2-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/rtps2-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. [PMID: 40203164]</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2025-03-03</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-03-03</DateLastModified></Summary>
