<Summary id="CDR0000816204" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Evidence-based, expert-reviewed summary about the PALB2 gene, the cancer risks associated with PALB2, screening, risk-reduction, treatment, and prognosis.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/palb2-hp-pdq">PALB2 (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000038832">breast cancer</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_2824">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of PALB2. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2825">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>breast cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle><GeneName>PALB2: Cancer Risks and Management</GeneName> (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">PALB2 and Associated Cancer Risks (PDQ®) </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">PALB2: Cancer Risks and Management</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_2826"><Title>Genetics</Title><Para id="_3751">The <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> (Partner And Localizer of <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>) <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> is located on <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 16p12.2. This gene interacts with both <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName> to restore and maintain genomic stability via homologous recombination repair of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> double-stranded breaks. Several studies have reported a high <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef> of breast cancer in women who carry <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef>. <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> is now included on all breast cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763019" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">multigene panel tests</GlossaryTermRef>. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">biallelic</GlossaryTermRef> loss-of-function of <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> variants (also known as <GeneName>FANCN</GeneName>) lead to Fanconi anemia. Fanconi anemia is a syndrome that is associated with early developmental defects, bone marrow failure, and cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809370" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">predisposition</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="32185139">Wu S, Zhou J, Zhang K, et al.: Molecular Mechanisms of PALB2 Function and Its Role in Breast Cancer Management. Front Oncol 10: 301, 2020.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2828"><Title>Prevalence of <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_2829">Several studies have reported prevalence rates of <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef>. These studies included case series, case-control studies, cohort studies, and commercial lab databases. There is considerable heterogeneity among these studies in terms of   study design, populations studied, strength of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family history,</GlossaryTermRef> sequencing techniques, and levels of coverage. Most of these studies included individuals who were referred for clinical genetic testing, and they are, therefore, are not representative of the general population. Prevalence rates in these studies ranged from 0.3% to 1.2%.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/><Reference refidx="8"/><Reference refidx="9"/><Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/> A meta-analysis analyzed data from 48 studies of women who were diagnosed with breast cancer and were referred for genetic testing. This meta-analysis found that prevalence of <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants was 0.9%, and the odds ratio for breast cancer was 4.87.<Reference refidx="14"/> Another study, which included only women with metastatic breast cancer, reported a <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> prevalence of 1.8%.<Reference refidx="15"/> A study from a genetic testing lab  found a <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> prevalence of 0.36% in Caucasian women who were diagnosed with ovarian cancer.<Reference refidx="3"/> Despite the variability in study design and study populations, prevalence rates for <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were very similar. </Para><Para id="_3752"><GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783962" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">founder pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> have been described in Finnish, Polish, Canadian, Russian, Argentinian, Greek, Italian, Australian, and Hispanic populations.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="26720728">Norquist BM, Harrell MI, Brady MF, et al.: Inherited Mutations in Women With Ovarian Carcinoma. JAMA Oncol 2 (4): 482-90, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="28008555">Pritzlaff M, Summerour P, McFarland R, et al.: Male breast cancer in a multi-gene panel testing cohort: insights and unexpected results. Breast Cancer Res Treat 161 (3): 575-586, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="28888541">Lilyquist J, LaDuca H, Polley E, et al.: Frequency of mutations in a large series of clinically ascertained ovarian cancer cases tested on multi-gene panels compared to reference controls. Gynecol Oncol 147 (2): 375-380, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="31206626">Weitzel JN, Neuhausen SL, Adamson A, et al.: Pathogenic and likely pathogenic variants in PALB2, CHEK2, and other known breast cancer susceptibility genes among 1054 BRCA-negative Hispanics with breast cancer. Cancer 125 (16): 2829-2836, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="30613976">Rizzolo P, Zelli V, Silvestri V, et al.: Insight into genetic susceptibility to male breast cancer by multigene panel testing: Results from a multicenter study in Italy. Int J Cancer 145 (2): 390-400, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="30720863">Deng M, Chen HH, Zhu X, et al.: Prevalence and clinical outcomes of germline mutations in BRCA1/2 and PALB2 genes in 2769 unselected breast cancer patients in China. Int J Cancer 145 (6): 1517-1528, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="34377931">Fan X, Wynn J, Shang N, et al.: Penetrance of Breast Cancer Susceptibility Genes From the eMERGE III Network. JNCI Cancer Spectr 5 (4): , 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="33780288">Fasching PA, Yadav S, Hu C, et al.: Mutations in BRCA1/2 and Other Panel Genes in Patients With Metastatic Breast Cancer -Association With Patient and Disease Characteristics and Effect on Prognosis. J Clin Oncol 39 (15): 1619-1630, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="37084156">Daly MB, Rosenthal E, Cummings S, et al.: The association between age at breast cancer diagnosis and prevalence of pathogenic variants. Breast Cancer Res Treat 199 (3): 617-626, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="35172496">Kurian AW, Hughes E, Handorf EA, et al.: Breast and Ovarian Cancer Penetrance Estimates Derived From Germline Multiple-Gene Sequencing Results in Women. JCO Precis Oncol 1: 1-12, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="37493628">Kotsopoulos J, Hathaway CA, Narod SA, et al.: Germline Mutations in 12 Genes and Risk of Ovarian Cancer in Three Population-Based Cohorts. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev 32 (10): 1402-1410, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="37262986">Bucalo A, Conti G, Valentini V, et al.: Male breast cancer risk associated with pathogenic variants in genes other than BRCA1/2: an Italian case-control study. Eur J Cancer 188: 183-191, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="36827971">Morra A, Mavaddat N, Muranen TA, et al.: The impact of coding germline variants on contralateral breast cancer risk and survival. Am J Hum Genet 110 (3): 475-486, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="30733081">Suszynska M, Klonowska K, Jasinska AJ, et al.: Large-scale meta-analysis of mutations identified in panels of breast/ovarian cancer-related genes - Providing evidence of cancer predisposition genes. Gynecol Oncol 153 (2): 452-462, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="35805063">Rolfes M, Borde J, Möllenhoff K, et al.: Prevalence of Cancer Predisposition Germline Variants in Male Breast Cancer Patients: Results of the German Consortium for Hereditary Breast and Ovarian Cancer. Cancers (Basel) 14 (13): , 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2830"><Title><GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Cancer Risks, Spectrum, and Characteristics</Title><SummarySection id="_2832"><Title>Female Breast Cancer Risk Associated with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_2833">The association between <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> and female breast cancer was first reported in 2007.<Reference refidx="1"/> After the publication of several small studies,   a 2014 report by the <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Interest Group (PALB2-IG)   (from 14 international research centers, involving 154 families with loss-of-function <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants) confirmed that the risk range for female breast cancer in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> overlapped with that of <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="2"/>  Analysis of 311 women from these 154 families   found that by age 70, absolute risk of female breast cancer was 33% (95% confidence interval [CI], 24%‒44%) for those without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family histories</GlossaryTermRef> of breast cancer and 58% (95% CI, 50%‒66%) for those with two or more <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460150" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">first-degree relatives</GlossaryTermRef> (FDRs) with early-onset breast cancer. A cohort effect   was also observed, in which breast cancer risk was significantly higher in women from more recent birth cohorts. Thirty percent of women with available hormone receptor and human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) statuses had <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639916" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">triple-negative breast cancers</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><Para id="_3753">In 2019, this study was updated and expanded to include 8,830 women in 524 families from 44 study centers in 21 countries.<Reference refidx="3"/> Families included at least one member with a <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant.</GlossaryTermRef> Individuals with known <GeneName>BRCA1/2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were excluded. The absolute risk of breast cancer was 16.9% (95% CI, 13.3%‒21.3%) by age 50 years and 52.8% (95% CI, 43.7%‒62.7%) by age 80 years. Like in the earlier study, both family history and birth cohort were significantly related to risk.</Para><Para id="_3754">To avoid bias of studying only women with increased breast cancer risk, researchers sequenced <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> in 16,501 unselected <GeneName>BRCA1/2</GeneName>-negative breast cancer patients from 10 provinces in China.<Reference refidx="4"/> This study found a <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variant</GlossaryTermRef> prevalence    of 0.97%, which is similar to prevalence estimates reported in other studies. The overall odds ratio (OR) for breast cancer risk in women with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants was 5.23 (95% CI, 2.84‒9.65). However, there was a significant association between breast cancer risk and age, with an OR of 10.09 (95% CI, 3.95‒25.70) for women age 30 years or younger and 5.06 (95% CI, 2.74‒9.43) for women older than 30 years. <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef> were more likely to have family histories of breast and/or ovarian cancer (20.63% vs.7.96% in noncarriers). These individuals were more likely to have larger tumors and positive axillary lymph nodes than controls. The Breast Cancer Association Consortium (BCAC) sequenced 34 suspected breast cancer susceptibility <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> in 60,466 women with invasive breast cancer and 53,461 controls to refine estimates for breast cancer risk.<Reference refidx="5"/> The OR for breast cancer risk in women with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>   pathogenic variants was 5.02 (95% CI, 3.73‒6.76). The OR was higher for estrogen receptor (ER)‒negative breast cancer. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2834"><Title>Contralateral Breast Cancer Risk Associated with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_2835">Data on contralateral breast cancer (CBC) risk in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers are limited. Although there are limited data, both the CARRIERS   Consortium and the BCAC have published similar findings.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/>   The CARRIERS study included data from ten prospective studies of 15,104 women with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000660739" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genotype</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460203" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">phenotype</GlossaryTermRef> data.<Reference refidx="6"/> The overall hazard ratio (HR) for CBC in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers   was 2.9 (95% CI, 1.4‒6.4). CBC risk was seen primarily in women with ER-negative disease. The HR for CBC in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers with ER-negative disease was 3.7 (95% CI, 1.5‒9.0).   The 10-year cumulative risk of CBC was 7.9% overall and 19.7% in women with ER-negative breast cancer. CBC risk was significantly higher in African American women with ER-negative breast cancer, in whom the HR was 4.8 (95% CI, 1.4–16.8). CBC risk in this population was observed predominantly in women who were premenopausal when they were diagnosed with breast cancer. The BCAC report included 30,628 women from 34 studies.<Reference refidx="7"/> The HR for CBC in women with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants was 2.67 (95% CI, 1.35‒5.35). <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers had poorer survival   when compared with noncarriers, but this association was not significant when it was adjusted to include tumor characteristics.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2836"><Title>Male Breast Cancer Risk Associated with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_2837">Risk of male breast cancer in the general population is 0.1%. However, this cancer clusters in families with   breast cancer cases. While there are few studies on pathogenic variants identified in men diagnosed with   breast cancer, several reports have detected <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants in this population. Data on 708 men with breast cancer who underwent testing at one genetic testing lab found an OR of 6.6 (95% CI, 1.7‒21.1) for breast cancer in men with a <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variant, although the number of individuals with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants in this study was small.<Reference refidx="8"/> A large case-control study from Italy that included 767 <GeneName>BRCA1/2</GeneName>-negative men with breast cancer found an OR   of 7.28 (95% CI, 1.17‒45.42) for male breast cancer in men with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants.<Reference refidx="9"/> Like in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339347" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sporadic male breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, most tumors    in men with non-<GeneName>BRCA1/2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were invasive ductal carcinomas that were ER-positive, progesterone receptor‒positive, and HER2-negative. Similarly, the PALB2-IG study of 524 families with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants reported a relative risk (RR) of 7.34 (95% CI, 1.28‒42.19) for male breast cancer.<Reference refidx="3"/> Despite small numbers, estimates of male breast cancer risk   associated with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> are consistent across studies. <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> is emerging as the second-most commonly mutated gene in male breast cancer, after <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2838"><Title>Pancreatic Cancer Risk Associated with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_2839">A study   first reported a <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variant in an individual with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460148" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">familial</GlossaryTermRef> pancreatic cancer in 2009 using exome   sequencing.<Reference refidx="10"/> In subsequent studies of individuals with exocrine pancreatic cancer, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were found in 2% to 4% of participants.<Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/> In the PALB2-IG study (with 524 <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> families), the RR was 2.4 (95% CI, 1.24‒4.50) for pancreatic cancer when <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were present.<Reference refidx="3"/> In individuals with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants, the absolute lifetime risk of pancreatic cancer is   estimated to be between 5% and 10%.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2840"><Title>Ovarian Cancer Risk Associated with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_2841">Although data on the association between <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants and ovarian cancer are mixed, there is growing acknowledgement that ovarian cancer risk may be moderately increased in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers. Ovarian cancer risk is further increased  in women who are diagnosed with ovarian cancer at young ages and in those with family histories of breast/ovarian cancers.</Para><Para id="_3757">A University of Washington study ascertained the frequency of <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants in patients with ovarian cancer.<Reference refidx="13"/> Patients were unselected for age/family history and were enrolled through a university biobank and two Gynecologic Oncology Group (GOG)   clinical trials for advanced ovarian cancer. The OR for ovarian cancer was 10.2   (95% CI, 2.2‒47.0).  A similar study on the frequency of pathogenic variants from <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000763019" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">multigene panel testing</GlossaryTermRef> in a series of clinically ascertained ovarian cancer cases (participants were referred to one genetic testing lab) found a standardized risk ratio of 3.08 (95% CI, 1.93‒4.67) for <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>.<Reference refidx="14"/> The authors speculated that this association was driven by a strong association between <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> and breast cancer risk, since participants were 3.5-times more likely to have personal or family histories of breast  cancer when compared with reference controls. Similar data from a different genetic testing lab reported an OR of 1.60 for ovarian cancer (95% CI, 0.98‒2.60), which did not meet statistical significance.<Reference refidx="15"/>  Researchers sequenced the coding regions of 54  candidate genes in 6,385 women with invasive ovarian cancer and 6,115 controls with broad European ancestry from 19 studies (mostly case-control studies).<Reference refidx="16"/> This study found that <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants were associated with a moderate risk of high-grade serous ovarian cancer   (OR, 2.60; 95% CI, 1.45‒4.64;  <Emphasis>P</Emphasis> = .0013). The cumulative absolute risk of ovarian cancer in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers   by age 80 years was 3.2% (95% CI, 1.8%‒5.7%). Similarly, the PALB2-IG study found an estimated RR   of 2.91 (95% CI, 1.40‒6.04) for ovarian cancer in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers and an absolute lifetime ovarian cancer risk of approximately   5%.<Reference refidx="3"/>  The aforementioned meta-analysis of 48 studies found an OR of 2.13 for ovarian cancer.<Reference refidx="17"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2842"><Title>Other Cancer Risks Associated with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Pathogenic Variants</Title><Para id="_2843"><GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic  variants have been described in colorectal, gastric, prostate, and other cancers.<Reference refidx="3"/> However,  <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>'s contribution to risk in these cancer types has not yet been confirmed. For  more information about research on <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> and gastric cancer risk, see  the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000802835#_3805" url="/types/stomach/hp/gastric-genetics-pdq">Other Genes Associated With Gastric Cancer</SummaryRef> section in Genetics of Gastric Cancer.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="17200668">Rahman N, Seal S, Thompson D, et al.: PALB2, which encodes a BRCA2-interacting protein, is a breast cancer susceptibility gene. Nat Genet 39 (2): 165-7, 2007.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="25099575">Antoniou AC, Casadei S, Heikkinen T, et al.: Breast-cancer risk in families with mutations in PALB2. N Engl J Med 371 (6): 497-506, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="31841383">Yang X, Leslie G, Doroszuk A, et al.: Cancer Risks Associated With Germline PALB2 Pathogenic Variants: An International Study of 524 Families. J Clin Oncol 38 (7): 674-685, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="32339256">Zhou J, Wang H, Fu F, et al.: Spectrum of PALB2 germline mutations and characteristics of PALB2-related breast cancer: Screening of 16,501 unselected patients with breast cancer and 5890 controls by next-generation sequencing. Cancer 126 (14): 3202-3208, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="33471991">Dorling L, Carvalho S, Allen J, et al.: Breast Cancer Risk Genes - Association Analysis in More than 113,000 Women. N Engl J Med 384 (5): 428-439, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="36623243">Yadav S, Boddicker NJ, Na J, et al.: Contralateral Breast Cancer Risk Among Carriers of Germline Pathogenic Variants in ATM, BRCA1, BRCA2, CHEK2, and PALB2. J Clin Oncol 41 (9): 1703-1713, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="36827971">Morra A, Mavaddat N, Muranen TA, et al.: The impact of coding germline variants on contralateral breast cancer risk and survival. Am J Hum Genet 110 (3): 475-486, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="28008555">Pritzlaff M, Summerour P, McFarland R, et al.: Male breast cancer in a multi-gene panel testing cohort: insights and unexpected results. Breast Cancer Res Treat 161 (3): 575-586, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="37262986">Bucalo A, Conti G, Valentini V, et al.: Male breast cancer risk associated with pathogenic variants in genes other than BRCA1/2: an Italian case-control study. Eur J Cancer 188: 183-191, 2023.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="19264984">Jones S, Hruban RH, Kamiyama M, et al.: Exomic sequencing identifies PALB2 as a pancreatic cancer susceptibility gene. Science 324 (5924): 217, 2009.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="20412113">Slater EP, Langer P, Niemczyk E, et al.: PALB2 mutations in European familial pancreatic cancer families. Clin Genet 78 (5): 490-4, 2010.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="21365267">Hofstatter EW, Domchek SM, Miron A, et al.: PALB2 mutations in familial breast and pancreatic cancer. Fam Cancer 10 (2): 225-31, 2011.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="26720728">Norquist BM, Harrell MI, Brady MF, et al.: Inherited Mutations in Women With Ovarian Carcinoma. JAMA Oncol 2 (4): 482-90, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="28888541">Lilyquist J, LaDuca H, Polley E, et al.: Frequency of mutations in a large series of clinically ascertained ovarian cancer cases tested on multi-gene panels compared to reference controls. Gynecol Oncol 147 (2): 375-380, 2017.</Citation><Citation idx="15">Kurian AW, Hughes E, Handorf E: Association of ovarian cancer (OC) risk with mutations detected by multiple-gene germline sequencing in 95,561 women. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol  34 (Suppl 15): A-5510, 2016. <ExternalRef xref="https://ascopubs.org/doi/10.1200/JCO.2016.34.15_suppl.5510">Also available online</ExternalRef>. Last accessed November 7, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="32546565">Song H, Dicks EM, Tyrer J, et al.: Population-based targeted sequencing of 54 candidate genes identifies PALB2 as a susceptibility gene for high-grade serous ovarian cancer. J Med Genet 58 (5): 305-313, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="30733081">Suszynska M, Klonowska K, Jasinska AJ, et al.: Large-scale meta-analysis of mutations identified in panels of breast/ovarian cancer-related genes - Providing evidence of cancer predisposition genes. Gynecol Oncol 153 (2): 452-462, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2844"><Title>Cancer Surveillance and Risk Management in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Carriers</Title><Para id="_2845">The National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) recommends breast cancer <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046171" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">screening</GlossaryTermRef> with annual mammogram and breast magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with contrast starting at age 30 years in women with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Given the increased contralateral breast cancer risk seen in premenopausal women with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants, MRI screening can also be conducted following a primary breast cancer. However, MRI screening may be of little benefit after age 65 years in this population. Risk-reducing mastectomy can be considered, based on the individual’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000302456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">family history</GlossaryTermRef>. In men with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants, breast cancer screening with annual mammogram may be considered starting at age 50 years or 10 years earlier than the youngest breast cancer diagnosis in the family.  Risk-reducing salpingo-oophorectomy may be considered for women starting at age 45 to 50 years. Because family history can impact ovarian cancer risk in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef>, individualized <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460214" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">risk assessment</GlossaryTermRef> is encouraged.<Reference refidx="2"/> Protocols for pancreatic cancer screening vary but mainly include contrast-enhanced MRI/magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography and endoscopic ultrasound starting at age 50 years or 10 years before the earliest pancreatic cancer diagnosis in the family.<Reference refidx="1"/> Historically, professional organizations have recommended pancreatic cancer screening only when a family history of pancreatic cancer is present. However,  recommendations conflict across professional organizations when a family history of pancreatic cancer is absent. Ongoing discussions with health care providers is encouraged, given the evolving data. </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Breast, Ovarian, and Pancreatic. Version 1.2025 . Plymouth Meeting, Pa: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2025. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_bop.pdf">Available online with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed October 30, 2024.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="36411032">Hanson H, Kulkarni A, Loong L, et al.: UK consensus recommendations for clinical management of cancer risk for women with germline pathogenic variants in cancer predisposition genes: RAD51C, RAD51D, BRIP1 and PALB2. J Med Genet 60 (5): 417-429, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2846"><Title>Prognosis in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Carriers</Title><SummarySection id="_2848"><Title>Breast Cancer Prognosis in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Carriers</Title><Para id="_2849">A prospective cohort study of 12,529 women with invasive breast cancer in Poland first reported an excess of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639916" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">triple-negative breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef> (TNBC) in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef> when compared with noncarriers.<Reference refidx="1"/> In this study, the hazard ratio (HR) for death associated with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> was 2.19 (95% confidence interval, 1.59‒3.02). However, this HR pertained to women with tumors   larger than 2 cm. In a study of 16,501 unselected <GeneName>BRCA1/2</GeneName>-negative breast cancer patients from China, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers were significantly more likely to have TNBCs than noncarriers (22.83% vs. 13.56%, respectively).<Reference refidx="2"/> <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers had larger tumors, more positive axillary lymph nodes, and more contralateral breast cancers. Other studies reported that <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers had TNBC rates ranging from 30% to 40%.<Reference refidx="3"/> A large population-based study in China observed a significantly shorter overall survival in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> carriers with breast cancer than in noncarriers.<Reference refidx="4"/> </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="25959805">Cybulski C, Kluźniak W, Huzarski T, et al.: Clinical outcomes in women with breast cancer and a PALB2 mutation: a prospective cohort analysis. Lancet Oncol 16 (6): 638-44, 2015.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="32339256">Zhou J, Wang H, Fu F, et al.: Spectrum of PALB2 germline mutations and characteristics of PALB2-related breast cancer: Screening of 16,501 unselected patients with breast cancer and 5890 controls by next-generation sequencing. Cancer 126 (14): 3202-3208, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="25099575">Antoniou AC, Casadei S, Heikkinen T, et al.: Breast-cancer risk in families with mutations in PALB2. N Engl J Med 371 (6): 497-506, 2014.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="30720863">Deng M, Chen HH, Zhu X, et al.: Prevalence and clinical outcomes of germline mutations in BRCA1/2 and PALB2 genes in 2769 unselected breast cancer patients in China. Int J Cancer 145 (6): 1517-1528, 2019.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2852"><Title>Cancer Treatment in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Carriers</Title><Para id="_2853">Because <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> are relatively rare, data on treatment are scarce. However, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> interacts with <GeneName>BRCA1/2</GeneName> to maintain the integrity of the homologous recombination pathway. Therefore, tumors that lack <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>   activity may respond similarly to drugs that are effective in <GeneName>BRCA1</GeneName>/<GeneName>2</GeneName>-mutated tumors.  A number of   studies have reported that solid tumors with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants had increased <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000322883" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">sensitivity</GlossaryTermRef> to platinum agents.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Several phase II trials have suggested that poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) inhibitors may exhibit activity in patients with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants. Although some data show that tumors with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants have high tumor mutational burdens and tumor neoantigen burdens, data on the activity of immunosuppressive therapies are lacking. Several studies are examining the efficacy of using PARP inhibitors with other agents in <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>-mutated breast tumors, ovarian tumors, and other solid tumors.<Reference refidx="2"/></Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="33976419">Tischkowitz M, Balmaña J, Foulkes WD, et al.: Management of individuals with germline variants in PALB2: a clinical practice resource of the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics (ACMG). Genet Med 23 (8): 1416-1423, 2021.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="37621724">Toss A, Ponzoni O, Riccò B, et al.: Management of PALB2-associated breast cancer: A literature review and case report. Clin Case Rep 11 (8): e7747, 2023.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2854"><Title><GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> Summary</Title><Para id="_2855">Although rare, <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> significantly increase the risk of breast, pancreatic, and ovarian cancers. <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variant prevalence rates   in published studies range from 0.3% to 1.8% and have been found in countries across the globe. Rates of breast cancer in individuals with <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants are similar to those associated with <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName>. However, individuals with     <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> and <GeneName>BRCA2</GeneName> pathogenic variants have higher rates of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000639916" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">triple-negative breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>. <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants are also associated with increased risks of contralateral breast cancer and male breast cancer.</Para><Para id="_3755"><GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460132" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">carriers</GlossaryTermRef> have significantly increased risk to develop pancreatic cancer. Although there are conflicting data about <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName>’s role in ovarian cancer, there is also growing evidence that <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic variants confer moderately increased ovarian cancer risk.</Para><Para id="_3756"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000496506" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">Surveillance</GlossaryTermRef> and risk management recommendations are mainly based on data from <GeneName>BRCA</GeneName> trials. There is increased interest and activity in clinical trials to include individuals who carry <GeneName>PALB2</GeneName> pathogenic <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000776887" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">variants</GlossaryTermRef>.  </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2856"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (02/14/2025)</Title><Para id="_2857">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly
         and updated as new information becomes available.  This section
         describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the
         date above.</Para><Para id="_3758">Editorial changes were made to this summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000816204#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/palb2-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about PALB2. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for PALB2 are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Doreen Agnese, MD (The Ohio State University)</ListItem><ListItem>Ilana Cass, MD (Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Lee-may Chen, MD (UCSF Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Mary B. Daly, MD, PhD (Fox Chase Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Megan Frone, MS, CGC (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Jessica Hatton , MS, CGC (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem><ListItem>Joanne Kotsopoulos, PhD (University of Toronto and Women's College Hospital)</ListItem><ListItem>Tuya Pal, MD, FACMG, FCCMG (Vanderbilt-Ingram Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Padma Sheila Rajagopal, MD, MPH, MSC (National Cancer Institute)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ PALB2. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/palb2-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/palb2-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2024-11-20</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-02-14</DateLastModified></Summary>
