<Summary id="CDR0000816826" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Genetics</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>MBD4-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome is a hereditary cancer syndrome associated with the MBD4 gene. Learn about MBD4-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome’s clinical features and management. </SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/mbd4-hp-pdq">MBD4-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000032120">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000043329">cancer genetics</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_2824">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the genetics of MBD4-associated neoplasia syndrome. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_2825">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>cancer genetics</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>MBD4</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle><GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser"><GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome (PDQ®) </AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage"><GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_2826"><Title>Introduction</Title><Para id="_2827">The   association between <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline,</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">biallelic</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> loss-of-function variants and a predisposition to acute myeloid leukemia (AML) was first described in 2018.<Reference refidx="1"/> In this initial report,  hallmark mutational features from three patients with biallelic germline <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef>   were described, including an increased somatic variant rate with the accumulation of CG&gt;TG somatic leukemogenic variants in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> frequently mutated in myeloid malignancies. Additional published reports suggest that biallelic <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> pathogenic variants may be associated with a multicancer predisposition syndrome, called <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-associated neoplasia syndrome (MANS). In addition to increasing the risk of developing AML, MANS increases the risk of gastrointestinal polyposis (comparable to attenuated familial adenomatous polyposis) and may also increase the risk of schwannoma.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> There are conflicting data from a limited number of studies on whether <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339341" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef> germline pathogenic variants in <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> increase the risk of developing uveal melanoma.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/> </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="30049810">Sanders MA, Chew E, Flensburg C, et al.: MBD4 guards against methylation damage and germ line deficiency predisposes to clonal hematopoiesis and early-onset AML. Blood 132 (14): 1526-1534, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="35460607">Palles C, West HD, Chew E, et al.: Germline MBD4 deficiency causes a multi-tumor predisposition syndrome. Am J Hum Genet 109 (5): 953-960, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="35381620">Blombery P, Ryland GL, Fox LC, et al.: Methyl-CpG binding domain 4, DNA glycosylase (MBD4)-associated neoplasia syndrome associated with a homozygous missense variant in MBD4: Expansion of an emerging phenotype. Br J Haematol 198 (1): 196-199, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="32421892">Repo P, Jäntti JE, Järvinen RS, et al.: Germline loss-of-function variants in MBD4 are rare in Finnish patients with uveal melanoma. Pigment Cell Melanoma Res 33 (5): 756-762, 2020.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="32239153">Derrien AC, Rodrigues M, Eeckhoutte A, et al.: Germline MBD4 Mutations and Predisposition to Uveal Melanoma. J Natl Cancer Inst 113 (1): 80-87, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2828"><Title>Genetics and Molecular Biology of <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome </Title><Para id="_2829">The <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">gene</GlossaryTermRef> codes for a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045671" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">DNA</GlossaryTermRef> glycosylase (similar to MUTYH and NTHL1) that is recruited in the base excision repair (BER) pathway. In mouse studies, MBD4 helped repair methylation damage incurred by spontaneous deamination of 5’-methylcytosine to thymine, which is characterized by mismatched CG&gt;TG.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/> Individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">biallelic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variants</GlossaryTermRef> lack the ability to use MBD4 for BER of GT mismatches. In turn, cancer risk is increased. Resulting cancers also appear to have elevated mutational burden and are enriched for this specific CG&gt;TG signature.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para><Para id="_2843"><GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> is located at <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046470" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">chromosome</GlossaryTermRef> 3q21.3. Germline disease-causing   <GeneName>MDB4</GeneName> variants described in acute myeloid leukemia are loss-of-function homozygous or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000766214" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">compound heterozygous</GlossaryTermRef> variants. Therefore, MANS has an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339339" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal recessive inheritance</GlossaryTermRef> pattern.  The types of loss-of-function variants reported include <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783965" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">nonsense variants</GlossaryTermRef> (conferring abnormal splicing), <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460141" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">deletions</GlossaryTermRef>, and duplications.<Reference refidx="3"/> </Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="12130785">Millar CB, Guy J, Sansom OJ, et al.: Enhanced CpG mutability and tumorigenesis in MBD4-deficient mice. Science 297 (5580): 403-5, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="12417741">Wong E, Yang K, Kuraguchi M, et al.: Mbd4 inactivation increases Cright-arrowT transition mutations and promotes gastrointestinal tumor formation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 99 (23): 14937-42, 2002.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="35460607">Palles C, West HD, Chew E, et al.: Germline MBD4 deficiency causes a multi-tumor predisposition syndrome. Am J Hum Genet 109 (5): 953-960, 2022.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2830"><Title>Clinical Manifestations of <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome</Title><SummarySection id="_2844"><Title>Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) in <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome</Title><Para id="_2845">Nine patients with this syndrome have been reported in the literature.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Based on these reports, individuals with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460154" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">germline</GlossaryTermRef> <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-associated AML tend to develop early onset disease, with all reported AML cases (four) occurring between 33 and 49 years. A fifth patient was diagnosed with myelodysplastic syndrome at age 37 years. There are not enough cases to estimate <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339344" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">penetrance</GlossaryTermRef>. Germline genetic testing   for <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-associated neoplasia syndrome (MANS)  may be indicated   for patients with AML and the following: 1)  increased mutational burden on myeloid neoplasm somatic sequencing, especially when the mutational burden is    enriched for CG&gt;GT variants; and/or  2) a personal history of colonic polyposis, schwannomatosis, or uveal melanoma (UVM). Because MANS is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000339339" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">autosomal recessive</GlossaryTermRef>, it may arise in individuals who do not have family histories of leukemia or other MANS-associated manifestations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2832"><Title>Colorectal Polyposis in <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome</Title><Para id="_2833">There are nine reported cases of MANS in the scientific literature.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/> Of these nine individuals, eight underwent colonoscopy at the time these cases were published. Almost all polyps were adenomas, and counts exceeded 20 polyps over multiple colonoscopies. One individual had more than 130 polyps.<Reference refidx="1"/> Another individual had 75 polyps, leading to colectomy at age 32   years.<Reference refidx="2"/> Another individual developed colorectal cancer (CRC) at age 40 years.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para><Para id="_2846">One  study ran <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740459" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">whole-exome</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000740456" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">whole-genome sequencing</GlossaryTermRef>   on 309 individuals who previously underwent genetic testing, which did not find a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000783960" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">pathogenic variant</GlossaryTermRef>.<Reference refidx="1"/> These individuals had one of the following: 1) multiple colorectal adenomas, or 2) family histories of multiple individuals with CRC. Patients with a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000775789" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">biallelic</GlossaryTermRef> loss of <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> presented with oligopolyposis. Cancers observed in <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000460124" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">affected individuals</GlossaryTermRef> included UVM, CRC, and AML. Most of the adenomas that were found had an accumulation of CG&gt;TG transitions in well-known CRC driver <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Genetics" audience="Health professional">genes</GlossaryTermRef> like <GeneName>APC</GeneName>, <GeneName>KRAS</GeneName>, and <GeneName>AMER1</GeneName>.</Para><Para id="_2847">One differential diagnosis for individuals with a history of early onset leukemia and polyposis is a history of receiving total body radiation as a part of a conditioning regimen for hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT). These individuals are also at an increased risk for    gastrointestinal polyps. A case series reported on five patients (all &lt; 1  yr) who underwent HSCT for leukemia after receiving total-body radiation.<Reference refidx="4"/> Every patient developed symptomatic gastrointestinal polyps 0.75 to 5.75 years after HSCT. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2834"><Title>Uveal Melanoma in <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome</Title><Para id="_2835">It is unclear if MANS is associated with an increased risk for UVM.   UVM was reported in two individuals with MANS: one individual developed two primary UVMs at age 38 years and age 45 years, and one individual developed UVM at age 53 years.<Reference refidx="1"/>  Interestingly, both individuals with UVM and MANS carried at least one   c.939dup <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName> variant.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2836"><Title>Other Manifestations in <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome</Title><Para id="_2837">There are two reports of schwannomas in individuals with MANS. One individual had a vestibular schwannoma at age 34 years.<Reference refidx="2"/> Another individual had two schwannomas   at age 50 years and also had a meningioma at age 41 years.<Reference refidx="1"/>  </Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="35460607">Palles C, West HD, Chew E, et al.: Germline MBD4 deficiency causes a multi-tumor predisposition syndrome. Am J Hum Genet 109 (5): 953-960, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="35381620">Blombery P, Ryland GL, Fox LC, et al.: Methyl-CpG binding domain 4, DNA glycosylase (MBD4)-associated neoplasia syndrome associated with a homozygous missense variant in MBD4: Expansion of an emerging phenotype. Br J Haematol 198 (1): 196-199, 2022.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="30049810">Sanders MA, Chew E, Flensburg C, et al.: MBD4 guards against methylation damage and germ line deficiency predisposes to clonal hematopoiesis and early-onset AML. Blood 132 (14): 1526-1534, 2018.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="33828034">Knight B, Anderson L, Lerner D, et al.: Case Series: Development of Polyps as a Late Effect After Total Body Irradiation-based Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation in Children With High-risk Leukemia. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 43 (8): e1159-e1163, 2021.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2838"><Title>Management and Prognosis for <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome</Title><Para id="_2839">National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) guidelines provide management  recommendations for individuals with molecularly confirmed <GeneName>MBD4</GeneName>-associated neoplasia syndrome (MANS):<Reference refidx="1"/></Para><ItemizedList id="_2848" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>NCCN recommends colonoscopy beginning at age 18 to 20 years or at the time of diagnosis to screen for colorectal polyps. Colonoscopy can be repeated every 2 to 3 years.   </ListItem><ListItem>NCCN  recommends annual ophthalmologic exam when the individual is diagnosed with MANS.</ListItem><ListItem>NCCN recommends complete blood count (CBC) when the individual is diagnosed with MANS, but it does not comment on the frequency of CBC afterwards.  There is no consensus on the ideal frequency for CBC in patients with MANS.   </ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_2849">Individualized treatment recommendations do not yet exist for individuals with MANS.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1">National Comprehensive Cancer Network: NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Genetic/Familial High-Risk Assessment: Colorectal, Endometrial, and Gastric. Version 2.2024. Plymouth Meeting, PA: National Comprehensive Cancer Network, 2024. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/genetics_ceg.pdf">Available with free registration.</ExternalRef> Last accessed October 7, 2024.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_2840"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This PDQ Summary (10/29/2024)</Title><Para id="_2841">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly
         and updated as new information becomes available.  This section
         describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the
         date above.</Para><Para id="_2842">
   This is a new summary.</Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000816826#_AboutThis_1" url="/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/mbd4-hp-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about MBD4-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/genetics">PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewers for MBD4-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome are:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Julia Cooper, MS, CGC (Ohio State University)</ListItem><ListItem>Courtney DiNardo, MD, MSC (University of Texas, M.D. Anderson Cancer Center)</ListItem><ListItem>Marcin  Wlodarski, MD, PhD (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Cancer Genetics Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000685387" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/genetics">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Cancer Genetics Editorial Board. PDQ MBD4-Associated Neoplasia Syndrome. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/mbd4-hp-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/information-summaries/genetics/mbd4-hp-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_19">The information in these summaries should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2024-10-23</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2024-10-29</DateLastModified></Summary>
