<Summary id="CDR0000817243" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Health professionals</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>Expert-reviewed information summary about the treatment of Hodgkin lymphoma during pregnancy.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/hp/hodgkin-lymphoma-treatment-during-pregnancy-pdq">Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment During Pregnancy (PDQ®)</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000041646">Hodgkin lymphoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_674">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of Hodgkin lymphoma during pregnancy. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients. It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para><Para id="_675">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>adult Hodgkin lymphoma</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment During Pregnancy (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment During Pregnancy (PDQ®)</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment During Pregnancy</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_676"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040208">adult Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042057">Hodgkin lymphoma during pregnancy</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Prognosis--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>General Information About Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment During Pregnancy</Title><Para id="_677">Hodgkin lymphoma (HL) primarily affects young women, some of whom may be pregnant. When treating a pregnant woman, an oncologist will provide therapy that minimizes risk to the fetus.  Treatment choice must be individualized,
taking the following into consideration:</Para><ItemizedList id="_678" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>The mother’s wishes.</ListItem><ListItem>The severity and aggressiveness of the
HL.</ListItem><ListItem>The trimester of the pregnancy.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_679"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040208">adult Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042057">Hodgkin lymphoma during pregnancy</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Stage explanation--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Stage Information for Hodgkin Lymphoma During Pregnancy</Title><Para id="_680">To avoid exposing a pregnant woman to ionizing
radiation, magnetic resonance imaging
is the preferred method for staging evaluation.<Reference refidx="1"/> The presenting stage, clinical behavior, prognosis, and histological subtypes of Hodgkin lymphoma (HL) in pregnant women do not differ from those in nonpregnant women during their childbearing years.<Reference refidx="2"/> For more information, see the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062675#_12" url="/types/lymphoma/hp/adult-hodgkin-treatment-pdq">Stage Information for HL</SummaryRef> section in Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment.</Para><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="11130469" MedlineID="21013025">Nicklas AH, Baker ME: Imaging strategies in the pregnant cancer patient. Semin Oncol 27 (6): 623-32, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="8674008" MedlineID="96284299">Gelb AB, van de Rijn M, Warnke RA, et al.: Pregnancy-associated lymphomas. A clinicopathologic study. Cancer 78 (2): 304-10, 1996.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_681"><SectMetaData><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000040208">adult Hodgkin lymphoma</SpecificDiagnosis><SpecificDiagnosis ref="CDR0000042057">Hodgkin lymphoma during pregnancy</SpecificDiagnosis><SectionType>Treatment option overview--legacy</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Treatment Options for Hodgkin Lymphoma During Pregnancy</Title><Para id="_682">Treatment options for Hodgkin lymphoma (HL) during pregnancy include:</Para><OrderedList id="_683" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Watchful waiting.</ListItem><ListItem>Radiation therapy.</ListItem><ListItem>Chemotherapy.</ListItem></OrderedList><Para id="_684">In one study, the 20-year survival rate of pregnant women with HL did not differ from the 20-year survival rate of nonpregnant women who were matched for similar stage of disease, age at diagnosis, and calendar year of treatment.<Reference refidx="1"/> </Para><Para id="_685">The long-term effects on children after chemotherapy exposure in utero are unknown.<Reference refidx="1"/><Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="3"/><Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/></Para><Para id="_686">Based on anecdotal series, there is no evidence that a pregnancy after completion of therapy increases the relapse rate for patients in remission.<Reference refidx="6"/><Reference refidx="7"/></Para><SummarySection id="_687"><Title>Therapy During the First Trimester</Title><Para id="_688">HL that is diagnosed in the first trimester of pregnancy does not constitute an absolute indication for therapeutic abortion.  Treatment options for each patient must take into account disease stage, rapidity of growth of the lymphoma, and the patient's wishes.<Reference refidx="8"/></Para><SummarySection id="_689"><Title>Watchful waiting</Title><Para id="_690">If the HL presents in
early stage above the diaphragm and is growing slowly, patients can
be observed carefully, with plans to induce delivery early and proceed with
definitive therapy.<Reference refidx="9"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_691"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_692">Alternatively, these patients can receive radiation
therapy with proper shielding.<Reference refidx="10"/><Reference refidx="11"/><Reference refidx="12"/><Reference refidx="13"/>  Investigators at the MD Anderson Cancer Center reported no
congenital abnormalities in 16 babies delivered after the mothers had received
supradiaphragmatic radiation while the uterus was shielded with five half-value
layers of lead.<Reference refidx="14"/> Because of  theoretical risks of the fetus developing future malignancies from even minimal scattered radiation doses outside the radiation field, postponing radiation therapy—if possible, until after delivery—should be considered.<Reference refidx="15"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_693"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_694">Evidence (chemotherapy during the first trimester):</Para><OrderedList id="_695" Style="Arabic">
     <ListItem>Chemotherapy that is administered during the first trimester has been
associated with congenital abnormalities in as many as 33% of infants.<Reference refidx="2"/><Reference refidx="16"/> 
Consequently, some
women may opt to continue the pregnancy and agree to radiation therapy or
chemotherapy if immediate treatment is required after the first trimester.</ListItem><ListItem>A multicenter retrospective analysis of 40 patients described pregnancy termination in 3 patients, deferral of therapy to the postpartum period in 13 patients (median 30-week gestation), and antenatal therapy given to the remaining 24 patients (median 21-week gestation, all done after the first trimester).<Reference refidx="17"/><ItemizedList id="_696" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>With a median follow-up of 41 months, the 3-year progression-free survival (PFS) rate was 85%, and the overall survival (OS) rate was 97%, often with the use of ABVD (doxorubicin, bleomycin, vinblastine, and dacarbazine).<Reference refidx="17"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>]</ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem><ListItem>A retrospective analysis of 39 patients from the MD Anderson Cancer Center described pregnancy termination in 3 patients, deferral of therapy to the postpartum period in 12 patients, and antenatal therapy given to 24 patients.<Reference refidx="18"/><ItemizedList id="_697" Style="bullet">
     <ListItem>Two women had a miscarriage after receiving doxorubicin-based chemotherapy during the first trimester.</ListItem><ListItem>With a median follow-up of 68 months from diagnosis, the 5-year PFS rate was 75%, and the OS rate was 82%. These rates did not differ between the antenatal and postpartum timing of therapy.<Reference refidx="18"/>[<LOERef href="CDR0000810039" dictionary="NotSet" audience="Health professional">Level of evidence C3</LOERef>] </ListItem></ItemizedList></ListItem></OrderedList></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_698"><Title>Therapy Later in Pregnancy</Title><SummarySection id="_699"><Title>Watchful waiting</Title><Para id="_700">In the second half of pregnancy, patients can be observed carefully,
and therapy can be postponed until induction of delivery at 32 to 36 weeks.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/><Reference refidx="16"/></Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_701"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_702">As an
alternative, a short course of radiation therapy can  be used before delivery in
cases of respiratory compromise caused by a  rapidly enlarging mediastinal mass.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_703"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_704">  If
chemotherapy is mandatory before delivery—such as for patients with
symptomatic advanced-stage disease—vinblastine alone, given intravenously at 6 mg/m²  every 2 weeks until induction of delivery, may
be considered because  it has not been associated with fetal abnormalities in the
second half of pregnancy.<Reference refidx="4"/><Reference refidx="5"/>  Combination chemotherapy with ABVD appears to be safe in the second half of pregnancy.<Reference refidx="3"/> If chemotherapy is required after the first trimester, many clinicians prefer the combination of drugs over single-agent drugs or radiation therapy. Steroids are used both for their
antitumor effect and  for hastening fetal pulmonary maturity.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_TrialSearch_681_sid_3"><Title>Current Clinical Trials</Title><Para id="_TrialSearch_681_22">Use our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search/advanced">advanced clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now enrolling patients. The search can be narrowed by location of the trial, type of treatment, name of the drug, and other criteria. <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">General information</ExternalRef> about clinical trials is also available.</Para></SummarySection><ReferenceSection><Citation idx="1" PMID="1733434" MedlineID="92126487">Lishner M, Zemlickis D, Degendorfer P, et al.: Maternal and foetal outcome following Hodgkin's disease in pregnancy. Br J Cancer 65 (1): 114-7, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="2" PMID="953978" MedlineID="76255463">Thomas PR, Biochem D, Peckham MJ: The investigation and management of Hodgkin's disease in the pregnant patient. Cancer 38 (3): 1443-51, 1976.</Citation><Citation idx="3" PMID="1707227" MedlineID="91189165">Avilés A, Díaz-Maqueo JC, Talavera A, et al.: Growth and development of children of mothers treated with chemotherapy during pregnancy: current status of 43 children. Am J Hematol 36 (4): 243-8, 1991.</Citation><Citation idx="4" PMID="7305142" MedlineID="82066428">Jacobs C, Donaldson SS, Rosenberg SA, et al.: Management of the pregnant patient with Hodgkin's disease. Ann Intern Med 95 (6): 669-75, 1981.</Citation><Citation idx="5" PMID="3717081" MedlineID="86239106">Nisce LZ, Tome MA, He S, et al.: Management of coexisting Hodgkin's disease and pregnancy. Am J Clin Oncol 9 (2): 146-51, 1986.</Citation><Citation idx="6" PMID="26668344">Weibull CE, Eloranta S, Smedby KE, et al.: Pregnancy and the Risk of Relapse in Patients Diagnosed With Hodgkin Lymphoma. J Clin Oncol 34 (4): 337-44, 2016.</Citation><Citation idx="7" PMID="30997537">Gaudio F, Nardelli C, Masciandaro P, et al.: Pregnancy rate and outcome of pregnancies in long-term survivors of Hodgkin's lymphoma. Ann Hematol 98 (8): 1947-1952, 2019.</Citation><Citation idx="8" PMID="2198503">Koren G, Weiner L, Lishner M, et al.: Cancer in pregnancy: identification of unanswered questions on maternal and fetal risks. Obstet Gynecol Surv 45 (8): 509-14, 1990.</Citation><Citation idx="9" PMID="10085508">Anselmo AP, Cavalieri E, Enrici RM, et al.: Hodgkin's disease during pregnancy: diagnostic and therapeutic management. Fetal Diagn Ther 14 (2): 102-5, 1999 Mar-Apr.</Citation><Citation idx="10" PMID="12742274">Mazonakis M, Varveris H, Fasoulaki M, et al.: Radiotherapy of Hodgkin's disease in early pregnancy: embryo dose measurements. Radiother Oncol 66 (3): 333-9, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="11" PMID="11130470" MedlineID="21013026">Greskovich JF, Macklis RM: Radiation therapy in pregnancy: risk calculation and risk minimization. Semin Oncol 27 (6): 633-45, 2000.</Citation><Citation idx="12" PMID="8958407">Fisher PM, Hancock BW: Hodgkin's disease in the pregnant patient. Br J Hosp Med 56 (10): 529-32, 1996 Nov 20-Dec 10.</Citation><Citation idx="13" PMID="8221483">Friedman E, Jones GW: Fetal outcome after maternal radiation treatment of supradiaphragmatic Hodgkin's disease. CMAJ 149 (9): 1281-3, 1993.</Citation><Citation idx="14" PMID="1587764" MedlineID="92267905">Woo SY, Fuller LM, Cundiff JH, et al.: Radiotherapy during pregnancy for clinical stages IA-IIA Hodgkin's disease. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 23 (2): 407-12, 1992.</Citation><Citation idx="15" PMID="12821536">Lishner M: Cancer in pregnancy. Ann Oncol 14 (Suppl 3): iii31-6, 2003.</Citation><Citation idx="16" PMID="15120665">Cardonick E, Iacobucci A: Use of chemotherapy during human pregnancy. Lancet Oncol 5 (5): 283-91, 2004.</Citation><Citation idx="17" PMID="24043736">Evens AM, Advani R, Press OW, et al.: Lymphoma occurring during pregnancy: antenatal therapy, complications, and maternal survival in a multicenter analysis. J Clin Oncol 31 (32): 4132-9, 2013.</Citation><Citation idx="18" PMID="27227654">Pinnix CC, Osborne EM, Chihara D, et al.: Maternal and Fetal Outcomes After Therapy for Hodgkin or Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma Diagnosed During Pregnancy. JAMA Oncol 2 (8): 1065-9, 2016.</Citation></ReferenceSection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_705"><SectMetaData><SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType></SectMetaData><Title>Latest Updates to This Summary (01/13/2025)</Title><Para id="_706">The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly
         and updated as new information becomes available.  This section
         describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the
         date above.</Para><Para id="_707">This is a new summary.
   </Para><Para id="_disclaimerHP_3">This summary is written and maintained by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is
editorially independent of NCI.  The summary reflects an independent review of
the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or NIH.  More
information about summary policies and the role of the PDQ Editorial Boards  in
maintaining the PDQ summaries can be found on the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817243#_AboutThis_1" url="/types/lymphoma/hp/hodgkin-lymphoma-treatment-during-pregnancy-pdq">About This PDQ Summary</SummaryRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq">PDQ® Cancer Information for Health Professionals</ExternalRef> pages.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">This PDQ cancer information summary for health professionals provides comprehensive, peer-reviewed, evidence-based information about the treatment of Hodgkin lymphoma during pregnancy. It is intended as a resource to inform and assist clinicians in the care of their patients.  It does not provide formal guidelines or recommendations for making health care decisions.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_4"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_5">This summary is reviewed regularly and updated as necessary by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/adult-treatment">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>, which is editorially independent of the National Cancer Institute (NCI).  The summary reflects an independent review of the literature and does not represent a policy statement of NCI or the National Institutes of Health (NIH).</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_22"> Board members review recently published articles each month to determine whether an article should:</Para><ItemizedList id="_AboutThis_6" Style="bullet"><ListItem>be discussed at a meeting,</ListItem><ListItem>be cited with text, or</ListItem><ListItem>replace or update an existing article that is already cited.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_7">Changes to the summaries are made through a consensus process in which Board members evaluate the strength of the evidence in  the published articles and determine how the article should be included in the summary.</Para><Para>The lead reviewer for Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment During Pregnancy is:</Para><ItemizedList Style="bullet"><ListItem>Eric J. Seifter, MD (Johns Hopkins University)</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_AboutThis_9">Any comments or questions about the summary content should be submitted to Cancer.gov through the NCI website's <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>. Do not contact the individual Board Members with questions or comments about the summaries. Board members will not respond to individual inquiries.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Levels of Evidence</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">Some of the reference citations in this summary are accompanied by a level-of-evidence designation. These designations are intended to help readers assess the strength of the evidence supporting the use of specific interventions or approaches. The PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board uses a <SummaryRef href="CDR0000062796" url="/publications/pdq/levels-evidence/treatment">formal evidence ranking system</SummaryRef> in developing its level-of-evidence designations.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_12"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_13">PDQ is a registered trademark. Although the content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text, it cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless it is presented in its entirety and is regularly updated. However, an author would be permitted to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks succinctly: [include excerpt from the summary].”</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_14">The preferred citation for this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">PDQ® Adult Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Hodgkin Lymphoma Treatment During Pregnancy. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/hp/hodgkin-lymphoma-treatment-during-pregnancy-pdq">https://www.cancer.gov/types/lymphoma/hp/hodgkin-lymphoma-treatment-during-pregnancy-pdq</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use within the PDQ summaries only. Permission to use images outside the context of PDQ information must be obtained from the owner(s) and cannot be granted by  the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the illustrations in this summary, along with many other cancer-related images, is available in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>, a collection of over 2,000 scientific images.

</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">Based on the strength of the available evidence, treatment options may be described as either “standard” or “under clinical evaluation.” These classifications should not be used as a basis for insurance reimbursement determinations. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_20"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_21">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">Email Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2025-01-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-01-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
