<Summary id="CDR0000817497" LegacyPDQID=""><SummaryMetaData><SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType><SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience><SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage><SummaryDescription>There are many types of kidney cancer that can occur in children. Learn about the risk factors, symptoms, and types of kidney cancer in children and how they are diagnosed and treated.</SummaryDescription><SummaryURL xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Kidney Cancer in Children (PDQ®): Treatment</SummaryURL><SummaryEditorialBoard ref="CDR0000028557">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</SummaryEditorialBoard><MainTopics><TermRef ref="CDR0000566199">childhood renal cell carcinoma</TermRef></MainTopics><SummaryAbstract><Para id="_1">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of kidney cancer in children. It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para><Para id="_2">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Date Last Modified") is the date of the most recent change. The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board.</Para></SummaryAbstract><SummaryKeyWords><SummaryKeyWord>anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood kidney cancer</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>childhood renal cell carcinoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>clear cell sarcoma of the kidney</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>congenital mesoblastic nephroma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>kidney cancer in children</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>multilocular cysticnephroma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>primary renal myoepithelial carcinoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>primary renal synovial sarcoma</SummaryKeyWord><SummaryKeyWord>rhabdoid tumor of the kidney</SummaryKeyWord></SummaryKeyWords></SummaryMetaData><SummaryTitle>Kidney Cancer in Children (PDQ®)–Patient Version</SummaryTitle><AltTitle TitleType="Browser">Kidney Cancer in Children</AltTitle><AltTitle TitleType="CancerTypeHomePage">Kidney Cancer in Children</AltTitle><SummarySection id="_3"><Title>What is kidney cancer in children?</Title><Para id="_18208">Kidney cancer occurs when cells in one or both <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046325" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">kidneys</GlossaryTermRef> start to grow without control and form a tumor. There are many types of kidney tumors that can occur in children and adolescents. Some are benign (not cancer), and others are cancerous. Most kidney tumors in children are cancer. Even though benign tumors don't spread like cancer, they can affect a child's health and kidney function. Treatment is usually needed for benign and cancerous tumors.</Para><Para id="_281">The kidneys are two bean-shaped organs located on either side of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000415914" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spine</GlossaryTermRef>, just above the waist. Their main job is to remove waste and extra fluids from the body to make urine:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18209" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Tiny tubules in the kidneys filter and clean the blood.</ListItem><ListItem>Urine passes from each kidney through a thin tube called a ureter into the bladder.</ListItem><ListItem>The bladder stores the  urine until it leaves the body through a tube called the urethra.</ListItem></ItemizedList><MediaLink ref="CDR0000666578" type="image/jpeg" alt="Anatomy of the urinary system; drawing showing the right and left kidneys, the ureters, the bladder filled with urine, and the urethra. The inside of the left kidney shows the renal pelvis. An inset shows the renal tubules and urine. The spine and adrenal glands are also shown." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_279"><Caption language="en">Anatomy of the urinary system showing the kidneys, ureters, bladder, and urethra. The inside of the left kidney shows the renal pelvis. An inset shows the renal tubules and urine. Also shown is the spine and adrenal glands. Urine is made in the renal tubules and collects in the renal pelvis of each kidney. The urine flows from the kidneys through the ureters to the bladder. The urine is stored in the bladder until it leaves the body through the urethra.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_445"><Title>Symptoms of kidney cancer in children</Title><Para id="_446">Sometimes childhood kidney cancer causes symptoms. But sometimes a parent finds a tumor in the abdomen by chance. Or a doctor finds a tumor during a well-child health check-up. It's important to check with your child's doctor if your child has:</Para><ItemizedList id="_447" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a lump, swelling, or pain in the abdomen</ListItem><ListItem>blood in the urine</ListItem><ListItem>back pain</ListItem><ListItem>fever for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>weight loss for no known reason</ListItem><ListItem>infection</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045360" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anemia</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045363" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hypercalcemia</GlossaryTermRef> with symptoms of loss of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000454699" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">appetite</GlossaryTermRef>, nausea and vomiting, weakness, or feeling very tired</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_448">These symptoms may also be caused by other problems. The only way to know is for your child to see a doctor.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_449"><Title>Tests to diagnose kidney cancer in children</Title><Para id="_450">If your child has symptoms that suggest kidney cancer, the doctor will need to find out if these are due to cancer or another problem. The doctor will ask when the symptoms started and how often your child has been having them. The doctor will also ask about your child's <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642021" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">personal</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000642015" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">family medical history</GlossaryTermRef> and do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270871" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">physical exam</GlossaryTermRef>. Depending on these results, they may recommend other tests. If your child is diagnosed with kidney cancer, the results of these tests will help plan treatment.</Para><Para id="_451">The tests used to diagnose kidney cancer may include:</Para><SummarySection id="_452"><Title>Complete blood count (CBC)</Title><Para id="_453">A CBC checks a sample of blood for:</Para><ItemizedList id="_454" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the number of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046124" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">red blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045993" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">white blood cells</GlossaryTermRef>, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045840" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">platelets</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>the amount of hemoglobin (the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046092" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">protein</GlossaryTermRef> that carries <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000538149" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">oxygen</GlossaryTermRef>) in the red blood cells</ListItem><ListItem>the amount of hematocrit (whole blood that is made up of red blood cells)</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_455"><Title>Blood chemistry studies</Title><Para id="_456"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304685" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Blood chemistry studies</GlossaryTermRef> use a blood sample to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign that the liver and kidneys are not working as they should. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_457"><Title>Renal function test</Title><Para id="_458">A renal function test uses blood or urine samples to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood or urine by the kidneys. An unusual amount of a substance can be a sign that the kidneys are not working as they should.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_459"><Title>Urinalysis</Title><Para id="_460">A urinalysis checks the color of urine and its contents, such as sugar, protein, blood, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044123" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bacteria</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_461"><Title>Ultrasound exam</Title><Para id="_462">Ultrasound exam uses high-energy sound waves that bounce off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046587" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sonogram</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775457" type="image/jpeg" alt="Abdominal ultrasound; drawing shows a child lying on an exam table during an abdominal ultrasound procedure. A technician is shown pressing a transducer (a device that makes sound waves that bounce off tissues inside the body) against the skin of the abdomen. A computer screen shows a sonogram (picture)." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_427"><Caption language="en">Abdominal ultrasound. An ultrasound transducer connected to a computer is pressed against the skin of the abdomen. The transducer bounces sound waves off internal organs and tissues to make echoes that form a sonogram (computer picture).</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_463"><Title>CT scan (CAT scan)</Title><Para id="_464">CT scan uses a computer linked to an x-ray machine to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the chest, abdomen, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046246" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pelvis</GlossaryTermRef>. The pictures are taken from different angles and are used to create 3-D views of tissue and organs. A dye is <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044678" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">injected</GlossaryTermRef> into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775531" type="image/jpeg" alt="Computed tomography (CT) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_428"><Caption language="en">Computed tomography (CT) scan. The child lies on a table that slides through the CT scanner, which takes a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_465"><Title>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with gadolinium</Title><Para id="_466">MRI uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, such as the abdomen or pelvis. A substance called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000597153" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gadolinium</GlossaryTermRef> is injected into a vein. The gadolinium collects around the cancer cells so they show up brighter in the picture. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI). </Para><MediaLink ref="CDR0000775532" type="image/jpeg" alt="Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan; drawing shows a child lying on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body." language="en" placement="image-center" id="_429"><Caption language="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. The child lies on a table that slides into the MRI machine, which takes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. The positioning of the child on the table depends on the part of the body being imaged.</Caption></MediaLink></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_467"><Title>X-ray</Title><Para id="_468">An x-ray is a type of radiation that can go through the body and make pictures of areas inside the body.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_469"><Title>PET-CT Scan</Title><Para id="_470">PET-CT scan combines the pictures from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046218" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">positron emission tomography (PET) scan</GlossaryTermRef> and a computed tomography (CT) scan. The PET and CT scans are done at the same time on the same machine. The combined scans make more detailed pictures than either test would make by itself.</Para><ItemizedList id="_471" Style="bullet"><ListItem>For the PET scan, a small amount of <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046550" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radioactive</GlossaryTermRef> sugar (also called radioactive glucose) is injected into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where sugar is being used in the body. Cancer cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more sugar than normal cells.</ListItem><ListItem>For the CT scan (CAT scan), a series of detailed x-ray pictures of areas inside the body is taken from different angles to create 3-D views of tissues and organs. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. Learn more about <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/ct-scans-fact-sheet">Computed Tomography (CT) Scans and Cancer</ExternalRef>.</ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_472"><Title>Biopsy</Title><Para id="_473">Biopsy is the removal of a sample of cells or tissue from the tumor so that a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef> can view it under a microscope to check for cancer.  Whether your child will have a biopsy is based on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_474" Style="bullet"><ListItem>The size of the tumor.</ListItem><ListItem>The <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045885" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stage</GlossaryTermRef> of the cancer. There will not be a biopsy if the tumor looks like it can be removed with surgery or it is stage 1 or stage 2. The reason for not doing a biopsy is to avoid the spread of tumor cells during the procedure.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether cancer is in one or both kidneys.</ListItem><ListItem>Whether imaging tests clearly show the cancer.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_475">Your child may have a biopsy before they receive any treatment, after chemotherapy to shrink the tumor, or during surgery to remove the tumor.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18105"><Title>Getting a second opinion</Title><Para id="_18106">You may want to get a second opinion to confirm your child’s diagnosis and treatment plan. If you seek a second opinion, you will need to get medical test results and reports from the first doctor to share with the second doctor. The second doctor will review the pathology report, slides, and scans. They may agree with the first doctor, suggest changes to the treatment plan, or provide more information about your child’s tumor.</Para><Para id="_18107">To learn more about choosing a doctor and getting a second opinion, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care/finding-cancer-care">Finding Cancer Care</ExternalRef>. You can contact <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">NCI's Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> via chat, email, or phone (both in English and Spanish) for help finding a doctor or hospital that can provide a second opinion. For questions you might want to ask at your child’s doctor visits, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/questions">Questions to Ask Your Doctor about Cancer</ExternalRef>. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_438"><Title>Genetic counseling for children with kidney cancer</Title><Para id="_439">If your child is diagnosed with kidney cancer, it may not be clear from the family medical history whether it was caused by an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045098" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">inherited</GlossaryTermRef> condition that increased their risk. Genetic counseling can assess the likelihood that your child's cancer is inherited and whether <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046128" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">genetic testing</GlossaryTermRef> is needed. <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000794108" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Genetic counselors</GlossaryTermRef> and other specially trained health professionals can discuss your child’s diagnosis and your family’s medical history to help you understand the:</Para><ItemizedList id="_440" Style="bullet"><ListItem>options for testing for <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045563" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Von Hippel-Lindau syndrome</GlossaryTermRef> and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000304692" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">tuberous sclerosis</GlossaryTermRef>, for children diagnosed with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000661352" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">renal cell carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem>options for testing for changes in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045693" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gene</GlossaryTermRef>, for children diagnosed with <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046139" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rhabdoid tumor</GlossaryTermRef> of the kidney</ListItem><ListItem>options for testing for changes in the <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> gene, for children diagnosed with multilocular <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000782356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">cystic nephroma</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045591" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">anaplastic</GlossaryTermRef> <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045562" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>  of the kidney</ListItem><ListItem>risk of your child developing other types of cancer</ListItem><ListItem>risk of kidney tumors and other cancers for your child's siblings</ListItem><ListItem>risks and benefits of learning genetic information</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_441">Genetic counselors can also help you cope with your child's genetic testing results. This can include how to discuss the results with family members. They can advise you about whether other members in your family should receive genetic testing.</Para><Para id="_444">Learn more about genetic testing at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/genetic-testing-fact-sheet">Genetic Testing for Inherited Cancer Risk</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18108"><Title>Stages of kidney cancer in children</Title><Para id="_18109">After your child is diagnosed with kidney cancer, they will be referred to a pediatric oncologist. This is a doctor who specializes in staging and treating cancer in children. </Para><Para id="_18110">Staging is the process of learning the extent of the cancer in the body. Sometimes cancer is found only in the kidney. Or, it may have spread to other parts of the body. The doctor will recommend tests to see if the cancer has spread, and if so, how far.</Para><Para id="_18210">To learn about the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000672851" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">TNM staging system</GlossaryTermRef> used for adults and children with renal cell cancer, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000276462#_26" url="/types/kidney/patient/kidney-treatment-pdq">Stages of Renal Cell Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_18207">To learn more about the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000689414" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Children's Oncology Group</GlossaryTermRef> staging system used for rhabdoid tumor of the kidney, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044997" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">clear cell sarcoma of the kidney</GlossaryTermRef>, or anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000415235#_29" url="/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">Stages of Wilms tumor</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_18211">When kidney cancer comes back after treatment, it is called recurrent kidney cancer. If there are signs that the cancer has returned, your child will have tests to find out where the cancer is in your child's body and if it has spread. The type of treatment will depend on the type of kidney cancer and where in the body it has come back.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_282"><Title>Types of kidney cancer in children</Title><Para id="_283">There are many types of kidney cancer that occur in children. The type of kidney cancer is often based on how the cancer cells look under a microscope, certain genetic changes that may be present in the tumor, and other tests.</Para><SummarySection id="_284"><Title>Wilms tumor</Title><Para id="_285"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045946" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Wilms tumor</GlossaryTermRef> is the most common kidney cancer in children younger than 15 years. It can occur in one or both kidneys. This cancer can spread to the lungs, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046312" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">liver</GlossaryTermRef>, bone, brain, or nearby <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045762" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">lymph nodes</GlossaryTermRef>. Learn more at <SummaryRef href="CDR0000415235" url="/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">Wilms Tumor</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_286"><Title>Renal cell cancer (RCC)</Title><Para id="_287">Renal cell cancer is the most common type of kidney cancer in adolescents aged 15 to 19 years and in adults. This cancer is rare in children younger than 15 years. RCC is often diagnosed at a later stage in children and adolescents. When the cancer is found, it may already have spread to the lungs, liver, bone, brain, or lymph nodes. </Para><Para id="_288">Renal medullary cancer is a rare subtype of renal cell cancer that grows and spreads quickly.</Para><SummarySection id="_18212"><Title>Causes and risk factors for RCC</Title><Para id="_314">Childhood RCC is caused by certain changes in the way kidney cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. The exact cause of these changes is often unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_315">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Not every child with one or more of these risk factors will develop RCC. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. </Para><Para id="_18213">RCC may be related to certain inherited conditions or prior cancer treatment, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045214" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">chemotherapy</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation therapy</GlossaryTermRef> for childhood cancers like <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045418" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">neuroblastoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046584" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissue sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemia</GlossaryTermRef>, or Wilms tumor.</Para><Para id="_316">Inherited conditions linked to RCC include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_317" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Von Hippel-Lindau disease (VHL), an inherited condition that can increase the risk of kidney tumors</ListItem><ListItem>tuberous sclerosis, a genetic disorder that causes fatty cysts in the kidney and other parts of the body</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000256552" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">familial</GlossaryTermRef> RCC, a condition that occurs when certain changes in the genes that cause kidney cancer are passed down from the parent to the child</ListItem><ListItem>sickle cell hemoglobinopathy, a genetic disorder that causes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000546598" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">sickle cell disease</GlossaryTermRef> and may be associated with renal medullary cancer (a rare subtype of renal cell carcinoma)</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000305992" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">hereditary leiomyomatosis</GlossaryTermRef>, an inherited disorder that increases the risk of having cancer of the kidney, skin, and <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046645" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">uterus</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18214">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18215"><Title>Monitoring children at risk of RCC</Title><Para id="_18216">If your child has VHL disease, they have a higher risk of developing RCC. Your child may be monitored with yearly check-ups, including an abdominal ultrasound and MRI, starting between the ages of 8 to 11 years to look for kidney tumors.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18150"><Title>Treatment of RCC</Title><Para id="_18151">Treatment of renal cell cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18152" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery, which may be either <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046265" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">nephrectomy</GlossaryTermRef> or partial nephrectomy with removal of lymph nodes</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045729" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immunotherapy</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045256" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-2</GlossaryTermRef>, for cancer that has spread to other parts of the body</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000270742" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">targeted therapy</GlossaryTermRef>, such as <DrugRef href="CDR0000491976" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/sunitinibmalate">sunitinib</DrugRef> or <DrugRef href="CDR0000743644" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cabozantinib-s-malate">cabozantinib</DrugRef>, for cancer that has spread to other parts of the body</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18153">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_18114" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Types of treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_18217">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and next steps. There might be treatment options that shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatment options, your child can receive care to control their cancer symptoms so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_289"><Title>Rhabdoid tumor of the kidney</Title><Para id="_290">Rhabdoid tumor of the kidney is a type of cancer that occurs mostly in infants and young children. It is often <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000478743" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">advanced</GlossaryTermRef> at the time of diagnosis and grows and spreads quickly, often to the lungs or brain.</Para><Para id="_291">Children with a certain change in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> or <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> genes can have cancer grow in the kidney, brain, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045882" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">soft tissues</GlossaryTermRef>. Children with <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> are checked regularly to see if a rhabdoid tumor has formed in the kidney or the brain.</Para><SummarySection id="_18218"><Title>Causes and risk factors for rhabdoid tumor of the kidney</Title><Para id="_31400">Rhabdoid tumor of the kidney is caused by certain changes in the way kidney cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. The exact cause of these changes is often unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_31500">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease. Children with a certain change in the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> or <GeneName>SMARCA4</GeneName> gene may have an increased risk of developing cancer in the kidney, brain, or soft tissues. Not every child with these risk factors will develop rhabdoid tumor of the kidney. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. </Para><Para id="_18219">Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_436"><Title>Monitoring children at risk of rhabdoid tumor of the kidney</Title><Para id="_437">If your child has an inherited change to the <GeneName>SMARCB1</GeneName> gene, they may have a higher risk of developing rhabdoid tumor of the kidney and other types of cancer. Your child may have check-ups from birth until age 5 years, including a brain MRI and an abdominal ultrasound every 3 months, to look for cancer.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18154"><Title>Treatment of rhabdoid tumor of the kidney</Title><Para id="_18155">There is no <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044930" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">standard treatment</GlossaryTermRef> for rhabdoid tumor of the kidney. Treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18156" Style="bullet"><ListItem>a combination of surgery, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy</ListItem><ListItem>high-dose chemotherapy with or without <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046695" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">stem cell transplant</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_181530">Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_18114" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Types of treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_18220">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_292"><Title>Clear cell sarcoma of the kidney</Title><Para id="_293">Clear cell sarcoma of the kidney is a rare cancer that occurs most often before age 3 years. It may spread to the bone, lungs, brain, liver, or soft tissue. Most <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045866" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">relapses</GlossaryTermRef> occur within 3 years of treatment. But it may come back up to 14 years after treatment, though this is rare. Clear cell sarcoma often comes back in the brain or lungs.</Para><Para id="_18158">Treatment of stage I clear cell sarcoma of the kidney may include: </Para><ItemizedList id="_18159" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery with removal of lymph nodes to test them for cancer cells followed by chemotherapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18160">Treatment of stages II, III, and IV clear cell sarcoma of the kidney may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18161" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery with removal of lymph nodes to test them for cancer cells followed by combination chemotherapy and radiation therapy</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18221">Treatment of recurrent clear cell sarcoma of the kidney may include chemotherapy, surgical resection (if possible), and radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_18222">Learn about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_18114" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Types of treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_294"><Title>Congenital mesoblastic nephroma</Title><Para id="_295"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000534218" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Congenital mesoblastic nephroma</GlossaryTermRef> is a tumor of the kidney that is often diagnosed during the first year of life or before birth. It is the most common kidney tumor found in infants younger than 6 months old and is found more often in males than in females.</Para><Para id="_296">Some of these tumors have cells with a certain genetic change called a translocation. This means that part of one chromosome switches places with part of another chromosome. In congenital mesoblastic nephroma an abnormal gene is formed when the <GeneName>ETV6</GeneName> gene on chromosome 12 switches places with the <GeneName>NTRK3</GeneName> gene on another chromosome. </Para><Para id="_18163">Treatment of stages I, II, and some children with stage III congenital mesoblastic nephroma may include surgery.</Para><Para id="_18164">Treatment for some children with stage III congenital mesoblastic nephroma may include surgery followed by chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_18223">Treatment of recurrent congenital mesoblastic nephroma may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18224" Style="bullet"><ListItem>surgery, chemotherapy, and radiation therapy</ListItem><ListItem>targeted therapy, such as <DrugRef href="CDR0000795854" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/larotrectinibsulfate">larotrectinib</DrugRef> or <DrugRef href="CDR0000799054" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/entrectinib">entrectinib</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18225">Learn about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_18114" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Types of treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_297"><Title>Ewing sarcoma of the kidney</Title><Para id="_298"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046031" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Ewing sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> of the kidney is a rare cancer that usually occurs in young adults. Young adults are usually diagnosed with large tumors that grow and spread to other parts of the body quickly. The cancer may spread to the lungs, liver or bone. </Para><Para id="_18166">There is no standard treatment for Ewing sarcoma of the kidney. Treatment may include a combination of surgery, chemotherapy, and radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_18167">It may also be treated in  the same way that Ewing sarcoma is treated. To learn more, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000403689" url="/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">Ewing Sarcoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_299"><Title>Primary renal myoepithelial carcinoma</Title><Para id="_300"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000785476" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Primary renal myoepithelial carcinoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a rare cancer that grows and spreads quickly. It usually affects soft tissues, but it sometimes forms in the internal organs, such as the kidney. </Para><Para id="_18169">There is no standard treatment for primary renal myoepithelial carcinoma. Treatment may include a combination of surgery, chemotherapy, and radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_18226">Learn about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_18114" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Types of treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_18227">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_301"><Title>Multilocular cystic nephroma</Title><Para id="_302">Multilocular cystic nephromas are benign tumors made up of cysts. They are most common in infants, young children, and adult women. These tumors can occur in one or both kidneys.</Para><Para id="_3140">Multilocular cystic nephroma is caused by certain changes in the way kidney cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. The exact cause of these changes is often unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_303">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease.  Multilocular cystic nephroma may be an inherited condition that is caused by a change in the <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> gene. Not every child with this risk factor will develop multilocular cystic nephroma. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_3150">Children with a change in the <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> gene may have imaging tests to check the lungs for cysts or solid tumors called <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000446557" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pleuropulmonary blastoma</GlossaryTermRef>. To learn more, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790954" url="/types/lung/patient/child-pleuropulmonary-blastoma-treatment-pdq">Pleuropulmonary Blastoma</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_18171">Treatment of multilocular cystic nephroma includes surgery. Learn more about this treatment in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_18114" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Types of treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_18228">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_304"><Title>Anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney</Title><Para id="_305">Anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney is a rare cancer that is most common in children or adolescents younger than age 15 years. Anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney often spreads to the lungs, liver, or bones. </Para><Para id="_3149">Anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney is caused by certain changes in the way kidney cells function, especially how they grow and divide into new cells. The exact cause of these changes is often unknown. Learn more about how cancer develops at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/understanding/what-is-cancer">What Is Cancer?</ExternalRef></Para><Para id="_306">A risk factor is anything that increases the chance of getting a disease.  Anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney may be an inherited condition that is caused by a change in the <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> gene. Not every child with this risk factor will develop anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney. And it will develop in some children who don't have a known risk factor. Talk with your child's doctor if you think your child may be at risk.</Para><Para id="_3039">Children with a change in the <GeneName>DICER1</GeneName> gene may also have imaging tests to check the lungs for cysts or solid tumors called pleuropulmonary blastoma. To learn more, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000790954" url="/types/lung/patient/child-pleuropulmonary-blastoma-treatment-pdq">Pleuropulmonary Blastoma</SummaryRef>.</Para><Para id="_18173">There is no standard treatment for anaplastic sarcoma of the kidney. Treatment is usually the same treatment given for anaplastic Wilms tumor or Ewing sarcoma. To learn more, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000415235" url="/types/kidney/patient/wilms-treatment-pdq">Wilms Tumor</SummaryRef> or <SummaryRef href="CDR0000403689" url="/types/bone/patient/ewing-treatment-pdq">Ewing Sarcoma Treatment</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_307"><Title>Primary renal synovial sarcoma </Title><Para id="_308"><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000748354" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">Primary</GlossaryTermRef> renal <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044626" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">synovial sarcoma</GlossaryTermRef> is a cyst-like cancer that is often found in the right kidney of young adults. These tumors grow and spread quickly. </Para><Para id="_309">Some tumors have cells with a certain genetic change called a translocation. This means that part of one chromosome switches places with part of another chromosome. In primary renal synovial sarcoma, the <GeneName>SS18</GeneName> gene on chromosome 18 switches places with the <GeneName>SSX</GeneName> gene on another chromosome to make an abnormal gene. To diagnose primary renal synovial sarcoma, the tumor cells may be checked for this genetic change.</Para><Para id="_18175">Treatment of primary renal synovial sarcoma usually includes surgery and maybe chemotherapy. Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_18114" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Types of treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para><Para id="_18229">If the cancer comes back after treatment, your child's doctor will talk with you about what to expect and possible next steps. There might be treatment options that may shrink the cancer or control its growth. If there are no treatments, your child can receive care to control symptoms from cancer so they can be as comfortable as possible.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_310"><Title>Nephroblastomatosis </Title><Para id="_311">Nephroblastomatosis (also called diffuse hyperplastic perilobar nephroblastomatosis) is not cancer. But if untreated, it can become a Wilms tumor, which is cancer. </Para><Para id="_312">Sometimes, after the kidneys form in the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046400" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fetus</GlossaryTermRef>, abnormal groups of kidney cells remain. These abnormal groups of cells may grow in many places inside the kidney or make a thick layer around the kidney. They most often occur in both kidneys. If these cells are found in one kidney after surgery for Wilms tumor, the child has an increased risk of Wilms tumor in the other kidney. </Para><Para id="_18177">Treatment of nephroblastomatosis may include chemotherapy followed by nephrectomy. Sometimes a partial nephrectomy may be done to keep as much kidney function as possible. Learn more about these treatments in the <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_18114" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Types of treatment</SummaryRef> section.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18114"><Title>Types of treatment for kidney cancer in children</Title><SummarySection id="_18115"><Title>Who treats children with kidney cancer?</Title><Para id="_18116">A pediatric oncologist, a doctor who specializes in treating children with cancer, oversees treatment of kidney cancer. The pediatric oncologist works with other health care providers who are experts in treating children with childhood kidney tumors and also specialize in other areas of medicine. Other specialists may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_1694" Style="bullet"><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000757278" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatrician</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318823" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric surgeon</GlossaryTermRef> or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046643" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">urologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046546" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">radiation oncologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046244" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pathologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318821" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pediatric nurse specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044730" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">social worker</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000318825" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">rehabilitation specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000044716" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">psychologist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000690737" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">child-life specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000809738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">fertility specialist</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18230"><Title>Treatment options</Title><Para id="_18117">There are different types of treatment for children and adolescents with kidney cancer. You and your child’s cancer team will work together to decide treatment. Treatment will depend on factors such as your child’s overall health and whether the cancer is newly diagnosed or has come back.</Para><Para id="_18118">Your child’s treatment plan will include information about the cancer, the goals for treatment, treatment options, and the possible side effects. It will be helpful to talk with your child’s cancer care team before treatment begins about what to expect. For help every step of the way, visit our booklet, <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_18104">Types of treatment your child might have include:</Para><SummarySection id="_18119"><Title>Surgery</Title><Para id="_18120">Children with kidney cancer may have surgery to obtain a biopsy sample or to remove the cancer. There are two types of surgery used to treat kidney cancer:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18121" Style="bullet"><ListItem>Nephrectomy is surgery to remove the whole kidney. This surgery is the most common treatment for kidney cancer. Nearby lymph nodes may also be removed and checked for cancer. <Para id="_18122">If the cancer is in both kidneys and they are not working well, your child may have a kidney transplant. A transplant is surgery to remove a kidney and replace it with one from a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000643010" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">donor</GlossaryTermRef>.</Para></ListItem><ListItem>Partial nephrectomy is the removal of the cancer in the kidney and a small amount of normal tissue around it. Your child may have this surgery if cancer is found in both kidneys or is likely to spread to both kidneys. The goal of the surgery is to keep as much of the kidney as possible. A partial nephrectomy is also called renal-sparing surgery.</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18123">After the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the surgery, your child may have chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or both to kill any cancer cells that are left. Sometimes after chemotherapy or radiation therapy, doctors will do a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045875" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">second-look surgery</GlossaryTermRef>  to see if cancer remains.</Para><Para id="_18124">Sometimes kidney cancer cannot be removed for one of these reasons:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18125" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the tumor is too close to important organs or blood vessels</ListItem><ListItem>the tumor is too large to remove</ListItem><ListItem>the cancer is in both kidneys, unless the tumors are very small</ListItem><ListItem>there is a <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000476017" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">blood clot</GlossaryTermRef> in the vessels near the liver</ListItem><ListItem>your child has trouble breathing because cancer has spread to the lungs</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18126">In this case, your child will have a biopsy first. Then they will receive chemotherapy to reduce the size of the tumor before surgery. The goal of this approach is to save as much healthy tissue as possible and reduce problems after surgery. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18127"><Title>Radiation therapy</Title><Para id="_18128">Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. A type of radiation therapy called external beam radiation is used to treat childhood kidney tumors. It uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the area of the body with cancer. Radiation therapy may be given alone or with other treatments, such as chemotherapy.</Para><Para id="_18129">To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/external-beam">External Beam Radiation Therapy for Cancer</ExternalRef> and <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/radiation-therapy/side-effects">Radiation Therapy Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18130"><Title>Chemotherapy</Title><Para id="_18131">Chemotherapy (also called chemo) uses drugs to kill cancer cells or stop them from dividing. Chemotherapy may be given alone or with other types of treatment, such as radiation therapy.</Para><Para id="_18132">For children with kidney cancer, chemotherapy is taken by mouth or injected into a vein. When given this way, chemotherapy enters the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body. Chemotherapy that is used alone or in combination to treat kidney cancer include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18133" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557107" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/carboplatin">carboplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000533338" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cisplatin">cisplatin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000557430" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cyclophosphamide">cyclophosphamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000720376" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/dactinomycin">dactinomycin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000542867" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/doxorubicinhydrochloride">doxorubicin</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000589795" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/etoposide">etoposide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000686471" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/ifosfamide">ifosfamide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000537382" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/irinotecanhydrochloride">irinotecan</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000496409" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/temozolomide">temozolomide</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000599877" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/vincristinesulfate">vincristine</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18134">Other chemotherapy not listed here may also be used.</Para><Para id="_18135">Sometimes chemotherapy is given before surgery to reduce the size of the tumor. Shrinking the tumor before surgery can help save as much healthy tissue as possible and reduce problems after surgery. This is called neoadjuvant chemotherapy. </Para><Para id="_18136">Learn more about how chemotherapy works, how it is given, common side effects, and more at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/chemotherapy">Chemotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18137"><Title>Immunotherapy</Title><Para id="_18138">Immunotherapy uses your child’s <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046356" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">immune system</GlossaryTermRef> to fight cancer. Immunotherapy that may be used to treat kidney cancer in children includes <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045256" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">interleukin-2</GlossaryTermRef> (IL-2).</Para><Para id="_18140">To learn more about immunotherapy, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/immunotherapy">Immunotherapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18141"><Title>Stem cell transplant</Title><Para id="_18142">Stem cell transplant (stem cell rescue) is a procedure to replace the blood-forming stem cells that are destroyed when high doses of chemotherapy are given to kill cancer cells.  Before high-dose chemotherapy, stem cells (immature blood cells) are removed from the blood or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045622" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">bone marrow</GlossaryTermRef> of your child and stored in a freezer. After your child completes chemotherapy, the frozen stem cells are thawed and given back to them through an <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045738" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infusion</GlossaryTermRef>. These stem cells grow into new blood cells. </Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18143"><Title>Targeted therapy</Title><Para id="_18144">Targeted therapy uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells. Targeted therapy that is used or being studied to treat childhood kidney cancer may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18145" Style="bullet"><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000743644" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/cabozantinib-s-malate">cabozantinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000799054" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/entrectinib">entrectinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000795854" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/larotrectinibsulfate">larotrectinib</DrugRef></ListItem><ListItem><DrugRef href="CDR0000491976" url="/about-cancer/treatment/drugs/sunitinibmalate">sunitinib</DrugRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18146">To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/types/targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapy to Treat Cancer</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18147"><Title>Clinical trials</Title><Para id="_18147_md_9">For some children, joining a clinical trial may be an option. There are different types of clinical trials for childhood cancer. For example, a treatment trial tests new treatments or new ways of using current treatments. Supportive care and palliative care trials look at ways to improve quality of life, especially for those who have side effects from cancer and its treatment.</Para><Para id="_18147_md_10">You can use the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials-search">clinical trial search</ExternalRef> to find NCI-supported cancer clinical trials accepting participants. The search allows you to filter trials based on the type of cancer, your child's age, and where the trials are being done. Clinical trials supported by other organizations can be found on the <ExternalRef xref="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ExternalRef> website.</Para><Para id="_18147_md_11">Learn more about clinical trials, including how to find and join one, at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">Clinical Trials Information for Patients and Caregivers</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18186"><Title>Prognostic factors for kidney cancer in children</Title><Para id="_18187">If your child has been diagnosed with kidney cancer, you likely have questions about how serious the cancer is and your child’s chances of survival. The likely outcome or course of a disease is called prognosis.</Para><Para id="_18188">The prognosis for renal cell cancer depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18189" Style="bullet"><ListItem>the stage of the cancer</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to the lymph nodes</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18190">The prognosis for rhabdoid tumor of the kidney depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18191" Style="bullet"><ListItem>your child's age at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>the stage of the cancer</ListItem><ListItem>whether the cancer has spread to the brain or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000340937" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">spinal cord</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18192">The prognosis for clear cell sarcoma of the kidney depends on:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18193" Style="bullet"><ListItem>your child's age at the time of diagnosis</ListItem><ListItem>the stage of the cancer</ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18194">No two people are alike, and responses to treatment can vary greatly. Your child's cancer care team is in the best position to talk with you about your child's prognosis.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18195"><Title>Side effects and late effects of treatment</Title><Para id="_18196">Cancer treatments can cause side effects. Which side effects your child has depends on the type of treatment they receive, the dose, and how their body reacts. Talk with your child's treatment team about which side effects to look for and ways to manage them.</Para><Para id="_18195_md_76">To learn more about <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046580" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">side effects</GlossaryTermRef> that begin during treatment for cancer, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects">Side Effects</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_18197">Problems from cancer treatment that begin 6 months or later after treatment and continue for months or years are called late effects. Late effects of cancer treatment may include:</Para><ItemizedList id="_18198" Style="bullet"><ListItem>physical problems, such as trouble with exercise, mobility, strength, and flexibility</ListItem><ListItem>chronic health conditions that could affect the heart, lungs, kidneys, intestines, and hormone levels</ListItem><ListItem><GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046348" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">infertility</GlossaryTermRef> or problems during <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000666677" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">pregnancy</GlossaryTermRef> including high blood pressure, early labor, or the baby being in an unusual position as birth approaches</ListItem><ListItem>neurological symptoms, such as changes in mood, feelings, thinking, learning, or memory</ListItem><ListItem>second cancers (new types of cancer), such as <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000045343" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">leukemias</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445091" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">thyroid cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, cancer of the <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000046189" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">gastrointestinal tract</GlossaryTermRef>, <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000444971" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">breast cancer</GlossaryTermRef>, or <GlossaryTermRef href="CDR0000445084" dictionary="Cancer.gov" audience="Patient">skin cancer</GlossaryTermRef></ListItem></ItemizedList><Para id="_18199">Some late effects may be treated or controlled. It is important to talk with your child's doctors about the effects cancer treatment can have on your child. Learn more about <SummaryRef href="CDR0000373791" url="/types/childhood-cancers/late-effects-pdq">Late Effects of Treatment for Childhood Cancer</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18200"><Title>Follow-up care</Title><Para id="_18201">As your child goes through treatment, they will have follow-up tests or check-ups. Some of the tests that they had to diagnose the cancer may be repeated. Some tests will be repeated to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.</Para><Para id="_18202">Your child will continue to have some tests from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your child's condition has changed or if the cancer has come back. </Para><Para id="_18203">To learn more about follow-up tests, visit <SummaryRef href="CDR0000817497#_449" url="/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">Tests to diagnose kidney cancer in children</SummaryRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18204"><Title>Coping with your child's kidney tumor</Title><Para id="_18205">When your child has a kidney tumor, every member of the family needs support. Taking care of yourself during this difficult time is important. Reach out to your child’s treatment team and to people in your family and community for support. To learn more, visit <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping/caregiver-support/parents">Support for Families: Childhood Cancer</ExternalRef> and the booklet <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/patient-education/guide-for-parents">Children with Cancer: A Guide for Parents</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_18206"><Title>Related resources</Title><Para id="_44">For more childhood cancer information and other general cancer resources, visit:</Para><ItemizedList id="_45" Style="bullet"><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney">Kidney Cancer Home Page</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer">About Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers">Childhood Cancers</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="http://www.curesearch.org/">CureSearch for Children's Cancer</ExternalRef>
</ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/aya">Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/childhood-cancers/child-adolescent-cancers-fact-sheet">Cancer in Children and Adolescents</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/diagnosis-staging/staging">Cancer Staging</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/coping">Coping with Cancer</ExternalRef></ListItem><ListItem><ExternalRef xref="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/ocs/resources/survivors.html">For Survivors, Caregivers, and Advocates</ExternalRef></ListItem></ItemizedList></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_1"><Title>About This PDQ Summary</Title><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_2"><Title>About PDQ</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_3">Physician Data Query (PDQ) is the National Cancer Institute's (NCI's) comprehensive cancer information database. The PDQ database contains summaries of the latest published information on cancer prevention, detection, genetics, treatment, supportive care, and complementary and alternative medicine. Most summaries come in two versions. The health professional versions have detailed information written in technical language. The patient versions are written in easy-to-understand, nontechnical language. Both versions have cancer information that is accurate and up to date and most versions are also available in <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/espanol/publicaciones/pdq">Spanish</ExternalRef>.</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_4">PDQ is a service of the NCI. The NCI is part of the National Institutes of Health (NIH). NIH is the federal government’s center of biomedical research.  The PDQ summaries are based on an independent review of the medical literature. They are not policy statements of the NCI or the NIH.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_5"><Title>Purpose of This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_6">This PDQ cancer information summary has current information about the treatment of kidney cancer in children.  It is meant to inform and help patients, families, and caregivers. It does not give formal guidelines or recommendations for making decisions about health care.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_7"><Title>Reviewers and Updates</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_8">Editorial Boards write the PDQ cancer information summaries and keep them up to date. These Boards are made up of experts in cancer treatment and other specialties related to cancer. The summaries are reviewed regularly and changes are made when there is new information. The date on each summary ("Updated") is the date of the most recent change.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_9">The information in this patient summary was taken from the health professional version, which is reviewed regularly and updated as needed, by the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/publications/pdq/editorial-boards/pediatric-treatment">PDQ Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board</ExternalRef>.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_10"><Title>Clinical Trial Information</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_11">A clinical trial is a study to answer a scientific question, such as whether one treatment is better than another. Trials are based on past studies and what has been learned in the laboratory. Each trial answers certain scientific questions in order to find new and better ways to help cancer patients. During treatment clinical trials, information is collected about the effects of a new treatment and how well it works. If a clinical trial shows that a new treatment is better than one currently being used, the new treatment may become "standard." Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_12">Clinical trials can be found online at <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/research/participate/clinical-trials">NCI's website</ExternalRef>. For more information, call the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/contact-center">Cancer Information Service</ExternalRef> (CIS), NCI's contact center, at 1-800-4-CANCER (1-800-422-6237).
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_13"><Title>Permission to Use This Summary</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_14">PDQ is a registered trademark. The content of PDQ documents can be used freely as text. It cannot be identified as an NCI PDQ cancer information summary unless the whole summary is shown and it is updated regularly. However, a user would be allowed to write a sentence such as “NCI’s PDQ cancer information summary about breast cancer prevention states the risks in the following way: [include excerpt from the summary].”
</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_15">The best way to cite this PDQ summary is:</Para><Para id="_AboutThis_21">PDQ® Pediatric Treatment Editorial Board. PDQ Kidney Cancer in Children. Bethesda, MD: National Cancer Institute. Updated  &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. Available at: <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer">https://www.cancer.gov/types/kidney/patient/childhood-kidney-cancer</ExternalRef>.  Accessed &lt;MM/DD/YYYY&gt;. </Para><Para id="_AboutThis_16">Images in this summary are used with permission of the author(s), artist, and/or publisher for use in the PDQ summaries only. If you want to use an image from a PDQ summary and you are not using the whole summary, you must get permission from the owner. It cannot be given by the National Cancer Institute. Information about using the images in this summary, along with many other images related to cancer can be found in <ExternalRef xref="https://visualsonline.cancer.gov/">Visuals Online</ExternalRef>. Visuals Online is a collection of more than 3,000 scientific images.
</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_17"><Title>Disclaimer</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_18">The information in these summaries should not be used to make decisions about insurance reimbursement. More information on insurance coverage is available on Cancer.gov on the <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/managing-care">Managing Cancer Care</ExternalRef> page.</Para></SummarySection><SummarySection id="_AboutThis_19"><Title>Contact Us</Title><Para id="_AboutThis_20">More information about contacting us or receiving help with the Cancer.gov website can be found on our <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact">Contact Us for Help</ExternalRef> page. Questions can also be submitted to Cancer.gov through the website’s <ExternalRef xref="https://www.cancer.gov/contact/email-us">E-mail Us</ExternalRef>.</Para></SummarySection></SummarySection><DateFirstPublished>2025-05-13</DateFirstPublished><DateLastModified>2025-05-13</DateLastModified></Summary>
